<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 02:34:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersion Outperforms Absorption: EIT-Enhanced Atomic Localization and Gradient Sensing with Super-Gaussian Beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a comprehensive theoretical comparison between absorption-based and electromagnetically induced transparency (EIT)-based atomic gradient sensing in a four-level tripod system. Both methods were evaluated under identical and optimized physical conditions to ensure a fair and unbiased comparison. The analysis demonstrates that EIT, driven by its steep dispersion response, consistently outperforms conventional absorption detection across a wide range of super-Gaussian beam profiles. Under optimal detuning, EIT achieved up to an order-of-magnitude enhancement in gradient sensitivity and maintained a twofold advantage even under identical detuning. Both approaches reached sub-diffraction spatial resolution in the range of 0.29lambda-0.40lambda, with EIT exhibiting sharper edge contrast and higher localization accuracy. These results confirm EIT as a fundamentally superior approach for precision atomic gradient sensing and sub-wavelength localization, offering clear guidance for the design of next-generation optical and quantum metrology systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02063v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahboob Ul Haq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Machine Learning for Secondary Frequency Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frequency control in power systems is critical to maintaining stability and preventing blackouts. Traditional methods like meta-heuristic algorithms and machine learning face limitations in real-time applicability and scalability. This paper introduces a novel approach using a pure variational quantum circuit (VQC) for real-time secondary frequency control in diesel generators. Unlike hybrid classical-quantum models, the proposed VQC operates independently during execution, eliminating latency from classical-quantum data exchange. The VQC is trained via supervised learning to map historical frequency deviations to optimal Proportional-Integral (PI) controller parameters using a pre-computed lookup table. Simulations demonstrate that the VQC achieves high prediction accuracy (over 90%) with sufficient quantum measurement shots and generalizes well across diverse test events. The quantum-optimized PI parameters significantly improve transient response, reducing frequency fluctuations and settling time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02065v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Younes Ghazagh Jahed, Alireza Khatiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Multi-Circuit Quantum Feature Fusion in Hybrid Quantum-Classical Convolutional Neural Networks for Breast Tumor Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning has emerged as a promising approach to improve feature extraction and classification tasks in high-dimensional data domains such as medical imaging. In this work, we present a hybrid Quantum-Classical Convolutional Neural Network (QCNN) architecture designed for the binary classification of the BreastMNIST dataset, a standardized benchmark for distinguishing between benign and malignant breast tumors. Our architecture integrates classical convolutional feature extraction with two distinct quantum circuits: an amplitude-encoding variational quantum circuit (VQC) and an angle-encoding VQC circuit with circular entanglement, both implemented on four qubits. These circuits generate quantum feature embeddings that are fused with classical features to form a joint feature space, which is subsequently processed by a fully connected classifier. To ensure fairness, the hybrid QCNN is parameter-matched against a baseline classical CNN, allowing us to isolate the contribution of quantum layers. Both models are trained under identical conditions using the Adam optimizer and binary cross-entropy loss. Experimental evaluation in five independent runs demonstrates that the hybrid QCNN achieves statistically significant improvements in classification accuracy compared to the classical CNN, as validated by a one-sided Wilcoxon signed rank test (p = 0.03125) and supported by large effect size of Cohen's d = 2.14. Our results indicate that hybrid QCNN architectures can leverage entanglement and quantum feature fusion to enhance medical image classification tasks. This work establishes a statistical validation framework for assessing hybrid quantum models in biomedical applications and highlights pathways for scaling to larger datasets and deployment on near-term quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02066v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ece Yurtseven</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Optimization on Lie Groups: A Lie-Theoretic Explanation of Barren Plateau Mitigation for Variational Quantum Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Barren plateaus, which means the training gradients become extremely small, pose a major challenge in optimizing parameterized quantum circuits, often making the learning process impractically slow or stall. This work shows why using neural networks to generate quantum circuit parameters helps overcome this difficulty. We introduce a geometric viewpoint that describes how the parameters produced by neural networks evolve during training. Our analysis shows that these parameters follow smooth and efficient paths that avoid the flat regions in the training that cause barren plateaus. This provides a computational explanation for the improved trainability observed in recent neural network-assisted quantum learning methods. Overall, our findings bridge ideas from quantum machine learning and computational optimization, offering new insight into the structure of quantum models and guiding future approaches for designing more trainable quantum circuits or parameter initialization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02078v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhehao Yi, Rahul Bhadani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Betti Numbers to Persistence Diagrams: A Hybrid Quantum Algorithm for Topological Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Persistence diagrams serve as a core tool in topological data analysis, playing a crucial role in pathological monitoring, drug discovery, and materials design. However, existing quantum topological algorithms, such as the LGZ algorithm, can only efficiently compute summary statistics like Betti numbers, failing to provide persistence diagram information that tracks the lifecycle of individual topological features, severely limiting their practical value. This paper proposes a novel quantum-classical hybrid algorithm that achieves, for the first time, the leap from "quantum computation of Betti numbers" to "quantum acquisition of practical persistence diagrams." The algorithm leverages the LGZ quantum algorithm as an efficient feature extractor, mining the harmonic form eigenvectors of the combinatorial Laplacian as well as Betti numbers, constructing specialized topological kernel functions to train a quantum support vector machine (QSVM), and learning the mapping from quantum topological features to persistence diagrams. The core contributions of this algorithm are: (1) elevating quantum topological computation from statistical summaries to pattern recognition, greatly expanding its application value; (2) obtaining more practical topological information in the form of persistence diagrams for real-world applications while maintaining the exponential speedup advantage of quantum computation; (3) proposing a novel hybrid paradigm of "classical precision guiding quantum efficiency." This method provides a feasible pathway for the practical implementation of quantum topological data analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02081v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of an anomaly in the statistics of Kibble-Zurek defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kibble-Zurek mechanism quantifies defect formation during adiabatic passage across a continuous phase transition, providing key insights into universality in quantum many-body systems. We explore counting statistics of defects in adiabatic passage experiments on long 1D Rydberg atom chains. The experiments reveal an anomaly in the defect number distribution at long ramp times, challenging the hypothesis of defect formation through independent domain mergers. Numerical simulations confirm the anomaly and suggest its link to non-critical coarsening dynamics, which we suppress in prepare-and-hold experiments. Our results highlight the ability of quantum simulators to uncover unexpected correlated quantum phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02112v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Balewski, Alexey Khudorozhkov, Siva Darbha, Omar A. Ashour, Fangli Liu, Ermal Rrapaj, Sheng-Tao Wang, Pedro L. S. Lopes, Katherine Klymko, Milan Kornja\v{c}a, Daan Camps</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network theory classification of quantum matter based on wave function snapshots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computers and simulators offer unparalleled capabilities of probing quantum many-body states, by obtaining snapshots of the many-body wave function via collective projective measurements. The probability distribution obtained by such snapshots (which are fundamentally limited to a negligible fraction of the Hilbert space) is of fundamental importance to determine the power of quantum computations. However, its relation to many-body collective properties is poorly understood. Here, we develop a theoretical framework to link quantum phases of matter to their snapshots, based on a combination of data complexity and network theory analyses. The first step in our scheme consists of applying Occam's razor principle to quantum sampling: given snapshots of a wave function, we identify a minimal-complexity measurement basis by analyzing the information compressibility of snapshots over different measurement bases. The second step consists of analyzing arbitrary correlations using network theory, building a wave-function network from the minimal-complexity basis data. This approach allows us to stochastically classify the output of quantum computers and simulations, with no assumptions on the underlying dynamics, and in a fully interpretable manner. We apply this method to quantum states of matter in one-dimensional translational invariant systems, where such classification is exhaustive, and where it reveals an interesting interplay between algorithmic and computational complexity for many-body states. Our framework is of immediate experimental relevance, and can be further extended both in terms of more advanced network mathematics, including discrete homology, as well as in terms of applications to physical phenomena, such as time-dependent dynamics and gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02121v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Andreoni, Vittorio Vitale, Cristiano Muzzi, Guido Caldarelli, Roberto Verdel, Marcello Dalmonte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Advantage in Resource Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing promises the ability to compute properties of quantum systems exponentially faster than classical computers. Quantum advantage is achieved when a practical problem is solved more efficiently on a quantum computer than on a classical computer. Demonstrating quantum advantage requires a powerful quantum computer with low error rates and an efficient quantum algorithm that has a useful application. Despite rapid progress in hardware development, we still lack useful applications that are feasible for the next generation of quantum computers. Here we argue that an exponential quantum advantage exists in producing numerical resource estimates of larger quantum algorithms by accurately measuring simulation errors. We provide a quantum algorithm for measuring simulation errors of Trotter-based algorithms. Our results indicate that this method will reduce runtimes of quantum algorithms by approximately three orders of magnitude for one-hundred qubit systems. We also predict that these reductions will increase with system size. The methods we propose require relatively few qubits and operations, meaning the next generation of quantum computers could compute simulation errors for classically intractable systems. Since the underlying computations that lead to reduced resource estimates are infeasible for classical computers, this task is a candidate for demonstrating practical quantum advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02131v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William A. Simon, Peter J. Love</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing ER = EPR with Hydrogen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: According to the ER = EPR conjecture, entangled particles are connected by quantum wormholes. Under the assumption that some of the electric field surrounding an entangled charged particle leaks into the wormhole, we show that this effect will modify the hyperfine structure of the hydrogen atom. In addition, if the quantum wormholes are non-traversable, this will also lead to a non-zero total effective charge for the hydrogen atom. These effects provide strong constraints on the amplitude of this potential ER = EPR effect, given high-precision measurements of the hydrogen atom's hyperfine structure and total charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02156v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irfan Javed, Edward Wilson-Ewing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Methodological Realism and Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I distinguish two senses in which one can take a given physical theory to be `complete'. On the first, a complete physical theory is one that, in principle, completely describes physical reality. On the second, a complete physical theory is one that provides all of the conceptual resources one needs to describe any (in general probabilistic) physical phenomenon to any level of detail one likes, in principle. I argue that while the (neo-)Everettian approach to interpreting quantum mechanics aims to show that it is complete in the first sense, the (neo-)Bohrian approach begins from an understanding of quantum mechanics as being complete in the second sense. I then discuss some of the essential differences between how classical and quantum theory describe phenomena, and the way in which the quantum description can be thought of as a ``natural generalisation'' (to use Bohr's phrase) of the classical description. Finally, I elaborate upon the two visions of physics from which one can motivate the first and the second sense of completeness, respectively: \emph{metaphysical realism}, on the one hand, and what I will call \emph{methodological realism}, on the other -- and discuss what one can say about the significance of the differences between quantum and classical description from each of these points of view. I suggest that there is a sense in which the views of (neo-)Everett and the views of (neo-)Bohr can be understood to be mutually supporting positions, from their respective perspectives, even though they are diametrically opposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02169v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael E. Cuffaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absorption-Based Qubit Estimation in Discrete-Time Quantum Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate state estimation in discrete-time quantum walks with a single absorbing boundary. Using a spectral approach, we obtain closed expressions for the escape probability as a function of the coin state and the boundary position, and their corresponding classical Fisher information for a simple absorption readout. Comparing with the single-copy quantum Fisher information shows a clear complementarity: near boundaries carry broad information about the population angle of the coin, whereas moderate or distant boundaries reveal phase-sensitive regions. Because a single boundary probes only one information direction, combining two boundary placements yields a full-rank Fisher matrix and tight joint Cram\'er--Rao bounds, while retaining a binary, tomography-free measurement. We outline an integrated-photonics implementation in which an on-chip sink realizes the absorber and estimate a substantial reduction in configuration count compared to mode-resolved qubit tomography. These results identify absorption in quantum walks as a simple and scalable primitive for coin-state metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02186v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edgard P. M. Amorim, Lorena R. Cerutti, O. P. de S\'a Neto, M. C. de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Progress in quantum metrology and applications for optical atomic clocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement offers powerful opportunities for enhancing measurement sensitivity beyond classical limits, with optical atomic clocks serving as a leading platform for such advances. This chapter introduces the principles of entanglement-enhanced quantum metrology and explores their applications to timekeeping. We review the theoretical framework of quantum phase estimation, comparing frequentist and Bayesian approaches, and discuss paradigmatic entangled states such as spin-squeezed and GHZ states. Particular emphasis is placed on the challenges posed by decoherence, which constrain the practical advantages that can be realized in large-scale devices. The discussion then turns to frequency estimation in atomic clocks, highlighting how experimental constraints shape the translation of abstract quantum limits into real performance gains. Finally, we outline emerging directions of contemporary quantum metrology. Together, these developments underscore the increasingly close interplay between quantum information processing and precision metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02202v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Kaubruegger, Adam M. Kaufman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced readout contrast of V2 ensembles in 4H-SiC through resonant optical excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The V2 silicon vacancy defect in 4H-SiC has emerged as a promising system for quantum technologies due to its favorable optical and spin properties and the advantages of the SiC host. However, the readout contrast - an important benchmark for quantum sensing - of V2 ensembles for optically-detected magnetic resonance (ODMR) is relatively low, usually &lt;1$\%$ at room temperature. To overcome this challenge, we resonantly excite the V2 ensembles at cryogenic temperatures and compare the results with the off-resonant case. We report a maximum ODMR contrast of 50$\%$ with only 2 $\mu$W of resonant laser power, almost 100 times improvement over off-resonant excitation. We attribute this high readout contrast to a subset of V2 centers that have one spin-selective optical transition resonant with the laser. The ODMR contrast decreases with temperature, approaching the non-resonant contrast by 60 K, likely due to broadening of the optical transition linewidths. We achieve a maximum sensitivity of 100 nT/$\sqrt{Hz}$ with a resonant laser power of 300 $\mu$W, while 100 times more non-resonant excitation power is needed to achieve comparable sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02235v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Infiter Tathfif, Samuel G. Carter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the eigenvalues and eigenstates of the single-particle reduced density operator during two-particle scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A particle initially in a pure state but interacting with some environment evolves into a discrete ensemble of pure states, the eigenstates of its reduced density operator, with ensemble probabilities given by the corresponding eigenvalues. In this work, we use numerics to present explicit results for the time-dependence of these eigenvalues and eigenstates for simple scattering experiments in one and two dimensions. This provides a time-resolved picture of the scattering process, showing in detail how an initial state described entirely in terms of continuous parameters evolves into a discrete set of possible outcomes, each with an associated probability and time-evolving wavefunction. We find that for scattering of Gaussian wavepackets in one dimension, the late time spectrum is dominated by two large eigenvalues nearly equal to the transmission and reflection probabilities associated with the central value of momentum. The corresponding eigenstates appear as single-peaked reflected or transmitted wavepackets. The remaining smaller eigenvalues, which increase to a maximum during scattering and then decrease to small values, correspond to reflected or transmitted wavepackets with multiple spatially separated parts. In this case and also for two-dimensional scattering, we find that successively smaller eigenvalues correspond to probability distributions with successively more peaks. These multi-peaked states correspond to outcomes of the scattering experiment where a particle initially in a single wavepacket ends up in a superposition of separated wavepackets after scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02239v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arsam Najafian, Mark Van Raamsdonk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave Circulation in an Extended Josephson Junction Ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Circulators are nonreciprocal devices that enable directional signal routing. Nonreciprocity, which requires time-reversal symmetry breaking, can be produced in waveguides in which the propagation medium moves relative to the waveguide at a moderate fraction of the wave speed. Motivated by this effect, here we propose a design for nonreciprocal microwave transmission based on an extended, annular Josephson junction, in which the propagation medium consists of a train of moving fluxons. We show how to harness this to build a high-quality resonant microwave circulator, and we theoretically evaluate the anticipated performance of such a device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02264v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sbtv-plf7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 230801 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dat Thanh Le, Arkady Fedorov, Thomas M. Stace</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Classical Separation in Bounded-Resource Tasks Arising from Measurement Contextuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The prevailing view is that quantum phenomena can be harnessed to tackle certain problems beyond the reach of classical approaches. Quantifying this capability as a quantum-classical separation and demonstrating it on current quantum processors has remained elusive. Using a superconducting qubit processor, we show that quantum contextuality enables certain tasks to be performed with success probabilities beyond classical limits. With a few qubits, we illustrate quantum contextuality with the magic square game, as well as quantify it through a Kochen--Specker--Bell inequality violation. To examine many-body contextuality, we implement the N-player GHZ game and separately solve a 2D hidden linear function problem, exceeding classical success rate in both. Our work proposes novel ways to benchmark quantum processors using contextuality-based algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02284v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashwat Kumar, Eliott Rosenberg, Alejandro Grajales Dau, Rodrigo Cortinas, Dmitri Maslov, Richard Oliver, Adam Zalcman, Matthew Neeley, Alice Pagano, Aaron Szasz, Ilya Drozdov, Zlatko Minev, Craig Gidney, Noureldin Yosri, Stijn J. de Graaf, Aniket Maiti, Dmitry Abanin, Rajeev Acharya, Laleh Aghababaie Beni, Georg Aigeldinger, Ross Alcaraz, Sayra Alcaraz, Trond I. Andersen, Markus Ansmann, Frank Arute, Kunal Arya, Walt Askew, Nikita Astrakhantsev, Juan Atalaya, Ryan Babbush, Brian Ballard, Joseph C. Bardin, Hector Bates, Andreas Bengtsson, Martin Bigdeli, Alexander Bilmes, Simon Bilodeau, Felix Borjans, Alexandre Bourassa, Jenna Bovaird, Dylan Bowers, Leon Brill, Peter Brooks, Michael Broughton, David A. Browne, Brett Buchea, Bob B. Buckley, Tim Burger, Brian Burkett, Nicholas Bushnell, Jamal Busnaina, Anthony Cabrera, Juan Campero, Hung-Shen Chang, Silas Chen, Zijun Chen, Ben Chiaro, Liang-Ying Chih, Jahan Claes, Agnetta Y. Cleland, Bryan Cochrane, Matt Cockrell, Josh Cogan, Roberto Collins, Paul Conner, Harold Cook, William Courtney, Alexander L. Crook, Ben Curtin, Sayan Das, Laura De Lorenzo, Sean Demura, Agustin Di Paolo, Paul Donohoe, Andrew Dunsworth, Valerie Ehimhen, Alec Eickbusch, Aviv Moshe Elbag, Lior Ella, Mahmoud Elzouka, David Enriquez, Catherine Erickson, Vinicius S. Ferreira, Marcos Flores, Leslie Flores Burgos, Ebrahim Forati, Jeremiah Ford, Austin G. Fowler, Brooks Foxen, Masaya Fukami, Alan Wing Lun Fung, Lenny Fuste, Suhas Ganjam, Gonzalo Garcia, Christopher Garrick, Robert Gasca, Helge Gehring, \'Elie Genois, William Giang, Dar Gilboa, James E. Goeders, Ed Gonzales, Raja Gosula, Dietrich Graumann, Joel Grebel, Alex Greene, Jonathan A. Gross, Jose Guerrero, Tan Ha, Steve Habegger, Tanner Hadick, Monica Hansen, Matthew P. Harrigan, Sean D. Harrington, Jeanne Hartshorn, Stephen Heslin, Paula Heu, Oscar Higgott, Reno Hiltermann, Jeremy Hilton, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Mike Hucka, Ashley Huff, William J. Huggins, Evan Jeffrey, Shaun Jevons, Zhang Jiang, Xiaoxuan Jin, Cody Jones, Chaitali Joshi, Pavol Juhas, Andreas Kabel, Dvir Kafri, Hui Kang, Amir H. Karamlou, Ryan Kaufman, Kostyantyn Kechedzhi, Trupti Khaire, Tanuj Khattar, Mostafa Khezri, Seon Kim, Paul V. Klimov, Can M. Knaut, Bryce Kobrin, Alexander N. Korotkov, Fedor Kostritsa, John Mark Kreikebaum, Ryuho Kudo, Ben Kueffler, Arun Kumar, Vladislav D. Kurilovich, Vitali Kutsko, David Landhuis, Tiano Lange-Dei, Brandon W. Langley, Pavel Laptev, Kim-Ming Lau, Lo\"ick Le Guevel, Emma Leavell, Justin Ledford, Joy Lee, Kenny Lee, Brian J. Lester, Wendy Leung, Lily L Li, Wing Yan Li, Alexander T. Lill, William P. Livingston, Matthew T. Lloyd, Aditya Locharla, Daniel Lundahl, Aaron Lunt, Sid Madhuk, Ashley Maloney, Salvatore Mandr\`a, Leigh S. Martin, Orion Martin, Eric Mascot, Paul Masih Das, Cameron Maxfield, Jarrod R. McClean, Matt McEwen, Seneca Meeks, Anthony Megrant, Kevin C. Miao, Reza Molavi, Sebastian Molina, Shirin Montazeri, Charles Neill, Michael Newman, Anthony Nguyen, Murray Nguyen, Chia-Hung Ni, Murphy Yuezhen Niu, Logan Oas, William D. Oliver, Raymond Orosco, Kristoffer Ottosson, Sherman Peek, David Peterson, Alex Pizzuto, Rebecca Potter, Orion Pritchard, Michael Qian, Chris Quintana, Ganesh Ramachandran, Arpit Ranadive, Matthew J. Reagor, Rachel Resnick, David M. Rhodes, Daniel Riley, Gabrielle Roberts, Roberto Rodriguez, Emma Ropes, Emma Rosenfeld, Dario Rosenstock, Elizabeth Rossi, David A. Rower, Kannan Sankaragomathi, Murat Can Sarihan, Kevin J. Satzinger, Sebastian Schroeder, Henry F. Schurkus, Aria Shahingohar, Michael J. Shearn, Aaron Shorter, Noah Shutty, Vladimir Shvarts, Volodymyr Sivak, Spencer Small, W. Clarke Smith, David A. Sobel, Barrett Spells, Sofia Springer, George Sterling, Jordan Suchard, Alexander Sztein, Madeline Taylor, Jothi Priyanka Thiruraman, Douglas Thor, Dogan Timucin, Eifu Tomita, Alfredo Torres, M. Mert Torunbalci, Hao Tran, Abeer Vaishnav, Justin Vargas, Sergey Vdovichev, Guifre Vidal, Catherine Vollgraff Heidweiller, Meghan Voorhees, Steven Waltman, Jonathan Waltz, Shannon X. Wang, Brayden Ware, James D. Watson, Travis Weidel, Theodore White, Kristi Wong, Bryan W. K. Woo, Christopher J. Wood, Maddy Woodson, Cheng Xing, Z. Jamie Yao, Ping Yeh, Bicheng Ying, Juhwan Yoo, Elliot Young, Grayson Young, Ran Zhang, Yaxing Zhang, Ningfeng Zhu, Nicholas Zobrist, Zhenjie Zou, Shruti Puri, Erik Lucero, Julian Kelly, Sergio Boixo, Yu Chen, Vadim Smelyanskiy, Hartmut Neven, Pedram Roushan, Michel Devoret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Sensitivity Bound for Thermal Quantum Dynamic Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work unifies the equilibrium and non-equilibrium frameworks of quantum metrology within the context of many-body systems. We investigate dynamic sensing schemes to derive an upper bound on the quantum Fisher information for probe states in thermal equilibrium with their environment. We establish that the dynamic quantum Fisher information for a thermal probe state is upper bounded by the degree of non-commutation between the transformed local generator and the Hamiltonian for the thermal state. Furthermore, we show that this upper bound scales as the square of the product of the inverse temperature and the evolution time. In the low-temperature limit, we establish an additional upper bound expressed as the seminorm of the commutator divided by the energy gap. We apply this thermal dynamic sensing scheme to various models, demonstrating that the dynamic quantum Fisher information satisfies the established upper bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02366v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Zhang, Yang Yang, Wenkui Ding, Xiaoguang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Local Observables via Cluster-Level Light-Cone Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02377v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulating large quantum circuits on hardware with limited qubit counts is often attempted through methods like circuit knitting, which typically incur sample costs that grow exponentially with the number of connections cut. In this work, we introduce a framework based on Cluster-level Light-cone analysis that leverages the natural locality of quantum workloads. We propose two complementary algorithms: the Causal Decoupling Algorithm, which exploits geometric disconnections in the light cone for sampling efficiency, and the Algebraic Decomposition Algorithm, which utilizes algebraic expansion to minimize hardware requirements. These methods allow simulation costs to depend on circuit depth and connectivity rather than system size. Together, our results generalize Lieb-Robinson-inspired locality to modular architectures and establish a quantitative framework for probing local physics on near-term quantum devices by decoupling the simulation cost from the global system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02377v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junxiang Huang, Yunxin Tang, Xiao Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum feature encoding optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Machine Learning (QML) holds the promise of enhancing machine learning modeling in terms of both complexity and accuracy. A key challenge in this domain is the encoding of input data, which plays a pivotal role in determining the performance of QML models. In this work, we tackle a largely unaddressed aspect of encoding that is unique to QML modeling -- rather than adjusting the ansatz used for encoding, we consider adjusting how data is conveyed to the ansatz. We specifically implement QML pipelines that leverage classical data manipulation (i.e., ordering, selecting, and weighting features) as a preprocessing step, and evaluate if these aspects of encoding can have a significant impact on QML model performance, and if they can be effectively optimized to improve performance. Our experimental results, applied across a wide variety of data sets, ansatz, and circuit sizes, with a representative QML approach, demonstrate that by optimizing how features are encoded in an ansatz we can substantially and consistently improve the performance of QML models, making a compelling case for integrating these techniques in future QML applications. Finally we demonstrate the practical feasibility of this approach by running it using real quantum hardware with 100 qubit circuits and successfully achieving improved QML modeling performance in this case as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02422v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Fioravanti, Brian Quanz, Gabriele Agliardi, Edgar Andres Ruiz Guzman, Gin\'es Carrascal, Jae-Eun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Based Self-Attention Mechanism for Hardware-Aware Differentiable Quantum Architecture Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The automated design of parameterized quantum circuits for variational algorithms in the NISQ era faces a fundamental limitation, as conventional differentiable architecture search relies on classical models that fail to adequately represent quantum gate interactions under hardware noise. We introduce the Quantum-Based Self-Attention for Differentiable Quantum Architecture Search (QBSA-DQAS), a meta-learning framework featuring quantum-based self-attention and hardware-aware multi-objective search. The framework employs a two-stage quantum self-attention module that computes contextual dependencies by mapping architectural parameters through parameterized quantum circuits, replacing classical similarity metrics with quantum-derived attention scores, then applies position-wise quantum transformations for feature enrichment. Architecture search is guided by a task-agnostic multi-objective function jointly optimizing noisy expressibility and Probability of Successful Trials (PST). A post-search optimization stage applies gate commutation, fusion, and elimination to reduce circuit complexity. Experimental validation demonstrates superior performance on VQE tasks and large-scale Wireless Sensor Networks. For VQE on H$_2$, QBSA-DQAS achieves 0.9 accuracy compared to 0.89 for standard DQAS. Post-search optimization reduces discovered circuit complexity by up to 44% in gate count and 47% in depth without accuracy degradation. The framework maintains robust performance across three molecules and five IBM quantum hardware noise models. For WSN routing, discovered circuits achieve 8.6% energy reduction versus QAOA and 40.7% versus classical greedy methods, establishing the effectiveness of quantum-native architecture search for NISQ applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02476v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Liu, Sixuan Li, Fanxu Meng, Zaichen Zhang, Xutao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qudits offer no advantages over dits for sending random messages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the following simple scenario: Alice has one of many possible messages, drawn from a known distribution, and wants to maximize the probability that Bob guesses her message correctly. We prove that if Alice can send only a qudit to Bob, without preshared entanglement, there is never any advantage over sending him a classical dit. This result was previously known only for a uniform distribution.
  We also prove a mixed-state generalization of this result in the form of an upper bound on the success probability of discriminating between mixed quantum states with a single measurement. This bound is based solely on the dimension, probability distribution, and eigenvalues of the states and is sharp among such bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02477v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronit Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superchannel without Tears: A Generalized Occam's Razor for Quantum Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum channels function as the operational primitives of quantum theory, while superchannels describe the most general transformations acting upon them. Yet the prevailing framework for superchannels is both internally inconsistent, owing to the coexistence of distinct Choi operator constructions, and structurally incomplete, lacking the analogue of representations that ground channel theory. We resolve these issues by combining tensor-network methods with a generalized Occam's razor introduced here, establishing a unified foundation for superchannels. Our framework establishes the connections between competing Choi formulations, develops the Kraus, Stinespring, and Liouville representations for superchannels, and provides a simplified derivation of the realization theorem that identifies the minimal memory required to implement a given transformation. These structural tools also enable characterizations of superchannels that destroy quantum correlations or causal structure, opening a systematic route to non-Markovian quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02493v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunlong Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Ising Meson Spectroscopy Simulation on a Noisy Digital Quantum Device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transverse-field Ising model serves as a paradigm for studying confinement and excitation spectra, particularly the emergence of $E_8$ symmetry near criticality. However, experimentally resolving the Ising meson spectroscopy required to verify these symmetries is challenging on near-term quantum hardware due to the depth of circuits required for real-time evolution. Here, we demonstrate improved spectroscopy of confined excitations using two distinct error-resilient circuit construction techniques on the IBM Torino device: first-order Trotter decomposition utilizing native fractional gates, and a tensor-network-based circuit compression via Riemannian optimization. By analyzing the Fourier spectrum of error-mitigated time-series data, we successfully identify key signatures of $E_8$ symmetry despite hardware noise. These results validate the viability of both circuit compression and hardware-efficient compilation for probing complex topological phenomena on NISQ devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02516v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Ti Hung, Isabel Nha Minh Le, Johannes Knolle, Ying-Jer Kao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of photon-level signals embedded in sunlight with an atomic photodetector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The detection of few-photon signals in a broadband background is an extreme challenge for photon counting, requiring filtering that accepts a narrow range of optical frequencies while strongly rejecting all others. Recent work [Zarraoa et. al, Phys. Rev. Res. 6, 033338 (2024)] demonstrated that trapped single atoms can act as low dark-count narrow-band photodetectors. Here we show that this ``quantum jump photodetector'' (QJPD) approach can also detect photon-level signals embedded in strong sunlight. Using a single rubidium atom as a QJPD, we count arrivals of individual narrow-band laser photons embedded in sunlight powers of order $10^{10}$ photons/s. We derive a rate-equation model for the atom's internal-state dynamics in sunlight, and find quantitative agreement with experiment. Using this model, we calculate the channel capacity over a noisy communication channel when sending weak coherent states and detecting them in the presence of sunlight, achieving a representative rate of 0.5 bits per symbol when sending 150 probe photons per 10 ms time-bin, embedded in 1 nW of sunlight (of order $10^{10}$ photons/s in the visible and near-infrared bands). The demonstration may benefit background-limited applications such as daytime light detection and ranging (LIDAR), remote magnetometry, and free-space classical and quantum optical communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02521v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Zarraoa, Romain Veyron, Tomas Lamich, Sondos Elsehimy, Morgan W. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-counting statistics and quantum information of dispersive readout with a squeezed environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the importance of dispersive readout in quantum technology, we study a prototypical dispersive readout setup that is probed by a squeezed vacuum in a time-reversal-symmetric fashion. To this end, we develop a full-counting-statistics framework for dispersive readout and analyze its measurement information, accompanied by a generalized mean-field approach suitable to deal with non-unitary dynamics. Distinct from conventional input-output theory, our full-counting-statistics approach enables the direct calculation of arbitrary-order cumulants for the measured cumulative (i.e., time-integrated) photonic distribution while maintaining applicability to nonlinear systems. The corresponding Fisher information exhibits an exponential dependence on the squeezing parameter and a robustness against residual nonlinearity, which can even approach the quantum Fisher information, setting an upper limit. This work introduces a conceptually streamlined and computationally efficient framework for continuous quantum measurements, making it well suited for widespread adoption in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02531v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Li, JunYan Luo, Gloria Platero, Georg Engelhardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraint-Optimal Driven Allocation for Scalable QEC Decoder Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fault-tolerant quantum computing (FTQC) requires fast and accurate decoding of Quantum Error Correction (QEC) syndromes. However, in large-scale systems, the number of available decoders is much smaller than the number of logical qubits, leading to a fundamental resource shortage. To address this limitation, Virtualized Quantum Decoder (VQD) architectures have been proposed to share a limited pool of decoders across multiple qubits. While the Minimize Longest Undecoded Sequence (MLS) heuristic has been introduced as an effective scheduling policy within the VQD framework, its locally greedy decision-making structure limits its ability to consider global circuit structure, causing inefficiencies in resource balancing and limited scalability. In this work, we propose Constraint-Optimal Driven Allocation (CODA), an optimization-based scheduling algorithm that leverages global circuit structure to minimize the longest undecoded sequence length. Across 19 benchmark circuits, CODA achieves an average 74\% reduction in the longest undecoded sequence length. Crucially, while the theoretical search space scales exponentially with circuit size, CODA effectively bypasses this combinatorial explosion. Our evaluation confirms that the scheduling time scales linearly with the number of qubits, determined by physical resource constraints rather than the combinatorial search space, ensuring robust scalability for large-scale FTQC systems. These results demonstrate that CODA provides a global optimization-based, scalable scheduling solution that enables efficient decoder virtualization in large-scale FTQC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02539v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongmin Kim, Jeonggeun Seo, Youngtae Kim, Youngsun Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified optical platform for non-Gaussian and fault-tolerant Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum technologies, encompassing communication, computation, and metrology, rely on the generation and control of non-Gaussian states of light. These states enable secure quantum communication, fault-tolerant quantum computation, and precision sensing beyond classical limits, yet their practical realisation remains a major challenge due to reliance on high-photon-number Fock states or strong non-linearities. Here we introduce a unified optical framework that removes this constraint, using only Gaussian inputs, optical parametric amplification, and heralded photon detection. Within a single architecture, we demonstrate the generation of photon-added squeezed states with near unit fidelity, cubic-phase-like states with strong non-linearities and fidelities above 98.5%, and squeezed-cat states exceeding 99% fidelity that can be iteratively bred into GKP grid states surpassing the 9.75 dB fault-tolerance threshold. Operating entirely below 3 dB of input squeezing, the approach provides a scalable, experimentally accessible platform that unites the state resources required for quantum communication, metrology, and computation within one coherent optical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02607v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ozlem Erkilic, Aritra Das, Biveen Shajilal, Ping Koy Lam, Timothy C. Ralph, Syed M. Assad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum LLMs Using Quantum Computing to Analyze and Process Semantic Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a quantum computing approach to analyzing Large Language Model (LLM) embeddings, leveraging complex-valued representations and modeling semantic relationships using quantum mechanical principles. By establishing a direct mapping between LLM semantic spaces and quantum circuits, we demonstrate the feasibility of estimating semantic similarity using quantum hardware. One of the key results is the experimental calculation of cosine similarity between Google Sentence Transformer embeddings using a real quantum computer, providing a tangible demonstration of a quantum approach to semantic analysis. This work reveals a connection between LLMs and quantum mechanics, suggesting that these principles can offer new perspectives on semantic representation and processing, and paving the way for future development of quantum algorithms for natural language processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02619v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timo Aukusti Laine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-harmonic generation from two weakly coupled molecules: a simple tight-binding model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The generation of high harmonics is a strongly nonlinear effect that allows to probe properties of the target and to study electron dynamics in matter. It has been investigated in many different kinds of targets, including molecular gases, liquids and solids. Recently, high-harmonic generation was studied in organic molecular crystals by Wiechmann et al. [Nat. Commun. 16, 9890 (2025)]. It was found that the laser-polarization-dependent harmonic yield is sensitive to the weak couplings between nearest- and next-nearest-neighbor molecules. In this paper, the impact of the laser polarization angle and the intermolecular interaction on the harmonic yield is examined in detail using a simple but insightful two-dimensional tight-binding system that models a molecular dimer, i.e. two weakly coupled molecules. We find that the intensities of lower harmonic orders tend to maximize for a laser polarization direction aligning with the molecular axes, whereas higher harmonic orders rather show the strongest yield for a polarization direction along the intermolecular axis. We further demonstrate that the harmonic order at which the maximum flips from the molecular to the intermolecular direction strongly depends on the intermolecular coupling strength. To gain a deeper insight into the origins of the findings, we include a detailed adiabatic analysis, showing that the flipping of the maximum yield towards the intermolecular direction is already contained qualitatively in the adiabatically following states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02623v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lina Bielke, Samuel Sch\"opa, Falk-Erik Wiechmann, Franziska Fennel, Dieter Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiplet technology for large-scale trapped-ion quantum processors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trapped ions are among the most promising platforms for realizing a large-scale quantum information processor. Current progress focuses on integrating optical and electronic components into microfabricated ion traps to allow scaling to large numbers of ion qubits. Most available fabrication strategies for such integrated processors employ monolithic integration of all processor components and rely heavily on CMOS-compatible semiconductor fabrication technologies that are not optimized for the requirements of a trapped-ion quantum processor. In this work, we present a modular approach in which the processor modules, called chiplets, have specific functions and are fabricated separately. The individual chiplets are then combined using heterogeneous integration techniques. This strategy opens up the possibility of choosing the optimal materials and fabrication technology for each of the chiplets, with a minimum amount of fabrication limitations compared to the monolithic approach. Chiplet technology furthermore enables novel processor functionalities to be added in a cost-effective, modular fashion by adding or modifying only a subset of the chiplets. We describe the design concept of a chiplet-based trapped-ion quantum processor and demonstrate the technology with an example of an integrated individual-ion addressing system for a ten-ion crystal. The addressing system emphasizes the modularity of the chiplet approach, combining a surface ion trap manufactured on a glass substrate with a silicon substrate carrying integrated waveguides and a stack of 3D-printed micro-optics, achieving diffraction-limited focal spots at the ion positions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02645v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bassem Badawi, Philip C. Holz, Michael Raffetseder, Nicolas Jungwirth, Juris Ulmanis, Hans-Joachim Quenzer, Dirk K\"ahler, Thomas Monz, Philipp Schindler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Simulation of the 2D Hubbard Model via Hilbert Space-Filling Curve Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate tensor network simulations of the two-dimensional Hubbard model by mapping the lattice onto a one-dimensional chain using space-filling curves. In particular, we focus on the Hilbert curve, whose locality-preserving structure minimizes the range of effective interactions in the mapped model. This enables a more compact matrix product state (MPS) representation compared to conventional snake mapping. Through systematic benchmarks, we show that the Hilbert curve consistently yields lower ground-state energies at fixed bond dimension, with the advantage increasing for larger system sizes and in physically relevant interaction regimes. Our implementation reaches clusters up to $32\times32$ sites with open and periodic boundary conditions, delivering reliable ground-state energies and correlation functions in agreement with established results, but at significantly reduced computational cost. These findings establish space-filling curve mappings, particularly the Hilbert curve, as a powerful tool for extending tensor-network studies of strongly correlated two-dimensional quantum systems beyond the limits accessible with standard approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02666v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashkan Abedi, Vittorio Giovannetti, Dario De Santis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-node quantum key distribution network using existing underground optical fibre infrastructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum key distribution (QKD) offers unconditional information security by allowing two distant users to establish a common encryption key resilient to hacking. Resultingly, QKD networks interconnecting critical infrastructure and enabling the secure exchange of classified information, can provide a solution to the increasing number of successful cyberattacks. To efficiently deploy quantum networks, the technology must be integrated over existing communication infrastructure, such as optical fibre links. Yet, QKD poses stringent requirements on the conditions of the network over which it is deployed. This work demonstrates the first quantum communication network in Cyprus via the deployment of a multi-node quantum network, exploiting existing commercial underground optical fibre. The network employs bidirectional occupation of fibres and wavelength multiplexing in a ring architecture to achieve, with minimal use of dark fibres, high-rate QKD. Results obtained reveal consistent key generation rates across all nodes, confirming reliable operation in a real-world environment. This deployment highlights the feasibility of leveraging existing telecom infrastructure for quantum-secured communication, marking a significant step toward scalable and cost-effective quantum networks suited for critical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02701v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/12.3066715</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. SPIE 13522, Eighth International Workshop on Specialty Optical Fibers and Their Applications (WSOF 2025), 1352219 (29 May 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mariella Minder, Andreas Siakolas, Stephanos Yerolatsitis, Konstantinos Katzis, Kyriacos Kalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lectures on Quantum Field Theory on a Quantum Computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The lecture notes cover the basics of quantum computing methods for quantum field theory applications. No detailed knowledge of either quantum computing or quantum field theory is assumed and we have attempted to keep the material at a pedagogical level. We review the anharmonic oscillator, using which we develop a hands-on treatment of certain interesting QFTs in $1+1D$: $\phi^4$ theory, Ising field theory, and the Schwinger model. We review quantum computing essentials as well as tensor network techniques. The latter form an essential part for quantum computing benchmarking. Some error modelling on QISKIT is also done in the hope of anticipating runs on NISQ devices.
  These lecture notes are the expanded version of a one semester course taught by AS during August-November 2025 at the Indian Institute of Science and TA-ed by UB. The programs written for this course are available in a GitHub repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02706v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aninda Sinha, Ujjwal Basumatary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative modeling using evolved quantum Boltzmann machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Born-rule generative modeling, a central task in quantum machine learning, seeks to learn probability distributions that can be efficiently sampled by measuring complex quantum states. One hope is for quantum models to efficiently capture probability distributions that are difficult to learn and simulate by classical means alone. Quantum Boltzmann machines were proposed about one decade ago for this purpose, yet efficient training methods have remained elusive. In this paper, I overcome this obstacle by proposing a practical solution that trains quantum Boltzmann machines for Born-rule generative modeling. Two key ingredients in the proposal are the Donsker-Varadhan variational representation of the classical relative entropy and the quantum Boltzmann gradient estimator of [Patel et al., arXiv:2410.12935]. I present the main result for a more general ansatz known as an evolved quantum Boltzmann machine [Minervini et al., arXiv:2501.03367], which combines parameterized real- and imaginary-time evolution. I also show how to extend the findings to other distinguishability measures beyond relative entropy. Finally, I present four different hybrid quantum-classical algorithms for the minimax optimization underlying training, and I discuss their theoretical convergence guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02721v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Modulation of Long Range Photon Magnon Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Evidence of non-hermitian behavior has been recently demonstrated in cavity magnonics, including the emergence of mode level attraction and exceptional points in spectroscopic measurements. This work demonstrates experimental evidence of time-domain dynamics of magnon-photon systems that are coupled through a long-range interaction (i.e. remote coupling) exhibiting level attraction mediated by an auxiliary mode. We directly observe the temporal evolution of dissipatively coupled cavity-magnon modes, where heavily damped transmission line modes mediate the interaction. Our frequency-domain measurements confirm the predicted level attraction, while time-domain ring-down measurements reveal the characteristic signatures of dissipative coupling dynamics. Our approach offers in situ tunability over the dissipative coupling strength, including complete suppression, without requiring physical modifications to the experimental setup, providing a versatile platform for exploring tunable, non-Hermitian physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02732v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alban Joseph, Mawgan A. Smith, Martin P. Weides, Rair Mac\^edo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal decomposition entropy and optimal representations of absolutely maximally entangled states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding and classifying multipartite entanglement is fundamental to quantum information processing. A useful measure of multipartite entanglement is the minimal decomposition entropy, defined as the minimum of the R\'enyi entropy $ S_q $ associated with the state's decomposition over all local product bases. This quantity identifies the product bases in which the state is maximally localized, thereby yielding optimal representations for analyzing local-unitary equivalence and structural properties of multipartite states.
  We investigate the minimal decomposition entropy for absolutely maximally entangled (AME) states, a class of highly entangled states characterized by their maximal entanglement across any bipartitions. We present a numerical algorithm for computing the minimal decomposition entropy for finite $ q&gt;1 $. Entropy distributions for AME and Haar random states are obtained for $ q=2 $ and $ q=\infty $ in qubit, qutrit, and ququad systems. For $ q=2 $, AME states of four qutrits and four ququads exhibit smaller minimal decomposition entropy than Haar random states, indicating more localized optimal representations. For $ q=\infty $, corresponding to the geometric measure of entanglement, AME states display higher entanglement than Haar random states. The algorithm additionally produces simpler and sparser decompositions of known AME states, aiding in distinguishing genuinely quantum AME states from those associated with classical combinatorial designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02749v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N Ramadas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of non-Hermitian many-body phase transition in a Rydberg-atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian quantum mechanics with parity-time (PT) symmetry offers a powerful framework for exploring the complex interplay of dissipation and coherent interactions in open quantum systems. While PT-symmetry breaking has been studied in various physical systems, its observation on a quantum many-body level remains elusive. Here, we experimentally realize a non-Hermitian XY model in a strongly-interacting Rydberg-atom array. By measuring the Loschmidt Echo of a fully polarized state, we observe distinct dynamical signatures of a PT-symmetry-breaking phase transition. Dipole interactions are found to play a crucial role, not only determining the transition point but also triggering a non-Hermitian many-body blockade effect that protects the Loschmidt Echo from decay with a non-monotonic dependence on the system size. Our results reveal intricate interaction-induced effects on PT-symmetry breaking and open the door for exploring non-Hermitian many-body dynamics beyond single-particle and mean-field paradigms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02753v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao-Wen Zhang, Biao Xu, Yijia Zhou, De-Sheng Xiang, Hao-Xiang Liu, Peng Zhou, Kuan Zhang, Ren Liao, Thomas Pohl, Weibin Li, Lin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fault-tolerant quantum computation with constant overhead for general noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fault-tolerant quantum computation traditionally incurs substantial resource overhead, with both qubit and time overheads scaling polylogarithmically with the size of the computation. While prior work by Gottesman showed that constant qubit overhead is achievable under stochastic noise using quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes, it has remained an open question whether similar guarantees hold under more general, non-stochastic noise models. In this work, we address this question by considering a general circuit-level noise model defined via the diamond norm, which captures both stochastic and non-stochastic noise, including coherent and amplitude damping noise. We prove that constant qubit overhead fault-tolerant quantum computation is achievable in this general setting, using QLDPC codes with constant rate and linear minimum distance. To establish our result, we develop a fault-tolerant error correction scheme and a method for implementing logic gates under general circuit noise. These results extend the theoretical foundations of fault-tolerant quantum computation and offer new directions for fault-tolerant architectures under realistic noise models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02760v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/k4cm-pp9p</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 040334, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Christandl, Omar Fawzi, Ashutosh Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of slowly decaying long-range interactions on topological qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the robustness of topological ground state degeneracy to long-range interactions in quantum many-body systems. We focus on slowly decaying two-body interactions that scale like a power-law $1/r^\alpha$ where $\alpha$ is smaller than the spatial dimension; such interactions are beyond the reach of known stability theorems which only apply to short-range or rapidly decaying long-range perturbations. Our main result is a computation of the ground state splitting of several toy models, which are variants of the 1D Ising model $H = -\sum_i \sigma^z_i \sigma^z_{i+1} + \lambda \sum_{ij} |i-j|^{-\alpha} \sigma^x_i \sigma^x_j$ with $\lambda &gt; 0$ and $\alpha &lt; 1$. These models are also closely connected to the Kitaev p-wave wire model with power-law density-density interactions. In these examples, we find that the splitting $\delta$ scales like a stretched exponential $\delta \sim \exp(-C L^{\frac{1+\alpha}{2}})$ where $L$ is the system size. Our computations are based on path integral techniques similar to the instanton method introduced by Coleman. We also study another toy model with long-range interactions that can be analyzed without path integral techniques and that shows similar behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02809v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etienne Granet, Michael Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation and Analysis of Quantum Majority Rules under Noisy Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum voting, inspired by quantum game theory, provides a framework in which the quantum majority rule (QMR) constitution of Bao and Yunger Halpern [Phys. Rev. A 95, 062306 (2017)] violates the quantum analogue of Arrow's impossibility theorem. We evaluate this QMR constitution analytically on classical profile data and implement its final measurement stage as a quantum circuit, running on both noiseless simulators and noisy IBM quantum hardware to map how realistic noise deforms the resulting societal ranking distribution. Moderate-high single-qubit noise does not change the qualitative behavior of QMR, whereas strong noise shifts the distribution toward other dominant winners than the classical one. We quantify this behavior using winner-agreement rates, Condorcet-winner flip rates, and Jensen-Shannon divergence between societal ranking distributions. In a second, exploratory component, we demonstrate an explicitly entanglement-based variant of the QMR constitution that serves as a testbed for multi-voter quantum correlations under noise, which we refer to as the QMR2-inspired variant. There, GHZ-type and separable superpositions over opposite rankings have the same expectation values but respond very differently to noise. Taken together, these two components connect the abstract QMR constitution to concrete implementations on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices and highlight design considerations for future quantum voting protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02813v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gal Amit, Yuval Idan, Michael Suleymanov, Luis Razo, Eliahu Cohen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phononic Casimir Effect in Planar Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Phononic Casimir effect between planar objects is investigated by deriving a formalism from the quantum partition function of the system following multiscattering approach. This fluctuation-induced coupling is mediated by phonons modeled as an effective elastic medium. We find that excitations with three types of polarizations arise from the resolved boundary conditions, however the coupling is dominated by only one of these degrees of freedom due to exponential suppression effects in the other two. The obtained scaling laws and dependence on materials properties and temperature suggest effective pathways of interaction control. Scenarios of materials combinations are envisioned where the Phononic Casimir effect is of similar order as the standard Casimir interaction mediated by electromagnetic fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02815v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Rodriguez-Lopez, Dai-Nam Le, Lilia M. Woods</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Blueprint for Distinguishing Decoherence from Objective Collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition from the quantum to the classical realm remains one of the most profound open questions in physics. While quantum theory predicts the existence of macroscopic superpositions, their apparent absence in the everyday world is attributed either to environmental decoherence or to an intrinsic mechanism for wave-function collapse. This work presents a quantitative and experimentally grounded framework for distinguishing these possibilities. We propose a levitated optomechanical platform capable of generating controllable Schrodinger-cat states in the center of mass motion of a dielectric nanosphere. A comprehensive master equation incorporates gas collisions, black-body radiation, and photon-recoil noise, establishing a calibrated environmental baseline. The Continuous Spontaneous Localization (CSL) model is embedded within the same framework, predicting a characteristic saturation of the decoherence rate with superposition size and a quadratic scaling with mass. A Bayesian inference protocol is outlined to discriminate collapse induced excess decoherence from environmental noise. Together these elements provide a concrete experimental blueprint for a decisive test of quantum linearity, either revealing new physics beyond standard quantum mechanics or setting the most stringent bounds to date on objective-collapse parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02838v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ridha Horchani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Symmetrizability in Physical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the problem of data transmission under the influence of a jammer, which is typical for wireless systems and commonly modeled as an arbitrarily varying channel (AVC) in information theory. AVC fulfilling a certain set of linear equations are called symmetrizable and are known to be prone to denial of service attacks. Recent work has shown that deciding if a given AVC is symmetrizable or not is a non-Turing computable problem. By relaxing the formulation of symmetrizability, we show the existence of a polynomial-time algorithm that determines whether a given AVC is non-symmetrizable, but displays a critical dependence on the number of jammer input states. We then show how imposing an energy constraint on the jammer allows the same algorithm to efficiently identify large classes of AVCs which are non-symmetrizable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02869v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Seitz, Janis N\"otzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDQC: Distributed Quantum Computing Architecture Utilizing Entangled Ion Qubit Shuttling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose Shuttling-based Distributed Quantum Computing (SDQC), a hybrid architecture that combines the strengths of physical qubit shuttling and distributed quantum computing to enable scalable trapped-ion quantum computing. SDQC performs non-local quantum operations by distributing entangled ion qubits via deterministic shuttling, combining the high-fidelity and deterministic operations of shuttling-based architectures with the parallelism and pipelining advantages of distributed quantum computing. We present (1) a practical architecture incorporating quantum error correction (QEC), (2) pipelining strategies to exploit parallelism in entanglement distribution and measurement, and (3) a performance evaluation in terms of logical error rate and clock speed. For a 256-bit elliptic-curve discrete logarithm problem (ECDLP) instance, which requires 2,871 logical qubits at code distance 13, SDQC achieves a logical error rate which is $1.20^{+0.94}_{-0.45}\times10^{-8}$ of Photonic DQC error rate and $3.79^{+5.09}_{-2.84}\times10^{-3}$ of Quantum Charge-Coupled Device (QCCD) error rate, while providing 2.82 times faster logical clock speed than QCCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02890v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seunghyun Baek, Seok-Hyung Lee, Dongmoon Min, Junki Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-series forecasting with multiphoton quantum states and integrated photonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning algorithms have very recently attracted significant attention in photonic platforms. In particular, reconfigurable integrated photonic circuits offer a promising route, thanks to the possibility of implementing adaptive feedback loops, which is an essential ingredient for achieving the necessary nonlinear behavior characteristic of neural networks. Here, we implement a quantum reservoir computing protocol in which information is processed through a reconfigurable linear optical integrated photonic circuit and measured using single-photon detectors. We exploit a multiphoton-based setup for time-series forecasting tasks in a variety of scenarios, where the input signal is encoded in one of the circuit's optical phases, thus modulating the quantum reservoir state. The resulting output probabilities are used to set the feedback phases and, at the end of the computation, are fed to a classical digital layer trained via linear regression to perform predictions. We then focus on the investigation of the role of input photon indistinguishability in the reservoir's capabilities of predicting time-series. We experimentally demonstrate that two-photon indistinguishable input states lead to significantly better performance compared to distinguishable ones. This enhancement arises from the quantum correlations present in indistinguishable states, which enable the system to approximate higher-order nonlinear functions when using comparable physical resources, highlighting the importance of quantum interference and indistinguishability as a resource in photonic quantum reservoir computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02928v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rosario Di Bartolo, Simone Piacentini, Francesco Ceccarelli, Giacomo Corrielli, Roberto Osellame, Valeria Cimini, Fabio Sciarrino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of quantum chaos against weak non-unitarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02934v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the quantum dynamics generated by the repeated action of a non-unitary evolution operator on a system of qubits. Breaking unitarity can lead to the purification of mixed initial states, which corresponds to the loss of sensitivity to initial conditions, and hence the absence of a key signature of dynamical chaos. However, the scrambling of quantum information can delay purification to times that are exponential in system size. Here we study purification in systems whose evolution operators are fixed in time, where all aspects of the dynamics are in principle encoded in spectral properties of the evolution operator for a single time step. The operators that we study consist of global Haar random unitary operators and non-unitary single-qubit operations. We show that exponentially slow purification arises from a distribution of eigenvalues in the complex plane that forms a ring with sharp edges at large radii, with the eigenvalue density exponentially large near these edges. We argue that the sharp edges of the eigenvalue distribution arise from level attraction along the radial direction in the complex plane. By calculating the spectral form factor we also show that there is level repulsion around the azimuthal direction, even close to the outer edge of the ring of eigenvalues. Our results connect this spectral signature of quantum chaos to the sensitivity of the system to its initial conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02934v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Cheng Wang, Ehud Altman, Samuel J. Garratt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Quantum Walk-Based Heuristics for the Minimum Vertex Cover Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel heuristic quantum algorithm for the Minimum Vertex Cover (MVC) problem based on continuous-time quantum walks (CTQWs). In this framework, the coherent propagation of a quantum walker over a graph encodes its structural properties into state amplitudes, enabling the identification of highly influential vertices through their transition probabilities. To enhance stability and solution quality, we introduce a dynamic decoupling (``freezing'') mechanism that isolates vertices already selected for the cover, preventing their interference in subsequent iterations of the algorithm. The method employs a compact binary encoding, requiring only $\lceil \log_2 (V)\rceil$ qubits to represent a graph with $V$ vertices, resulting in an exponential reduction of quantum resources compared to conventional vertex-based encodings. We benchmark the proposed heuristic against exact solutions obtained via Mixed-Integer Linear Programming (MILP) and against established classical heuristics, including Simulated Annealing, FastVC, and the 2-Approximation algorithm, across Erd\H{o}s--R\'enyi, Barab\'asi--Albert and regular random graph ensembles. Our results demonstrate that the CTQW-based heuristic consistently achieves superior approximation ratios and exhibits remarkable robustness with respect to network topology, outperforming classical approaches in both heterogeneous and homogeneous structures. These findings indicate that continuous-time quantum walks, when combined with topology-independent decoupling strategies, provide a powerful paradigm for large-scale combinatorial optimization and complex network control, with potential applications spanning infrastructure resilience, epidemic containment, sensor network optimization, and biological systems analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02940v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. S. Luiz, A. K. F. Iwakami, D. H. Moraes, M. C. de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum hypergraph states: a concise review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum hypergraph states emerged in the literature as a generalization of graph states, and since then, much has been developed in the direction of implementing this class of genuine multipartite entangled states for quantum information and computation. Here, we review the definition of hypergraph states and their main applications so far, both in discrete-variable and continuous-variable quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02955v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vin\'icius Salem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic construction of ROCN Bell-inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-testing constitutes one of the most powerful forms of device certification, enabling a complete and device-independent characterization of a quantum apparatus solely from the observed correlations. In recent work by the authors [23], a general framework was introduced for constructing Bell inequalities that self-test entire families of Clifford generators. In this manuscript, we develop an alternative and complementary self-testing criterion based on symmetric spanning sets. This formulation provides an explicit and constructive route to designing self-testing Bell inequalities in arbitrary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02957v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arturo Konderak, Patryk Michalski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body $k$-local ground states as probes for unitary quantum metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multipartite quantum states saturating the Heisenberg limit of sensitivity typically require full-body correlators to be prepared. On the other hand, experimentally practical Hamiltonians often involve few-body correlators only. Here, we study the metrological performances under this constraint, using tools derived from the quantum Fisher information. Our work applies to any encoding generator, also including a dependence on the parameter. We find that typical random symmetric ground states of $k$-body permutation-invariant Hamiltonians exhibit Heisenberg scaling. Finally, we establish a tradeoff between the Hamiltonian's gap, which quantifies preparation hardness, and the quantum Fisher information of the corresponding ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02976v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Majid Hassani, Mengyao Hu, Guillem M\"uller-Rigat, Matteo Fadel, Jordi Tura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured Clifford+T Circuits for Efficient Generation of Quantum Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of quantum chaos and unitary T-design behavior in derandomized Clifford+T circuits using causal cover architectures. Motivated by the need for deterministic constructions that can exhibit chaotic behavior across diverse quantum hardware platforms, we explore deterministic Clifford circuit architectures (random Clifford circuits with causal cover, bitonic sorting networks, and permutation-based routing circuits) to drive quantum circuits toward Wigner-Dyson (WD) entanglement spectrum statistics and OTOC decay.Our experiments demonstrate that causal connectivity, not circuit depth or randomness, is a critical feature that drives circuits to chaos. We show that initializing with n T-states and adding a second T-layer after a causally covered Clifford evolution yields consistent OTOC decay and WD statistics. This also enables deeper understanding of the circuit structures that generate complex entanglement behavior. Notably, our work suggests polylogarithmic-depth deterministic circuits suffice to approximate chaotic behavior, highlighting that causal connectivity is sufficient for operator spreading to induce Wigner-Dyson entanglement statistics and OTOC decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02996v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asim Sharma, Avah Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial foundations for solvable chaotic local Euclidean quantum circuits in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a graph-theoretic problem motivated by questions in quantum computing concerning the propagation of information in quantum circuits. A graph $G$ is said to be a bounded extension of its subgraph $L$ if they share the same vertex set, and the graph distance $d_L(u, v)$ is uniformly bounded for edges $uv\in G$. Given vertices $u, v$ in $G$ and an integer $k$, the geodesic slice $S(u, v, k)$ denotes the subset of vertices $w$ lying on a geodesic in $G$ between $u$ and $v$ with $d_G(u, w) = k$. We say that $G$ has bounded geodesic slices if $|S(u, v, k)|$ is uniformly bounded over all $u, v, k$. We call a graph $L$ geodesically directable if it has a bounded extension $G$ with bounded geodesic slices.
  Contrary to previous expectations, we prove that $\mathbb{Z}^2$ is geodesically directable. Physically, this provides a setting in which one could devise exactly-solvable chaotic local quantum circuits with non-trivial correlation patterns on 2D Euclidean lattices. In fact, we show that any bounded extension of $\mathbb{Z}^2$ is geodesically directable. This further implies that all two-dimensional regular tilings are geodesically directable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03029v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fredy Yip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information dynamics and symmetry breaking in generic monitored $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetric open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the steady-state phases of generic $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetric monitored, open quantum dynamics. We describe the phases systematically in terms of both information-theoretic diagnostics and spontaneous breaking of strong and weak symmetries of the dynamics. We find a completely broken phase where information is retained by the quantum system, a strong-to-weak broken phase where information is leaked to the environment, and an unbroken phase where information is learned by the observer. We find that weak measurement and dephasing alone constitute a minimal model for generic open systems with $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry, but we also explore perturbations by unitary gates. For a 1d set of qubits, we examine information-theoretic and symmetry-breaking observables in the path integral of the doubled state. This path integral reduces to the standard classical 2d random-bond Ising model in certain limits but generically involves negative weights, enabling a special self-dual random-bond Ising model at the critical point when only measurements are present. We obtain numerical evidence for the steady-state phases using efficient tensor network simulations of the doubled state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03031v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Hauser, Ali Lavasani, Sagar Vijay, Matthew P. A. Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covert Communication Over a Quantum MAC with a Helper</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study covert classical communication over a quantum multiple-access channel (MAC) with a helper. Specifically, we consider three transmitters, where one transmitter helps the other two transmitters communicate covertly with a receiver. We demonstrate the feasibility of achieving a positive covert rate over this channel and establish an achievable rate region. Our result recovers as a special case known results for classical communication over classical MACs with a degraded message set, classical communication over quantum MACs, and classical communication over MACs with a helper. To the best of our knowledge, our result is the first to achieve covert communication with positive rates over both classical and quantum MACs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18747v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan ZivariFard, R\'emi A. Chou, Xiaodong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order spectral form factors of circular unitary ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spectral form factor (SFF), one of the key quantity from random matrix theory, serves as an important tool to probe universality in disordered quantum systems and quantum chaos. In this work, we present exact closed-form expressions for the second- and third-order SFFs in the circular unitary ensemble (CUE), valid for all real values of the time parameter, and analyze their asymptotic behavior in different regimes. In particular, for the second-order SFF, we derive an exact closed-form expression in terms of polygamma functions. In the limit of infinite matrix size, and when the time parameter is restricted to integer values, the second-order SFF reproduces the standard result established in earlier studies. When the time parameter is of order one relative to the matrix size, we demonstrate that the second-order SFF grows logarithmically with the ensemble dimension. For the third-order SFFs, a closed-form result in a special case is obtained by exploiting the translational invariance of CUE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01304v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Sohail, Youyi Huang, Lu Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The measurement-induced phase transition in strongly disordered spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of strongly disordered spin chains in the presence of random local measurements. By studying the transverse-field Ising model with a site-dependent random longitudinal field and an effective $l$-bit many-body localized Hamiltonian, we show that the prethermal and MBL regimes are unstable to local measurements along any direction. Any non-zero measurement density induces a volume-law entangled phase with a subsequent phase transition into an area-law state as the measurement rate is further increased. The critical measurement rate $p_c$, where the transition occurs, is exponentially small in the strength of disorder $W$ and the average overlap between the measurement operator and the local integrals of motion $O$ as $p_c \sim \exp[-\alpha W/(1-O^2)]$. In the measurement-induced volume-law phase, the saturation time scales as $t_s \sim L $, contrasting the exponentially slow saturation $t_s \sim e^{aL}$ in the prethermal and MBL regimes at $p = 0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02100v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Tang, Pradip Kattel, Arijeet Pal, Emil A. Yuzbashyan, J. H. Pixley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum entanglement at colliders: the $H \to WW,ZZ$ case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02104v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address momentum entanglement in Higgs decays to weak boson pairs, $H \to WW,ZZ$, by discretising momentum space. The momenta of the two weak bosons are entangled, as well as the degrees of freedom in momentum and spin spaces. For $H \to ZZ$ in the four-lepton final state, we also estimate the statistical sensitivity of entanglement measures at the Large Hadron Collider and future upgrades. The discretisation method introduced here is broadly applicable, offering a framework for studies of momentum entanglement at the energy frontier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02104v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Aguilar-Saavedra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalies on the Lattice, Homotopy of Quantum Cellular Automata, and a Spectrum of Invertible States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02105v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a rigorous topological theory of anomalies on the lattice, which are obstructions to gauging global symmetries and the existence of trivial symmetric states. We also construct $\Omega$-spectra of a class of invertible states and quantum cellular automata, which allows us to classify both anomalies and symmetry protected topological phases up to blend equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02105v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander M. Czajka, Roman Geiko, Ryan Thorngren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing fusion rules by shuffle: Symmetry-based classifications of nonlocal systems constructed from similarity transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study fusion rings, or symmetry topological field theories (SymTFTs), which lie outside the non-negative integer matrix representation (NIM-rep), by combining knowledge from generalized symmetry and that from pseudo-Hermitian systems. By applying the Galois shuffle operation to the SymTFTs, we reconstruct fusion rings that correspond to nonlocal CFTs constructed from the corresponding local nonunitary CFTs by applying the similarity transformations. The resultant SymTFTs are outside of NIM-rep, whereas they are ring isomorphic to the NIM-rep of the corresponding local nonunitary CFTs. We study the consequences of this correspondence between the nonlocal unitary model and local nonunitary models. We demonstrate the correspondence between their classifications of massive or massless renormalization group flows and the discrepancies between their boundary or domain wall phenomena. Our work reveals a new connection between ring isomorphism and similarity transformations, providing the fundamental implications of ring-theoretic ideas in the context of symmetry in physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02139v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi, Taishi Kawamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty Principle and Angular Momentum Generation in Microscopic Fission Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02207v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The generation of angular momentum (intrinsic spin) in fission fragments has recently attracted renewed attention. While several microscopic approaches reproduce the spin distribution qualitatively using projection techniques, the physical origin of the fragments' angular momentum in density functional theory remains unclear. In this work, we investigate the mechanisms responsible for the spin distribution of fission fragments within a microscopic TDDFT framework. We compare spin distributions obtained from projection operators with those predicted by a simple expression derived from the uncertainty relation between angle and angular momentum, where angular fluctuations are estimated using a Monte Carlo sampling of nucleon positions. We find that a large portion of the spin distribution obtained from projection methods can be explained by the uncertainty principle. Our results thus show that, within microscopic approaches, the spin of fission fragments originates primarily from quantum uncertainty associated with their orientation angle with respect to the fission axis, mainly due to quadrupole deformation and, to a lesser extent, octupole deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02207v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Scamps, A. Guilleux, D. Regnier, A. Bernard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric effect in the mixed valence polyoxovanadate cage V$_{12}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02215v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Development of spintronic and quantum computing devices increases demand for efficient, energy saving method of spin manipulation at molecular scale. Polyoxovanadate molecular magnets being susceptible to both electric and magnetic fields may serve here as a good base material. In this paper two isostructural anions [V$_{12}$As$_8$O$_{40}$(HCO$_2$)]$^{n-}$ (with $n=3,5$) featuring two different mixed-valence states with itinerant and localized valence electrons are studied. The impact of the electric field on their magnetic properties is investigated by means of two complementary methods informed by magnetic measurements: effective Hamiltonian calculations and density functional theory. It is demonstrated that the magnetoelectric effect in theses molecules is induced mostly by relocation of itinerant electrons, is highly anisotropic, depends on the valence state and can be detected even at room temperature. These findings can pave the way to practical applications in which an electric field control over spin state is required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02215v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Koz{\l}owski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the Power of Boltzmann Machines by Parallelizable Sampler and Efficient Temperature Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02323v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Boltzmann machines (BMs) are powerful energy-based generative models, but their heavy training cost has largely confined practical use to Restricted BMs (RBMs) trained with an efficient learning method called contrastive divergence. More accurate learning typically requires Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) Boltzmann sampling, but it is time-consuming due to the difficulty of parallelization for more expressive models. To address this limitation, we first propose a new Boltzmann sampler inspired by a quantum-inspired combinatorial optimization called simulated bifurcation (SB). This SB-inspired approach, which we name Langevin SB (LSB), enables parallelized sampling while maintaining accuracy comparable to MCMC. Furthermore, this is applicable not only to RBMs but also to BMs with general couplings. However, LSB cannot control the inverse temperature of the output Boltzmann distribution, which hinders learning and degrades performance. To overcome this limitation, we also developed an efficient method for estimating the inverse temperature during the learning process, which we call conditional expectation matching (CEM). By combining LSB and CEM, we establish an efficient learning framework for BMs with greater expressive power than RBMs. We refer to this framework as sampler-adaptive learning (SAL). SAL opens new avenues for energy-based generative modeling beyond RBMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02323v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Kubo, Hayato Goto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Quantum Simulation of Non-Adiabatic Molecular Dynamics with Precise Electronic Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the study of non-adiabatic chemical processes such as photocatalysis and photosynthesis, non-adiabatic molecular dynamics (NAMD) is an indispensable theoretical tool, which requires precise potential energy surfaces (PESs) of ground and excited states. Quantum computing offers promising potential for calculating PESs that are intractable for classical computers. However, its realistic application poses significant challenges to the development of quantum algorithms that are sufficiently general to enable efficient and precise PES calculations across chemical systems with diverse properties, as well as to seamlessly adapt existing NAMD theories to quantum computing. In this work, we introduce a quantum-adapted extension to the Landau-Zener-Surface-Hopping (LZSH) NAMD. This extension incorporates curvature-driven hopping corrections that protect the population evolution while maintaining the efficiency gained from avoiding the computation of non-adiabatic couplings (NACs), as well as preserving the trajectory independence that enables parallelization. Furthermore, to ensure the high-precision PESs required for surface hopping dynamics, we develop a sub-microhartree-accurate PES calculation protocol. This protocol supports active space selection, enables parallel acceleration either on quantum or classical clusters, and demonstrates adaptability to diverse chemical systems - including the charged H3+ ion and the C2H4 molecule, a prototypical multi-reference benchmark. This work paves the way for practical application of quantum computing in NAMD, showcasing the potential of parallel simulation on quantum-classical heterogeneous clusters for ab-initio computational chemistry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02376v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyi Li, Yumeng Zeng, Qiming Ding, Zixuan Huo, Xiaosi Xu, Jiajun Ren, Diandong Tang, Xiaoxia Cai, Xiao Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Coulomb drag signatures of Majorana bound states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Majorana bound states (MBSs), with their non-Abelian statistics and topological protection, are key candidates for fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, their unambiguous identification in solid-state systems remains a fundamental challenge. Here, we present a theoretical study demonstrating that drag transport in a capacitively coupled double quantum dot system offers a robust and nonlocal probe of weakly coupled MBSs. Using the master equation approach, we investigate both steady-state and transient dynamics and uncover a distinctive signature of MBSs, i.e., the emergence of pronounced split peaks in the drag transconductance, directly linked to inter-MBS coupling. We further show that the dynamics of quantum coherence exhibit an inverse correlation with the emergence and enhancement of MBS-induced split peaks in the drag transconductance as the inter-MBS coupling increases. A comparative analysis with Andreev bound states (ABSs) reveals key differences, that is, MBS-induced transconductance peaks are symmetric and robust, while ABS features are asymmetric and sensitive to perturbations. These findings establish clear experimental criteria for distinguishing MBSs and provide a practical framework for probing Majorana physics through nonlocal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02401v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Wei Li, Jiaojiao Chen, Wei Xiong, Xiao Xue, Zeng-Zhao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model driven by sequences of two unitaries: periodic, quasiperiodic and random protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02470v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the effect of driving the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model using two unitary operators $U_1$ and $U_2$ in different combinations; the unitaries differ in the values of the inter-cell hopping amplitudes. Specifically, we study the cases where the unitaries are applied periodically, quasiperiodically and randomly. For a periodic protocol, when $U_1$ and $U_2$ are applied alternately, we find that end modes may appear, but the number of end modes does not always agree with the winding number which is a $Z$-valued topological invariant. We then study the Loschmidt echo ($LE$) starting with a random initial state. We find that the $LE$ exhibits pronounced oscillations whose Fourier transform has peaks at frequencies which agree with the most prominent gaps between pairs of quasienergies. Next, when $U_1$ and $U_2$ are applied in a quasiperiodic way (we consider Fibonacci and Thue-Morse protocols), we study the $LE$ starting with an initial state which is an end mode of one of the unitaries. When the inter-cell hoppings differ by a small amount denoted by $\epsilon$, and the time period $T$ of each unitary is also small, the distance between the unitaries is found to be proportional to $\epsilon T$. We then find that the $LE$ oscillates around a particular value for a very long time before decaying to zero. The deviation of the value of the $LE$ from 1 scales as $\epsilon^2$ for a fixed value of $T$, while the time after which the $LE$ starts decaying to zero has an interesting dependence on $\epsilon$ and $T$. Finally, when $U_1$ and $U_2$ are applied in a random order, the $LE$ rapidly decays to zero with increasing time. We have presented a qualitative understanding of the above results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02470v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maitri Ganguli, Diptiman Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational regulation strategies of interstitial localized electrons in electride: A density functional theory study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02674v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As a class of electron-rich materials, electrides demonstrate promising applications in many fields. However, the required high pressure restricts the practical applications to some extent. This study reveals that the unique feature of electride, i.e., the localization of interstitial electrons, can be greatly enhanced and tuned by self-defective doping, applying tensile/compressive stress, or shear stress. Moreover, the requirement of orbital orthogonality between the valence and core electron wave functions, as well as the Pauli exclusion principle, should be the driven force for the electron interstitial localization; and the exertion of external pressure modifies the available space to accommodate the electronic wave functions, thus enhances the interstitial localization. These discoveries lay down the ground for searching for promising electrides that are practicable at ambient conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02674v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.commatsci.2025.114117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computational Materials Science 258 (2025) 114117</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. Zhang, D. Wang, H. Wang, J. Li, Y. F. Wang, Q. Wu, Hua Y. Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Mpemba effect through good observables in open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Mpemba effect refers to the anomalous relaxation of a quantum state that, despite being initially farther from equilibrium, relaxes faster than a closer counterpart. Detecting such a quantum Mpemba effect typically requires full knowledge of the quantum state during its time evolution, which is an experimentally challenging task since state tomography becomes exponentially difficult as system size increases. This poses a significant obstacle in studying Mpemba effect in complex many-body systems. In this work, we demonstrate that this limitation can be overcome by identifying suitable observables that signal rapid relaxation. Moreover, as long as the system equilibrates to a known unique steady-state, it is possible to fully detect the occurrence of quantum Mpemba effect just by measuring the observable for known state preparations. Our approach thus significantly reduces experimental complexity and offers a practical route for observing the quantum Mpemba effect in complex and extended multi-qubit setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02709v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pitambar Bagui, Arijit Chatterjee, Bijay Kumar Agarwalla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaching Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev physics by shaking the Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model has attracted widespread attention due to its relevance to diverse areas of physics, such as high temperature superconductivity, black holes, and quantum chaos. The model is, however, extremely challenging to realize experimentally. In this work, we show how a particular form of Floquet engineering, termed ``kinetic driving'', effectively eliminates single-particle processes and creates quasi-random all-to-all interactions when applied to models of Hubbard type. For the specific case of the Bose-Hubbard model, we explicitly verify that the driven system indeed reproduces SYK physics by direct comparison of the spectral form factor and out-of-time ordered correlation functions (OTOCs). Our findings indicate that a cold-atom realization of kinetic driving -- achieved through modulation of hopping amplitudes in an optical lattice -- offers a practical and accurate platform for quantum simulation of the SYK model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Creffield, Fernando Sols, Marco Schir\`o, Nathan Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Second-Order Topological Superconductors with Tunable Majorana Zero Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dirac semimetals, with their protected Dirac points, present an ideal platform for realizing intrinsic topological superconductivity. In this work, we investigate superconductivity in a two-dimensional, square-lattice nonsymmorphic Dirac semimetal. In the normal state near half-filling, the Fermi surface consists of two distinct pockets, each enclosing a Dirac point at a time-reversal invariant momentum ($\textbf{X}=(\pi,0)$ and $\textbf{Y}=(0,\pi)$). Considering an on-site repulsive and nearest-neighbor attractive interaction, we use self-consistent mean-field theory to determine the ground-state pairing symmetry. We find that an even-parity, spin-singlet $d_{x^{2}-y^{2}}$-wave pairing is favored as it gives rise to a fully gapped superconducting state. Since the pairing amplitude has opposite signs on the two Dirac Fermi pockets, the superconducting state is identified as a second-order topological superconductor. The hallmark of this topological phase is the emergence of Majorana zero modes at the system's boundaries. Notably, the positions of these Majorana modes are highly controllable and can be manipulated simply by tailoring the boundary sublattice terminations. Our results highlight the promise of nonsymmorphic Dirac semimetals for realizing and manipulating Majorana modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02775v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Jiao Wang, Yijie Mo, Zhi Wang, Zhigang Wu, Zhongbo Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of single-photon emission from neutral and charged excitons in a polarization-selective cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Single-photon sources based on neutral or charged excitons in a semiconductor quantum dot are attractive resources for photonic quantum computers and simulators. To obtain indistinguishable photons, the source is pumped on resonance with polarized laser pulses, and the output is collected in orthogonal polarization. However, for sources featuring vertical emission of light, 50% of the emitted photons are unavoidably lost in this way. Here, we theoretically study the quantum dynamics of an exciton embedded in an asymmetric vertical cavity that favors emission in a specific polarization. We identify the configuration for optimal state initialization and demonstrate a path toward near-unity polarized efficiency. We also derive simple analytical formulas for the photon output in each polarization as a function of the Purcell-enhanced emission rates, which shed light on the physical mechanism behind our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Vannucci, Niels Gregersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable giant Purcell enhancement of quantum light emitters by means of acoustic graphene plasmons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the remarkable ability of plasmons to boost radiative emission rates, we propose leveraging acoustic graphene plasmons (AGPs) to realize tunable, giant Purcell enhancements for single-photon, entangled-photon, and multipolar quantum emitters. These AGPs are localized inside a cavity defined by a graphene sheet and a metallic nanocube and filled with a dielectric of thickness of a few nanometers and consisting of stacked layers of 2D materials, containing impurities or defects that act as quantum light emitters. Through finite-difference time domain (FDTD) calculations, we show that this geometry can achieve giant Purcell enhancement factors over a large portion of the infrared (IR) spectrum, up to 6 orders of magnitude in the mid-IR and up to 4 orders of magnitude at telecommunications wavelengths, reaching quantum efficiencies of 95\% and 89\%, respectively, with high-mobility graphene. We obtain Purcell enhancement factors for single-photon electric dipole (E1), electric quadrupole (E2), and electric octupole (E3) transitions and two-photon spontaneous emission (2PSE) transitions, of the orders of $10^{4}$, $10^{7}$, $10^{9}$, and $10^9$, respectively, and a quantum efficiency of 79\% for entangled-photon emission with high-mobility graphene at a wavelength of $\lambda=1.55$ $\mu$m. Importantly, AGP mode frequencies depend on the graphene Fermi energy, which can be tuned via electrostatic gating to modulate fluorescence enhancement in real time. As an example, we consider the Purcell enhancement of spontaneous single- and two-photon emissions from an erbium atom inside single-layer (SL) WS$_2$. Our results could be useful for electrically tunable quantum emitter devices with applications in quantum communication and quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02907v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Gruber, Mahtab A. Khan, Dirk R. Englund, Michael N. Leuenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal nondiffractive topological spin textures in vortex cores of light and sound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report universal skyrmionic spin textures in the cores of optical and acoustic vortex beams, described within the framework of Laguerre-Gaussian modes. We analytically demonstrate nondiffractive propagating spin merons, independent of whether the field is transverse or longitudinal, with their sign controlled by the wavefront helicity. Experimental confirmation is provided in acoustics through full three-dimensional measurements of the velocity vector field. Although these phenomena are intrinsic to vortex cores, we also show that the claimed universality breaks down for higher-order topological charges, depending on the carrier mode, here exemplified using the Bessel framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02964v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Annenkova, Andrei Afanasev, Etienne Brasselet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable polarization-entangled near-infrared photons from orthogonal GaAs nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement is a fundamental resource for emerging quantum technologies, enabling secure communication and enhanced sensing. For decades, generating polarization entangled states has been mainly achieved using bulk crystals with spontaneous parametric down conversion (SPDC), preventing scalability and on-chip integration. Miniaturizing the quantum source provides access to more versatility and tunability while enabling an easier integration to other devices, notably necessary for satellite-based quantum communication, and eventually reducing fabrication costs. This challenging task can be achieved with Zinc Blende GaAs nanowires. They already have shown an efficient photon pairs generation via SPDC at 1550 nm. Here we demonstrate that a pair of orthogonal GaAs nanowires constitutes a new nanoscale platform to control the quantum state at telecommunication wavelength, enabling a transition from polarization entangled to separable states as a function of the pump polarization, with fidelities reaching 90%</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02980v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elise Bailly-Rioufreyt, Zoya Polshchykova, Gr\'egoire Saerens, Wenhe Jia, Thomas Dursap, Andreas Maeder, Philippe Regreny, Robert J. Chapman, Helena Weigand, Alexandre Danescu, Nicolas Chauvin, Jos\'e Penuelas, Rachel Grange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement evolution from entangled multipodal states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a periodic lattice system an entangled antipodal pair state, otherwise known as a crosscap state, is a simple two site product state in which spins at antipodal sites are prepared in Bell pairs. Such states have maximal bipartite entanglement and serve as a useful platform for studying the quench dynamics of systems which have large initial entanglement. In this paper, we study a generalization of these states which we dub entangled mutipodal states. These states, which are defined for fermionic systems, generalize the crosscap states by having correlations among more than two sites, specifically, those which sit at the vertices of regular polygons. By construction, the states are Gaussian and translationally invariant allowing many of their properties to be understood. We study the bipartite entanglement entropy of these states both in and out of equilibrium. In equilibrium, the entanglement profile as a function of subsystem size exhibits two distinct regimes, a volume-law growth followed by a saturation to a constant value, thus generalizing the Page-curve profile of the crosscap state. In the non-equilibrium setting, we study quenches from these initial states to the free-fermion chain, whose ensuing dynamics displays a far richer structure compared to the crosscap case. We interpret our results in terms of the quasiparticle picture, which requires multiplets of quasiparticles to be excited non-locally around the system. This scenario is confirmed by the appearance of a post-quench, negative tripartite information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03032v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Chalas, Pasquale Calabrese, Colin Rylands</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing confinement in a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory on a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.08905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.08905v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gauge theories describe the fundamental forces in the standard model of particle physics and play an important role in condensed matter physics. The constituents of gauge theories, for example charged matter and electric gauge field, are governed by local gauge constraints, which lead to key phenomena such as confinement of particles that are not fully understood. In this context, quantum simulators may address questions that are challenging for classical methods. While engineering gauge constraints is highly demanding, recent advances in quantum computing are beginning to enable digital quantum simulations of gauge theories. Here, we simulate confinement dynamics in a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory on a superconducting quantum processor. Tuning a term that couples only to the electric field produces confinement of charges, a manifestation of the tight bond that the gauge constraint generates between both. Moreover, we show how a modification of the gauge constraint from $\mathbb{Z}_2$ towards $\mathrm{U}(1)$ symmetry freezes the system dynamics. Our work illustrates the restriction that the underlying gauge constraint imposes on the dynamics of a lattice gauge theory, it showcases how gauge constraints can be modified and protected, and it promotes the study of other models governed by multi-body interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.08905v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02723-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. 21, 312-317 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julius Mildenberger, Wojciech Mruczkiewicz, Jad C. Halimeh, Zhang Jiang, Philipp Hauke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of coherent interaction-free detection of pulses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05214v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum physics allows an object to be detected even in the absence of photon absorption by the use of so-called interaction-free measurements. We provide a formulation of this protocol using a three-level system, where the object to be detected is a pulse coupled resonantly to the second transition. In the original formulation of interaction-free measurements, the absorption is associated with a projection operator onto the third state. We perform an in-depth analytical and numerical analysis of the coherent protocol, where coherent interaction between the object and the detector replaces the projective operators, resulting in higher detection efficiencies. We provide approximate asymptotic analytical results to support this finding. We find that our protocol reaches the Heisenberg limit when evaluating the Fisher information at small strengths of the pulses we aim to detect -- in contrast to the projective protocol that can only reach the standard quantum limit. We also demonstrate that the coherent protocol remains remarkably robust under errors such as pulse-rotation phases and strengths, the effects of relaxation rates and detunings, as well as different thermalized initial states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05214v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.5.033012</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 5, 033012 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>John J. McCord, Shruti Dogra, Gheorghe Sorin Paraoanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The formation of Schrodinger cat-like states in the process of spontaneous parametric down-conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14526v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, there has been an increased interest in the generation of superpositions of coherent states with opposite phases, the so-called photonic Schrodinger cat states. These experiments are challenging, and, so far, cats involving only small photon numbers have been implemented. Here, we propose to consider two-mode squeezed states as examples of Schrodinger cat-like states. For this, we apply criteria that aim to identify macroscopic superpositions in a more general sense. We extend some of these criteria to the two-mode continuous variable regime. Furthermore, we compare the size of states obtained in several experiments and discuss experimental challenges for further improvements. Our results not only promote two-mode squeezed states for exploring quantum effects at the macroscopic level but also provide direct measures to evaluate their usefulness for quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14526v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranjit Singh, Alexander E. Teretenkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qudit Quantum Programming with Projective Cliffords</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16801v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel abstraction for programming quantum operations, specifically projective Cliffords, as functions over the qudit Pauli group. Generalizing the idea behind Pauli tableaux, we introduce a type system and lambda calculus for projective Cliffords called LambdaPC, which captures well-formed Clifford operations via a Curry-Howard correspondence with a particular encoding of the Clifford and Pauli groups. Importantly, the language captures not just qubit operations, but qudit operations for any dimension $d$.
  Throughout the paper we explore what it means to program with projective Cliffords through a number of examples and a case study focusing on stabilizer error correcting codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16801v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3776646</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Paykin, Sam Winnick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimally robust shortcuts to population inversion in cat-state qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00464v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cat-state qubits formed by photonic coherent states are a promising candidate for realizing fault-tolerant quantum computing. Such logic qubits have a biased noise channel that the bit-flip error dominates over all the other errors. In this manuscript, we propose an optimally robust protocol using the control method of shortcuts to adiabaticity to realize a nearly perfect population inversion in a cat-state qubit. We construct a shortcut based on the Lewis-Riesenfeld invariant and examine the stability versus different types of perturbations for the fast and robust population inversion. Numerical simulations demonstrate that the population inversion can be mostly insensitive to systematic errors in our protocol. Even when the parameter imperfection rate for bit-flip control is $20\%$, the final population of the target state can still reach $\geq 99\%$. The optimally robust control provides a feasible method for fault-tolerant and scalable quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00464v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/oe.569776</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Vol. 33, Issue 19, pp. 40755-40773 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Wei Xu, Zhong-Zheng Zhang, Yue-Ying Guo, Ye-Hong Chen, Yan Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reducing depth and measurement weights in Pauli-based computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04007v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pauli-based computation (PBC) is a universal measurement-based quantum computation model steered by an adaptive sequence of independent and compatible Pauli measurements on separable magic-state qubits. Here, we propose several new techniques for reducing the weight of the Pauli measurements and their associated \textsc{cnot} complexity; we also demonstrate how to decrease this model's computational depth. We start by proving new upper bounds on the required weights and computational depth, obtained via a pre-compilation step. We also propose a heuristic algorithm that can contribute reductions of over 30\% to the average weight of Pauli measurements (and associated \textsc{cnot} count) when simulating and compiling Clifford-dominated random quantum circuits with up to 22 $T$ gates and over 20\% for instances with larger $T$ counts. This PBC-compilation scheme, boosted by the heuristic algorithm, outperforms state-of-the-art compilers for the former circuits, reducing the \textsc{cnot} count by 18\% to 96\% compared with the values achieved by other techniques. In contrast, for the latter circuits with larger $T$ counts, it leads to a number of \textsc{cnot}s roughly 30\% larger. Finally, inspired by known state-transfer methods, we introduce incPBC, a universal model for quantum computation requiring a larger number of (now incompatible) Pauli measurements of weight at most 2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04007v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/d3x5-cgky</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 062604 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filipa C. R. Peres, Ernesto F. Galv\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fault-tolerant quantum input/output</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05260v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Usual scenarios of fault-tolerant computation are concerned with the fault-tolerant realization of quantum algorithms that compute classical functions, such as Shor's algorithm for factoring. In particular, this means that input and output to the quantum algorithm are classical. In contrast to stand-alone single-core quantum computers, in many distributed scenarios, quantum information might have to be passed on from one quantum information processing system to another one, possibly via noisy quantum communication channels with noise levels above fault-tolerant thresholds. In such situations, quantum information processing devices will have quantum inputs, quantum outputs or even both, which pass qubits among each other.
  Working in the fault-tolerant framework of [Kitaev, 1997], we show that any quantum circuit with quantum input and output can be transformed into a fault-tolerant circuit that produces the ideal circuit with some controlled noise applied at the input and output. The framework allows the direct composition of the statements, enabling versatile future applications. We illustrate this with a concrete application, namely, communication over a noisy channel with faulty encoding and decoding operations [Christandl and M{\"u}ller-Hermes, 2024]. For communication codes with linear minimum distance, we construct fault-tolerant encoders and decoders for general noise (including coherent errors). For the weaker, but standard, model of local stochastic noise, we obtain fault-tolerant encoders and decoders for any communication code that can correct a constant fraction random errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05260v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Christandl, Omar Fawzi, Ashutosh Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Circuit Lower Bounds and Quantum-Classical Separations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16406v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We continue the study of the circuit class GC^0, which augments AC^0 with unbounded-fan-in gates that compute arbitrary functions inside a sufficiently small Hamming ball but must be constant outside it. While GC^0 can compute functions requiring exponential-size circuits, Kumar (CCC 2023) showed that switching-lemma lower bounds for AC^0 extend to GC^0 with no loss in parameters.
  We prove a parallel result for the polynomial method: any lower bound for AC^0[p] obtained via the polynomial method extends to GC^0[p] without loss in parameters. As a consequence, we show that the majority function MAJ requires depth-$d$ GC^0[p] circuits of size $2^{\Omega(n^{1/2(d-1)})}$, matching the best-known lower bounds for AC^0[p]. This yields the most expressive class of non-monotone circuits for which exponential-size lower bounds are known for an explicit function. We also prove a similar result for the algorithmic method, showing that E^NP requires exponential-size GCC^0 circuits, extending a result of Williams (JACM 2014).
  Finally, leveraging our improved classical lower bounds, we establish the strongest known unconditional separations between quantum and classical circuit classes. We separate QNC^0 from GC^0 and GC^0[p] in various settings and show that BQLOGTIME is not contained in GC^0. As a consequence, we construct an oracle relative to which BQP lies outside uniform GC^0, extending the Raz-Tal oracle separation between BQP and PH (STOC 2019).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16406v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabee Grewal, Vinayak M. Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient finite-resource formulation of non-Abelian lattice gauge theories beyond one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04441v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-Abelian gauge theories provide the most accurate description of fundamental interactions, showing remarkable agreement with experimental data in cosmology and particle physics. Highly precise predictions can be made using standard techniques, both in the continuum and in the lattice frameworks. However, classical methods have limitations, particularly when attempting to extrapolate the continuum limit from the study of lattice gauge theories. Complementing classical computations or combining them with quantum computational methods, to improve the predictions towards the continuum limit with current quantum resources, is a formidable open challenge. In this paper, we propose a resource-efficient method to compute the running of the coupling in non-Abelian gauge theories beyond one spatial dimension. We first represent the Hamiltonian on periodic lattices in terms of loop variables and conjugate loop electric fields, exploiting the Gauss law to retain the gauge-independent ones. Then, we identify a local basis for small and large loops variationally to minimize the truncation error while computing the running of the coupling on small tori. Our method enables computations at arbitrary values of the bare coupling and lattice spacing with current quantum computers, simulators and tensor-network calculations, in regimes otherwise inaccessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04441v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/k9p6-c649</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 15, 031065 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pierpaolo Fontana, Marc Miranda Riaza, Alessio Celi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit error bounds with commutator scaling for time-dependent product and multi-product formulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14243v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Product formula (PF), which approximates the time evolution under a many-body Hamiltonian by the product of local time evolution operators, is one of the central approaches for simulating quantum dynamics by quantum computers. It has been of great interest whether PFs have a bound of the error from the exact time evolution, which is expressed by commutators among local terms (called commutator scaling), since it brings the substantial suppression of the computational cost in the system size. Although recent studies have revealed the presence and the explicit formulas of the PF error bounds for time-independent systems, those for time-dependent Hamiltonians remain to be a difficult problem except for low-order PFs. In this paper, we derive an explicit error bound of generic PFs for smooth time-dependent Hamiltonians, which is expressed by commutators among local terms and their time derivatives. This error bound can also host the substantial suppression in the system size for generic local Hamiltonians with finite-, short-, and long-ranged interactions, thereby giving a much better estimate of gate counts. Our derivation employs Floquet theory; Embedding generic smooth time-dependent Hamiltonians into time-periodic ones, we map the time-dependent PF error to the time-independent one defined on an infinite-dimensional space. This approach allows to obtain the error bounds not only for the ordinary time-dependent PF but also for its various family. In particular, we also clarify the explicit error bound of a time-dependent multi-product formula, with which we can achieve much smaller error by a linear combination of time-dependent PFs. Our results will shed light on various applications of quantum computers, ranging from quantum simulation of nonequilibrium materials to faster algorithms exploiting time-dependent Hamiltonians like adiabatic state preparation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14243v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaoru Mizuta, Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda, Keisuke Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LUCI in the Surface Code with Dropouts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14891v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, usage of detecting regions facilitated the discovery of new circuits for fault-tolerantly implementing the surface code. Building on these ideas, we present LUCI, a framework for constructing fault-tolerant circuits flexible enough to construct aperiodic and anisotropic circuits, making it a clear step towards quantum error correction beyond static codes. We show that LUCI can be used to adapt surface code circuits to lattices with imperfect qubit and coupler yield, a key challenge for fault-tolerant quantum computers using solid-state architectures. These circuits preserve spacelike distance for isolated broken couplers or isolated broken measure qubits in exchange for halving timelike distance, substantially reducing the penalty for dropout compared to the state of the art and creating opportunities in device architecture design. For qubit and coupler dropout rates of 1% and a patch diameter of 15, LUCI achieves an average spacelike distance of 13.1, compared to 9.1 for the best method in the literature. For a SI1000(0.001) circuit noise model, this translates to a 36x improvement in median logical error rate per round, a factor which increases with device performance. At these dropout and error rates, LUCI requires roughly 25% fewer physical qubits to reach algorithmically relevant one-in-a-trillion logical codeblock error rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14891v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dripto M. Debroy, Matt McEwen, Craig Gidney, Noah Shutty, Adam Zalcman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Exponential Separation Between Quantum and Quantum-Inspired Classical Algorithms for Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02087v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Achieving a provable exponential quantum speedup for an important machine learning task has been a central research goal since the seminal HHL quantum algorithm for solving linear systems and the subsequent quantum recommender systems algorithm by Kerenidis and Prakash. These algorithms were initially believed to be strong candidates for exponential speedups, but a lower bound ruling out similar classical improvements remained absent. In breakthrough work by Tang, it was demonstrated that this lack of progress in classical lower bounds was for good reasons. Concretely, she gave a classical counterpart of the quantum recommender systems algorithm, reducing the quantum advantage to a mere polynomial. Her approach is quite general and was named quantum-inspired classical algorithms. Since then, almost all the initially exponential quantum machine learning speedups have been reduced to polynomial via new quantum-inspired classical algorithms. From the current state-of-affairs, it is unclear whether we can hope for exponential quantum speedups for any natural machine learning task.
  In this work, we present the first such provable exponential separation between quantum and quantum-inspired classical algorithms for the basic problem of solving a linear system when the input matrix is well-conditioned and has sparse rows and columns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02087v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allan Gr{\o}nlund, Kasper Green Larsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous emission in Casimir-Rabi oscillations through a weak optomechanical coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03719v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dynamical Casimir effect (DCE) describes the energy conversion from a mechanical motion to the electromagnetic fields. When the mechanical oscillator is in a mechanically excited state, the free evolution due to the DCE produces radiation in the vacuum, in analogy with the spontaneous emission from an excited atom. In this manuscript, we investigate such a spontaneous radiation process by employing the quantum trajectory approach. When the dissipation rate of the system is very low, there can be a reversible energy exchange between the mirror in the excited state and the vacuum field, and this reversible exchange is called vacuum Casimir-Rabi oscillations. Multiple quantum trajectory simulations of this process show that the number of trajectories responsible for the generation of radiation can reach a significant value when the mechanical dissipation rate is less than the photon dissipation rate. We also find that two-photon (two/three-phonon) bundle emission occurs in photon (phonon) emission. In comparison to pure two-photon and three-phonon free dissipation, the probability of two-photon bundle emission and two-phonon bundle emission are observed to be marginally elevated as a consequence of the presence of the DCE. This pattern may assist in developing a deeper comprehension of the physical characteristics of photon and phonon emission in the DCE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03719v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/oe.563278</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Vol. 33, Issue 19, pp. 39283-39303 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ke-Xiong Yan, Yuan Qiu, Yang Xiao, Jie Song, Ye-Hong Chen, Yan Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compare Similarities Between DNA Sequences Using Permutation-Invariant Quantum Kernel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05465v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Computing the similarity between two DNA sequences is of vital importance in bioscience, yet it can be computationally expensive on classical hardware. For example, the edit distance with move operations (EDM), a DNA similarity measure of interest in biology, is proven to be NP-Complete to compute exactly on classical hardware. Recently, applied quantum algorithms have been anticipated to offer potential advantages over classical approaches. In this paper, we propose a novel variational quantum kernel model served as a surrogate model for estimating similarity between DNA sequences defined by EDM. Since the EDM metric exhibits a pairwise permutation-insensitive property, we incorporate a permutation-invariant structure into the variational quantum kernel to approximate this symmetry. Furthermore, to encode the four nucleotide bases as quantum states, we introduce a theoretically motivated encoding scheme based on symmetric informationally complete positive operator-valued measure (SIC-POVM) states. This encoding ensures mutual equivalence among bases, as each pair of symbols is mapped to quantum states that are equidistant on the Bloch sphere. We experimentally show that, equipped with the permutation-invariant circuit design and mutual-equivalence encoding, the proposed quantum kernel model achieves strong performance in approximating the similarity defined by EDM. Compared with classical kernel learning methods, our quantum approach achieves significantly higher accuracy while using substantially fewer trainable parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05465v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu Shi, Gabriele Leoni, Mauro Petrillo, Antonio Puertas Gallardo, Hao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Overhead Tailoring and Learning of Noise in Graph States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12870v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graph and hypergraph states are important resource states for realizing universal quantum computation and diverse non-local physical phenomena. However, noise learning in such states is challenging due to their large entanglement and magic. This work establishes a low Clifford hierarchy circuit-based scheme for tailoring and learning noise in (hyper)graph states generated by multiple controlled-Z gates. The key is to convert the noisy input state into a diagonal form and derive the convolution equation of diagonal noise rate, which proves to have a lower resource overhead. Such a diagonal form can be used in real quantum simulation by using the same tailoring technique into the graph state input. We demonstrate that a single-depth Bell measurement is sufficient in our scheme for arbitrary graph states, while noise tailoring can be done via Pauli operations. After that, we suggest the Walsh-Hadamard transform and some approximation method for decoding the noise. We prove that constant sampling and polynomial time complexities are sufficient to guarantee bounded noise estimation error with respect to the $l_2$-norm, which usually requires exponential complexity with existing noise estimation methods. The polynomial complexities are maintained even for the more stringent $l_1$ approximation under the sparse noise assumption. Conclusively, we propose novel methods for characterizing the noise properties of an entangled state at a lower cost than that of state generation. Moreover, compared with state verification methods, we can attain richer information on noise rates and enable noise mitigation, thereby providing guarantees for the preparation of graph states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12870v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guedong Park, Jinzhao Sun, Hyunseok Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QUITS: A modular Qldpc code circUIT Simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02673v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To achieve quantum fault tolerance with lower overhead, quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes have emerged as a promising alternative to topological codes such as the surface code, offering higher code rates. To support their study, an end-to-end framework for simulating QLDPC codes at the circuit level is needed. In this work, we present QUITS, a modular and flexible circuit-level simulator for QLDPC codes. Its design allows users to freely combine LDPC code constructions, syndrome extraction circuits, decoding algorithms, and noise models, enabling comprehensive and customizable studies of the performance of QLDPC codes under circuit-level noise. QUITS supports several leading QLDPC families, including hypergraph product codes, lifted product codes, and balanced product codes. As part of the framework, we introduce a syndrome extraction circuit improved from Tremblay, Delfosse, and Beverland [Phys. Rev. Lett. 129, 050504 (2022)] that applies to all three code families. In particular, for a small hypergraph product code, our circuit achieves lower depth than the conventional method, resulting in improved logical performance. Using QUITS, we evaluate the performance of state-of-the-art QLDPC codes and decoders under various settings, revealing trade-offs between the decoding runtime and the logical failure rate. The source code of QUITS is available online.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02673v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyu Kang, Yingjia Lin, Hanwen Yao, Mert G\"okduman, Arianna Meinking, Kenneth R. Brown</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedforward suppression of readout-induced faults in quantum error correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13083v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Qubit measurements in quantum devices involve various types of errors, including erroneous state determination, correlated preparation errors and measurement-induced leakage from the computational states. We propose a feedforward protocol to reduce readout-induced faults, applicable for qubits with errors biased between the different states, in settings like quantum error correction with repeated measurement cycles. The method consists of an adaptive readout sequence conditioned on each check qubit's readout result from the previous cycle, which is optimized for the expected measured state. Focusing on a simple realization of conditionally flipping (by an X gate) the state of check qubits before their measurement, we investigate the effect of such state-dependent errors using simulations in the setup of a low-density parity check code. We show that the suggested protocol can reduce both logical errors and decoding time, two important aspects of fault-tolerant quantum computations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13083v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ght4-yqmb</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review A 112 (5), L050602 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Liran Shirizly, Dekel Meirom, Malcolm Carroll, Haggai Landa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Process Tomography with Digital Twins of Error Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate and robust quantum process tomography (QPT) is crucial for verifying quantum gates and diagnosing implementation faults in experiments aimed at building universal quantum computers. However, the reliability of QPT protocols is often compromised by faulty probes, particularly state preparation and measurement (SPAM) errors, which introduce fundamental inconsistencies in traditional QPT algorithms. We propose and investigate enhanced QPT for multi-qubit systems by integrating the error matrix in a digital twin of the identity process matrix, enabling statistical refinement of SPAM error learning and improving QPT precision. Through numerical simulations, we demonstrate that our approach enables highly accurate and faithful process characterization. We further validate our method experimentally using superconducting quantum gates, achieving at least an order-of-magnitude fidelity improvement over standard QPT. Our results provide a practical and precise method for assessing quantum gate fidelity and enhancing QPT on a given hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07725v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dpgy-rtxr</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 230601(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tangyou Huang, Akshay Gaikwad, Ilya Moskalenko, Anuj Aggarwal, Tahereh Abad, Marko Kuzmanovic, Yu-Han Chang, Ognjen Stanisavljevic, Emil Hogedal, Christopher Warren, Irshad Ahmad, Janka Bizn\'arov\'a, Amr Osman, Mamta Dahiya, Marcus Rommel, Anita Fadavi Rousari, Andreas Nylander, Liangyu Chen, Jonas Bylander, Gheorghe Sorin Paraoanu, Anton Frisk Kockum, Giovanna Tancredi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathcal{PT-}$Symmetric Open Quantum Systems: Information Theoretic Facets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16545v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The theory of an $\eta$-pseudo Hermitian Hamiltonian with $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry is reviewed and extended to include open system dynamics. A first-principles derivation of the generalized Gorini-Kossakowski-Sudarshan-Lindblad master equation appropriate for a $\mathcal{PT}-$symmetric Hamiltonian is presented. Inspired by a simple light matter interaction open system model, information theoretic quantities like a non-Markovian witness and fidelity are calculated for the $\mathcal{PT-}$symmetric Hamiltonian, and the results are compared with their corresponding Hermitian counterparts. The nature of entanglement between two $\mathcal{PT-}$symmetric and Hermitian open quantum systems is calculated, and the contrast observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16545v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baibhab Bose, Devvrat Tiwari, Subhashish Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic recurrent neural network as the first type of non-Euclidean neural quantum state ansatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22083v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce the first type of non-Euclidean neural quantum state (NQS) ansatz, in the form of the hyperbolic GRU (a variant of recurrent neural networks (RNNs)), to be used in the Variational Monte Carlo method of approximating the ground state energy for quantum many-body systems. In particular, we examine the performances of NQS ansatzes constructed from both conventional or Euclidean RNN/GRU and from hyperbolic GRU in the prototypical settings of the one- and two-dimensional transverse field Ising models (TFIM) and the one-dimensional Heisenberg $J_1J_2$ and $J_1J_2J_3$ systems. By virtue of the fact that, for all of the experiments performed in this work, hyperbolic GRU can yield performances comparable to or better than Euclidean RNNs, which have been extensively studied in these settings in the literature, our work is a proof-of-concept for the viability of hyperbolic GRU as the first type of non-Euclidean NQS ansatz for quantum many-body systems. Furthermore, in settings where the Hamiltonian displays a clear hierarchical interaction structure, such as the 1D Heisenberg $J_1J_2$ &amp; $J_1J_2J_3$ systems with the 1st, 2nd and even 3rd nearest neighbor interactions, our results show that hyperbolic GRU definitively outperforms its Euclidean version in almost all instances. The fact that these results are reminiscent of the established ones from natural language processing where hyperbolic GRU almost always outperforms Euclidean RNNs when the training data exhibit a tree-like or hierarchical structure leads us to hypothesize that hyperbolic GRU NQS ansatz would likely outperform Euclidean RNN/GRU NQS ansatz in quantum spin systems that involve different degrees of nearest neighbor interactions. Finally, with this work, we hope to initiate future studies of other types of non-Euclidean NQS beyond hyperbolic GRU.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22083v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. L. Dao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Dialogue through Non-destructive Discrimination of Cluster State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04847v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an efficient, measurement-based quantum dialogue protocol through non-destructive discrimination (NDD) of cluster state. We use ancilla-based measurements that allow the state to be reused without destroying its entanglement. The initial state is a local unitary (LU-) equivalent of the five-qubit cluster state, which significantly reduces the state components from 32 to 4, simultaneously allowing one to write its different subspaces using two different bases. The protocol utilizes single qubit unitaries from the Pauli group to encode the messages, thus preserving the stabilizer nature of the initial state throughout. We demonstrate that the proposed protocol is secure under common quantum attacks and outlining the procedure for the scalability of the scheme to transmit an n-bit message. The proposed protocol has been experimentally verified using IBM quantum backend 'IBM-Torino' as a proof of concept. Using the stabilizer nature of the state, we further introduce a single-qubit error correction mechanism that enhances robustness against noise without requiring any additional qubits. further, the use of NDD allows one to reuse the quantum resources in advancing the two-way dialogue, marking the importance and novelty of the proposed scheme over preexisting methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04847v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mandar Thatte, Shreya Banerjee, Prasanta K. Panigrahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-mitigated quantum metrology via enhanced virtual purification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07618v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum metrology stands as a leading application of quantum science and technology, yet noise often constrains its precision and sensitivity. In near-term quantum metrology, existing protocols largely depend on virtual state purification, but significant noise accumulation and additional noise from the implementations of these protocols can impede their effectiveness. We propose enhanced virtual channel purification to address these problems, yielding enhanced virtual state purification as a by-product. Within sequential quantum metrology schemes, our error analysis reveals substantial bias reduction and quantum advantages in sampling cost when the number of encoding channels is ${\mathcal{O}}(p^{-1})$, where $p$ represents the error rate of encoding channels. In this range, our methods demonstrate significant improvements in parameter estimation precision and robustness against practical noise, as evidenced by numerical simulations for both single- and multi-parameter tasks. Particularly, these methods can naturally extend beyond quantum metrology, indicating their broad applicability in quantum information and quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07618v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodie Lin, Haidong Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise tolerance via reinforcement: Learning a reinforced quantum dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12418v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The performance of quantum simulations heavily depends on the efficiency of noise mitigation techniques and error correction algorithms. Reinforcement has emerged as a powerful strategy to enhance the efficiency of learning and optimization algorithms. In this study, we demonstrate that a reinforced quantum dynamics can exhibit significant robustness against interactions with a noisy environment. We study a quantum annealing process where, through reinforcement, the system is encouraged to maintain its current state or follow a noise-free evolution. A learning algorithm is employed to derive a concise approximation of this reinforced dynamics, reducing the total evolution time and, consequently, the system's exposure to noisy interactions. This also avoids the complexities associated with implementing quantum feedback in such reinforcement algorithms. The efficacy of our method is demonstrated through numerical simulations of reinforced quantum annealing with one- and two-qubit systems under Pauli noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12418v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1742-5468/ae1a4c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Stat. Mech. (2025) 123401</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abolfazl Ramezanpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The logical structure of contextuality and nonclassicality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15071v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum contextuality represents a fundamental form of nonclassicality in quantum mechanics. To provide a more complete characterization of nonclassical properties in quantum systems, we adopt a logical perspective and propose a mathematical framework based on exclusive partial Boolean algebras (epBAs). This framework enables a unified description of contextuality and nonclassicality across finite general, quantum, and classical systems. We establish a unified and minimal classical counterpart for any finite general system. Within this framework, we formalize major categories of quantum contextuality, demonstrating that: 12 projectors suffice to generate Kochen-Specker scenarios; 10 projectors suffice to witness state-independent contextuality; and 3 observables suffice to witness quantum contextuality. Finally, we prove that contextuality is a sufficient but not necessary condition for nonclassicality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15071v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songyi Liu, Yongjun Wang, Baoshan Wang, Chang He, Jincheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Daemonic ergotropy of Gaussian quantum states and the role of measurement-induced purification via general-dyne detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22288v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: According to the Maxwell demon paradigm, additional work can be extracted from a classical or quantum system by exploiting information obtained through measurements on a correlated ancillary system. In the quantum setting, the maximum work extractable via unitary operations in such measurement-assisted protocols is referred to as daemonic ergotropy. In this work, we explore this concept in the context of continuous-variable quantum systems, focusing on Gaussian states and general-dyne (Gaussian) measurements. We derive a general expression for the daemonic ergotropy and examine two key scenarios: (i) bipartite Gaussian states where a general-dyne measurement is performed on one of the two parties, and (ii) open Gaussian quantum systems under continuous general-dyne monitoring of the environment. Remarkably, we show that for single-mode Gaussian states, the ergotropy depends solely on the state's energy and purity. This enables us to express the daemonic ergotropy as a simple function of the unconditional energy and the purity of the conditional states, revealing that enhanced daemonic work extraction is directly linked to measurement-induced purification. We illustrate our findings through two paradigmatic examples: extracting daemonic work from a two-mode squeezed thermal state and from a continuously monitored optical parametric oscillator. In both case we identify the optimal general-dyne strategies that maximize the conditional purity and, in turn, the daemonic ergotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22288v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2058-9565/ae2200</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum Sci. Technol. 11, 015014 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. H. Kua, Alessio Serafini, Marco G. Genoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential speed-up in VQE molecular energy ranking with Sridhara-compressed Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) are residual and intermediary molecules in the Chemical Vapor Deposition (CVD) to produce graphene from methane. Ranking a combinatorial space of variants of PAHs by energy allows the CVD to be optimized, while simulations of PAHs are strong candidates for quantum advantage in quantum computers. We extend on Sridhara's root formula to perform block diagonalization (SBD) of six PAHs using Hartree-Fock Hamiltonians with STO-3G basis set and $(2,2)$, $(4,4)$, $(6,6)$ settings of active orbitals and active electrons. We show that the proposed SBD algorithm followed by Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) allows ranking molecules by ground state energy with $77.8\%$ of success in comparison with the uncompressed VQE, while speeding up the VQE simulation in $164.16\%$ (median) keeping its average error of active space reduction down to $0.09\%$. We conclude that the flexibilization of constraints of the SBD algorithm makes it a fast and reliable estimator for active space reduction in molecular simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12678v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Lima, Saif Al-Kuwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangled Quantum Walkers for Secure Quantum Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05593v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum Key Distribution (QKD) is an emerging cryptographic method designed for secure key sharing. Its security is theoretically guaranteed by fundamental principles of quantum mechanics, making it a leading candidate for future communication protocols. Quantum Random Walks (QRWs), on the other hand, are quantum processes that exhibit intriguing phenomena such as interference and superposition, enabling the generation of decentralized and asymmetric probability distributions. Inspired by both fields of study, we propose a novel QKD protocol based on two entangled quantum walkers. Our protocol exploits the unique correlations between the walkers at extremal positions of the walk to establish secret keys shared exclusively by the two parties. The security of the protocol is augmented by analyzing the joint probability distributions of the walkers' measured positions and their associated coin states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05593v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chia-Tso Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Convex Optimization for Bosonic State Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06305v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum states encoded in electromagnetic fields, also known as bosonic states, have been widely applied in quantum sensing, quantum communication, and quantum error correction. Accurate characterization is therefore essential yet difficult when states cannot be reconstructed with sparse Pauli measurements. Tomography must work with dense measurement bases, high-dimensional Hilbert spaces, and often sample-based data. However, existing convex optimization-based techniques are not efficient enough and scale poorly when extended to large and multi-mode systems. In this work, we explore convex optimization as an effective framework to address problems in bosonic state tomography, introducing three techniques to enhance efficiency and scalability: efficient displacement operator computation, Hilbert space truncation, and stochastic convex optimization, which mitigate common limitations of existing approaches. Then we propose a sample-based, convex maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE) method specifically designed for flying mode tomography. Numerical simulations of flying four-mode and nine-mode problems demonstrate the accuracy and practicality of our methods. This method provides practical tools for reliable bosonic mode quantum state reconstruction in high-dimensional and multi-mode systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06305v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengyong Li, Yanjin Yue, Ying Hu, Rui-Yang Gong, Qianchuan Zhao, Zhihui Peng, Hou Ian, Pengtao Song, Zeliang Xiang, Jing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Quantum Mechanics with Quantum Computers: Qubit Information Capacity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated in part by John Wheeler's assertion that the continuum nature of Hilbert Space conceals the information-theoretic character of the quantum wavefunction, a specific discretisation of complex Hilbert Space is proposed. Although the Schr\"{o}dinger equation is not modified, the bases in which the quantum state is mathematically defined must satisfy certain `rationality conditions'. This leads to the notion of Qubit Information Capacity $N_{\mathrm{max}}$. For any $N &gt; N_{\mathrm{max}}$ - qubit state, there is insufficient information in the $N$ qubits (linearly growing in $N$) to allocate even one bit to each of the $2^{N+1}-2$ degrees of freedom demanded by complex Hilbert Space (exponentially growing in $N$) and hence unitary quantum mechanics (QM, where $N_{\mathrm{max}}=\infty$). Here, state reduction to the classical limit corresponds to a steady coarsening of the discretisation with time. Using the Di\'{o}si-Penrose model for gravitised state reduction, it is estimated that $N_{\mathrm{max}}$ lies between about 200 and 400 for current qubit technologies, and will never exceed 1,000. It is therefore predicted that the exponential advantage of Shor's algorithm over classical algorithms, will have saturated at 1,000 qubits. Hence, insofar as a classical computer will never factor a 2048-bit RSA integer, neither will a quantum computer. This predicted breakdown of QM is potentially testable in a few years. Importantly, the proposed QIC is not itself due to gravitational or other types of state collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02877v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Palmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Improved Quantum Algorithm for 3-Tuple Lattice Sieving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08473v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The assumed hardness of the Shortest Vector Problem in high-dimensional lattices is one of the cornerstones of post-quantum cryptography. The fastest known heuristic attacks on SVP are via so-called sieving methods. While these still take exponential time in the dimension $d$, they are significantly faster than non-heuristic approaches and their heuristic assumptions are verified by extensive experiments. $k$-Tuple sieving is an iterative method where each iteration takes as input a large number of lattice vectors of a certain norm, and produces an equal number of lattice vectors of slightly smaller norm, by taking sums and differences of $k$ of the input vectors. Iterating these ''sieving steps'' sufficiently many times produces a short lattice vector. The fastest attacks (both classical and quantum) are for $k=2$, but taking larger $k$ reduces the amount of memory required for the attack. In this paper we improve the quantum time complexity of 3-tuple sieving from $2^{0.3098 d}$ to $2^{0.2846 d}$, using a two-level amplitude amplification aided by a preprocessing step that associates the given lattice vectors with nearby ''center points'' to focus the search on the neighborhoods of these center points. Our algorithm uses $2^{0.1887d}$ classical bits and QCRAM bits, and $2^{o(d)}$ qubits. This is the fastest known quantum algorithm for SVP when total memory is limited to $2^{0.1887d}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08473v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lynn Engelberts, Yanlin Chen, Amin Shiraz Gilani, Maya-Iggy van Hoof, Stacey Jeffery, Ronald de Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase assumption-free multiparty quantum clock synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16895v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate methods to broadcast timing information from a central clock to all other clocks by the use of multipartite entanglement. This task is a necessary step in establishing a coordinated universal time, currently performed using classical synchronization methods. Using an entanglement-based method has the advantage that the timing results are independent of the intervening medium. We generalize existing bipartite quantum clock synchronization methods and take special care to address issues of different phase conventions being adopted at each node (the ``Preskill phase problem''). Using supersinglet purification, we show that this allows for a scalable method with a time signal that is a constant with respect to the number of nodes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16895v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hatim A. Oujaa, Qiao Liu, Ebubechukwu O. Ilo-Okeke, Valentin Ivannikov, Jonathan P. Dowling, Tim Byrnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trade-off between complexity and energy in quantum phase estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05458v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Driven by the desire to make quantum technologies more sustainable, in this work we introduce a framework for analysing the interplay between complexity and energy cost of quantum procedures. In particular, we study a sequential quantum phase estimation protocol, where a phase of physical significance is encoded in a quantum channel. The channel is applied to a probe state repetitively until the probe is measured and the outcome leads to an estimate on the phase. We establish a trade-off relation between the implementation energy of the channel and the number of times it is applied (complexity), while reaching a desired estimation precision. The principles of our analysis can be adapted to optimise the energy consumption in other quantum protocols and devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05458v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukuan Tao, Madalin Guta, Gerardo Adesso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subradiant Decay in 2D and 3D Atomic Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11374v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Subradiance is a phenomenon where coupled emitters radiate light at a slower rate than independent ones. While its observation was first reported in disordered cold atom clouds, ordered subwavelength arrays of emitters have emerged as promising platforms to design highly cooperative optical properties based on dipolar interactions. In this work we characterize the eigenmodes of 2D and 3D regular arrays, using a method which can be used for both infinite and very large systems. In particular, we show how finite-size effects impact the lifetimes of these large arrays. Our results may have interesting applications for quantum memories and topological effects in ordered atomic arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11374v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Piovella, Romain Bachelard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Squeezing-Enhanced Photon-Number Measurements for GKP State Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14737v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an architecture for the generation of GKP states in which quadrature squeezing operations are used to control the average photon number statistics of probabilistic photon number measurements on Gaussian resource states. Specifically, we present an architecture employing a teleportation-based squeezing protocol and polynomial-gate applications integrated into a time-multiplexed multi-mode cluster state to generate cat states with high amplitudes, which are consequently used to generate GKP states with high quadrature effective squeezing. Compared to our previous work, in addition to using squeezing as a resource, the present architecture reduces damping and noise by minimizing the number of homodyne measurements required in GKP state generation. We demonstrate the effectiveness of these improvements - including dynamic input-state resetting and an improved breeding algorithm - by achieving a fault-tolerance threshold of 11.5 dB cluster squeezing using the RHG surface code for error correction, without requiring active switching or photon-number resource states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14737v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Renault, Patrick Yard, Raphael Pooser, Hussain Zaidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Entanglement Facilitated by Opto-Mechanical Cooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optomechanical generation of entangled optical beams is usually hindered by thermal noise. We present a theoretical study of low frequency entanglement generation between two optical harmonics emitted from a cavity optomechanical system operating in the resolved-sideband regime. The system comprises three nearly equidistant optical modes in a high-finesse cavity, with the central mode coherently driven. This configuration enables radiation-pressure interactions that generate strong quantum correlations between the two sideband modes. Remarkably, these correlations persist even at large numbers of thermal quanta if one properly engineers the optical cooling rate of the mechanical mode. Our findings demonstrate the feasibility of robust entanglement under ambient conditions, opening new avenues for hybrid quantum technologies based on mechanical interfaces and continuous-variable quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17244v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandr V. Karpenko, Andrey B. Matsko, Sergey P. Vyatchanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wave-Particle Complementarity as the Optimal Limit of Unambiguous Quantum-State Discrimination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22871v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a direct operational interpretation of wave--particle complementarity in induced-coherence interferometry by linking interference visibility to the optimal performance of unambiguous quantum-state discrimination. In the low-gain Zou--Wang--Mandel interferometer, the idler modes of the two SPDC crystals act as nonorthogonal which-crystal marker states, and we show that the single-photon visibility equals the minimal inconclusive probability of the optimal Ivanovic--Dieks--Peres (IDP) strategy, $V = P_I^{\mathrm{opt}}$, so that the complementarity relation $D^{2}+V^{2}=1$ expresses a measurement-optimality boundary rather than a geometric constraint. Our results reveal that wave--particle duality in induced coherence is not limited by interferometer geometry but by measurement optimality in zero-error discrimination on the idler, with experimentally testable consequences predicting distinguishability beyond that inferred from visibility alone. In the presence of thermal noise we derive the hierarchy $V \le F(\rho_A,\rho_B) \le P_I^{\mathrm{opt}}$, linking visibility, fidelity, and optimal discrimination. These results identify distinguishability as fundamentally measurement-limited and motivate discrimination-enhanced induced-coherence imaging and sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22871v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theerthagiri L</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Dynamics of Multiparticle Carroll-Schr\"dinger Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of multiparticle Carroll-Schr\"odinger (CS) quantum systems in $1{+}1$ dimensions, where $x$ acts as the evolution variable and $t$ as the configuration coordinate. We derive the $N$-body theory on equal-$x$ slices as the Carrollian limit of a relativistic multi-time Klein-Gordon model, introducing temporal interactions via minimal coupling to the temporal energy operators. An $x$-dependent gauge transformation maps this to an equivalent description with explicit many-body potentials, illustrated by a temporal coupled-oscillator model that exhibits synchronization. Adopting a complementary spatial viewpoint with a static potential $U_{\!tot}(\mathbf x)$, we show that the evolution is driven by the collective force $\sum_j\partial_{x_j}U_{\!tot}$; for any translation-invariant interaction (such as a regularized Coulomb potential), these internal forces cancel, rendering the collective dynamics free and highlighting Carrollian ultralocality. We also construct a coordinate duality mapping separable Schr\"odinger Hamiltonians to CS generators via Schwarzian derivatives. Exchange symmetry is formulated in the time domain, yielding temporal bunching for bosons and antibunching for fermions via the second-order coherence function $g^{(2)}(t,t')$. In second quantization, the contact limit yields a temporal derivative cubic--quintic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with a theoretically fixed nonlinearity coefficient $\beta=-3/16$. Finally, by coupling canonical pairs to external scalar and gauge fields, we establish an isomorphism with one-dimensional current-density functional theory, outlining a Carrollian Hohenberg-Kohn mapping and Kohn-Sham scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00247v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Rojas, Melvin Arias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimized Many-Hypercube Codes toward Lower Logical Error Rates and Earlier Realization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00561v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many-hypercube codes [H. Goto, Sci. Adv. 10, eadp6388 (2024)], concatenated ${[[n,n-2,2]]}$ quantum error-detecting codes ($n$ is even), have recently been proposed as high-rate quantum codes suitable for fault-tolerant quantum computing. While the original many-hypercube codes with ${n=6}$ can achieve remarkably high encoding rates (about 30% and 20% at concatenation levels 3 and 4, respectively), they have large code block sizes at high levels (216 and 1296 physical qubits per block at levels 3 and 4, respectively), making not only experimental realization difficult but also logical error rates per block high. Toward earlier experimental realization and lower logical error rates, here we comprehensively investigate smaller many-hypercube codes with $[[6,4,2]]$ and/or $[[4,2,2]]$ codes, where, e.g., $D_{6,4,4}$ denotes the many-hypercube code using $[[6,4,2]]$ at level 1 and $[[4,2,2]]$ at levels 2 and 3. As a result, we found a notable fact that $D_{6,4,4}$ ($D_{6,6,4,4}$) can achieve lower block error rates than $D_{4,4,4}$ ($D_{4,4,4,4}$), despite its higher encoding rate. Focusing on level 3, we also developed efficient fault-tolerant encoders realizing about 60% overhead reduction while maintaining or even improving the performance, compared to the original design. Using them, we numerically confirmed that $D_{6,4,4}$ also achieves the best performance for logical controlled-NOT gates in a circuit-level noise model. These results will be useful for early experimental realization of fault-tolerant quantum computing with high-rate quantum codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00561v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayato Goto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmentation is Efficiently Learnable by Quantum Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00751v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hilbert space fragmentation is a phenomenon in which the Hilbert space of a quantum system is dynamically decoupled into exponentially many Krylov subspaces. We can define the Schur transform as a unitary operation mapping some set of preferred bases of these Krylov subspaces to computational basis states labeling them. We prove that this transformation can be efficiently learned via gradient descent from a set of training data using quantum neural networks, provided that the fragmentation is sufficiently strong such that the summed dimension of the unique Krylov subspaces is polynomial in the system size. To demonstrate this, we analyze the loss landscapes of random quantum neural networks constructed out of Hilbert space fragmented systems. We prove that in this setting, it is possible to eliminate barren plateaus and poor local minima, suggesting efficient trainability when using gradient descent. Furthermore, as the algebra defining the fragmentation is not known a priori and not guaranteed to have sparse algebra elements, to the best of our knowledge there are no existing efficient classical algorithms generally capable of simulating expectation values in these networks. Our setting thus provides a rare example of a physically motivated quantum learning task with no known dequantization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00751v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Mints, Eric R. Anschuetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear and nonlinear edge dynamics of trapped fractional quantum Hall droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.02539v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report numerical studies of the linear and nonlinear edge dynamics of a non-harmonically confined macroscopic fractional quantum Hall fluid. In the long-wavelength and weak excitation limit, observable consequences of the fractional transverse conductivity are recovered. The first non-universal corrections to the chiral Luttinger liquid theory are then characterized: for a weak excitation in the linear response regime, cubic corrections to the linear wave dispersion and a broadening of the dynamical structure factor of the edge excitations are identified; for stronger excitations, sizable nonlinear effects are found in the dynamics. The numerically observed features are quantitatively captured by a nonlinear chiral Luttinger liquid quantum Hamiltonian that reduces to a driven Korteweg-de Vries equation in the semiclassical limit. Experimental observability of our predictions is finally discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.02539v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.107.033320</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 107, 3, 033320 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Nardin, Iacopo Carusotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust and scalable rf spectroscopy in first-order magnetic sensitive states at second-long coherence time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.01486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.01486v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Trapped-ion quantum sensors have become highly sensitive tools for the search of physics beyond the Standard Model. Recently, stringent tests of local Lorentz-invariance (LLI) have been conducted with precision spectroscopy in trapped ions. We here elaborate on robust radio-frequency composite-pulse spectroscopy at second long coherence times in the magnetic sublevels of the long-lived $^{2}F_{7/2}$ state of a trapped $^{172}$Yb$^{+}$ ion which is scalable to spatially extended multi-ion systems. We compare two Ramsey-type composite rf pulse sequences, a GSE sequence and a UR10 that decouple the energy levels from magnetic field noise, enabling robust and accurate spectroscopy. Both sequences are characterized theoretically and experimentally in the spin-$1/2$\ $^{2}S_{1/2}$ electronic ground state of $^{172}$Yb$^+$ and results show that the UR10 sequence is 38 (13) times more robust against pulse duration (frequency detuning) errors than the GSE sequence. We extend our simulations to the eight-level manifold of the $^2F_{7/2}$ state, which is highly sensitive to a possible violation of LLI, and show that the UR10 sequence can be used for high-fidelity Ramsey spectroscopy in noisy environments. The UR10 sequence is implemented experimentally in the $^2F_{7/2}$ manifold and a coherent signal of up to 2.5\,s is reached. In reference we have implemented this sequence and used it to perform the most stringent test of LLI in the electron-photon sector to date with a single Yb$^{+}$ ion. Due to the high robustness of the UR10 sequence, it can be applied on larger ion crystals to improve tests of Lorentz symmetry further. We demonstrate that the sequence can also be used to extract the quadrupole moment of the meta-stable $^{2}F_{7/2}$ state, obtaining a value of $\Theta\,=\,-0.0298(38)\,ea^{2}_{0}$ which is in agreement with the value deduced from clock measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.01486v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/acfc14</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>New J. Phys. 25, 093054 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>C. -H. Yeh, K. C. Grensemann, L. S. Dreissen, H. A. F\"urst, T. E. Mehlst\"aubler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic complexity and the Hubble tension: a quantum gravity portrayal for the large scale structure of the cosmos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05267v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we propose a relationship between the so-called Hubble-Lema\^{i}tre constant $H_{0}$ and holographic complexity related to the emergence of spacetime in quantum gravity. Such a result can represent an important step to understanding the Hubble tension by introducing a quantum gravity perspective for cosmological observations: regarding the degree of quantum complexity we measure around us.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05267v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ae2416.</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative volume of comparable pairs under semigroup majorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23196v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Any semigroup $\mathcal{S}$ of stochastic matrices induces a semigroup majorization relation $\prec^{\mathcal{S}}$ on the set $\Delta_{n-1}$ of probability $n$-vectors. Pick $X,Y$ at random in $\Delta_{n-1}$: what is the probability that $X$ and $Y$ are comparable under $\prec^{\mathcal{S}}$? We review recent asymptotic ($n\to\infty$) results and conjectures in the case of majorization relation (when $\mathcal{S}$ is the set of doubly stochastic matrices), discuss natural generalisations, and prove a new asymptotic result in the case of majorization, and new exact finite-$n$ formulae in the case of UT-majorization relation, i.e. when $\mathcal{S}$ is the set of upper-triangular stochastic matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23196v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11005-025-01968-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lett. Math. Phys. 115, 79 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Deelan Cunden, Jakub Czartowski, Giovanni Gramegna, A. de Oliveira Junior</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-Vacuum-Induced Chiral Spin Liquids in Kagome Lattices: Tuning and Probing Topological Quantum Phases via Cavity Quantum Electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08121v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological phases in frustrated quantum magnetic systems have captivated researchers for decades, with the chiral spin liquid (CSL) standing out as one of the most compelling examples. Featured by long-range entanglement, topological order, and exotic fractional excitations, the CSL has inspired extensive exploration for practical realizations. In this work, we demonstrate that CSLs can emerge in a kagome lattice driven by vacuum quantum fluctuations over the non-interacting vacuum within a single-mode gyrotropic cavity. The gyrotropic cavity imprints quantum fluctuations with time-reversal symmetry breaking and stabilizes a robust CSL phase without external laser excitation. Moreover, we identify experimentally accessible observables -- such as average photon number and transport properties -- that reveal connections between photon dynamics and the emergent chiral order. Our findings establish a novel pathway for creating, controlling, and probing topological and symmetry-breaking quantum phases in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08121v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8qx2-xxh2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 236901 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chenan Wei, Liu Yang, Qing-Dong Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrashort-pulse-pumped, single-mode type-0 squeezers in lithium niobate nanophotonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17708v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present design principles for ultrashort-pulse, type-0 phase-matched optical parametric amplifiers to generate and measure spectrally pure degenerate squeezed light. We consider a fundamental signal (second-harmonic) mode at 2090 (1045) nm and show that our proposed design achieves a Schmidt number of $K \approx 1.02$ with squeezing levels greater than 15 dB on a single temporal mode spanning over $5$ THz in bandwidth with cm-scale devices on thin-film lithium niobate (TFLN) on insulator platform. Our work opens up promising avenues for large-scale circuits for ultrafast quantum information processing and quantum sensing applications on the rapidly advancing TFLN platform with already demonstrated linear components and photodetection capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17708v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/OPTICAQ.566703</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Optica Quantum 3, 560-568 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martin Houde, Liam Beaudoin, Robert Kwolek, Kazuki Hirota, Rajveer Nehra, Nicol\'as Quesada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free Probability approach to spectral and operator statistics in Rosenzweig-Porter random matrix ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04520v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Utilizing the framework of free probability, we analyze the spectral and operator statistics of the Rosenzweig-Porter random matrix ensembles, which exhibit a rich phase structure encompassing ergodic, fractal, and localized regimes. Leveraging subordination formulae, we develop a perturbative scheme that yields semi-analytic expressions for the density of states up to second order in system size, in good agreement with numerical results. We compute higher-point correlation functions in the ergodic regime using both numerical and suitable analytic approximations. Our analysis of operator statistics for various spin operators across these regimes reveals close agreement with free probability predictions in the ergodic phase, in contrast to persistent deviations observed in the fractal and localized phases, even at late times. Notably, the fractal phase exhibits partial freeness while retaining memory of the initial spectrum, highlighting the importance of non-localized eigenstates and associated with the late-time dynamics of cumulative out-of-time-ordered-correlators (OTOCs). Employing distance measures and statistical tools such as the $\chi^2$ statistic, Kullback-Leibler divergence, and Kolmogorov-Smirnov hypothesis testing, we define a characteristic time scale-the free time-that marks the onset of the validity of free probability predictions for operator spectral statistics in the ergodic phase. Remarkably, our findings demonstrate consistency across these different approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04520v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2025)002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 12 (2025) 002</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Jahnke, Pratik Nandy, Kuntal Pal, Hugo A. Camargo, Keun-Young Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Background Suppression in Quantum Sensing of Dark Matter via $W$ State Projection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01816v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that measuring dark matter signal by projecting quantum sensors in the collective excited state can highly suppress the non-collective noise background, hence improving the sensitivity significantly. We trace the evolution of the sensors' state in the presence of both dark matter effect and sensors' decoherence effects, optimizing the protocol execution time, and show that the suppression of background by a factor equal to the number of sensors is possible. This method does not require the entanglement of sensors during the signal accumulation time, hence circumventing the difficulty of maintaining the lifetime of the entangled state that is present in other enhancement proposals. This protocol is also general regarding the type of qubit sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01816v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shion Chen, Hajime Fukuda, Yutaro Iiyama, Yuya Mino, Takeo Moroi, Mikio Nakahara, Tatsumi Nitta, Thanaporn Sichanugrist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exciton and biexciton preparation via coherent swing-up excitation in a GaAs quantum dot embedded in micropillar cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21428v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Coherent control of quantum emitters is essential for scalable quantum photonic technologies. The recently proposed swing-up of quantum emitter (SUPER) scheme allows efficient and coherent preparation of single photons via off-resonant, red-detuned laser pulses, simplifying laser suppression and enhancing photon collection. We present a systematic study of SUPER excitation applied to a single GaAs quantum dot in a low-Q micropillar cavity. We perform a comparison of the key figures of merit against the well-established two-photon excitation (TPE). Despite requiring higher excitation powers, SUPER achieves near-unity population inversion of the exciton state ($\sim$95%) and high single-photon purity ($g^{(2)}=0.03$) comparable to that under TPE, while also exhibiting a shortened decay time ($\sim$200 ps) reducing the time jitter in the exciton population. A polarization-resolved analysis reveals that when both excitation and collection are aligned with one of the exciton dipoles, SUPER results in polarized single-photon emission, exceeding the resonant TPE saturation by a factor of 1.45. Under optimized excitation conditions, we also observe biexciton preparation via a distinct SUPER resonance, confirmed by the appearance of the biexciton emission line, constituting the first experimental demonstration of biexciton preparation using SUPER. These findings are in good agreement with a proposed four-level theoretical model that incorporates the biexciton state. We also report that a slight misalignment of laser polarization induces an additional SUPER resonance that selectively populates the orthogonal exciton dipole, without altering the nominal excitation polarization. This unexpected behavior reveals a new degree of freedom for coherent state preparation. Our findings establish the SUPER scheme as a versatile tool for state-selective exciton and biexciton control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21428v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudia Piccinini, Aleksander Rodek, Abdulmalik A. Madigawa, Ailton Garcia Jr., Saimon F. Covre da Silva, Martin A. Jacobsen, Luca Vannucci, Gregor Weihs, Armando Rastelli, Vikas Remesh, Niels Gregersen, Battulga Munkhbat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-temperature superconducting Majorana fermions platforms in the layered Kitaev Materials: Case study of $Li_2IrO_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01551v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in Kitaev materials have highlighted their potential to host Majorana fermions without or high-temperature of superconductivity. In this research, we propose $Li_2IrO_3$ as a promising High-temperature superconducting platform supporting Majorana edge modes due to its strong spin-orbit coupling, honeycomb lattice structure, and proximity to a quantum spin liquid (QSL) phase. A theoretical and numerical framework based on the Kitaev-Heisenberg Hamiltonian is developed to model spin interactions in $Li_2IrO_3$. Here, the existence of topological zero-energy states is demonstrated, and their signatures in the edge-localized spectral weight are identified. A device concept based on this material is also proposed with potential industrial applications in spintronics, magnetic field sensing, and topological quantum memory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01551v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elnaz Rostampour, Badie Ghavami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Phase Gradient Imaging Using a Nonlocal Metasurface System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09922v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum phase imaging enables the analysis of transparent samples with thickness and refractive index variations in scenarios requiring precise measurements under low-light conditions. Here, we present a compact quantum phase-gradient imaging system integrating a lithium niobate (LiNbO3) metasurface for generating spatially entangled photon pairs and a silicon (Si) metasurface for phase gradient extraction. By leveraging nonlocal resonances, the LiNbO3 metasurface enables efficient spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC) with all-optically angularly tunable emission, while the Si metasurface provides a nearly linear optical transfer function (OTF) that differentiates the photon wavefunction and extracts phase gradients.Experimental proof-of-concept results demonstrate the imaging of up to 25~rad/mm phase gradients, achieving 89% similarity with the reference values. The pixel resolution of the system can be potentially enhanced by orders of magnitude by increasing the metasurface dimensions and resonance quality factor.Our work showcases the application of metasurfaces in both generating and detecting quantum states and establishes a new paradigm for portable quantum phase-gradient imaging, with potential applications in quantum sensing, microscopy, and LiDAR technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09922v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinliang Ren, Jinyong Ma, Katsuya Tanaka, Lukas Wesemann, Ann Roberts, Frank Setzpfandt, Andrey A. Sukhorukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Obstructions and the Collapse of Elementary Structure in the Kronecker Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22856v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While Kronecker coefficients $g(\lambda,\mu,\nu)$ with bounded rows are polynomial-time computable via lattice-point methods, no explicit closed-form formulas have been obtained for genuinely three-row cases in the 87 years since Murnaghan's foundational work. This paper provides such formulas for the first time and identifies a universal structural boundary at parameter value 5 where elementary combinatorial patterns collapse.
  We analyze two independent families of genuinely three-row coefficients and establish that for $k \leq 4$, the formulas exhibit elementary structure: oscillation bounds follow the triangular-Hogben pattern, and polynomial expressions factor completely over $\mathbb{Z}$. At the critical threshold $k=5$, this structure collapses: the triangular pattern fails, and algebraic obstructions -- irreducible quadratic factors with negative discriminant -- emerge.
  We develop integer forcing, a proof technique exploiting the tension between continuous asymptotics and discrete integrality. As concrete results, we prove that $g((n,n,1)^3) = 2 - (n \mod 2)$ for all $n \geq 3$ -- the first explicit formula for a genuinely three-row Kronecker coefficient -- derive five explicit polynomial formulas for staircase-hook coefficients, and verify Saxl's conjecture for 132 three-row partitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22856v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soong Kyum Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RapunSL: Untangling Quantum Computing with Separation, Linear Combination and Mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum Separation Logic (QSL) has been proposed as an effective tool to improve the scalability of deductive reasoning for quantum programs. In QSL, separation is interpreted as disentanglement, and the frame rule brings a notion of entanglement-local specification (one that only talks about the qubits entangled with those acted upon by the program). In this paper, we identify two notions of locality unique to the quantum domain, and we construct a novel quantum separation logic, RapunSL, which is able to soundly reduce reasoning about superposition states to reasoning about pure states (basis-locality), and reasoning about mixed states arising from measurement to reasoning about pure states (outcome-locality). To do so, we introduce two connectives, linear combination and mixing, which together with separation provide a dramatic improvement in the scalability of reasoning, as we demonstrate on a series of challenging case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23472v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3776648</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Matsushita, Kengo Hirata, Ryo Wakizaka, Emanuele D'Osualdo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
