<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coordinate Space Modification of Fock's Theory-Harmonic Tensors in the Quantum Coulomb Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider Fock's fundamental theory of the hydrogen atom in momentum space which allows a realization of the previously predicted rotation group of a three-dimensional (3D) sphere in four-dimensional (4D) space. We then modify Fock's theory and abandon the momentum space description. To transform and simplify the theory, we use invariant tensor methods of electrostatics in 3D and 4D spaces. We find a coordinate 4D space where the Schrodinger equation becomes the 4D Laplace equation. The transition from harmonic 4D polynomials to original 3D physical space is algebraic and involves derivatives with respect to a coordinate that is interpreted as time. We obtain a differential equation for eigenfunctions in the momentum space and find its solutions. A concise calculation of the quadratic Stark effect is given. The Schwinger resolvent is derived by the method of harmonic polynomials. Vector ladder operators are also considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00010v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3367/UFNe.2021.04.038966</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Usp.,65:9,pp.952-967 (2022) (in russian)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergei P. Efimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GroverGPT: A Large Language Model with 8 Billion Parameters for Quantum Searching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing is an exciting non-Von Neumann paradigm, offering provable speedups over classical computing for specific problems. However, the practical limits of classical simulatability for quantum circuits remain unclear, especially with current noisy quantum devices. In this work, we explore the potential of leveraging Large Language Models (LLMs) to simulate the output of a quantum Turing machine using Grover's quantum circuits, known to provide quadratic speedups over classical counterparts. To this end, we developed GroverGPT, a specialized model based on LLaMA's 8-billion-parameter architecture, trained on over 15 trillion tokens. Unlike brute-force state-vector simulations, which demand substantial computational resources, GroverGPT employs pattern recognition to approximate quantum search algorithms without explicitly representing quantum states. Analyzing 97K quantum search instances, GroverGPT consistently outperformed OpenAI's GPT-4o (45\% accuracy), achieving nearly 100\% accuracy on 6- and 10-qubit datasets when trained on 4-qubit or larger datasets. It also demonstrated strong generalization, surpassing 95\% accuracy for systems with over 20 qubits when trained on 3- to 6-qubit data. Analysis indicates GroverGPT captures quantum features of Grover's search rather than classical patterns, supported by novel prompting strategies to enhance performance. Although accuracy declines with increasing system size, these findings offer insights into the practical boundaries of classical simulatability. This work suggests task-specific LLMs can surpass general-purpose models like GPT-4o in quantum algorithm learning and serve as powerful tools for advancing quantum research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00135v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoran Wang, Pingzhi Li, Min Chen, Jinglei Cheng, Junyu Liu, Tianlong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Aldous--Lyons Conjecture II: Undecidability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper, and its companion [BCLV24], are devoted to a negative resolution of the Aldous--Lyons Conjecture [AL07, Ald07].
  In this part we study tailored non-local games. This is a subclass of non-local games -- combinatorial objects which model certain experiments in quantum mechanics, as well as interactive proofs in complexity theory. Our main result is that, given a tailored non-local game $G$, it is undecidable to distinguish between the case where $G$ has a special kind of perfect strategy, and the case where every strategy for $G$ is far from being perfect. Using a reduction introduced in the companion paper [BCLV24], this undecidability result implies a negative answer to the Aldous--Lyons conjecture. Namely, it implies the existence of unimodular networks that are non-sofic.
  To prove our result, we use a variant of the compression technique developed in MIP*=RE [JNV+21]. Our main technical contribution is to adapt this technique to the class of tailored non-local games. The main difficulty is in establishing answer reduction, which requires a very careful adaptation of existing techniques in the construction of probabilistically checkable proofs. As a byproduct, we are reproving the negation of Connes' embedding problem [Con76] -- i.e., the existence of a $\mathrm{II}_1$-factor which cannot be embedded in an ultrapower of the hyperfinite $\mathrm{II}_1$-factor -- first proved in [JNV+21], using an arguably more streamlined proof. In particular, we incorporate recent simplifications from the literature [dlS22b, Vid22] due to de la Salle and the third author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00173v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lewis Bowen, Michael Chapman, Thomas Vidick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Coherence-Protection Scheme for Quantum Sensors Based on Ultra-Shallow Single Nitrogen-Vacancy Centers in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in the engineering of diamond surface make it possible to stabilize the charge state of 7-30 nanometers deep nitrogen-vacancy (NV) quantum sensors in diamond and to principally remove the charge noise at the surface. However, it is still a challenge to simultaneously increase the action volume of the quantum sensor by placing NV centers 0.5-2 nanometers deep and maintain their favorable spin coherence properties which will be definitely limited by the magnetic noise from the fluctuating nuclear spins of the terminating surface species of diamond. Here we show that leveraging the interplay of the surface induced strain and small constant magnetic fields, the spin coherence times of the ultra-shallow 1-nanometer deep NV center can be significantly enhanced up to the spin-phonon limited regime at room temperature in $^{12}$C enriched diamonds. We demonstrate that our measurement protocol is beneficial to $\sim$10-nanometers deep NV centers too in diamonds with naturally abundant carbon isotopes where the variable response of the spin bath to the direction of the small constant magnetic fields establishes vector magnetometry at the nanoscale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00180v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Pershin, Andr\'as T\'ark\'anyi, Vladimir Verkhovlyuk, Viktor Iv\'ady, Adam Gali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal asymptotic precision bounds for nonlinear quantum metrology under collective dephasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interactions among sensors can provide, in addition to entanglement, an important resource for boosting the precision in quantum estimation protocols. Dephasing noise, however, remains a leading source of decoherence in state-of-the-art quantum sensing platforms. We analyze the impact of classical {\em collective dephasing with arbitrary temporal correlations} on the performance of generalized Ramsey interferometry protocols with \emph{quadratic} encoding of a target frequency parameter. The optimal asymptotic precision bounds are derived for both product coherent spin states and for a class of experimentally relevant entangled spin-squeezed states of $N$ qubit sensors. While, as in linear metrology, entanglement offers no advantage if the noise is Markovian, a precision scaling of $N^{-1}$ is reachable with classical input states in the quadratic setting, which is improved to $N^{-5/4}$ when temporal correlations are present and the Zeno regime is accessible. The use of nonclassical spin-squeezed states and a nonlinear readout further allows for an $N^{-3/2}$ precision scaling, which we prove is asymptotically optimal. We also show how to counter {\em noise-induced bias} by introducing a simple ratio estimator which relies on detecting two suitable system observables, and show that it remains asymptotically unbiased in the presence of dephasing, without detriment to the achievable precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00189v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Riberi, Lorenza Viola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the switching dynamics in a quantum double-well potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spontaneous switching of a quantum particle between the wells of a double-well potential is a phenomenon of general interest to physics and chemistry. It was broadly believed that the switching rate decreases steadily with the size of the energy barrier. This view was challenged by a recent experiment on a driven superconducting Kerr nonlinear oscillator (often called the Kerr-cat qubit or the Kerr parametric oscillator), whose energy barrier can be increased by ramping up the drive. Remarkably, as the drive amplitude increases, the switching rate exhibits a step-like decrease termed the "staircase". The view challenged by the experiment demands a deep review of our understanding of quantum effects in double wells. In this work, we derive a semi-analytical formula for the switching rate that resolves a continuous transition between tunneling- and dissipation-dominated dynamics. These two dynamics are observed respectively in the flat and the steep parts of each step in the staircase. Our formula exposes two distinct dissipative processes that limit tunneling: dephasing and decay. This allows us to predict the critical drive amplitudes where steps occur. In addition, we show that in the regime of a few states in the well and under moderate to low temperatures, highly excited states are populated predominantly via cascaded and direct thermal heating rather than quantum heating. At very low temperatures, however, the perturbation induced by the nonhermitian Hamiltonian becomes important and facilitates a new form of quantum heating. We numerically map the activation mechanism as a function of drive amplitude, damping rate, and temperature. Our theory deepens the understanding of switching dynamics between metastable quantum states, highlights the importance of a general interplay between tunneling and dissipation, and identifies a novel quantum regime in activated transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00209v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qile Su, Rodrigo G. Corti\~nas, Jayameenakshi Venkatraman, Shruti Puri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Global Quantum Communication via Satellite Constellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the optimization of global quantum communication through satellite constellations. We address the challenge of quantum key distribution (QKD) across vast distances and the limitations posed by terrestrial fiber-optic networks. Our research focuses on the configuration of satellite constellations to improve QKD between ground stations and the application of innovative orbital mechanics to reduce latency in quantum information transfer. We introduce a novel approach using quantum relay satellites in Molniya orbits, enhancing communication efficiency and coverage. The use of these high eccentricity orbits allows us to extend the operational presence of satellites over targeted hemispheres, thus maximizing the quantum network's reach. Our findings provide a strategic framework for deploying quantum satellites and relay systems to achieve a robust and efficient global quantum communication network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00280v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichen Gao, Guanqun Song, Ting Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control in Nearly-Adiabatic Two-Level Quantum Systems via Time-Dependent Resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we theoretically analyzed a control protocol based on ``time-dependent resonance" in nearly adiabatic two-level quantum systems, demonstrating that it exhibits properties equivalent to adiabatic control. This protocol is based on ``time-dependent resonance", where the frequency corresponds to the time-dependent energy gap. Through numerical calculations, we showed that this protocol serves as an optimal control protocol. This approach enables efficient and high-precision transitions to the target state. Our findings provide a new perspective on quantum optimal control theory and suggest potential applications in qubit controls and quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00293v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Pure State Uniqueness in Tomography via Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum state tomography (QST) is crucial for understanding and characterizing quantum systems through measurement data. Traditional QST methods face scalability challenges, requiring $\mathcal{O}(d^2)$ measurements for a general $d$-dimensional state. This complexity can be substantially reduced to $\mathcal{O}(d)$ in pure state tomography, indicating that full measurements are unnecessary for pure states. In this paper, we investigate the conditions under which a given pure state can be uniquely determined by a subset of full measurements, focusing on the concepts of uniquely determined among pure states (UDP) and uniquely determined among all states (UDA). The UDP determination inherently involves non-convexity challenges, while the UDA determination, though convex, becomes computationally intensive for high-dimensional systems. To address these issues, we develop a unified framework based on the Augmented Lagrangian Method (ALM). Specifically, our theorem on the existence of low-rank solutions in QST allows us to reformulate the UDA problem with low-rank constraints, thereby reducing the number of variables involved. Our approach entails parameterizing quantum states and employing ALM to handle the constrained non-convex optimization tasks associated with UDP and low-rank UDA determinations. Numerical experiments conducted on qutrit systems and four-qubit symmetric states not only validate theoretical findings but also reveal the complete distribution of quantum states across three uniqueness categories: (A) UDA, (B) UDP but not UDA, and (C) neither UDP nor UDA. This work provides a practical approach for determining state uniqueness, advancing our understanding of quantum state reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahui Wu, Zheng An, Chao Zhang, Xuanran Zhu, Shilin Huang, Bei Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Q3DE: A fault-tolerant quantum computer architecture for multi-bit burst errors by cosmic rays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Demonstrating small error rates by integrating quantum error correction (QEC) into an architecture of quantum computing is the next milestone towards scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing (FTQC). Encoding logical qubits with superconducting qubits and surface codes is considered a promising candidate for FTQC architectures. In this paper, we propose an FTQC architecture, which we call Q3DE, that enhances the tolerance to multi-bit burst errors (MBBEs) by cosmic rays with moderate changes and overhead. There are three core components in Q3DE: in-situ anomaly DEtection, dynamic code DEformation, and optimized error DEcoding. In this architecture, MBBEs are detected only from syndrome values for error correction. The effect of MBBEs is immediately mitigated by dynamically increasing the encoding level of logical qubits and re-estimating probable recovery operation with the rollback of the decoding process. We investigate the performance and overhead of the Q3DE architecture with quantum-error simulators and demonstrate that Q3DE effectively reduces the period of MBBEs by 1000 times and halves the size of their region. Therefore, Q3DE significantly relaxes the requirement of qubit density and qubit chip size to realize FTQC. Our scheme is versatile for mitigating MBBEs, i.e., temporal variations of error properties, on a wide range of physical devices and FTQC architectures since it relies only on the standard features of topological stabilizer codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00331v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/MICRO56248.2022.00079</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2022 55th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Chicago, IL, USA, 2022, pp. 1110-1125</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yasunari Suzuki, Takanori Sugiyama, Tomochika Arai, Wang Liao, Koji Inoue, Teruo Tanimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of memory effects in the dynamic evolution of the spin-boson model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum information processing relies on how dynamics unfold in open quantum systems. In this work, we study the non-Markovian dynamics in the single mode spin-boson model at strong couplings. In order to apply perturbation theory, we transform our Hamiltonian to polaron frame, so that the effective system-bath coupling gets reduced. We employ coherence defined by l1-norm to analyze the non-Markovian effects in the spin-boson model. In the transformed frame of reference, the correlation timescales for the bath are significantly shorter than the system's relaxation timescale-a key assumption for Markovian dynamics. However, intriguingly, we demonstrate that under the large polaron theory, the reduced dynamics exhibit effective non-Markovian behaviour within a specific range of couplings, while remaining Markovian beyond this range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00350v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayees A Mala, Mehboob Rashid, Muzaffar Qadir Lone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence dynamics in a polaron system with collective dephasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within quantum information frameworks, managing decoherence stands as a pivotal task. The present work delves into decoherence dynamics of a dressed qubit, represented by a spinless fermion hopping between two lattice sites that are strongly coupled to a collective bosonic bath. To simplify calculations under strong coupling, we adopt the Lang-Firsov transformation, effectively minimizing system-bath interactions. Within the polaron perspective using Ohmic bath spectral density with a Gaussian cutoff, we identify a fundamental timescale $s$ (equivalently a length scale $l$), dictating coherence decay. Utilizing a quantum master equation in the energy eigen basis while maintaining fixed particle number, we demonstrate that coherence persists for small $s$ values but diminishes for larger ones. Additionally, we explore the utilization of $\pi$-pulses to manipulate decoherence within the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00355v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saima Bashir, Muzaffar Qadir Lone, Prince A Ganai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersinglets can be self-tested with perfect quantum strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersinglets are states of spin zero of $d \ge 3$ particles of $d$ levels. They are invariant under unitary transformations of the form $U^{\otimes d}$ and have applications in metrology, error protection, and communication. They also violate some specific Bell inequalities. However, neither any of these applications {\em require} supersinglets nor any of these of these Bell inequality violations capture the unique properties of the supersinglets. This leads to two questions. Question 1 is whether there exists a task that can only be solved with supersinglets. Question 2 is whether supersinglets can produce a unique $d$-partite, $d$-dimensional nonlocal signature. Here, we answer both questions affirmatively by presenting a protocol that self-test all supersinglets by producing $d$-partite, $d$-dimensional {\em perfect} quantum strategies for any $d \ge 3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00409v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debashis Saha, Ad\'an Cabello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast mixing of weakly interacting fermionic systems at any temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the mixing time of a recently proposed efficiently implementable Lindbladian designed to prepare the Gibbs states in the setting of weakly interacting fermionic systems. We show that at any temperature, the Lindbladian spectral gap for even parity observables is lower bounded by a constant that is independent of the system size, when the interaction strength (e.g., the on-site interaction strength for the Fermi-Hubbard model) is below a constant threshold, which is also independent of the system size. This leads to a mixing time estimate that is at most linear in the system size, thus showing that the corresponding Gibbs states can be prepared efficiently on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00443v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Tong, Yongtao Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The phase diagram of quantum chromodynamics in one dimension on a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum chromodynamics (QCD) phase diagram is key to answering open questions in physics, from states of matter in neutron stars to the early universe. However, classical simulations of QCD face significant computational barriers, such as the sign problem at finite matter densities. Quantum computing offers a promising solution to overcome these challenges. Here, we take an important step toward exploring the QCD phase diagram with quantum devices by preparing thermal states in one-dimensional non-Abelian gauge theories. We experimentally simulate the thermal states of SU(2) and SU(3) gauge theories at finite densities on a trapped-ion quantum computer using a variational method. This is achieved by introducing two features: Firstly, we add motional ancillae to the existing qubit register to efficiently prepare thermal probability distributions. Secondly, we introduce gauge-invariant measurements to enforce local gauge symmetries. This work marks the first lattice gauge theory quantum simulation of QCD at finite density and temperature for two and three colors, laying the foundation to explore QCD phenomena on quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00579v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton T. Than, Yasar Y. Atas, Abhijit Chakraborty, Jinglei Zhang, Matthew T. Diaz, Kalea Wen, Xingxin Liu, Randy Lewis, Alaina M. Green, Christine A. Muschik, Norbert M. Linke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>String breaking dynamics in Ising chain with local vibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the dynamics in the one-dimensional quantum Ising model in which each spin coherently interacts with its phononic mode. The model is motivated by quantum simulators based on Rydberg atoms in tweezers or trapped ions. The configuration of two domain walls simulates the particle-antiparticle connecting string. We concentrate on the effect the local vibrations have on the dynamics of this initial state. Our study supplements recent investigations of string breaking, traditionally studied within quantum chromodynamics (QCD), to quantum many-body systems. Two regimes are identified depending on the strength of the coupling with local vibrations. For weak coupling, the string breaking is slowed down as compared to the dynamics in an isolated Ising string. The strong coupling leads to complicated dynamics in which the domain wall character of excitation is dissolved among many coupled states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00604v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arindam Mallick, Maciej Lewenstein, Jakub Zakrzewski, Marcin P{\l}odzie\'n</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violation of the Thermodynamic Uncertainty Relation in Quantum Collisional Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thermodynamic uncertainty relation (TUR) is a fundamental principle in non-equilibrium thermodynamics that relates entropy production to fluctuations in a system, establishing a trade-off between the precision of an observable and the thermodynamic cost. Investigating TUR violations challenges classical thermodynamic limits, offering the potential for improved precision-entropy trade-offs, which is crucial for enhancing performance and optimization in quantum technologies. In this work, we investigate the thermodynamic uncertainty relation within a quantum collisional model, which offers the advantage of discretizing interactions into successive collisions with auxiliaries, allowing for precise tracking of dynamics and the incorporation of memory effects and non-Markovian behavior. We consider three types of dynamics in the collisional model: one is Markovian evolution, achieved by taking the continuous time limit and imposing the stability condition, while the other two are non-Markovian dynamics - one arising from increasing the collision time between the system and the auxiliaries, and the other from incorporating interactions between the auxiliaries. For the Markovian dynamics, we examine the classical and quantum TUR bounds in the non-equilibrium steady-state regime, and also the finite-time TUR bound. We demonstrate that the classical TUR bound is violated once a certain threshold of collisions with the auxiliaries is exceeded, with the maximum violation observed at the steady state. For the two non-Markovian approaches, we find that the violation of the finite-time TUR bound is highly dependent on the type of non-Markovianity, warranting a detailed comparison.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arghya Maity, Ahana Ghoshal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Noise Considerations for Designing Integrated Solid-State Quantum Memories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As quantum networks expand and are deployed outside research laboratories, a need arises to design and integrate compact control electronics for each memory node. It is essential to understand the performance requirements for such systems, especially concerning tolerable levels of noise, since these specifications dramatically affect a system's design complexity and cost. Here, using an approach that can be easily generalized across quantum-hardware platforms, we present a case study based on nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond. We model and experimentally verify the effects of phase noise and timing jitter in the control system in conjunction with the spin qubit's environmental noise. We further consider the impact of different phase noise characteristics on the fidelity of dynamical decoupling sequences. The results demonstrate a procedure to specify design requirements for integrated quantum control signal generators for solid-state spin qubits, depending on their coherence time, intrinsic noise spectrum, and required fidelity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00683v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tzu-Yung Huang, David A. Hopper, Kaisarbek Omirzakhov, Mohamad Hossein Idjadi, S. Alexander Breitweiser, Firooz Aflatouni, Lee C. Bassett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Probability Theory: notes for a short course</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A slightly revised version of notes distributed during a short course on GPTs, given at the Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics in March and April of 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00718v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Wilce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of long-range interaction in critical quantum metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-range interacting quantum systems are useful for improving the performance of various applications of quantum technologies. In this work, we carry out a detailed analysis of how the long-range interaction affects the measurement precision in critical quantum metrology. By employing the paradigmatic model of a Kiteav chain with power-law decaying interaction, we focus on the impacts of long-range interaction on the critical sensing for the scenarios with and without uncertainty in system parameters.We show that the long-range interaction can be used as a valuable resource for enhancing the sensitivity of critical parameter estimation in both scenarios. Our findings not only provide more insights into the features of the long-range interacting systems, but also verify the usefulness of long-range interacting systems in quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00771v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Xia Niu, Qian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic work and heat for a quantum process: Approach by Hamiltonian decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The separation of internal energy into heat and work in quantum thermodynamics is a controversial issue for a long time, and we revisit and solve this problem in this work. It is shown that the Hamiltonian plays dual roles for a quantum system, and by decomposing the interaction Hamiltonian between system and environment accordingly, an ``effective Hamiltonian" for an open quantum system can be proposed. The explicit expression of the effective Hamiltonian is obtained systematically, and as a consequence, the internal energy of an open quantum system can be well defined, leading to the reasonable definitions of work and heat for a general quantum process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00832v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Zhou, Jiangyang Pu, Xiaohua Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon-photon coupling induced bound state in the continuum and transparency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents the coherent and dissipative coupling realized in the hybrid photonic resonators that have been achieved via the constructive and destructive interference of the photonic resonator fields with the radiation of a common transmission line fed with microwave photons. In the dissipative coupling regime we have found the coexistence of a peculiar phenomenon bound state in the continuum (BIC) near the crossing of frequency of the uncoupled resonators by satisfying the Friedrich-Wintgen BICs condition. Again just by rotating one of the samples and with the dynamic adjustment of a parameter we have achieved coupling induced transparency between the photonic resonators. This transition from BIC in the absorption regime to transparency opens avenues for different sorts of plain or programmable oscillators, filters, quantum information processors, sensors etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00900v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ekta Tunwal, Kuldeep Kumar Shrivastava, Rakesh Kumar Nayak, Ravi Kumar, Somak Bhattacharyya, Rajeev Singh, Biswanath Bhoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provable DI-QRNG protocols based on self-testing methodologies in preparation and measure scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present two Device Independent Quantum Random Number Generator (DI-QRNG) protocols using two self-testing methodologies in Preparation \&amp; Measure (P\&amp;M) scenario. These two methodologies are the variants of two well-known non-local games, namely, CHSH and pseudo-telepathy games, in P\&amp;M framework. We exploit them as distinguishers in black-box settings to differentiate the classical and the quantum paradigms and hence to certify the Device Independence. The first self-test was proposed by Tavakoli et al. (Phys. Rev. A, 2018). We show that this is actually a P\&amp;M variant of the CHSH game. Then based on this self-test, we design our first DI-QRNG protocol. We also propose a new self-testing methodology, which is the first of its kind that is reducible from pseudo-telepathy game in P\&amp;M framework. Based on this new self-test, we design our second DI-QRNG protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00916v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asmita Samanta, Arpita Maitra, Goutam Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudorandom quantum authentication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the pseudorandom quantum authentication scheme (PQAS), an efficient method for encrypting quantum states that relies solely on the existence of pseudorandom unitaries (PRUs). The scheme guarantees that for any eavesdropper with quantum polynomial-time (QPT) computational power, the encrypted states are indistinguishable from the maximally mixed state. Furthermore, the receiver can verify that the state has not been tampered with and recover the original state with asymptotically unit fidelity. Our scheme is cost-effective, requiring only polylogarithmic circuit depth and a single shared key to encrypt a polynomial number of states. Notably, the PQAS can potentially exist even without quantum-secure one-way functions, requiring fundamentally weaker computational assumptions than semantic classical cryptography. Additionally, PQAS is secure against attacks that plague protocols based on QPT indistinguishability from Haar random states, such as chosen-plaintext attacks (CPAs) and attacks that reveal meta-information such as quantum resources. We relate the amount of meta-information that is leaked to quantum pseudoresources, giving the concept a practical meaning. As an application, we construct important cryptographic primitives, such as verifiable pseudorandom density matrices (VPRDMs), which are QPT-indistinguishable from random mixed states while being efficiently verifiable via a secret key, as well as verifiable noise-robust EFI pairs and one-way state generators (OWSGs). Our results establish a new paradigm of quantum information processing with weaker computational assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00951v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Haug, Nikhil Bansal, Wai-Keong Mok, Dax Enshan Koh, Kishor Bharti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional point in a trimer chain of oscillators with a quadratic driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exceptional points of a dissipative chain of three coupled oscillators (trimer), which is driven by quadratic photon, are investigated. The exceptional points emerge from the coalescence of both eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the dynamical matrix that describes the first moments of the trimer. At the exceptional point, we found that the optical spectrum is split into two peaks, instead of a conventional single peak, as in the case of a single oscillator. In particular, the positions of these peaks correspond to the natural frequency of the trimer in a \textit{closed system}, which depends only on the coupling strength. Furthermore, after passing the exceptional point, the peak positions do not change, which can be used to estimate the coupling strength between oscillators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01033v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M Shoufie Ukhtary, Albert Andersen, Donny Dwiputra, M. Jauhar Kholili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Genetic Algorithm Framework for the MaxCut Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01058v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The MaxCut problem is a fundamental problem in Combinatorial Optimization, with significant implications across diverse domains such as logistics, network design, and statistical physics. The algorithm represents innovative approaches that balance theoretical rigor with practical scalability. The proposed method introduces a Quantum Genetic Algorithm (QGA) using a Grover-based evolutionary framework and divide-and-conquer principles. By partitioning graphs into manageable subgraphs, optimizing each independently, and applying graph contraction to merge the solutions, the method exploits the inherent binary symmetry of MaxCut to ensure computational efficiency and robust approximation performance. Theoretical analysis establishes a foundation for the efficiency of the algorithm, while empirical evaluations provide quantitative evidence of its effectiveness. On complete graphs, the proposed method consistently achieves the true optimal MaxCut values, outperforming the Semidefinite Programming (SDP) approach, which provides up to 99.7\% of the optimal solution for larger graphs. On Erd\H{o}s-R\'{e}nyi random graphs, the QGA demonstrates competitive performance, achieving median solutions within 92-96\% of the SDP results. These results showcase the potential of the QGA framework to deliver competitive solutions, even under heuristic constraints, while demonstrating its promise for scalability as quantum hardware evolves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01058v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo A. Viana, Fernando M. de Paula Neto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting high-dimensional entanglement by local randomized projections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The characterization of high-dimensional entanglement plays a crucial role in the field of quantum information science. Conventional methods perform either fixed measurement bases or randomized measurements with high-order moments. Here, we introduce a criterion for estimating the Schmidt number of bipartite high-dimensional states based on local randomized projections with first-order moments. To extract more information from limited experimental data, we propose an estimation algorithm of the Schmidt number. We exhibit the performance of the proposed approach by considering the maximally entangled state under depolarizing and random noise models. Our approach not only obtains a more accurate estimation of the Schmidt number but also reduces the number of projections compared to known methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01088v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Min Liang, Shuheng Liu, Shao-Ming Fei, Qiongyi He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurable Improvement in Multi-Qubit Readout Using a Kinetic Inductance Traveling Wave Parametric Amplifier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01185v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Increasing the size and complexity of quantum information systems requires highly-multiplexed readout architectures, as well as amplifier chains operating near the quantum limit (QL) of added noise. While documented prior efforts in KITWPA integration in quantum systems are scarce, in this work we demonstrate integration of a KI-TWPA with a multiplexed-qubit device. To quantify the system noise improvement we perform an ac Stark shift calibration to precisely determine noise power levels on-chip (at each cavity's reference plane) and the total system gain. We then characterize the qubit state measurement fidelity and the corresponding signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). To conduct the most faithful measurement of the benefits offered by the KI-TWPA we perform these measurements for readout chains where the high electron mobility transistor (HEMT) amplifier is the first-stage amplifier (FSA) - with none of the external hardware required to operate the KI-TWPA - and with the KI-TWPA as the FSA. While some readout cavities fall outside the KI-TWPA bandwidth, for those inside the bandwidth we demonstrate a maximum improvement in the state measurement SNR by a factor of 1.45, and increase the fidelity from 96.2% to 97.8%. These measurements demonstrate a system noise below 5 quanta referenced on-chip and we bound the KI-TWPA excess noise to be below 4 quanta for the six cavities inside its bandwidth. These results show a promising path forward for realizing quantum-limited readout chains in large qubit systems using a single parametric amplifier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01185v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TASC.2024.3525451</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Castellanos-Beltran, L. Howe, A. Giachero, M. R. Vissers, D. Labranca, J. N. Ullom, P. F. Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric quantum computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a systematic study of "symmetric quantum circuits", a restricted model of quantum computation where the restriction is symmetry-based. This model is well-adapted for studying the role of symmetries in quantum speedups, and it extends a powerful notion of symmetric computation studied in the classical setting.
  We show that symmetric quantum circuits go beyond the capabilities of their classical counterparts by efficiently implementing key quantum subroutines such as amplitude amplification and phase estimation, as well as the linear combination of unitaries technique. In addition, we consider the task of symmetric state preparation and show that it can be performed efficiently in several interesting and nontrivial cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01214v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davi Castro-Silva, Tom Gur, Sergii Strelchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Recurrence Criteria for Classes of Open Quantum Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the recurrence of open quantum walks (OQWs) induced by finite-dimensional coins $(L,B,R)$. The focus is on homogeneous OQWs with a set of vertices $\mathbb{Z}$, the set of integers. We present three distinct recurrence criteria, each adapted to different types of coins. The first criterion was developed for a class of Lazy OQWs in any finite dimension, where the presented criterion is associated with an auxiliary map and its only invariant state, resulting in the first recurrence criterion for Lazy OQWs. The second one is restricted to Lazy OQWs of dimension 2, where we provide a complete characterization of the recurrence for this lower dimension. Finally, we present a general criterion for finite-dimensional coins in the non-lazy case $(B=0)$, which generalizes many of the previously known results. This new criterion holds for irreducible and reducible OQWs through a decomposition of the Hilbert space where our quantum states act.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01249v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Newton Loebens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-Qubit Variational Algorithms in Silicon Photonics with Integrated Entangled Photon Sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms are hybrid quantum-classical approaches extensively studied for their potential to leverage near-term quantum hardware for computational advantages. In this work, we successfully execute two variational quantum algorithms on a silicon photonic integrated circuit at room temperature: a variational quantum eigensolver for the Hydrogen molecule and a variational quantum factorization for semi-prime numbers. In our reconfigurable silicon photonic circuit, four identical spontaneous-four-wave-mixing-based integrated photon pair sources are used to prepare two path-entangled ququarts, whose correlation gives rise to the resource for generic trial states' preparation. This marks a first demonstration of variational quantum algorithms on a photonic quantum simulator with integrated photon pair sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01301v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Baldazzi, Matteo Sanna, Massimo Borghi, Stefano Azzini, Lorenzo Pavesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructive impact of Wannier-Stark field on environment-boosted quantum batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the ground states of the Bose- and Fermi-Hubbard model as the battery's initial state, we demonstrate that using the Wannier-Stark (WS) field for charging in addition to onsite interactions can increase the maximum power of the battery. Although the benefit is not ubiquitous, bosonic batteries are more affected by the WS field than fermionic ones. In particular, there exists a critical WS field strength above which the power gets increased in the battery. Further, we determine a closed form expression of the stored work when the battery is in the ground state of the Bose- and Fermi-Hubbard model with only hopping term and the charging is carried out with onsite interactions and WS field irrespective of lattice-size of the battery. Moreover, we exhibit that it is possible to extract work in the fermionic batteries even without charging when the edge sites are attached to two local thermal baths having high temperatures -- this process we refer to as {\it environment-assisted ergotropy}. Note, however, that the bosonic batteries are able to exhibit such an environmental benefit in the transient regime when the lattice-size is increased and when Wannier-Stark field is present. Nonetheless, if the onsite interaction or WS potential with a critical strength is utilized as a charger, energy can be stored and extracted from both bosonic and fermionic batteries in the presence of the thermal baths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01309v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Animesh Ghosh, Tanoy Kanti Konar, Leela Ganesh Chandra Lakkaraju, Aditi Sen De</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum-induced atomic grating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atom-field interactions, induced by the vacuum of the electromagnetic field, exhibit a variety of fundamental phenomena and effects. In this paper, we study the electromagnetically induced atomic grating due to the vacuum state of the radiation field. Using an ensemble of cold atoms, strongly coupled to an optical cavity, we show that a probe field, propagating through the atomic medium, diffracts to zeroth and first-order diffraction peaks with few photons and even by the electromagnetic vacuum field of the cavity mode. As the number of photons in the cavity increases, the intensity of the first-order diffraction peak initially rises and then exhibits a decreasing trend. Furthermore, we observe that the first-order peak intensity reaches its maximum at resonance for both the vacuum and single-photon cavity state. However, as the number of photons increases further, this peak at resonance transforms into a dip, accompanied by two side peaks at off-resonance positions. This transition from a peak to a dip may potentially be used to distinguish the quantum state of the cavity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01385v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.063717</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 063717 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Shuraim, Muhammad Waseem, Shahid Qamar, Muhammad Irfan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel assembly of neutral atom arrays with an SLM using linear phase interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present fast parallel rearrangement of single atoms in optical tweezers into arbitrary geometries by updating holograms displayed by an ultra fast spatial light modulator. Using linear interpolation of the tweezer position and the optical phase between the start and end arrays, we can calculate and display holograms every 2.76(2) ms. To show the versatility of our method, we sort the same atomic sample into multiple geometries with success probabilities exceeding 99 % per imaging and rearrangement cycle. This makes the method a useful tool for rearranging large atom arrays for quantum computation and quantum simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01391v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivo H. A. Knottnerus, Yu Chih Tseng, Alexander Urech, Robert J. C. Spreeuw, Florian Schreck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Time Quantum Gibbs Sampling for Fermi-Hubbard Model at any Temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, there have been several advancements in quantum algorithms for Gibbs sampling. These algorithms simulate the dynamics generated by an artificial Lindbladian, which is meticulously constructed to obey a detailed-balance condition with the Gibbs state of interest, ensuring it is a stationary point of the evolution, while simultaneously having efficiently implementable time steps. The overall complexity then depends primarily on the mixing time of the Lindbladian, which can vary drastically, but which has been previously bounded in the regime of high enough temperatures [Rouz\'e {\it et al.}~arXiv:2403.12691 and arXiv:2411.04885].
  In this work, we calculate the spectral gap of the Lindbladian for free fermions using third quantisation, and then prove a constant gap of the perturbed Lindbladian corresponding to interacting fermions up to some maximal coupling strength. This is achieved by using theorems about stability of the gap for lattice fermions. Our methods apply at any constant temperature and independently of the system size. The gap then provides an upper bound on the mixing time, and hence on the overall complexity of the quantum algorithm, proving that the purified Gibbs state of weakly interacting (quasi-)local fermionic systems of any dimension can be prepared in $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}} (n^3 \operatorname{polylog}(1/\epsilon))$ time on $\mathcal{O}(n)$ qubits, where $n$ denotes the size of the system and $\epsilon$ the desired accuracy. We provide exact numerical simulations for small system sizes supporting the theory and also identify different suitable jump operators and filter functions for the sought-after regime of intermediate coupling in the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01412v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\v{S}t\v{e}p\'an \v{S}m\'id, Richard Meister, Mario Berta, Roberto Bondesan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir Effect in Stochastic Semi-Classical Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article aims to examine the Casimir effect in the framework of stochastic semi-classical gravity. We commence with the semi-classical Einstein-Langevin equation, which introduces a first-order correction to the semi-classical gravity theory. Subsequently, we analyze the alteration in the Casimir force caused by this type of correction. Our results demonstrate that the corrections exhibit significant sensitivity to both the distance between the two parallel plates and the order parameter of the weak field. This finding underscores the nuanced interplay between these factors and the overall behavior of the system, providing valuable insights into the underlying dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01415v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Hossein. B. Khoshnevis, Sadaf Ebadi, M. Reza Lahooti, Reza Pirmoradian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic and Real-time Dynamic Properties of Complex Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.16270v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the complex Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (cSYK) numerically and investigate thermodynamic behavior of cSYK model across varying chemical potentials. We discover that the cSYK model remarkably mirrors the first-order phase transition seen in the van der Waals-Maxwell system, culminating at a non-mean-field critical point with distinctively different critical exponents. We analyze in detail the similarity between the van der Waals phase transition and the cSYK model, and further explore the mechanism by which the chemical potential drives the phase transition in the system. Exact diagonalization for the cSYK model reveals the significant impact of chemical potential on energy distribution, with observable energy gaps in the gapped phase. Quantum chaos indicators, including spectral form factors, suggest more stable energy states in the neutral case. Real-time dynamics, analyzed via analytical continuation of Schwinger-Dyson equations, show rapid decay in the gapless phase and prolonged oscillation lifetimes in the gapped regime. Spectral functions imply a shift from a continuous to a discrete energy level distribution, emphasizing the critical role of chemical potential in shaping spectral properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.16270v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sizheng Cao, Xian-Hui Ge, Yi-Cheng Rui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A QUBO Formulation for the Generalized Takuzu/LinkedIn Tango Game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we present a QUBO formulation for the Takuzu game (or Binairo), for the most recent LinkedIn game, Tango, and for its generalizations. We optimize the number of variables needed to solve the combinatorial problem, making it suitable to be solved by quantum devices with fewer resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00002v1</guid>
      <category>cs.OH</category>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mata Ali, Edgar Mencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear topological pumping of edge solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00019v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study how nonlinear strength affects topological pumping of edge solitons by using nonlinear Gross-Pitaevskii equation. For weak nonlinear strength, the introduction of nonlinearity breaks the symmetry of the energy spectrum, which makes the topological pumping from the left edge to the right edges differ from the inverse process. For moderate nonlinear strength, self-crossing structures appear in the spectrum, the right-to-left adiabatic pumping channel is destroyed, and only left-to-right topological pumping can be achieved under slow modulation. As the nonlinear strength further inreases, although left-to-right topological pumping in one pumping cycle also breaks down, we find that a thin soliton which is located in a single left edge can be mixed with the bulk soliton, and hybridized topological pumping of edge and bulk solitons can be realized after multiple pumping cycles. For stronger nonlinear strength, edge solitons are self-trapped and all topological pumping channels are shut down. Our work could trigger further studies of the interplay between nonlinearity and topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00019v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinrui You, Liaoyuan Xiao, Yongguan Ke, Chaohong Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Idealism II: Reassessment of Competing Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores the intersection of identity, individuality, and reality through competing frameworks, including classical metaphysics, quantum mechanics, and computational theories. Traditional metaphysical notions of fixed identity are challenged by advancements in cloning, teletransportation, and digital replication, which reveal the fluid and relational nature of individuality. Quantum mechanics further complicates these notions, emphasizing the indistinguishability and contextuality of fundamental particles. Computational approaches, such as the Ruliad and Constructor Theory, offer expansive views of emergent realities but often lack practical constraints for observer relevance. Algorithmic idealism is introduced as a unifying framework, proposing that reality is an emergent construct governed by computational rules prioritizing coherence, sufficiency, and observer-dependent experiences. By redefining identity as an informational construct and reality as a process shaped by algorithmic transitions, algorithmic idealism resolves foundational paradoxes and offers a superior lens for understanding existence in an increasingly digital and interconnected world. The framework bridges gaps between competing theories, providing a coherent and pragmatic model for addressing ethical, metaphysical, and technological challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00022v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Sienicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar, Vector Perturbations and Effective Hawking Radiation of Cylindrical Black Holes in $f(\mathcal{R})$ and Ricci-Inverse Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00060v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates scalar perturbations and quasinormal modes (QNMs) associated with cylindrical black holes constructed within the frameworks of $f(\mathcal{R})$-gravity and Ricci-Inverse ($\mathcal{RI}$) gravity. Moreover, we study the modified Hawking radiation in these black hole solutions and analyze the effects of coupling constants. These modified theories, which extend general relativity by introducing higher-order curvature corrections and additional geometric terms, provide a rich platform for exploring deviations from standard gravitational physics. The study begins by revisiting the cylindrical black holes in these modified gravity theories, where the effective cosmological constants respectively, are represented by $\Lambda_m^{f(\mathcal{R})}$ and $\Lambda_m^{\mathcal{RI}}$ related to the coupling constants unique to each framework. Afterwards, the QNMs, intrinsic damped oscillations of the black hole space-time, are analyzed to probe the stability of the system, with the effective potential $V$ revealing the impact of the modified gravity parameters. Additionally, the thermodynamic properties of the black holes are examined through the lens of the Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP), which introduces quantum corrections to Hawking radiation. The GUP-modified Hawking temperature and entropy are derived, demonstrating significant deviations from classical results and highlighting the quantum gravitational effects in these modified frameworks. By linking QNMs, thermodynamics, and quantum corrections, this work not only deepens the understanding of modified gravity theories but also offers potential observational pathways to test their validity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00060v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faizuddin Ahmed, \.Izzet Sakall{\i}, Ahmad Al-Badawi, Abdelmalek Bouzenada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Community detection by simulated bifurcation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00075v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Community detection, also known as graph partitioning, is a well-known NP-hard combinatorial optimization problem with applications in diverse fields such as complex network theory, transportation, and smart power grids. The problem's solution space grows drastically with the number of vertices and subgroups, making efficient algorithms crucial. In recent years, quantum computing has emerged as a promising approach to tackling NP-hard problems. This study explores the use of a quantum-inspired algorithm, Simulated Bifurcation (SB), for community detection. Modularity is employed as both the objective function and a metric to evaluate the solutions. The community detection problem is formulated as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problem, enabling seamless integration with the SB algorithm. Experimental results demonstrate that SB effectively identifies community structures in benchmark networks such as Zachary's Karate Club and the IEEE 33-bus system. Remarkably, SB achieved the highest modularity, matching the performance of Fujitsu's Digital Annealer, while surpassing results obtained from two quantum machines, D-Wave and IBM. These findings highlight the potential of Simulated Bifurcation as a powerful tool for solving community detection problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00075v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Li, Yi-Lun Du, Nan Su, Konrad Tywoniuk, Kyle Godbey, Horst St\"ocker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Invariant Quantum Latin Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A quantum Latin square is an $n \times n$ array of unit vectors where each row and column forms an orthonormal basis of a fixed complex vector space. We introduce the notion of $(G,G')$-invariant quantum Latin squares for finite groups $G$ and $G'$. These are quantum Latin squares with rows and columns indexed by $G$ and $G'$ respectively such that the inner product of the $a,b$-entry with the $c,d$-entry depends only on $a^{-1}c \in G$ and $b^{-1}d \in G'$. This definition is motivated by the notion of group invariant bijective correlations introduced in [Roberson \&amp; Schmidt (2020)], and every group invariant quantum Latin square produces a group invariant bijective correlation, though the converse does not hold. In this work we investigate these group invariant quantum Latin squares and their corresponding correlations. Our main result is that, up to applying a global isometry to every vector in a $(G,G')$-invariant quantum Latin square, there is a natural bijection between these objects and trace and conjugate transpose preserving isomorphisms between the group algebras of $G$ and $G'$. This in particular proves that a $(G,G')$-invariant quantum Latin square exists if and only if the multisets of degrees of irreducible representations are equal for $G$ and $G'$. Another motivation for this line of work is that whenever Cayley graphs for groups $G$ and $G'$ are quantum isomorphic, then there is a $(G,G')$-invariant quantum correlation witnessing this, and thus it suffices to consider such correlations when searching for quantum isomorphic Cayley graphs. Given a group invariant quantum correlation, we show how to construct all pairs of graphs for which it gives a quantum isomorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00196v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnbj\"org Soff\'ia \'Arnad\'ottir, David E. Roberson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on the local calculation of decoherence of quantum superpositions in de Sitter spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00213v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the decoherence effect of quantum superposition in de Sitter (dS) spacetime due to the presence of the cosmological horizon. Using the algebraic approach of quantum field theory on curved spacetime, we derive the precise expression for the expected number of entangling particles in the scalar field case. This expression establishes the relation between the decoherence and the local two-point correlation function. Specifically, we analyze the quantum superposition Gendankenexperiment performed by a local observer at the center of dS spacetime. We compute the entangling particle numbers in scalar field, electromagnetic field, and gravitational field scenarios. It is demonstrated that the quantum spatial superposition state can be decohered by emitting entangling particles into the cosmological horizon. Our setup is equivalent to an accelerating observer in 5-dimensional Minkowski spacetime. The results for the scalar and electromagnetic cases are consistent with those obtained in Ref.[1], which investigated the decoherence effect from the perspective of an accelerating observer in Minkovski spacetime. However, our result fixes the numerical prefactor of the gravitational decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00213v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ran Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative entropy formulation of thermalization process in a Schwarzschild spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00229v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of the thermalization process in an entropic formulation for the Unruh-DeWitt (UDW) detector outside a Schwarzschild black hole. We derive the late-time dynamics of the detector in the context of open quantum system, and capture the path distinguishability and thermodynamic irreversibility of detector thermalization process by using quantum relative entropy (QRE). We find that beyond the Planckian transition rate, the refined thermalization process in detector Hilbert space can be distinguished by the time behavior of the related QRE. We show that the exotic position-dependent behaviors of the QRE emerge corresponding to different choices of black hole vacua (i.e., the Boulware, Hartle-Hawking, and Unruh vacua). Finally, from a perspective of quantum thermodynamics, we recast the free energy change of the UDW detector undergoing Hawking radiation into an entropic combination form, where the classical Kullback-Leibler divergence and quantum coherence are presented in specific QRE-like forms. With growing Hawking temperature, we find that the consumption rate of quantum coherence is larger than that of its classical counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00229v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Wei Han, Zhichun Ouyang, Zhiyao Hu, Jun Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of quantum entanglement in superposed diamond spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A comprehensive study integrating the microscopic structure of spacetime and the principle of quantum superposition is capable of offering a fundamental bottom-up approach for understanding the quantum aspect of gravity. In this paper, we present a framework for the superposition causal diamond spacetime and analyze the behavior of quantum entanglement influenced by the spacetime superposition from the perspective of relativistic quantum information. For the first time, we combine the concept of spacetime superposition with causal diamonds and derive the analytical expression of the Unruh-diamond vacuum state for Dirac fields in the superposed causal diamond spacetime. Based on this, we analyze both initially correlated and uncorrelated modes in superposed and classical causal diamond spacetimes, and quantify how quantum thermal effects arising from spacetime structure alter entanglement. Our findings reveal that quantum entanglement degrades in classical diamond spacetime, while the superposing structure of spacetime generates additional entanglement resources between modes in superposed diamond spacetimes. From a quantum information perspective, our results suggest that the characteristics of spacetime superposition can serve as valuable resources for performing quantum information processing tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00246v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaofang Liu, Changjing Zeng, Jieci Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectra of Magnetoroton and Chiral Graviton Modes of Fractional Chern Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Employing the state-of-the-art time-dependent variational principle algorithm, we compute the spectra of charge neutral excitations in the $\nu=1/2$ fractional Chern insulator (FCI) on the Haldane honeycomb lattice model with hard-core bosons. The magnetoroton visualized from the dynamic density structure factor, acquire a minimum gap at finite momentum that can go soft with increasing interaction and give rise to a charge density wave (CDW) at the same wavevector. The sharper and more concentrated spectral weight of the roton mode is observed when approaching the FCI-CDW transition while the single-particle gap remains intact. We also resolve the graviton mode around $\Gamma$ point of the Brillouin zone by measuring the dynamic quadrupolar density correlations. Interestingly, we not only reveal the graviton response is chiral for a certain FCI, but also show the different chiralities of the graviton of opposite-sign Hall conductance for the first time. Our results offer the clear spectral observations of magnetoroton and chiral graviton in a lattice model of FCI and will have relevance towards the on-going experiments of tunable FCIs in quantum moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00247v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Long, Hongyu Lu, Han-Qing Wu, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clifford circuits Augmented Matrix Product States for fermion systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00413v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Clifford circuits Augmented Matrix Product States (CAMPS) was recently proposed to leverage the advantages of both Clifford circuits and Matrix Product States (MPS). Clifford circuits can support large entanglement and can be efficiently simulated classically according to the Gottesman-Knill theorem. So in CAMPS, MPS needs only to handle the so-called Non-stabilizerness Entanglement Entropy which significantly improves the simulation accuracy for a given bond dimension. In this work, we generalize CAMPS to study the Fermion system by taking advantage of the Jordan-Wigner transformation which can map the studied Fermion system to a spin system. We benchmark the method on both the spinless $t-V$ model and the spinful Hubbard model. Our test results show significant improvement of the accuracy of CAMPS over MPS, especially when the interactions are strong. Fermionic CAMPS provides a useful tool for the accurate study of many-body fermion systems in the future and has the potential to help resolve long-standing issues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00413v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiale Huang, Xiangjian Qian, Mingpu Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intuitive Analysis of the Quantization-based Optimization: From Stochastic and Quantum Mechanical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an intuitive analysis of the optimization technique based on the quantization of an objective function. Quantization of an objective function is an effective optimization methodology that decreases the measure of a level set containing several saddle points and local minima and finds the optimal point at the limit level set. To investigate the dynamics of quantization-based optimization, we derive an overdamped Langevin dynamics model from an intuitive analysis to minimize the level set by iterative quantization. We claim that quantization-based optimization involves the quantities of thermodynamical and quantum mechanical optimization as the core methodologies of global optimization. Furthermore, on the basis of the proposed SDE, we provide thermodynamic and quantum mechanical analysis with Witten-Laplacian. The simulation results with the benchmark functions, which compare the performance of the nonlinear optimization, demonstrate the validity of the quantization-based optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00436v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwuk Seok, Changsik Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Physics of Quantum 2.0: Challenges in understanding Quantum Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00447v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Almost a century on from the culmination of the first revolution in quantum physics, we are poised for another. Even as we engage in the creation of impactful quantum technologies, it is imperative for us to face the challenges in understanding the phenomenology of various emergent forms of quantum matter. This will involve building on decades of progress in quantum condensed matter physics, and going beyond the well-established Ginzburg-Landau-Wilson paradigm for quantum matter. We outline and discuss several outstanding challenges, including the need to explore and identify the organisational principles that can guide the development of theories, key experimental phenomenologies that continue to confound, and the formulation of methods that enable progress. These efforts will enable the prediction of new quantum materials whose properties facilitate the creation of next generation technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00447v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2399-1984/ad9976</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Futures 8 (2024) 042502</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Siddhartha Lal, Mayank Shreshtha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic role of chemical bonding in the formation of altermagnetism: Reflection from correlated electron system NiS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Altermagnetism, a new collinear magnetic state that has traits of both ferromagnetism and antiferromagnetism, has gained significant attention in the last few years and the underlying mechanisms driving this quantum phase are still evolving. Going beyond the phenomenological models and group theoretical analyses, which focus on providing a binary explanation of the presence or absence of the altermagnetic state, in this work, we explored the role of crystal chemical bonding. As the latter successfully integrates the crystal and orbital symmetries and is tunable, it provides a quantitative and more realistic mechanism to explain the formation of altermagnetism. From the first principle calculations and tight-binding models within the framework of the linear combination of atomic orbitals on NiS, belonging to the hexagonal NiAs family (e.g. CrSb, MnTe, etc.), we reveal that the second neighbor interaction between the orbitals of the non-magnetic atoms is the most deterministic in inducing altermagnetism. These second-neighbor bondings modulate the intra-sublattice interactions differently for the opposite spin sublattices. As a consequence, the antiferromagnetic sublattice band degeneracy is lifted and it results in momentum dependent altermagnetic spin split (ASS). We further reveal that the strong altermagnetism is observed in these materials due to the participation of multiple and selective orbitals, both from Ni and S, in the chemical bonding. We proposed twelve antinodal regions in the NiAs type hexagonal crystals, where ASS split is maximum. Specific to NiS, ASS increases with correlation, and for the edge valence and conduction bands it can go beyond 1eV, which makes this compound ideal for carrying out altermagnetic experiments and for exploring non-trivial quantum transport through electron and hole doping. The present study opens up new pathways to tailor tunable altermagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00453v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arijit Mandal, Arindom Das, B. R. K. Nanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analogue black string in a quantum harmonic oscillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a scalar particle without self-interaction or backreaction from the space-time background, the dynamics are governed by the Klein-Gordon equation. In this work, we write the exact solution of this equation in the background of a chargeless, static black string in terms of the biconfluent Heun function. In this curious system, we are able to explore what happens if we have negative values for the masses. The eigenvalue problem provides complex energy values for the particle, which may indicate the presence of quasinormal modes. We show a simple quantum system that can imitate the particle in the black string background, whose solutions are also applications of the biconfluent Heun function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00478v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus E. Pereira, Alexandre G. M. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum many-body dynamics for fermionic t-J model simulated with atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00552v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fermionic t-J model has been widely recognized as a canonical model in understanding various strongly correlated phases like cuprate high-Tc superconductivity. Simulating this model with controllable quantum platforms offers new possibilities to probe high-Tc physics, yet suffering challenges. Here we propose a novel scheme to realize the t-J model in a programmable Rydberg-dressed tweezer array. By properly engineering the Rydberg-dressed dipole-dipole interaction and inter-tweezer couplings, a highly tunable fermionic t-J model with next-nearest-neighbour hopping terms is achieved. We particularly explore quantum many-body dynamics in the large J/t limit, a regime far beyond the conventional optical lattices and cuprates. Notably, we predict a nontrivial self-pinning effect enforced by local quantum entanglement that characterizes a novel type of Hilbert space fragmentation. This effect leads to the breakdown of Krylov restricted thermalization. Our prediction opens a new horizon in exploring exotic quantum many-body dynamics with t-J model in tweezer arrays, and shall also make a step towards simulating the high-Tc physics in cold atom systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00552v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye-bing Zhang, Xin-Chi Zhou, Bao-Zong Wang, Xiong-Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of ST2 centers in natural and CVD diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ST2 center is an optically addressable point defect in diamond that facilitates spin initialization and readout. However, while this study presents the discovery of ST2 centers first observed in a natural diamond and provides a reliable technique for artificially creating them, its chemical structure remains unknown. To assess the potential of ST2, we map out its basic optical characteristics, reveal its electronic level structure, and quantify the intrinsic transition rates. Furthermore, we investigate its response to microwaves, static magnetic fields, and the polarization of excitation laser light, revealing twelve inequivalent orientations of the ST2 center. Simultaneous exposure to microwaves and static magnetic fields also reveals an exceptionally wide acceptance angle for sensing strong magnetic fields, unlike the well-established NV center, which is sensitive only within a narrow cone aligned with its symmetry axis. This finding establishes the ST2 center as a highly promising candidate for nanoscale quantum sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00570v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Foglszinger, Andrej Denisenko, Georgy V. Astakhov, Lev Kazak, Petr Siyushev, Alexander M. Zaitsev, Roman Kolesov, J\"org Wrachtrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Parallelism for Fast Feynman Diagrammatics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diagrammatic expansions are a paradigmatic and powerful tool of quantum many-body theory. Their evaluation to high order, e.g., by the Diagrammatic Monte Carlo technique, can provide unbiased results in strongly correlated and challenging regimes. However, calculating a factorial number of terms to acceptable precision remains very costly even for state-of-the-art methods. We achieve a dramatic acceleration of evaluating Feynman's diagrammatic series by use of specialised hardware architecture within the recently introduced combinatorial summation (CoS) framework. We present how exploiting the massive parallelism and concurrency available from GPUs leads to orders of magnitude improvement in computation time even on consumer-grade hardware. This provides a platform for making probes of novel phenomena of strong correlations much more accessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00675v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Sturt, Evgeny Kozik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensuring superior learning outcomes and data security for authorized learner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The learner's ability to generate a hypothesis that closely approximates the target function is crucial in machine learning. Achieving this requires sufficient data; however, unauthorized access by an eavesdropping learner can lead to security risks. Thus, it is important to ensure the performance of the "authorized" learner by limiting the quality of the training data accessible to eavesdroppers. Unlike previous studies focusing on encryption or access controls, we provide a theorem to ensure superior learning outcomes exclusively for the authorized learner with quantum label encoding. In this context, we use the probably-approximately-correct (PAC) learning framework and introduce the concept of learning probability to quantitatively assess learner performance. Our theorem allows the condition that, given a training dataset, an authorized learner is guaranteed to achieve a certain quality of learning outcome, while eavesdroppers are not. Notably, this condition can be constructed based only on the authorized-learning-only measurable quantities of the training data, i.e., its size and noise degree. We validate our theoretical proofs and predictions through convolutional neural networks (CNNs) image classification learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00754v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongho Bang, Wooyeong Song, Kyujin Shin, Yong-Su Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Landauer-B\"{u}ttiker Formula for Current through Open Quantum Systems with Gain or Loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Landauer-B\"{u}ttiker formula, which characterizes the current flowing through a finite region connected to leads, has significantly advanced our understanding of transport. We extend this formula to describe particle and energy currents with gain or loss in the intermediate region by using the Lindblad-Keldysh formalism. Based on the derived formula, several novel effects induced by gain or loss in the current are discussed: the breaking of inversion symmetry in the gain and loss terms or in the system can lead to current generation; the anomalous phenomenon that disorder can induce current generation; the presence of gain and loss makes the thermal and electrical conductances continuous and ensures they follow the Wiedemann-Franz law even outside the energy band; the effect of bond loss-induced skin effect on current. This work deepens and extends our understanding of transport phenomena in open systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00844v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Yang, Yucheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of quantum many-body scars in the presence of Markovian bath</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00886v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A generic closed quantum many-body system will inevitably tend to thermalization, whose local information encoded in the initial state eventually scrambles into the full space, known as quantum ergodicity. A paradigmatic exception in closed quantum systems for strong ergodicity breaking is known as many-body localization, where strong disorder-induced localization prevents the occurrence of thermalization. It is generally recognized that a localized quantum system would be delocalized under dissipation induced by the environment. However, this consequence recently has received challenges where an exotic dissipation-induced localization mechanism is proposed, and transitions between localized and extended phases are found. In this Letter, we promote this mechanism to systems for weak ergodicity breaking hosting quantum many-body scars (QMBS). We find that the system relaxes to a steady state dominated by QMBS, and the dissipative dynamics exhibit dynamic revivals by suitably preparing an initial state. We point out an experimental realization of the controlled dissipation with a cold atomic setup. This makes the signature of ergodicity breaking visible over dissipative dynamics and offers potential possibilities for experimentally preparing stable QMBS with associated coherent dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00886v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Ping Jiang, Mingdi Xu, Xuanpu Yang, Yucheng Wang, Lei Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is a phonon excitation of a superfluid Bose gas a Goldstone boson?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00893v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is generally accepted that phonons in a superfluid Bose gas are Goldstone bosons. This is justified by spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB), which is usually defined as follows: the Hamiltonian of the system is invariant under the $U(1)$ transformation $\hat{\Psi}(\mathbf{r},t)\rightarrow e^{i\alpha}% \hat{\Psi}(\mathbf{r},t)$, whereas the order parameter $\Psi(\mathbf{r},t)$ is not. However, the strict definition of SSB is different: the Hamiltonian and the boundary conditions are invariant under a symmetry transformation, while the \emph{ground state} is not. Based on the latter criterion, we study a finite system of spinless, weakly interacting bosons using three approaches: the standard Bogoliubov method, the particle-number-conserving Bogoliubov method, and the approach based on the exact ground-state wave function. Our results show that the answer to the question in the title is \textquotedblleft no\textquotedblright. Thus, phonons in a real-world (finite) superfluid Bose gas are similar to sound in a classical gas: they are not Goldstone bosons, but quantised collective vibrational modes arising from the interaction between atoms. In the case of an infinite Bose gas, however, the picture becomes paradoxical: the ground state can be regarded as either infinitely degenerate or non-degenerate, making the phonon both similar to a Goldstone boson and different from it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00893v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksim Tomchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Waterfall: a unitary phenomenological model for black hole evaporation with Page curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00948v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a unitary phenomenological model for black hole evaporation based on the analogy of the laboratory process of spontaneous parametric down conversion (SPDC) \cite{Alsing:2015,Alsing:2016} when the black hole (pump) is allowed to deplete to zero mass. The model incorporates an additional new feature that allows for the interior Hawking partner-particles (idlers) behind the horizon to further generate new Hawking particle pairs of lower energy, one of which remains behind the horizon, and the other that adds to the externally emitted Hawking radiation (signals) outside the horizon. This model produces a Page curve for the evolution of the reduced density matrices for the evaporating black hole internal degrees of freedom entangled with the generated Hawking radiation pairs entangled across the horizon. The Page curve yields an entropy that rises at early times during the evaporation process as Hawking pairs are generated, reaches a peak midway through the evolution, and then decays to zero upon complete evaporation of the black hole. The entire system remains in a pure state at all times undergoing unitary (squeezed state) evolution, with the initial state of the black hole modeled as a bosonic Fock state of large, but finite number $n_{p0}$ of particles. For the final state of the system, the black hole reaches the vacuum state of zero mass, while the external Hawking radiation carries away the total energy of the initial black hole. Inside the horizon there remains $n_{p0}$ Hawking partner-particles of vanishingly small total energy, reminiscent of the "soft-hair" (zero energy) qubit model of Hotta, Nambu and Yamaguchi \cite{Hotta_Nambu_Yamaguchi:2018}, but now from a Hamiltonian for squeezed state generation perspective. The model presented here can be readily extended to encompass arbitrary initial pure states for the black hole, and in falling matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00948v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul M. Alsing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor network method for solving the Ising model with a magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01098v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the two-dimensional square lattice Ising ferromagnet and antiferromagnet with a magnetic field by using tensor network method. Focusing on the role of guage fixing, we present the partition function in terms of a tensor network. The tensor has a different symmetry property for ferromagnets and antiferromagnets. The tensor network of the partition function is interpreted as a multiple product of the one-dimensional quantum Hamiltonian. We perform infinite density matrix renormalization group to contract the two-dimensional tensor network. We present the numerical result of magnetization and entanglement entropy for the Ising ferromagnet and antiferromagnet side by side. In order to determine the critical line in the parameter space of temperature and magnetic field, we use the half-chain entanglement entropy of the one-dimensional quantum state. The entanglement entropy precisely indicates the critical line forming the parabolic shape for the antiferromagnetic case, but shows the critical point for the ferromagnetic case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01098v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Myung-Hoon Chung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Computational Complexity of 3D Ising Spin Glass: Lessons from D-Wave Annealer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01107v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Finding an exact ground state of a 3D Ising spin glass is proven to be an NP-hard problem. There is a widespread belief that this statement implies an exponential scaling, $\sim 2^{N/\beta}$, of necessary computational efforts (classical or quantum), with the number of spins, $N$. Yet, what is a factor $\beta$ here and are there any fundamental limits on how large it can be? Here we report results of extensive experimentation with D-Wave 3D annealer with $N\leq 5627$. We found exact ground states (in a probabilistic sense) for typical realizations of 3D spin glasses with the efficiency, characterized by $\beta\approx 10^{3}$. We argue that with a further improvement of annealing protocols, post-processing algorithms and device noise reduction, $\beta$ can be increased even further. We provide a theoretical argumentation for this observation based on statistical analysis of low energy states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01107v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Alex Kamenev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing for Partition Function Estimation of a Markov Random Field in a Radar Anomaly Detection Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In probability theory, the partition function is a factor used to reduce any probability function to a density function with total probability of one. Among other statistical models used to represent joint distribution, Markov random fields (MRF) can be used to efficiently represent statistical dependencies between variables. As the number of terms in the partition function scales exponentially with the number of variables, the potential of each configuration cannot be computed exactly in a reasonable time for large instances. In this paper, we aim to take advantage of the exponential scalability of quantum computing to speed up the estimation of the partition function of a MRF representing the dependencies between operating variables of an airborne radar. For that purpose, we implement a quantum algorithm for partition function estimation in the one clean qubit model. After proposing suitable formulations, we discuss the performances and scalability of our approach in comparison to the theoretical performances of the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01154v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothe Presles, Cyrille Enderli, Gilles Burel, El Houssain Baghious</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulational Instability and Dynamical Growth Blockade in the Nonlinear Hatano-Nelson Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Hatano-Nelson model is a cornerstone of non-Hermitian physics, describing asymmetric hopping dynamics on a one-dimensional lattice, which gives rise to fascinating phenomena such as directional transport, non-Hermitian topology, and the non-Hermitian skin effect. It has been widely studied in both classical and quantum systems, with applications in condensed matter physics, photonics, and cold atomic gases. Recently, nonlinear extensions of the Hatano-Nelson model have opened a new avenue for exploring the interplay between nonlinearity and non-Hermitian effects. Particularly, in lattices with open boundary conditions, nonlinear skin modes and solitons, localized at the edge or within the bulk of the lattice, have been predicted. In this work, we examine the nonlinear extension of the Hatano-Nelson model with periodic boundary conditions and reveal a novel dynamical phenomenon arising from the modulational instability of nonlinear plane waves: growth blockade. This phenomenon is characterized by the abrupt halt of norm growth, as observed in the linear Hatano-Nelson model, and can be interpreted as a stopping of convective motion arising from self-induced disorder in the lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01226v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/apxr.202400154</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Physics Res. 2024, 2400154</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Longhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heitler effect and resonance fluorescence in quantum magnonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a coupled system of a qubit and a magnon mode in which the qubit is weakly driven. We demonstrate that the spectral steady-state responses of both the qubit and the magnon show, in addition to two sidebands split by the coupling, also a peak at the driving frequency with virtually zero linewidth. This phenomenon, which persists at both strong and weak coupling, is an analog of the Heitler effect in atomic physics, and shows the path towards building of coherent magnon sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01254v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enes Ilbu\u{g}a, V. V. Dobrovitski, Ya. M. Blanter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commutator Estimates and Quantitative Local Weyl's Law for Sch\"odinger Operators with Non-Smooth Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze semi-classical Schr\"odinger operators with potentials of class $C^{1,1/2}$ and establish commutator estimates for the associated projection operators in Schatten norms. These are then applied to prove quantitative versions of the local and phase space Weyl laws in $L^p$ spaces. We study both non-interacting, and interacting particle systems. In particular, we are able to treat the case of the minimizers of the Hartree energy in the case of repulsive singular pair interactions such as the Coulomb potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01381v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban C\'ardenas, Laurent Lafleche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional quantum anomalous Hall effect in Weyl semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01399v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum anomalous Hall effect (QAHE) is a quantum phenomenon in which a two-dimensional system exhibits a quantized Hall resistance $h/e^2$ in the absence of magnetic field, where $h$ is the Planck constant and $e$ is the electron charge. In this work, we extend this novel phase to three dimensions and thus propose a three-dimensional QAHE exhibiting richer and more versatile transport behaviors. We first confirm this three-dimensional QAHE through the quantized Chern number, then establish its bulk-boundary correspondence, and finally reaffirm it via the distinctive transport properties. Remarkably, we find that the three-dimensional QAHE hosts two chiral surface states along one spatial direction while a pair of chiral hinge states along another direction, and the location of the hinge states depends sensitively on the Fermi energy. These two types of boundary states are further connected through a perpendicular chiral surface states, whose chirality is also Fermi energy dependent. Consequently, depending on the transport direction, its Hall resistance can quantize to $0$, $h/e^2$, or $\pm h/e^2$ when the Fermi energy is tuned across the charge neutral point. This three-dimensional QAHE not only fill the gap in the Hall effect family but also holds significant potentials in device applications such as in-memory computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Qiang Zhang, Yu-Hang Li, Ming Lu, Hongfang Liu, Hailong Li, Hua Jiang, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximally Extendable Product Codes are Good Coboundary Expanders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01411v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the coboundary expansion property of product codes called product expansion, which plays an important role in the recent constructions of good quantum LDPC codes and classical locally testable codes. Prior research revealed that this property is equivalent to agreement testability and robust testability for products of two codes of linear distance. However, for products of more than two codes, product expansion is a strictly stronger property. In this paper, we prove that the collection of random codes over a sufficiently large field has good product expansion. We believe that in the case of four codes, these ideas can be used to construct good quantum locally testable codes in a way similar to the current constructions using only products of two codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01411v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gleb Kalachev, Pavel Panteleev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding maximal quantum resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.13475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.13475v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For many applications the presence of a quantum advantage crucially depends on the availability of resourceful states. Although the resource typically depends on the particular task, in the context of multipartite systems entangled quantum states are often regarded as resourceful. We propose an algorithmic method to find maximally resourceful states of several particles for various applications and quantifiers. We discuss in detail the case of the geometric measure, identifying physically interesting states and delivering insights to the problem of absolutely maximally entangled states. Moreover, we demonstrate the universality of our approach by applying it to maximally entangled subspaces, the Schmidt-rank, the stabilizer rank as well as the preparability in triangle networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.13475v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.062428</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 062428 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Steinberg, Otfried G\"uhne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Information Measures in Quartic and Symmetric Potentials using perturbative approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the Shannon and Fisher information measures for systems subjected to quartic and symmetric potential wells. The wave functions are obtained by solving the time-independent Schr\"{o}dinger equation, using aspects of perturbation theory. We examine how the information for various quantum states evolves with changes in the width of the potential well. For both potentials, the Shannon entropy decreases in position space and increases in momentum space as the width increases, maintaining a constant sum of entropies, consistent with Heisenberg's uncertainty principle. The Fisher information measure shows different behaviors for the two potentials: it remains nearly constant for the quartic potential. For the symmetric well potential, the Fisher information decreases in position space and increases in momentum space as localization in position space increases, also consistent with the analogue of Heisenberg's uncertainty principle. Additionally, the Bialynicki-Birula-Mycielski inequality is evaluated across various cases and is confirmed to hold in each instance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07353v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vikash Kumar Ojha, Ramkumar Radhakrishnan, Mariyah Ughradar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Des-q: a quantum algorithm to provably speedup retraining of decision trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09976v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Decision trees are widely adopted machine learning models due to their simplicity and explainability. However, as training data size grows, standard methods become increasingly slow, scaling polynomially with the number of training examples. In this work, we introduce Des-q, a novel quantum algorithm to construct and retrain decision trees for regression and binary classification tasks. Assuming the data stream produces small, periodic increments of new training examples, Des-q significantly reduces the tree retraining time. Des-q achieves a logarithmic complexity in the combined total number of old and new examples, even accounting for the time needed to load the new samples into quantum-accessible memory. Our approach to grow the tree from any given node involves performing piecewise linear splits to generate multiple hyperplanes, thus partitioning the input feature space into distinct regions. To determine the suitable anchor points for these splits, we develop an efficient quantum-supervised clustering method, building upon the q-means algorithm introduced by Kerenidis et al. We benchmark the simulated version of Des-q against the state-of-the-art classical methods on multiple data sets and observe that our algorithm exhibits similar performance to the state-of-the-art decision trees while significantly speeding up the periodic tree retraining.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09976v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niraj Kumar, Romina Yalovetzky, Changhao Li, Pierre Minssen, Marco Pistoia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streaming quantum state purification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16387v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum state purification is the task of recovering a nearly pure copy of an unknown pure quantum state using multiple noisy copies of the state. This basic task has applications to quantum communication over noisy channels and quantum computation with imperfect devices, but has only been studied previously for the case of qubits. We derive an efficient purification procedure based on the swap test for qudits of any dimension, starting with any initial error parameter. Treating the initial error parameter and the dimension as constants, we show that our procedure has sample complexity asymptotically optimal in the final error parameter. Our protocol has a simple recursive structure that can be applied when the states are provided one at a time in a streaming fashion, requiring only a small quantum memory to implement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16387v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew M. Childs, Honghao Fu, Debbie Leung, Zhi Li, Maris Ozols, Vedang Vyas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Quantum Reinforcement Learning using Evolutionary Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05546v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning is becoming increasingly more important in times of autonomous driving and other smart industrial applications. Simultaneously a promising new approach to Reinforcement Learning arises using the inherent properties of quantum mechanics, reducing the trainable parameters of a model significantly. However, gradient-based Multi-Agent Quantum Reinforcement Learning methods often have to struggle with barren plateaus, holding them back from matching the performance of classical approaches. While gradient free Quantum Reinforcement Learning methods may alleviate some of these challenges, they too are not immune to the difficulties posed by barren plateaus. We build upon an existing approach for gradient free Quantum Reinforcement Learning and propose three genetic variations with Variational Quantum Circuits for Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning using evolutionary optimization. We evaluate our genetic variations in the Coin Game environment and also compare them to classical approaches. We showed that our Variational Quantum Circuit approaches perform significantly better compared to a neural network with a similar amount of trainable parameters. Compared to the larger neural network, our approaches archive similar results using $97.88\%$ less parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05546v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5220/0012382800003636</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michael K\"olle, Felix Topp, Thomy Phan, Philipp Altmann, Jonas N\"u{\ss}lein, Claudia Linnhoff-Popien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling quantum neural networks for unified estimation of quantum entropies and distance measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07716v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The estimation of quantum entropies and distance measures, such as von Neumann entropy, R\'{e}nyi entropy, Tsallis entropy, trace distance, and fidelity-induced distances such as the Bures distance, has been a key area of research in quantum information science. In our study, we introduce the disentangling quantum neural network (DEQNN), designed to efficiently estimate various physical quantities in quantum information. Estimation algorithms for these quantities are generally tied to the size of the Hilbert space of the quantum state to be estimated. Our proposed DEQNN offers a unified dimensionality reduction methodology that can significantly reduce the size of the Hilbert space while preserving the values of diverse physical quantities. We provide an in-depth discussion of the physical scenarios and limitations in which our algorithm is applicable, as well as the learnability of the proposed quantum neural network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07716v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.062418</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Myeongjin Shin, Seungwoo Lee, Junseo Lee, Mingyu Lee, Donghwa Ji, Hyeonjun Yeo, Kabgyun Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Starter Problems: Solving Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization Models on Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08989v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This tutorial offers a quick hands-on introduction to solving Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problems on currently available quantum computers. We cover both IBM and D-Wave machines: IBM utilizes a gate/circuit architecture, and D-Wave is a quantum annealer. We provide examples of three canonical problems and two models from practical applications. An associated GitHub repository provides the implementations in five companion notebooks. In addition to undergraduate and graduate students in computationally intensive disciplines, this article aims to reach working industry professionals seeking to explore the potential of near-term quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08989v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arul Mazumder, Sridhar Tayur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning interacting fermionic Hamiltonians at the Heisenberg limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00069v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficiently learning an unknown Hamiltonian given access to its dynamics is a problem of interest for quantum metrology, many-body physics and machine learning. A fundamental question is whether learning can be performed at the Heisenberg limit, where the Hamiltonian evolution time scales inversely with the error, $\varepsilon$, in the reconstructed parameters. The Heisenberg limit has previously been shown to be achievable for certain classes of qubit and bosonic Hamiltonians. Most recently, a Heisenberg-limited learning algorithm was proposed for a simplified class of fermionic Hubbard Hamiltonians restricted to real hopping amplitudes and zero chemical potential at all sites, along with on-site interactions. In this work, we provide an algorithm to learn a more general class of fermionic Hubbard Hamiltonians at the Heisenberg limit, allowing complex hopping amplitudes and nonzero chemical potentials in addition to the on-site interactions, thereby including several models of physical interest. The required evolution time across all experiments in our protocol is $\mathcal{O}(1/\varepsilon)$ and the number of experiments required to learn all the Hamiltonian parameters is $\mathcal{O}(\text{polylog}(1/\varepsilon))$, independent of system size as long as each fermionic mode interacts with $\mathcal{O}(1)$ other modes. Unlike prior algorithms for bosonic and fermionic Hamiltonians, to obey fermionic parity superselection constraints in our more general setting, our protocol utilizes $\mathcal{O}(N)$ ancillary fermionic modes, where $N$ is the system size. Each experiment involves preparing fermionic Gaussian states, interleaving time evolution with fermionic linear optics unitaries, and performing local occupation number measurements on the fermionic modes. The protocol is robust to a constant amount of state preparation and measurement error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00069v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.062421</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 062421 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Mirani, Patrick Hayden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum theory of molecular orientations: topological classification, complete entanglement, and fault-tolerant encodings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04572v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate a quantum phase space for molecular rotational and nuclear-spin states. Taking in molecular geometry and nuclear-spin data, we reproduce a molecule's admissible angular momentum states known from spectroscopy, introduce its angular position states using quantization theory, and develop a generalized Fourier transform converting between the two. We classify molecules into three types -- asymmetric, rotationally symmetric, and perrotationally symmetric -- with the last type having no macroscopic analogue due to nuclear-spin statistics constraints. We discuss two general features in perrotationally symmetric state spaces that are Hamiltonian-independent and induced solely by symmetry and spin statistics. First, we quantify when and how the state space of a molecular species is completely rotation-spin entangled, meaning that it does not admit any separable states. Second, we identify molecular species whose position states house an internal pseudo-spin or "fiber" degree of freedom, and the fiber's Berry phase or matrix after adiabatic changes in position yields naturally robust operations, akin to braiding anyonic quasiparticles or realizing fault-tolerant quantum gates. We outline how the fiber can be used as a quantum error-correcting code and discuss scenarios where these features can be experimentally probed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04572v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor V. Albert, Eric Kubischta, Mikhail Lemeshko, Lee R. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum speed limit and nonclassicality in open quantum system models using the Wigner function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01741v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quantum speed limit and the Wigner function of open system models are studied. To this end, we use the phase covariant and a two-qubit model interacting with a squeezed thermal bath via position-dependent coupling. The dependence of the coupling on the position of the qubits allows for the study of the dynamics in the collective regime, which is conducive to speeding up the evolution. An interesting interplay is observed between non-Markovian behavior, quantumness, and the quantum speed limit. The presence of quantum correlations is seen to speed up the evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01741v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/andp.202400194</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ANNALEN DER PHYSIK 2024, 2400194</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arti Gaharwar, Devvrat Tiwari, Subhashish Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement engineering of optomechanical systems by reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04550v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Entanglement is fundamental to quantum information science and technology, yet controlling and manipulating entanglement -- so-called entanglement engineering -- for arbitrary quantum systems remains a formidable challenge. There are two difficulties: the fragility of quantum entanglement and its experimental characterization. We develop a model-free deep reinforcement-learning (RL) approach to entanglement engineering, in which feedback control together with weak continuous measurement and partial state observation is exploited to generate and maintain desired entanglement. We employ quantum optomechanical systems with linear or nonlinear photon-phonon interactions to demonstrate the workings of our machine-learning-based entanglement engineering protocol. In particular, the RL agent sequentially interacts with one or multiple parallel quantum optomechanical environments, collects trajectories, and updates the policy to maximize the accumulated reward to create and stabilize quantum entanglement over an arbitrary amount of time. The machine-learning-based model-free control principle is applicable to the entanglement engineering of experimental quantum systems in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04550v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Li Ye, Christian Arenz, Joseph M. Lukens, Ying-Cheng Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Upper Bound on Ergotropy and No-Go Theorem by the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11112v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the maximum extractable work (ergotropy) from a quantum many-body system is constrained by local athermality of an initial state and local entropy decrease brought about by quantum operations. The obtained universal upper bound on ergotropy implies that the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis prohibits work extraction from energy eigenstates by means of finite-time unitary operations. This no-go property implies that Planck's principle, a form of the second law of thermodynamics, holds even for pure quantum states. Our result bridges two independently studied concepts of quantum thermodynamics, the second law and thermalization, via intrasystem correlations in many-body systems as a resource for work extraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11112v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Hokkyo, Masahito Ueda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Belief Propagation Decoding Algorithms for Surface Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11523v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum error correction is crucial for universal fault-tolerant quantum computing. Highly accurate and low-time-complexity decoding algorithms play an indispensable role in ensuring quantum error correction works effectively. Among existing decoding algorithms, belief propagation (BP) is notable for its nearly linear time complexity and general applicability to stabilizer codes. However, BP's decoding accuracy without post-processing is unsatisfactory in most situations. This article focuses on improving the decoding accuracy of BP over GF(4) for surface codes. Inspired by machine learning optimization techniques, we first propose Momentum-BP and AdaGrad-BP to reduce oscillations in message updating, breaking the trapping sets of surface codes. We further propose EWAInit-BP, which adaptively updates initial probabilities and provides a 1 to 3 orders of magnitude improvement over traditional BP for planar surface code, toric code, and XZZX surface code without any post-processing method, showing high decoding accuracy even under parallel scheduling. The theoretical $O(1)$ time complexity under parallel implementation and high accuracy of EWAInit-BP make it a promising candidate for high-precision real-time decoders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11523v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahan Chen, Zhengzhong Yi, Zhipeng Liang, Xuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically pumped h-BN single-photon emission in van der Waals heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Atomic defects in solids offer a versatile basis to study and realize quantum phenomena and information science in various integrated systems. All-electrical pumping of single defects to create quantum light emission has been realized in several platforms including color centers in diamond and silicon carbide, which could lead to the circuit network of electrically triggered single-photon sources. However, a wide conduction channel which reduces the carrier injection per defect site has been a major obstacle. Here, we realize a device concept to construct electrically pumped single-photon emission using a van der Waals stacked structure with atomic plane precision. Defect-induced tunneling currents across graphene and NbSe2 electrodes sandwiching an atomically thin h-BN layer allow robust and persistent generation of non-classical light from h-BN. The collected emission photon energies range between 1.4 and 2.9 eV, revealing the electrical excitation of a variety of atomic defects. By analyzing the dipole axis of observed emitters, we further confirm that emitters are crystallographic defect structures of h-BN crystal. Our work facilitates implementing efficient and miniaturized single-photon devices in van der Waals platforms toward applications in quantum optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14070v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.4c10276</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mihyang Yu, Jeonghan Lee, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Jieun Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal quantum mechanics of causal diamonds: Time evolution, thermality, and instability via path integral functionals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18177v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An observer with a finite lifetime $\mathcal{T}$ perceives the Minkowski vacuum as a thermal state at temperature $T_D = 2 \hbar/(\pi \mathcal{T})$, as a result of being constrained to a double-coned-shaped region known as a causal diamond. In this paper, we explore the emergence of thermality in causal diamonds due to the role played by the symmetries of conformal quantum mechanics (CQM) as a (0+1)-dimensional conformal field theory, within the de Alfaro-Fubini-Furlan model and generalizations. In this context, the hyperbolic operator $S$ of the SO(2,1) symmetry of CQM: (i) is the generator of the time evolution of a diamond observer; (ii) its dynamical behavior leads to the predicted thermal nature; and (iii) its associated quantum instability has a Lyapunov exponent $\lambda_L = \pi T_D/\hbar$, which is half the upper saturation bound of the information scrambling rate. Our approach is based on a comprehensive framework of path-integral representations of the CQM generators in canonical and microcanonical forms, supplemented by semiclassical arguments. The properties of the operator $S$ are studied with emphasis on an operator duality with the corresponding elliptic operator $R$, using a representation in terms of an effective scale-invariant inverse square potential combined with inverted and ordinary harmonic oscillator potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18177v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.124043</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 124043 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H. E. Camblong, A. Chakraborty, P. Lopez-Duque, C. R. Ord\'o\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal quantum mechanics of causal diamonds: Quantum instability and semiclassical approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18191v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Causal diamonds are known to have thermal behavior that can be probed by finite-lifetime observers equipped with energy-scaled detectors. This thermality can be attributed to the time evolution of observers within the causal diamond, governed by one of the conformal quantum mechanics (CQM) symmetry generators: the noncompact hyperbolic operator $S$. In this paper, we show that the unbounded nature of $S$ endows it with a quantum instability, which is a generalization of a similar property exhibited by the inverted harmonic oscillator potential. Our analysis is semiclassical, including a detailed phase-space study of the classical dynamics of $S$ and its dual operator $R$, and a general semiclassical framework yielding basic instability and thermality properties that play a crucial role in the quantum behavior of the theory. For an observer with a finite lifetime $\mathcal{T}$, the detected temperature
  $T_D = 2 \hbar/(\pi \mathcal{T})$ is associated with a Lyapunov exponent $\lambda_L = \pi T_D/\hbar$, which is half the upper saturation bound of the information scrambling rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18191v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. E. Camblong, A. Chakraborty, P. Lopez-Duque, C. Ord\'o\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Review of Quantum Circuit Optimization: Current Trends and Future Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08941v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optimizing quantum circuits is critical for enhancing computational speed and mitigating errors caused by quantum noise. Effective optimization must be achieved without compromising the correctness of the computations. This survey explores re-cent advancements in quantum circuit optimization, encompassing both hardware-independent and hardware-dependent techniques. It reviews state-of-the-art approaches, including analytical algorithms, heuristic strategies, machine learning based methods, and hybrid quantum-classical frameworks. The paper highlights the strengths and limitations of each method, along with the challenges they pose. Furthermore, it identifies potential research opportunities in this evolving field, offering insights into the future directions of quantum circuit optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08941v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/quantum7010002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum Rep. 2025, 7, 2</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Krishnageetha Karuppasamy, Varun Puram, Stevens Johnson, Johnson P Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmon qubit modeling and characterization for Dark Matter search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05988v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents the design, simulation, and experimental characterization of a superconducting transmon qubit circuit prototype for potential applications in dark matter detection experiments. We describe a planar circuit design featuring two non-interacting transmon qubits, one with fixed frequency and the other flux tunable. Finite-element simulations were employed to extract key Hamiltonian parameters and optimize component geometries. The qubit was fabricated and then characterized at $20$ mK, allowing for a comparison between simulated and measured qubit parameters. Good agreement was found for transition frequencies and anharmonicities (within 1\% and 10\% respectively) while coupling strengths exhibited larger discrepancies (30\%). We discuss potential causes for measured coherence times falling below expectations ($T_1\sim\,$1-2 \textmu s) and propose strategies for future design improvements. Notably, we demonstrate the application of a hybrid 3D-2D simulation approach for energy participation ratio evaluation, yielding a more accurate estimation of dielectric losses. This work represents an important first step in developing planar Quantum Non-Demolition (QND) single-photon counters for dark matter searches, particularly for axion and dark photon detection schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05988v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Moretti, D. Labranca, P. Campana, R. Carobene, M. Gobbo, M. A. Castellanos-Beltran, D. Olaya, P. F. Hopkins, L. Banchi, M. Borghesi, A. Candido, S. Carrazza, H. A. Corti, A. D'Elia, M. Faverzani, E. Ferri, A. Nucciotti, L. Origo, A. Pasquale, A. S. Piedjou Komnang, A. Rettaroli, S. Tocci, C. Gatti, A. Giachero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Constant-Time Logical Gates for Large-Scale Quantum Computation Using Window-Based Correlated Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large-scale quantum computation requires to be performed in the fault-tolerant manner. One crucial challenge of fault-tolerant quantum computing (FTQC) is reducing the overhead of implementing logical gates. Recently work proposed correlated decoding and ``algorithmic fault tolerance" to achieve constant-time logical gates that enables universal quantum computation. However, for circuits involving mid-circuit measurements and feedback, the previous scheme for constant-time logical gates is incompatible with window-based decoding, which is a scalable approach for handling large-scale circuits. In this work, we propose an architecture that employs delayed fixup circuits and window-based correlated decoding, realizing scalable constant-time logical gates. This design significantly reduces both the frequency and duration of decoding, while maintaining support for constant-time and universal logical gates across a broad class of quantum codes. More importantly, by spatial parallelism of windows, this architecture well adapts to time-optimal FTQC, making it particularly useful for large-scale quantum computation. Using Shor's algorithm as an example, we explore the application of our architecture and reveals the promising potential of using constant-time logical gates to perform large-scale quantum computation with acceptable overhead on physical systems like ion traps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16963v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxuan Zhang, Zhao-Yun Chen, Jia-Ning Li, Tian-Hao Wei, Huan-Yu Liu, Xi-Ning Zhuang, Qing-Song Li, Yu-Chun Wu, Guo-Ping Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum One-Time Protection of any Randomized Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03305v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The meteoric rise in power and popularity of machine learning models dependent on valuable training data has reignited a basic tension between the power of running a program locally and the risk of exposing details of that program to the user. At the same time, fundamental properties of quantum states offer new solutions to data and program security that can require strikingly few quantum resources to exploit, and offer advantages outside of mere computational run time. In this work, we demonstrate such a solution with quantum one-time tokens.
  A quantum one-time token is a quantum state that permits a certain program to be evaluated exactly once. One-time security guarantees, roughly, that the token cannot be used to evaluate the program more than once. We propose a scheme for building quantum one-time tokens for any randomized classical program, which include generative AI models. We prove that the scheme satisfies an interesting definition of one-time security as long as outputs of the classical algorithm have high enough min-entropy, in a black box model.
  Importantly, the classical program being protected does not need to be implemented coherently on a quantum computer. In fact, the size and complexity of the quantum one-time token is independent of the program being protected, and additional quantum resources serve only to increase the security of the protocol. Due to this flexibility in adjusting the security, we believe that our proposal is parsimonious enough to serve as a promising candidate for a near-term useful demonstration of quantum computing in either the NISQ or early fault tolerant regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03305v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Gunn, Ramis Movassagh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of Qubit Readout Circuit for Purcell Rate Suppressing and Nonclassicality Enhancing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07153v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Purcell effect, a common issue in qubit-resonator systems leading to both fidelity and nonclassicality losses is studied while its suppression is achieved using a novel qubit readout circuit design. Our approach utilizes a unique coupling architecture in which, the qubit first interacts with a filter resonator before coupling to the readout resonator. This configuration enables precise control over the Purcell decay rate and ac Stark factor without impacting on measuring time. The mentioned factor is highly sensitive to the coupling strength between the readout resonator and the filter, meaning that the factor adjustment directly impacts the qubit state detection. A major advantage of this design is that tuning the resonator-filter coupling strength is relatively straightforward, offering flexibility in fine-tuning ac Stark factor. This work extensively analyzes the system using full quantum mechanical theory, deriving the total Hamiltonian and investigates mode dynamics via quantum Langevin equations. Key parameters influencing the nonclassicality of output signals are also explored through quantum correlation metrics, including symplectic eigenvalues, quantum discord, and classical discord. The main goal is to find any compromises exsting between the ac Stark factor increasing and the quantum correlation created in the readout circuit. By optimizing the critical factors, by which the ac Stark factor mainly affected, the proposed design not only improves the distinguishability of the qubit states but also ensures robust nonclassicality in the output signals. Results demonstrate the potential of the proposed system to bridge the gap between a high fidelity readout and quantum correlation preservation in scalable quantum architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07153v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Salmanogli, Hesam Zandi, Saeed Hajihosseini, Mahdi Esmaeili, M. Hossein Eskandari, Mohsen Akbari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal coarse geometry of spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07912v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The prospect of realizing highly entangled states on quantum processors with fundamentally different hardware geometries raises the question: to what extent does a state of a quantum spin system have an intrinsic geometry? In this paper, we propose that both states and dynamics of a spin system have a canonically associated coarse geometry, in the sense of Roe, on the set of sites in the thermodynamic limit. For a state $\phi$ on an (abstract) spin system with an infinite collection of sites $X$, we define a universal coarse structure $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}$ on the set $X$ with the property that a state has decay of correlations with respect to a coarse structure $\mathcal{E}$ on $X$ if and only if $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}\subseteq \mathcal{E}$. We show that under mild assumptions, the coarsely connected completion $(\mathcal{E}_{\phi})_{con}$ is stable under quasi-local perturbations of the state $\phi$. We also develop in parallel a dynamical coarse structure for arbitrary quantum channels, and prove a similar stability result. We show that several order parameters of a state only depend on the coarse structure of an underlying spatial metric, and we establish a basic compatibility between the dynamical coarse structure associated to a quantum circuit $\alpha$ and the coarse structure of the state $\psi\circ \alpha$ where $\psi$ is any product state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07912v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Elokl, Corey Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Geometric Substructure for Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08230v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The description of a closed quantum system is extended with the identification of an underlying substructure in which an expanded formulation of dynamics in the Heisenberg picture is given. Between measurements a ``state point" moves in an underlying multi-dimensional complex, projective space with constant velocity determined by the quantum state vector. Following a measurement, the point changes direction and moves with new constant velocity along one of several possible new orthogonal paths, with probabilities determined by Born's Rule. A possible generalization to a Riemannian substructure is speculated upon, suggesting an unexpected interaction with the background gravitational field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08230v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony John Bracken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic limitations on fault-tolerant quantum computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12805v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the thermodynamic limits on scaling fault-tolerant quantum computers due to heating from quantum error correction (QEC). Quantum computers require error correction, which accounts for 99.9% of the qubit demand and generates heat through information-erasing processes. This heating increases the error rate, necessitating more rounds of error correction. We introduce a dynamical model that characterizes heat generation and dissipation for arrays of qubits weakly coupled to a refrigerator and identify a dynamical phase transition between two operational regimes: a bounded-error phase, where temperature stabilizes and error rates remain below fault-tolerance thresholds, and an unbounded-error phase, where rising temperatures drive error rates beyond sustainable levels, making fault tolerance infeasible. Applying our model to a superconducting qubit system performing Shor's algorithm to factor 2048-bit RSA integers, we find that current experimental parameters place the system in the bounded-error phase. Our results indicate that, while inherent heating can become significant, this thermodynamic constraint should not limit scalable fault tolerance if current hardware capabilities are maintained as systems scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12805v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mykhailo Bilokur, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Shayan Majidy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the application of the Rayleigh-Ritz method to a projected Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14490v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply the well known Rayleigh-Ritz method (RRM) to the projection of a Hamiltonian operator chosen recently for the extension of the Rayleigh-Ritz variational principle to ensemble states. By means of a toy model we show that the RRM eigenvalues approach to those of the projected Hamiltonian from below in most cases but a few ones. We also discuss the effect of an energy shift and the projection of the identity operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14490v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco M. Fern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical and Quantum Algorithms for the Deterministic L-system Inductive Inference Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: L-systems can be made to model and create simulations of many biological processes, such as plant development. Finding an L-system for a given process is typically solved by hand, by experts, in a massively time-consuming process. It would be significant if this could be done automatically from data, such as from sequences of images. In this paper, we are interested in inferring a particular type of L-system, deterministic context-free L-system (D0L-system) from a sequence of strings. We introduce the characteristic graph of a sequence of strings, which we then utilize to translate our problem (inferring D0L-system) in polynomial time into the maximum independent set problem (MIS) and the SAT problem. After that, we offer a classical exact algorithm and an approximate quantum algorithm for the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19906v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Lotfi, Ian McQuillan, Steven Rayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Dynamic Range of Sub-Quantum-Limit Measurements via Quantum Deamplification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15061v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Balancing high sensitivity with a broad dynamic range is a fundamental challenge in measurement science, as improving one often compromises the other. While traditional quantum metrology has prioritized enhancing local sensitivity, a large dynamic range is crucial for applications such as atomic clocks, where extended phase interrogation times contribute to wider phase range. In this Letter, we introduce a novel quantum deamplification mechanism that extends dynamic range at a minimal cost of sensitivity. Our approach uses two sequential spin-squeezing operations to generate and detect an entangled probe state, respectively. We demonstrate that the optimal quantum interferometer limit can be approached through two-axis counter-twisting dynamics. Further expansion of dynamic range is possible by using sequential quantum deamplification interspersed with phase encoding processes. Additionally, we show that robustness against detection noise can be enhanced by a hybrid sensing scheme that combines quantum deamplification with quantum amplification. Our protocol is within the reach of state-of-the-art atomic-molecular-optical platforms, offering a scalable, noise-resilient pathway for entanglement-enhanced metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15061v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Liu, Ming Xue, Xinwei Li, Denis V. Vasilyev, Ling-Na Wu, Vladan Vuleti\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wave function evolution from source to detection and the measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15409v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the evolution of a particle wave function when it propagates through free space in the longitudinal z-direction from a thin entrance slit to a detector behind a thin exit slit parallel to the horizontal y-axis. We consider an extra aperture slit between the two slits to probe the evolution of the wave function and close the aperture slit starting from wide open until the detection counting rate in a repeated experiment drops to half. When all the slits are long and thin, the 1D Schroedinger equation gives the wave function evolution until the final detection. The width of the aperture slit in the vertical x-direction depends on the z-position of the slit providing an approximate description of the wave function evolution. The width of the function characterizing this dependence starts from the entrance slit. It grows wider until it reaches a maximum and then shrinks narrower and finally collapses into the exit slit where the particle is detected. Thus the envelope of this function has a spindle shape with its pointed ends at the two slits. Hence it is very different from the well-known wave function of the Schroedinger equation with the initial condition at the entrance slit, which is narrow only at the beginning, then grows wider until it reaches the exit slit, where it is much larger than the slit width. However, the phase information is lost because the aperture slit distorts the wave function. To keep the phase information, we replace the aperture slit with a thin pin (parallel to the y-axis) that blocks the wave function. We then study its perturbative effect on the counting rate of the detector. This analysis provides a function to probe the process of the wave function collapse right before the detection. We show this function is real-valued, with amplitude and phase information, and is closely related to the wave function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15409v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>LiHua Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Algorithm for Vector Set Orthogonal Normalization and Matrix QR Decomposition with Polynomial Speedup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19090v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vector set orthogonal normalization and matrix QR decomposition are fundamental problems in matrix analysis with important applications in many fields. We know that Gram-Schmidt process is a widely used method to solve these two problems. However, the existing methods, including Gram-Schmidt process have problems of high complexity, scaling $O(N^3)$ in the system dimension $N$, which leads to difficulties when calculating large-scale or ill-conditioned problems. With the development of quantum information processing, a series of quantum algorithms have been proposed, providing advantages and speedups over classical algorithms in many fields. In this paper, we propose quantum algorithms to solve these two problems based on the idea of Gram-Schmidt process and quantum phase estimation. The complexity of proposed quantum algorithms is also theoretically and numerically analyzed. We find that our algorithms provide polynomial acceleration over the best-known classical and quantum algorithms on these two problems, scaling $O(N^2\mathrm{poly}(\log N))$ in the dimension $N$ of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19090v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Ming Li, Yu-xi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Bohr Model of the Atom through Brownian Motion of the Electron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19918v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we enhance the Bohr model of the hydrogen atom by incorporating Stochastic Mechanics to describe the electron's behavior through Brownian motion. In contrast to traditional quantum mechanics, where the Born rule postulates the physical interpretation of the wave function, our model derives the Born rule by performing statistical averaging of single-particle positions. Because the particle always has a definite, though random, position, there is no need for wave function collapse, as required by the Copenhagen interpretation. In this approach, we use the wave function to compute the electron's optimal drift velocity within its stochastic equation of motion. We develop modified stochastic equations in curvilinear spherical coordinates and demonstrate that the resulting radial and angular kinetic energies align with those from the operator approach. Numerical simulations validate our theoretical framework by showing stable electron orbits and accurately reproducing the probability distribution of finding the electron around the hydrogen nucleus as defined by the Born rule. We show that at very short timescales, wave function-based single electron probability distributions can be inadequate due to insufficient statistical averaging of single-particle trajectories. This model thus offers enhanced insights into the quantum world beyond conventional interpretations. Our findings underscore the potential of applying wave function-derived drift velocities within Stochastic Mechanics to the hydrogen atom, providing new perspectives on atomic dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19918v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasil Yordanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Intensity Limits for Long-Distance Quantum Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20265v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum Key Distribution (QKD) enables the sharing of cryptographic keys secured by quantum mechanics. The BB84 protocol assumed single-photon sources, but practical systems rely on weak coherent pulses vulnerable to photon-number-splitting (PNS) attacks. The Gottesman-Lo-L\"utkenhaus-Preskill (GLLP) framework addressed these imperfections, deriving secure key rate bounds under limited PNS. The Decoy-state protocol further improved performance by refining single-photon yield estimates, but still considered multi-photon states as insecure, limiting intensities and thereby constraining key rate and distance. Here, we show that higher intensities can be securely permitted by applying Bayesian inference to estimate key parameters directly from observed data rather than relying on worst-case assumptions. By raising the pulse intensity to 10 photons, we achieve 50 times the key rate and a 62.2% increase in operational range (about 200 km) compared to the decoy-state protocol. Furthermore, we accurately model after-pulsing using a Hidden Markov Model and reveal inaccuracies in decoy-state calculations that may produce erroneous key-rate estimates. By bridging theoretical security and real-world conditions, this Bayesian methodology provides a versatile post-processing step for many discrete-variable QKD protocols, advancing their reach, efficiency, and facilitating broader adoption of quantum-secured communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20265v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahim Almosallam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence revival under the Unruh effect and its metrological advantage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.01358v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the quantum coherence extraction {between} two accelerating Unruh-DeWitt detectors, coupling to a scalar field in $(3+1)$-dimensional Minkowski spacetime. We find that quantum coherence as a nonclassical correlation can be generated through the Markovian evolution of the {detector} system, just like quantum entanglement. However, with growing Unruh temperature, in contrast to monotonously degrading entanglement, we find that quantum coherence exhibits a striking revival phenomenon. For certain detectors' initial state choices, {the} coherence measure will reduce to zero at first {and} then grow to an asymptotic value. We verify such coherence revival by inspecting its metrological advantage on the quantum Fisher information (QFI) enhancement. Since the maximal QFI {bounds} the accuracy of quantum parameter estimation, we conclude that the extracted coherence can be utilized as a physical resource in quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.01358v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1572-9494/ad9f4b</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jiafan Wang, Jingjun Zhang, Jun Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bichromatic Rabi Control of Semiconductor Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01720v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Electrically driven spin resonance is a powerful technique for controlling semiconductor spin qubits. However, it faces challenges in qubit addressability and off-resonance driving in larger systems. We demonstrate coherent bichromatic Rabi control of quantum dot hole spin qubits, offering a spatially selective approach for large qubit arrays. By applying simultaneous microwave bursts to different gate electrodes, we observe multichromatic resonance lines and resonance anticrossings that are caused by the ac Stark shift. Our theoretical framework aligns with experimental data, highlighting interdot motion as the dominant mechanism for bichromatic driving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01720v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.067001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 067001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Valentin John, Francesco Borsoi, Zolt\'an Gy\"orgy, Chien-An Wang, G\'abor Sz\'echenyi, Floor van Riggelen, William I. L. Lawrie, Nico W. Hendrickx, Amir Sammak, Giordano Scappucci, Andr\'as P\'alyi, Menno Veldhorst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental emulator of pulse dynamics in fractional nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a nonlinear optical platform to emulate a nonlinear \textit{L\'{e}vy waveguide} that supports the pulse propagation governed by a generalized fractional nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation (FNLSE). Our approach distinguishes between intra-cavity and extra-cavity regimes, exploring the interplay between the effective fractional group-velocity dispersion (FGVD) and Kerr nonlinearity. In the intra-cavity configuration, we observe stable \textit{fractional solitons} enabled by an engineered combination of the fractional and regular dispersions in the fiber cavity. The soliton pulses exhibit their specific characteristics, \textit{viz.}, "heavy tails" and a "spectral valley" in the temporal and frequency domain, respectively, highlighting the effective nonlocality introduced by FGVD. Further investigation in the extra-cavity regime reveals the generation of spectral valleys with multiple lobes, offering potential applications to the design of high-dimensional data encoding. To elucidate the spectral valleys arising from the interplay of FGVD and nonlinearity, we have developed an innovative "force" model supported by comprehensive numerical analysis. These findings open new avenues for experimental studies of spectral-temporal dynamics in fractional nonlinear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15150v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilong Liu, Yingwen Zhang, St\'ephane Virally, Ebrahim Karimi, Boris A. Malomed, Denis V. Seletskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analogue of collectively induced transparency in metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15534v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Most recently, a brand new optical phenomenon, collectively induced transparency (CIT) has already been proposed in the cavity quantum electrodynamics system, which comes from the coupling between the cavity and ions and the quantum interference of collective ions. In this paper, we propose the CIT in terahertz (THz) metamaterial device by employing the coupling between bright mode and interference of dark modes for the first time. We give the theoretical analysis, analytical calculations and simulations to present the transmission spectrum of CIT metamaterials. Furthermore, we can observe the tendency of CIT's transmission spectrum by experiments which well verify our idea. Ideal CIT metamaterial device can produce a very high Q peak in the middle of transmission spectrum of Electromagnetically induced transparency (EIT), which can be useful for highly sensitive metamaterial sensors, optical switches and photo-memory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15534v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Huang, Shi-Ting Cao, Shi-Jun Liang, Shan Yin, Wentao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-time-ordered correlators of mean-field bosons via Bogoliubov theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01736v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum many-body chaos concerns the scrambling of quantum information among large numbers of degrees of freedom. It rests on the prediction that out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs) of the form $\langle [A(t),B]^2\rangle$ can be connected to classical symplectic dynamics. We rigorously prove a variant of this correspondence principle for mean-field bosons. We show that the $N\to\infty$ limit of the OTOC $\langle [A(t),B]^2\rangle$ is explicitly given by a suitable symplectic Bogoliubov dynamics. In practical terms, we describe the dynamical build-up of many-body entanglement between a particle and the whole system by an explicit nonlinear PDE on $L^2(\mathbb{R}^3) \oplus L^2(\mathbb{R}^3)$. For higher-order correlators, we obtain an out-of-time-ordered analog of the Wick rule. The proof uses Bogoliubov theory. Our finding spotlights a new problem in nonlinear dispersive PDE with implications for quantum many-body chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01736v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Lemm, Simone Rademacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling the Impact of Quantum Circuit Imperfections on Networks and Computer Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00062v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Post Quantum and Quantum Cryptography schemes are feasible quantum computer applications for 7G networks. These schemes could possibly replace existing schemes. These algorithms have been compromised by advances in quantum search algorithms run on quantum computers like Shor algorithm. Shor algorithm is a quantum algorithm for finding the prime factors of an integer which is the basis of existing algorithm. This has become an available quantum computer application putting the use of ESA algorithm at risk. Our recent paper provides a detailed survey of the work on post quantum and quantum cryptography algorithms with focus on their applicability in 7G networks.
  Since the paper focuses on the cryptography algorithms as a follow up, in this paper, we provide a new framework for quantum network optimization and survey in detail the work on enabling technologies (quantum hardware) for the practical implementation of these algorithms including the most important segments of quantum hardware in 7G. As always in engineering practice practical solutions are a compromise between the performance and complexity of the implementation. For this reason, as the main contribution, the paper presents a network and computer applications optimization framework that includes implementation imperfections. The tools should be useful in optimizing future generation practical computer system design. After that a comprehensive survey of the existing work on quantum hardware is presented pointing out the sources of these imperfections. This enables us to make a fair assessment of how much investment into quantum hardware improvements contributes to the performance enhancement of the overall system. In this way a decision can be made on proper partitioning between the investment in hardware and system level complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00062v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Savo Glisic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic VQE calculations of molecular electric dipole moments on trapped ion quantum hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04992v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quantum-classical hybrid variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) algorithm is among the most actively studied topics in atomic and molecular calculations on quantum computers, yet few studies address properties other than energies or account for relativistic effects. This work presents high-precision 18-qubit relativistic VQE simulations for calculating the permanent electric dipole moments (PDMs) of BeH to RaH molecules on traditional computers, and 6- and 12-qubit PDM computations for SrH on IonQ quantum devices. To achieve high precision on current noisy intermediate scale era quantum hardware, we apply various resource reduction methods, including Reinforcement Learning and causal flow preserving ZX-Calculus routines, along with error mitigation and post-selection techniques. Our approach reduces the two-qubit gate count in our 12-qubit circuit by 99.71%, with only a 2.35% trade-off in precision for PDM when evaluated classically within a suitably chosen active space. On the current generation IonQ Forte-I hardware, the error in PDM is -1.17% relative to classical calculations and only 1.21% compared to the unoptimized circuit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04992v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Palak Chawla,  Shweta, K. R. Swain, Tushti Patel, Renu Bala, Disha Shetty, Kenji Sugisaki, Sudhindu Bikash Mandal, Jordi Riu, Jan Nogue, V. S. Prasannaa, B. P. Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Evolution of Relativistic Quantum Fields in Spatial Subregions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the time evolution of a state of a relativistic quantum field theory restricted to a spatial subregion $\Omega$. More precisely, we use the Feynman-Vernon influence functional formalism to describe the dynamics of the field theory in the interior of $\Omega$ arising after integrating out the degrees of freedom in the exterior. We show how the influence of the environment gets encoded in a boundary term. Furthermore, we derive a stochastic equation of motion for the field expectation value in the interior. We find that the boundary conditions obtained in this way are energy non-conserving and non-local in space and time. Our results find applications in understanding the emergence of local thermalization in relativistic quantum field theories and the relationship between quantum field theory and relativistic fluid dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05795v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Schr\"ofl, Stefan Floerchinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representing arbitrary ground states of toric code by a restricted Boltzmann machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01451v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically analyze the representability of toric code ground states by Restricted Boltzmann Machine with only local connections between hidden and visible neurons. This analysis is pivotal for evaluating the model's capability to represent diverse ground states, thus enhancing our understanding of its strengths and weaknesses. Subsequently, we modify the Restricted Boltzmann Machine to accommodate arbitrary ground states by introducing essential non-local connections efficiently. The new model is not only analytically solvable but also demonstrates efficient and accurate performance when solved using machine learning techniques. Then we generalize our the model from $Z_2$ to $Z_n$ toric code and discuss future directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01451v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045101</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 045101 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Penghua Chen, Bowen Yan, Shawn X. Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-dispersive resonator readout of a quantum-dot qubit using longitudinal coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08869v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform readout of a quantum-dot hybrid qubit coupled to a superconducting resonator through a parametric, longitudinal interaction mechanism. Our experiments are performed with the qubit and resonator frequencies detuned by $\sim$10 GHz, demonstrating that longitudinal coupling can facilitate semiconductor qubit operation in the 'ultra-dispersive' regime of circuit quantum electrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08869v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Harpt, J. Corrigan, Nathan Holman, Piotr Marciniec, D. Rosenberg, D. Yost, R. Das, Rusko Ruskov, Charles Tahan, William D. Oliver, R. McDermott, Mark Friesen, M. A. Eriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic classification of Hietarinta's solutions of Yang-Baxter equations~:~invertible $4\times 4$ operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05375v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In order to examine the simulation of integrable quantum systems using quantum computers, it is crucial to first classify Yang-Baxter operators. Hietarinta was among the first to classify constant Yang-Baxter solutions for a two-dimensional local Hilbert space (qubit representation). Including the one produced by the permutation operator, he was able to construct eleven families of invertible solutions. These techniques are effective for 4 by 4 solutions, but they become difficult to use for representations with more dimensions. To get over this limitation, we use algebraic ans\"{a}tze to generate the constant Yang-Baxter solutions in a representation independent way. We employ four distinct algebraic structures that, depending on the qubit representation, replicate 10 of the 11 Hietarinta families. Among the techniques are partition algebras, Clifford algebras, Temperley-Lieb algebras, and a collection of commuting operators. Using these techniques, we do not obtain the $(2,2)$ Hietarinta class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05375v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)067</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 67 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Somnath Maity, Vivek Kumar Singh, Pramod Padmanabhan, Vladimir Korepin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Particle Universality of the Many-Body Spectral Form Factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07306v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider systems of fermions evolved by non-interacting unitary circuits with correlated on-site potentials. When these potentials are drawn from the eigenvalue distribution of a circular random matrix ensemble, the single-particle sector exhibits chaotic dynamics. We study the corresponding many-body spectral statistics and show that the spectral form factor (SFF) can be computed \textit{exactly}. Due to the absence of interactions the SFF grows exponentially in time, a result which we demonstrate through simple arguments, scaling collapses, and closed-form evaluation of the SFF. We study the role of interactions by numerically analyzing a kicked Ising model and find that the SFF crosses over to a linear growth regime consistent with many-body random matrix universality. Our exact results for the SFF provide a baseline for future studies of the crossover between single-particle and many-body random matrix behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07306v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael O. Flynn, Lev Vidmar, Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact spectral form factors of non-interacting fermions with Dyson statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08269v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The spectral form factor (SFF) is a powerful diagnostic of random matrix behavior in quantum many-body systems. We introduce a family of random circuit ensembles whose SFFs can be computed \textit{exactly}. These ensembles describe the evolution of non-interacting fermions in the presence of correlated on-site potentials drawn from the eigenvalue distribution of a circular ensemble. For disorder parameters drawn from the circular unitary ensemble (CUE), we derive an exact closed form for the SFF, valid for any choice of system size $L$ and integer time $t$. When the disorder is drawn from the circular orthogonal or symplectic ensembles (COE and CSE, respectively), we carry out the disorder averages analytically and reduce the computation of the SFF at integer times to a combinatorial problem amenable to transfer matrix methods. In each of these cases the SFF grows exponentially in time, which we argue is a signature of random matrix universality at the single-particle level. Finally, we develop matchgate circuit representations of our circuit ensembles, enabling their experimental realization in quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08269v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda, Lev Vidmar, Michael O. Flynn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hybrid Quantum-Classical Autoencoder Framework for End-to-End Communication Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20241v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the application of quantum machine learning to End-to-End (E2E) communication systems in wireless fading scenarios. We introduce a novel hybrid quantum-classical autoencoder architecture that combines parameterized quantum circuits with classical deep neural networks (DNNs). Specifically, we propose a hybrid quantum-classical autoencoder (QAE) framework to optimize the E2E communication system. Our results demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed hybrid system, and reveal that it is the first work that can achieve comparable block error rate (BLER) performance to classical DNN-based and conventional channel coding schemes, while significantly reducing the number of trainable parameters. Additionally, the proposed QAE exhibits steady and superior BLER convergence over the classical autoencoder baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20241v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bolun Zhang, Gan Zheng, Nguyen Van Huynh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Light Bosonic Dark Matter with Transmon Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20850v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the constraints of the transmon qubit, an improved version of the charge qubit, on bosonic light dark matters. Phonon excitations induced by the scattering or absorption of dark matter on a superconductor may destroy the Cooper pair, leading to the production of quasiparticles made by the electron. By measuring the production rate of the quasiparticle density, one may read out the coupling between dark matter and ordinary matter, assuming that these quasiparticles are solely induced by dark matter interactions. For the first time, we show constraints on the parameter space of the dark photon, light scalar dark matter, and axion-like particles from the measurement of quasiparticles in transmon qubit experiments. This study offers insights for the development of quantum qubit experiments aimed at the direct detection of dark matter in underground laboratories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20850v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Chao, Yu Gao, Ming-jie Jin, Xiao-sheng Liu, Xi-lei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles Spin and Optical Properties of Vacancy Clusters in Lithium Fluoride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vacancy-cluster color centers in lithium fluoride have been studied in detail both theoretically and experimentally for over a century, giving rise to various applications in solid-state lasers, broadband photonic devices, and radiation dosimeters. These color centers are also attractive candidate platforms for applications in quantum information science, due to their spin properties and strong coupling to the crystal lattice, which allows their properties to be easily tuned. Here we present hybrid functional calculations of common vacancy defects in lithium fluoride, including their energetic, spin, and optical properties. We show that for a wide range of hybrid functional parameters tuned to match the experimental band gap, certain defects have little variation in their predicted optical properties. We further demonstrate that the parameters needed to satisfy the generalized Koopman's theorem and correctly position defect levels within the gap, can vary dramatically, even for different charge states of the same defect. Our work establishes the accuracy of the computationally lightweight hybrid-functional approach for predicting the optical and energetic properties of color centers in polar materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21060v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariano Guerrero Perez, Keegan Walkup, Jordan Chapman, Pranshu Bhaumik, Giti A. Khodaparast, Brenden A. Magill, Patrick Huber, Vsevolod Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum tunneling and its absence in deep wells and strong magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21100v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present new results on quantum tunneling between deep potential wells, in the presence of a strong constant magnetic field. We construct a family of double well potentials containing examples for which the low-energy eigenvalue splitting vanishes, and hence quantum tunneling is eliminated. Further, by deforming within this family, the magnetic ground state can be made to transition from symmetric to anti-symmetric. However, for typical double wells in a certain regime, tunneling is not suppressed, and we provide a lower bound for the eigenvalue splitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21100v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles L. Fefferman, Jacob Shapiro, Michael I. Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
