<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 05:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of flat-band skin effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetry-protected ideal flat bands in one-dimensional (1D) Hermitian lattices are populated by compact localized states (CLS) - a special class of localization with wavefunctions confined within a small region. In this work, we discover that the non-Hermitian skin effect (NHSE) can appear in a flat band. Unlike conventional NHSEs for dispersive bands that are protected by nontrivial point-gap topology, the flat band remains a point on the complex-energy plane and is therefore always topologically trivial. We found that, intriguingly, the flat-band skin effect (FBSE) is associated with the non-trivial spectral topology of the dispersive bands enclosing the flat band on the complex-energy plane, so it only emerges within a finite range of non-Hermitian parameters and can counterintuitively disappear at large non-Hermiticity. Moreover, the gaps between the flat and the dispersive bands can close at higher-order exceptional points under both periodic and open boundary conditions. The flat-band wavefunctions are discontinuous in quantum distance across these exceptional points, signifying that the gap-closing is singular. The FBSE was experimentally observed in a non-Hermitian mechanical lattice. Our work reveals flat-band phenomena unique to non-Hermitian systems and highlights new possibilities in quantum geometry and localization control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19745v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xulong Wang, Dongyi Wang, Congwei Lu, Ruo-Yang Zhang, Ching Hua Lee, Kun Ding, Guancong Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composable, unconditional security without a Quantum secret key: public broadcast channels and their conceptualizations, adaptive bit transmission rates, fidelity pruning under wiretaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine public broadcast, forward conceptual, and backward conceptual, Quantum channels in the context of communication protocols that are independent of secret keys. Given research directions of interest previously identified in arXiv: 1804.01797, besides converse upper bounds on the bit transmission rate obtained by the author in recent work (arXiv: 2507.03035), additional possibilities remain, including: (1) determining whether aspects of QKD dependent protocols can be incorporated into steps of QKD independent protocols; (2) whether there would be any amplification to the Quantum-classical performance gap that Alice and Bob can exploit towards prospective Quantum advantage; (3) formulating the conditions under which secrecy and authentication can be simultaneously achieved. To characterize the conditions for which secrecy can be achieved with high probability, we argue that there not only exists suitable protocols which enable Alice and Bob to map into the authenticated space of bit codewords with high probability, but also that forward conceptual channels, through cascading, can significantly increase Eve's probability of false acceptance. Albeit the fact that secrecy, along with conceputalizations of the public broadcast channel, were initially discussed by Maurer for QKD dependent protocols, determining whether aspects of such protocols can be adapted for unconditional security without the use of a secret key is of great interest to explore. We demonstrate that Eve's error probability, through the cascading procedure, can be analyzed with the Holevo information under an optimal decoder. Furthermore, through post-processing of the outputs of a Completely Positive Trace Preserving (CPTP) map, we also demonstrate how to decrease Holevo sum quantities with data-processing and entropy-continuity bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19759v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pete Rigas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Scalable Spin Squeezing with Disordered Quantum Dipoles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin squeezed entanglement enables metrological precision beyond the classical limit. Understood through the lens of continuous symmetry breaking, dipolar spin systems exhibit the remarkable ability to generate spin squeezing via their intrinsic quench dynamics. To date, this understanding has primarily focused on lattice spin systems; in practice however, dipolar spin systems$\unicode{x2014}$ranging from ultracold molecules to nuclear spin ensembles and solid-state color centers$\unicode{x2014}$often exhibit significant amounts of positional disorder. Here, we develop a theory for scalable spin squeezing in a two-dimensional randomly diluted lattice of quantum dipoles, which naturally realize a dipolar XXZ model. Via extensive quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we map out the phase diagram for finite-temperature XY order, and by extension scalable spin squeezing, as a function of both disorder and Ising anisotropy. As the disorder increases, we find that scalable spin squeezing survives only near the Heisenberg point. We show that this behavior is due to the presence of rare tightly-coupled dimers, which effectively heat the system post-quench. In the case of strongly-interacting nitrogen-vacancy centers in diamond, we demonstrate that an experimentally feasible strategy to decouple the problematic dimers from the dynamics is sufficient to enable scalable spin squeezing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19781v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avi Kaplan-Lipkin, Philip J. D. Crowley, Jonathan N. Hall\'en, Zilin Wang, Weijie Wu, Sabrina Chern, Chris R. Laumann, Lode Pollet, Norman Y. Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning transitions of topological surface codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the surface code, topological quantum order allows one to encode logical quantum information in a robust, long-range entangled many-body quantum state. However, if an observer probes this quantum state by performing measurements on the underlying qubits, thereby collecting an ensemble of highly correlated classical snapshots, two closely related questions arise: (i) do measurements decohere the topological order of the quantum state; and (ii) how much of the logical information can one learn from the snapshots? Here we address these questions for measurements in a uniform basis on all qubits. We find that for generic measurement angles, sufficiently far away from the Clifford X, Y, and Z directions (such as the X+Y+Z basis) the logical information is never lost in one of the following two ways: (i) for weak measurement, the topological order is absolutely robust; (ii) for projective measurement, the quantum state inevitably collapses, but the logical quantum information is faithfully transferred from the quantum system to the observer in the form of a tomographically complete classical shadow. At these generic measurement angles and in the projective-measurement limit, the measurement ensemble enforced by Born probabilities can be represented by a 2D tensor network that can be fermionized into a disordered, free-fermion network model in symmetry class DIII, which gives rise to a Majorana "metal" phase. When the measurement angle is biased towards the X or Z limits, a critical angle indicates the threshold of a learning transition beyond which the classical shadow no longer reveals full tomographic information (but reduces to a measurement of the logical X or Z state). This learning transition can be described in the language of the network model as a "metal to insulator" transition...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19786v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finn Eckstein, Bo Han, Simon Trebst, Guo-Yi Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passive quantum reference frame transformations cannot create entanglement between physical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We find a necessary condition for subsystems to become entangled after a quantum reference frame transformation. By distinguishing between quantum systems suitable to act as reference frames and physical systems described relative to these frames, we define passive quantum reference frames and show that transformations between these cannot produce entanglement between physical systems. Our results also apply to the study of entanglement between subsystems in the perspectival framework even when there is no distinction between physical and reference systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19790v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Rick Perche, Nat\'alia Salom\'e M\'oller, Guilherme Franzmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-efficiency loading of 2,400 Ytterbium atoms in optical tweezer arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutral atom arrays have emerged as a powerful platform for quantum computation, simulation, and metrology. Among them, alkaline-earth-like atoms exhibit distinct advantages, including long coherence time and high-fidelity Rydberg gates. However, their scalability has lagged behind that of the alkali atoms. Here, we report 2,400 Ytterbium-174 atoms trapped in an optical tweezer array with enhanced single-atom loading efficiency of 83.5(1)%. Notably, the loading efficiency is largely maintained for array sizes ranging from dozens to thousands, exhibiting excellent scalability. We demonstrate the broad applicability of the enhanced loading method by showing that the enhancement exists robustly across a range of interatomic potentials, suggesting its utility for other atomic species. To establish the capability of the 174Yb arrays toward universal quantum computation, we propose to encode the qubit in the ground-clock state manifold and estimate a 99.9% two-qubit gate fidelity with experimentally feasible parameters. Our work advances the prospects for realizing large-scale quantum computers using alkaline-earth-like atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19795v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawen Zhu, Changfeng Chen, Li Zhou, Xiangru Xie, Chenyang Jiang, Zhuoli Ding, Fan Wu, Fan Yang, Guoqing Wang, Qihuang Gong, Peng Zhang, Sheng Zhang, Pai Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ergotropy of quantum many-body scars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum many-body scars break ergodicity and evade thermalization, resulting in area law entanglement entropy even with high energy density. While their quantum correlations and entanglement have been elaborated previously, their capacity in storing extractable energy, quantified by the notion ergotropy, remains an open question. Here we focus on the representative PXP model, and unveil the extensive ergotropy scaling of a family of states interpolating between quantum many-body scars and thermal states, the latter of which are known to be passive with vanishing ergotropy. A phenomenological relation between ergotropy and entanglement is uncovered, which generalizes the existing free fermion integrable results to an interacting scenario. The ergotropy in a dynamical protocol shows that a reset with a global uniform coherent rotation can inject extractable energy, as a proof of principle way to charge a quantum "battery". Our protocol is tailored for near term Rydberg neutral atoms array, while also being feasible for other quantum processors. Our results establish that quantum many-body scars, despite the tiny fraction of the Hilbert space they occupy, can be efficiently exploited for storing extractable energy, and "scarring" a many-body system as a promising route for engineering quantum many-body battery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19801v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaohui Zhi, Qingyun Qian, Jin-Guo Liu, Guo-Yi Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Operations and Field Mediated Entanglement without a Local Tensor Product Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum information has become a powerful tool for probing the structure of quantum field theories, yet its application to gauge theories remains subtle. On the one hand, quantum information theory assumes subsystem locality, i.e.~the factorization of the total Hilbert space into subsystems. On the other hand, gauge constraints prevent the total Hilbert space to decompose into a spacetime-local tensor product structure. Because the Hilbert space structure of gauge theories does not accommodate the subsystem decomposition used in quantum information theory, standard information-theoretic results, such as the Local Operations and Classical Communication (LOCC) theorem, cannot be used straightforwardly in the context of gauge theories. In this work, we bridge this gap in the case of a two-dimensional lattice gauge model that captures key features of electromagnetism. In particular, we construct gauge-invariant local algebras and derive a physically meaningful decomposition of the Hilbert space, providing an operationally consistent notion of locality in the absence of a local tensor-product structure. We apply this framework to field-mediated entanglement protocols relevant to proposed tests of the quantum nature of gravity. We show that the discretized version of electromagnetism satisfies an analogue of the LOCC theorem: entanglement cannot be generated without genuine quantum field interactions, even in the absence of a spacetime-local tensor product factorization of the Hilbert space. This may point towards an operational way to define a subsystem structure for gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19806v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Spalvieri, S\'ebastien Christophe Garmier, Flaminia Giacomini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamentals of quantum Boltzmann machine learning with visible and hidden units</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the primary applications of classical Boltzmann machines is generative modeling, wherein the goal is to tune the parameters of a model distribution so that it closely approximates a target distribution. Training relies on estimating the gradient of the relative entropy between the target and model distributions, a task that is well understood when the classical Boltzmann machine has both visible and hidden units. For some years now, it has been an obstacle to generalize this finding to quantum state learning with quantum Boltzmann machines that have both visible and hidden units. In this paper, I derive an analytical expression for the gradient of the quantum relative entropy between a target quantum state and the reduced state of the visible units of a quantum Boltzmann machine. Crucially, this expression is amenable to estimation on a quantum computer, as it involves modular-flow-generated unitary rotations reminiscent of those appearing in my prior work on rotated Petz recovery maps. This leads to a quantum algorithm for gradient estimation in this setting. I then specialize the setting to quantum visible units and classical hidden units, and vice versa, and provide analytical expressions for the gradients, along with quantum algorithms for estimating them. Finally, I replace the quantum relative entropy objective function with the Petz-Tsallis relative entropy; here I develop an analytical expression for the gradient and sketch a quantum algorithm for estimating it, as an application of a novel formula for the derivative of the matrix power function, which also involves modular-flow-generated unitary rotations. Ultimately, this paper demarcates progress in training quantum Boltzmann machines with visible and hidden units for generative modeling and quantum state learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19819v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a point-to-point CV-QKD system: Implementation challenges and perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article presents an analysis of the practical challenges and implementation perspectives of point-to-point continuous-variable quantum key distribution (CV-QKD) systems over optical fiber. The study addresses the physical layer, including the design of transmitters, quantum channels, and receivers, with emphasis on impairments such as attenuation, chromatic dispersion, polarization fluctuations, and coexistence with classical channels. We further examine the role of digital signal processing (DSP) as the bridge between quantum state transmission and classical post-processing, highlighting its impact on excess noise mitigation, covariance matrix estimation, and reconciliation efficiency. The post-processing pipeline is detailed with a focus on parameter estimation in the finite-size regime, information reconciliation using LDPC-based codes optimized for low-SNR conditions, and privacy amplification employing large-block universal hashing. From a hardware perspective, we discuss modular digital architectures that integrate dedicated accelerators with programmable processors, supported by a reference software framework (CV-QKD-ModSim) for algorithm validation and hardware co-design. Finally, we outline perspectives for the deployment of CV-QKD in Brazil, starting from metropolitan testbeds and extending toward hybrid fiber/FSO and space-based infrastructures. The work establishes the foundations for the first point-to-point CV-QKD system in Brazil, while providing a roadmap for scalable and interoperable quantum communication networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19834v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davi Juv\^encio Gomes de Sousa, Nelson Alves Ferreira Neto, Christiano M. S. Nascimento, Lucas Q. Galv\~ao, Mauro Queiroz Nooblath Neto, Micael Andrade Dias, C\'assio de Castro Silva, Braian Pinheiro da Silva, Alexandre B. Tacla, Val\'eria Loureiro da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanics on Lie Groups: I. Noncommutative Fourier Transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starting from square-integrable wave functions on a Lie group, we build an invertible Fourier transform mapping them on wave functions on the dual of the Lie algebra. This is a group-theoretic version of the map from position space to momentum space, with generally noncommuting momenta owing to the group structure. As a result, the multiplication of momentum-dependent functions involves star products, which makes the construction of noncommutative Fourier series much more involved than that of their commutative cousin. We show that our formalism provides an isometry of Hilbert spaces, and use it to derive a noncommutative Poisson summation formula for any compact Lie group. This is a key preliminary for the computation of Wigner functions and path integrals for quantum systems on group manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19840v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Beauvillain, Blagoje Oblak, Marios Petropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity and Information in Quantum and Classical Trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze emission trajectories from a driven-dissipative two-qubit system and a classical telegraph model with matched rates. Using Lempel-Ziv complexity, mutual information, and temporal correlations, we show that both models undergo a transition from independent to synchronized dynamics as coupling increases, but only the quantum trajectories develop enhanced complexity and sustained information sharing at large drive-to-decay ratio. Classical correlations are short-lived and quickly suppressed by strong drive. A strong complexity-information correlation appears uniquely in the quantum case, providing a clear trajectory-level signature of quantum effects. These results show that complexity and information measures extracted directly from jump records provide an efficient way to distinguish quantum and classical dynamics in open systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19848v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hira Ali, Naeem Shahid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum information scrambling in strongly disordered Rydberg spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the fact that power-law interactions occur in a plethora of physical systems, their many-body dynamics is far less understood than that of nearest-neighbor interacting systems. Here, we study information scrambling in strongly disordered spin systems with power-law interactions via out-of-time-order correlators (OTOCs). Numerically, we find pronounced differences in the dynamical spreading of OTOCs between nearest-neighbor and power-law interacting systems. This deviation persists even for short-range interactions, opposing the common view that these interactions produce dynamics equivalent to the nearest-neighbor case. In a detailed experimental proposal, tailored but not limited to Rydberg tweezer setups, we present a protocol to extract OTOCs in XXZ Heisenberg spin systems with tunable anisotropy and programmable disorder based on currently available techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19856v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian M\"ullenbach, Sebastian Geier, Adrian Braemer, Eduard Braun, Titus Franz, Gerhard Z\"urn, Matthias Weidem\"uller, Martin G\"arttner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative quantum algorithms for excited-state quantum chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electronic excited states are central to a vast array of physical and chemical phenomena, yet accurate and efficient methods for preparing them on quantum devices remain challenging and comparatively underexplored. We introduce a general dissipative algorithm for selectively preparing ab initio electronic excited states. The key idea is to recast excited-state preparation as an effective ground-state problem by suitably modifying the underlying Lindblad dynamics so that the target excited state becomes the unique steady state of a designed quantum channel. We develop three complementary strategies, tailored to different types of prior information about the excited state, such as symmetry and approximate energy. We demonstrate the effectiveness and versatility of these schemes through numerical simulations of atomic and molecular spectra, including valence excitations in prototypical planar conjugated molecules and transition-metal complexes. Taken together, these results provide a new pathway for advancing quantum simulation methods for realistic strongly correlated electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19870v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-En Li, Lin Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized coherent states in thermal field dynamics in the frame of diagonal ordering operator technique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although the thermofield dynamics (TFD) was developed specifically for systems to which the ladder canonical operators and are associated, in the paper we showed that this approach can also be formulated for systems of deformed bosons, associated with a pair of deformed operators and . In this context we built sets of temperature dependent coherent states, both of the Barut-Girardello and of the Klauder-Perelomov type, these two types being dual to each other. In calculations involving ladder operators, both independent and temperature-dependent, we used the Diagonal Operator Ordering Technique (DOOT), which is a generalization of the Integration Within an Ordered Product technique (IWOP) applicable to canonical operators associated with the one-dimensional harmonic oscillator. We also refer to the connection between TFD and thermodynamic quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19880v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Du\v{s}an Popov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gate-Based Microwave Quantum Repeater Via Grid-State Encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In autonomous quantum error correction the lifetime of a logical bosonic qubit can be extended beyond its physical constituents without feedback measurements. Leveraging autonomous error correction, we propose a second-generation gate-based microwave quantum repeater (GBMQR) with encoded bosonic grid states. Each repeater station comprises a transmon and two bosonic resonators: one resonator serving as a stationary quantum memory utilizing autonomous error correction, and the other as an information bus for entanglement generation. Entanglement is generated sequentially through the successful absorption of a microwave photon wavepacket. This method enables deterministic entanglement generation, in contrast to a probabilistic mixing of two heralding signals on a balanced beamsplitter. Furthermore, our GBMQR employs an all-bosonic entanglement swapping Bell-state measurement. This is implemented via a bosonic controlled-Z gate and two separate X-basis projective homodyne measurements on the stationary stored codewords. Our approach circumvents mode-mismatch losses associated with routing and interfering of heralding modes on a beamsplitter, and confines losses to those arising from stationary storage. We evaluate the performance of the proposed quantum repeater by calculating its secret key rate under realistic lab environments. Moreover, we explicitly demonstrate that at stationary damping rate of $\kappa^{-1}_{\text{damp}}=$~\SI{40}{\milli\second}, GBMQR can achieve entanglement generation and swapping success probabilities approx.~$0.75$, and $0.58$ respectively, surpassing the hallmark success probability of $1/2$ set by ideal linear beamsplitter-based Bell-state measurements. The proposed device can be implemented using currently available superconducting microwave technology and is suited for secure chip-to-chip communication and distributed quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19896v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hany Khalifa, Matti Silveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DC-powered broadband quantum-limited microwave amplifier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fast, high-fidelity, single-shot readout of superconducting qubits in quantum processors demands quantum-limited amplifiers to preserve the optimal signal-to-noise ratio. Typically, quantum-limited amplification is achieved with parametric down-conversion of a strong pump tone, which imposes significant hardware overhead and severely limits scalability. Here, we demonstrate the first DC-powered broadband amplifier operating within 0.2 photons of the quantum limit. Our impedance-engineered Inelastic Cooper-pair Tunneling Amplifier (ICTA)-a voltage-biased SQUID in which Cooper pairs tunnel inelastically by emitting signal-idler photon pairs-operates in reflection, delivering 13 dB of average gain across a 3.5 GHz bandwidth in a single stage. Semiclassical simulations accurately predict the gain and saturation power, enabling further design improvements. By eliminating the pump-tone infrastructure, the broadband ICTA promises to dramatically reduce the hardware complexity of quantum-limited amplification in superconducting quantum processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19902v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Nehra, N. Bourlet, A. H. Esmaeili, B. Monge, F. Cyrenne-Bergeron, A. Paquette, M. Arabmohammadi, A. Rogalle, Y. Lapointe, M. Hofheinz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical blueprint for 99.999% fidelity X-gates on present superconducting hardware under strong driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving very fast gates that undercut the natural limits set by decoherence requires going into the strong driving limit. Realizing single-qubit control predicted beyond semi-classical, time-dependent modeling has yet to be experimentally realized on superconducting and most other computing platforms. In this regime, the common model of dynamics within a three-level manifold breaks down, and instead, we see new quantum error channels growing abruptly with decreasing time. To identify these error processes we systematically calculate the effect of multi-photon transitions that occur out of the computational space. We then derive analytical formulas to suppress these effects, as well as amplitude and phase errors on the qubit space; we term these R1D for suppressing the $|0\rangle-|2\rangle$ transition and R2D when also suppressing $|1\rangle-|3\rangle$ leakage. We also answer long-standing questions about the optimal values of the DRAG prefactor as well as constant detuning, when accounting for time-ordering, and also show how to calibrate other prefactors for further performance improvement. Upon correcting these varied sources of error, we numerically demonstrate gate infidelities below $10^{-5}$ for a 7ns $\pi$-rotation when incorporating existing decoherence rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19919v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Diogo Da Costa Jesus, Boxi Li, Yuan Gao, Rami Barends, Francisco Andr\'es C\'ardenas-L\'opez, Felix Motzoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonclassicality of Mixed States with Photon Number Coherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19953v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The operational resource theory (ORT) measure is a nonclassicality measure for bosonic states, notable for its resource-theoretic properties and connection to metrology. However, it can be difficult to evaluate, being linked to an optimization problem for mixed states. Here, we present the first ORT measure calculations for mixed states with photon number coherence. We give exact formulas governing the ORT measure of a broad class of rank-two mixed states, and numerical solutions for some higher-rank states. We also compare the nonclassicality of these states to their metrological power, thus showing in what regimes the metrological power manages to saturate the ORT bound. Throughout, we consider the role of coherence. In particular, we show that nonclassicality and metrological power never increase under bosonic dephasing, but may plateau in a manner similar to entanglement sudden death. Nevertheless, lowering photon number coherence more freely can sometimes yield more nonclassical and metrologically useful states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19953v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer Rogers, Salman Shahid, Wenchao Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Segment Display Problems Using Quantum Grover's Search Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new Boolean-based methodology for constructing Segment Display Problems (SDPs) in the quantum domain and solving them using Grover's quantum search algorithm. In the classical domain, the SDPs are typically solved using various techniques, such as human deduction, heuristic search, and methods for solving Boolean satisfiability (SAT) and constraint satisfaction problems (CSPs) that are based on different problem design models. In this paper, our newly introduced methodology proposes a quantum-based approach for solving such SDPs, by building their quantum oracle using binary reversible circuits and our previously proposed step-decreasing structures shaped operators (Stesso). To demonstrate the usability of this proposed method, we experimentally solve an SDP instance of the matchstick problem using Grover's algorithm with a noisy simulated quantum computer implemented in Qiskit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19969v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shanyan Chen, Ali Al-Bayaty, Xiaoyu Song, Marek Perkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real Matrix Representations of Quantum Operators: An Introduction to Quantum Index Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce Quantum Index Algebra (QIA) as a finite, index-based algebraic framework for representing and manipulating quantum operators on Hilbert spaces of dimension $2^m$. In QIA, operators are expressed as structured combinations of basis elements indexed by Boolean codes, allowing products, commutators, and conjugations to be computed through finite rules on discrete indices rather than through dense matrix arithmetic. This representation unifies combinatorial index structure, explicit matrix realization, and transformation properties under Walsh-Hadamard-type transforms within a single formalism. Using QIA and its associated block-matrix realization, we reformulate the Bernstein-Vazirani hidden-string problem in its phase-oracle form entirely within a real, finite-dimensional algebraic setting. We show that, under structured oracle access, the QIA procedure reproduces the Bernstein-Vazirani algorithm exactly and achieves the same asymptotic query complexity and circuit depth as the standard quantum algorithm. In particular, the hidden string is recovered by symbolic manipulation of a sparse algebraic representation of the oracle rather than by numerical simulation of quantum amplitudes. Our results demonstrate that the apparent quantum speed-up in this setting is a consequence of operator structure rather than Hilbert-space dimensionality alone. QIA thus provides a precise language for separating genuinely quantum resources from those arising from algebraic and combinatorial structures and offers a new perspective on the classical simulability of structured quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19977v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Yu. Volkov, G. A. Koroteev, Yu. S. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regression of Functions by Quantum Neural Networks Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The performance of quantum neural network models depends strongly on architectural decisions, including circuit depth, placement of parametrized operations, and data-encoding strategies. Selecting an effective architecture is challenging and closely related to the classical difficulty of choosing suitable neural-network topologies, which is computationally hard. This work investigates automated quantum-circuit construction for regression tasks and introduces a genetic-algorithm framework that discovers Reduced Regressor QNN architectures. The approach explores depth, parametrized gate configurations, and flexible data re-uploading patterns, formulating the construction of quantum regressors as an optimization process. The discovered circuits are evaluated against seventeen classical regression models on twenty-two nonlinear benchmark functions and four analytical functions. Although classical methods often achieve comparable results, they typically require far more parameters, whereas the evolved quantum models remain compact while providing competitive performance. We further analyze dataset complexity using twelve structural descriptors and show, across five increasingly challenging meta-learning scenarios, that these measures can reliably predict which quantum architecture will perform best. The results demonstrate perfect or near-perfect predictive accuracy in several scenarios, indicating that complexity metrics offer powerful and compact representations of dataset structure and can effectively guide automated model selection. Overall, this study provides a principled basis for meta-learning-driven quantum architecture design and advances the understanding of how quantum models behave in regression settings--a topic that has received limited exploration in prior work. These findings pave the way for more systematic and theoretically grounded approaches to quantum regression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19978v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando M. de Paula Neto, Lucas dos Reis Silva, Paulo S. G. de Mattos Neto, Felipe F. Fanchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Efficient Source-Independent Quantum Conference Key Agreement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20038v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multipartite entanglement enables secure group key distribution among multiple users while providing immunity against hacking attacks targeting source devices, thereby realizing source-independent quantum conference key agreement (SI-QCKA). However, previous experimental demonstrations of SI-QCKA have encountered substantial technical challenges, primarily due to the low efficiency and scalability limitations inherent in the generation and distribution of multipartite entanglement. Here, we experimentally demonstrate a scalable and efficient SI-QCKA protocol using polarization-entangled photon pairs in a three-user star network, where Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger correlations are realized via a post-matching method. We achieve a secure group key rate of $2.11 \times 10^{4}$ bits/s under the single-user channel transmission of 1.64 $\times$ $10^{-1}$ in a symmetric channel loss network. Additionally, we conduct six sets of experiments to investigate the impact of varying channel transmission and random basis selection probabilities on secure key rates. Our work establishes an efficient pathway for SI-QCKA and demonstrates potential scalability for future large-scale multi-user quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20038v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.34133/research.1034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Research 8, 1034 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Ji Hua, Yi-Ran Xiao, Yu Bao, Hua-Lei Yin, Zeng-Bing Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathscr{H}_2$ Model Reduction for Augmented Model of Linear Non-Markovian Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An augmented system model provides an effective way to model non-Markovian quantum systems, which is useful in filtering and control for this class of systems. However, since a large number of ancillary quantum oscillators representing internal modes of a non-Markovian environment directly interact with the principal system in these models, the dimension of the augmented system may be very large causing significant computational burden in designing filters and controllers. In this context, this paper proposes an $\mathscr{H}_2$ model reduction method for the augmented model of linear non-Markovian quantum systems. We first establish necessary and sufficient conditions for the physical realizability of the augmented model of linear non-Markovian quantum systems, which are more stringent than those for Markovian quantum systems. However, these physical realizability conditions of augmented system model pose non-convex constrains in the optimization problem of model reduction, which makes the problem different from the corresponding classical model reduction problem. To solve the problem, we derive necessary conditions for determining the input matrix in the reduced model, with which a theorem for designing the system matrix of the ancillary system in the reduced system is proved. Building on this, we convert the nonlinear equality constraints into inequality constraints so that a semidefinite programming algorithm can be developed to solve the optimization problem for model reduction.
  A numerical example of a two-mode linear quantum system driven by three internal modes of a non-Markovian environment validates the effectiveness of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20040v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangpu Wu, Shibei Xue, Guofeng Zhang, Rebing Wu, Min Jiang, Ian R. Petersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov Chain Model of Entanglement Setup in Noisy Dynamic LEO Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20047v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement routing in dynamic Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellite networks is important for achieving scalable and high-fidelity quantum communication. However, the dynamic characteristics of satellite network topology, limited quantum resources, and strict coherence time constraints pose significant challenges to reliable entanglement routing. An entanglement distribution analysis model for this unique environment is critical and helpful for entanglement routing research. We address the fundamental challenge of establishing and maintaining quantum entanglement links between satellites operating in free space, where links are subject to both transmission losses and quantum memory decoherence. This paper presents a comprehensive Markov chain model with a state space defined by link storage age and physical distance for analyzing entanglement distribution in noisy dynamic LEO satellite quantum networks. We construct transition matrices that capture system dynamics under varying request arrival rates, and derive analytical expressions for key performance metrics, including request satisfaction rate, average waiting time, link utilization efficiency, and average consumed link fidelity. Our analysis reveals that the critical trade-offs of higher request rates lead to faster link consumption with higher fidelity but potentially lower satisfaction rates, while lower request rates allow longer storage times at the cost of lower fidelity of increased decoherence effect. Moreover, this paper proves it is reasonable to leave out polarization rotation when the transmission distance is very short (40-50 km). In summary, this work provides theoretical foundations for designing and optimizing quantum entanglement distribution strategies in satellite networks, with applications to global-scale quantum communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20047v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Gao, Alvin Valera, Winston K. G. Seah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fault Injection Attacks on Machine Learning-based Quantum Computer Readout Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine-learning (ML) classifiers are increasingly used in quantum computing systems to improve multi-qubit readout discrimination and to mitigate correlated readout errors. These ML classifiers are an integral component of today's quantum computer's control and readout stacks. This paper is the first to analyze the susceptibility of such ML classifiers to physical fault-injection which can result in generation of incorrect readout results from quantum computers. The study targets 5-qubit (thus 32-class) readout error-correction model. Using the ChipWhisperer Husky for physical voltage glitching, this work leverages an automated algorithm for scanning the fault injection parameter search space to find various successful faults in all the layers of the target ML model. Across repeated trials, this work finds that fault susceptibility is strongly layer-dependent: early-layers demonstrate higher rates of misprediction when faults are triggered in them, whereas later layers have smaller misprediction rates. This work further characterizes the resulting readout failures at the bitstring level using Hamming-distance and per-bit flip statistics, showing that single-shot glitches can induce structured readout corruption rather than purely random noise. These results motivate treating ML-based quantum computer readout and readout correction as a security-critical component of quantum systems and highlight the need for lightweight, deployment-friendly fault detection and redundancy mechanisms in the quantum computer readout pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20077v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Etim, Jakub Szefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force Sensing Beyond the Standard Quantum Limit in a Hybrid Optomechanical Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate quantum measurement noise in a hybrid optomechanical system, focusing on radiation pressure back action and its impact on force sensing. The setup consists of an optomechanical cavity with a movable mirror, a fixed semi transparent mirror, an ensemble of quantum dots (QD) coupled to the cavity mode, and an intracavity optical parametric amplifier (OPA). We show how the QD induced response, together with the system nonlinearity, modifies the noise spectral density and thereby improves the force measurement sensitivity. In this setup, coherent quantum noise cancellation (CQNC) can completely remove the back action noise. In addition, increasing the OPA pump gain enables sensitivity beyond the standard quantum limit (SQL) at reduced laser power. These combined effects allow weak force sensing beyond the SQL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20081v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alolika Roy, Amarendra K. Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision Bounds for Characterising Quantum Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum measurements, alongside quantum states and processes, form a cornerstone of quantum information processing. However, unlike states and processes, their efficient characterisation remains relatively unexplored. We resolve this asymmetry by introducing a comprehensive framework for efficient detector estimation that reveals the fundamental limits to extractable parameter information and errors arising in detector analysis - the \emph{detector quantum Fisher information}. Our development eliminates the need to optimise for the best probe state, while highlighting aspects of detector analysis that fundamentally differ from quantum state estimation. Through proofs, examples and experimental validation, we demonstrate the relevance and robustness of our proposal for current quantum detector technologies. By formalising a dual perspective to state estimation, our framework completes and connects the triad of efficient state, process, and detector tomography, advancing quantum information theory with broader implications for emerging technologies reliant on precisely calibrated measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20091v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Das, Simon K. Yung, Lorcan O. Conlon, Ozlem Erkilic, Angus Walsh, Yong-Su Kim, Ping K. Lam, Syed M. Assad, Jie Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-size Effects on The Edge Loss Probability in Non-Hermitian Quantum Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A dynamical bulk-edge relation in quantum walks has been theoretically proposed and experimentally observed, in which a power-law dependence of the bulk loss probability is associated with a pronounced peak of loss probability at the edge. This behavior has been proven to arise from imaginary gap closing and the non-Hermitian skin effect in the infinite limit without boundary effects. However, in a finite-size chain, we find that boundary scattering can suppress this edge burst. Meanwhile, imaginary gap opening together with the non-Hermitian skin effect, can also induce a large loss probability at the edge. Our results provide insights into finite-size quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20106v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaixian Liu, Yulan Dong, Bowen Zeng, Mengqiu Long</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal control of population transfer in multi-level systems by dynamical quantum geometric tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The optimal control of population transfer for multi-level systems is investigated from the perspective of quantum geometry. Firstly, the general theoretical framework of optimizing the stimulated Raman adiabatic passage (STIRAP) scheme based on the dynamical quantum geometric tensor is given, and then the dynamical quantum geometric tensor and the nonadiabatic transition rate are calculated by taking the detuned $\Lambda$-type three-level system and tripod-type four-level system for example. Secondly, the transfer dynamics of the particle population of the system are investigated in detail. For a three-level system, the optimal STIRAP scheme has an efficiency of over 98\% in transferring the population to the final state, while the transfer efficiency of traditional STIRAP is about 72\%. The superposition states with arbitrary proportions can be efficiently prepared for a four-level system due to the decoupling of the degenerate dark states. Finally, the influences of system parameters, such as the operation time of the Rabi pulses, the amplitude fluctuation and the single-photon detuning, on the transfer process are discussed. Especially, the phenomenon of the adiabatic resonance transfer is revealed. Choosing the pulse parameters in the resonance window can reduce the infidelity of the population transfer to below $10^{-3}$. It is found that the optimal STIRAP scheme by the dynamical quantum geometric tensor provides faster and more efficient transfer than the traditional STIRAP scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20131v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7498/aps.74.20250210</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Guan-Qiang Li, Yu-Qi Zhang, Hao Guo, You-Jiao Dong, Zhi-Yu Lin, Ping Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mixed UDA states and additivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mixed states that are uniquely determined among all (UDA) states are vital in efficient quantum tomography. We show the necessary and sufficient conditions by which some multipartite mixed states are UDA by their $k$-partite reduced density matrices. The case for $k=2$ is mostly studied, which requires minimal local information and shows practical benefits. Based on that, we establish a systematic method for determining UDA states and provide a complete characterization of the additivity of UDA bipartite and three-qubit product states. We show the application of mixed UDA states and their characterization from the perspectives of tomography and other tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20133v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Qiu, Lin Chen, Genwei Li, Delin Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly Tunable Two-Qubit Interactions in Si/SiGe Quantum Dots by Interchanging the Roles of Qubit-Defining Gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Silicon quantum dot spin qubits have become a promising platform for scalable quantum computing because of their small size and compatibility with industrial semiconductor manufacturing processes. Although Si/SiGe heterostructures are commonly used to host spin qubits due to their high mobility and low percolation density, the SiGe spacer creates a gap between the qubits and control electrodes, which limits the ability to tune exchange coupling. As a result, residual coupling leads to unwanted single-qubit phase shifts, making multi-qubit control more difficult. In this work, we explore swapping the roles of overlapping nanogates to overcome this issue. By reconfiguring the gate voltages, we demonstrate in situ role switching while maintaining multi-qubit control. Additionally, this method significantly improves the tunability of exchange coupling by several orders of magnitude over the traditional approach. This strategy reduces unintended single-qubit phase shifts and minimizes the complexity of multi-qubit control, supporting scalable growth with minimal experimental overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20142v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaemin Park, Hyeongyu Jang, Hanseo Sohn, Younguk Song, Lucas E. A. Stehouwer, Davide Degli Esposti, Giordano Scappucci, Dohun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder-induced broadening of quantum momentum distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the long-time behavior of a non-interacting two-dimensional quantum gas in a weak random potential with long-range correlations. Any peaked initial momentum distribution will eventually become isotropic and broaden due to scattering events with the random potential. We derive an expression for the long-time average of the momentum distribution and test it against computer simulations. We also discuss momentum isotropization and spatial diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20170v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vili Heinonen, Jani Lukkarinen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network-based prediction of drug combinations with quantum annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The systematic discovery of effective drug combinations is a challenging problem in modern pharmacology, driven by the combinatorial growth of potential pairings and dosage configurations. Network medicine, modeling diseases and drugs as interconnected modules of the human protein-protein interactome, has emerged as a new paradigm for understanding disease mechanisms and drug action. In this work, we propose a quantum annealing-based algorithm for identifying effective drug combinations. Underlying our approach is the biologically motivated principle of `Complementary Exposure', which posits that therapeutic drug combinations target distinct yet complementary regions of a disease module. We translate this into a quadratic unconstrained binary optimisation problem. We test our method for Diabetes Mellitus, Rheumatoid Arthritis, Asthma, and Brain Neoplasms, relying on experimentally validated drug combinations for these diseases. Our simulated quantum annealing experiments reveal that low-energy configurations align with biologically plausible combinations, demonstrating the algorithm's ability to generate novel predictions for drug combinations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20199v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diogo Ramos, Bruno Coutinho, Duarte Magano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveguide-integrated colour centres in silicon carbide with broadband photonic crystal reflectors for efficient readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-active colour centres in 4H silicon carbide are promising candidates as building blocks for quantum information applications. To increase the photon count rate of the emitters at low temperatures, the colour centres must be integrated into nanophotonic structures and characterised under cryogenic conditions. Here, we design and fabricate waveguide structures attached with an efficient Dinosaur photonic crystal reflector at one side. The devices show broadband reflection over a range of 60 THz with a peak reflectance above 80 %. Additionally, colour centres were integrated into these structures and characterised at cryogenic conditions. The emission was collected by a tapered-waveguide-tapered-fibre interface. Although the spectral stability of the emitters must be further improved for high excitation powers, the saturation intensity in standard PLE measurements is about 104 kcps. The count rate can be further improved to about 125 kcps with a charge-resonance check measurement scheme. To highlight the relevance of our devices, we theoretically show that these count rates enable optical single-shot readout with a fidelity exceeding 98 %.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20200v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcel Krumrein, Julian M. Bopp, Timo Steidl, Wolfgang Knolle, Jawad Ul-Hassan, Vadim Vorobyov, Tim Schr\"oder, J\"org Wrachtrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect quantum state transfer in a dispersion-engineered waveguide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-fidelity state transfer is fundamentally limited by time-reversal symmetry: one qubit emits a photon with a certain temporal pulse shape, whereas a second qubit requires the time-reversed pulse shape to efficiently absorb this photon. This limit is often overcome by introducing active elements. Here, we propose an alternative solution: by tailoring the dispersion relation of a waveguide, the photon pulse emitted by one qubit is passively reshaped into its time-reversed counterpart, thus enabling perfect absorption. We analytically derive the optimal dispersion relations in the limit of small and large qubit-qubit separations, and numerically extend our results to arbitrary separations via multiparameter optimization. We further propose a spatially inhomogeneous waveguide that renders the state transfer robust to variations in qubit separations. In all cases, we obtain near-unity transfer fidelity (&gt;= 98%). Our dispersion-engineered waveguide provides a compact and passive route toward on-chip quantum networks, highlighting engineered dispersion as a powerful resource in waveguide quantum electrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20212v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyu Kuang, Oliver Diekmann, Lorenz Fischer, Stefan Rotter, Carlos Gonzalez-Ballestero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tree tensor network states represent low-energy states faithfully</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extending corresponding results for matrix product states [Verstraete and Cirac, PRB 73, 094423 (2006); Schuch et al. PRL 100, 030504 (2008)], it is shown how the approximation error of tree tensor network states (TTNS) can be bounded using Schmidt spectra or R\'{e}nyi entanglement entropies of the target quantum state. Conversely, one obtains bounds on TTNS bond dimensions needed to achieve a specific approximation accuracy. For tree lattices, the result implies that efficient TTNS approximations exist if $\alpha&lt;1$ R\'{e}nyi entanglement entropies for single-branch cuts obey an area law, as in ground and low-energy states of certain gapped systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20215v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Barthel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A resource-efficient and noise-robust entanglement witness based on the swap test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement is an essential resource for quantum technologies, and the controlled swap test provides a versatile tool for its detection and quantification. Here, we propose a SWAP-based entanglement witness that applies to arbitrary two-qubit states - both pure and mixed - and provides a lower bound on the concurrence. The method is resource-efficient, robust to noise, and platform-independent. As an example, we validate the approach on a room-temperature photonic chip, where the swap test is carried out using only linear and well-established integrated optical components. The robustness of the method against photonic-hardware noise is also analysed. Our results establish a simple and reliable tool for entanglement witnessing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20235v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Guaraldo, Sonia Mazzucchi, Alessio Baldazzi, Stefano Azzini, Lorenzo Pavesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Geometric Tensor in the Wild: Resolving Stokes Phenomena via Floquet-Monodromy Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Standard topological invariants, such as the Chern number and Berry phase, form the bedrock of modern quantum matter classification. However, we demonstrate that this framework undergoes a \textbf{catastrophic failure} in the presence of essential singularities -- ubiquitous in open, driven, and non-Hermitian systems ("Wild" regime). In these settings, the local geometric tensor diverges, rendering standard invariants ill-defined and causing perturbative predictions to deviate from reality by order unity ($\sim 100\%$). We resolve this crisis by introducing the \textbf{Floquet-Monodromy Spectroscopy (FMS)} protocol, a pulse-level control sequence, which experimentally extracts the hidden \textit{Stokes Phenomenon} -- the "missing" geometric data that completes the topological description. By mapping the singularity's Stokes multipliers to time-domain observables, FMS provides a rigorous experimental bridge to \textbf{Resurgence Theory}, allowing for the exact reconstruction of non-perturbative physics from divergent asymptotic series. We validate this framework on a superconducting qudit model, demonstrating that the "Stokes Invariant" serves as the next-generation quantum number for classifying phases of matter beyond the reach of conventional topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20253v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prasoon Saurabh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathcal{PT}$-Symmetric Spin--Boson Model with a Continuous Bosonic Spectrum: Exceptional Points and Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work studies a $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric non-Hermitian spin--boson model, consisting of a non-Hermitian two-level system coupled to a continuous bosonic bath. The static properties of the system are analyzed through a projection method derived from the displacement operator. We find that only a single exceptional point (EP) emerges, in contrast to non-Hermitian spin--boson models with finite modes, which typically exhibit multiple EPs. Notably, only a single real eigenvalue is found before the EP, which differs markedly from typical non-Hermitian systems where a pair of real eigenvalues precedes the EP. The time evolution of observables is further investigated via the Dirac--Frenkel time-dependent variational principle. Compared to its Hermitian counterpart, the non-Hermitian model exhibits distinct dynamical signatures, most notably the emergence of oscillations with periodic amplified amplitude. In the $\mathcal{PT}$-unbroken phase, the system exhibits sustained oscillatory dynamics with suppressed decoherence, whereas in the $\mathcal{PT}$-broken phase, additional dissipative channels accelerate decoherence and drive rapid convergence toward a stable steady state. These results shed light on how $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry protects coherent light--matter interactions in non-Hermitian quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20277v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Xin Zhang, Qing-Hu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization and coherent control of 25 nuclear spins in Silicon Carbide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optically addressable spin defects are excellent candidate platform for quantum sensing and quantum network. Nuclear spins coupled to color centers naturally enable long lived quantum memories and local qubits registers. To fully leverage this potential precise characterization of the surrounding nuclear-spin environment augmented with refined DFT models is required. In this work, we report angstrom-level 3D localization of 25 nuclear spins around a single V2 center in 4H Silicon Carbide. Utilizing specially placed robust nuclear memory as a highly efficient readout ancilla for readout, we apply correlation based spectroscopy and by selecting multi-spin chains up to length four, we access and characterize extended nuclear spin cluster. Using the coupling map we reconstruct their couplings to the central electron spin and neighboring nuclei. This work paves the way towards advanced quantum register applications on Silicon Carbide platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20281v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Kuna, Erik Hesselmeier-H\"uttmann, Phillip Schillinger, Felix Gloistein, Istv\'an Tak\'acs, Viktor Iv\'ady, Wolfgang Knolle, Jawad Ul-Hassan, J\"org Wrachtrup, Vadim Vorobyov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Krylov complexity in ergodically constrained nonintegrable transverse-field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nonintegrable transverse-field Ising model is a common platform for studying ergodic quantum dynamics. In this work, we introduce a simple variant of the model in which this ergodic behaviour is suppressed by introducing a spatial inhomogeneity in the interaction strengths. For this we partition the chain into two equal segments within which the spins interact with different coupling strengths. The ratio of these couplings defines an inhomogeneity parameter, whose variation away from unity leads to constrained dynamics. We characterize this crossover using multiple diagnostics, such as the long-time saturation of out-of-time-ordered correlators, level-spacing statistics, and the spectral form factor. We further examine the consequences for operator growth in Krylov space and for entanglement generation in the system's eigenstates. Together, these results demonstrate that introducing a macroscopic inhomogeneity in coupling strengths provides a minimal, disorder-free route to breaking ergodicity in this specific model of interacting spins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20285v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Rudra Malik, Jeet Sharma, Rohit Kumar Shukla, S. Aravinda, Sunil Kumar Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Solution of Schr\"odinger equation for Complex Mass Quantum System under Complex Morse Potential to study emergent matter types and its phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present exact solutions of the Schr\"odinger equation for a quantum system with complex mass subjected to a complex Morse potential in the extended complex phase space. The normalized eigenfunctions and corresponding eigenspectra are derived within a non-Hermitian framework, ensuring consistent probability densities. Conditions for the reality of the spectra are established and used to analyze the dependence of eigenvalue behaviour on potential parameters. The study reveals distinct regimes of spectral characteristics arising from the interplay of complex mass, the Morse parameter, and eigenvalues, leading to the emergence of five intrinsic matter types. By analysing the energy eigenspectra, normalization conditions, and probability density profiles across parameter space, we identify regimes corresponding to real-spectrum Hermitian-like matter, quasi-stable or resonant states, purely complex quantum matter, non-physical, non-normalizable states, and a quasi-classical determinate regime in which the probability density becomes spatially static. One of these system exhibits a non-dissipative, collisionless state with long-range gravitational-like characteristics, suggesting a theoretical analogue for dark matter within a non-Hermitian quantum framework. Further, the five identified classes of matter may be interpreted as distinct phases of a single quantum system governed by complex mass and Morse parameters This classification elucidates the boundary between physical and non-physical regimes in complex quantum systems and provides a unified approach for interpreting stability, resonance, and emergent classicality arising from complex parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20318v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha Sarathi, Bhaskar Singh Rawat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic quantum states, quantum phase transition for $N$ three-level atoms in an optical cavity -- Gauge principle and non-Hermitian Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study in this paper the quantum phase transition (QPT) from normal phase (NP) to superradiant phase (SP) for $N$ three-level atoms in a single-mode optical cavity for both Hermitian and non Hermitian Hamiltonians, where the $\Xi$-type three-level atom is described by spin-$1$ pseudo-spin operators. The long standing gauge-choice ambiguity of $\mathbf{A\cdot p}$ and $\mathbf{d\cdot E}$ called respectively the Coulomb and dipole gauges is resolved by the time-dependent gauge transformation on the Schr\"{o}dinger equation. Both $\mathbf{A\cdot p}$ and $\mathbf{d\cdot E}$ interactions are included in the unified gauge, which is truly gauge equivalent to the minimum coupling principle. The Coulomb and dipole interactions are just the special cases of unified gauge. Remarkably three interactions lead to the same results under the resonant condition of field-atom frequencies, while significant difference appears in red and blue detunings. The QPT is analyzed in terms of spin coherent-state variational method, which indicates the abrupt changes of energy spectrum, average photon number as well as the atomic population at the critical point of interaction constant. Crucially, we reveal the sensitive dependence on the initial optical-phase, which is particularly useful to test the validity of three gauges experimentally. The non-Hermitian atom-field interaction results in the exceptional point (EP), beyond which the semiclassical energy function becomes complex. However the energy spectrum of variational ground state is real in the absence of EP, and does not become complex. The superradiant state is unstable due to the non-Hermitian interaction induced photon-number loss. Thus only the NP exists in the non-Hermitian Dicke Model Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20321v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ni Liu, Xinyu Jia, J. -Q. Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lov\'asz theta lower bound on Quantum Max Cut</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a lower bound to quantum Max Cut of a graph in terms of the Lov\'asz theta function of its complement. For a graph with $m$ edges, $\text{qmc}(G) \geq \tfrac{m}{4}\big( 1 + \tfrac{8}{3\pi}\tfrac{1}{\vartheta(\bar{G}) -1} \big)$, with the bound achieved by a product state. The proof extends a result by Balla, Janzer, and Sudakov on classical Max Cut and is also inspired by the randomized rounding method of Gharibian and Parekh. The bound outperforms the classical bound when applied to quantum Max Cut.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20326v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Huber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie algebra-assisted quantum simulation and quantum optimal control via high-order Magnus expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The evolution of a quantum system under time-dependent driving exhibits phenomena that are absent in its stationary counterpart. However, the high dimensionality and non-commutative nature of quantum dynamics make this a challenging problem. The Magnus expansion provides an analytic framework to approximate the effective dynamics on short time-scales, but computing high-order terms with existing methods is computationally expensive. We introduce a scalable approach that reduces the computational effort to depend only on the degrees of freedom defining the time-dependent control function. We focus specifically on Hamiltonians consisting of a constant drift term and a controllable term. Our method provides a polynomial expression for the Magnus expansion which can be evaluated several orders of magnitude faster than previous techniques, enabling broad applications in the realms of quantum simulation and quantum optimal control. We showcase an application of the method by designing control pulses for the 5-qubit phase gate on a neutral-atom platform utilizing Rydberg atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20357v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. F. dos Santos, S. J. J. M. F. Kokkelmans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Exact Uncertainty Relation and Geometric Speed Limits in Krylov Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that Hall's exact uncertainty relation acquires a simple geometric form in the Krylov basis generated by the Liouvillian. In this canonical operator frame, the uncertainty equality implies that the operator amplitude vector evolves on the unit Krylov sphere with constant speed fixed solely by the first Lanczos coefficient. This yields an exact linear bound on geometric operator evolution, independent of higher Lanczos coefficients and valid for arbitrary Hamiltonians, integrable or chaotic. Our results provide the first unified geometric interpretation of exact quantum speed limits and operator growth, identifying the first Lanczos coefficient as the intrinsic speed scale of quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20359v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Alishahiha, Souvik Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Storage and retrieval of optical skyrmions with topological characteristics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical skyrmions are topological structures of light whose defining property, the skyrmion number, is robust against perturbations. This makes them attractive for applications in quantum information storage, where resilience to decoherence is paramount. However, their preservation during coherent storage remains unexplored. We report the first experimental demonstration of storing and retrieving optical skyrmions in a cold $^{87}$Rb vapor using a dual-path electromagnetically induced transparency memory. Crucially, we show that the skyrmion number remains invariant for storage times up to several microseconds, even when subjected to imbalanced loss between the two paths and substantial perturbations in control beam power. Our work demonstrates the survival of a non-trivial topological invariant in a quantum memory, marking a significant step towards topologically protected photonic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20378v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwen Wang, Xin Yang, Yun Chen, Zhujun Ye, Xinji Zeng, Yongkun Zhou, Shuya Zhang, Claire Marie Cisowski, Chengyuan Wang, Katsuya Inoue, Yijie Shen, Sonja Franke-Arnold, Hong Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profusion of Symmetry-Protected Qubits from Stable Ergodicity Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how combining a discrete symmetry with topological Hilbert space fragmentation can give rise to exponentially many topologically stable qubits protected by a single discrete symmetry. We illustrate this explicitly with the example of the $\mathsf{CZ}_p$ model, where the encoded qubits are stable to arbitrary symmetry-respecting perturbations for parametrically long times, substantially enhancing the robustness of a recently proposed construction based on nontopological fragmentation. In this model, the encoded qubits naturally come in pairs for which a universal set of transversal logical gates can be performed, ruling out (by the Eastin-Knill theorem) the possibility of using them for quantum error correction. We also comment on the combination of symmetry enrichment and topological fragmentation more generally, and the implications for use of systems exhibiting Hilbert space fragmentation as quantum memories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20393v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Iadecola, Rahul Nandkishore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrologically advantageous states: long-range entanglement and asymmetric error correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum metrology aims to exploit many-body quantum states to achieve parameter-estimation precision beyond the standard quantum limit. For unitary parameter encoding generated by local Hamiltonians, such enhancement is characterized by superlinear scaling of the quantum Fisher information (QFI) with system size. Despite extensive progress, a systematic understanding of which many-body quantum states can exhibit this scaling has remained elusive. Here, we develop a general framework that connects metrological performance to long-range entanglement, state-preparation complexity, and quantum error-correction properties. We prove that super-linear QFI scaling necessarily requires long-range entanglement by deriving rigorous complexity-dependent upper bounds on the QFI. We further show that, for two broad classes of quantum error-correcting codes, nondegenerate codes and Calderbank--Shor--Steane quantum low-density parity-check codes, a nonconstant code distance precludes super-linear QFI scaling for a wide class of local Hamiltonians, revealing a fundamental incompatibility between metrological sensitivity and protection against local noise. Finally, we identify constructive routes that evade this obstruction by exploiting asymmetric code structures. In particular, we show that states associated with classical low-density parity-check codes, as well as asymmetric toric code states, both having asymmetric logical distances, can achieve Heisenberg-limited scaling. Together, our results establish long-range entanglement and asymmetric error correction as the essential resource underlying quantum metrology and clarify the interplay among state complexity, error correction, and metrological power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20426v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Chen, Rui Luo, Yuxuan Yan, You Zhou, Xiongfeng Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the nature of gravity with quantum information methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this article is to provide an introduction to the use of quantum information methods for investigating the interface between quantum theory and gravity. To this end, we discuss the basic principles of two current research streams that use this approach. The first one explores a phenomenon known as gravitationally induced entanglement, which aims to infer whether the gravitational field responsible for the interaction between two massive bodies must be quantized or not. The second stream investigates causal structures, thereby providing indirect evidence that spacetime may exhibit non-classical behavior. Before presenting these topics, we briefly review some fundamental concepts and experiments from quantum information theory, such as the Mach-Zehnder interferometer, the Stern-Gerlach experiment, Bell inequalities and entanglement, and the language of quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20429v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruna Sahdo, Nat\'alia Salom\'e M\'oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling roadmap for modular trapped-ion QEC and lattice-surgery teleportation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a footprint study for the scaling of modular quantum error correction (QEC) protocols designed for triangular color codes, including a lattice-surgery-based logical teleportation gadget, and compare the performance of various possible architectures based on trapped ions. The differences in these architectures arise from the technology that enables the connectivity between physical qubits and the modularity required for the QEC gadgets, which is either based on laser-beam deflectors focused to independent modules hosting mid-size ion crystals, or integrated photonics guided to segmented modules of the trap and allowing for the manipulation of smaller ion crystals. Our approach integrates the transpilation of the QEC gadgets into native trapped-ion primitives and a detailed account of the specific laser addressing and ion transport leading to different amounts of crosstalk errors, motional excitation and idle qubit errors. Combining a microscopically-informed noise model with an efficient Pauli-frame simulator and different scalable decoders, we assess the near-term performance of the color-code memory and teleportation protocols on these architectures. Our analysis demonstrates that modular color-code teleportation is achievable in these near-term trapped-ion architectures, and identifies the integrated-photonics connectivity as the most promising route for longer-term scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20435v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'esar Benito, Alfredo Ricci Vasquez, Jonathan Home, Karan K. Mehta, Thomas Monz, Markus M\"uller, Alejandro Bermudez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Bayesian Optimization for the Automatic Tuning of Lorenz-96 as a Surrogate Climate Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20437v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a hybrid quantum-inspired heuristic for automatically tuning the Lorenz-96 model -- a simple proxy to describe atmospheric dynamics, yet exhibiting chaotic behavior. Building on the history matching framework by Lguensat et al. (2023), we fully automate the tuning process with a new convergence criterion and propose replacing classical Gaussian process emulators with quantum counterparts. We benchmark three quantum kernel architectures, distinguished by their quantum feature map circuits. A dimensionality argument implies, in principle, an increased expressivity of the quantum kernels over their classical competitors. For each kernel type, we perform an extensive hyperparameter optimization of our tuning algorithm. We confirm the validity of a quantum-inspired approach based on statevector simulation by numerically demonstrating the superiority of two studied quantum kernels over the canonical classical RBF kernel. Finally, we discuss the pathway towards real quantum hardware, mainly driven by a transition to shot-based simulations and evaluating quantum kernels via randomized measurements, which can mitigate the effect of gate errors. The very low qubit requirements and moderate circuit depths, together with a minimal number of trainable circuit parameters, make our method particularly NISQ-friendly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20437v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul J. Christiansen, Daniel Ohl de Mello, Cedric Br\"ugmann, Steffen Hien, Felix Herbort, Martin Kiffner, Lorenzo Pastori, Veronika Eyring, Mierk Schwabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enriching Earth Observation labeled data with Quantum Conditioned Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid adoption of diffusion models (DMs) in the Earth Observation (EO) domain has unlocked new generative capabilities aimed at producing new samples, whose statistical properties closely match real imagery, for tasks such as synthesizing missing data, augmenting scarce labeled datasets, and improving image reconstruction. This is particularly relevant in EO, where labeled data are often costly to obtain and limited in availability. However, classical DMs still face significant computational limitations, requiring hundreds to thousands of inference steps, as well as difficulties in capturing the intricate spatial and spectral correlations characteristic of EO data. Recent research in Quantum Machine Learning (QML), including initial attempts of Quantum Generative Models, offers a fundamentally different approach to overcome these challenges. Motivated by these considerations, we introduce the Quanvolutional Conditioned U-Net (QCU-Net), a hybrid quantum--classical architecture that applies quantum operations within a conditioned diffusion framework using a novel quanvolutional feature-extraction approach, for generating synthetic labeled EO imagery. Extensive experiments on the EuroSAT RGB dataset demonstrate that our QCU-Net achieves superior results. Notably, it reduces the Fr\'echet Inception Distance by 64%, lowers the Kernel Inception Distance by 76%, and yields higher semantic accuracy. Ablation studies further reveal that strategically positioning quantum layers and employing entangling variational circuits enhance model performance and convergence. This work represents the first successful adaptation of class-conditioned quantum diffusion modeling in the EO domain, paving the way for quantum-enhanced remote sensing imagery synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20448v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Mauro, Francesca De Falco, Lorenzo Papa, Andrea Ceschini, Alessandro Sebastianelli, Paolo Gamba, Massimo Panella, Silvia Ullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High-Dimensional Quantum Blockchain Protocol Based on Time- Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapid advancements in quantum computing and machine learning threaten the long-term security of classical blockchain systems, whose protection mechanisms largely rely on computational difficulties. In this study, we propose a quantum blockchain protocol whose protection mechanism is directly derived from quantum mechanical principles. The protocol combines high-dimensional Bell states, time-entanglement, entanglement switching, and high-dimensional superdense coding. Encoding classical block information into time-delimited qudit states allows block identity and data verification to be implemented through the causal sequencing of quantum measurements instead of cryptographic hash functions. High-dimensional coding increases the information capacity per quantum carrier and improves noise resistance. Time-entanglement provides distributed authentication, non-repudiation, and tamper detection across the blockchain. Each block derives its own public-private key pair directly from the observed quantum correlations by performing high-dimensional Bell state measurements in successive time steps. Because these keys are dependent on the time ordering of measurements, attempts to alter block data or disrupt the protocol's timing structure inevitably affect the reconstructed correlations and are revealed during validation. Recent advances in the creation and detection of high-dimensional time-slice entanglement demonstrate that the necessary quantum resources are compatible with emerging quantum communication platforms. Taken together, these considerations suggest that the proposed framework can be evaluated as a viable and scalable candidate for quantum-secure blockchain architectures in future quantum network environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20489v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Akta\c{s},  Arzu,  Y{\i}lmaz,  \.Ihsan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end Optimization of Single-Shot Quantum Machine Learning for Bayesian Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce an end-to-end optimization strategy for quantum machine learning that directly targets performance under finite measurement resources, where learning objectives are defined directly at the level of task performance. The method is applied on a Bayesian quantum metrology task since it provides a natural testbed with known fundamental limits and scaling with system size. The sampling-aware hybrid algorithm achieves a single-shot risk within 1 dB of the -20 dB Bayesian limit using 32 qubits. We extend the Bayesian framework from parameter estimation to global function inference, where the task is to infer a target function of the sensor input drawn from an arbitrary prior, and we demonstrate a clear computational-sensing advantage for direct functional inference over indirect reconstruction. We relate the corresponding Bayesian risk to the Capacity metric and argue that the Resolvable Expressive Capacity provides a natural measure of the space of functions accessible in a single shot. The resulting eigentask analysis identifies noise-robust feature combinations that yield compact estimators with improved accuracy and reduced optimization cost in resource-limited or real-time on-device settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20492v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodoros Ilias, Fangjun Hu, Marti Vives, Hakan E. T\"ureci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopically distinguishable superposition in infinitely many degrees of freedom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the concept of macroscopically distinguishable superpositions within an infinite array of boson sites. Our approach is rigorous within the frame of Hilbert space theory. In this context, it is natural to differentiate between states -- and corresponding dynamics -- that involve only finitely many degrees of freedom, referred to as local, and those that are inherently nonlocal. Previous studies have shown that such systems can support nonlocal coherent states (NCS). In this work, we demonstrate that NCS can dynamically evolve into nonlocal cat states under the influence of a nonlocal Hamiltonian -- specifically, the square of the total number operator. Crucially, the resulting dynamics cannot be decomposed into local factors. Furthermore, we explore broader mathematical implications of these phenomena within the framework of generalized bosons. Our findings highlight that the concepts of coherent states and nonlocal cat states are not inherently bound together; rather, their fusion is a distinctive feature of standard bosons. Finally, we propose that if the generalized boson framework can be physically realized in engineered quantum systems, the phenomena described here may hold significant relevance for both physics and materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20512v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Fransson, B. C. Sanders, A. P. Sowa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small quantum Tanner codes from left--right Cayley complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Tanner codes are a class of quantum low-density parity-check codes that provably display a linear minimum distance and a constant encoding rate in the asymptotic limit. When built from left--right Cayley complexes, they can be described through a lifting procedure and a base code, which we characterize. We also compute the dimension of quantum Tanner codes when the right degree of the complex is 2. Finally, we perform an extensive search over small groups and identify instances of quantum Tanner codes with parameters $[[144,12,11]]$, $[[432,20,\leq 22]]$ and $[[576,28,\leq 24]]$ for generators of weight 9.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20532v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Leverrier, Wouter Rozendaal, Gilles Z\'emor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On super additivity of Fisher information in fully Gaussian metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Famously, the quantum Fisher information -- the maximum Fisher information over all physical measurements -- is additive for independent copies of a system and the optimal measurement acts locally. We are left to wonder: does the same hold when the set of accessible measurements is constrained? Such constraints are necessary to account for realistic experimental restrictions. Here, we consider a fully Gaussian scenario focusing on only Gaussian measurements. We prove that the optimal Gaussian measurement protocol remains local, if the information is encoded in either the displacement or the covariance matrix. However, when the information is imprinted on both, this no longer holds true: we construct a simple global Gaussian measurement where the Fisher information becomes super additive. These results can improve parameter estimation tasks via feasible tools. Namely, in quantum optical platforms our proposed global operation requires only passive global operations and single mode Gaussian measurements. We demonstrate this in two examples where we estimate squeezing and losses. While in the former case there is a significant gap between the Fisher information of the optimal Gaussian measurement and the quantum Fisher information for a single copy, this gap can be reduced with joint Gaussian measurements and closed in the asymptotic limit of many copies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20534v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Navarro, Simon Morelli, Mikel Sanz, Mohammad Mehboudi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum State Preparation via Schmidt Spectrum Optimisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce an efficient algorithm for the systematic design of shallow-depth quantum circuits capable of preparing many-body quantum states represented as Matrix Product States (MPS). The proposed method leverages Schmidt spectrum optimization (SSO) to minimize circuit depth while preserving the entanglement structure inherent to MPS representations, thereby enabling scalable state preparation on near-term quantum hardware. The core idea is to \textit{disentangle} the target MPS using a sequence of optimised local unitaries, and then reverse this process to obtain a state preparation circuit. Specifically, we define a loss function directly on the Schmidt spectra of intermediate states and use automatic differentiation to optimise each circuit layer so as to systematically reduce entanglement entropy. Once a disentangling sequence has been learned, we take the adjoints of the optimised unitaries to obtain a shallow-depth circuit that approximately reconstructs the target MPS from the computational all-zero state. We benchmark SSO across a range of MPS approximations to the ground states of local Hamiltonians and demonstrate state-of-the-art shallow-depth performance, improving accuracy by up to an order of magnitude over existing methods. Finally, we provide numerical evidence that SSO mitigates the adverse time-complexity scaling observed in previous disentangling-based approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20537v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Green, Joshua Snow, Jingbo B Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental characterization of the Toffoli gate via channel spectrum benchmarking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Channel spectrum benchmarking (CSB) provides a robust framework for characterizing quantum gate fidelities while remaining insensitive to state preparation and measurement (SPAM) errors. Yet, current CSB implementations encounter fundamental challenges when reconstructing noisy eigenvalues, particularly in the presence of spectral degeneracies and off-diagonal noise components in the target gate's eigenbasis. These issues become especially pronounced in the strong noise regime for gates with fidelities around $90\%$. To address these limitations, we introduce an extended CSB model together with a fidelity estimate interval (FEI) -- an interval-valued estimate of the target gate fidelity. Numerical simulation demonstrates that FEI remains sufficiently narrow, with its midpoint reliably approximating the true fidelity. We further validate the protocol on a trapped-ion quantum processor by benchmarking two implementations of the three-qubit Toffoli gate. The results reveal a clear advantage of the qutrit-based implementation over its qubit-based counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20545v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. K. Korliakov, B. I. Bantysh, A. S. Borisenko, I. V. Zalivako, E. O. Kiktenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware-aware and Resource-efficient Circuit Packing and Scheduling on Trapped-Ion Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid expansion of quantum cloud services has led to long job queues due to single-tenant execution models that underutilize hardware resources. Quantum multi-programming (QMP) mitigates this by executing multiple circuits in parallel on a single device, but existing methods target superconducting systems with limited connectivity, high crosstalk, and lower gate fidelity. Trapped-ion architectures, with all-to-all connectivity, long coherence times, and high-fidelity mid-circuit measurement properties, presents itself as a more suitable platform for scalable QMP. We present CircPack, a hardware-aware circuit packing framework designed for modular trapped-ion devices based on the Quantum Charge-Coupled Device (QCCD) architecture. CircPack formulates static circuit scheduling as a two-dimensional packing problem with hardware-specific shuttling constraints. Compared to superconducting-based QMP approaches, CircPack achieves up to 70.72% better fidelity, 62.67% higher utilization, and 32.80% improved layer reduction. This framework is also capable of scalable, balanced scheduling across a cluster of independent QCCD modules, highlighting trapped-ion systems' potential in improving the throughput of quantum cloud computing in the near future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20554v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TQE.2025.3632540</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE TQE, vol. 7, pp. 1-15, 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Palma (Fordham University), Shuwen Kan (Fordham University), Wenqi Wei (Fordham University), Juntao Chen (Fordham University), Kaixun Hua (University of South Florida), Sara Mouradian (University of Washington), Ying Mao (Fordham University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification using quantum kernels in a radial basis function network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radial basis function (RBF) networks are expanded to incorporate quantum kernel functions enabling a new type of hybrid quantum-classical machine learning algorithm. Using this approach, synthetic examples are introduced which allow for proof of concept on interpolation and classification applications. Quantum kernels have primarily been applied to support vector machines (SVMs), however the quantum kernel RBF network offers potential benefit over quantum kernel based SVMs due to the RBF networks ability to perform multi-class classification natively compared to the standard implementation of the SVM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20567v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Micklethwaite, Adam Lowe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Gates from Wolfram Model Multiway Rewriting Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20587v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how representations of finite-dimensional quantum operators can be constructed using nondeterministic rewriting systems. In particular, we investigate Wolfram model multiway rewriting systems based on string substitutions. Multiway systems were proposed by S. Wolfram as generic model systems for multicomputational processes, emphasizing their significance as a foundation for modeling complexity, nondeterminism, and branching structures of measurement outcomes. Here, we investigate a specific class of multiway systems based on cyclic character strings with a neighborhood constraint - the latter called Leibnizian strings. We show that such strings exhibit a Fermi-Dirac distribution for expectation values of occupation numbers of character neighborhoods. A Leibnizian string serves as an abstraction of a $N$-fermion system. A multiway system of these strings encodes causal relations between rewriting events in a nondeterministic manner. The collection of character strings realizes a $\mathbb{Z}$-module with a symmetric $\mathbb{Z}$-bilinear form. For discrete spaces, this generalizes the notion of an inner product over a vector field. This admits a discrete analogue of the path integral and a $S$-matrix for multiway systems of Leibnizian strings. The elements of this $S$-matrix yield transition amplitudes between states of the multiway system based on an action defined over a sequence of Leibnizian strings. We then show that these $S$-matrices give explicit representations of quantum gates for qubits and qudits, and also circuits composed of such gates. We find that, as formal models of nondeterministic computation, rewriting systems of Leibnizian strings with causal structure encode representations of the CNOT, $\pi/8$, and Hadamard gates. Hence, using multiway systems one can represent quantum circuits for qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20587v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Furkan Semih D\"undar, Xerxes D. Arsiwalla, Hatem Elshatlawy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certified Lower Bounds and Efficient Estimation of Minimum Accuracy in Quantum Kernel Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The minimum accuracy heuristic evaluates quantum feature maps without requiring full quantum support vector machine (QSVM) training. However, the original formulation is computationally expensive, restricted to balanced datasets, and lacks theoretical backing. This work generalizes the metric to arbitrary binary datasets and formally proves it constitutes a certified lower bound on the optimal empirical accuracy of any linear classifier in the same feature space. Furthermore, we introduce Monte Carlo strategies to efficiently estimate this bound using a random subset of Pauli directions, accompanied by rigorous probabilistic guarantees. These contributions establish minimum accuracy as a scalable, theoretically sound tool for pre-screening feature maps on near-term quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20588v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Demerson N. Gon\c{c}alves, Tharso D. Fernandes, Andrias M. M. Cordeiro, Pedro H. G. Lugao, Jo\~ao T. Dias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Stinespring superchannel: converting channel queries into dilation isometry queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recently introduced random purification channel, which converts $n$ copies of an arbitrary mixed quantum state into $n$ copies of the same uniformly random purification, has emerged as a powerful tool in quantum information theory. Motivated by this development, we introduce a channel-level analogue, which we call the random Stinespring superchannel. This consists in a procedure to transform $n$ parallel queries of an arbitrary quantum channel into $n$ parallel queries of the same uniformly random Stinespring isometry, via universal encoding and decoding operations that are efficiently implementable. When the channel is promised to have Choi rank at most $r$, the procedure can be tailored to yield a Stinespring environment of dimension $r$. As a consequence, quantum channel learning reduces to isometry learning, yielding a simple channel learning algorithm, based on existing isometry learning protocols, that matches the performance of the two recently proposed channel tomography algorithms. Complementarily, whereas the optimality of these algorithms had previously been established only up to a logarithmic factor in the dimension, we close this gap by removing this logarithmic factor from the lower bound. Taken together, our results fully establish the optimality of these recently introduced channel learning algorithms, showing that the optimal query complexity of learning a quantum channel with input dimension $d_A$, output dimension $d_B$, and Choi rank $r$ is $\Theta(d_A d_B r)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20599v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Girardi, Francesco Anna Mele, Haimeng Zhao, Marco Fanizza, Ludovico Lami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of distinct Discrete Time-Crystalline orders in the Floquet Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the distinct discrete time crystals (DTCs) that emerge in the Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model, subjected to spatially nonuniform periodic driving. Intriguingly, we demonstrate that by appropriately tailoring the drive protocol, distinct DTC orders can be realized in different spatial regions of the system. Consequently, the system exhibits spatially varying sub-harmonic responses with distinct frequencies. We employ a semi-classical analysis to establish the stability of these co-existing DTC orders in the thermodynamic limit. Furthermore, we establish the stability of the stability of these co-existing DTCs in the presence of quantum fluctuations. Our results establish spatially structured driving as a powerful route to engineer novel forms of time-crystalline order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20603v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashank Mishra, Sayan Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-LED-pumped, room-temperature, solid-state maser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Through their ability to achieve `cryogenic' levels of noise performance while operating at room temperature, optically-pumped, solid-state (OPSS) masers show great promise as quantum sensors, oscillators, and amplifiers. We here demonstrate maser oscillation in a microwave cavity containing a crystal of pentacene-doped \textit{para}-terphenyl (ptc:ptp) pumped by a single, chip-scale LED. Here, unlike previous work, the size of the pump source no longer dominates the size of the maser system as a whole. This miniaturization is achieved through invasive optical pumping in the form of a waveguide, the tip of which is embedded into the maser crystal. Combining experimental measurements with ray-tracing analysis, we find that our approach offers at least a factor of 2 enhancement in the cooperativity over end-on optical excitation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20611v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Newns, Shirley Xu, Mingyang Liu, Zike Cheng, Zike Cheng, Ziqiu Huang, Max Attwood, Mark Oxborrow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational (matrix) product states for combinatorial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To compute approximate solutions for combinatorial optimization problems, we describe variational methods based on the product state (PS) and matrix product state (MPS) ansatzes. We perform variational energy minimization with respect to a quantum annealing Hamiltonian and utilize randomness by embedding the approaches in the metaheuristic iterated local search (ILS). The resulting quantum-inspired ILS algorithms are benchmarked on maximum cut problems of up to 50000 variables. We show that they can outperform traditional (M)PS methods, classical ILS, the quantum approximate optimization algorithm and other variational quantum-inspired solvers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20613v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Preisser, Conor Mc Keever, Michael Lubasch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunably realizing flat-bands and exceptional points in kinetically frustrated systems: An example on the non-Hermitian Creutz ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a non-Hermitian extension of the Creutz ladder with generic non-reciprocal hopping. By mapping the ladder onto two decoupled non-Hermitian Su--Schrieffer--Heeger (SSH) chains, we uncover a rich structure in parameter space under different boundary conditions. Under periodic boundary conditions, the spectrum admits a fine-tuned line in parameter space with entirely real eigenvalues, while deviations from this line induce a real--complex spectral transition without crossing exceptional points. In contrast, an exact analytical diagonalization under open boundary conditions reveals extended regions in parameter space with purely real or purely imaginary spectra, separated from complex spectral domains by exceptional lines. The intersections of these exceptional lines define triple-junction points where distinct spectral regimes meet, giving rise to a structured phase diagram that is absent under periodic boundary conditions. We further show that flat bands in this system can occur both as Hermitian diabolical points and as non-Hermitian exceptional points, known as exceptional flat bands, where the dynamics is more stringent than in the Hermitian case, leading to distinct spectral and dynamical signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20614v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debashish Dutta, Sayan Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Onsager's Real Cavity model near solid interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop an extended Onsager real-cavity framework to describe the Casimir-Polder interaction of small molecules dissolved in dielectric liquids near planar interfaces. By analytically resolving the geometry of the cavity opening, we derive a closed expression that arises when the molecule approaches a surface and connects them smoothly to the asymptotic medium-assisted interaction. Using experimentally established dielectric functions for water, propanol, and PTFE together with accurate molecular polarisabilities for O2 and N2, we compute the full distance-dependent potential for four molecule (O2 and N2)-liquid (water and propanol)-surface (PTFE) combinations. The results reveal how local-field screening inside the cavity, molecular polarisability, and liquid permittivity jointly determine the magnitude and shape of the interaction, including the characteristic transition from the open cavity (small separations) and closed cavity (large separations). The framework provides a transparent baseline for dispersion forces in liquids, while highlighting limitations associated with the point-dipole description, the absence of repulsive contributions, and the breakdown of the dipole approximation at ultrashort separations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19714v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Fiedler, Drew F. Parsons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micromagnet-free operation of electron spin qubits in Si/Si$_{1-x}$Ge$_x$ vertical double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19785v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a vertical double quantum dot (DQD) in a Si/Si$_{1-x}$Ge$_x$/Si double-well heterostructure for full electrical control of electron Loss-DiVincenzo (LD) spin qubits, using realistic device modeling and numerical simulations. Due to the emerging spin-orbit interaction in the DQD, as well as strain from the gate electrodes, small (percentage range) but finite $g$ tensor variations emerge. In addition, we find a large valley splitting, on the order of $E_v{\sim}250\,\mu$eV. As a result, multiple avenues for fast electrical single qubit rotations emerge. An ac electric field gives rise to electric dipole spin resonance (EDSR), while electron spin resonance (ESR) in the presence of an ac magnetic field can be electrically controlled by local gates due to varying $g$ factors in DQDs. We also show that shuttling between neighboring dots, in vertical and horizontal direction, results in ultrafast single qubit gates of less than a nanosecond. Remarkably, this DQD architecture completely eliminates the need for micromagnets, significantly facilitating the scalability of LD spin qubits in semiconductor foundries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19785v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhikbrata Sarkar, Daniel Loss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preparation of a Quantum Spin Liquid in Non-Hermitian Quantum Dimer Models and Rydberg Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We identify an unconventional form of the non-Hermitian skin effect that occurs not in position space but in many-body Fock space, which we call the Fock space skin effect (FSSE). Using quantum dimer models, we characterize FSSE analytically and numerically, and propose a concrete route toward its realization in Rydberg atom arrays. The dimer constraint is enforced through Rydberg gadgets employing the blockade mechanism, while directional reservoirs generate non-Hermitian flipping amplitudes. We show that FSSE enables the preparation of gapped spin liquid states, and in particular, we demonstrate how a Rydberg geometry realizing a square lattice quantum dimer model with next-nearest neighbor dimers can be driven by non-Hermiticity into an exact spin liquid ground state. Our results establish Fock-space non-Hermiticity as a powerful principle for engineering exotic quantum phases and dynamical state-preparation protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19809v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashwat Chakraborty, Taylor L. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relation between classical and quantum Lyapunov exponent and the bound on chaos in classically chaotic quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Out-of-Time-Ordered Commutators (OTOCs), representing a key diagnostic for scrambling as a facet of short-time quantum chaos, have attracted wide-ranging interest, from many-body physics to quantum gravity. By means of a suitable form of the Wigner-Moyal expansion, and invoking ensemble equivalence in statistical physics, we provide a consistent approach to the growth rate of the OTOC for many-body systems with chaotic classical limit where both the classical Lyapunov exponent and the quantum nature of the density of states enter. Applying this construction to quantized high-dimensional hyperbolic motion, i.e., a quantum chaotic system that exhibits gravity-like correlation functions in the late-time regime, we compute the OTOC growth rate $\Lambda$ as a function of the number of degrees of freedom, $f$, and inverse temperature, $\beta$.
  We show that the scaled growth rate, $\Lambda/f$, can be described by a universal function of $f \beta$ and displays a cross-over from classical to quantum behavior as we increase $f$ and/or lower the temperature. In the deep quantum regime of infinite $f$, we find maximally fast scrambling in the sense of the Maldacena-Shenker-Stanford bound on chaos. This elucidates the non-perturbative mechanism underlying the saturation of the bound via quantum contributions to the mean density of states, and it provides further support for this dynamical system as a dual to two-dimensional quantum gravity. In this way, we present first evidence of maximally fast scrambling in a quantum chaotic system with a well-defined classical Hamiltonian limit, without invoking any external mechanism such as (disorder) averaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19869v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Haneder, Gerrit Caspari, Juan Diego Urbina, Klaus Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement cohomology for GHZ and W states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Entanglement cohomology assigns a graded cohomology ring to a multipartite pure state, providing homological invariants that are stable under local unitaries and characterize inequivalent patterns of entanglement. In this work we derive exact expressions for the dimensions of these cohomology groups in two canonical entanglement classes, generalized GHZ and W states on an arbitrary number of parties and local Hilbert space dimensions, thus proving conjectures of arXiv:1901.02011. Using the additional structure of the Hodge star and wedge product operations, we propose two new classes of local unitary invariants: the spectrum of the natural Laplacian acting on entanglement $k$-forms, and the intersection numbers obtained from wedge products of representatives for cohomology classes. We present numerical experiments which investigate these invariants in particular states, suggesting that they may provide useful quantities for describing multipartite entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19889v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ferko, Keiichiro Furuya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Learning of Lattice Gauge Theories with Fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19891v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a learning method for recovering action parameters in lattice field theories. Our method is based on the minimization of a convex loss function constructed using the Schwinger-Dyson relations. We show that score matching, a popular learning method, is a special case of our construction of an infinite family of valid loss functions. Importantly, our general Schwinger-Dyson-based construction applies to gauge theories and models with Grassmann-valued fields used to represent dynamical fermions. In particular, we extend our method to realistic lattice field theories including quantum chromodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19891v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Shukla, Yukari Yamauchi, Andrey Y. Lokhov, Scott Lawrence, Abhijith Jayakumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to monitored quantum systems and quantum trajectories: spectrum, typicality, and phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19922v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thanks to recent experimental advances in simulating and detecting quantum dynamics with high precision and controllability, our understanding of the physics of monitored quantum systems has considerably deepened over the past decades. In this article, we provide an introductory theoretical review on the basic formalisms governing open quantum dynamics under measurement, along with recent developments in their spectral and typical aspects. After reviewing quantum measurement theory, we introduce the concept of quantum trajectories, which are the conditional dynamics of monitored states shaped by a set of measurement outcomes. We then discuss the spectral properties of the dynamical map describing the evolution averaged over measurement outcomes. As has recently been recognized, these spectral features are intimately connected to whether quantum trajectories exhibit typical behaviors, such as the ergodicity and purification. Moreover, we introduce Lyapunov exponents of typical quantum trajectories and discuss how these quantities serve as indicators of measurement-induced phase transitions in monitored quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19922v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryusuke Hamazaki, Ken Mochizuki, Hisanori Oshima, Yohei Fuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian Exceptional Topology on a Klein Bottle Photonic Circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian physics has unlocked a wealth of unconventional wave phenomena beyond the reach of Hermitian systems, with exceptional points (EPs) driving enhanced sensitivity, nonreciprocal transport, and topological behavior unique to non-Hermitian degeneracies. Here, we present a scalable and reconfigurable silicon photonic integrated circuit capable of emulating arbitrary non-Hermitian time evolution with high precision. Using this programmable platform, we implement a two-band non-Hermitian Hamiltonian defined on a Klein-bottle topology a nonorientable parameter space that enables exceptional phases forbidden on orientable manifolds. Through an on-chip amplitude-and-phase reconstruction protocol, we retrieve the full complex Hamiltonian at multiple points in parameter space and experimentally map the associated Fermi arc where the imaginary eigenvalue gap closes. The orientation of the measured Fermi arc reveals a nontrivial exceptional topology: it implies the presence of same-charge EPs (or an EP monopole) that cannot annihilate locally on the Klein bottle. Our results demonstrate the first photonic realization of exceptional topology on a nonorientable manifold and establish a versatile platform for exploring exotic non-Hermitian and topological models relevant to classical and quantum photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20273v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze-Sheng Xu, J. Lukas K. K\"onig, Andrea Cataldo, Rohan Yadgirkar, Govind Krishna, Venkatesh Deenadayalan, Val Zwiller, Stefan Preble, Emil J. Bergholtz, Jun Gao, Ali W. Elshaari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-Temperature Thermally-Assisted-Occupation Density Functional Theory, Ab Initio Molecular Dynamics, and Quantum Mechanics/Molecular Mechanics Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20313v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, thermally-assisted-occupation density functional theory (TAO-DFT) [J.-D. Chai, J. Chem. Phys. 136, 154104 (2012)] has been demonstrated to be an efficient and accurate electronic structure method for studying the ground-state properties of large multi-reference (MR) systems at absolute zero. To explore the thermal equilibrium properties of large MR systems at finite electronic temperatures, in the present work, we propose the finite-temperature (FT) extension of TAO-DFT, denoted as FT-TAO-DFT. Besides, to unlock the dynamical information of large MR systems at finite temperatures, FT-TAO-DFT is combined with ab initio molecular dynamics, leading to FT-TAO-AIMD. In addition, we also develop FT-TAO-DFT-based quantum mechanics/molecular mechanics (QM/MM), denoted as FT-TAO-QM/MM, to provide a cost-effective description of the thermal equilibrium properties of a QM subsystem with MR character embedded in an MM environment at finite temperatures. Moreover, the FT-TAO-DFT, FT-TAO-AIMD, and FT-TAO-QM/MM methods are employed to explore the radical nature and infrared (IR) spectra of n-acenes (n = 2--6), consisting of n linearly fused benzene rings, in vacuum and in an argon (Ar) matrix at finite temperatures. According to our calculations, for n-acenes at 1000 K or below, the electronic temperature effects on the radical nature and IR spectra are very minor, while the nuclear temperature effects on these properties are noticeable. For n-acene in an Ar matrx at absolute zero, the Ar matrix has minimal impact on the radical nature of n-acene, while the co-deposition procedure of n-acene and Ar atoms may affect the IR spectrum of n-acene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20313v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaozhi Li, Jeng-Da Chai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical Drive of a Josephson Junction Array using a Cryogenic BiCMOS Pulse Pattern Generator: Towards a Fully Integrated Josephson Arbitrary Waveform Synthesizer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We combine a cryogenic BiCMOS integrated circuit, which generates high-speed return-to-zero (RTZ) pulses, with a superconducting Josephson junction array. The BiCMOS circuit acts as a cryogenic pulse pattern generator, delivering data rates of 30 Gb/s, while consuming 302 mW at 4 K. Each electrical pulse of the serializer effectively transfers one magnetic flux quantum through every Josephson junction, so that the average output voltage of the array produces well-defined plateaus (Shapiro steps) in its current-to-voltage characteristic. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first integration of a Josephson junction array with a cryogenic BiCMOS chip. The presented results pave the way toward a hybrid and fully integrated Josephson arbitrary waveform synthesizer (JAWS) that can generate ultra-low-noise signals for quantum voltage metrology and quantum information systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20367v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yerzhan Kudabay, Oliver Kieler, Michael Starkloff, Marco Schubert, Michael Haas, Johannes Kohlmann, Mark Bieler, Vadim Issakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological resolution of conical intersection seams and the coupled cluster bifurcation via mixed Hodge modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20414v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rigorous description of Conical Intersections (CIs) remains the central challenge of non-adiabatic quantum chemistry. While the ``Yarkony Seam'' -- the $(3N-8)$-dimensional manifold of degeneracy -- is well-understood geometrically, its accurate characterization by high-level electronic structure methods is plagued by numerical instabilities. Specifically, standard Coupled Cluster (CC) theory suffers from root bifurcations near Ground State CIs, rendering the ``Gold Standard'' of chemistry inapplicable where it is needed most. Here, we present \textbf{QuMorpheus}, an open-source computational package that resolves these singularities by implementing a topological framework based on Dissipative Mixed Hodge Modules (DMHM) [P. Saurabh, arXiv:2512.19487 (2025)]. By algorithmically mapping the CC polynomial equations to a spectral sheaf, we compute the exact Monodromy ($\mu$) invariants of the intersection. We demonstrate that this automated algebraic geometry approach correctly identifies the physical ground state topology in the K\"{o}hn-Tajti model and resolves the intersection seams of realistic chemical systems, including Ethylene and the Chloronium ion ($\mathrm{H_2Cl^+}$). Furthermore, we apply QuMorpheus to the photoisomerization of Previtamin D, proving that the experimentally observed Woodward-Hoffmann selection rules are a direct consequence of a topological ``Monodromy Wall'' ($\mu=1, \gamma=\pi$) rather than purely energetic barriers. This establishes a general software solution to the ``Yarkony Problem,'' enabling the robust, automated mapping of global intersection seams in complex molecular systems. The topological stability of these intersections allows for the control protocols discussed in Ref.[P. Saurabh, Submitted to Phys. Rev. X (2025)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20414v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prasoon Saurabh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Run and Tumble Dynamics of Biased Quantum Trajectories in a Monitored Qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the active stochastic dynamics of a qubit subjected to continuous measurement and conditional feedback. The stochastic equation governing the state vector trajectory of the qubit can be mapped, in the high-diffusion limit, to the dynamics of a classical persistent Run-and-Tumble Particle (p-RTP) in a bounded one-dimensional domain. The mapping enables us to use analytical results from classical active matter to derive an approximate non-equilibrium steady-state (NESS) distribution for the monitored quantum system. The competition between the coherent Rabi drive and the measurement-induced feedback leads to a rich NESS phase displaying Zeno--anti-Zeno transition--which is statistically equivalent to the propulsion-induced trapping observed in confined active particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Kundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R\'enyi-like entanglement probe of the chiral central charge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a ground state entanglement probe for gapped, two-dimensional quantum many-body systems that involves taking powers of reduced density matrices in a particular geometric configuration. This quantity, which we denote by $\omega_{\alpha,\beta}$, is parameterized by two positive real numbers $\alpha, \beta$, and can be seen as a ``R\'enyi-like" generalization of the modular commutator -- another entanglement probe proposed as a way to compute the chiral central charge from a bulk wave function. We obtain analytic expressions for $\omega_{\alpha,\beta}$ for gapped ground states of non-interacting fermion Hamiltonians as well as ground states of string-net models. In both cases, we find that $\omega_{\alpha,\beta}$ takes a universal value related to the chiral central charge. For integer values of $\alpha$ and $\beta$, our quantity $\omega_{\alpha,\beta}$ can be expressed as an expectation value of permutation operators acting on an appropriate replica system, providing a natural route to measuring $\omega_{\alpha,\beta}$ in numerical simulations and potentially, experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20608v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Gass, Michael Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipartite entanglement classes of a multiport beam-splitter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02619v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The states generated by a multiport beam-splitter usually display genuine multipartite entanglement between the many spatial modes. Here we investigate the different classes of multipartite entangled states that arise in this practical situation, working within the paradigm of Stochastic Local Operations with Classical Communication. We highlight three scenarios, one where the multipartite entanglement classes follow a total number hierarchy, another where the various classes follow a nonclassicality degree hierarchy and a third one that is a combination of the previous two. Moreover, the multipartite entanglement of higher-dimensional versions of Dicke states relate naturally to our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02619v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.022409</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review A 110 (2), 022409 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. E. S. Steinhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing Quantum Processor for the Analysis of Strongly Correlated Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02509v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study introduces a systematic approach for analyzing strongly correlated systems by adapting the conventional quantum cluster method to a quantum circuit model. We have developed a more concise formula for calculating the cluster's Green's function, requiring only real-number computations on the quantum circuit instead of complex ones. This approach is inherently more suited to quantum circuits, which primarily yield statistical probabilities. As an illustrative example, we explored the Hubbard model on a 2D lattice. The ground state is determined utilizing Xiaohong, a superconducting quantum processor equipped with 66 qubits, supplied by QuantumCTek Co., Ltd. Subsequently, we employed the circuit model to compute the real-time retarded Green's function for the cluster, which is then used to determine the lattice Green's function. We conducted an examination of the band structure in the insulator phase of the lattice system. This preliminary investigation lays the groundwork for exploring a wealth of innovative physics within the field of condensed matter physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02509v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ad770b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Scr. 99 105117 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hengyue Li, Yusheng Yang, Pin Lv, Jinglong Qu, Zhe-Hui Wang, Jian Sun, Shenggang Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Circuit-Based Quantum State Tomography via Sparse Entry Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many quantum states arising in algorithms and physical systems occupy only a small, structured subset of the exponentially large Hilbert space, yet standard quantum state tomography fails to exploit this structure. We present an efficient circuit-based tomography framework for pure quantum states that are sparse in a computational basis. For an $n$-qubit state supported on $k$ basis elements, the protocol reconstructs all amplitudes using $1 + 2(k-1)$ measurement settings. The method admits both entanglement-assisted and entanglement-free implementations, enabling explicit tradeoffs between two-qubit gate usage and statistical noise. We derive bounds on the required number of CNOT gates from the combinatorial structure of the state support and analyze their effect on reconstruction infidelity. The framework extends naturally to closed-system process tomography and is validated via numerical simulations using Qiskit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20298v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi-Kwong Li, Kevin Yipu Wu, Zherui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic relaxation in quantum Markovian dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14313v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the long-time behavior of quantum Markovian dynamics generated by time-dependent Gorini-Kossakowski-Lindblad-Sudarshan (GKLS) master equations. We introduce a notion of weak relaxation and derive sufficient conditions guaranteeing asymptotic independence from the initial state. Our results provide a quantitative extension of the Spohn-Frigerio theorem to time-dependent generators, yielding explicit contraction bounds in terms of the instantaneous steady state and time-integrated dissipation rates. For a class of microscopically derived master equations, we further obtain a graph-theoretic characterization of the aforementioned conditions that directly links the structure of the jump operators to the relaxation properties. The general theory is illustrated by applications to driven finite-level systems, including a detailed three-level example, and is extended to a non-Markovian setting by means of time-local master equations that become of GKLS form at long times. These findings pave the way for the development of a more general theory of relaxation beyond the Markovian case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14313v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Di Meglio, Dariusz Chru\'sci\'nski, Koenraad Audenaert, Martin B. Plenio, Susana F. Huelga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model using time-dependent disorder in optical cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17802v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Sachdev--Ye--Kitaev (SYK) model is a paradigm for extreme quantum chaos, non-Fermi-liquid behavior, and holographic matter. Yet, the dense random all-to-all interactions that characterize it are an extreme challenge for realistic laboratory realizations. Here, we propose a general scheme for densifying the coupling distribution of random disorder Hamiltonians, using a Trotterized cycling through sparse time-dependent disorder realizations. To diagnose the convergence of sparse to dense models, we introduce an information-theory inspired diagnostic. We illustrate how the scheme can come to bear in the realization of the complex SYK$_4$ model in cQED platforms with available experimental resources, using a single cavity mode together with a fast cycling through independent speckle patterns. The simulation scheme applies to the SYK class of models as well as spin glasses, spin liquids, and related disorder models, bringing them into reach of quantum simulation using single-mode cavity-QED setups and other platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17802v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahel Baumgartner, Pietro Pelliconi, Soumik Bandyopadhyay, Francesca Orsi, Nick Sauerwein, Philipp Hauke, Jean-Philippe Brantut, Julian Sonner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Encoding of Structured Data with Matrix Product States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16464v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The amplitude encoding of an arbitrary $n$-qubit state vector requires $\Omega(2^n)$ gate operations, owing to the exponential dimension of the Hilbert space. We can, however, form dimensionality-reduced representations of quantum states using matrix product states (MPS). In this article, we illustrate that MPS techniques enable the preparation of quantum states representative of functions with complexity up to low-degree piecewise polynomials via shallow-depth quantum circuits with accuracy exceeding 99.99\%. We extend these results to the approximate amplitude encoding of pixel values. We showcase this approach by efficiently preparing a $128\times 128$ ChestMNIST medical image (https://medmnist.com/) on 14 qubits with fidelity exceeding 99.2\% on a circuit with a total depth of just 425 single-qubit rotation and CNOT gates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16464v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Green, Jingbo B Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization-dependent topology in quantum emitter chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14770v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The role of polarization in the topology of quantum emitter chains is investigated theoretically, whereby "polarization" refers to the transition dipole moments of the emitters. We show that, if the chain is zigzag-shaped, different topological phases can be realized by adjusting the polarization direction. It turns out that long-range dipole-dipole couplings weaken the bulk-boundary correspondence, but on the other hand give rise to higher-order topological phases with four observable edge modes. We also demonstrate how the polarization orientation can be used to define an additional dimension and simulate a synthetic Chern insulator. Our findings open up a way to actively switch between various topological phases within a single arrangement of quantum emitters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14770v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3t6s-fnsq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, L032069 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sturm, Adriana P\'alffy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-enabled optical large-baseline interferometry: applications, protocols and feasibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04765v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optical Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) offers the potential for unprecedented angular resolution in both astronomical imaging and precision measurements. Classical approaches, however, face significant limitations due to photon loss, background noise, and the requirements for dynamical delay lines over large distances. This document surveys recent developments in quantum-enabled VLBI, which aim to address these challenges using entanglement-assisted protocols, quantum memory storage, and nonlocal measurement techniques. While its application to astronomy is well known, we also examine how these techniques may be extended to geodesy -- specifically, the monitoring of Earth's rotation. Particular attention is given to quantum-enhanced telescope architectures, including repeater-based long baseline interferometry and quantum error-corrected encoding schemes, which offer a pathway toward high-fidelity optical VLBI. To aid the discussion, we also compare specifications for key enabling technologies to current state-of-the-art experimental components, including switching rates, gate times, entanglement distribution rates, and memory lifetimes. By integrating quantum technologies, future interferometric networks may achieve diffraction-limited imaging at optical and near-infrared wavelengths, surpassing the constraints of classical techniques and enabling new precision tests of astrophysical and fundamental physics phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04765v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/23746149.2025.2597311</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Physics: X, 11(1), 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zixin Huang, Oleg Titov, Mikolaj K. Schmidt, Benjamin Pope, Gavin K. Brennen, Daniel Oi, Pieter Kok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the excitability of two-level atoms by spectrally encoded single-photon wave packets in quantum networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17482v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the time-dependent interaction between a two-level atom and a spectrally encoded single-photon wave packet using the Heisenberg-Langevin equations and derive the atomic excitation probability. Spectral phase encoding broadens the photon wave packet in the time domain and reduces its peak intensity, leading to markedly weaker atomic excitation than for an unencoded photon. We formalize this behavior via an overlap bound with the time-reversed spontaneous emission mode and show how excitation depends on code length, bandwidth, and phase errors. Interpreted at the quantum network level, atoms behave as phase-sensitive, and mode-selective receivers whose response scales with a spectral-overlap functional that captures decoding fidelity, detuning, and multiuser interference. From this, we extract design rules and performance bounds for encoded links, quantifying trade-offs among code length, addressability, cross-talk, and identifying tolerances for decoding error. These results clarify how spectrally encoded photons couple to quantum nodes and provide guidelines for efficient, scalable, and secure quantum networking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17482v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamid Reza Naeij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation and representation of qudit multi-controlled unitaries and hypergraph states by N-body angular momentum couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21831v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a representation of qudit multi-controlled unitary operators in terms of N-body angular momentum interactions. The representation is particularly convenient for odd-dimensional systems, with interesting connections to the Pegg-Barnett phase formalism. We illustrate the main points in the special case of qutrits, where simplifications and connections to dipole-quadrupole and quadrupole-quadrupole interactions can be established. We describe the representation of the closely related set of qudit hypergraph states, identifying possible realizations and their main obstacles. Qutrit tripartite controlled unitaries are decomposed in terms of more familiar two-body angular momentum couplings, enabling their implementation in a variety of physical systems. We give then a concrete example of implementation of qutrit unitaries and hypergraph states in optical systems that employs single-photon sources, two-mode cross-Kerr interactions and linear optical operations. Moreover, we define a new set of states, called angular momentum hypergraph states, which are more directly related to the angular momentum representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21831v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. E. S. Steinhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nontrivial local observables and impermeable and permeable boundary conditions for 1D KFGM particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17225v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Real solutions of the 1D Klein-Fock-Gordon (KFG) equation automatically cancel out the usual two-vector current density; consequently, the respective continuity equation is trivially satisfied, and a globally conserved quantity cannot be obtained. Additionally, distinguishing between impermeable and permeable boundary conditions (BCs) at a given point is not possible. We address these first-quantized conflicts by using the simplest nontrivial local observables, i.e., an energy density and an energy current density, which allows us to characterize a strictly neutral 1D KFG particle, i.e., a 1D KFG-Majorana (KFGM) particle, when it is confined to an interval and when it is restricted, e.g., in an interval with transparent walls. All the BCs for this system are extracted from the pseudo self-adjointness of the Feshbach-Villars (FV) Hamiltonian plus two Majorana conditions. We show that these energy densities are components of an unusual energy-momentum tensor and can satisfy a continuity equation, leading to a conserved quantity for all available BCs. Moreover, the energy current density can characterize all the BCs as either impermeable or permeable. In contrast, the commonly used energy current density -- a component of the usual energy-momentum tensor -- cannot characterize all the BCs. Additionally, this quantity and its respective energy density -- another component of the usual energy-momentum tensor -- may not lead to a conserved quantity. We also obtain the BCs for which the abovementioned densities and those commonly used are equally satisfactory. In fact, this occurs only for four impermeable BCs and a one-parameter set of permeable BCs. Our results highlight the important role played by the BCs when they are imposed on a system in which particles occupy a finite region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17225v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Techapon Kampu, Salvatore De Vincenzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity realisation of CNOT gate in Majorana-based optical platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14641v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the experimental realisation of a robust CNOT quantum gate using Majorana zero modes simulated on a photonic platform. Three Kitaev chains supporting Majorana zero modes at their endpoints are used to encode two logical qubits, and both intra-chain and inter-chain braiding operations are performed to implement the CNOT gate. While the topological encoding of quantum information in Majorana fermions does not offer full topological protection in our non-interacting photonic setting, it nevertheless exhibits a natural resilience to the dominant noise and decoherence effects present in the experiment. Consequently, the fidelity of the CNOT gate is significantly enhanced, surpassing 0.992 and addressing a key limitation in the path toward scalable quantum computation. These results represent a major advancement in topological quantum computing with Majorana fermions and underscore the potential of photonic platforms for realising high-fidelity quantum gates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14641v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Kun Li, Kai Sun, Ze-Yan Hao, Jia-He Liang, Jiannis K. Pachos, Lucy Byles, Jin-Shi Xu, Yong-Jian Han, Chuan-Feng Li, Guang-Can Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge-of-chaos enhanced quantum-inspired algorithm for combinatorial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17655v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear dynamical systems with continuous variables can be used for solving combinatorial optimization problems with discrete variables. Numerical simulations of them are also useful as heuristic algorithms with a desirable property, namely, parallelizability, which allows us to execute them in a massively parallel manner, leading to ultrafast performance. However, the dynamical-system approaches with continuous variables are usually less accurate than conventional approaches with discrete variables such as simulated annealing. To improve the solution accuracy of a quantum-inspired algorithm called simulated bifurcation (SB), which was found from classical simulation of a quantum nonlinear oscillator network exhibiting quantum bifurcation, here we generalize it by introducing nonlinear control of individual bifurcation parameters and show that the generalized SB (GSB) can achieve surprisingly high performance, namely, almost 100% success probabilities for some large-scale problems. As a result, the time to solution for a 2,000-variable problem is shortened to 10 ms by a GSB-based machine, which is two orders of magnitude shorter than the best known value, 1.3 s, previously obtained by an SB-based machine. To examine the reason for the ultrahigh performance, we investigated chaos in the GSB changing the nonlinear-control strength and found that the dramatic increase of success probabilities happens near the edge of chaos. That is, the GSB can find a solution with high probability by harnessing the edge of chaos. This finding suggests that dynamical-system approaches to combinatorial optimization will be enhanced by harnessing the edge of chaos, opening a broad possibility to tackle intractable combinatorial optimization problems by physics-inspired approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17655v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayato Goto, Ryo Hidaka, Kosuke Tatsumura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace Variational Quantum Simulation: Fidelity Lower Bounds as Measures of Training Success</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06360v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an iterative variational quantum algorithm to simulate the time evolution of arbitrary initial states within a given subspace. The algorithm compresses the Trotter circuit into a shorter-depth parameterized circuit, which is optimized simultaneously over multiple initial states in a single training process using fidelity-based cost functions. After the whole training procedure, we provide an efficiently computable lower bound on the fidelities for arbitrary states within the subspace, which guarantees the performance of the algorithm in the worst-case training scenario. We also show our cost function exhibits a barren-plateau-free region near the initial parameters at each iteration in the training landscape. The experimental demonstration of the algorithm is presented through the simulation of a 2-qubit Ising model on an IBMQ processor. As a demonstration for a larger system, a simulation of a 10-qubit Ising model is also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06360v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung Park, Dongkeun Lee, Jeongho Bang, Hoon Ryu, Kyunghyun Baek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empty-Signal Detection: Overcoming the Fundamental QBER Limit in Repeaterless Quantum Communication in Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The distance of practical repeaterless quantum communication (PRQC) has long been theoretically limited by the fundamental quantum bit error rate (QBER) induced by vacuum signals and single-photon detector (SPD) dark counts. As the communication distance increases, the channel transmission rate decays exponentially, causing vacuum-induced dark counts to dominate detection events and drive the QBER toward 50%, thereby rendering PRQC infeasible. To address this fundamental limitation, we introduce an empty-signal detection (ESD) paradigm that provides a rigorous theoretical framework for overcoming the fundamental distance limit of PRQC. By encoding particle-existence information (PEI) onto auxiliary degrees of freedom (DOF) and employing controlled operations together with multi-copy analysis, the ESD module enables vacuum events to be reliably identified and discarded without disturbing the transmitted quantum state. This stabilizes the non-empty signal rate (NESR) at a high, distance-independent value and suppresses the fundamental QBER to a sufficiently low level, irrespective of the channel transmission rate. Consequently, PRQC can, in principle, be extended to arbitrarily long distances, limited only by efficiency considerations rather than by intrinsic feasibility constraints imposed by fundamental QBER. Despite ESD requiring further integration of quantum technologies and PRQC remaining speed-limited in practice, this work establishes the first rigorous theoretical framework that, in principle, overcomes the fundamental QBER limitation in PRQC, thereby clarifying its ultimate feasibility over arbitrarily long distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15884v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Shu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Quantum Genetic Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15059v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum Genetic Algorithms (QGAs) are an emerging field of multivariate quantum optimization that emulate Darwinian evolution and natural selection, with vast applications in chemistry and engineering. The appropriate application of fitness functions and fitness selection are the problem-encoding step and the slowest step in designing QGAs for specific physical applications. In this paper, we provide a comprehensive review of these crucial steps. Our survey maps cases of quantum advantage, classifies and illustrates QGAs and their subroutines, and discusses the two main physical problems tackled by QGAs: potential energy minimization of particles on a sphere, and molecular eigensolving. We conclude that the encoding used by the Thomson problem is a decisive step toward the use of QGAs in a variety of physical applications, while Grover's search as a selection step in Reduced QGAs is the main driver of quantum speedup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15059v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Lima, Rakesh Saini, Saif Al-Kuwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure, Optimality, and Symmetry in Shadow Unitary Inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24880v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reversing unitary operations is a key task in quantum computing and quantum control. In this work, we introduce and develop the framework of shadow unitary inversion, a relaxed variant of unitary inversion in which the goal is to reproduce the action of the inverse unitary only at the level of the expectation value of a fixed observable. This task captures an operational setting in which only shadow information is required and allows query complexities significantly below those of full unitary inversion. We establish a dimension-dependent lower bound showing that any $t$-query scheme requires $t$ to scale at least linearly with the system dimension, with the constant determined by the spectral properties of the target observable. In the qubit case, we construct a deterministic three-query sequential protocol that achieves exact shadow inversion, and we provide a complete characterization of all admissible qubit channels satisfying the shadow constraint. Numerical evidence suggests that three queries are optimal. For higher-dimensional systems, we develop a semidefinite-programming formulation for optimizing shadow-inversion combs and introduce a representation-theoretic symmetry reduction that decomposes the problem into invariant blocks, substantially reducing the problem size. These results provide the first systematic study for shadow unitary inversion and establish its resource requirements and symmetry structure across dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24880v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guocheng Zhen, Yu-Ao Chen, Mingrui Jing, Jingu Xie, Ranyiliu Chen, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic and Universal Frequency-Bin Gate for High-Dimensional Quantum Technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06191v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-dimensional photonic systems access large Hilbert spaces for quantum information processing. They offer proven advantages in quantum computation, communication, and sensing. However, implementing scalable, low-loss unitary gates across many modes remains a central challenge. Here we propose a deterministic, universal, and fully programmable high-dimensional quantum gate based on a cavity-assisted sum-frequency-generation process, achieving near-unity fidelity. The device implements an M-by-N truncated unitary transformation (with 1 &lt;= M &lt; N), or a full unitary when M = N, on frequency-bin modes. With current technology, the attainable dimensionality reaches M-by-N on the order of ten to the power of four, with N up to about one thousand, and can be further increased using multiple pulse shapers. Combined with compatible SPDC sources, high-efficiency detection, and fast feed-forward, this approach provides a scalable, fiber-compatible platform for high-dimensional frequency-bin quantum processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06191v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Non-Markovianity in Logical Qubit Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08893v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Logical qubits encoded in quantum error correcting codes can exhibit non-Markovian dynamical evolution, even when the underlying physical noise is Markovian. To understand this emergent non-Markovianity, we define a Markovianity condition appropriate to logical gate operations, and study it by relating logical operations to their physical implementation (operations on the data qubits into which the logical qubit is encoded). We apply our analysis to small quantum codes, and show that they exhibit non-Markovian dynamics even for very simple physical noise models. We show that non-Markovianity can emerge from Markovian physical operations if (and only if) the physical qubits are not necessarily returned to the code subspace after every round of QEC. In this situation, the syndrome qubits can act as a memory, mediating time correlations and enabling violation of the Markov condition. We quantify the emergent non-Markovianity in simple examples, and propose sufficient conditions for reliable use of gate-based characterization techniques like gate set tomography in early fault-tolerant quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08893v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jalan A. Ziyad, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kenneth Rudinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric quantum thermodynamics: A fibre bundle approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14383v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Classical thermodynamics is a theory based on coarse-graining, meaning that the thermodynamic variables arise from discarding information related to the microscopic features of the system at hand. In quantum mechanics, however, where one has a high degree of control over microscopic systems, information theory plays an important role in describing the thermal properties of quantum systems. Recently, a new approach has been proposed in the form of a quantum thermodynamic gauge theory, where the notion of redundant information arises from a group of physically motivated gauge transformations called the thermodynamic group. In this work, we explore the geometrical structure of quantum thermodynamics. Particularly, we do so by explicitly constructing the relevant principal fibre bundle. We then show that there are two distinct (albeit related) geometric structures associated with the gauge theory of quantum thermodynamics. In this way, we express thermodynamics in the same mathematical (geometric) language as the fundamental theories of physics. Finally, we discuss how the geometric and topological properties of these structures may help explain fundamental properties of thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14383v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Pernambuco, L. C. C\'eleri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Bluestein's Algorithm for Arbitrary-Size Quantum Fourier Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.15349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a quantum analogue of Bluestein's algorithm (QBA) that implements an exact $N$-point Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) for arbitrary $N$. Our construction factors the $N$-dimensional QFT unitary into three diagonal quadratic-phase gates and two standard radix-2 QFT subcircuits of size $M = 2^m$ (with $M \ge 2N - 1$). This achieves asymptotic gate complexity $O((\log N)^2)$ and uses $O(\log N)$ qubits, matching the performance of a power-of-two QFT on $m$ qubits while avoiding the need to embed into a larger Hilbert space. We validate the correctness of the algorithm through a concrete implementation in Qiskit and classical simulation, confirming that QBA produces the exact $N$-point discrete Fourier transform on arbitrary-length inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.15349v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan-Hong Kuo, Renata Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prefix Sums via Kronecker Products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16309v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we revisit prefix sums through the lens of linear algebra. We describe an identity that decomposes triangular all-ones matrices as a sum of two Kronecker products, and apply it to design recursive prefix sum algorithms and circuits. Notably, the proposed family of circuits is the first one that achieves the following three properties simultaneously: (i) zero-deficiency, (ii) constant fan-out per-level, and (iii) depth that is asymptotically strictly smaller than $2\log(n)$ for input length $n$. As an application, we show how to use these circuits to design quantum adders with $1.893\log(n)+O(1)$ Toffoli depth, $O(n)$ Toffoli gates, and $O(n)$ additional qubits, improving the Toffoli depth and/or Toffoli size of existing constructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16309v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandros Sobczyk, Anastasios Zouzias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of Quantum Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16775v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the traditional ways of introducing bosons and fermions is through creation-annihilation algebras. Historically, these have been associated with emission and absorption processes at the quantum level and are characteristic of the language of second quantization. In this work, we formulate the transition from first to second quantization by taking quotients of the state spaces of distinguishable particles, so that the resulting equivalence classes identify states that contain no information capable of distinguishing between particles, thereby generalising the usual symmetrisation procedure. Assuming that the resulting indistinguishable-particle space (i) admits an ordered basis compatible with how an observer may label the accessible modes, (ii) is invariant under unitary transformations of those modes, and (iii) supports particle counting as a mode-wise local operation, we derive a new class of creation-annihilation algebras. These algebras reproduce the partition functions of transtatistics, the maximal generalisations of bosons and fermions consistent with these operational principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16775v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\'as Medina S\'anchez, Borivoje Daki\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timelike transitions in an atom by a mirror in light cone and Kruskal-Szekeres regions: a status of quantum equivalence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12378v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the timelike transitions in a two-level atom in the presence of an infinite reflecting mirror in the future-past light cone regions of a Minkowski spacetime, as well as in the region interior of a $(1+1)$ dimensional Schwarzschild black hole. In particular, when considering the light cone regions, two specific scenarios are dealt with -- $(i)$ a mirror is static in Minkowski spacetime while the atom is attached to a frame confined inside the future light cone region, $(ii)$ an atom is static in Minkowski spacetime, and the mirror is confined inside the future light cone region. For both situations, the atom is interacting with field modes defined in the mirror's frame. Analogous configurations are considered in the black hole spacetime: in one case, the mirror carries field modes represented by the Kruskal time, while the atom follows the Schwarzschild time defined inside the black hole; in the other case, the situations are reversed. The analyses, depending on the frame of the atom, are respectively done within the light cone, Minkowski, Schwarzschild, and Kruskal time-interaction pictures. In all of these scenarios, we observe that the excitation probabilities contain a thermal factor and depend periodically on the separation between the atom and the mirror. At the level of transition probabilities, the aforesaid two scenarios in $(1+1)$ dimensional Minkowski-light cone regions appear to be the same for the equal field and atomic frequencies. However, the same is not true when we consider the $(3+1)$ dimensional Minkowski-light cone or the Schwarzschild interior regions. We also estimate the de-excitation probabilities and encounter similar situations. However, we observe that the excitation to de-excitation ratios (EDRs) corresponding to analogous scenarios are equal for equal atomic and field frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12378v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhajit Barman, Pradeep Kumar Kumawat, Bibhas Ranjan Majhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hodge Theory for Entanglement Cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12529v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore and extend the application of homological algebra to describe quantum entanglement, initiated in arXiv:1901.02011, focusing on the Hodge-theoretic structure of entanglement cohomology in finite-dimensional quantum systems. We construct analogues of the Hodge star operator, inner product, codifferential, and Laplacian for entanglement $k$-forms. We also prove that such $k$-forms obey versions of the Hodge isomorphism theorem and Hodge decomposition, and that they exhibit Hodge duality. As a corollary, we conclude that the dimensions of the $k$-th and $(n-k)$-th cohomologies coincide for entanglement in $n$-partite pure states, which explains a symmetry property ("Poincare duality") of the associated Poincare polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12529v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.A 111 (2025) 3, 032422</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ferko, Eashan Iyer, Kasra Mossayebi, Gregor Sanfey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Entanglement is Quantum: ZZ Production at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12125v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polarization and spin correlations in diboson systems serve as powerful tools for precision tests and searches for new physics. Recently, interpreting these observables through the lens of quantum information, for instance by examining whether the diboson systems exhibit entanglement, has introduced a compelling new dimension to these studies. We analyze the angular coefficients in the processes $pp\to e^+e^-\mu^+\mu^-$ and $h\to e^+e^-\mu^+\mu^-$, incorporating higher-order QCD and electroweak corrections. Guided by the fundamental properties of the spin density matrix, we assess the stability of the two-qutrit interpretation under radiative effects. For the $pp \to e^+e^-\mu^+\mu^-$ process, NLO QCD corrections preserve the two-qutrit structure but weaken entanglement indicators, an effect that can be partially mitigated by jet binning. In contrast, electroweak corrections introduce non-factorizable contributions that modify the quantum properties of the system. While these effects can be largely depleted by selecting events with a double-resonant $ZZ$ structure, such a kinematic handle is not available for Higgs decays. In the $h \to e^+e^-\mu^+\mu^-$ channel, singly-resonant NLO electroweak corrections substantially distort the angular coefficients, challenging the description of these events as a two-qutrit system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12125v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2025)122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2025, 122 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dorival Gon\c{c}alves, Ajay Kaladharan, Frank Krauss, Alberto Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surprisingly High Redundancy in Electronic Structure Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09001v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of electronic structure underpins advances in chemistry, materials science, and condensed matter physics. In recent years, Machine Learning (ML) has enabled the development of powerful surrogate models that can enable the prediction of the ground state electron density and related properties at a fraction of the computational cost of conventional first principles simulations. Such ML models typically rely on massive datasets generated through expensive Kohn-Sham Density Functional Theory calculations. A key reason for relying on such large datasets is the lack of prior knowledge about which portions of the data are essential, and which are redundant. This study reveals significant redundancies in electronic structure datasets across various material systems, including molecules, simple metals, and chemically complex alloys -- challenging the notion that extensive datasets are essential for accurate ML-based electronic structure predictions. We demonstrate that even random pruning can substantially reduce dataset size with minimal loss in predictive accuracy. Furthermore, a state-of-the-art coverage-based pruning strategy that selects data across all learning difficulties, retains chemical accuracy and model generalizability using up to 100-fold less data, while reducing training time by threefold or greater. By contrast, widely used importance-based pruning methods, which eliminate easy-to-learn data, can catastrophically fail at higher pruning factors due to significant reduction in data coverage. This heretofore unexplored high redundancy in electronic structure data holds the potential to identify a minimal, essential dataset representative of each material class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09001v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sazzad Hossain, Ponkrshnan Thiagarajan, Shashank Pathrudkar, Stephanie Taylor, Abhijeet S. Gangan, Amartya S. Banerjee, Susanta Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path-Integral Formulation of Bosonic Markovian Open Quantum Dynamics with Monte Carlo stochastic trajectories using the Glauber-Sudarshan P, Wigner, and Husimi Q Functions and Hybrids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01991v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Monte Carlo (MC) trajectory sampling of stochastic differential equations (SDEs) based on the quasiprobabilities, such as the Glauber-Sudarshan P, Wigner, and Husimi Q functions, enables us to investigate bosonic open quantum many-body dynamics described by the Gorini-Kossakowski-Sudarshan-Lindblad (GKSL) equation. In this method, the MC samplings for the initial distribution and stochastic noises incorporate quantum fluctuations, and thus, we can go beyond the mean-field approximation. However, description using SDEs is possible only when the corresponding Fokker-Planck equation has a positive-semidefinite diffusion matrix. In this work, we analytically derive the SDEs for arbitrary Hamiltonian and jump operators based on the path-integral formula, independently of the derivation of the Fokker-Planck equation (FPE). In the course of the derivation, we formulate the path-integral representation of the GKSL equation by using the $s$-ordered quasiprobability, which systematically describes the aforementioned quasiprobabilities by changing the real parameter $s$. The essential point of this derivation is that we employ the Hubbard-Stratonovich (HS) transformation in the path integral, and its application is not always feasible. We find that the feasible condition of the HS transformation is identical to the positive-semidefiniteness condition of the diffusion matrix in the FPE. In the benchmark calculations, we confirm that the MC simulations of the obtained SDEs well reproduce the exact dynamics of physical quantities and non-equal time correlation functions of numerically solvable models, including the Bose-Hubbard model. This work clarifies the applicability of the approximation and gives systematic and simplified procedures to obtain the SDEs to be numerically solved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01991v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2025.170325</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. Phys.485, 170325 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Toma Yoneya, Kazuya Fujimoto, Yuki Kawaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Zero Added Loss Multiplexing (ZALM) Source Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Zero Added Loss Multiplexing (ZALM) offers broadband, per channel heralded EPR pairs, with a rich parameter space that allows its performance to be tailored for specific applications. We present a modular ZALM simulator that demonstrates how design choices affect output rate and fidelity. Built in NetSquid with QSI controllers, it exposes 20+ tunable parameters, supports IDEAL and REALISTIC modes, and provides reusable components for Spontaneous Parametric Down Conversion (SPDC) sources, interference, Dense Wavelength Division Multiplexing (DWDM) filtering, fiber delay, active polarization gates, detectors, and lossy fiber. Physics based models capture Hong Ou Mandel (HOM) visibility, insertion loss, detector efficiency, gate errors, and attenuation. Using this tool, we map trade offs among fidelity, link distance, and entangled pairs per use, and show how SPDC bandwidth and DWDM grid spacing steer performance. Using the default configuration settings, average fidelity emains constant at 0.8 but the ebit rate decreases from 0.0175 at the source to 0.0 at 50 km; narrowing the SPDC degeneracy bandwidth increases the ebit rate significantly without affecting fidelity. The simulator enables codesign of source, filtering, and feedforward settings for specific quantum memories and integrates as a building block for end to end quantum network studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26009v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerry Horgan, Alexander Nico-Katz, Shelbi L. Jenkins, Ashley N. Tittelbaugh, Vivek Visan, Rohan Bali, Marco Ruffini, Boulat A. Bash, Daniel C. Kilper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing quantum dimensions: Symmetry-based classification of local pseudo-Hermitian systems and the corresponding domain walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11059v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study conformal field theories (CFTs) and their classifications from a modern perspective based on the abstract algebraic formalism of symmetries or conserved charges, known as symmetry topological field theories (SymTFTs). By studying the algebraic structure of the SymTFTs in detail, we found a natural generalization of the quantum dimensions associated with (pseudo-)Hermitian systems and (non)-unitary CFTs. These generalized data of SymTFTs provide classifications of massless and massive renormalization group flows, which will describe the quantum phase transitions of the corresponding pseudo-Hermitian systems. Moreover, our discussions straightforwardly enable one to relate a general class of coset constructions or level-rank dualities to domain wall problems between topological quantum field theories (or a series of corresponding quantum phase transitions related to the Higgs mechanism). Our work provides a systematic reduction and classification of algebraic data, symmetries, for pseudo-Hermitian systems based on ideas from established mathematical fields, linear algebra and ring theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11059v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi, Taishi Kawamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical structural properties of many-body chaotic eigenfunctions and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07016v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ a semiperturbative theory to study the statistical structural properties of energy eigenfunctions (EFs) in many-body quantum chaotic systems consisting of a central system coupled to an environment. Under certain assumptions, we derive both the average shape and the statistical fluctuations of EFs on the basis formed by the direct product of the energy eigenbases of the system and the environment. Furthermore, we apply our results to two fundamental questions: (i) the properties of the reduced density matrix of the central system in an eigenstate, and (ii) the structure of the off-diagonal smooth function within the framework of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis. Numerical results are also presented in support of our main findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07016v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-ge Wang, Qingchen Li, Jiaozi Wang, Xiao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum canonical purifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17014v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct and characterize canonical purifications for general algebraic states, extending prior constructions by Woronowicz and by Dutta/Faulkner to general quantum theories. Given a state on a $*$-algebra, the canonical purification is a state on a "doubled" algebra that admits an interpretation in terms of CRT reflection. This interpretation holds for all quantum theories, even in the absence of gravity. We then identify conditions under which canonical purifications are "pure" in the technical sense, compute their modular conjugations, and relate them to GNS and natural-cone purifications in certain settings. In an appendix, we develop a general theory of von Neumann algebras generated by unbounded $*$-algebras. In a forthcoming paper with Caminiti and Capeccia, we provide an application of this general theory to the problem of excitability in quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17014v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sorce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum-resolved spectral functions of super-moir\'e systems using tensor networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Computing spectral functions in large, non-periodic super-moir\'e systems remains an open problem due to the exceptionally large system size that must be considered. Here, we establish a tensor network methodology that allows computing momentum-resolved spectral functions of non-interacting and interacting super-moir\'e systems at an atomistic level. Our methodology relies on encoding an exponentially large tight-binding problem as an auxiliary quantum many-body problem, solved with a many-body kernel polynomial tensor network algorithm combined with a quantum Fourier transform tensor network. We demonstrate the method for one and two-dimensional super-moir\'e systems, including super-moir\'e with non-uniform strain, interactions treated at the mean-field level, and quasicrystalline super-moir\'e patterns. Furthermore, we demonstrate that our methodology allows us to compute momentum-resolved spectral functions restricted to selected regions of a super-moir\'e, enabling direct imaging of position-dependent electronic structure and minigaps in super-moir\'e systems with non-uniform strain. Our results establish a powerful methodology to compute momentum-resolved spectral functions in exceptionally large super-moir\'e systems, providing a tool to directly model scanning twisting microscope tunneling experiments in twisted van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18397v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anouar Moustaj, Yitao Sun, Tiago V. C. Ant\~ao, Jose L. Lado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio prediction of strain-tunable spin defects in quasi-1D TiS3 and NbS3 nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19391v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Defects in atomically thin van der Waals materials have recently been investigated as sources of spin-photon entanglement with sensitivity to strain tuning. Unlike many two-dimensional materials, quasi-one-dimensional materials such as transition metal trichalcogenides exhibit in-plane anisotropy resulting in axis-dependent responses to compressive and tensile strains. Herein, we characterize the tunable spin and optical properties of intrinsic vacancy defects in titanium trisulfide (TiS3) and niobium trisulfide (NbS3) nanowires. Within our ab initio approach, we show that sulfur vacancies and divacancies (VS and VD , respectively) in TiS3 and NbS3 adopt strain-dependent defect geometries between in-plane strains of -3 % and 3 %. The calculated electronic structures indicate that both VS and VD possess in-gap defect states with optically bright electronic transitions whose position relative to the conduction and valence bands varies with in-plane strain. Further, our calculations predict that VS in TiS3 and VD in NbS3 exhibit transitions in their ground state spins; specifically, a compressive strain of 0.4 % along the direction of nanowire growth causes a shift from a triplet state to a singlet state for the VS defect in TiS3, whereas a tensile strain of 2.9 % along the same direction in NbS3 induces a triplet ground state with a zero-phonon line of 0.83 eV in the VD defect. Our work shows that the anisotropic geometry of TiS3 and NbS3 nanowires offers exceptional tunability of optically active spin defects that can be used in quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19391v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Chapman, Arindom Nag, Thang Pham, Vsevolod Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
