<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and challenges of quantum computing for climate modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Adaptation to climate change requires robust climate projections, yet the uncertainty in these projections performed by ensembles of Earth system models (ESMs) remains large. This is mainly due to uncertainties in the representation of subgrid-scale processes such as turbulence or convection that are partly alleviated at higher resolution. New developments in machine learning-based hybrid ESMs demonstrate great potential for systematically reduced errors compared to traditional ESMs. Building on the work of hybrid (physics + AI) ESMs, we here discuss the additional potential of further improving and accelerating climate models with quantum computing. We discuss how quantum computers could accelerate climate models by solving the underlying differential equations faster, how quantum machine learning could better represent subgrid-scale phenomena in ESMs even with currently available noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices, how quantum algorithms aimed at solving optimisation problems could assist in tuning the many parameters in ESMs, a currently time-consuming and challenging process, and how quantum computers could aid in the analysis of climate models. We also discuss hurdles and obstacles facing current quantum computing paradigms. Strong interdisciplinary collaboration between climate scientists and quantum computing experts could help overcome these hurdles and harness the potential of quantum computing for this urgent topic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10488v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mierk Schwabe, Lorenzo Pastori, In\'es de Vega, Pierre Gentine, Luigi Iapichino, Valtteri Lahtinen, Martin Leib, Jeanette M. Lorenz, Veronika Eyring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quantum Wave Function as a Complex Probability Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper suggests an interpretation for the wave function, based on some elements of Nelson's stochastic mechanics, the time-symmetric laws of quantum theory and complex probabilities. Our main purpose is to demonstrate that the wave function and its complex conjugate can be interpreted as complex probability densities (or quasi-probability distributions) related to non-real forward and backward in time stochastic motion respectively. Those two quasi-Brownian motions serve as mathematical abstracts in order to derive the Born rule using probability theory and the intersection of the two probability sets that describe each of those motions. This proposal is useful also for explaining more about the role of complex numbers in quantum mechanics that produces this so-called "wave-like" nature of quantum reality. Our perspective also challenges the notion of physical superposition which is a fundamental concept in the Copenhagen interpretation and some other interpretations of quantum theory. Moreover, it is suggested that, embracing the idea of stochastic processes in quantum theory, may explain the reasons for the appearance of classical behavior in large objects, in contrast to the quantum behavior of small ones. In other words, we claim that a combination of a probabilistic and no-ontic view of the wave function with a stochastic hidden-variables approach, like Nelson's and others', may provide some insight into the quantum physical reality and potentially establish the groundwork for a novel interpretation of quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10523v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charalampos Antonakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Fanout and GHZ states using spin-exchange interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how the fanout operation on $n$ logical qubits can be implemented via spin-exchange (Heisenberg) interactions between $2n$ physical qubits, together with a physical target qubit and $1$- and $2$-qubit gates in constant depth. We also show that the same interactions can be used to implement Mod_q gates for any $q&gt;1$. These results allow for unequal coupling strengths between physical qubits. This work generalizes an earlier result by Fenner &amp; Zhang [arXiv: quant-ph/0407125], wherein the authors showed similar results assuming all pairwise couplings are equal. The current results give exact conditions on the pairwise couplings that allow for this implementation. Precisely, each logical qubit is encoded into two physical qubits. Couplings between physical qubits encoding the same logical qubit are termed as internal couplings and couplings between the ones encoding different logical qubits are termed as external couplings. We show that for a suitable time $T$ of evolution, the following conditions should hold: a) every external coupling should be an odd integer multiple of $\pi/2T$; b) every internal coupling should be an integer multiple of $\pi/T$; and c) the external magnetic strength in $z$-direction should be an integer multiple of $\pi/T$. Since generalized GHZ (''cat'') states can be created in constant depth using fanout, the same interactions can be used to create these states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10602v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Fenner, Rabins Wosti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieving maximum information of symmetric states from their corrupted copies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using quantum measurements to extract information from states is a matter of routine in quantum science and technologies. A recent work [Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 040202 (2024)] reported the finding that the symmetric structures of a state can be harnessed to dramatically reduce the sample complexity in extracting information from the state. However, due to the presence of noise, the actual state at hand is often corrupted, making its symmetric structures distorted before the execution of quantum measurements. Here, using the methodology of quantum metrology, we identify the optimal measurement that can retrieve maximum information of a symmetric state from its corrupted copies. We show that this measurement can be found by solving a semidefinite program in generic cases and can be explicitly determined for a large class of noise models covariant under the symmetry group in question. The results of this study nicely complement the recent work by providing a method to optimally utilize the distorted symmetric structures of corrupted states for information retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.022424</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, 022424(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhao-Yi Zhou, Da-Jian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast Quantum Image Compression Algorithm based on Taylor Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the increasing demand for storing images, traditional image compression methods face challenges in balancing the compressed size and image quality. However, the hybrid quantum-classical model can recover this weakness by using the advantage of qubits. In this study, we upgrade a quantum image compression algorithm within parameterized quantum circuits. Our approach encodes image data as unitary operator parameters and applies the quantum compilation algorithm to emulate the encryption process. By utilizing first-order Taylor expansion, we significantly reduce both the computational cost and loss, better than the previous version. Experimental results on benchmark images, including Lenna and Cameraman, show that our method achieves up to 86\% reduction in the number of iterations while maintaining a lower compression loss, better for high-resolution images. The results confirm that the proposed algorithm provides an efficient and scalable image compression mechanism, making it a promising candidate for future image processing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10684v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vu Tuan Hai, Huynh Ho Thi Mong Trinh, Pham Hoai Luan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing the stabilizer formalism for quantum machine learning applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum machine learning model is emerging as a new model that merges quantum computing and machine learning. Simulating very deep quantum machine learning models requires a lot of resources, increasing exponentially based on the number of qubits and polynomially based on the depth value. Almost all related works use state-vector-based simulators due to their parallelization and scalability. Extended stabilizer formalism simulators solve the same problem with fewer computations because they act on stabilizers rather than long vectors. However, the gate application sequential property leads to less popularity and poor performance. In this work, we parallelize the process, making it feasible to deploy on multi-core devices. The results show that the proposal implementation on Python is faster than Qiskit, the current fastest simulator, 4.23 times in the case of 4-qubits, 60,2K gates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10685v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vu Tuan Hai, Le Vu Trung Duong, Pham Hoai Luan, Yasuhiko Nakashima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alternating and Gaussian fermionic Isometric Tensor Network States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Isometric tensor networks in two dimensions enable efficient and accurate study of quantum many-body states, yet the effect of the isometric restriction on the represented quantum states is not fully understood. We address this question in two main contributions. First, we introduce an improved variant of isometric network states (isoTNS) in two dimensions, where the isometric arrows on the columns of the network alternate between pointing upward and downward, hence the name alternating isometric tensor network states. Second, we introduce a numerical tool -- isometric Gaussian fermionic TNS (isoGfTNS) -- that incorporates isometric constraints into the framework of Gaussian fermionic tensor network states. We demonstrate in numerous ways that alternating isoTNS represent many-body ground states of two-dimensional quantum systems significantly better than the original isoTNS. First, we show that the entanglement in an isoTNS is mediated along the isometric arrows and that alternating isoTNS mediate entanglement more efficiently than conventional isoTNS. Second, alternating isoTNS correspond to a deeper, thus more representative, sequential circuit construction of depth $\mathcal{O}(L_x \cdot L_y)$ compared to the original isoTNS of depth $\mathcal{O}(L_x + L_y)$. Third, using the Gaussian framework and gradient-based energy minimization, we provide numerical evidences of better bond-dimension scaling and variational energy of alternating isoGfTNS for ground states of various free fermionic models, including the Fermi surface, the band insulator, and the $p_x + ip_y$ mean-field superconductor.
  Finally, we find improved performance of alternating isoTNS as compared to the original isoTNS for the ground state energy of the (interacting) transverse field Ising model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10695v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yantao Wu, Zhehao Dai, Sajant Anand, Sheng-Hsuan Lin, Qi Yang, Lei Wang, Frank Pollmann, Michael P. Zaletel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-mitigated entanglement-assisted quantum process tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the era of noisy intermediate-scale quantum computing, it is of crucial importance to verify quantum processes and extract information. Quantum process tomography is a typical approach, however, both resource-intensive and vulnerable to state preparation and measurement errors. Here, we propose an error-mitigated entanglement-assisted quantum process tomography (EM-EAPT) framework to address these limitations. By leveraging a maximally entangled state to reduce state preparation complexity and integrating error mitigation techniques, our method significantly enhances robustness against SPAM errors. Experimental validation on a superconducting processor demonstrates the efficacy of EM-EAPT for two-qubit and three-qubit quantum processes. Results show more accurate average gate fidelities close to the realistic estimation, achieving 98.1$\pm$ 0.03% for a CNOT gate and 88.1%$\pm$ 0.04% for a cascaded CNOT process after error mitigation, compared to non-mitigated implementations. This work advances practical quantum verification tools for NISQ devices, enabling higher-fidelity characterization of quantum processes under realistic noise conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10715v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihao Wu, Lingling Lao, Chengqi Zhuke, Yantong Liu, Xinfang Zhang, Shichuan Xue, Mingtang Deng, Junjie Wu, Kai Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NPA Hierarchy and Extremal Criterion in the Simplest Bell Scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is difficult to establish an analytical criterion to identify the boundaries of quantum correlations, even for the simplest Bell scenario. Here, we briefly reviewed the plausible analytical criterion, and we found a way to confirm the extremal conditions from another direction. For that purpose, we analyzed the Navascu\'es-Pironio-Ac\'{\i}n (NPA) hierarchy to study the algebraic structure and found that the problem could not be simplified using $1\!+\!AB$ level. However, considering the plausible criterion, the $1\!+\!AB$ and second levels for correlations were equal, and the extremal condition in the simplest Bell scenario was replaced by that in the $1\!+\!AB$ level. Thus, the correctness of the plausible criterion was verified, and the results demonstrated that the plausible criterion held, thereby explaining its simplicity. It seemed plausible, but now it becomes more certain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10746v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e27020182</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 2025, 27(2), 182</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Ishizaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optomechanically induced transparency in Four-wave mixing atomic ensemble assisted Laguerre-Gaussian vortex cavity system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the steady-state optical response of a Laguerre-Gaussian vortex cavity system integrated with cold atoms featuring a double-$\Lambda$ energy level structure. Within this hybrid system, the atoms are driven by cavity mode and three coherent vortex beams, each carrying independent orbital angular momentum (OAM). We first check the steady-state output spectrum of the hybrid system in the passive/active case (without/with external cavity driving). Our findings reveal that the optomechanically induced transparency (OMIT) spectrum is modulated by the OAM difference $(\Delta \ell\hbar)$ from the atomic component throughout the four-wave mixing (FWM) process. The resulting loop phase ($\Delta \ell\theta$) can achieve a switching effect on the absorption and gain behavior of the hybrid system for the probe beam. Additionally, the group delay, indicative of fast/slow light phenomena, is also tuned by $\Delta \ell$. We further display how the atomic OAM modulates the periodicity of the output spot pattern in the hybrid system. This research provides valuable insights into the modulation of optical responses in Laguerre-Gaussian vortex cavity systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10806v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue-Tong Hao, Yi-Mou Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum phase transitions in a Dicke trimer with both photon and atom hoppings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate superradiant quantum phase transitions in a Dicke trimer model consisting of two types of hoppings, i.e., photon hoppings and atom hoppings. In the superradiant regime, the system can exist in two distinct phases: normal and frustrated superradiant phases, which are governed by both types of hoppings. Particularly, the interplay between these hoppings gives rise to interesting effects, such as triggering superradiance with much lower coupling strengths when both hoppings exhibit the same tendency. In contrast, with opposite tendencies, the competition between hoppings leads to a first-order phase transition between two different superradiant phases with translational symmetry broken. These findings enable the system to undergo a sequence of transitions across three phases by changing the coupling strength. Our work provides deep insights into competing interactions and quantum phase transitions in multi-cavity systems with geometric structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10839v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Wen Luo, Bo Wang, Ze-Liang Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Fourier transform computational accuracy analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present a rigorous accuracy analysis of the quantum Fourier transform (QFT), that identifies three natural sources of accuracy degeneracy: (i) discretization accuracy inherited from classical sampling theory, (ii) accuracy degeneracy due to limited resolution in eigenvalue (phase) estimation, and (iii) accuracy degeneracy resulting from finite quantum resources. We formalize these accuracy degradation sources by proving two theorems that relate the minimal amplitude and eigenvalue resolution to the number of qubits. In addition, we describe a gate-level implementation of the QFT and present simulation results on small-scale quantum systems that illustrate our theoretical findings. Our results clarify the interplay between classical signal discretization limits and quantum hardware limitations, and they provide guidelines for the resource requirements needed to achieve a desired precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10840v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marina O. Lisnichenko, Oleg M. Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dephasing enhanced transport of spin excitations in a two dimensional lossy lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Noise is commonly regarded as an adverse effect disrupting communication and coher- ent transport processes or limiting their efficiency. However, as has been shown for example for small light-harvesting protein complexes decoherence processes can play a significant role in facilitating transport processes, a phenomenon termed environment- assisted quantum transport (ENAQT). We here study numerically and analytically how dephasing noise improves the efficiency of spin excitation transport in a two dimen- sional lattice with small homogeneous losses. In particular we investigate the efficiency and time of excitation transfer from a random initial site to a specific target site and show that for system sizes below a characteristic scale it can be substantially enhanced by adding small dephasing noise. We derive approximate analytic expressions for the efficiency which become rather accurate in the two limits of small (coherent regime) and large noise (Zeno regime) and give a very good overall estimate. These analytic expressions provide a quantitative description of ENAQT in spatially extended systems and allow to derive conditions for its existence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10854v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Skalkin, Razmik Unanyan, Michael Fleischhauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-Mediated Collective Resonant Suppression of Local Molecular Vibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in polaritonic chemistry suggest that chemical reactions can be controlled via collective vibrational strong coupling (VSC) in a cavity. We provide an analytical framework for the dynamics of a molecular ensemble under VSC, revealing that strong collective coupling induces a collective beating, with a period inversely proportional to the collective vacuum Rabi splitting. This emergent beating period occurs over significantly longer time scales than either the individual molecular vibration or cavity field oscillation period, and peaks at the cavity-molecule resonance, consistent with polaritonic chemistry experiments. Most importantly, the collective beating is imprinted on the local dynamics and resonantly suppresses individual molecular vibrations when the molecules are vibrationally excited, as in activated complexes, formed in chemical reactions. The cavity mediates an energy exchange between the excited and the ground-state molecules, affecting the dynamics of the whole ensemble. In the ultrastrong coupling regime, we find that the local vibrations are modified by the cavity even at short time scales. Our analytical model offers insights into how collective VSC can resonantly dampen local molecular vibrations in the collective regime, potentially altering chemical reactivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10917v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasil Rokaj, Ilia Tutunnikov, H. R. Sadeghpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SVM/SVR Kernels as Quantum Propagators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11153v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we establish the equivalence between Support Vector Machine (SVM) kernels and quantum Green's functions. Drawing on the analogy between margin maximization in SVMs and action extremization in Lagrangian mechanics, we show that many standard kernels correspond naturally to Green's functions and that this correspondence arises from the inversion of physical operators. We further demonstrate how positive semi-definiteness, which is essential for valid SVM kernels, aligns with the spectral properties that ensure well-defined Green's functions.
  We employ the Kernel Polynomial Method (KPM) to create custom kernels for cases where the commonly employed kernels don't lead to a convergence. These custom kernels approximate the desired Green's functions. We furthermore demonstrate numerically on examples taken from physical problems, such as electrical conductivity, scattering amplitudes, photonic crystals, and energy levels of anharmonic oscillators, that selecting kernel functions that mirror the mathematical form of the associated Green's function can significantly enhance the predictive accuracy of machine learning models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11153v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan-Hong Kuo, Tsung-Wei Chiang, Renata Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Potential of Quantum Machine Learning in Cybersecurity: A Case-Study on PCA-based Intrusion Detection Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing promises to revolutionize our understanding of the limits of computation, and its implications in cryptography have long been evident. Today, cryptographers are actively devising post-quantum solutions to counter the threats posed by quantum-enabled adversaries. Meanwhile, quantum scientists are innovating quantum protocols to empower defenders. However, the broader impact of quantum computing and quantum machine learning (QML) on other cybersecurity domains still needs to be explored. In this work, we investigate the potential impact of QML on cybersecurity applications of traditional ML. First, we explore the potential advantages of quantum computing in machine learning problems specifically related to cybersecurity. Then, we describe a methodology to quantify the future impact of fault-tolerant QML algorithms on real-world problems. As a case study, we apply our approach to standard methods and datasets in network intrusion detection, one of the most studied applications of machine learning in cybersecurity. Our results provide insight into the conditions for obtaining a quantum advantage and the need for future quantum hardware and software advancements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11173v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cose.2025.104341</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Armando Bellante, Tommaso Fioravanti, Michele Carminati, Stefano Zanero, Alessandro Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-Based Entanglement Distillation and Constant-Rate Quantum Repeaters over Arbitrary Distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurement-based quantum repeaters employ entanglement distillation and swapping across links using locally prepared resource states of minimal size and local Bell measurements. In this paper, we introduce a systematic protocol for measurement-based entanglement distillation and its application to repeaters that can leverage any stabilizer code. Given a code, we explicitly define the corresponding resource state and derive an error-recovery operation based on all Bell measurement outcomes. Our approach offers deeper insights into the impact of resource state noise on repeater performance while also providing strategies for efficient preparation and fault-tolerant preservation of resource states. As an application, we propose a measurement-based repeater protocol based on quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes, enabling constant-yield Bell state distribution over arbitrary distances. Numerical simulations confirm exponential suppression of infidelity with increasing code size while maintaining a fixed code rate. This work establishes a scalable backbone for future global-scale fault-tolerant quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11174v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Shi, Ashlesha Patil, Saikat Guha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards identifying possible fault-tolerant advantage of quantum linear system algorithms in terms of space, time and energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing, a prominent non-Von Neumann paradigm beyond Moore's law, can offer superpolynomial speedups for certain problems. Yet its advantages in efficiency for tasks like machine learning remain under investigation, and quantum noise complicates resource estimations and classical comparisons. We provide a detailed estimation of space, time, and energy resources for fault-tolerant superconducting devices running the Harrow-Hassidim-Lloyd (HHL) algorithm, a quantum linear system solver relevant to linear algebra and machine learning. Excluding memory and data transfer, possible quantum advantages over the classical conjugate gradient method could emerge at $N \approx 2^{33} \sim 2^{48}$ or even lower, requiring ${O}(10^5)$ physical qubits, ${O}(10^{12}\sim10^{13})$ Joules, and ${O}(10^6)$ seconds under surface code fault-tolerance with three types of magic state distillation (15-1, 116-12, 225-1). Key parameters include condition number, sparsity, and precision $\kappa, s\approx{O}(10\sim100)$, $\epsilon\sim0.01$, and physical error $10^{-5}$. Our resource estimator adjusts $N, \kappa, s, \epsilon$, providing a map of quantum-classical boundaries and revealing where a practical quantum advantage may arise. Our work quantitatively determine how advanced a fault-tolerant quantum computer should be to achieve possible, significant benefits on problems related to real-world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11239v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Tu, Mark Dubynskyi, Mohammad Mohammadisiahroudi, Ekaterina Riashchentceva, Jinglei Cheng, Dmitry Ryashchentsev, Tam\'as Terlaky, Junyu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Q-Spellbook: Crafting Surface Code Layouts and Magic State Protocols for Large-Scale Quantum Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum error correction is a cornerstone of reliable quantum computing, with surface codes emerging as a prominent method for protecting quantum information. Surface codes are efficient for Clifford gates but require magic state distillation protocols to process non-Clifford gates, such as T gates, essential for universal quantum computation. In large-scale quantum architectures capable of correcting arbitrary circuits, specialized surface codes for data qubits and distinct codes for magic state distillation are needed. These architectures can be organized into data blocks and distillation blocks. The system works by having distillation blocks produce magic states and data blocks consume them, causing stalls due to either a shortage or excess of magic states. This bottleneck presents an opportunity to optimize quantum space by balancing data and distillation blocks. While prior research offers insights into selecting distillation protocols and estimating qubit requirements, it lacks a tailored optimization approach. We present a framework for optimizing large-scale quantum architectures, focusing on data block layouts and magic state distillation protocols. We evaluate three data block layouts and four distillation protocols under three optimization strategies: minimizing tiles, minimizing steps, and achieving a balanced trade-off. Through a comparative analysis of brute force, dynamic programming, greedy, and random algorithms, we find that brute force delivers optimal results, while greedy deviates by 7% for minimizing steps and dynamic programming matches brute force in tile minimization. We observe that total steps increase with columns, while total tiles scale with qubits. Finally, we propose a heuristic to help users select algorithms suited to their objectives, enabling scalable and efficient quantum architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11253v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avimita Chatterjee, Archisman Ghosh, Swaroop Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on Consequences of the single-pair measurement of the Bell parameter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Genovese and Piacentini [Phys.Rev.A 111, 022204 (2025)] claim that in a recent experiment[S.Virz\`i et al., Quantum Sci. Technol. 9, 045027 (2024)] the Bell parameter was measured on a single pair of photons thus it challenges several conclusions and discussions on the meaning of Bell inequalities as well as certain QM interpretations. We explain that the parameter measured in Virzi et al. experiment it is not the Bell parameter S which was discussed and estimated in many loophole free tests. Therefore, this experiment neither challenges our understanding of Bell Tests nor allows having doubts about Bohr complementarity and contextuality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11261v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marian Kupczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directional Transport in Rydberg Atom Arrays via Kinetic Constraints and Temporal Modulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an experimentally feasible scheme to achieve directional transport of Rydberg excitations and entangled states in atomic arrays with unequal spacings. By leveraging distance-dependent Rydberg-Rydberg interactions and temporally modulated laser detunings, our method directs excitation flow without requiring local addressing. Numerical simulations demonstrate robust and coherent transport under experimentally realistic conditions. Additionally, we show that this scheme enables controlled transport of Bell pairs and preserves entanglement during propagation. The approach provides a versatile platform for programmable directional transport, with potential applications in quantum simulation, entanglement distribution, and the design of scalable quantum processors and networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11282v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yupeng Wang, Junjie Wang, Aishik Panja, Xinghan Wang, Qi-Yu Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Error Mitigation for Sampling Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental breakthroughs have signalled the imminent arrival of the early fault-tolerant era. However, for a considerable period in the foreseeable future, relying solely on quantum error correction for full error suppression will remain extremely challenging due to its substantial hardware overhead. Additional help from quantum error mitigation (QEM) is essential for bridging this gap towards achieving quantum advantage. The application of QEM has so far been restricted to expectation value estimation, leaving its extension to sampling-based algorithms -- which is expected to play a pivotal role in the early fault-tolerant era -- an unresolved challenge. In this work, we present a framework for applying any QEM techniques to obtain the error-mitigated output distribution, showing that this incurs no greater cost than estimating a single observable. We also devised a way to sample from this distribution and constructed an explicit scheme for applying any QEM methods to quantum phase estimation, which can be generalised to other sampling algorithms. Numerical experiments were conducted to validate the efficacy of these methods. We believe our methods significantly broaden the scope of QEM, extending its applicability to most algorithms of practical interest and forming a crucial step towards realising quantum advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11285v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kecheng Liu, Zhenyu Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Detecting Steering in Qutrit-Pair States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Only a few states in high-dimensional systems can be identified as (un)steerable using existing theoretical or experimental methods. We utilize semidefinite programming (SDP) to construct a dataset for steerability detection in qutrit-qutrit systems. For the full-information feature $F_1$, artificial neural networks achieve high classification accuracy and generalization, and preform better than the support vector machine. As feature engineering playing a pivotal role, we introduce a steering ellipsoid-like feature $F_2$, which significantly enhances the performance of each of our models. Given the SDP method provides only a sufficient condition for steerability detection, we establish the first rigorously constructed, accurately labeled dataset based on theoretical foundations. This dataset enables models to exhibit outstanding accuracy and generalization capabilities, independent of the choice of features. As applications, we investigate the steerability boundaries of isotropic states and partially entangled states, and find new steerable states. This work not only advances the application of machine learning for probing quantum steerability in high-dimensional systems but also deepens the theoretical understanding of quantum steerability itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11365v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pu Wang, Zhongyan Li, Huixian Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Single-Photon Adder and Subtractor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-photon addition and subtraction are fundamental operations in quantum information processing. Traditionally, the behavior of a single-photon adder (SPA) and single-photon subtractor (SPS) has been theoretically described using creation and annihilation operators, respectively. However, we demonstrate that this ladder-operator-based description contains significant theoretical flaws. To address these issues, we develop a theoretical framework based on Kraus operators, applicable to both coherent and incoherent SPAs and SPSs. Furthermore, we propose a method for realizing deterministic SPAs and SPSs of a cavity mode using three-level atoms. We analyze the effects of these operations on various quantum states. Additionally, we demonstrate that the use of a control pulse could enhance the performance of SPAs and SPSs, effectively preserving the quantum coherence of the resulting photon state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11376v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Qi Jiang, Hai-Jun Xing, Li-Ping Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circuit Partitioning and Full Circuit Execution: A Comparative Study of GPU-Based Quantum Circuit Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Executing large quantum circuits is not feasible using the currently available NISQ (noisy intermediate-scale quantum) devices. The high costs of using real quantum devices make it further challenging to research and develop quantum algorithms. As a result, performing classical simulations is usually the preferred method for researching and validating large-scale quantum algorithms. However, these simulations require a huge amount of resources, as each additional qubit exponentially increases the computational space required.
  Distributed Quantum Computing (DQC) is a promising alternative to reduce the resources required for simulating large quantum algorithms at the cost of increased runtime. This study presents a comparative analysis of two simulation methods: circuit-splitting and full-circuit execution using distributed memory, each having a different type of overhead.
  The first method, using CutQC, cuts the circuit into smaller subcircuits and allows us to simulate a large quantum circuit on smaller machines. The second method, using Qiskit-Aer-GPU, distributes the computational space across a distributed memory system to simulate the entire quantum circuit. Results indicate that full-circuit executions are faster than circuit-splitting for simulations performed on a single node. However, circuit-splitting simulations show promising results in specific scenarios as the number of qubits is scaled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11385v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kartikey Sarode, Daniel E. Huang, E. Wes Bethel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TEMPO: A Python Package for Time Evolution of Pulse Sequences in QuTiP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: TEMPO (Time-dependent Evolution of Multiple Pulse Operations) offers accessible and efficient simulations of pulse sequences in Python, using the suite of master equation solvers available in the Quantum Toolbox in Python (QuTiP). It enables straightforward definition of pulse sequence structures, including any underlying time-dependent Hamiltonians and pulse timing information, and faster simulations of pulse sequence dynamics (compared to naive implementations using QuTiP) while remaining compatible with the existing collection of QuTiP subpackages. Given the ubiquitous use of pulse sequences throughout quantum information/computing sciences, magnetic resonance studies, and quantum metrology, this work has immediate relevance to a wide array of research applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11389v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jner Tzern Oon, Sonja A. Hakala, George A. Witt, Ronald Walsworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum decision trees with information entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a classification algorithm for quantum states, inspired by decision-tree methods. To adapt the decision-tree framework to the probabilistic nature of quantum measurements, we utilize conditional probabilities to compute information gain, thereby optimizing the measurement scheme. For each measurement shot on an unknown quantum state, the algorithm selects the observable with the highest expected information gain, continuing until convergence. We demonstrate using the simulations that this algorithm effectively identifies quantum states sampled from the Haar random distribution. However, despite not relying on circuit-based quantum neural networks, the algorithm still encounters challenges akin to the barren plateau problem. In the leading order, we show that the information gain is proportional to the variance of the observable's expectation values over candidate states. As the system size increases, this variance, and consequently the information gain, are exponentially suppressed, which poses significant challenges for classifying general Haar-random quantum states. Finally, we apply the quantum decision tree to classify the ground states of various Hamiltonians using physically-motivated observables. On both simulators and quantum computers, the quantum decision tree yields better performances when compared to methods that are not information-optimized. This indicates that the measurement of physically-motivated observables can significantly improve the classification performance, guiding towards the future direction of this approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11412v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhelun Li, Koji Terashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monogamy and polygamy for multi-qudit generalized $W$-class states based on concurrence of assistance and Tsallis-$q$ entanglement of assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By analyzing the reduced density matrices derived from a generalized $W$-class state under any partition, we present new analytical monogamy inequalities satisfied by the $\alpha$-th ($\alpha\geq\gamma,~\gamma\geq2$) power and $\beta$-th ($0\leq\beta\leq\frac{\gamma}{2},~\gamma\geq2$) power of the concurrence of assistance for multi-qudit generalized $W$-class states, which are demonstrated to be tighter than previous studies through detailed examples. Furthermore, using the Tsallis-$q$ entanglement of assistance, we also establish new monogamy and polygamy relations, which are shown to be valid even for multipartite higher-dimensional states that the CKW inequality is violated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11526v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-025-06035-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. Plus (2025) 140:131</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen Zhou, Zhong-Xi Shen, Dong-Ping Xuan, Zhi-Xi Wang, Shao-Ming Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiband dispersion and warped vortices of strongly-interacting photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study quantum correlations between interacting photons realized through co-propagating Rydberg polaritons. We show that the evolution of the $n$-photon wavefunction is governed by a multiband dispersion featuring one massive mode and $n-1$ degenerate modes, such as two Dirac cones for $n=3$. The band structure exhibits an $n$-fold rotational symmetry, including an $n$-fold warped light cone, in contrast to the single-band, parabolic approximation often assumed for interacting polaritons. For three photons, the dispersion breaks the symmetry between a photon pair propagating ahead versus behind a single photon. We confirm these findings experimentally by measuring the three-photon phase and intensity correlation functions, revealing trigonal warping of the quantum vortex-ring generated by the three-photon interactions. Our analytical results are supported by rigorous numerical modeling that fully accounts for the photon propagation before, inside, and after the finite atomic medium. These findings advance the understanding of multi-photon interactions and the development of future multi-photon control tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11553v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bankim Chandra Das, Dmytro Kiselov, Lee Drori, Ariel Nakav, Alexander Poddubny, Ofer Firstenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An ultra-compact deterministic source of maximally entangled photon pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an ultra-compact source of maximally entangled on-demand photon pairs. Our results are based on coupling of single GaAs quantum dots that are embedded in monolithic micro-lenses to a single-mode fiber with directly attached to 3D-printed micro-optics (NA of 0.6) inside a cryogenic environment. This approach, which is geared towards future integration into industrial environments, yields state-of-the-art entangled photon pair creation performance while retaining flexibility and adjustability required for long-term operation of such a device - all while dramatically reducing the overall system footprint. We demonstrate near diffraction-limited performance and hyperspectral imaging utilizing a 3D-printed micro-objective with a full width at half maximum resolution limit of 604(16) nm when operating the system at a cryogenic temperature of 3.8 K. Furthermore, we prove that this system can be used to achieve single photon emission rates of 392(20) kHz at a 76 MHz pump rate and purities of 99.2(5) % using two-photon resonant excitation. Utilizing the exciton-biexciton emission cascade available in GaAs quantum dots under resonant excitation, near maximally entangled photon pairs with peak entanglement negatives 2n of 0.96(2) in a 4 ps time window, and 0.81(1) when averaged over one exciton lifetime, are demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11623v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Langer, P. Ruchka, A. Rahimi, S. Jakovljevic, Y. G. Zena, A. Danilov, M. Pal, R. Bassoli, F. H. P. Fitzek, O. G. Schmidt, H. Giessen, C. Hopfmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing the heralded photon number-state characterization by understanding the interplay of experimental imperfections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically explore the properties of heralded number states including up to three photons that are generated from single-mode twin beams. We investigate the effects of different parameters involved in the state preparation by using the fidelity, normalized second-order factorial moment of photon number for the heralded state $(g^{(2)}_h)$, and photon-number parity as figures of merit. Especially, the photon-number parity offers a practical and robust tool for inferring the target state quality by capturing the contamination of all undesired photon-number contributions. We focus on expressing our results in terms of experimentally easily accessible parameters such as the coincidences-to-accidentals ratio and the detection efficiencies. Our results identify the optimal parameter regions for generating high quality photon-number states and provide useful insights for advancing their use in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11631v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Borrero Landazabal, Kaisa Laiho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix Low-dimensional Qubit Casting Based Quantum Electromagnetic Transient Network Simulation Program</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In modern power systems, the integration of converter-interfaced generations requires the development of electromagnetic transient network simulation programs (EMTP) that can capture rapid fluctuations. However, as the power system scales, the EMTP's computing complexity increases exponentially, leading to a curse of dimensionality that hinders its practical application. Facing this challenge, quantum computing offers a promising approach for achieving exponential acceleration. To realize this in noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers, the variational quantum linear solution (VQLS) was advocated because of its robustness against depolarizing noise. However, it suffers data inflation issues in its preprocessing phase, and no prior research has applied quantum computing to high-frequency switching EMT networks.To address these issues, this paper first designs the matrix low-dimension qubit casting (MLQC) method to address the data inflation problem in the preprocessing of the admittance matrix for VQLS in EMT networks. Besides, we propose a real-only quantum circuit reduction method tailored to the characteristics of the EMT network admittance matrices. Finally, the proposed quantum EMTP algorithm (QEMTP) has been successfully verified for EMT networks containing a large number of high-frequency switching elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11728v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Lou, Yijun Xu, Wei Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time crystal optomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time crystals are an enigmatic phase of matter in which a quantum mechanical system displays repetitive, observable motion - they spontaneously break the time translation symmetry. On the other hand optomechanical systems, where mechanical and optical degrees of freedom are coupled, are well established and enable a range of applications and measurements with unparalleled precision. Here, we connect a time crystal formed of magnetic quasiparticles, magnons, to a mechanical resonator, a gravity wave mode on a nearby liquid surface, and show that their joint dynamics evolves as a cavity optomechanical system. Our results pave way for exploiting the spontaneous coherence of time crystals in an optomechanical setting and remove the experimental barrier between time crystals and other phases of condensed matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11730v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. T. M\"akinen, P. J. Heikkinen, S. Autti, V. V. Zavjalov, V. B. Eltsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Continuous Variable Quantum Key Distribution for Securing a Future Global Quantum Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuous variable quantum key distribution (CVQKD) is a developing method to secure information exchange in future quantum networks. With the recent developments in quantum technology and greater access to space, a global quantum network secured by CVQKD could be within reach. In this work, the structures of existing QKD networks are analysed, and how they can be fit into a general overarching three-layer QKD network architecture for the endeavour of a global QKD network. Such a network could comprise of different links in fibre and free-space. The finite size limit secret key rates (SKRs) with multidimensional reconciliation were calculated for the different links for which CVQKD can be used in such a network. The results show that CVQKD generally achieves longer distances and larger SKRs in inter-satellite, satellite-to-ground, fibre, and underwater links in descending order. The different links and nodes were classified and secret key distribution was studied as a graph problem. The link capacity, a routing metric for secret key distribution, which considers a dynamic SKR based on dynamic links is presented. Its use in simulated CVQKD networks is presented for the aim of spatiotemporal secret key distribution through a dynamic CVQKD network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11746v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhael T. Sayat, Sebastian P. Kish, Ping Koy Lam, Nicholas J. Rattenbury, John E. Cater</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous estimations of quantum state and detector through multiple quantum processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The estimation of all the parameters in an unknown quantum state or measurement device, commonly known as quantum state tomography (QST) and quantum detector tomography (QDT), is crucial for comprehensively characterizing and controlling quantum systems. In this paper, we introduce a framework, in two different bases, that utilizes multiple quantum processes to simultaneously identify a quantum state and a detector. We develop a closed-form algorithm for this purpose and prove that the mean squared error (MSE) scales as $O(1/N) $ for both QST and QDT, where $N $ denotes the total number of state copies. This scaling aligns with established patterns observed in previous works that addressed QST and QDT as independent tasks. Furthermore, we formulate the problem as a sum of squares (SOS) optimization problem with semialgebraic constraints, where the physical constraints of the state and detector are characterized by polynomial equalities and inequalities. The effectiveness of our proposed methods is validated through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11772v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuixin Xiao, Weichao Liang, Yuanlong Wang, Daoyi Dong, Ian R. Petersen, Valery Ugrinovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure, Positivity and Classical Simulability of Kirkwood-Dirac Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kirkwood-Dirac (KD) quasiprobability distribution is known for its role in quantum metrology, thermodynamics, as well as the foundations of quantum mechanics. Here, we study the superoperator evolution of KD distributions and show that unitaries which preserve KD positivity do not always correspond to a stochastic evolution of quasiprobabilities. Conversely, we show that stochastic KD superoperators are always induced by generalised permutations within the KD reference bases. We identify bounds for pure KD positive states in distributions defined on mutually unbiased bases, showing that they always form uniform distributions, in full analogy to the stabilizer states. Subsequently, we show that the discrete Fourier transform of KD distributions on qudits in the Fourier basis follows a self-similarity constraint and provides the expectation values of the state with respect to the Weyl-Heisenberg unitaries, which can then be transformed into the (odd-dimensional) Wigner distribution. This defines a direct mapping between the Wigner, and qudit KD distributions without a reconstruction of the density matrix. Finally, we identify instances where the classical sampling-based simulation algorithm of Pashayan et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 115, 070501] becomes exponentially inefficient in spite of the state being KD positive throughout its evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11784v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\k{e}drzej Burkat, Sergii Strelchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Harmonic Generation in a Crystal Driven by Quantum Light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study intraband high-harmonic generation (HHG) in a crystal driven by quantum light. Previous theoretical studies have developed a framework based on coherent state expansions in terms of P distributions to consider nonclassical driving fields for HHG in atoms. Here, we adapt this framework to the context of solids and consider an intraband model of ZnO. We investigate the effect of the quantum optical nature of the driving field on the harmonic spectra including the cutoff and the intensity scaling of the harmonics with driving field intensity. Based on analytical calculations in the Floquet limit, we explain why driving with thermal light or bright-squeezed vacuum (BSV) produces a much higher cutoff than when driving with fields described by coherent or Fock states. Further, we derive an expression for the generated time-dependent electric field and its fluctuations and find that it inherits characteristics of the driving field. Finally, we discuss the limitations of an approximative positive P representation, which is introduced to be able to reduce the numerical complexity for Fock and BSV driving fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11803v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasmus Vesterager Gothelf, Christian Saugbjerg Lange, Lars Bojer Madsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncontextual ontological models of operational probabilistic theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An experiment or theory is classically explainable if it can be reproduced by some noncontextual ontological model. In this work, we adapt the notion of ontological models and generalized noncontextuality so it applies to the framework of operational probabilistic theories (OPTs). A defining feature of quotiented OPTs, which sets them apart from the closely related framework of generalized probabilistic theories (GPTs), is their explicit specification of the structure of instruments, these being generalizations of $\textit{quantum instruments}$ (including nondestructive measurements); in particular, one needs to explicitly declare which collections of transformations constitute a valid instrument. We are particularly interested in strongly causal OPTs, in which the choice of a future instrument can be conditioned on a past measurement outcome. This instrument structure might seem to permit the possibility of a contextual kind of ontological representation, where the representation of a given transformation depends on which instrument it is considered a part of. However, we prove that this is not possible by showing that for strongly causal quotiented OPTs the structure of instruments does $\textit{not}$ allow for such a contextual ontological representation. It follows that ontological representations of strongly causal quotiented OPTs are entirely determined by their action on individual transformations, with no dependence on the structure of instruments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11842v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sina Soltani, Marco Erba, David Schmid, John H. Selby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A measurement-device-independent quantum key distribution network using optical frequency comb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum key distribution (QKD), which promises secure key exchange between two remote parties, is now moving toward the realization of scalable and secure QKD networks (QNs). Fully connected, trusted node-free QNs have been realized based on entanglement distribution, in which the low key rate as well as the large overhead makes their practical deployment and application challenging. Here, we propose and experimentally demonstrate a fully connected multi-user QKD network based on a wavelength-multiplexed measurement-device-independent (MDI) QKD protocol. By combining this novel protocol with integrated optical frequency combs, we achieve an average secure key rate of 267 bits per second for about 30 dB of link attenuation per user pair -- more than three orders of magnitude higher than previous entanglement-based works. More importantly, we realize secure key sharing between two different pairs of users simultaneously, which requires four-photon detection and is not possible with the previous two-photon entanglement distribution. Our work paves the way for the realization of large-scale QKD networks with full connectivity and simultaneous communication capability among multiple users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11860v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhan Yan, Xiaodong Zheng, Wenjun Wen, Liangliang Lu, Yifeng Du, Yanqing Lu, Shining Zhu, Xiao-Song Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ansatz-free Hamiltonian learning with Heisenberg-limited scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning the unknown interactions that govern a quantum system is crucial for quantum information processing, device benchmarking, and quantum sensing. The problem, known as Hamiltonian learning, is well understood under the assumption that interactions are local, but this assumption may not hold for arbitrary Hamiltonians. Previous methods all require high-order inverse polynomial dependency with precision, unable to surpass the standard quantum limit and reach the gold standard Heisenberg-limited scaling. Whether Heisenberg-limited Hamiltonian learning is possible without prior assumptions about the interaction structures, a challenge we term \emph{ansatz-free Hamiltonian learning}, remains an open question. In this work, we present a quantum algorithm to learn arbitrary sparse Hamiltonians without any structure constraints using only black-box queries of the system's real-time evolution and minimal digital controls to attain Heisenberg-limited scaling in estimation error. Our method is also resilient to state-preparation-and-measurement errors, enhancing its practical feasibility. Moreover, we establish a fundamental trade-off between total evolution time and quantum control on learning arbitrary interactions, revealing the intrinsic interplay between controllability and total evolution time complexity for any learning algorithm. These results pave the way for further exploration into Heisenberg-limited Hamiltonian learning in complex quantum systems under minimal assumptions, potentially enabling new benchmarking and verification protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11900v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Ye Hu, Muzhou Ma, Weiyuan Gong, Qi Ye, Yu Tong, Steven T. Flammia, Susanne F. Yelin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Quantum Control Landscape and Solution Space Complexity through Dimensionality Reduction &amp; Optimization Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the quantum control landscape (QCL) is important for designing effective quantum control strategies. In this study, we analyze the QCL for a single two-level quantum system (qubit) using various control strategies. We employ Principal Component Analysis (PCA), to visualize and analyze the QCL for higher dimensional control parameters. Our results indicate that dimensionality reduction techniques such as PCA, can play an important role in understanding the complex nature of quantum control in higher dimensions. Evaluations of traditional control techniques and machine learning algorithms reveal that Genetic Algorithms (GA) outperform Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD), while Q-learning (QL) shows great promise compared to Deep Q-Networks (DQN) and Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO). Additionally, our experiments highlight the importance of reward function design in DQN and PPO demonstrating that using immediate reward results in improved performance rather than delayed rewards for systems with short time steps. A study of solution space complexity was conducted by using Cluster Density Index (CDI) as a key metric for analyzing the density of optimal solutions in the landscape. The CDI reflects cluster quality and helps determine whether a given algorithm generates regions of high fidelity or not. Our results provide insights into effective quantum control strategies, emphasizing the significance of parameter selection and algorithm optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11905v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haftu W. Fentaw, Steve Campbell, Simon Caton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clifford circuit based heuristic optimization of fermion-to-qubit mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11933v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulation of interacting fermionic Hamiltonians is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. However, the feasibility of analysing fermionic systems with a quantum computer hinges on the efficiency of fermion-to-qubit mappings that encode non-local fermionic degrees of freedom in local qubit degrees of freedom. While recent works have highlighted the importance of designing fermion-to-qubit mappings that are tailored to specific problem Hamiltonians, the methods proposed so far are either restricted to a narrow class of mappings or they use computationally expensive and unscalable brute-force search algorithms. Here, we address this challenge by designing a $\mathrm{\textbf{heuristic}}$ numerical optimization framework for fermion-to-qubit mappings. To this end, we first translate the fermion-to-qubit mapping problem to a Clifford circuit optimization problem, and then use simulated annealing to optimize the average Pauli weight of the problem Hamiltonian. For all fermionic Hamiltonians we have considered, the numerically optimized mappings outperform their conventional counterparts, including ternary-tree-based mappings that are known to be optimal for single creation and annihilation operators. We find that our optimized mappings yield between $15\%$ to $40\%$ improvements on the average Pauli weight when the simulation Hamiltonian has an intermediate level of complexity. Most remarkably, the optimized mappings improve the average Pauli weight for $6 \times 6$ nearest-neighbor hopping and Hubbard models by more than $40\%$ and $20\%$, respectively. Surprisingly, we also find specific interaction Hamiltonians for which the optimized mapping outperform $\mathrm{\textbf{any}}$ ternary-tree-based mapping. Our results establish heuristic numerical optimization as an effective method for obtaining mappings tailored for specific fermionic Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11933v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffery Yu, Yuan Liu, Sho Sugiura, Troy Van Voorhis, Sina Zeytino\u{g}lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-Optical Photoluminescence Spectra of Nitrogen-Vacancy Ensembles in Diamond at Low Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: All-optical (AO), microwave-free magnetometry using nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond is attractive due to its broad sample compatibility and reduced experimental complexity. In this work, we investigate room-temperature AO photoluminescence (PL) at low magnetic fields (&lt;2 mT) using diamonds with NV ensembles at ppm concentrations. Measured AO-PL contrast features as a function of applied magnetic field magnitude and direction are correlated with near-degenerate NV electronic spin and hyperfine transitions from different NV orientations within the diamond host. Reasonable agreement is found between low-field AO-PL measurements and model-based simulations of the effects of resonant dipolar interactions between NV centers. Maximum observed AO-PL contrast depends on both NV concentration and laser illumination intensity at 532 nm. These results imply different optimal conditions for low-field AO NV sensing compared to conventional optically detected magnetic resonance (ODMR) techniques, suggesting new research and application opportunities using AO measurements with lower system complexity, size, weight, and power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11943v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiechen Zheng, Jeyson T\'amara-Isaza, Zechuan Yin, Johannes Cremer, John W. Blanchard, Connor A. Hart, Michael Crescimanno, Paul V. Petruzzi, Matthew J. Turner, Ronald L. Walsworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitality Conditions on Subsystems in Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is known that non-unital noise such as the amplitude damping can sometimes increase quantum correlations, while unital noise such as the dephasing usually decreases quantum correlations. It is, therefore, important to delineate the conditions, when noise can enhance the quantumness of the system. Here, we show that if the noise acting on the system is unital (non-unital), then the noise acting on the environment must also be unital (non-unital), for the evolution to be unitary in the joint system-environment space. For example, if the first two qubits are treated as system and the third qubit is treated as environment, then both the system and the environment evolve unitally in case of a three-qubit GHZ state, and both of them evolve non-unitally in case of a three-qubit W state. Our result may be of interest in quantum information, and we anticipate it to be useful in various contexts, such as to better tackle noise in quantum computing and quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11956v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anumita Mukhopadhyay, Shibdas Roy, Arun Kumar Pati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveguide QED Analysis of Quantum-Coherent Links for Modular Quantum Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Waveguides potentially offer an effective medium for interconnecting quantum processors within a modular framework, facilitating the coherent quantum state transfer between the qubits across separate chips. In this work, we analyze a quantum communication scenario where two qubits are connected to a shared waveguide, whose resonance frequency may match or not match that of the qubits. Both configurations are simulated from the perspective of quantum electrodynamics (QED) to assess the system behavior and key factors that influence reliable inter-chip communication. The primary performance metrics analyzed are quantum state transfer fidelity and latency, considering the impact of key system parameters such as the qubit-waveguide detuning, coupling strength, waveguide decay rate, and qubit decay rate. We present the system design requirements that yield enhanced state transmission fidelity rates and lowered latency, and discuss the scalability of waveguide-mediated interconnects considering various configurations of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11972v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junaid Khan, Sergio Navarro Reyes, Sahar Ben Rached, Eduard Alarcon, Peter Haring Bolivar, Carmen G. Almudever, Sergi Abadal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Quantum Algorithms for Many-Body Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11985v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) incorporate hybrid quantum-classical computation aimed at harnessing the power of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) computers to solve challenging computational problems. In this thesis, three main VQAs are presented, each tackling a different facet of many-body physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11985v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirko Consiglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Conceptual Framework for Integrating Awareness into Relational Quantum Dynamics (RQD)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a conceptual framework that integrates awareness into Relational Quantum Dynamics (RQD) by reinterpreting quantum interactions as intrinsic acts of awareness. Drawing on insights from quantum physics, idealist philosophies, and quantum information theory, our framework posits that consciousness is the fundamental substrate of being, with awareness emerging through the relational updating of information between interacting systems. We operationalize awareness as the realization of a quantum event-quantified by measures such as mutual information and the integrated information metric ($\Phi$) from Integrated Information Theory (IIT). Employing tools from category theory, we map physical processes, states and interactions, to corresponding awareness processes via functorial relationships, thereby casting measurement updates as awareness events. A toy model is presented in which a simple observer-system interaction is recast in terms of information exchange and Bayesian updating, illustrating how an interaction can give rise to an awareness update. We contrast this awareness-based RQD with existing interpretations, notably Relational Quantum Mechanics (RQM) and Quantum Bayesianism (QBism), arguing that while these approaches acknowledge the role of observers, they do not ascribe an ontological role to awareness. Although experimental tests remain conceptual, potential avenues, including proposals based on quantum gravitational entanglement and observer-dependent phenomena-are discussed. Overall, this roadmap seeks to provide a unified perspective on mind and matter by suggesting that every quantum interaction is a manifestation of an underlying, universal awareness that underpins the fabric of reality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12016v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arash Zaghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of Quantum Coherence and Nonequilibrium Quantum Transport: An Exact Density Matrix Formulation in the Heisenberg Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We aim to bridge the gap between quantum coherence, quantum correlations, and nonequilibrium quantum transport in a quantum double-dot (QDD) system interacting with fermionic reservoirs. The system-reservoir coupling is modeled using a Fano-Anderson-type Hamiltonian. The density operator elements of the QDD system are expressed in terms of expectation values involving various combinations of the fermionic creation and annihilation operators associated with the system. By utilizing the quantum Langevin equation and the Heisenberg equation of motion, we derive the precise temporal behavior of these operator averages in terms of nonequilibrium Green's functions and subsequently obtain the time evolution of the density operator elements. Our approach is valid in both the strong coupling and non-Markovian regimes. Additionally, we examine the time evolution of quantum coherence in the QDD system, quantifying it using standard measures such as the l1-norm and the relative entropy of coherence. As observed, coherence reaches a non-zero steady-state value, highlighting its significant potential for applications in quantum information processing and quantum technologies. Furthermore, we establish a connection between quantum coherence and transport current in a QDD system serially coupled to fermionic reservoirs. We then investigate the effects of coupling strength and reservoir memory by tuning the finite spectral width of the reservoir, examining their impact on both transient and steady-state properties, such as quantum coherence and particle current, which could play a crucial role in ultrafast nanodevice applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12105v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikumar Krithivasan, Thingujam Yaiphalemba Meitei, Arijit Sen, Md Manirul Ali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of negative probabilities: An exact representation of the dynamics of quantum spin chains as classical stochastic processes with particle/antiparticle pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10502v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since the advent of quantum mechanics, classical probability interpretations have faced significant challenges. A notable issue arises with the emergence of negative probabilities when attempting to define the joint probability of non-commutative observables. In this work, we propose a resolution to this dilemma by introducing an exact representation of the dynamics of quantum spin chains using classical continuous-time Markov chains (CTMCs). These CTMCs effectively model the creation, annihilation, and propagation of pairs of classical particles and antiparticles. The quantum dynamics then emerges by averaging over various realizations of this classical process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10502v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultracold long-range van der Waals Rydberg trimer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10555v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rydberg molecules, Rydberg-atom or Rydberg-molecule, are an essential ingredient of cold molecular sciences. However, due to the richness of Rydberg-neutral interactions, new kinds of Rydberg molecules and binding mechanisms are still to be discovered. In this work, we predict the existence of ultra-long-range van der Waals trimers in dilute atom-gas mixtures. These are bound states of a Rydberg atom and a diatomic polar molecule mediated by the long-range van der Waals interaction. This new binding mechanism gives rise to trimers with sizes between 5-500~nm and binding energies between 2 MHz and 0.2 kHz depending on the atomic principal quantum number $n$ and orbital angular momentum $L$. We show that these molecules can be produced via two-photon photoassociation, with rates on the order of (10$^{-13}$ - 10$^{-11}$) cm$^{3}$s$^{-1}$ for temperatures in the range of (0.5 $\mu K$ - 10$\mu K$), and discuss the feasibility of observing trimer resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10555v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateo Londo\~no, Vanessa C. Olaya-Agudelo, Felipe Herrera, Jes\'us P\'erez-R\'ios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of nontrivial local conserved quantities in the quantum compass model on the square lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By extending the method developed by Shiraishi, we prove that the quantum compass model on the square lattice does not possess any local conserved quantities except for the Hamiltonian itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10791v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahiro Futami, Hal Tasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative metasurfaces enabled diverse quantum path entanglement of structured photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement, a fundamental concept in quantum mechanics, lies at the heart of many current and future quantum technologies. A pivotal task is generation and control of diverse quantum entangled states in a more compact and flexible manner. Here, we introduce an approach to achieve diverse path entanglement by exploiting the interaction between noncommutative metasurfaces and entangled photons. Different from other path entanglement, our quantum path entanglement is evolvement path entanglement of photons on Poincar\'e sphere. Due to quantum entanglement between idler photons and structured signal photons, evolvement path of idler photons on the fundamental Poincar\'e sphere can be nonlocally mirrored by structured signal photons on any high-order Poincar\'e sphere, resulting in quantum path entanglement. Benefiting from noncommutative metasurfaces, diverse quantum path entanglement can be switched across different higher-order Poincar\'e spheres using distinct combination sequences of metasurfaces. Our method allows for the tuning of diverse quantum path entanglement across a broad spectrum of quantum states, offering a significant advancement in the manipulation of quantum entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10963v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Wang, Yichang Shou, Jiawei Liu, Qiang Yang, Shizhen Chen, Weixing Shu, Shuangchun Wen, Hailu Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging current flow and injection in scalable graphene devices through NV-magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11076v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The global electronic properties of solid-state devices are strongly affected by the microscopic spatial paths of charge carriers. Visualising these paths in novel devices produced by scalable processes would provide a quality assessment method that can propel the device performance metrics towards commercial use. Here, we use high-resolution nitrogen-vacancy (NV) magnetometry to visualise the charge flow in gold-contacted, single-layer graphene devices produced by scalable methods. Modulating the majority carrier type via field effect reveals a strong asymmetry between the spatial current distributions in the electron and hole regimes that we attribute to an inhomogeneous microscopic potential landscape, inaccessible to conventional measurement techniques. In addition, we observe large, unexpected, differences in charge flow through nominally identical gold-graphene contacts. Moreover, we find that the current transfer into the graphene occurs several microns before the metal contact edge. Our findings establish high-resolution NV-magnetometry as a key tool for characterizing scalable 2D material based devices, uncovering quality deficits of the material, substrate, and electrical contacts that are invisible to conventional methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11076v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaj Dockx, Michele Buscema, Saravana Kumar, Tijmen van Ree, Abbas Mohtashami, Leon van Dooren, Gabriele Bulgarini, Richard van Rijn, Clara I. Osorio, Toeno van der Sar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Standalone FPGA-Based QAOA Emulator for Weighted-MaxCut on Embedded Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum computing QC emulation is crucial for advancing QC applications, especially given the scalability constraints of current devices. FPGA-based designs offer an efficient and scalable alternative to traditional large-scale platforms, but most are tightly integrated with high-performance systems, limiting their use in mobile and edge environments. This study introduces a compact, standalone FPGA-based QC emulator designed for embedded systems, leveraging the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) to solve the Weighted-MaxCut problem. By restructuring QAOA operations for hardware compatibility, the proposed design reduces time complexity from O(N^2) to O(N), where N equals 2^n for n qubits. This reduction, coupled with a pipeline architecture, significantly minimizes resource consumption, enabling support for up to nine qubits on mid-tier FPGAs, roughly three times more than comparable designs. Additionally, the emulator achieved energy savings ranging from 1.53 times for two-qubit configurations to up to 852 times for nine-qubit configurations, compared to software-based QAOA on embedded processors. These results highlight the practical scalability and resource efficiency of the proposed design, providing a robust foundation for QC emulation in resource-constrained edge devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11316v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seonghyun Choi, Kyeongwon Lee, Jae-Jin Lee, Woojoo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-driven losses for atoms in a dark-state lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we estimate the collisional loss rate of ultracold bosons in the optical potential featuring subwavelength-width peaks. This is established by using $\Lambda$ arrangement of three atomic states coupled (almost) resonantly by lasers. Using Fermi's Golden Rule, we find that the loss rate is influenced by the overall strength of the lasers, with the largest losses occurring when the two-photon transition is blue-detuned from the excited state of the $\Lambda$ system. Overall, the predicted loss rates are low, which may allow the use of ultracold bosons in the construction of dark-state potentials in the $\Lambda$-type many-level system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11341v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Kubala, Mateusz \L\k{a}cki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduction of Magnetic-Field-Induced Shift in Quantum Frequency Standards Based on Coherent Population Trapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11587v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the magnetic-field-induced frequency shift (MFS) of the clock "0-0" transition in the microwave quantum frequency standard (atomic clock) based on coherent population trapping (CPT) in $^{87}$Rb vapor. To scan the CPT resonance and to form the error signal, a method analogous to the Pound-Drever-Hall (PDH) technique in the optical frequency range is employed, where the modulating frequency ($f_m$) significantly exceeds the resonance linewidth (FWHM). The experiments demonstrate that this technique offers brilliant capabilities for controlling the sensitivity of the clock transition frequency to magnetic field variations in the vapor cell compared to the conventional method with low-frequency modulation ($f_m$$\,\ll\,$FWHM). Specifically, the PDH technique provides several optimal values of the bias magnetic field generated by the solenoid, at which the "0-0" transition frequency exhibits extremely low sensitivity to small variations in the external magnetic field. Furthermore, these magnetic field values can be easily adjusted by changing $f_m$, which is relevant for optimization of the atomic clock's operating regime. The experimental results show that by using the PDH technique, the influence of MFS on the clock transition can be suppressed down to $\approx\,$$3.2$$\,\times\,$$10^{-13}$$\delta B^2$ mG$^{-2}$. These findings can be leveraged both to relax stringent requirements for magnetic field shielding in state-of-the-art CPT-based miniature atomic clocks (MACs) and to build a new generation of such clocks with long-term frequency stability better than $10^{-12}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11587v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Vishnyakov, D. V. Brazhnikov, M. N. Skvortsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitary orthonormal bases of finite dimensional inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11821v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study unitary orthonormal bases in the sense of Pimsner and Popa for inclusions $(\mathcal{B}\subseteq \mathcal{A}, E),$ where $\mathcal{A}, \mathcal{B}$ are finite dimensional von Neumann algebras and $E$ is a conditional expectation map from $\mathcal{A}$ onto $\mathcal{B}$. It is shown that existence of such bases requires that the associated inclusion matrix satisfies a spectral condition forcing dimension vectors to be Perron-Frobenius eigenvectors and the conditional expectation map preserves the Markov trace. Subject to these conditions, explicit unitary orthonormal bases are constructed if either one of the algebras is abelian or simple. They generalize complex Hadamard matrices, Weyl unitary bases, and a recent work of Crann et al which correspond to the special cases of $\mathcal{A}$ being abelian, simple, and general multi-matrix algebras respectively with $\mathcal{B}$ being the algebra of complex numbers. For the first time $\mathcal{B}$ is more general. As an application of these results it is shown that if $(\mathcal{B}\subseteq \mathcal{A}, E),$ admits a unitary orthonormal basis then the Connes-St{\o}rmer relative entropy $H(\mathcal{A}_1|\mathcal{A})$ equals the logarithm of the square of the norm of the inclusion matrix, where $\mathcal{A}_1$ denotes the Jones basic construction of the inclusion. As a further application, we prove the existence of unitary orthonormal bases for a large class of depth 2 subfactors with abelian relative commutant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11821v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keshab Chandra Bakshi, B V Rajarama Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qubit-Based Framework for Quantum Machine Learning: Bridging Classical Data and Quantum Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper dives into the exciting and rapidly growing field of quantum computing, explaining its core ideas, current progress, and how it could revolutionize the way we solve complex problems. It starts by breaking down the basics, like qubits, quantum circuits, and how principles like superposition and entanglement make quantum computers fundamentally different-and far more powerful for certain tasks-than the classical computers we use today. We also explore how quantum computing deals with complex problems and why it is uniquely suited for challenges classical systems struggle to handle. A big part of this paper focuses on Quantum Machine Learning (QML), where the strengths of quantum computing meet the world of artificial intelligence. By processing massive datasets and optimizing intricate algorithms, quantum systems offer new possibilities for machine learning. We highlight different approaches to combining quantum and classical computing, showing how they can work together to produce faster and more accurate results. Additionally, we explore the tools and platforms available-like TensorFlow Quantum, Qiskit and PennyLane-that are helping researchers and developers bring these theories to life. Of course, quantum computing has its hurdles. Challenges like scaling up hardware, correcting errors, and keeping qubits stable are significant roadblocks. Yet, with rapid advancements in cloud-based platforms and innovative technologies, the potential of quantum computing feels closer than ever. This paper aims to offer readers a clear and comprehensive introduction to quantum computing, its role in machine learning, and the immense possibilities it holds for the future of technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11951v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhavna Bose, Saurav Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Hard Maximum Cut Instances for Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12012v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms, such as the Recursive Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (RQAOA), have become increasingly popular, offering promising avenues for employing Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum devices to address challenging combinatorial optimization tasks like the maximum cut problem. In this study, we utilize an evolutionary algorithm equipped with a unique fitness function. This approach targets hard maximum cut instances within the latent space of a Graph Autoencoder, identifying those that pose significant challenges or are particularly tractable for RQAOA, in contrast to the classic Goemans and Williamson algorithm. Our findings not only delineate the distinct capabilities and limitations of each algorithm but also expand our understanding of RQAOA's operational limits. Furthermore, the diverse set of graphs we have generated serves as a crucial benchmarking asset, emphasizing the need for more advanced algorithms to tackle combinatorial optimization challenges. Additionally, our results pave the way for new avenues in graph generation research, offering exciting opportunities for future explorations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12012v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaiqun Pan, Yash J. Patel, Aneta Neumann, Frank Neumann, Thomas B\"ack, Hao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic Gauge Potential as a Tool for Detecting Chaos in Classical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12046v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interplay between chaos and thermalization in weakly non-integrable systems is a rich and complex subject. Interest in this area is further motivated by a desire to develop a unified picture of chaos for both quantum and classical systems. In this work, we study the adiabatic gauge potential (AGP), an object typically studied in quantum mechanics that describes deformations of a quantum state under adiabatic variation of the Hamiltonian, in classical Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou (FPUT) and Toda models. We show how the time variance of the AGP over a trajectory probes the long-time correlations of a generic observable and can be used to distinguish among nearly integrable, weakly chaotic, and strongly chaotic regimes. We draw connections between the evolution of the AGP and diffusion and derive a fluctuation-dissipation relation that connects its variance to long-time correlations of the observable. Within this framework, we demonstrate that strongly and weakly chaotic regimes correspond to normal and anomalous diffusion, respectively. The latter gives rise to a marked increase in the variance as the time interval is increased, and this behavior serves as the basis for our probe of the onset times of chaos. Numerical results are presented for FPUT and Toda systems that highlight integrable, weakly chaotic, and strongly chaotic regimes. We conclude by commenting on the wide applicability of our method to a broader class of systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12046v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nachiket Karve, Nathan Rose, David Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Wyner and Ziv Met Bayes in Quantum-Classical Realm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we address the lossy quantum-classical source coding with the quantum side-information (QC-QSI) problem. The task is to compress the classical information about a quantum source, obtained after performing a measurement while incurring a bounded reconstruction error. Here, the decoder is allowed to use the side information to recover the classical data obtained from measurements on the source states. We introduce a new formulation based on a backward (posterior) channel, replacing the single-letter distortion observable with a single-letter posterior channel to capture reconstruction error. Unlike the rate-distortion framework, this formulation imposes a block error constraint. An analogous formulation is developed for lossy classical source coding with classical side information (C-CSI) problem. We derive an inner bound on the asymptotic performance limit in terms of single-letter quantum and classical mutual information quantities of the given posterior channel for QC-QSI and C-CSI cases, respectively. Furthermore, we establish a connection between rate-distortion and rate-channel theory, showing that a rate-channel compression protocol attains the optimal rate-distortion function for a specific distortion measure and level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12129v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Aamir Sohail, Touheed Anwar Atif, S. Sandeep Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reliable Simulation of Quantum Channels: the Error Exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.04475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.04475v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Quantum Reverse Shannon Theorem has been a milestone in quantum information theory. It states that asymptotically reliable simulation of a quantum channel, assisted by unlimited shared entanglement, requires a rate of classical communication equal to the channel's entanglement-assisted classical capacity. In this paper, we study the error exponent of quantum channel simulation, which characterizes the optimal speed of exponential convergence of the performance towards the perfect, as the blocklength increases. Based on channel purified distance, we derive lower and upper bounds for the error exponent. Then we show that the two bounds coincide when the classical communication rate is below a critical value, and hence, we have determined the exact formula of the error exponent in the low-rate case. This enables us to obtain an operational interpretation to the channel's sandwiched R\'enyi information of order from 1 to 2, since our formula is expressed as a transform of this quantity. In the derivation, we have also obtained an achievability bound for quantum channel simulation in the finite-blocklength setting, which is of realistic significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.04475v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2024.3487417</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Tran. Inf. Theory 71(1), 518-529 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ke Li, Yongsheng Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A reconstruction of quantum theory for spinning particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.13364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.13364v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As part of a probabilistic reconstruction of quantum theory (QT), we show that spin is not a purely quantum mechanical phenomenon, as has long been assumed. Rather, this phenomenon occurs before the transition to QT takes place, namely in the area of the quasi-classical (here better quasi-quantum) theory. This borderland between classical physics and QT can be reached within the framework of our reconstruction by the replacement $p \rightarrow M (q, t)$, where $p$ is the momentum variable of the particle and $M(q, t)$ is the momentum field in configuration space. The occurrence of spin, and its special value $1/2$ , is a consequence of the fact that $M(q,t)$ must have exactly three independent components $M_{k}(q,t)$ for a single particle because of the three-dimensionality of space. In the Schr\"odinger equation for a "particle with spin zero", the momentum field is usually represented as a gradient of a single function $S$. This implies dependencies between the components $M_{k}(q,t)$ for which no explanation exists. In reality, $M(q,t)$ needs to be represented by three functions, two of which are rotational degrees of freedom. The latter are responsible for the existence of spin. All massive structureless particles in nature must therefore be spin-one-half particles, simply because they have to be described by $4$ real fields, one of which has the physical meaning of a probability density, while the other three are required to represent the momentum field in three-dimensional space. We derive the Pauli-Schr\"odinger equation, the correct value $g=2$ of the gyromagnetic ratio, the classical limit of the Pauli-Schr\"odinger equation, and clarify some other open questions in the borderland between classical physics and QT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.13364v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulf Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum signatures of chaos in noisy tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.11221v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: How does quantum chaos lead to rapid scrambling of information as well as errors across a system when one introduces perturbations in the dynamics? What are its consequences for the reliability of quantum simulations and quantum information processing? We employ continuous measurement quantum tomography as a paradigm to study these questions. The measurement record is generated as a sequence of expectation values of a Hermitian observable evolving under repeated application of the Floquet map of the quantum kicked top. Interestingly, we find that the reconstruction fidelity initially increases regardless of the degree of chaos or the strength of perturbations in the dynamics. For random states, when the measurement record is obtained from a random initial observable, the subsequent drop in the fidelity obtained is inversely correlated to the degree of chaos in the dynamics. More importantly, this also gives us an operational interpretation of Loschmidt echo for operators by connecting it to the performance of quantum tomography. We define a quantity to capture the scrambling of errors, an out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC) between two operators under perturbed and unperturbed system dynamics that serves as a signature of chaos and quantifies the spread of errors. Our results demonstrate not only a fundamental link between Loschmidt echo and scrambling of errors, as captured by "error OTOCs", but that such a link can have operational consequences in quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.11221v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abinash Sahu, Naga Dileep Varikuti, Vaibhav Madhok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk-to-boundary anyon fusion from microscopic models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.01835v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological quantum error correction based on the manipulation of the anyonic defects constitutes one of the most promising frameworks towards realizing fault-tolerant quantum devices. Hence, it is crucial to understand how these defects interact with external defects such as boundaries or domain walls. Motivated by this line of thought, in this work, we study the fusion events between anyons in the bulk and at the boundary in fixed-point models of 2+1-dimensional non-chiral topological order defined by arbitrary fusion categories. Our construction uses generalized tube algebra techniques to construct a bi-representation of bulk and boundary defects. We explicitly derive a formula to calculate the fusion multiplicities of a bulk-to-boundary fusion event for twisted quantum double models and calculate some exemplary fusion events for Abelian models and the (twisted) quantum double model of S3, the simplest non-Abelian group-theoretical model. Moreover, we use the folding trick to study the anyonic behavior at non-trivial domain walls between twisted S3 and twisted Z2 as well as Z3 models. A recurring theme in our construction is an isomorphism relating twisted cohomology groups to untwisted ones. The results of this work can directly be applied to study logical operators in two-dimensional topological error correcting codes with boundaries described by a twisted gauge theory of a finite group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.01835v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0147335</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 64, 111904 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julio C. Magdalena de la Fuente, Jens Eisert, Andreas Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of quantum temporal correlations well beyond Luders bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.06590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum correlations, both spatial and temporal, are the central pillars of quantum mechanics. Over the last two decades, a big breakthrough in quantum physics is its complex extension to the non-Hermitian realm, and dizzying varieties of novel phenomena and applications beyond the Hermitian framework have been uncovered. However, unique features of non-Hermitian quantum correlations, especially in the time domain, still remain to be explored. Here, for the first time, we experimentally achieve this goal by using a parity-time (PT)-symmetric trapped-ion system. The upper limit of temporal quantum correlations, known as the algebraic bound, which has so far not been achieved in the standard measurement scenario, is reached here by approaching the exceptional point (EP), thus showing the unexpected ability of EPs in tuning temporal quantum correlation effects. Our study, unveiling the fundamental interplay of non-Hermiticity, nonlinearity, and temporal quantum correlations, provides the first step towards exploring and utilizing various non-Hermitian temporal quantum effects by operating a wide range of EP devices, which are important for both fundamental studies and applications of quantum EP systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.06590v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013058</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013058 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chun-Wang Wu, Man-Chao Zhang, Yan-Li Zhou, Ting Chen, Ran Huang, Yi Xie, Wen-bo Su Bao-Quan Ou, Wei Wu, Adam Miranowicz, Franco Nori, Jie Zhang, Hui Jing, Ping-Xing Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Border Ranks of Positive and Invariant Tensor Decompositions: Applications to Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13478v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The matrix rank and its positive versions are robust for small approximations, i.e. they do not decrease under small perturbations. In contrast, the multipartite tensor rank can collapse for arbitrarily small errors, i.e. there may be a gap between rank and border rank, leading to instabilities in the optimization over sets with fixed tensor rank. Can multipartite positive ranks also collapse for small perturbations? In this work, we prove that multipartite positive and invariant tensor decompositions exhibit gaps between rank and border rank, including tensor rank purifications and cyclic separable decompositions. We also prove a correspondence between positive decompositions and membership in certain sets of multipartite probability distributions, and leverage the gaps between rank and border rank to prove that these correlation sets are not closed. It follows that testing membership of probability distributions arising from resources like translational invariant Matrix Product States is impossible in finite time. Overall, this work sheds light on the instability of ranks and the unique behavior of bipartite systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13478v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Klingler, Tim Netzer, Gemma De les Coves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Virtual Quantum Device (VQD): A tool for detailed emulation of quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07342v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the Virtual Quantum Device (VQD) platform, a system based on the QuEST quantum emulator. Through the use of VQDs, non-expert users can emulate specific quantum computers with detailed error models, bespoke gate sets and connectivities. The platform boasts an intuitive interface, powerful visualisation, and compatibility with high-performance computation for effective testing and optimisation of complex quantum algorithms or ideas across a range of quantum computing hardware. We create and explore five families of VQDs corresponding to trapped ions, nitrogen-vacancy-centres, neutral atom arrays, silicon quantum dot spins, and superconducting devices. Each is highly configurable through a set of tailored parameters. We showcase the key characteristics of each virtual device, providing practical examples of the tool's usefulness and highlighting each device's specific attributes. By offering user-friendly encapsulated descriptions of diverse quantum hardware, the VQD platform offers researchers the ability to rapidly explore algorithms and protocols in a realistic setting; meanwhile hardware experts can create their own VQDs to compare with their experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07342v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cica Gustiani, Tyson Jones, Simon C. Benjamin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online calibration scheme for training restricted Boltzmann machines with quantum annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a scheme to calibrate the internal parameters of a quantum annealer to obtain well-approximated samples for training a restricted Boltzmann machine (RBM). Empirically, samples from quantum annealers obey the Boltzmann distribution, making them suitable for RBM training. Quantum annealers utilize physical phenomena to generate a large number of samples in a short time. However, hardware imperfections make it challenging to obtain accurate samples. Existing research often estimates the inverse temperature for the compensation. Our scheme efficiently utilizes samples for RBM training also to estimate internal parameters. Furthermore, we consider additional parameters and demonstrate that they improve sample quality. We evaluate our approach by comparing the obtained samples with classical Gibbs sampling, which theoretically generates accurate samples. Our results indicate that our scheme demonstrates performance on par with Gibbs sampling. In addition, the training results with our estimation scheme outperform those of the contrastive divergence algorithm, a standard training algorithm for RBM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09785v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.034002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 034002 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takeru Goto, Masayuki Ohzeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quaternary Neural Belief Propagation Decoding of Quantum LDPC Codes with Overcomplete Check Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08208v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes are promising candidates for error correction in quantum computers. One of the major challenges in implementing QLDPC codes in quantum computers is the lack of a universal decoder. In this work, we first propose to decode QLDPC codes with a belief propagation (BP) decoder operating on overcomplete check matrices. Then, we extend the neural BP (NBP) decoder, which was originally studied for suboptimal binary BP decoding of QLPDC codes, to quaternary BP decoders. Numerical simulation results demonstrate that both approaches as well as their combination yield a low-latency, high-performance decoder for several short to moderate length QLDPC codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08208v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2025.3539475</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>S. Miao, A. Schnerring, H. Li and L. Schmalen, "Quaternary Neural Belief Propagation Decoding of Quantum LDPC Codes With Overcomplete Check Matrices," in IEEE Access, vol. 13, pp. 25637-25649, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sisi Miao, Alexander Schnerring, Haizheng Li, Laurent Schmalen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomized term grouping over physical law on digital quantum simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14378v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a randomized algorithm based on qDrift to compute Hamiltonian dynamics on digital quantum computers. We frame it as physDrift because conservation laws in physics are obeyed during evolution of arbitrary quantum states. Empirically we achieved better spectral error reduction with hydrogen chain model compared to previous protocols. Noisy model are investigated as well and we characterised them in the circuit with different schemes, i.e. an attenuation of the measured expectation value is fixed by keeping the circuit depth the same and depolarising error is simulated with randomly applied Pauli gates. This makes it our proposal particularly feasible for implementing and testing on present-day noisy hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14378v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songqinghao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling reduced density matrix to extract fine levels of entanglement spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16709v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Low-lying entanglement spectrum provides the quintessential fingerprint to identify the highly entangled quantum matter with topological and conformal field-theoretical properties. However, when the entangling region acquires long boundary with the environment, such as that between long coupled chains or in two or higher dimensions, there unfortunately exists no universal yet practical method to compute the entanglement spectra with affordable computational cost. Here we propose a new scheme to overcome such difficulty and successfully extract the low-lying fine entanglement spectrum (ES). We trace out the environment via quantum Monte Carlo simulation and diagonalize the reduced density matrix to gain the ES. We demonstrate the strength and reliability of our method through long coupled spin chains and answer its long-standing controversy. Our simulation results, with unprecedentedly large system sizes, establish the practical computation scheme of the entanglement spectrum with a huge freedom degree of environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16709v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin-Bin Mao, Yi-Ming Ding, Zheng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application-level Benchmarking of Quantum Computers using Nonlocal Game Strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01363v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a nonlocal game, two noncommunicating players cooperate to convince a referee that they possess a strategy that does not violate the rules of the game. Quantum strategies allow players to optimally win some games by performing joint measurements on a shared entangled state, but computing these strategies can be challenging. We present a variational quantum algorithm to compute quantum strategies for nonlocal games by encoding the rules of a nonlocal game into a Hamiltonian. We show how this algorithm can generate a short-depth optimal quantum strategy for a graph coloring game with a quantum advantage. This quantum strategy is then evaluated on fourteen different quantum hardware platforms to demonstrate its utility as a benchmark. Finally, we discuss potential sources of errors that can explain the observed decreased performance of the executed task and derive an expression for the number of samples required to accurately estimate the win rate in the presence of noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01363v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jim Furches, Sarah Chehade, Kathleen Hamilton, Nathan Wiebe, Carlos Ortiz Marrero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Computational Advantage of MIP* Vanishes in the Presence of Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04360v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum multiprover interactive proof systems with entanglement MIP* are much more powerful than its classical counterpart MIP (Babai et al. '91, Ji et al. '20): while MIP = NEXP, the quantum class MIP* is equal to RE, a class including the halting problem. This is because the provers in MIP* can share unbounded quantum entanglement. However, recent works of Qin and Yao '21 and '23 have shown that this advantage is significantly reduced if the provers' shared state contains noise. This paper attempts to exactly characterize the effect of noise on the computational power of quantum multiprover interactive proof systems. We investigate the quantum two-prover one-round interactive system MIP*[poly, O(1)], where the verifier sends polynomially many bits to the provers and the provers send back constantly many bits. We show noise completely destroys the computational advantage given by shared entanglement in this model. Specifically, we show that if the provers are allowed to share arbitrarily many noisy EPR states, where each EPR state is affected by an arbitrarily small constant amount of noise, the resulting complexity class is equivalent to NEXP = MIP. This improves significantly on the previous best-known bound of NEEEXP (nondeterministic triply exponential time) by Qin and Yao '21. We also show that this collapse in power is due to the noise, rather than the O(1) answer size, by showing that allowing for noiseless EPR states gives the class the full power of RE = MIP*[poly, poly]. Along the way, we develop two technical tools of independent interest. First, we give a new, deterministic tester for the positivity of an exponentially large matrix, provided it has a low-degree Fourier decomposition in terms of Pauli matrices. Secondly, we develop a new invariance principle for smooth matrix functions having bounded third-order Fr\'echet derivatives or which are Lipschitz continous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04360v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangjing Dong, Honghao Fu, Anand Natarajan, Minglong Qin, Haochen Xu, Penghui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal entanglement in cavity magnomechanics exploiting chiral cavity-magnon coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02280v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new mechanism to achieve nonreciprocal quantum entanglement in a cavity magnomechanical system by exploiting the chiral cavity-magnon coupling. The system consists of a magnon mode, a mechanical vibration mode, and two degenerate counter-propagating microwave cavity modes in a torus-shaped cavity. We show that nonreciprocal stationary microwave-magnon and -phonon bipartite entanglements and photon-magnon-phonon tripartite entanglement can be achieved by respectively driving different circulating cavity modes that hold a chiral coupling to the magnon mode. The nonreciprocal entanglements are shown to be robust against various experimental imperfections. We specifically show how such nonreciprocal entanglement can realize the channel multiplexing quantum teleportation from a microwave field to a solid-state magnon mode. The work may find promising applications of the cavity magnomechanical systems in noise-tolerant quantum processing, channel multiplexing quantum teleportation, and chiral magnonic quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02280v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Yuan Fan, Xuan Zuo, Hao-Tian Li, Jie Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practicality of training a quantum-classical machine in the NISQ era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12089v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Advancements in classical computing have significantly enhanced machine learning applications, yet inherent limitations persist in terms of energy, resource and speed. Quantum machine learning algorithms offer a promising avenue to overcome these limitations but poses its own hurdles. This experimental study explores the limits of training a real experimental quantum classical hybrid system using supervised training protocols, on an ion trap platform. Challenges associated with ion trap-coupled classical processors are addressed, highlighting the $robustness$ of the genetic algorithm as a classical optimizer in navigating the noisy channels of NISQ-devices and the complex optimization landscape inherent in binary classification problems with many local minima. We intricately discuss why gradient-based optimizers may not be suitable in the NISQ era through a thorough analysis. These findings contribute insights into the performance of quantum-classical hybrid systems, emphasizing the significance of efficient training strategies and hardware considerations for practical quantum machine learning applications. This work not only advances the understanding of hybrid quantum-classical systems but also underscores the potential impact on real-world challenges through the convergence of quantum and classical computing paradigms operating without the aid of classical simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12089v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tarun Dutta, Alex Jin, Clarence Liu Huihong, J I Latorre, Manas Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficacy of tomographic markers of photon addition to coherent states of light: Comparison with experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Photon addition to quantum states of light is of immense current interest, both experimentally and theoretically. We identify a set of markers of photon addition to coherent states of light, which are directly computable from relevant optical tomograms. The amplification gain due to photon addition, and the dependence of quadrature variances on relevant parameters, are calculated from the tomograms and compared with results from a recent experiment, obtained after state reconstruction. Our results match well with the fidelity plots reported by the experimenters. These markers could provide a viable procedure to characterize specific aspects of photon addition to light from the corresponding tomograms themselves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16098v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumyabrata Paul, S. Lakshmibala, V. Balakrishnan, S. Ramanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin coherence in strongly coupled spin baths in quasi-two-dimensional layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16169v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the spin-coherence decay of NV$^-$-spins interacting with the strongly-coupled bath of nitrogen defects in diamond layers. For thin diamond layers, we demonstrate that the spin-coherence times exceed those of bulk diamond, thus allowing to surpass the limit imposed by high defect concentrations in bulk. We show that the stretched-exponential parameter for the short-time spin-coherence decay is governed by the hyperfine interaction in the bath, thereby constraining random-noise models. We introduce a novel method based on the cluster-correlation expansion applied to strongly-interacting bath partitions. Our results facilitate material development for quantum-technology devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16169v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.L220302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, L220302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Philip Sch\"atzle, Reyhaneh Ghassemizadeh, Daniel F. Urban, Thomas Wellens, Peter Knittel, Florentin Reiter, Jan Jeske, Walter Hahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-variable quantum key distribution with noisy squeezed states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address the role of noisy squeezing in security and performance of continuous-variable (CV) quantum key distribution (QKD) protocols. Squeezing has long been recognized for its numerous advantages in CV QKD, such as enhanced robustness against channel noise and loss, and improved secret key rates. However, the noise of the squeezed states, that unavoidably originates already from optical loss in the source, raises concerns about its potential exploitation by an eavesdropper. This is particularly relevant if this noise is pessimistically assumed untrusted. We address the allocation of untrusted noise within a squeezed state and show that anti-squeezing noise is typically more harmful for security of the protocols, as it potentially provides more information to an eavesdropper. Although the anti-squeezing noise may not directly contribute to the generated key data, it is involved in parameter estimation and can in fact be harmful even if considered trusted. Our study covers the effects of anti-squeezing noise in both the asymptotic and finite-size regimes. We highlight the positive effects and limitations of imposing trust assumption on anti-squeezing noise. Additionally, we emphasize the detrimental impact of untrusted noise in both fiber and free-space fading links. Our findings offer essential insights for practical implementations and optimization of squeezed-state CV QKD protocols in realistic scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05247v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash nag Oruganti, Ivan Derkach, Radim Filip, Vladyslav C. Usenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden multi-dimensional modulation side channels in quantum protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14216v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum protocols including quantum key distribution and blind quantum computing often require the preparation of quantum states of known dimensions. Here, we show that, rather surprisingly, hidden multi-dimensional modulation is often performed by practical devices. This violates the dimensional assumption in quantum protocols, thus creating side channels and security loopholes. Our work has important impacts on the security of quantum cryptographic protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14216v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amita Gnanapandithan, Li Qian, Hoi-Kwong Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driven transitions between megastable quantized orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03906v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a nonlinear oscillator with state-dependent time-delay that displays a countably infinite number of nested limit cycle attractors, \emph{i.e.} megastability. In the low-memory regime, the equation reduces to a self-excited nonlinear oscillator and we use averaging methods to analytically show quasilinear increasing amplitude of the megastable spectrum of quantized quasicircular orbits. We further assign a mechanical energy to each orbit using the Lyapunov energy function and obtain a quadratically increasing energy spectrum and (almost) constant frequency spectrum. We demonstrate transitions between different quantized orbits, i.e. different energy levels, by subjecting the system to an external finite-time harmonic driving. For large driving amplitude with frequency close to the limit cycle frequency, resonance drives transitions to higher energy levels. Alternatively, for large driving amplitude with frequency slightly detuned from limit-cycle frequency, beating effects can lead to transitions to lower energy levels. Such driven transitions between quantized orbits form a classical analog of quantum jumps. For excitations to higher energy levels, we show amplitude locking where nearby values of driving amplitudes result in the same response amplitude, i.e. the same final higher energy level. We rationalize this effect based on the basins of different limit cycles in phase space. From a practical viewpoint, our work might find applications in physical and engineering system where controlled transitions between several limit cycles of a multistable dynamical system is desired.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03906v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Alvaro G. L\'opez, Rahil N. Valani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary Time Crystals as AC sensors: enhancements and constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06273v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the use of a boundary time crystals (BTCs) as quantum sensors of AC fields. Boundary time crystals are non-equilibrium phases of matter in contact to an environment, for which a macroscopic fraction of the many-body system breaks the time translation symmetry. We find an enhanced sensitivity of the BTC when its spins are resonant with the applied AC field, as quantified by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). The QFI dynamics in this regime is shown to be captured by a relatively simple ansatz consisting of an initial power-law growth and late-time exponential decay. We study the scaling of the ansatz parameters with resources (encoding time and number of spins) and identify a moderate quantum enhancement in the sensor performance through comparison with classical QFI bounds. Investigating the precise source of this performance, we find that despite of its long coherence time and multipartite correlations (advantageous properties for quantum metrology), the entropic cost of the BTC (which grows indefinitely in the thermodynamic limit) hinders an optimal decoding of the AC field information. This result has implications for future candidates of quantum sensors in open system and we hope it will encourage future study into the role of entropy in quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06273v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic Gribben, Anna Sanpera, Rosario Fazio, Jamir Marino, Fernando Iemini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Low-Depth Quantum Signal-Processing Phase Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01583v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum effects like entanglement and coherent amplification can be used to drastically enhance the accuracy of quantum parameter estimation beyond classical limits. However, challenges such as decoherence and time-dependent errors hinder Heisenberg-limited amplification. We introduce Quantum Signal-Processing Phase Estimation algorithms that are robust against these challenges and achieve optimal performance as dictated by the Cram\'{e}r-Rao bound. These algorithms use quantum signal transformation to decouple interdependent phase parameters into largely orthogonal ones, ensuring that time-dependent errors in one do not compromise the accuracy of learning the other. Combining provably optimal classical estimation with near-optimal quantum circuit design, our approach achieves a standard deviation accuracy of $10^{-4}$ radians for estimating unwanted swap angles in superconducting two-qubit experiments, using low-depth ($&lt;10$) circuits. This represents up to two orders of magnitude improvement over existing methods. Theoretically and numerically, we demonstrate the optimality of our algorithm against time-dependent phase errors, observing that the variance of the time-sensitive parameter $\varphi$ scales faster than the asymptotic Heisenberg scaling in the small-depth regime. Our results are rigorously validated against the quantum Fisher information, confirming our protocol's ability to achieve unmatched precision for two-qubit gate learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01583v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-56724-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, no. 1 (2025): 1504</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yulong Dong, Jonathan A. Gross, Murphy Yuezhen Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violation of the Leggett-Garg inequality for dynamics of a Bose-Einstein condensate in a double-well potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05304v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Leggett-Garg inequality (LGI) serves as a criterion to determine the adherence of macroscopic system dynamics to macrorealism, as introduced by Leggett and Garg. A violation of this inequality implies either the absence of a realistic description of the system or the impossibility of noninvasive measurement. In this Letter, we investigate the violation of the LGI for the system of bosons in a double-well potential. Specifically, we explore the violation of the LGI in the dynamics of bosons in a double-well potential in the Bose-Einstein-condensation (BEC) regime, where the system can be considered as two weakly coupled Bose condensates, and in the single-particle regime to establish the conditions under which the violation of the LGI occurs. Our analysis reveals that the LGI is violated due to Josephson oscillations, while it remains unviolated in the strong coupling regime, attributed to the self-trapping phenomena. Notably, we observe that the violation of the LGI becomes increasingly significant as the particle number increases. These findings provide valuable insights into the macrorealistic behavior of Bose condensates and highlight the effect of measurements on the dynamics of a macroscopic system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05304v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.L021302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, L021302 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tsubasa Sakamoto, Ryosuke Yoshii, Shunji Tsuchiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of nonclassical properties of two-mode squeezed vacuum state with postselected von Neumann measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11367v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of weak value amplification on the nonclassical properties of two-mode squeezing vacuum state. To show the advantages of the two-mode squeezing vacuum state based post-selective weak measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11367v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.052611</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 052611,2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Janarbek Yuanbek, Yi-Fang Ren, Ahmad Abliz, Yusuf Turek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reliability Function of Classical-Quantum Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12403v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the reliability function of general classical-quantum channels, which describes the optimal exponent of the decay of decoding error when the communication rate is below the capacity. As the main result, we prove a lower bound, in terms of the quantum Renyi information in Petz's form, for the reliability function. This resolves Holevo's conjecture proposed in 2000, a long-standing open problem in quantum information theory. It turns out that the obtained lower bound matches the upper bound derived by Dalai in 2013, when the communication rate is above a critical value. Thus, we have determined the reliability function in this high-rate case. Our approach relies on Renes' breakthrough made in 2022, which relates classical-quantum channel coding to that of privacy amplification, as well as our new characterization of the channel Renyi information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12403v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.010802</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 010802 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ke Li, Dong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High ground state overlap via quantum embedding methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum computers can accurately compute ground state energies using phase estimation, but this requires a guiding state that has significant overlap with the true ground state. For large molecules and extended materials, it becomes difficult to find guiding states with good ground state overlap for growing molecule sizes. Additionally, the required number of qubits and quantum gates may become prohibitively large. One approach for dealing with these challenges is to use a quantum embedding method, which allows a reduction to one or multiple smaller quantum cores embedded in a larger quantum region. In such situations it is unclear how the embedding method affects the hardness of constructing good guiding states. In this work, we therefore investigate the preparation of guiding states in the context of quantum embedding methods. We extend previous work on quantum impurity problems, a framework in which we can rigorously analyze the embedding of a subset of orbitals. While there exist results for optimal active orbital space selection in terms of energy minimization, we rigorously demonstrate how the same principles can be used to define selected orbital spaces for state preparation in terms of the overlap with the ground state. Moreover, we perform numerical studies of molecular systems relevant to biochemistry, one field in which quantum embedding methods are required due to the large size of biomacromolecules such as proteins and nucleic acids. We investigate two different embedding strategies which can exhibit qualitatively different orbital entanglement. In all cases we demonstrate that the easy-to-obtain mean-field state will have a sufficiently high overlap with the target state to perform quantum phase estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01940v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXLife.3.013003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Life 3 (2025) 013003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mihael Erakovic, Freek Witteveen, Dylan Harley, Jakob G\"unther, Moritz Bensberg, Oinam Romesh Meitei, Minsik Cho, Troy Van Voorhis, Markus Reiher, Matthias Christandl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Correlated Errors on Quantum Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08786v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent results on constant overhead LDPC code-based fault-tolerance against i.i.d. errors naturally lead to the question of fault-tolerance against errors with long-range correlations. Ideally, any correlation can be captured by a joint (system and bath) Hamiltonian. However, an arbitrary joint Hamiltonian is often intractable, and hence, the joint Hamiltonian model with pairwise terms was introduced and developed in a series of foundational works. However, the analysis of the new constant overhead codes in that error model appears to be quite challenging. In this paper, to model correlated errors in quantum memory, we introduce a correlation model which is a generalization of the well-known hidden random fields. This proposed model, which includes stationary and ergodic (non-Markov) error distributions, is shown to capture correlations not captured by the joint Hamiltonian model with pairwise terms. On the other hand, building on non-i.i.d. measure concentration, we show that for a broad class of non-Markov and (possibly) non-stationary error distributions, quantum Tanner codes ensure an exponential retention time (in the number of physical qubits), when the error rate is below a threshold. An implication of these results is that the rate of decay of the correlation with distance does not necessarily differentiate between good and bad correlation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08786v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Smita Bagewadi, Avhishek Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetry Amplification by a Nonadiabatic Passage through a Critical Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15897v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose and solve a minimal model of dynamic passage through a second-order phase transition in the presence of symmetry breaking interactions and no dissipation. Our model generalizes the Hamiltonian dynamics of the Painleve'-2 equation to the case with many degrees of freedom, while maintaining the integrability property. The evolution eventually leads to a highly asymmetric state, no matter how weak the symmetry breaking parameter of the Hamiltonian is. This suggests a potential mechanism for strong asymmetry in the production of quasi-particles with nearly identical characteristics. The model's integrability also yields exact exponents for the scaling of the density of the nonadiabatically excited quasi-particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15897v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhavay Tyagi, Fumika Suzuki, Vladimir A. Chernyak, Nikolai A. Sinitsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudospectral method for solving PDEs using Matrix Product States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02916v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This research focuses on solving time-dependent partial differential equations (PDEs), in particular the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation, using matrix product states (MPS). We propose an extension of Hermite Distributed Approximating Functionals (HDAF) to MPS, a highly accurate pseudospectral method for approximating functions of derivatives. Integrating HDAF into an MPS finite precision algebra, we test four types of quantum-inspired algorithms for time evolution: explicit Runge-Kutta methods, Crank-Nicolson method, explicitly restarted Arnoli iteration and split-step. The benchmark problem is the expansion of a particle in a quantum quench, characterized by a rapid increase in space requirements, where HDAF surpasses traditional finite difference methods in accuracy with a comparable cost. Moreover, the efficient HDAF approximation to the free propagator avoids the need for Fourier transforms in split-step methods, significantly enhancing their performance with an improved balance in cost and accuracy. Both approaches exhibit similar error scaling and run times compared to FFT vector methods; however, MPS offer an exponential advantage in memory, overcoming vector limitations to enable larger discretizations and expansions. Finally, the MPS HDAF split-step method successfully reproduces the physical behavior of a particle expansion in a double-well potential, demonstrating viability for actual research scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02916v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Gidi, Paula Garc\'ia-Molina, Luca Tagliacozzo, Juan Jos\'e Garc\'ia-Ripoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking the performance of quantum computing software</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present Benchpress, a benchmarking suite for evaluating the performance and range of functionality of multiple quantum computing software development kits. This suite consists of a collection of over $1000$ tests measuring key performance metrics for a wide variety of operations on quantum circuits comprised of up to $930$ qubits and $\mathcal{O}(10^{6})$ two-qubit gates, as well as an execution framework for running the tests over multiple quantum software packages in a unified manner. We give a detailed overview of the benchmark suite, its methodology, and generate representative results over seven different quantum software packages. The flexibility of the Benchpress framework allows for benchmarking that not only keeps pace with quantum hardware improvements but can preemptively gauge the quantum circuit processing costs of future device architectures. Being open-source, Benchpress ensures the transparency and verification of performance claims.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08844v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul D. Nation, Abdullah Ash Saki, Sebastian Brandhofer, Luciano Bello, Shelly Garion, Matthew Treinish, Ali Javadi-Abhari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Circuit-Based Compression Perspective for Parameter-Efficient Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09846v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum-centric supercomputing presents a compelling framework for large-scale hybrid quantum-classical tasks. Although quantum machine learning (QML) offers theoretical benefits in various applications, challenges such as large-size data encoding in the input stage and the reliance on quantum resources in the inference stage limit its practicality for tasks like fine-tuning large language models (LLMs). Quantum parameter generation, a novel approach of QML, addresses these limitations by using quantum neural networks (QNNs) to generate classical model weights (parameters) exclusively during training, thereby decoupling inference from quantum hardware. In this work, we introduce Quantum Parameter Adaptation (QPA) in the framework of quantum parameter generation, which integrates QNNs with a classical multi-layer perceptron mapping model to generate parameters for fine-tuning methods. Using Gemma-2 and GPT-2 as case studies, QPA demonstrates significant parameter reduction for parameter-efficient fine-tuning methods, such as Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), while maintaining comparable or improved performance in text generation tasks. Specifically, QPA reduces the number of parameters to $52.06\%$ of the original LoRA for GPT-2 with a slight performance gain of $0.75\%$, and to $16.84\%$ for Gemma-2, with a marginal performance improvement of $0.07\%$. These results highlight QPA's ability to achieve efficient parameter reduction without sacrificing performance in the quantum parameter generation framework. This work showcases the potential of quantum-enhanced parameter reduction, offering a scalable quantum-classical solution for fine-tuning LLMs while preserving the feasibility of inference on classical hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09846v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen-Yu Liu, Chao-Han Huck Yang, Hsi-Sheng Goan, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Probability Geometrically Realized in Projective Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18266v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The principal goal of this paper is to pass all quantum probability formulas to the projective space associated to the complex Hilbert space of a given quantum system, providing a more complete geometrization of quantum theory. Quantum events have consecutive and conditional probabilities, which have been used in the author's previous work to clarify `collapse' and to generalize the concept of entanglement by incorporating it into quantum probability theory. In this way all of standard textbook quantum theory can be understood as a geometric theory of projective subspaces without any special role for the zero-dimensional projective subspaces, which are also called pure states. The upshot is that quantum theory is the probability theory of projective subspaces, or equivalently, of quantum events. For the sake of simplicity the ideas are developed here in the context of a type I factor, but comments will be given about how to adopt this approach to more general von Neumann algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18266v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Bruce Sontz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating and probing many-body quantum states in waveguide-QED systems with giant atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20653v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Waveguide quantum electrodynamics (wQED) with giant atoms provides a distinctive opportunity to study one-dimensional (1D) coupled spin systems through its unique decoherence-free interactions. This study presents a theoretical framework for simulating the diagonal Aubry-Andr\'e-Harper (AAH) model in the context of giant-atom wQED. The proposed scheme employs photonic modes in the waveguide to not only mediate interactions between atoms but also to detect the energy spectrum of the atom array. To illustrate the effectiveness of this approach, we present a simulation of the Hofstadter butterfly spectrum with high precision. Furthermore, for an incommensurate AAH atomic chain, we demonstrate that the photon transmission spectrum can accurately distinguish between the many-body localized phase and the extended phase. The method presented here is also applicable to the simulation of other types of 1D atomic chains based on giant-atom wQED.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20653v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. L. Yang, W. Z. Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Policy Gradient in Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06650v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Parametrised quantum circuits offer expressive and data-efficient representations for machine learning. Due to quantum states residing in a high-dimensional Hilbert space, parametrised quantum circuits have a natural interpretation in terms of kernel methods. The representation of quantum circuits in terms of quantum kernels has been studied widely in quantum supervised learning, but has been overlooked in the context of quantum RL. This paper proposes parametric and non-parametric policy gradient and actor-critic algorithms with quantum kernel policies in quantum environments. This approach, implemented with both numerical and analytical quantum policy gradient techniques, allows exploiting the many advantages of kernel methods, including available analytic forms for the gradient of the policy and tunable expressiveness. The proposed approach is suitable for vector-valued action spaces and each of the formulations demonstrates a quadratic reduction in query complexity compared to their classical counterparts. Two actor-critic algorithms, one based on stochastic policy gradient and one based on deterministic policy gradient (comparable to the popular DDPG algorithm), demonstrate additional query complexity reductions compared to quantum policy gradient algorithms under favourable conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06650v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David M. Bossens, Kishor Bharti, Jayne Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-protected Landau-Zener-St\"uckelberg-Majorana interference and non-adiabatic topological transport of edge states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10750v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically investigate Landau-Zener-St\"uckelberg-Majorana (LZSM) interference under chiral-mirror-like symmetry and propose its application to non-adiabatic topological transport of edge states. Protected by this symmetry, complete destructive interference emerges and can be characterized through occupation probability. This symmetry-protected LZSM interference enables state transitions to be achieved within remarkably short time scales. To demonstrate our mechanism, we provide two distinctive two-level systems as examples and survey them in detail. By tuning evolution speed or increasing holding time, the complete destructive interferences are observed. Furthermore, we make use of this mechanism for topological edge states of Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) chain by taking them as an isolated two-level system. Through carefully designed time sequences, we construct symmetry-protected LZSM interference of topological edge states, enabling non-adiabatic topological transport. Our work unveils an alternative way to study quantum control, quantum state transfer, and quantum communication via non-adiabatic topological transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10750v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Hu, Shihao Li, Meiqing Hu, Zhoutao Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab-Initio Approach to Many-Body Quantum Spin Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13190v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A fundamental longstanding problem in studying spin models is the efficient and accurate numerical simulation of the long-time behavior of larger systems. The exponential growth of the Hilbert space and the entanglement accumulation at long times pose major challenges for current methods. To address these issues, we employ the multilayer multiconfiguration time-dependent Hartree (ML-MCTDH) framework to simulate the many-body spin dynamics of the Heisenberg model in various settings, including the Ising and XYZ limits with different interaction ranges and random couplings. Benchmarks with analytical and exact numerical approaches show that ML-MCTDH accurately captures the time evolution of one- and two-body observables in both one- and two-dimensional lattices. A comparison with the discrete truncated Wigner approximation (DTWA) highlights that ML-MCTDH is particularly well-suited for handling anisotropic models and provides more reliable results for two-point observables across all tested cases. The behavior of the corresponding entanglement dynamics is analyzed to reveal the complexity of the quantum states. Our findings indicate that the rate of entanglement growth strongly depends on the interaction range and the presence of disorder. This particular relationship is then used to examine the convergence behavior of ML-MCTDH. Our results indicate that the multilayer structure of ML-MCTDH is a promising numerical framework for handling the dynamics of generic many-body spin systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13190v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Dubey, Zeki Zeybek, Fabian K\"ohler, Rick Mukherjee, Peter Schmelcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-selected von Neumann Measurement with Superpositions of Orbital-Angular-Momentum Pointer States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14210v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigated an orbital angular momentum (OAM) pointer within the framework of von Neumann measurements and discovered its significant impact on optimizing superpositions of Gaussian and Laguerre-Gaussian (LG) states. Calculations of the quadrature squeezing, the second-order cross-correlation function, the Wigner function, and the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) support our findings. Specifically, by carefully selecting the anomalous weak value and the coupling strength between the measured system and the pointer, we demonstrated that the initial Gaussian state transforms into a non-Gaussian state after postselection. This transition highlights the potential of OAM pointers in enhancing the performance of quantum systems by tailoring state properties for specific applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14210v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janarbek Yuanbek, Yi-Fang Ren, Yusuf Turek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hamiltonian Descent for Graph Partition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14696v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce Quantum Hamiltonian Descent as a novel approach to solve the graph partition problem. By reformulating graph partition as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problem, we leverage QHD's quantum-inspired dynamics to identify optimal community structures. Our method implements a multi-level refinement strategy that alternates between QUBO formulation and QHD optimization to iteratively improve partition quality. Experimental results demonstrate that our QHD-based approach achieves superior modularity scores (up to 5.49\%) improvement with reduced computational overhead compared to traditional optimization methods. This work establishes QHD as an effective quantum-inspired framework for tackling graph partition challenges in large-scale networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14696v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinglei Cheng, Ruilin Zhou, Yuhang Gan, Chen Qian, Junyu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a bipolar 50 V output digital-to-analog converter system for ion-shuttling operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07363v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quantum charge-coupled device (QCCD) is one of the notable architectures to achieve large-scale trapped-ion quantum computers. To realize QCCD architecture, ions must be transported quickly while minimizing motional excitation. High-voltage sources are necessary to achieve such high-quality ion transport through a high secular frequency. In this study, we report the development of a field programmable gate array (FPGA)-based digital-to-analog converter (DAC) system with an output voltage range of +/-50 V and demonstrate its effectiveness in ion transport operations. The device provides 16-channel analog output, maximum update rate of 16 mega updates per second (MUPS), slew rate of 20 V/us, and bandwidth of &gt; 200 kHz. By optimizing the voltage sets with quadratic programming, we experimentally confirmed that this DAC system can achieve more than twice the secular frequency attainable when its output range is restricted to +/-10 V. Since the output range of many commercially available DACs is commonly limited to +/-10 V, this increase is effective for ion shuttling operations, such as transport, split and merge. The developed DAC system has potential to increase the speed of ion transport thereby reducing processing times in QCCD-based quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07363v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Oshio, R. Nishimoto, T. Higuchi, K. Hayasaka, K. Koike, S. Morisaka, T. Miyoshi, R. Ohira, U. Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error analysis of quantum operators written as a linear combination of permutations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12762v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider matrices given as a linear combination of permutations and analyze the impact of bit and phase flips on the perturbation of the eigenvalues. When the coefficients in the linear combination are positive, we observe that the eigenvalues of the resulting matrices are resilient to quantum bit-flip errors. In addition, we analyze the bit flips in combination with positive and negative coefficients and the phase flips. Although matrices with mixed-sign coefficients are less resilient to the bit-flip and phase-flip errors,the numerical evidence shows that the perturbation of the eigenspectrum is very small when the rate of these errors is small. We also discuss the situation when this matrix is implemented through block encoding and there is a control register. Since any square matrix can be written as a sum of permutations with some coefficients, this paper gives a framework to study matrix computations in quantum algorithms related to numerical linear algebra. In addition, it can give ideas to design more error-resilient algorithms that may involve quantum registers with different error characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12762v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ammar Daskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Photon Interference of Photons from Remote Tin-Vacancy Centers in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17539v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scalable quantum networks rely on optical connections between long-lived qubits to distribute entanglement. Tin vacancies in diamond have emerged as promising long-lived qubits, offering extended spin coherence times at liquid helium temperatures and spin-dependent, highly coherent optical transitions for effective photon-based communication. Connecting remote nodes requires quantum interference of indistinguishable photons, which is challenging in an inhomogeneous solid-state environment. Here, we demonstrate a two-node experiment with tin vacancies in diamond, which exhibit a resonant frequency distribution spanning approximately 8 GHz. To overcome the frequency mismatch, we tune the resonant frequencies of one node using the Stark effect. We achieve tunability up to 4 GHz while maintaining optical coherence. As a demonstration, we achieve detuning-dependent remote two-photon interference between separate nodes, obtaining 80(6)% interference visibility without postprocessing when the defects' optical transitions are tuned into resonance, and 63(8)% with detuning up to 20 times their natural linewidths. These results highlight the potential of tin-vacancy centres in diamond for establishing robust optical links between remote quantum registers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17539v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladislav Bushmakin, Oliver von Berg, Colin Sauerzapf, Sreehari Jayaram, Andrej Denisenko, Cristina Tar\'in, Jens Anders, Vadim Vorobyov, Ilja Gerhardt, Di Liu, J\"org Wrachtrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transfer Learning Analysis of Variational Quantum Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work analyzes transfer learning of the Variational Quantum Circuit (VQC). Our framework begins with a pretrained VQC configured in one domain and calculates the transition of 1-parameter unitary subgroups required for a new domain. A formalism is established to investigate the adaptability and capability of a VQC under the analysis of loss bounds. Our theory observes knowledge transfer in VQCs and provides a heuristic interpretation for the mechanism. An analytical fine-tuning method is derived to attain the optimal transition for adaptations of similar domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01507v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan-Hsin Tseng, Hsin-Yi Lin, Samuel Yen-Chi Chen, Shinjae Yoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian two-time correlation functions for optomechanical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we focus on the two-time correlation function (TTCF) of the cavity optomechanical system, which serves as the most popular tool in precision detection technologies. We utilize the stochastic Schrodinger equation approach to study TTCF for the cavity optomechanical system in the long-time steady state TTCF and time-dependent case. Our numerical simulations support two major conclusions: (1) long-time steady states in Markovian and non-Markovian regimes are different, resulting in the distinct TTCF, and (2) the time-dependent TTCF can reveal more information about the environment, rather than the traditional spectral function method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07678v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusui Chen, Kaiqi Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Quantum Coherence of V-type Atom in Dissipative Cavity by Detuning and Weak Measurement Reversal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, an interactive system composed of a V-type atom and a dissipative single-mode cavity is considered and the atomic quantum coherences are investigated under parameters including spontaneously generated interference (SGI), cavity-environment coupling, weak measurement and its reversal, and detuning between the atom and the cavity. The results indicate that, the strong coupling can induce coherence sudden death (CSD) and coherence sudden birth (CSB), and the non-zero SGI parameter only induces CSB but the detuning may avoid CSD and CSB. Moreover, detuning and weak measurement reversal can very effectively protect quantum coherence, while the SGI parameter, weak measurement, and strong coupling can accelerate its attenuation. The SGI parameter, detuning, weak measurement reversal, and strong coupling all promote the generation of coherence, whereas weak measurement alone can suppress it. In particular, the maximal coherent state can be very effectively protected and the coherent state can be prepared if all parameters are selected appropriately. Physical interpretations are also provided for these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11010v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiying Pan, Fuhua Li, Hong-Mei Zou, Zijin Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic limits of the Mpemba effect: A unified resource theory analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00123v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Mpemba effect, a counterintuitive thermodynamic phenomenon in which a hotter system cools more rapidly than a colder one, has been observed in both classical and quantum systems. However, its fundamental mechanisms remain inadequately understood. In this letter, we investigate the role of classical and quantum correlations in driving anomalous relaxation behaviors within the framework of quantum resource theories. Through an analysis of multi-qubit systems in local thermal equilibrium, we establish that classical correlations alone can give rise to the Mpemba effect, while quantum correlations become relevant under specific energy degeneracy conditions. Furthermore, we demonstrate that non-Markovian memory effects and Hilbert space dimensionality play a crucial role in determining the temperature range over which this effect manifests. Finally, we discuss the possibility that the original anomalous cooling behavior observed in water may also arise from classical or quantum correlations, offering new insights into the underlying mechanisms of the phenomena collectively referred to as the Mpemba effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00123v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Doruk Can Aly\"ur\"uk, Mahir H. Ye\c{s}iller, Vlatko Vedral, Onur Pusuluk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convex Split Lemma without Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06526v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a refinement to the convex split lemma by replacing the max mutual information with the collision mutual information, transforming the inequality into an equality. This refinement yields tighter achievability bounds for quantum source coding tasks, including state merging and state splitting. Furthermore, we derive a universal upper bound on the smoothed max mutual information, where "universal" signifies that the bound depends exclusively on R\'enyi entropies and is independent of the system's dimensions. This result has significant implications for quantum information processing, particularly in applications such as the reverse quantum Shannon theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06526v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilad Gour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Materials and spin characteristics of amino-terminated nanodiamonds embedded with nitrogen-vacancy color centers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07706v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding and controlling fluorescent nanodiamonds (FNDs) with optically read qubits is a key focus of research, as they show high potential for detecting electric and magnetic fields, temperature, and other physico-chemical quantities at the nanoscale, which are highly sought after in chemistry and biology. Proper functionalization of FNDs is required for their application as probes in chemical and biological processes. However, modifying the surface of FNDs can affect the properties of qubit sensors. In this work, we thoroughly study the fundamental properties of embedded nitrogen-vacancy (NV) color centers as a function of FND size and surface termination. The FNDs were produced by milling high-pressure, high-temperature diamonds, and NV centers were introduced via electron beam irradiation and annealing. In particular, the initial FNDs, covered with various oxygen groups, were homogenized through a reduction process to predominantly cover them with alcohol ($-$OH) groups as reference FNDs. Additionally, a Hofmann degradation process was applied to terminate FNDs with amine ($-$NH$_2$) groups, enabling direct linkage of proteins and other biomolecules to the FNDs. We monitored the charge state stability upon illumination, the zero-field splitting parameters, and the longitudinal spin-relaxation time of the NV centers in these FNDs. Our findings indicate that charge state stabilization of the NV centers was achieved in both $-$OH- and $-$NH$_2$-terminated FNDs beyond a certain FND size. Furthermore, we demonstrate that $-$NH$_2$-terminated FNDs embedding NV centers exhibit a $T_1$ longitudinal relaxation time of approximately 25~$\mu$s, independent of FND size within the studied range of 10~nm to 140~nm. This relaxation time is comparable to that of larger-sized reference FNDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07706v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikoletta Jegenyes, Vladimir Verkhovlyuk, Szabolcs Czene, Attila Cs\'aki, Olga Krafcsik, Zsolt Czig\'any, David Beke, Adam Gali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum learning advantage on a scalable photonic platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07770v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum technologies have opened new horizons for exploring the physical world in ways once deemed impossible. Central to these breakthroughs is the concept of quantum advantage, where quantum systems outperform their classical counterparts in solving specific tasks. While much attention has been devoted to computational speedups, quantum advantage in learning physical systems remains a largely untapped frontier. Here, we present a photonic implementation of a quantum-enhanced protocol for learning the probability distribution of a multimode bosonic displacement process. By harnessing the unique properties of continuous-variable quantum entanglement, we obtain a massive advantage in sample complexity with respect to conventional methods without entangled resources. With approximately 5 dB of two-mode squeezing -- corresponding to imperfect Einstein--Podolsky--Rosen (EPR) entanglement -- we learn a 100-mode bosonic displacement process using 11.8 orders of magnitude fewer samples than a conventional scheme. Our results demonstrate that even with non-ideal, noisy entanglement, a significant quantum advantage can be realized in continuous-variable quantum systems. This marks an important step towards practical quantum-enhanced learning protocols with implications for quantum metrology, certification, and machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07770v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Hao Liu, Romain Brunel, Emil E. B. {\O}stergaard, Oscar Cordero, Senrui Chen, Yat Wong, Jens A. H. Nielsen, Axel B. Bregnsbo, Sisi Zhou, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Changhun Oh, Liang Jiang, John Preskill, Jonas S. Neergaard-Nielsen, Ulrik L. Andersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid-stable Collective Charging and Reverse Suppressing in Many-Body Quantum Batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two major challenges in the process of practical development of quantum batteries (QBs) are: how to achieve rapid-stable charging, i.e., the maximum extractable work quantified via ergotropy, and how to identify the reverse mechanism of rapid-stable charging and propose contrary control strategies in many-body quantum systems. This work proposes a strongly coupled many-body collective charging QB scheme interacting with the surrounding environment, analyzes its physical operating mechanisms as a battery system, explores the mechanisms for achieving fast and stable collective charging under strong environmental coupling, and provides a detailed analysis of various physical methods for suppressing the reverse mechanism. This work highlights the novel properties of many-body QB systems and advances the physical research needed to accelerate the practical application of QBs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08665v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun-Cai Zhao, Yi-Fan Yang, Zi-Ran Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Freedom at the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless Transition without Fine-Tuning Using a Qubit Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06117v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a two-dimensional hard-core loop-gas model as a way to regularize the asymptotically free massive continuum quantum field theory that emerges at the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition. Without fine-tuning, our model can reproduce the universal step-scaling function of the classical lattice XY model in the massive phase as we approach the phase transition. This is achieved by lowering the fugacity of Fock-vacuum sites in the loop-gas configuration space to zero in the thermodynamic limit. Some of the universal quantities at the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition show smaller finite size effects in our model as compared to the traditional XY model. Our model is a prime example of qubit regularization of an asymptotically free massive quantum field theory in Euclidean space-time and helps understand how asymptotic freedom can arise as a relevant perturbation at a decoupled fixed point without fine-tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06117v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.041601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 132 (2024) 4, 041601</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sandip Maiti, Debasish Banerjee, Shailesh Chandrasekharan, Marina K. Marinkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishable consequence of classical gravity on quantum matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09105v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: What if gravity is classical? If true, a consistent co-existence of classical gravity and quantum matter requires that gravity exhibit irreducible fluctuations. These fluctuations can mediate classical correlations, but not quantum entanglement, between the quantized motion of the gravitationally interacting matter. We use a consistent theory of quantum-classical dynamics in the Newtonian limit of gravity to show that experimentally relevant observables can conclusively test the hypothesis that gravity is classical. This can be done for example by letting highly coherent source masses interact with each other gravitationally, and performing precise measurements of the cross-correlation of their motion. Theory predicts a characteristic phase response that distinguishes classical gravity from quantum gravity, and from naive sources of decoherence. Such experiments are imminently viable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09105v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.061501</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 061501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Serhii Kryhin, Vivishek Sudhir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing Symmetry-Broken Superconducting Configurations by Density Functional Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00719v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A coherent theory for the superconductivity of both conventional and unconventional superconductors is currently lacking. Here we show that superconductivity arises from the formation of a symmetry-broken superconducting configuration (SCC) due to atomic perturbation of the normal conducting configuration (NCC). This perturbation creates straight one-dimensional tunnels (SODTs) for charge density of electrons and/or holes as revealed by the calculations based on density functional theory (DFT). The SODTs act as resistance-free superhighways and are correlated to the Cooper pairs in the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) theory. The formation of SODTs implies that the electron-phonon interaction in the BCS theory can be represented by the difference in charge densities between SCC and NCC predicted by DFT. The present work highlights that in conventional superconductors, SODTs are embedded within the bulk materials and are easily destroyed by phonon vibrations, resulting in a low critical superconducting temperature (T_C). Conversely, in unconventional superconductors such as YBa2Cu3O7 (YBCO7), SODTs are protected by a layered pontoon structure with very weak bonding to the bulk materials, maintaining SODTs' stability at higher temperatures and leading to a much higher T_C. The present approach is validated for 13 conventional superconductors of 18 pure elements examined in this work, including the presently predicted superconductivity in Cu, Ag, Au, Sb, and Bi at 0 K and 0 GPa, and one unconventional superconductor of YBCO7. Our discovery indicates that DFT can be a practical tool for predicting superconductors, enabling a systematic search for new superconducting materials in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00719v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Kui Liu, Shun-Li Shang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon Counting Interferometry to Detect Geontropic Space-Time Fluctuations with GQuEST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07524v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The GQuEST (Gravity from the Quantum Entanglement of Space-Time) experiment uses tabletop-scale Michelson laser interferometers to probe for fluctuations in space-time. We present a practicable interferometer design featuring a novel photon counting readout method that provides unprecedented sensitivity, as it is not subject to the interferometric standard quantum limit. We evaluate the potential of this design to measure space-time fluctuations motivated by recent `geontropic' quantum gravity models. The accelerated accrual of Fisher information offered by the photon counting readout enables GQuEST to detect the predicted quantum gravity phenomena within measurement times at least 100 times shorter than equivalent conventional interferometers. The GQuEST design thus enables a fast and sensitive search for signatures of quantum gravity in a laboratory-scale experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07524v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevX.15.011034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 15, 011034, Published 14 February, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sander M. Vermeulen, Torrey Cullen, Daniel Grass, Ian A. O. MacMillan, Alexander J. Ramirez, Jeffrey Wack, Boris Korzh, Vincent S. H. Lee, Kathryn M. Zurek, Chris Stoughton, Lee McCuller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error Bounds for Open Quantum Systems with Harmonic Bosonic Bath</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the dependence of physical observable of open quantum systems with Bosonic bath on the bath correlation function. We provide an error estimate of the difference of physical observable induced by the variation of bath correlation function, based on diagrammatic and combinatorial arguments. This gives a mathematically rigorous justification of the result in [Mascherpa et al, Phys Rev Lett 2017].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04009v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaizhao Liu, Jianfeng Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Models of interacting bosons with exact ground states: a unified approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15319v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define an infinite class of ``frustration-free'' interacting lattice quantum Hamiltonians for bosons, constructed such that their exact ground states have a density distribution specified by the Boltzmann weight of a corresponding classical lattice gas problem. By appropriately choosing the classical weights, we obtain boson representations of various known solvable models, including quantum dimer and vertex models, toric code, and certain Levin-Wen string-net models. We also systematically construct solvable models with other interesting ground states, including ``quantum spin liquids,'' supersolids, ``Bose-Einstein insulators,'' Bose liquids with ``Bose surfaces'', and Bose-Einstein condensates that permit adiabatic evolution from a non-interacting limit to a Gutzwiller-projected limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15319v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Han, Steven A. Kivelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological zero modes and bounded modes at smooth domain walls: Exact solutions and dualities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16466v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topology describes global quantities invariant under continuous deformations, such as the number of elementary excitations at a phase boundary, without detailing specifics. Conversely, differential laws are needed to understand the physical properties of these excitations, such as their localization and spatial behavior. For instance, topology mandates the existence of solitonic zero-energy modes at the domain walls between topologically inequivalent phases in topological insulators and superconductors. However, the spatial dependence of these modes is only known in the idealized (and unrealistic) case of a sharp domain wall. Here, we find the analytical solutions of these zero-modes by assuming a smooth and exponentially-confined domain wall. This allows us to characterize the zero-modes using a few length scales: the domain wall width, the exponential decay length, and oscillation wavelength. These quantities define distinct regimes: featureless modes with "no hair" at sharp domain walls, and nonfeatureless modes at smooth domain walls, respectively, with "short hair", i.e., featureless at long distances, and "long hair", i.e., nonfeatureless at all length scales. We thus establish a universal relation between the bulk excitation gap, decay rate, and oscillation momentum of the zero modes, which quantifies the bulk-boundary correspondence in terms of experimentally measurable physical quantities. Additionally, we reveal an unexpected duality between topological zero modes and Shockley modes, unifying the understanding of topologically-protected and nontopological boundary modes. These findings shed some new light on the localization properties of edge modes in topological insulators and Majorana zero modes in topological superconductors and on the differences and similarities between topological and nontopological zero modes in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16466v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptae186</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Marra, Angela Nigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing magic angles in twisted bilayer graphene from information theory markers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07935v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Zero energy eigenstates $\psi_0(\theta)$ of the twisted bilayer graphene Hamiltonian at the Dirac point show a high sensitivity to the twist angle $\theta$ near the magic angles where the effective Fermi velocity vanishes. We use information theory markers, like fidelity-susceptibility and entanglement entropy of the reduced density matrix to the layer sector, to capture this quantum criticality of zero modes at magic twist angles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07935v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physe.2025.116199</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica E 169 (2025) 116119</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Calixto, Alberto Mayorgas, Octavio Casta\~nos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Annealing and Nanostructuring on Properties of NV Centers Created by Different Techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07354v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamonds have been an epicenter of research for diverse applications in quantum technologies. It is therefore imperative that their fabrication techniques are well understood and characterized for the technological scalability of these applications. A comparative study of the optical and spin properties of NVs created by ion implantation and chemical vapor deposition delta-doping is thus presented, combined with an investigation on the impact of annealing in vacuum at different temperatures. In addition, nanopillars are fabricated with electron beam lithography and reactive ion etching for enhanced photon collection efficiency. An extensive combination of characterization techniques is employed. Notably, the smallest nanopillars present fluorescence enhancements of factor around 50, compared to the unstructured regions. Annealing is also demonstrated to increase the optical contrast between the NVs' electronic states, the coherence and relaxation times both in bulk as in pillars. Regarding the NV preparation technique, the delta-doping is shown to create NVs with less lattice defects and strain compared to implantation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07354v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miriam Mendoza Delgado, Lucas Tsunaki, Shaul Michaelson, Mohan K. Kuntumalla, Johann P. Reithmaier, Alon Hoffman, Boris Naydenov, Cyril Popov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Multi-Entropy Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07549v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the multi-partite entanglement structure of an evaporating black hole and its Hawking radiation by dividing the radiation into finer subsystems. We approximate an evaporating black hole and its radiation with a Haar-random state for this purpose. Using the multi-entropy of these configurations, we define a black hole multi-entropy curve, which describes how the multi-entropy changes during the black hole evaporation. This black hole multi-entropy curve is a natural generalization of the Page curve since the multi-entropy reduces to the entanglement entropy for the bi-partite case. The multi-entropy curve keeps increasing in the early time. It reaches the maximum value at the multi-entropy time, which is later than the Page time, and starts to decrease. However, it does not decrease to zero at the end of the black hole evaporation. This non-zero value of the multi-entropy represents the secret entanglement between Hawking particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07549v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Iizuka, Simon Lin, Mitsuhiro Nishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric tensor and wavepacket dynamics in two-dimensional non-Hermitian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08141v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quantum geometric tensor (QGT) characterizes the local geometry of quantum states, and its components directly account for the dynamical effects observed, e.g., in condensed matter systems. In this work, we address the problem of extending the QGT formalism to non-Hermitian systems with gain and loss. In particular, we investigate a wave-packet dynamics in two-band non-Hermitian systems to elucidate how non-Hermiticity affects the definition of QGT. We employ first-order perturbation theory to account for non-adiabatic corrections due to interband mixing. Our results suggest that two different generalizations of the QGT, one defined using only the right eigenstates and the other one using both the left and right eigenstates, both play a significant role in wave-packet dynamics. We then determine the accuracy of the perturbative approach by simulating a wave-packet dynamics in a well studied physical non-Hermitian system -- exciton polaritons in a semiconductor microcavity. Our work aids deeper understanding of quantum geometry and dynamical behaviour in non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08141v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. -M. Robin Hu, Elena A. Ostrovskaya, Eliezer Estrecho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A two-dimensional 10-qubit array in germanium with robust and localised qubit control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16044v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum computers require the systematic operation of qubits with high fidelity. For holes in germanium, the spin-orbit interaction allows for \textit{in situ} electric fast and high-fidelity qubit gates. However, the interaction also causes a large qubit variability due to strong g-tensor anisotropy and dependence on the environment. Here, we leverage advances in material growth, device fabrication, and qubit control to realise a two-dimensional 10-spin qubit array, with qubits coupled up to four neighbours that can be controlled with high fidelity. By exploring the large parameter space of gate voltages and quantum dot occupancies, we demonstrate that plunger gate driving in the three-hole occupation enhances electric-dipole spin resonance (EDSR), creating a highly localised qubit drive. Our findings, confirmed with analytical and numerical models, highlight the crucial role of intradot Coulomb interaction and magnetic field direction. Furthermore, the ability to engineer qubits for robust control is a key asset for further scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16044v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentin John, C\'ecile X. Yu, Barnaby van Straaten, Esteban A. Rodr\'iguez-Mena, Mauricio Rodr\'iguez, Stefan Oosterhout, Lucas E. A. Stehouwer, Giordano Scappucci, Stefano Bosco, Maximilian Rimbach-Russ, Yann-Michel Niquet, Francesco Borsoi, Menno Veldhorst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repulsive quantum gravitoelectric-gravitomagnetic interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02470v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate, in the framework of linearized quantum gravity, the quantum gravitational interaction between a gravitoelectrically polarizable object and a gravitomagnetically polarizable object. This interaction originates from the coupling between the instantaneous mass quadrupole moment and the mass-current quadrupole moment of the objects, induced by fluctuating gravitoelectric and gravitomagnetic fields in a vacuum. Using leading-order perturbation theory, we derive the explicit expression of the quantum gravitoelectric-gravitomagnetic interaction energy, which shows a distance dependence of $r^{-8}$ in the near regime and $r^{-11}$ in the far regime, where $r$ is the distance between the two objects. Remarkably, this interaction energy is positive, indicating that the force is repulsive. Since interactions between objects polarizable in the same gravitoelectric or gravitomagnetic manner are inherently attractive, for objects which are both gravitoelectrically and gravitomagnetically polarizable, the overall quantum gravitational interaction potential is reduced when the repulsive quantum gravitoelectric-gravitomagnetic interaction is taken into account. However, for two isotropically polarizable objects with identical gravitoelectric and gravitomagnetic polarizabilities and energy level spacing, the repulsive quantum interaction cannot surpass the attractive interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02470v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.026015</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 026015 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Di Hao, Jiawei Hu, Hongwei Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis in a Quantum Point Contact Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03076v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is known that the long-range quantum entanglement exhibited in free fermion systems is sufficient to "thermalize" a small subsystem in that the subsystem reduced density matrix computed from a typical excited eigenstate of the combined system is approximately thermal. Remarkably, fermions without any interactions are thus thought to satisfy the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH). We explore this hypothesis when the fermion subsystem is only minimally coupled to a quantum reservoir (in the form of another fermion system) through a quantum point contact (QPC). The entanglement entropy of two 2-d free fermion systems connected by one or more quantum point contacts (QPC) is examined at finite energy and in the ground state. When the combined system is in a typical excited state, it is shown that the entanglement entropy of a subsystem connected by a small number of QPCs is sub-extensive, scaling as the linear size of the subsystem ($L_A$). For sufficiently low energies ($E$) and small subsystems, it is demonstrated numerically that the entanglement entropy $S_A \sim L_A E$, what one would expect for the thermodynamics of a one-dimensional system. In this limit, we suggest that the entropy carried by each additional QPC is quantized using the one-dimensional finite size/temperature conformal scaling: $\Delta S_A = \alpha \log{(1/E)\sinh{(L_AE)}}$. The sub-extensive entropy in the case of a small number of QPCs should be contrasted with the expectation for both classical, ergodic systems and quantum chaotic systems wherein a restricted geometry might affect the equilibrium relaxation times, but not the equilibrium properties themselves, such as extensive entropy and heat capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03076v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. C. Levine, B. A. Friedman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic States and Mechanical Behaviors of Phosphorus Carbide Nanotubes -- Structural and Quantum Phase Transitions in a Quasi-one-dimensional Material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11239v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quasi-one-dimensional (1D) materials can manifest exotic electronic properties in manners that are distinct from the bulk phase or other low-dimensional systems. Helical symmetries in such materials -- e.g., nanotubes with intrinsic or applied twist -- can simultaneously lead to strong electronic correlation and anomalous transport behavior. However, these materials remain underexplored, in part due to computational challenges. Using specialized symmetry-adapted first-principles calculations, we show that mono-layer $P_2C_3$ -- identified in a previous letter to possess ``double Kagome bands'' -- exhibits a number of striking properties when rolled up into phosphorous carbide nanotubes ($P_2C_3$NTs). Both armchair and zigzag $P_2C_3$NTs are stable at room temperature and display a degenerate combination of Dirac points and electronic flat bands at the Fermi level. Notably, these flat bands are highly resilient to elastic deformations. Large strains can transform the nanotube structure from honeycomb-kagome to ``brick-wall'', and trigger multiple quantum phase transitions. Edge states in $P_2C_3$NTs, spin-degeneracy lifting induced by vacancies and dopants, and strain-tunable magnetism are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11239v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Sharma, Chenhaoyue Wang, Hsuan Ming Yu, Amartya S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain induced topological phase transitions in split and line graphs of bipartite lattices featuring flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11783v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, materials with topological flat bands have attracted significant attention due to their association with extraordinary transport properties and strongly correlated electrons. This includes phenomena such as high-temperature superconductivity, magnetism, Wigner crystallization, and Mott-insulating behavior. Among these systems, two-dimensional (2D) materials are particularly compelling as they can host electronic states with unique band structures, such as dispersionless states alongside linearly dispersive Dirac cones. In this work, we use tight-binding models to comprehensively investigate a class of 2D lattices that generically support flat bands, and focus on the effects of strain on their electronic and topological properties. The studied lattices are constructed within a unifying graph-theoretic framework, whereupon split-graph and line-graph operations on bipartite square and hexagonal lattices are employed to generate new structures. In the absence of strain, the introduction of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) induces a bulk excitation gap, which transforms flat bands into quasi-flat bands with topologically nontrivial characteristics. By tuning system parameters and external strain, we observe the emergence of directional flat bands, and tilted and semi-Dirac cones. Remarkably, all lattices studied show phase transitions among trivial insulating, semimetallic, and topological phases. Our results highlight the potential of strain engineering as a versatile tool for manipulating electronic and topological phases in a wide variety of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11783v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Sharma, Amartya S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The foot, the fan, and the cuprate phase diagram: Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16417v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Fermi liquid with a 'large' Fermi surface (FL) can have a quantum phase transition to a spin density wave state (SDW) with reconstructed 'small' Fermi pockets. Both FL and SDW phases obey the Luttinger constraints on the volume enclosed by the Fermi surfaces. Critical spin fluctuations lead to spin-singlet $d$-wave pairing, as observed in the cuprates. Studies of the influence of spatial disorder on the FL-SDW quantum phase transition predict an extended quantum-critical Griffiths-type phase at low temperatures on the large Fermi surface side. These computations agree with the 'foot' of strange metal transport, and recent low temperature neutron scattering observations on La$_{2-x}$Sr$_x$CuO$_4$.
  However, this theory cannot explain the higher temperature pseudogap and the 'fan' of strange metal behavior of the hole-doped cuprates. Here we need to consider underlying Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions without symmetry breaking. Then the small Fermi surface phase does not obey the Luttinger constraint, and the pseudogap metal is described by thermal fluctuations above a 'fractionalized Fermi liquid' (FL*) or a 'holon metal', with the descriptions related by a duality on a background spin liquid. The quantum critical fan is described using a field theory for an underlying FL-FL* quantum phase transition in the presence of spatial disorder. This field theory can be mapped to a form which can be analyzed using the methods of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model. Such an analysis successfully models linear-in-temperature resistivity, optical conductivity and thermopower observations in the quantum critical fan.
  The confinement crossover connecting these lower and higher temperature descriptions is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16417v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subir Sachdev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularity and universality from von Neumann to R\'enyi entanglement entropy and disorder operator in Motzkin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17368v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The R\'enyi entanglement entropy is widely used in studying quantum entanglement properties in strongly correlated systems, whose analytic continuation as $n \to 1$ is often believed to give rise to the celebrated von Neumann entanglement entropy. However, this process for the colored Motzkin spin chain exhibits a singularity that yields different scaling behaviors of $\sim \sqrt{l}$ and $\sim \log{l}$ for the von Neumann and R\'enyi entropies, respectively. It can be understood by the exponential increasing desity of states in its entanglement spectrum. We have also employed disorder operators under various symmetries to study such a system. The analytical and numerical results reveal that the scaling of disorder operators is also $\log{l}$ in the leading term, the same as the R\'enyi entanglement entropy. We propose that the coefficient of the term $\log{l}$ is a universal constant, both in R\'enyi entropies and disorder operators, which could be used to identify the constraint physics of Motzkin walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17368v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyu Wang, Zenan Liu, Zheng Yan, Congjun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor-network toolbox for probing dynamics of non-Abelian gauge theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18301v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tensor-network methods enable probing dynamics of strongly interacting quantum many-body systems, including gauge theories, via Hamiltonian simulation, hence bypassing sign problems. They also have the potential to inform efficient quantum-simulation algorithms of the same theories. We develop and benchmark a matrix-product-state ansatz for the SU(2) lattice gauge theory using the loop-string-hadron formulation. This formulation has been demonstrated to be advantageous in Hamiltonian simulation of non-Abelian gauge theories. It is applicable to both SU(2) and SU(3) gauge groups, to periodic and open boundary conditions, and to 1+1 and higher dimensions. In this work, we report on progress in computing static and dynamical observables in a SU(2) gauge theory in (1+1)D, pushing the boundary of existing studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18301v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emil Mathew, Navya Gupta, Saurabh V. Kadam, Aniruddha Bapat, Jesse Stryker, Zohreh Davoudi, Indrakshi Raychowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigorous Test for Quantum Integrability and Nonintegrability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18400v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Whether or not a quantum many-body system is integrable, which is characterized by the presence or absence of local conserved quantities, drastically impacts the dynamics of isolated systems, including thermalization. Nevertheless, a rigorous and comprehensive method for deciding integrability or nonintegrability has remained elusive. In this paper, we address this challenge by introducing rigorously provable tests for integrability and nonintegrability of quantum spin systems with finite-range interactions. Our approach establishes a new paradigm, moving beyond the conventional artisanal methods in the study of nonintegrability. Furthermore, it partially resolves the long-standing conjecture that integrability is governed by the presence or absence of local conserved quantities with small supports. The proposed framework guarantees that the nonintegrability of one-dimensional spin systems with translational symmetry can be confirmed algorithmically, regardless of system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18400v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Hokkyo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Simulation of the Adaptive Continuous Entanglement Generation Protocol</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01964v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generating and distributing remote entangled pairs (EPs) is a primary function of quantum networks, as entanglement is the fundamental resource for key quantum network applications. A critical performance metric for quantum networks is the time-to-serve (TTS) for users' EP requests, which is the time to distribute EPs between the requested nodes. Minimizing the TTS is essential given the limited qubit coherence time. In this paper, we study the Adaptive Continuous entanglement generation Protocol (ACP), which enables quantum network nodes to continuously generate EPs with their neighbors, while adaptively selecting the neighbors to optimize TTS. Meanwhile, entanglement purification is used to mitigate decoherence in pre-generated EPs prior to the arrival of user requests. We extend the SeQUeNCe simulator to fully implement ACP and conduct extensive simulations across various network scales. Our results show that ACP reduces TTS by up to 94% and increases entanglement fidelity by up to 0.05.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01964v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caitao Zhan, Joaquin Chung, Allen Zang, Alexander Kolar, Rajkumar Kettimuthu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Hawking radiation in quantum many-body systems: deviations from the thermal spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08199v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate a recently proposed one-to-one correspondence between quantum field theories in two-dimensional curved spacetime and quantum many-body systems, which enables the simulation of Hawking radiation in static background spacetimes. In particular, we demonstrate that deviations from the thermal spectrum, as predicted by the well-known tunneling method, can be observed in many-body simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08199v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gokhan Alkac, Ege \"Ozg\"un</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
