<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino thermalization via randomization on a quantum processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamical evolution of neutrino flavor in supernovae can be modeled by an all-to-all spin Hamiltonian with random couplings. Simulating such two-local Hamiltonian dynamics remains a major challenge, as methods with controllable accuracy require circuit depths that increase at least linearly with system size, exceeding the capabilities of current quantum devices. The eigenstate thermalization hypothesis predicts that these systems should thermalize, a behavior confirmed in small-scale classical simulations. In this work, we investigate flavor thermalization in much larger systems using random quantum circuits as an empirical tool to emulate the non-local dynamics, and demonstrate that the thermal behavior can be reproduced using a depth independent of the system size. By simulating dynamics of over one hundred qubits, we find that the thermalization time grows approximately as the square root of the system size, consistent with predictions from semi-classical methods. Beyond this specific result, our study illustrates that near-term quantum devices are useful tools to test and validate empirical classical methods. It also highlights a new application of random circuits in physics, providing insight into complex many-body dynamics that are classically intractable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24841v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oriel Kiss, Ivano Tavernelli, Francesco Tacchino, Denis Lacroix, Alessandro Roggero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frustration-Free Control and Absorbing-State Transport in Entangled State Preparation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study frustration-free control, a measurement-feedback protocol for quantum state preparation that extends the concept of frustration-free Hamiltonians to stochastic dynamics. The protocol drives many-body systems into highly entangled target states, common dark states of all measurement projectors, through minimal local unitary corrections that realize an absorbing-state dynamics without post-selection. We show that relaxation to the target state is governed by emergent transport of nonlocal charges, such as singlet excitations in SU$(2)$-symmetric dynamics. While measurement-feedback annihilates compatible charge configurations, both measurement and scrambling unitaries induce charge transport and thus determine the convergence time. Mapping a baseline model of SU$(N)$ SWAP measurements with local corrections to a solvable absorbing random walk yields a runtime scaling $t \sim L^z$ with transport exponent $z=2$. Simulations of Motzkin and Fredkin chains reveal subdiffusive scaling $z \ge \tfrac{8}{3}$, confirming the transport picture and suggesting strategies for controlled entangled-state preparation and charge-transport probing in monitored quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24845v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. D\"orstel, T. Iadecola, J. H. Wilson, M. Buchhold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing-induced phase transition in the non-reciprocal Kitaev chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Investigating the robustness of non-reciprocity in the presence of competing interactions is central to understanding non-reciprocal quantum matter. In this work, we use reservoir engineering to induce non-reciprocal hopping and pairing in the fermionic Kitaev chain, and reveal the emergence of a pairing-induced phase transition. The two phases appear in the spectrum of the non-Hermitian Kitaev Hamiltonian describing the dynamics of correlations, separated by an exceptional point. In the non-reciprocal phase, dynamics are characterized by directionality and slow relaxation, and the steady state supports non-reciprocal density and spatial correlations. At strong pairing, we uncover an unexpected density wave phase, featuring short relaxation times, a modulation in particle occupation and strikingly different correlation spreading depending on pairing non-reciprocity. Our work highlights the non-trivial breakdown of non-reciprocity due to superconducting pairing and invites experimental investigation of non-reciprocal fermionic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24851v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Brighi, Andreas Nunnenkamp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure, Optimality, and Symmetry in Shadow Unitary Inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to reverse any unknown unitary operation plays a fundamental role in quantum computing. While existing studies mostly focus on realizing the inversion map of the unknown unitary, how to reverse a unitary with respect to a given observable, which we call shadow unitary inversion, has remained a natural basic question that is less developed. In this work, we systematically investigate shadow unitary inversion by providing explicit protocols and optimization problem simplification. First, we present a deterministic protocol for shadow inversion of qubit-unitaries. Such construction sequentially queries the unitary 3 times, which is suggested to be optimal by our numerical experiments. Second, we provide a complete characterization of feasible quantum operations for qubit shadow inversion under any fixed qubit observable. Third, for the qudit case, we give a framework of semidefinite programming for optimizing the shadow unitary inversion sequential protocol for tackling high-dimensional cases, utilizing tools from representation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24880v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guocheng Zhen, Yu-Ao Chen, Mingrui Jing, Jingu Xie, Ranyiliu Chen, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Unxtendibility via Virtual State Extension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24895v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The monogamy of entanglement, which restricts how entanglement can be shared among multiple parties, provides a powerful lens through which to characterize its structure, often formalized through the concept of symmetric extendibility. In this work, we propose a novel, operational viewpoint to quantify the degree to which a state is not extendible by introducing a virtual state extension task. We define the virtual extension cost as the minimum simulation cost of a non-physical protocol that satisfies the marginal conditions of a $k$-extension. We derive an exact, closed-form expression for this cost for the important family of isotropic states. Our central result establishes a profound connection between entanglement theory and quantum communication theory: the virtual extension cost of a maximally entangled state is precisely equal to the optimal simulation cost of universal virtual quantum broadcasting. Leveraging the algebraic machinery of the partially transposed permutations matrix algebra, we find an analytical formula for this cost and construct an explicit quantum circuit for the optimal broadcasting protocol, thereby resolving an open question. Furthermore, we demonstrate the connection between the virtual extension cost and the absolute robustness of unextendibility, thus endowing the latter with a clear operational meaning. We also show the natural properties of virtual extension cost as an entanglement measure, including its role as a bound for entanglement distillation and its relationship with logarithmic negativity. Our findings unify disparate concepts and offer a new perspective on entanglement quantification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24895v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongshun Yao, Jingu Xie, Xuanqiang Zhao, Chengkai Zhu, Ranyiliu Chen, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classically Prepared, Quantumly Evolved: Hybrid Algorithm for Molecular Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a hybrid classical-quantum algorithm to compute dynamical correlation functions and excitation spectra in many-body quantum systems, with a focus on molecular systems. The method combines classical preparation of a perturbed ground state with short-time quantum evolution of product states sampled from it. The resulting quantum samples define an effective subspace of the Hilbert space, onto which the Hamiltonian is projected to enable efficient classical simulation of long-time dynamics. This subspace-based approach achieves high-resolution spectral reconstruction using shallow circuits and few samples. Benchmarks on molecular systems show excellent agreement with exact diagonalization and demonstrate access to dynamical timescales beyond the reach of purely classical methods, highlighting its suitability for near-term and early fault-tolerant quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24911v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Santini, Stefano Barison, Filippo Vicentini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Limits on Quantum Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fundamental limits of quantum correlations set the foundation of quantum mechanics and quantum information science. Exact bounds-the Cramer-Rao inequality, the Heisenberg limit, and the Lieb-Robinson bound-have anchored entire fields, yet each applies only to a narrow class of systems or observables. Here we introduce a general framework from which all known correlation limits, as well as new ones, can be derived from a single geometric principle: the positivity of quantum state space. This intrinsic positive geometry defines a unique determinant-ratio invariant, denoted chi, which quantifies the combinatorial structure of correlations in any quantum system. Every measure of nonclassical correlation is bounded by a simple function of chi, yielding universal, model-independent floors and ceilings valid for arbitrary architectures. For systems with Lie-group symmetries, the bounds acquire compact closed forms. We recover the Heisenberg and Cramer-Rao limits and uncover previously unknown constraints, including an exact entanglement floor in multimode squeezing networks and a universal Fisher-information ceiling in fully connected spin ensembles-demonstrating that even all-to-all connectivity cannot exceed the positivity-imposed light cone in state space. Finally, we show that every correlation bound, old or new, exhibits local catastrophe-theoretic structure, with universal critical exponents classifying its approach to saturation. Positivity geometry thus provides a unified, first-principles theory of quantum limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24950v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Alperin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering chlorine-based emitters in silicon carbide for telecom-band quantum technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the experimental realization and optical characterization of chlorine-vacancy (ClV) color centers in 4H-SiC emitting in the fiber-optic telecom bands. These defects are created via chlorine ion implantation followed by high-temperature annealing. Photoluminescence spectroscopy reveals four distinct ClV configurations with zero-phonon lines (ZPLs) located in the O-band (1260 - 1360 nm), S-band (1460 - 1530 nm) and C-band (1530 - 1565 nm). Controlled implantation and annealing experiments confirm that the ClV centers originate specifically from chlorine incorporation into SiC and are not intrinsic to this material. We optimize the creation conditions for ClV ensembles and demonstrate negligible reduction of the ZPL intensity up to a temperature of 30 K. These results establish ClV defects as a new class of telecom-band color centers in a CMOS-compatible platform, offering strong potential for scalable quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25008v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. N. Anisimov, A. V. Mathews, K. Mavridou, U. Kentsch, M. Helm, G. V. Astakhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties and Applications of Partially Deterministic Polytopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The assumption of a deterministic local hidden variable model constrains the experimentally accessible statistics in a Bell experiment to be contained in the Bell-local polytope. But what if the outputs for only a subset of the measurements at each site are predetermined by the model? In this work, we thoroughly explore this concept of `partial determinism', allowing for arbitrary numbers of parties, inputs and outputs per site. The resulting objects form new classes of convex polytopes which recover the Bell and the no-signalling polytopes as special cases. Nontrivial equivalence classes of partially deterministic models arise, which we classify completely. In particular, the Bell polytope for any scenario can be expressed in multiple different ways in terms of local partially deterministic models. This allows us to generalise Fine's theorem, recovering the original formulation as a special case, but finding new constraints otherwise. We discuss scenarios with different physical motivations, which do not require the causal structure of the Bell scenario, and where classes of partially deterministic polytopes are relevant. Our example applications include device-independent quantum state inseparability witnesses, classes of broadcast-local polytopes, and Local Friendliness scenarios in quantum foundations. We also point out instances in previous literature where classes of related objects have been studied. In the case of correlations compatible with the Local Friendliness assumptions, we find a one-to-one correspondence between partially deterministic polytopes and sequential extended Wigner's friend scenarios so that every partially deterministic polytope has physical relevance. We discuss how the framework captures a broad class of non-classicality notions, and identify an even broader notion of `composable sets', of which partially deterministic polytopes are special cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25127v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwan Haddara, Howard M. Wiseman, Eric G. Cavalcanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Phase-Coupled Caldeira-Leggett Model: Non-Markovian Open Quantum Dynamics beyond Linear Dissipation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the \textit{Phase-Coupled Caldeira-Leggett} (PCL) model of quantum dissipation and develop an exact framework for its dynamics. Unlike the conventional Caldeira-Leggett model with linear system-bath coupling $H_{\mathrm{SB}}\propto\hat F$, the PCL model features an exponential interaction $H_{\mathrm{SB}}\propto e^{i\lambda \hat F}$, where $\hat F$ denotes the collective bath coordinate. This model unifies concepts from quantum Brownian motion and polaron physics, providing a general platform to study phase-mediated dissipation and decoherence beyond the linear-response regime. Despite its nonlinear system-bath coupling, the Gaussian nature of the environment allows a nonperturbative and non-Markovian treatment of PCL model within the algebra of dissipative quasiparticles. We obtain an exact closed-form equation of motion for the reduced density operator, and numerical simulations reveal distinctive dynamical behaviors that deviate markedly from those predicted by the conventional Caldeira-Leggett model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25133v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ao-Xiang Chang, Yu Su, Zi-Fan Zhu, Yao Wang, Rui-Xue Xu, YiJing Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sustainable NARMA-10 Benchmarking for Quantum Reservoir Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25183v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study compares Quantum Reservoir Computing (QRC) with classical models such as Echo State Networks (ESNs) and Long Short-Term Memory networks (LSTMs), as well as hybrid quantum-classical architectures (QLSTM), for the nonlinear autoregressive moving average task (NARMA-10). We evaluate forecasting accuracy (NRMSE), computational cost, and evaluation time. Results show that QRC achieves competitive accuracy while offering potential sustainability advantages, particularly in resource-constrained settings, highlighting its promise for sustainable time-series AI applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25183v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avyay Kodali, Priyanshi Singh, Pranay Pandey, Krishna Bhatia, Shalini Devendrababu, Srinjoy Ganguly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Platform Architecture for Tight Coupling of High-Performance Computing with Quantum Processors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25213v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an architecture, called NVQLink, for connecting high-performance computing (HPC) resources to the control system of a quantum processing unit (QPU) to accelerate workloads necessary to the operation of the QPU. We aim to support every physical modality of QPU and every type of QPU system controller (QSC). The HPC resource is optimized for real-time (latency-bounded) processing on tasks with latency tolerances of tens of microseconds. The network connecting the HPC and QSC is implemented on commercially available Ethernet and can be adopted relatively easily by QPU and QSC builders, and we report a round-trip latency measurement of 3.96 microseconds (max) with prospects of further optimization. We describe an extension to the CUDA-Q programming model and runtime architecture to support real-time callbacks and data marshaling between the HPC and QSC. By doing so, NVQLink extends heterogeneous, kernel-based programming to the QSC, allowing the programmer to address CPU, GPU, and FPGA subsystems in the QSC, all in the same C++ program, avoiding the use of a performance-limiting HTTP interface. We provide a pattern for QSC builders to integrate with this architecture by making use of multi-level intermediate representation dialects and progressive lowering to encapsulate QSC code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25213v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shane A. Caldwell, Moein Khazraee, Elena Agostini, Tom Lassiter, Corey Simpson, Omri Kahalon, Mrudula Kanuri, Jin-Sung Kim, Sam Stanwyck, Muyuan Li, Jan Olle, Christopher Chamberland, Ben Howe, Bruno Schmitt, Justin G. Lietz, Alex McCaskey, Jun Ye, Ang Li, Alicia B. Magann, Corey I. Ostrove, Kenneth Rudinger, Robin Blume-Kohout, Kevin Young, Nathan E. Miller, Yilun Xu, Gang Huang, Irfan Siddiqi, John Lange, Christopher Zimmer, Travis Humble</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoder Switching: Breaking the Speed-Accuracy Tradeoff in Real-Time Quantum Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The realization of fault-tolerant quantum computers hinges on the construction of high-speed, high-accuracy, real-time decoding systems. The persistent challenge lies in the fundamental trade-off between speed and accuracy: efforts to improve the decoder's accuracy often lead to unacceptable increases in decoding time and hardware complexity, while attempts to accelerate decoding result in a significant degradation in logical error rate. To overcome this challenge, we propose a novel framework, decoder switching, which balances these competing demands by combining a faster, soft-output decoder ("weak decoder") with a slower, high-accuracy decoder ("strong decoder"). In usual rounds, the weak decoder processes error syndromes and simultaneously evaluates its reliability via soft information. Only when encountering a decoding window with low reliability do we switch to the strong decoder to achieve more accurate decoding. Numerical simulations suggest that this framework can achieve accuracy comparable to, or even surpassing, that of the strong decoder, while maintaining an average decoding time on par with the weak decoder. We also develop an online decoding scheme tailored to our framework, named double window decoding, and elucidate the criteria for preventing an exponential slowdown of quantum computation. These findings break the long-standing speed-accuracy trade-off, paving the way for scalable real-time decoding devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25222v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riki Toshio, Kaito Kishi, Jun Fujisaki, Hirotaka Oshima, Shintaro Sato, Keisuke Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Encoding computationally hard problems in triangular Rydberg atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rydberg atom arrays are a promising platform for quantum optimization, encoding computationally hard problems by reducing them to independent set problems with unit-disk graph topology. In Nguyen et al., PRX Quantum 4, 010316 (2023), a systematic and efficient strategy was introduced to encode multiple problems into a special unit-disk graph: the King's subgraph. However, King's subgraphs are not the optimal choice in two dimensions. Due to the power-law decay of Rydberg interaction strengths, the approximation to unit-disk graphs in real devices is poor, necessitating post-processing that lacks physical interpretability. In this work, we develop an encoding scheme that can universally encode computationally hard problems on triangular lattices, based on our innovative automated gadget search strategy. Numerical simulations demonstrate that quantum optimization on triangular lattices reduces independence-constraint violations by approximately two orders of magnitude compared to King's subgraphs, substantially alleviating the need for post-processing in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25249v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi-Wei Pan, Huan-Hai Zhou, Yi-Ming Lu, Jin-Guo Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Physics from Quantum Envariance Principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build on the foundational work of Deffner and Zurek [S.~Deffner and W.~H.~Zurek, {New J.~Phys.18, 063013 (2016)}] to demonstrate how the principles of statistical mechanics can be derived from quantum mechanics using the concept of envariance (environment-assisted invariance). In particular, we show how the Binomial, Poisson, and Gaussian distributions naturally emerge from entangled system--environment states. Furthermore, we resolve the Gibbs paradox using entanglement entropy, obtaining the Sackur--Tetrode equation with quantum corrections. Extending this framework, we derive a modified Saha equation for ionization equilibrium and recover Bose--Einstein and Fermi--Dirac statistics from quantum symmetries. Our results reinforce and extend the view that statistical mechanics arises as a direct consequence of quantum information dynamics, rather than being founded on phenomenological postulates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25253v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amul Ojha, Shubhit Sardana, Arnab Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Fabrication of Metal-Shielded Fiber-Cavity Mirrors for Ion-Trap Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trapped ions in micro-cavities constitute a key platform for advancing quantum information processing and quantum networking. By providing an efficient light-matter interface within a compact architecture, they serve as highly efficient quantum nodes with strong potential for scalable quantum network. However, in such systems, ion trapping stability is often compromised by surface charging effects, and nearby dielectric materials are known to cause a dramatic increase in the ion heating rate by several orders of magnitude. These challenges significantly hinder the practical implementation of ion trap systems integrated with micro-cavities. To overcome these limitations, we present the design and fabrication of metal-shielded micro-cavity mirrors, enabling the stable realization of ion trap systems integrated with micro cavities. Using this method, we constructed a needle ion trap integrated with fiber Fabry-Perot cavity and successfully achieved stable trapping of a single ion within the cavity. The measured ion heating rate was reduced by more than an order of magnitude compared with unshielded configurations. This work establishes a key technique toward fully integrated ion-photon interfaces for scalable quantum network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25294v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Bin Chen, Ding Fang, Cheng-Hao Zhang, Jin-Ming Cui, Yun-Feng Huang, Chuan-Feng Li, Guang-Can Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaginarity measures induced by real part states and the complementarity relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complex numbers are indispensable in quantum mechanics and the resource theory of imaginarity has been developed recently. In this paper, we propose a method to construct imaginary measures by real part states. Specifically, we propose an imaginarity measure in terms of fidelity and explore its properties. The analytical expression of the imaginarity measure is presented in qubit systems. The relations between the proposed imaginarity measure and some other imaginarity measures (such as geometric imaginarity, Tsallis relative entropy imaginarity and trace norm imaginarity) are derived. The complementarity relations of the imaginarity measure under a complete set of mutually unbiased bases are provided in low-dimensional systems. This work not only highlights the prominent role of the real part state in the imaginarity resource theory, but also reveals the constraint of imaginarity on a complete set of mutually unbiased bases physically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25313v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyan Liu, Yue Sun, Jianwei Xu, Ming-Jing Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-correlated photons from spectrally-separated modes of a cavity coupled to a strongly-driven two-level atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photon counting statistics are explored, theoretically, from a pair of cavity modes coupled to the fluorescent transitions in a strongly-driven two-level atom. We show that the cavity modes acquire nonclassical photon statistics that are representative of dressed-state picture atomic transitions. In particular, the modes are shown to be antibunched, while simultaneously having a cross-correlation value greater than unity. Furthermore, we propose an implementation of the system with a nanofiber cavity QED system, based on a strongly-driven cesium atom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25331v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Elliott, Jacob Ngaha, Scott Parkins, Takao Aoki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational quantum computing for quantum simulation: principles, implementations, and challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a comprehensive overview of variational quantum computing and their key role in advancing quantum simulation. This work explores the simulation of quantum systems and sets itself apart from approaches centered on classical data processing, by focusing on the critical role of quantum data in Variational Quantum Algorithms (VQA) and Quantum Machine Learning (QML). We systematically delineate the foundational principles of variational quantum computing, establish their motivational and challenges context within the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, and critically examine their application across a range of prototypical quantum simulation problems. Operating within a hybrid quantum-classical framework, these algorithms represent a promising yet problem-dependent pathway whose practicality remains contingent on trainability and scalability under noise and barren-plateau constraints.This review serves to complement and extend existing literature by synthesizing the most recent advancements in the field and providing a focused perspective on the persistent challenges and emerging opportunities that define the current landscape of variational quantum computing for quantum simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25449v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Q. Galv\~ao, Anna Beatriz M. de Souza, Marcelo A. Moret, Clebson Cruz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Fisher Information With General Quantum Coherence in multi-dimensional quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum metrology is a science about quantum measurements and it plays a key role in precision of quantum parameter estimation. Meanwhile, quantum coherence is an important quantum feature and quantum Fisher information (QFI) is an important indicator for precision of quantum parameter estimation. In this paper, we explore the relationship between QFI and quantum coherence in multi-dimensional quantum systems. We introduce a new concept referred to as General Quantum Coherence (GQC), which characterizes the quantum coherence and the eigenenergies of the Hamiltonian in the interaction processes. GQC captures quantum nature of high-dimensional quantum states and addresses shortcomings in coherence measurement. Additionally, we observe a stringent square relationship between GQC and QFI. This finding provides a crucial guideline for improving the precision of parameter estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25457v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Long Zhao, Li Yu, Ming Yang, Chui-Ping Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized collective quantum tomography: algorithm design, optimization, and validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum tomography is a fundamental technique for characterizing, benchmarking, and verifying quantum states and devices. It plays a crucial role in advancing quantum technologies and deepening our understanding of quantum mechanics. Collective quantum state tomography, which estimates an unknown state \r{ho} through joint measurements on multiple copies $\rho\otimes\cdots\otimes\rho$ of the unknown state, offers superior information extraction efficiency. Here we extend this framework to a generalized setting where the target becomes $S_1\otimes\cdots\otimes S_n$, with each $S_i$ representing identical or distinct quantum states, detectors, or processes from the same category. We formulate these tasks as optimization problems and develop three algorithms for collective quantum state, detector and process tomography, respectively, each accompanied by an analytical characterization of the computational complexity and mean squared error (MSE) scaling. Furthermore, we develop optimal solutions of these optimization problems using sum of squares (SOS) techniques with semi-algebraic constraints. The effectiveness of our proposed methods is demonstrated through numerical examples. Additionally, we experimentally demonstrate the algorithms using two-copy collective measurements, where entangled measurements directly provide information about the state purity. Compared to existing methods, our algorithms achieve lower MSEs and approach the collective MSE bound by effectively leveraging purity information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25466v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuixin Xiao, Yuanlong Wang, Zhibo Hou, Aritra Das, Ian R. Petersen, Farhad Farokhi, Guo-Yong Xiang, Jie Zhao, Daoyi Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detuning Choice for solving MIS and MWIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the realization of a Maximum Weighted Independent Set (MWIS) and its quantum analogue under the constraints of Pasqal's neutral-atom processor: limited qubit number, bounds on $\Omega$ and $\Delta$, sequence duration, confinement space, minimum interatomic distance, and parasitic interactions. Our goal is to obtain results directly compatible with current hardware, on asymmetric graphs whose size is limited only by the QPU's topology. We introduce a novel detuning computation method that departs from conventional bounds, as parasitic interactions between nearby but unconnected atoms can significantly bias results. Three implementations are proposed, suited to different hardware maturity levels: (I) a speculative local-detuning approach demonstrating the pure theory; (II) a \emph{Detuning Map Modulation} (DMM) method approximating this theory for future QPU integration; and (III) a global-pulse and frequency-shift approach, diverging from theory but experimentally viable today. Tests using Pasqal's emulators on graphs up to $30$ qubits confirm the practicality of our methods within all QPU constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25473v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sem Saada Khelkhal, Louis Barcikowsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence Estimation of Superconducting Qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decoherence of quantum bits arises primarily from the parasitic resistance within the qubit. This study presents the analysis of the decoherence process due to physical interactions between the qubit photons and parasitic resistance atoms, utilizing exclusively the Caldeira-Leggett electrical model, without relying on external Hamiltonians. The analysis shows a good agreement between the model of the electrical noise and the Johnson-Nyquist noise. The emission and absorption rates of the qubit's coherent loss, required for the Lindblad master equation that approximates the decoherence, are obtained. A numerical substitution in the analysis result yields a strong correlation with previous measurements. The present analysis enables also the derivation of the appropriate circuit characteristics for future simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25491v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoav Koral, Shilo Avraham, Manimuthu Peryasamy, Shmuel E. Schacham, Eliyahu Farber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-order Stark shifts exceeding 10$\,$GHz in electrically contacted SiV$^-$ centers in diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Negatively charged silicon vacancy centers (SiV$^-$) in diamond exhibit excellent spin coherence and optical properties, making them promising candidates for quantum technologies. However, the strain-induced inhomogeneous distribution of optical transition frequencies poses a challenge for scalability. We demonstrate electrical tuning of the SiV$^-$ center zero-phonon lines using in-plane contacts to apply moderate electric fields up to 45$\,$MV/m. The second-order Stark shift exceeds 10$\,$GHz, which is of the same order of magnitude as the 15$\,$GHz inhomogeneous distribution of SiV$^-$ observed in emitters embedded in optical nanostructures such as photonic crystal nanocavities. Analysis of individual SiV$^-$ centers shows significant variation in polarizabilities between defects indicating that the polarizability strongly depends on local parameters like strain. The observed polarizabilities are 3-25 times larger than those of tin vacancy centers, which we attribute to valence band resonances that delocalize the $e_u$ wavefunctions. Photoluminescence excitation measurements reveal that optical linewidths increase moderately with applied electric field strength. Our results demonstrate that large electrical Stark shifts can overcome the inhomogeneous distribution of transition frequencies, representing a significant step toward scalable SiV$^-$-based quantum technologies such as quantum repeaters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25543v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Rieger, Nori N. Chavira Leal, Rubek Poudel, Tobias Waldmann, Lina M. Todenhagen, Stefan Kresta, Viviana Villafane, Martin S. Brandt, Kai M\"uller, Jonathan J. Finley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-Moir\'e Spin Textures in Twisted Antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stacking two-dimensional (2D) layered materials offers a powerful platform to engineer electronic and magnetic states. In general, the resulting states, such as Moir\'e magnetism, have a periodicity at the length scale of the Moir\'e unit cell. Here, we report a new type of magnetism -- dubbed a super-Moir\'e magnetic state -- which is characterized by long-range magnetic textures extending beyond the single Moir\'e unit cell -- in twisted double bilayer chromium triiodide (tDB CrI$_3$). We found that at small twist angles, the size of the spontaneous magnetic texture increases with twist angle, opposite to the underlying Moir\'e periodicity. The spin-texture size reaches a maximum of about 300 nm in 1.1${\deg}$ twisted devices, an order of magnitude larger than the underlying Moir\'e wavelength, and vanishes at twist angles above 2${\deg}$. Employing scanning quantum spin magnetometry, the obtained vector field maps suggest the formation of antiferromagnetic N\'eel-type skyrmions spanning multiple Moir\'e cells. The twist-angle-dependent study combined with large-scale atomistic simulations suggests that complex magnetic competition between the Dzyaloshinskii--Moriya interaction, magnetic anisotropy, and exchange interactions controlled by the relative rotation of the layers produces the topological textures which arise in the super-Moir\'e spin orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25545v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>King Cho Wong, Ruoming Peng, Eric Anderson, Jackson Ross, Bowen Yang, Meixin Cheng, Sreehari Jayaram, Malik Lenger, Xuankai Zhou, Yan Tung Kong, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Michael A. McGuire, Rainer St\"ohr, Adam Wei Tsen, Elton J. G. Santos, Xiaodong Xu, J\"org Wrachtrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Reduction for Controlled Quantum Markov Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of model reduction for Markovian quantum systems whose dynamics are described by a time-dependent Lindblad generator -- notably, as arising in the presence of external control. Our approach, which builds upon Krylov operator subspaces and operator-algebraic techniques introduced for time-independent generators, returns a reduced model that reproduces exactly the evolution of observables of interest and is guaranteed to be in Lindblad form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25546v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Grigoletto, Lorenza Viola, Francesco Ticozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge-Preserving Operations in Quantum Batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ergotropy provides a fundamental measure of the extractable work from a quantum system and, consequently, of the maximal useful energy, or charge, stored within it. Understanding how this quantity can be manipulated and transformed efficiently is crucial for advancing quantum energy management technologies. Here, we introduce and formalize the concepts of isoergotropic states and ergotropy-preserving operations, which reorganize the internal structure of ergotropy while keeping its total value unchanged. These ideas are illustrated for both discrete (two-level systems) and continuous-variable systems (single-mode Gaussian states). In each case, we show how ergotropy-preserving operations redistribute the respective coherent-incoherent and displacement-squeezing components. We further examine the thermodynamic exchanges accompanying ergotropy-preserving operations, including variations in energy and entropy, and demonstrate that these transformations can be dynamically implemented through standard beam-splitter-type interactions with an auxiliary system. Finally, we discuss the practical implications of isoergotropic states and operations in optimizing charging protocols and mitigating charge loss in open quantum batteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25549v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e H. A. Malavazi, Borhan Ahmadi, Pawe{\l} Horodecki, Pedro R. Dieguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition-Aware Decomposition of Single-Qudit Gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25561v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computation with $d$-level quantum systems, also known as qudits, benefits from the possibility to use a richer computational space compared to qubits. However, for arbitrary qudit-based hardware platform the issue is that a generic qudit operation has to be decomposed into the sequence of native operations $-$ pulses that are adjusted to the transitions between two levels in a qudit. Typically, not all levels in a qudit are simply connected to each other due to specific selection rules. Moreover, the number of pulses plays a significant role, since each pulse takes a certain execution time and may introduce error. In this paper, we propose a resource-efficient algorithm to decompose single-qudit operations into the sequence of pulses that are allowed by qudit selection rules. Using the developed algorithm, the number of pulses is at most $d(d{-}1)/2$ for an arbitrary single-qudit operation. For specific operations the algorithm could produce even fewer pulses. We provide a comparison of qudit decompositions for several types of trapped ions, specifically $^{171}\text{Yb}^+$, $^{137}\text{Ba}^+$, $^{40}\text{Ca}^+$, $^{86}\text{Rb}^+$ with different selection rules, and also decomposition for superconducting qudits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25561v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis A. Drozhzhin, Evgeniy O. Kiktenko, Aleksey K. Fedorov, Anastasiia S. Nikolaeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Non-Binary Extension of LDPC-CSS Codes Preserving Orthogonality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study finite-field extensions that preserve the same support as the parity-check matrices defining a given binary CSS code. Here, an LDPC-CSS code refers to a CSS code whose parity-check matrices are orthogonal in the sense that each pair of corresponding rows overlaps in an even (possibly zero) number of positions, typically at most twice in sparse constructions. Beyond the low-density setting, we further propose a systematic construction method that extends to arbitrary CSS codes, providing feasible finite-field generalizations that maintain both the binary support and the orthogonality condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25583v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Kasai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling the Dynamical Evolution of Quantum Coherence and Quantum Correlations in $ e^{+}e^{-} \to \Lambda\bar{\Lambda}$ Processes at BESIII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum coherence, a cornerstone of quantum mechanics, is of paramount importance for quantum information protocols. However, maintaining coherence in elementary particle systems presents significant challenges. In this work, we investigate quantum coherence and quantum correlations in the $e^{+}e^{-} \to \Lambda\bar{\Lambda}$ processes at BESIII using experimentally feasible parameters, where $\Lambda$ and $\bar{\Lambda}$ denote the spin-$1/2$ hyperon and its antihyperon, respectively. We analyze the dependence of quantum coherence and quantum correlations on the scattering angle $\varphi$. Notably, these resources reach their maximum at $\varphi=\pi/2$. We demonstrate that classical correlations can significantly delay the decay of quantum correlations and coherence. This study underscores the importance of understanding the interplay between classical and quantum correlations in high-energy particle physics, particularly in the context of hyperon-antihyperon interactions explored in the BESIII experiment. This result could have potential applications in quantum information processing and high-energy physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25615v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elhabib Jaloum, Mohamed Amazioug</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Atom-Photon Hybridization with Density-Modulated Atomic Ensembles in Coupled Cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radiation-matter hybridization allows atoms to serve as mediators of effective interactions between light modes and, conversely, to interact among themselves via light. Here we exploit the spatial structure of atomic ensembles to control the coupling between modes of distinct cavities, thereby reshaping the resulting atom-photon spectra. We show that extended homogeneous clouds suppress mode-mode couplings through destructive interference, whereas grated clouds can preserve them under specific Bragg conditions. This leads to mode-mode spectral subsplittings, where collectivity arises not only from the atom number but also from the ability to tune modes of different cavities independently. Our results establish spatially engineered atomic ensembles as a pathway to selective photon transfer between modes and precise control of many-body complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25617v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos E. M\'aximo, Romain Bachelard, Tobias Donner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoelectric detection of single spins in diamond by optically controlled discharge of long-lived trap states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrical detection methods for solid-state spins are attractive for quantum technologies, being readily chip-scalable and not subject to the small photon budgets of single emitters. However, realising electrical spin readout in wide-bandgap materials with similar fidelity and bandwidth to optical approaches remains challenging. Here, we introduce a photoelectrical spin readout scheme that detects spin information stored long-term as trapped electrical charges. Using nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centres in diamond as a model system, spin-dependent photoionisation generates charge carriers that are stored in long-lived trap states at a diamond-metal Schottky junction. On-demand illumination of the junction under electrical bias releases stored charge, yielding a photocurrent transient proportional to the amount of trapped charge and hence spin state. Spin readout after coherent control of single NVs is demonstrated using charge readout in a protocol we call charge-capture detected magnetic resonance (CCDMR), and we use charge-based imaging to identify charge carrier generation and trapping processes. Our results establish CCDMR as a new technique for solid-state spin qubit readout, combining attaractive features of electrical detection with the stability of long-lived charge traps in wide-bandgap materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25619v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. C. Ulibarri, D. J. McCloskey, D. Wang, N. Dontschuk, A. M. Martin, A. A. Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-scale implementation of quantum subspace expansion with classical shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum subspace expansion (QSE) offers promising avenues to perform spectral calculations on quantum processors but comes with a large measurement overhead. Informationally complete (IC) measurements, such as classical shadows, were recently proposed to overcome this bottleneck. Here, we report the first large-scale implementation of QSE with IC measurements. In particular, we probe the quantum phase transition of a spin model with three-body interactions, for which we observe accurate ground state energy recovery and mitigation of local order parameters across system sizes of up to 80 qubits. We achieve this by reformulating QSE as a constrained optimization problem, obtaining rigorous statistical error estimates and avoiding numerical ill-conditioning. With over $3 \times 10^4$ measurement basis randomizations per circuit and the evaluation of $O(10^{14})$ Pauli traces, this represents one of the most significant experimental realizations of classical shadows to date.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25640v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurin E. Fischer, Daniel Bultrini, Ivano Tavernelli, Francesco Tacchino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Leakage Speculation for Quantum Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Error Correction (QEC) protects qubits against bit- and phase-flip errors in the |0&gt; or |1&gt; subspace, but physical qubits can also leak into higher energy levels (e.g., |2&gt;). Leakage is especially harmful, as it corrupts all subsequent syndrome measurements and can spread to neighboring qubits. Detecting leakage on data qubits is particularly challenging, since they are never measured directly during QEC cycles. Prior work, such as eraser, addresses this by inferring leakage from syndrome patterns using a fixed heuristic. However, this approach often misclassifies benign syndromes, triggering excessive leakage-reduction circuits (LRCs). Because LRCs are themselves noisy and slow, these false triggers lengthen QEC cycles and inflate logical error rates.
  We propose gladiator, a general and adaptable leakage speculation framework that works across surface code, color code, and qLDPC codes. Offline, gladiator builds a code-aware error-propagation graph calibrated to device data. Online, it classifies each syndrome in a few nanoseconds and schedules LRC only when the observed pattern is provably leakage-dominated. This precise speculation eliminates up to 3x (and on average 2x) unnecessary LRCs, shortens QEC cycles, and suppresses false positives at their source. Evaluated on standard fault-tolerant benchmarks, gladiator delivers 1.7x-3.9x speedups and 16% reduction in logical error rate, advancing the efficiency of fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25661v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3725843.3756053</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chaithanya Naik Mude, Swamit Tannu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of actinide chemistry: towards scalable algorithms on trapped ion quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to the wide range of technical applications of actinide elements, a thorough understanding of their electronic structure could complement technological improvements in many different areas. Quantum computing could greatly aid in this understanding, as it can potentially provide exponential speedups over classical approaches, thereby offering insights into the complex electronic structure of actinide compounds. As a first foray into quantum computational chemistry of actinides, this paper compares the method of quantum computed moments (QCM) as a noisy intermediate-scale quantum algorithm with a single-ancilla version of quantum phase estimation (QPE), a quantum algorithm expected to run on fault-tolerant quantum computers. We employ these algorithms to study the reaction energetics of plutonium oxides and hydrides. In order to enable quantum hardware experiments, we use several techniques to reduce resource requirements: screening individual Hamiltonian Pauli terms to reduce the measurement requirements of QCM and variational compilation to reduce the depth of QPE circuits. Finally, we derive electronic structure descriptions from a series of representative chemical models and compute the energetics from quantum experiments on Quantinuum's H-series ion trap devices using up to 19 qubits. We find our experiments to be in excellent agreement with results from classical electronic structure calculations and state vector simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25675v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kesha Sorathia, Cono Di Paola, Gabriel Greene-Diniz, Carlo A. Gaggioli, David Zsolt Manrique, Joe Gibbs, Sean Harding, Thomas M. Soini, Neil Gaspar, Robert Harker, Mark Storr, David Munoz Ramo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry and Asymmetry in Bosonic Gaussian Systems: A Resource-Theoretic Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the interplay of symmetries and Gaussianity in bosonic systems, under closed and open dynamics, and develop a resource theory of Gaussian asymmetry. Specifically, we focus on Gaussian symmetry-respecting (covariant) operations, which serve as the free operations in this framework. We prove that any such operation can be realized via Gaussian Hamiltonians that respect the symmetry under consideration, coupled to an environment prepared in a symmetry-respecting pure Gaussian state. We further identify a family of tractable monotone functions of states that remain non-increasing under Gaussian symmetry-respecting dynamics, and are exactly conserved in closed systems. We demonstrate that these monotones are not generally respected under non-Gaussian symmetry-respecting dynamics. Along the way, we provide several technical results of independent interest to the quantum information and optics communities, including a new approach to the Stinespring dilation theorem, and an extension of Williamson's theorem for the simultaneous normal mode decomposition of Gaussian systems and conserved charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25719v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Koukoulekidis, Iman Marvian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse-free quantum state estimation with Heisenberg scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25750v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an inverse-free pure quantum state estimation protocol that achieves Heisenberg scaling. Specifically, let $\mathcal{H}\cong \mathbb{C}^d$ be a $d$-dimensional Hilbert space with an orthonormal basis $\{|1\rangle,\ldots,|d\rangle\}$ and $U$ be an unknown unitary on $\mathcal{H}$. Our protocol estimates $U|d\rangle$ to within trace distance error $\varepsilon$ using $O(\min\{d^{3/2}/\varepsilon,d/\varepsilon^2\})$ forward queries to $U$. This complements the previous result $O(d\log(d)/\varepsilon)$ by van Apeldoorn, Cornelissen, Gily\'en, and Nannicini (SODA 2023), which requires both forward and inverse queries. Moreover, our result implies a query upper bound $O(\min\{d^{3/2}/\varepsilon,1/\varepsilon^2\})$ for inverse-free amplitude estimation, improving the previous best upper bound $O(\min\{d^{2}/\varepsilon,1/\varepsilon^2\})$ based on optimal unitary estimation by Haah, Kothari, O'Donnell, and Tang (FOCS 2023), and disproving a conjecture posed in Tang and Wright (2025).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25750v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kean Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Equilibrium Propagation training in nonlinear wave systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Backpropagation learning algorithm, the workhorse of modern artificial intelligence, is notoriously difficult to implement in physical neural networks. Equilibrium Propagation (EP) is an alternative with comparable efficiency and strong potential for in-situ training. We extend EP learning to both discrete and continuous complex-valued wave systems. In contrast to previous EP implementations, our scheme is valid in the weakly dissipative regime, and readily applicable to a wide range of physical settings, even without well defined nodes, where trainable inter-node connections can be replaced by trainable local potential. We test the method in driven-dissipative exciton-polariton condensates governed by generalized Gross-Pitaevskii dynamics. Numerical studies on standard benchmarks, including a simple logical task and handwritten-digit recognition, demonstrate stable convergence, establishing a practical route to in-situ learning in physical systems in which system control is restricted to local parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16084v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Sajnok, Micha{\l} Matuszewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Compressive Sensing Inspired Monte-Carlo Method for Combinatorial Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present the Monte-Carlo Compressive Optimization algorithm, a new method to solve a combinatorial optimization problem that is assumed compressible. The method relies on random queries to the objective function in order to estimate generalized moments. Next, a greedy algorithm from compressive sensing is repurposed to find the global optimum when not overfitting to samples. We provide numerical results giving evidences that our methods overcome state-of-the-art dual annealing. Moreover, we also give theoretical justification of the algorithm success and analyze its properties. The practicality of our algorithm is enhanced by the ability to tune heuristic parameters to available computational resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24755v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Chevalier, Shimpei Yamaguchi, Wojciech Roga, Masahiro Takeoka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Glass Dynamics on Complex Hardware Topologies: A Bond-Correlated Percolation Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding how frustration and disorder shape relaxation in complex systems is a central problem in statistical physics and quantum annealing. Spin-glass models provide a natural framework to explore this connection, as their energy landscapes are governed by competing interactions and constrained topologies. We investigate the non-exponential relaxation behavior of spin glasses on network architectures relevant to quantum annealing hardware -- such as finite size Chimera, Pegasus, and Zephyr graphs -- where embedding constraints and finite connectivity strongly modulate the distribution of barriers and metastable states. This slow relaxation arises from the combined effects of frustration and disorder, which persist even beyond the conventional spin-glass transition. Within the Fortuin-Kasteleyn-Coniglio-Klein (FKCK) cluster formalism, the appearance of unfrustrated cluster regions gives rise to multiple relaxation scales, as distinct domains follow different dynamical pathways across a rugged energy landscape. This framework enables a more comprehensive characterization of spin-glass energy landscapes and offers valuable insight into how topological constraints and disorder jointly govern relaxation dynamics, providing quantitative benchmarks for evaluating the performance and limitations of quantum annealing architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24867v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viviana G\'omez, Gabriel T\'ellez, Fernando J. G\'omez-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Euclidean Monte-Carlo-informed route to ground-state preparation for quantum simulation of scalar field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulators hold great promise for studying real-time (Minkowski) dynamics of quantum field theories. Nonetheless, preparing non-trivial initial states remains a major obstacle. Euclidean-time Monte-Carlo methods yield ground-state spectra and static correlation functions that can, in principle, guide state preparation. In this work, we exploit this classical information to bridge Euclidean and Minkowski descriptions for a (1+1)-dimensional interacting scalar field theory. We propose variational ansatz families which achieve comparable ground-state energies, yet exhibit distinct correlations and local non-Gaussianity. By optimizing selected wavefunction moments with Monte-Carlo data, we obtain ansatzes that can be efficiently translated into quantum circuits. Our algorithmic cost analysis shows these circuits' gate complexity scales polynomially in system size. Our work paves the way for systematically leveraging classically-computed information to prepare initial states in quantum field theories of interest in nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24875v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Navya Gupta, Christopher David White, Zohreh Davoudi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of vector rogue waves in repulsive three-component atomic mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the experimental observation of vector extensions of Peregrine solitons in highly particle-imbalanced, pairwise immiscible three-component repulsive Bose-Einstein condensates (BECs). The possibility of an effectively attractive character of the minority components is established by constructing a generalized reduction scheme for an imbalanced N-component setup with arbitrary interaction signs. These components may suffer intra- and inter-component modulation instability, which along with the presence of an attractive potential well induces the dynamical formation of highly reproducible vector rogue waves. Exploiting different Rb hyperfine states, it is possible to flexibly tune the effective interactions stimulating the realization of a plethora of vector rogue waves, including single and double Peregrine-like wave peaks. The experimental findings are in quantitative agreement with suitable three-dimensional mean-field simulations, while quasi-one-dimensional analysis of the non-polynomial Schr\"odinger model provides additional insights into the rogue wave characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24917v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bougas, G. C. Katsimiga, S. Mossman, P. Engels, P. G. Kevrekidis, S. I. Mistakidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gouy Phase-Related Effects in the Free-Space Optical Modulation of Free Electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24939v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modulating the free-electron wave function with light brings new opportunities to create attosecond electron pulse trains, to probe the quantum coherence of systems with significantly improved spatial resolution, and to generate classical and non-classical states of light with wide tunability. It is therefore crucial to efficiently generate free-electron wave functions that are suitable for these applications. In this study, we theoretically investigate an efficient free-space optical modulation of free electrons with two counter-propagating Gaussian beams. We find that the Gaussian beams' Gouy phase not only plays a crucial role in the interaction, but also enables straight-forward generation of valuable free-electron states, including comb-shape spectra with similar amplitudes, and states with high degree of coherence. We also discuss the feasibility of demonstrating these Gouy phase-related effects with chirped femto-second laser pulses. Our study establishes a theoretical foundation and physical intuition about the role of the Gouy phase. It can provide guidance to efficiently shape the free-electron wave function for a wide range of quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24939v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhexin Zhao, Yiqi Fang, Mevlana Yunus Uluda\u{g}, Peter Hommelhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Dynamical Duality of Quantum Particles in One Dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a generalized dynamical duality for identical particles in one dimension (1D). Namely, 1D systems with arbitrary statistics -- including bosons, fermions and anyons -- approach the same momentum distribution after long-time expansion from a trap, provided they share the same scattering length for short-range interactions. This momentum distribution is uniquely given by the rapidities, or quasi-momenta, of the initial trapped state. Our results can be readily detected in quasi-1D ultracold gases with tunable s- and p-wave interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25056v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Chen, Xiaoling Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Gap Hf-HfOx-Hf Josephson Junctions for meV-Scale Particle Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25203v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconducting qubits have motivated the exploration of Josephson-junction technologies beyond quantum computing, with emerging applications in low-energy photon and phonon detection for astrophysics and dark matter searches. Achieving sensitivity at the THz (meV) scale requires materials with smaller superconducting gaps than those of conventional aluminum or niobium-based devices. Here, we report the fabrication and characterization of hafnium (Hf)-based Josephson junctions (Hf-HfOx-Hf), demonstrating Hf as a promising low-Tc material platform for ultra-low threshold single THz photon and single-phonon detection. Structural and chemical analyses reveal crystalline films and well-defined oxide barriers, while electrical transport measurements at both room and cryogenic temperatures exhibit clear Josephson behavior, enabling extraction of key junction parameters such as critical current, superconducting gap and normal-state resistance. This work presents the first comprehensive study of Hf-based junctions and their potential for next-generation superconducting detectors and qubit architectures leveraging low superconducting gap energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25203v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Balaji, M. Surendran, X. Li, A. Kemelbay, A. Gashi, C. Salemi, A. Suzuki, A. Tynes Hammack, A. Schwartzberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Silicon-based Josephson junction field-effect transistors enabling cryogenic logic and quantum technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25208v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The continuous miniaturisation of metal-oxide-semiconductor field-effect transistors (MOSFETs) from long- to short-channel architectures has advanced beyond the predictions of Moore's Law. Continued advances in semiconductor electronics, even near current scaling and performance boundaries under cryogenic conditions, are driving the development of innovative device paradigms that enable ultra-low-power and high-speed functionality. Among emerging candidates, the Josephson Junction Field-Effect Transistor (JJFET or JoFET) provides an alternative by integrating superconducting source and drain electrodes for efficient, phase-coherent operation at ultra-low temperatures. These hybrid devices have the potential to bridge conventional semiconductor electronics with cryogenic logic and quantum circuits, enabling energy-efficient and high-coherence signal processing across temperature domains. This review traces the evolution from Josephson junctions to field-effect transistors, emphasising the structural and functional innovations that underpin modern device scalability. The performance and material compatibility of JJFETs fabricated on Si, GaAs, and InGaAs substrates are analysed, alongside an assessment of their switching dynamics and material compatibility. Particular attention is given to superconductor-silicon-superconductor Josephson junctions as the active core of JJFET architectures. By unfolding more than four decades of experimental progress, this work highlights the promise of JJFETs as foundational building blocks for next-generation cryogenic logic and quantum electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25208v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusheng Xiong, Kaveh Delfanazari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immobile and mobile excitations of three-spin interactions on the diamond chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a solvable one-dimensional spin-1/2 model on the diamond chain featuring three-spin interactions, which displays both, mobile excitations driving a second-order phase transition between an ordered and a $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetry broken phase, as well as non-trivial fully immobile excitations. The model is motivated by the physics of fracton excitations, which only possess mobility in a reduced dimension compared to the full model. We provide an exact mapping of this model to an arbitrary number of independent transverse-field Ising chain segments with open boundary conditions. The number and lengths of these segments correspond directly to the number of immobile excitations and their respective distances from one another. Furthermore, we demonstrate that multiple immobile excitations exhibit Casimir-like forces between them, resulting in a non-trivial spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25349v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Bayer, M. Vieweg, K. P. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Representations of Lorentz Transformations Extended to Superluminal Observers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25385v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct an extension of the proper orthochronous Lorentz group that includes space-time transformations for observers moving with superluminal relative velocities in arbitrary direction. This extension is generated by a realization of the Klein four group depending on polar and azimuthal angles identifying a spatial direction and is obtained with matrices representing infinite velocity limits of superluminal Lorentz boosts. The resulting group has the same identity component of the whole Lorentz group O(3,1) but involutive operators corresponding to an infinite speed boost and its negative in place of parity and time reversal. Different spatial directions in the definition of Klein group realization give rise to equivalent group extensions. We then define the extended Poincare group including translations and classify its unitary irreducible representations (UIRs). The resulting UIRs are induced from Wigner's UIRs of standard Poincare group and depend on the action of the extended Lorentz group defined on momentum space. UIRs corresponding to non lightlike orbits restrict to the ordinary Poincare subgroup as a multiplicity one direct sum of a massive forward, a massive backward and a tachyonic Wigner UIR while for lightlike orbits as a multiplicity one direct sum of a forward and backward massless Wigner UIR. We then derive wave equations corresponding to solutions of the Casimir eigenvalue problem of Poincare algebra obtained differentiating the above representations. This set of equations contains all the wave equations known to date in quantum field theory together with new wave equations describing tachyonic behaviour and a new class of massless representations. We finally show that tachyonic wave functions provide a relevant representation theoretic tool for interpretation of parity violation phenomena in quantum field theory</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25385v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Zaopo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the injective norm of random fermionic states and skew-symmetric tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25474v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the injective norm of random skew-symmetric tensors and the associated fermionic quantum states, a natural measure of multipartite entanglement for systems of indistinguishable particles. Extending recent advances on random quantum states, we analyze both real and complex skew-symmetric Gaussian ensembles in two asymptotic regimes: fixed particle number with increasing one-particle Hilbert space dimension, and joint scaling with fixed filling fraction. Using the Kac--Rice formula on the Grassmann manifold, we derive high-probability upper bounds on the injective norm and establish sharp asymptotics in both regimes. Interestingly, a duality relation under particle--hole transformation is uncovered, revealing a symmetry of the injective norm under the action of the Hodge star operator. We complement our analytical results with numerical simulations for low fermion numbers, which match the predicted bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25474v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephane Dartois, Parham Radpay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of entanglement fluctuations and quantum Mpemba effect in the $\nu=1$ QSSEP model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the out-of-equilibrium dynamics of entanglement fluctuations in the $\nu=1$ Quantum Symmetric Simple Exclusion Process, a free-fermion chain with hopping amplitudes that are stochastic in time but homogeneous in space. Previous work showed that the average entanglement growth after a quantum quench can be explained in terms of pairs of entangled quasiparticles performing random walks, leading to diffusive entanglement spreading. By incorporating the noise-induced statistical correlations between the quasiparticles, we extend this description to the full-time probability distribution of the entanglement entropy. Our generalized quasiparticle picture allows us to compute the average time evolution of a generic function of the reduced density matrix of a subsystem. We also apply our result to the entanglement asymmetry. This allows us to investigate the restoration of particle-number symmetry in the dynamics from initial states with no well-defined particle number, and the emergence of the quantum Mpemba effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Russotto, Filiberto Ares, Pasquale Calabrese, Vincenzo Alba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-generation interferometry with gauge-invariant linear optical scatterers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25535v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Measurement technology employing optical interference phenomena such as a fringe pattern or frequency shift has been evolving for more than a century. The systems are being designed better, and their components are being built better. But the major components themselves hardly change. Most modern interferometers rely on the same conventional set of components to separate the electromagnetic field into multiple beams, such as plate optics and beam-splitters. This naturally limits the design scope and thus the potential applicability and performance. However, recent investigations suggest that incorporating novel, higher-dimensional linear-optical splitters in interferometer design can lead to several improvements. In this work, we review the underlying theory of these novel optical scatterers and some demonstrated configurations with enhanced resolution. The basic principles of optical interference and optical phase sensing are discussed in tandem. Emphasis is placed on both familiar and unfamiliar scatterers, such as the maximally-symmetric Grover multiport, whose actions are left unchanged by certain gauge transformations. These higher-dimensional, gauge-invariant multiports embody a new class of building blocks which can tailor optical interference for metrology in unconventional ways.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25535v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/metrology5040065</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Metrology 2025, 5, 65</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christopher R. Schwarze, Anthony D. Manni, David S. Simon, Abdoulaye Ndao, Alexander V. Sergienko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25557v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a hybrid quantum-classical recurrent neural network (QRNN) architecture in which the entire recurrent core is realized as a parametrized quantum circuit (PQC) controlled by a classical feedforward network. The hidden state is the quantum state of an $n$-qubit PQC, residing in an exponentially large Hilbert space $\mathbb{C}^{2^n}$. The PQC is unitary by construction, making the hidden-state evolution norm-preserving without external constraints. At each timestep, mid-circuit readouts are combined with the input embedding and processed by the feedforward network, which provides explicit classical nonlinearity. The outputs parametrize the PQC, which updates the hidden state via unitary dynamics. The QRNN is compact and physically consistent, and it unifies (i) unitary recurrence as a high-capacity memory, (ii) partial observation via mid-circuit measurements, and (iii) nonlinear classical control for input-conditioned parametrization. We evaluate the model in simulation with up to 14 qubits on sentiment analysis, MNIST, permuted MNIST, copying memory, and language modeling, adopting projective measurements as a limiting case to obtain mid-circuit readouts while maintaining a coherent recurrent quantum memory. We further devise a soft attention mechanism over the mid-circuit readouts in a sequence-to-sequence model and show its effectiveness for machine translation. To our knowledge, this is the first model (RNN or otherwise) grounded in quantum operations to achieve competitive performance against strong classical baselines across a broad class of sequence-learning tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25557v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenduan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Blocks in 2d Carrollian/Galilean CFTs and Excited State Entanglement Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We advance the study of flat space holography by computing the entanglement entropy of highly excited states in two-dimensional Carrollian/Galilean Conformal Field Theories (C/G CFTs). Our approach is centered on a novel, physically intuitive derivation of the heavy-light conformal block in the large central charge limit, where the backreaction of heavy operators is absorbed by a C/G conformal coordinate transformation. Using this result and the replica trick, we find that the entanglement entropy of highly excited states assumes a thermal form, providing a concrete realization of the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH). This field-theoretic result perfectly reproduces the holographic entanglement entropy computed via the swing surface proposal in three-dimensional Einstein gravity, for backgrounds corresponding to spinning particles and Flat Space Cosmological solutions. This agreement establishes a precise dictionary relating the weight $\Delta$ and charge $\xi$ of the boundary state to the mass $m$ and angular momentum $j$ of the dual spacetime, offering a powerful consistency check for the Flat/CCFT correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25688v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng-Xiang Hao, Shunta Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast high-fidelity baseband reset of a latched state for quantum dot qubit readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25703v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A common method for reading out the state of a spin qubit is by latching one logical qubit state, either $|1\rangle$ or $|0\rangle$, onto a different, metastable charge state. Such a latched state can provide a superior charge sensing signal for qubit readout, and it can have a lifetime chosen to be long enough that the charge sensed readout can be high fidelity. However, the passive reset out of latched states is inherently long, which is not desirable. In this work, we demonstrate an on-demand, high fidelity (&gt; 99%) re-initialization of a quantum dot qubit out of a latched readout state. The method is simple to apply as it involves a single baseband voltage pulse to a specific region in the quantum dot stability diagram where the relaxation time from the latched state to the ground state is over 50 times faster. We describe the mechanism for the reset process as well as the boundaries for the optimal reset region in the qubit gate voltage space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25703v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Marciniec, M. A. Wolfe, Tyler Kovach, J. Reily, Sanghyeok Park, Jared Benson, Mark Friesen, Benjamin D. Woods, Matthew J. Curry, Nathaniel C. Bishop, J. Corrigan, M. A. Eriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ETH-monotonicity in two-dimensional systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a recently discovered property of many-body quantum chaotic systems called ETH-monotonicity in two-dimensional systems. Our new results further support ETH-monotonicity in these higher dimensional systems. We show that the flattening rate of the $f$-function is directly proportional to the number of degrees of freedom in the system, so as $L^2$ where $L$ is the linear size of the system, and in general, expected to be $L^d$ where $d$ is the spatial dimension of the system. We also show that the flattening rate is directly proportional to the particle (or hole) number for systems of same spatial size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25711v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilakash Sorokhaibam, Anjan Daimari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Random Matrix Behavior of a Fermionic Quantum Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The pursuit of universal governing principles is a foundational endeavor in physics, driving breakthroughs from thermodynamics to general relativity and quantum mechanics. In 1951, Wigner introduced the concept of a statistical description of energy levels of heavy atoms, which led to the rise of Random Matrix Theory (RMT) in physics. The theory successfully captured spectral properties across a wide range of atomic systems, circumventing the complexities of quantum many-body interactions. Rooted in the fundamental principles of stochasticity and symmetry, RMT has since found applications and revealed universal laws in diverse physical contexts, from quantum field theory to disordered systems and wireless communications. A particularly compelling application arises in describing the mathematical structure of the many-body wavefunction of non-interacting Fermi gases, which underpins a complex spatial organization driven by Pauli's exclusion principle. However, experimental validation of the counting statistics predicted in such systems has remained elusive. Here, we probe at the single-atom level ultracold atomic Fermi gases made of two interacting spin states, obtaining direct access to their counting statistics in situ. Our measurements show that, while the system is strongly attractive, each spin-component is extremely well described by RMT predictions based on Fredholm determinants. Our results constitutes the first experimental validation of the Fermi-sphere point process through the lens of RMT, and establishes its relevance for strongly-interacting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Dixmerias, Giuseppe Del Vecchio Del Vecchio, Cyprien Daix, Joris Verstraten, Tim de Jongh, Bruno Peaudecerf, Pierre Le Doussal, Gr\'egory Schehr, Tarik Yefsah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of Enhanced Shortcuts to Adiabaticity in Lattice Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.04420v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Shortcuts to adiabaticity (STA) are a collection of quantum control techniques that achieve high fidelity outside of the adiabatic regime. Recently an extension to shortcuts to adiabaticity was proposed by the authors [Phys. Rev. Research 2, 023360 (2020)]. This new method, enhanced shortcuts to adiabaticity (eSTA), provides an extension to the original STA control functions and allows effective control of systems not amenable to STA methods. It is conjectured that eSTA schemes also enjoy an improved stability over their STA counterparts. We provide numerical evidence of this claim by applying eSTA to fast atomic transport using an optical lattice, and evaluating appropriate stability measures. We show that the eSTA schemes not only produce higher fidelities, but also remain more stable against errors than the original STA schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.04420v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.105.013311</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chris Whitty, Anthony Kiely, Andreas Ruschhaupt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved anharmonic trap expansion through enhanced shortcuts to adiabaticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.02288v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Shortcuts to adiabaticity (STA) have been successfully applied both theoretically and experimentally to a wide variety of quantum control tasks. In previous work the authors have developed an analytic extension to shortcuts to adiabaticity, called enhanced shortcuts to adiabaticity (eSTA), that extends STA methods to systems where STA cannot be applied directly [Phys. Rev. Research 2, 023360 (2020)]. Here we generalize this approach and construct an alternative eSTA method that takes advantage of higher order terms. We apply this eSTA method to the expansion of both a Gaussian trap and accordion lattice potential, demonstrating the improved fidelity and robustness of eSTA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.02288v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6455/ac8bb7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>C. Whitty, A. Kiely, A. Ruschhaupt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Transformer: Accelerating model inference via quantum linear algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16714v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Powerful generative artificial intelligence from large language models (LLMs) harnesses extensive computational resources for inference. In this work, we investigate the transformer architecture, a key component of these models, under the lens of fault-tolerant quantum computing. We develop quantum subroutines to construct the building blocks in the transformer, including the self-attention, residual connection with layer normalization, and feed-forward network. As an important subroutine, we show how to efficiently implement the Hadamard product and element-wise functions of matrices on quantum computers. Our algorithm prepares an amplitude encoding of the transformer output, which can be measured for prediction or use in the next layer. We find that the matrix norm of the input sequence plays a dominant role in the quantum complexity. With numerical experiments on open-source LLMs, including for bio-informatics applications, we demonstrate the potential of a quantum speedup for transformer inference in practical regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16714v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naixu Guo, Zhan Yu, Matthew Choi, Yizhan Han, Aman Agrawal, Kouhei Nakaji, Al\'an Aspuru-Guzik, Patrick Rebentrost</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sum of entanglement and subsystem coherence is invariant under quantum reference frame transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19448v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent work on quantum reference frames (QRFs) has demonstrated that superposition and entanglement are properties that change under QRF transformations. Given their utility in quantum information processing, it is important to understand how a mere change of perspective can produce or reduce these resources. Here we find a trade-off between entanglement and subsystem coherence under a QRF transformation, in the form of a conservation theorem for their sum, for two pairs of measures. Moreover, we find a weaker trade-off for any possible pair of measures. Finally, we discuss the implications of this interplay for violations of Bell's inequalities, clarifying that for any choice of QRF, there is a quantum resource responsible for the violation. These findings contribute to a better understanding of the quantum information theoretic aspects of QRFs, offering a foundation for future exploration in both quantum theory and quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19448v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/h6b3-y4vt</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 010201 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Cepollaro, Ali Akil, Pawe{\l} Cie\'sli\'nski, Anne-Catherine de la Hamette, \v{C}aslav Brukner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the phase transition of the massive Thirring model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00803v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum computing technology have enabled the study of fermionic systems at finite temperature via quantum simulations. This presents a novel approach to investigating the chiral phase transition in such systems. Among these, the quantum minimally entangled typical thermal states~(QMETTS) algorithm has recently attracted considerable interest. The massive Thirring model, which exhibits a variety of phenomena at low temperatures, includes both a chiral phase transition and a topologically non-trivial ground state. It therefore raises the intriguing question of whether its phase transition can be studied using a quantum simulation approach. In this study, the chiral phase transition of the massive Thirring model and its dual topological phase transition are studied using the QMETTS algorithm. Numerical results are obtained on a classical computer simulating circuit-based quantum computations. The results show that QMETTS is able to accurately reproduce the phase transition and thermodynamic properties of the massive Thirring model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00803v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP09(2025)120</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics volume 2025, Article number: 120 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Qi Gong, Ji-Chong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics in an emergent quantum-like state space generated by a nonlinear classical network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07500v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work exploits a framework whereby a graph (in the mathematical sense) serves to connect a classical system to a state space that we call `quantum-like' (QL). The QL states comprise arbitrary superpositions of states in a tensor product basis. The graph plays a special dual role by directing design of the classical system and defining the state space. We study a specific example of a large, dynamical classical system -- a system of coupled phase oscillators -- that maps, via a graph, to the QL state space. We investigate how mixedness of the state diminishes or increases as the underlying classical system synchronizes or de-synchronizes respectively. This shows the interplay between the nonlinear dynamics of the variables of the classical system and the QL state space. We prove that maps from one time point to another in the state space are linear maps. In the limit of a strongly phase-locked classical network -- that is, where couplings between phase oscillators are very large -- the state space evolves according to unitary dynamics, whereas in the cases of weaker synchronization, the classical variables act as a hidden environment that promotes decoherence of superpositions. We examine how similar the properties of QL states are to quantum states. We find that during decoherence of the QL states, the off-diagonal density matrix elements decay and that this decay can be observed in any basis we choose for measurement. More surprisingly, we show that a no-cloning theorem (that is, a state of a QL bit cannot be copied) applies not only to the QL states, but also to the underlying classical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07500v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory D. Scholes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-overhead Magic State Circuits with Transversal CNOTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10291v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the successful demonstration of transversal CNOTs in many recent experiments, it is the right moment to examine its implications on one of the most critical parts of fault-tolerant computation -- magic state preparation. Using an algorithm that can recompile and simplify a circuit of consecutive multi-qubit phase rotations, we manage to construct fault-tolerant circuits for CCZ, CS and T states with much lower CNOT depths and qubit counts than before and minimal T-depth for the given workspace. These circuits can play crucial roles in fault-tolerant computation with transversal CNOTs, and we hope that the algorithms and methods developed in this paper can be used to further simplify other protocols in similar contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10291v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Fazio, Mark Webster, Zhenyu Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-resolved and Superradiantly Amplified Unruh Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16219v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We identify low-acceleration conditions under which the Unruh effect manifests as an early superradiant burst in a collection of excited atoms. The resulting amplified Unruh signal is resolved from the inertial signal both in time and intensity. We demonstrate theoretically that these conditions are realized inside a sub-resonant cavity that highly suppresses the response of an inertial atom, while allowing significant response from an accelerated atom as, owing to the acceleration-induced spectral broadening, it can still couple to the available field modes. The setup thus selectively amplifies the modified field fluctuations underlying the Unruh effect into an early superradiant burst. In comparison, the field fluctuations perceived inertially would cause a superradiant burst much later. In this way, we simultaneously address the extreme acceleration requirement, the weak Unruh signal, and the dominance of the inertial signal, all within a single experimental arrangement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16219v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6z1l-kkmk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 183601 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Akhil Deswal, Navdeep Arya, Kinjalk Lochan, Sandeep K. Goyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Analysis of Zero-Noise Extrapolation: Polynomial Methods, Error Bounds, and Simultaneous Physical-Algorithmic Error Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20673v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Zero-noise extrapolation (ZNE) is a widely used quantum error mitigation technique that artificially amplifies circuit noise and then extrapolates the results to the noise-free circuit. A common ZNE approach is Richardson extrapolation, which relies on polynomial interpolation. Despite its simplicity, efficient implementations of Richardson extrapolation face several challenges, including approximation errors from the non-polynomial behavior of noise channels, overfitting due to polynomial interpolation, and exponentially amplified measurement noise. This paper provides a comprehensive analysis of these challenges, presenting bias and variance bounds that quantify approximation errors. Additionally, for any precision $\varepsilon$, our results offer an estimate of the necessary sample complexity. We further extend the analysis to polynomial least squares-based extrapolation, which mitigates measurement noise and avoids overfitting. Finally, we propose a strategy for simultaneously mitigating circuit and algorithmic errors in the Trotter-Suzuki algorithm by jointly scaling the time step size and the noise level. This strategy provides a practical tool to enhance the reliability of near-term quantum computations. We support our theoretical findings with numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20673v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pegah Mohammadipour, Xiantao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steiner Traveling Salesman Problem with Quantum Annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02388v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Steiner Traveling Salesman Problem (STSP) is a variant of the classical Traveling Salesman Problem. The STSP involves incorporating steiner nodes, which are extra nodes not originally part of the required visit set but that can be added to the route to enhance the overall solution and minimize the total travel cost. Given the NP-hard nature of the STSP, we propose a quantum approach to address it. Specifically, we employ quantum annealing using D-Wave's hardware to explore its potential for solving this problem. To enhance computational feasibility, we develop a preprocessing method that effectively reduces the network size. Our experimental results demonstrate that this reduction technique significantly decreases the problem complexity, making the Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization formulation, the standard input for quantum annealers, better suited for existing quantum hardware. Furthermore, the results highlight the potential of quantum annealing as a promising and innovative approach for solving the STSP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02388v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3712255.3734313</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alessia Ciacco, Francesca Guerriero, Eneko Osaba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invasive mid-circuit measurement and reset on atomic qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12538v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mid-circuit measurement and reset of subsets of qubits is a crucial ingredient of quantum error correction and many quantum information applications. Measurement of atomic qubits is accomplished through resonant fluorescence, which typically disturbs neighboring atoms due to photon scattering. We propose and prototype a new scheme for measurement that provides both spatial and spectral isolation by using tightly-focused individual laser beams and narrow atomic transitions. The unique advantage of this scheme is that all operations are applied exclusively to the read-out qubit, with negligible disturbance to the other qubits of the same species and little overhead. In this letter, we pave the way for non-invasive and high fidelity mid-circuit measurement and demonstrate all key building blocks on a single trapped barium ion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12538v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuo-Yao Chen, Isabella Goetting, George Toh, Yichao Yu, Mikhail Shalaev, Sagnik Saha, Ashish Kalakuntla, Harriet Bufan Shi, Christopher Monroe, Alexander Kozhanov, Crystal Noel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact analysis of AC sensors based on Floquet time crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22731v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the behavior of general Floquet Time Crystals (FTCs), including prethermal ones, in closed systems acting as AC sensors. We provide an analytical treatment of their quantum Fisher information (QFI) dynamics, which characterizes the ultimate sensor accuracy. By tuning the direction and frequency of the AC field, we show how to induce transitions resonantly between macroscopic paired cat states in the FTC sensor. This allows for robust Heisenberg scaling precision (QFI $\sim N^2 t^2$) for exponentially long times in the system size. The QFI dynamics exhibit, moreover, a characteristic step-like structure in time due to the eventual dephasing along the cat subspaces. The behavior is discussed for various initial sensor preparations, including ground states and low- and high-correlated states. Furthermore, we examine the performance of the sensor along the FTC phase transition; with the QFI capturing its critical exponents. Our findings are presented for both linear and nonlinear response regimes and illustrated for a specific FTC based on the long-range interacting LMG model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22731v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Tsypilnikov, Matheus Fibger, Fernando Iemini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conclusive Local State Marking: More Nonlocality With No Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09415v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlocality exhibited by ensembles of composite quantum states, wherein local operations and classical communication (LOCC) yield suboptimal discrimination probabilities compared to global strategies, is one of the striking nonclassical features of quantum theory. A variant of this phenomenon arises in conclusive local state discrimination, where the correct state must be identified with zero error, albeit allowing for inconclusive outcomes. More recently, the notion of local state marking has been introduced, with the focus shifted to correctly identifying the permutation of a subset of states randomly chosen from a given set of multipartite states under LOCC. In this work, we unify these two approaches by introducing the task of conclusive local state marking, which reveals a finer hierarchy of nonlocality in multipartite quantum state ensembles. Notably, we demonstrate that certain ensembles of product states can exhibit a stronger form of nonlocality than entangled ensembles traditionally considered highly nonlocal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09415v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samrat Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying imaginarity of quantum operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Complex numbers are theoretically proved and experimentally confirmed as necessary in quantum mechanics and quantum information, and a resource theory of imaginarity of quantum states has been established. In this work, we establish a framework to quantify the imaginarity of quantum operations from the perspective of the ability to create or detect imaginarity, following the idea by Theurer {\it et al.} [Phys. Rev. Lett. \textbf{122}, 190405 (2019)] used in coherence theory. We present two types of imaginarity measures of quantum operations based on the norm and the weight, investigate their properties and relations, and derive the analytical formulas of the measure under the trace norm for qubit unitary operations. The results provide new insights into imaginarity of operations and deepen our understanding of dynamical imaginarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09747v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanfa Wu, Zhaoqi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective many-body dynamics in a solid-state quantum sensor controlled through nanoscale magnetic gradients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11920v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Coherent collective dynamics of strongly interacting qubits are a central resource in quantum information science, with applications from quantum computing and simulation to metrology. While electronic spins interact strongly via dipolar couplings in dense solid-state ensembles, imperfections and positional disorder pose major obstacles to coherent correlated behavior, limiting their usefulness. Here, we realize collective many-body dynamics by combining time-dependent magnetic field gradients with global coherent control of dense electron spin ensembles in diamond. We control and probe the dynamics of nanometer-scale spin spirals, and, by exploiting Hamiltonian engineering that enhances the microscopic symmetry of the interactions, we observe a disorder-resilient collective spin evolution. Our results establish a pathway to interaction-enhanced quantum metrology and nanoscale imaging of materials and biological systems under ambient conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11920v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Put, Nathaniel T. Leitao, Haoyang Gao, Christina Spaegele, Oksana Makarova, Lillian B. Hughes Wyatt, Andrew C. Maccabe, Matthew Mammen, Bartholomeus Machielse, Hengyun Zhou, Szymon Pustelny, Ania C. Bleszynski Jayich, Federico Capasso, Leigh S. Martin, Hongkun Park, Mikhail D. Lukin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity Optomechanical Probe of Gravity Between Massive Mechanical Oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13398v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exploring gravitational interactions between objects with small masses has become increasingly timely. Concurrently, oscillators with masses ranging between milligrams and grams in cavity optomechanical systems sparked interest for probing gravity, and even investigating gravity within macroscopic quantum systems. Here we present a measurement scheme for probing gravity in a microwave optomechanical setup that incorporates periodic gravitational modulation between the test mass and the driven source mass at the milligram scale. Optomechanically induced transparency (OMIT) can be utilized to sense the gravitational interactions between test masses and source masses. Specifically, the relative variation in the height of the OMIT peak, expressed as $|1 + re^{i\phi}|^2 - 1$, where $r$ represents the ratio of the amplitude of the gravitational driving force to the radiation pressure force of the probe tone, and $\phi$ denotes their phase difference, can reach up to 2.3\% under plausible experimental conditions. This work may facilitate cavity-optomechanical probing of gravitational coupling between milligram-scale mechanical oscillators, a mass regime where quantum and gravitational effects converge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13398v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/m2zy-3ywx</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ziqian Tang, Wenlong Li, Huanying Sun, Xiaoxia Cai, Tiefu Li, Yulong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase structure of below-threshold harmonics in aligned molecules: a few-level model system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20829v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We utilize few-level model systems to analyze the polarization and phase properties of below-threshold harmonics generated from aligned molecules. In a two-level system, we find that the phase of emitted harmonics undergoes a distinct change. For harmonics with photon energies below the transition energy between the dominant field-dressed states, the phase alternates by $\pi$ between successive odd harmonic orders. In contrast, the phase remains constant for harmonics above the transition energy. Exploiting this behavior, we construct a four-level model composed of two uncoupled two-level systems aligned along orthogonal directions. We demonstrate that with selected transition frequencies lower-order harmonics follow the polarization of the linearly polarized driving field while higher-order harmonics exhibit a mirrored polarization. The model predicts that aligned systems with orthogonal transition dipoles may show analogous phase and polarization features in the below-threshold regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20829v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Sch\"opa, Falk-Erik Wiechmann, Franziska Fennel, Dieter Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorizability of multi-party quantum sequence discrimination under local operations and classical communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider multi-party quantum sequence discrimination under local operations and classical communication(LOCC), and provide conditions under which the optimal LOCC discrimination of a multi-party quantum sequence ensemble can be factorized into that of each individual ensemble. In other words, the optimal LOCC discrimination of a multi-party quantum sequence ensemble can be achieved just by performing optimal LOCC discrimination independently at each step of the quantum sequence. We also illustrate through examples of multi-party quantum states that such factorizability of optimal LOCC discrimination is possible. We further establish a necessary and sufficient condition under which the optimal LOCC discrimination of a multi-party quantum state ensemble can be realized just by guessing the state with the largest probability. Our results can provide a useful application to investigate the fundamental limits of quantum data hiding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05050v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghoon Ha, Jeong San Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superstrong Dynamics and Directional Emission of a Giant Atom in a Structured Bath</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01579v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum emitters coupled to waveguides with nonlinear dispersion show rich quantum dynamics with the promise of implementing non-trivial non-Markovian quantum models. Recent advances in engineered photonic environments now allow the realization of discrete-site waveguides with tailored dispersion, yet most implementations of waveguide QED remain limited to a local qubit-waveguide coupling. Here, we study a transmon qubit non-locally coupled to a high-impedance coupled cavity array (CCA), thus implementing a \emph{giant atom} in a structured photonic environment. The non-local coupling produces interference with the CCA modes, selectively enhancing interaction with even and long-wavelength modes, while suppressing coupling to odd and short-wavelength modes. For a subset of symmetric, long-wavelength modes, we reach the superstrong coupling regime. In this regime, measurements of the atomic participation ratio reveal strongly hybridized eigenmodes on a par with a strongly reduced qubit participation at the frequency of maximum hybridization with the qubit, in agreement with theory. Time-domain measurements of the qubit dynamics show clear deviations from the single-mode Jaynes--Cummings model, marked by the emergence of mode--mode interactions. By breaking spatial inversion symmetry of the CCA, the qubit seeds dressed eigenmodes confined to either the right or left of the qubit, which we exploit to implement and characterize a directional photon-emission protocol. These results demonstrate precise control over multimode light--matter interaction in a structured photonic environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01579v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Jouanny, L\'eo Peyruchat, Marco Scigliuzzo, Alberto Mercurio, Enrico Di Benedetto, Daniele De Bernardis, Davide Sbroggi\`o, Simone Frasca, Vincenzo Savona, Francesco Ciccarello, Pasquale Scarlino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Fisher information matrix via its classical counterpart from random measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08196v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Preconditioning with the quantum Fisher information matrix (QFIM) is a popular approach in quantum variational algorithms. Yet the QFIM is costly to obtain directly, usually requiring more state preparation than its classical counterpart: the classical Fisher information matrix (CFIM). By revealing its relation to covariant measurement in quantum metrology, we show that averaging the classical Fisher information matrix over Haar-random measurement bases yields $\mathbb{E}_{U\sim\mu_H}[F^U(\boldsymbol{\theta})] = \frac{1}{2}Q(\boldsymbol{\theta})$ for pure states in $\mathbb{C}^N$. Furthermore, we obtain the variance of CFIM ($O(N^{-1})$) and establish non-asymptotic concentration bounds ($\exp(-\Theta(N)t^2)$), demonstrating that using few random measurement bases is sufficient to approximate the QFIM accurately, especially in high-dimensional settings. This work establishes a solid theoretical foundation for efficient quantum natural gradient methods via randomized measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08196v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianfeng Lu, Kecen Sha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on Marek Czachor article entitled "On Relativity of Quantumness as Implied by Relativity of Arithmetic and Probability"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02412v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Czachor's model of hierarchical arithmetics begins with a valid formal premise but fixes the key probability mapping g by importing the Born rule and Fubini-Study metric from standard quantum mechanics, where Born probabilities are Kolmogorov within a fixed measurement context. This g is then applied in a non-Newtonian hidden-variable setting, producing a hybrid framework whose agreement with quantum correlations is built in by design, not derived from new physics, and thus does not constitute a genuine counterexample to Bell's theorem</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02412v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Sienicki, Miko{\l}aj Sienicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of quantum processes: An operational framework for free energy and reversible athermality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12790v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the thermodynamics of quantum processes (quantum channels) by axiomatically introducing the free energy for channels, defined via the quantum relative entropy with an absolutely thermal channel whose fixed output is in equilibrium with a thermal reservoir. This definition finds strong support through its operational interpretations in designated quantum information and thermodynamic tasks. We construct a resource theory of athermality for quantum processes, where free operations are Gibbs preserving superchannels and golden units are unitary channels with respect to absolutely thermal channel having fully degenerate output Hamiltonian. We exactly characterize the one-shot distillation and formation of quantum channels using hypothesis-testing and max-relative entropy with respect to the absolutely thermal channel. These rates converge asymptotically to the channel free energy (up to a multiplicative factor of half the inverse temperature), establishing its operational meaning and proving the asymptotic reversibility of the athermality. We show the direct relation between the resource theory of athermality and quantum information tasks such as private randomness and purity distillation, and thermodynamic tasks of erasure and work extraction. Our work connects the core thermodynamic concepts of free energy, energy, entropy, and maximal extractable work of quantum processes to their information processing capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12790v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Badhani, Dhanuja G S, Siddhartha Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal key rates for quantum key distribution with partial source characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Numerical security proofs based on conic optimization are known to deliver optimal secret-key rates, but so far they have mostly assumed that the emitted states are fully characterized. In practice, this assumption is unrealistic, since real devices inevitably suffer from imperfections and side channels that are extremely difficult to model in detail. Here, we extend conic-optimization methods to scenarios where only partial information about the emitted states is known, covering both prepare-and-measure and measurement-device-independent protocols. We demonstrate that our method outperforms state-of-the-art analytical and numerical approaches under realistic source imperfections, especially for protocols that use non-qubit encodings. These results advance numerical-based proofs towards a standard, implementation-ready framework for evaluating quantum key distribution protocols in the presence of source imperfections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13085v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margarida Pereira, Guillermo Curr\'as-Lorenzo, Mateus Ara\'ujo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced State Embedding for Error Correction in Quantum Cryptography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19989v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Encoding in a high-dimensional Hilbert space improves noise resilience in quantum information processing. This approach, however, may result in cross-mode coupling and detection complexities, thereby reducing quantum cryptography performance. This fundamental trade-off between correctness and secrecy motivates the search for quantum error-correction approaches for cryptography. Here, we introduce state embeddings that use a k-symbol subset within a d-dimensional Hilbert space, tailored to the channel's error structure. In the framework of quantum error-correction, our reduced-state embedding realizes an explicit erasure-type error-correction within the quantum channel. We demonstrate the advantage of our scheme in realistic quantum channels, producing a higher secure key rate. We validate our approach using a d=25 quantum key distribution (QKD) experimental data, derive closed-form expressions for the key rate and threshold, and determine the optimum at k=5. These findings advance high-dimensional QKD and pave the way to error-correction and modulation for quantum cryptography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19989v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Kam, Kfir Sulimany, Shai Tsesses, Uzi Pereg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorizability of optimal quantum sequence discrimination under maximum-confidence measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20311v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the discrimination of quantum sequences under maximum-confidence measurements and show that the optimal discrimination of a quantum sequence ensemble can always be factorized into that of each individual ensemble. In other words, the optimal quantum sequence discrimination under maximum-confidence measurements can be achieved just by performing a maximum-confidence discrimination independently at each step of the quantum sequence. We also show that the maximum confidence of identifying a quantum sequence is to achieve the maximum confidence of identifying each state comprising the quantum sequence. We further provide a necessary and sufficient condition for the optimal quantum state discrimination under maximum-confidence measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20311v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghoon Ha, Jeong San Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phenomenological Noise Models and Optimal Thresholds of the 3D Toric Code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20489v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Three-dimensional (3D) topological codes offer the advantage of supporting fault-tolerant implementations of non-Clifford gates, yet their performance against realistic noise remains largely unexplored. In this work, we focus on the paradigmatic 3D toric code and investigate its fault-tolerance thresholds in the presence of both Pauli and measurement errors. Two randomly coupled lattice gauge models that describe the code's correctability are derived, including a random 2-form $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge theory. By exploiting a generalized duality technique, we show that the 3D toric code exhibits optimal thresholds of $p^{X,M}_{th} \approx 11\%$ and $p^{Z,M}_{th} \approx 2\%$ against bit-flip and phase-flip errors, respectively. These threshold values show modest reductions compared to the case of perfect measurements, establishing the robustness of the 3D toric code against measurement errors. Our results constitute a substantial advance towards assessing the practical performance of 3D topological codes. This contribution is timely and in high demand, as rapid hardware advancements are bringing complex codes into experimental reach. Moreover, our work highlights the interdisciplinary nature of fault-tolerant quantum computation and holds significant interest for quantum information science, high-energy physics, and condensed matter physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20489v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Ze Xu, Yin Zhong, Miguel A. Martin-Delgado, Hao Song, Ke Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Van Hove singularities in stabilizer entropy densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22253v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The probability distribution of a measure of non-stabilizerness, also known as magic, is investigated for Haar-random pure quantum states. Focusing on the stabilizer R\'enyi entropies, the associated probability density functions (PDFs) are found to display distinct non-analytic features analogous to Van Hove singularities in condensed matter systems. For a single qubit, the stabilizer purity exhibits a logarithmic divergence at a critical value corresponding to a saddle point on the Bloch sphere. This divergence occurs at the $|H\rangle$-magic states, which hence can be identified as states for which the density of non-stabilizerness in the Hilbert space is infinite. An exact expression for the PDF is derived for the case $\alpha = 2$, with analytical predictions confirmed by numerical simulations. The logarithmic divergence disappears for dimensions $d \ge 3$, in agreement with the behavior of ordinary Van Hove singularities on flat manifolds. In addition, it is shown that, for one qubit, the linear stabilizer entropy is directly related to the partial incompatibility of quantum measurements, one of the defining properties of quantum mechanics, at the basis of Stern-Gerlach experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22253v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Iannotti, Lorenzo Campos Venuti, Alioscia Hamma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple electromagnetic model of the electron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22384v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a toroidal electromagnetic ansatz that provides a realistic microscopic model of the QED electron. The proposed toroidal electromagnetic wave satisfies Maxwell's equations and reproduces fundamental properties of the electron as described in quantum electrodynamics (QED). Within this framework, the electron is modeled as a rotating electromagnetic wave confined to a toroidal geometry. Parameter optimization yields quantitative agreement with the electron charge e, spin $\hbar/2$, and magnetic moment $\mu_B(1 + \alpha/2\pi)$, incorporating the Schwinger anomalous magnetic moment correction. The model yields an amplitude on the order of the Schwinger scale where electron-positron pair production occurs. The major radius corresponds to the Compton wavelength scale, while the monochromatic frequency is consistent with the de Broglie-Dirac frequency. The phase velocity is found to be $2c$, and the computed rest energy approximates $0.8 m_e c^2$. This representation provides a microscopic classical electromagnetic framework that encapsulates the properties of the QED electron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22384v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos A. M. dos Santos, Marc J. J. Fleury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanics of Stochastic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23654v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a fundamental framework for the quantum mechanics of stochastic systems (QMSS), showing that classical discrete stochastic processes emerge naturally as perturbations of the quantum harmonic oscillator (QHO). By constructing exact perturbation potentials that transform QHO eigenstates into stochastic representations, we demonstrate that canonical probability distributions, including Binomial, Negative Binomial, and Poisson, arise from specific modifications of the harmonic potential. Each stochastic system is governed by a Count Operator (N), with probabilities determined by squared amplitudes in a Born-rule-like manner.
  The framework introduces a complete operator algebra for moment generation and information-theoretic analysis, together with modular projection operators (R_M) that enable finite-dimensional approximations supported by rigorous uniform convergence theorems. This mathematical structure underpins True Uniform Random Number Generation (TURNG) [Kuang, Sci. Rep., 2025], eliminating the need for external whitening processes.
  Beyond randomness generation, the QMSS framework enables quantum probability engineering: the physical realization of classical distributions through designed quantum perturbations. These results demonstrate that stochastic systems are inherently quantum-mechanical in structure, bridging quantum dynamics, statistical physics, and experimental probability realization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23654v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Yurang (Randy),  Kuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct Types of Parent Hamiltonians for Quantum States: Insights from the $W$ State as a Quantum Many-Body Scar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24713v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The construction of parent Hamiltonians that possess a given state as their ground state is a well-studied problem. In this work, we generalize this notion by considering simple quantum states and examining the local Hamiltonians that have these states as exact eigenstates. These states often correspond to Quantum Many-Body Scars (QMBS) of their respective parent Hamiltonians. Motivated by earlier works on Hamiltonians with QMBS, in this work we formalize the differences between three distinct types of parent Hamiltonians, which differ in their decompositions into strictly local terms with the same eigenstates. We illustrate this classification using the $W$ state as the primary example, for which we rigorously derive the complete set of local parent Hamiltonians, which also allows us to establish general results such as the existence of asymptotic QMBS, and distinct dynamical signatures associated with the different parent Hamiltonian types. Finally, we derive more general results on the parent Hamiltonian types that allow us to obtain some immediate results for simple quantum states such as product states, where only a single type exists, and for short-range-entangled states, for which we identify constraints on the admissible types. Altogether, our work opens the door to classifying the rich structures and dynamical properties of parent Hamiltonians that arise from the interplay between locality and QMBS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24713v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Gioia, Sanjay Moudgalya, Olexei I. Motrunich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-fiber microendoscopic polarization sensing at single-photon level aided by deep-learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02172v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The polarization of light conveys crucial information about the spatial ordering and optical properties of a specimen. However, precise polarization measurement in challenging conditions, including constrained spaces, low light levels, and high-speed scenarios, remains a severe challenge. Addressing this problem, we introduce a real-time polarization measurement method that is accurate down to a single-photon level and provides complete information about the polarization state. Free of moving components, the polarization sensor utilizes a short rigid piece of few-mode fiber followed by a fiber array and a detector array. The calibration of the sensor relies on a neural network yielding unprecedented accuracy across all polarization states, including partially polarized light. We validate the approach by visualizing the polarization structure of biological specimens and the liquid crystal polymer sample (birefringent USAF test). Our method offers an efficient and reliable solution for real-time polarization sensing and microendoscopy under low-light conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02172v4</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/lpor.202501775</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bielak, Dominik Va\v{s}inka, Miroslav Je\v{z}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum machine learning classifier to search for new physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18847v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to the success of the Standard Model~(SM), it is reasonable to anticipate that the signal of new physics~(NP) beyond the SM is small. Consequently, future searches for NP and precision tests of the SM will require high luminosity collider experiments. Moreover, as precision tests advance, rare processes with many final-state particles require consideration which demand the analysis of a vast number of observables. The high luminosity produces a large amount of experimental data spanning a large observable space, posing a significant data-processing challenge. In recent years, quantum machine learning has emerged as a promising approach for processing large amounts of complex data on a quantum computer. In this study, we propose quantum searching neighbor~(QSN) and variational QSN~(VQSN) algorithms to search for NP. The QSN is a classification algorithm. The VQSN introduces variation to the QSN to process classical data. As applications, we apply the (V)QSN in the phenomenological study of the NP at the Large Hadron Collider and muon colliders. Examples are implemented on a real quantum hardware, which confirms reliable performance under noisy conditions. The results indicate that the VQSN demonstrates superior efficiency in the sense of computational complexity to a classical counterpart k-nearest neighbor algorithm, even when dealing with classical data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18847v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Chong Yang, Shuai Zhang, Chong-Xing Yue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of the absence of nontrivial local conserved quantities in the spin-1 bilinear-biquadratic chain and its anisotropic extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04945v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a complete classification of the integrability and nonintegrability of the spin-1 bilinear-biquadratic model with a uniaxial anisotropic field, which includes the Heisenberg model and the Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki model. It is rigorously shown that, within this class, the only integrable systems are those that have been solved by the Bethe ansatz method, and that all other systems are nonintegrable, in the sense that they do not have nontrivial local conserved quantities. Here, "nontrivial" excludes quantities like the Hamiltonian or the total magnetization, and "local" refers to sums of operators that act only on sites within a finite distance. This result establishes the nonintegrability of the Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki model and, consequently, demonstrates that the quantum many-body scars observed in this model emerge independently of any conservation laws of local quantities. Furthermore, we extend the proof of nonintegrability to more general spin-1 models that encompass anisotropic extensions of the bilinear-biquadratic Hamiltonian, and completely classify the integrability of generic Hamiltonians that possess translational symmetry, $U(1)$ symmetry, time-reversal symmetry, and spin-flip symmetry. Our result accomplishes a breakthrough in nonintegrability proofs by expanding their scope to spin-1 systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04945v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Hokkyo, Mizuki Yamaguchi, Yuuya Chiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Grassmann manifolds in topological systems via quantum distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20046v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum states defined over a parameter space form a Grassmann manifold. To capture the geometry of the associated gauge structure, gauge-invariant quantities are essential. We employ the projector of a multilevel system to quantify the quantum distance between states. Using the multidimensional scaling method, we transform the quantum distance into a reconstructed manifold embedded in Euclidean space. This approach is demonstrated with examples of topological systems, showcasing their topological features within these manifolds. Our method provides a comprehensive view of the manifold, rather than focusing on local properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20046v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin-Ming Huang, Dimitrios Giataganas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body localization and particle multioccupancy in the disordered Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03712v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the potential influence of the particle multi-occupations on the stability of many-body localization in the disordered Bose-Hubbard model. Within the higher-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, we find that there is no apparent finite-size boundary drift between the thermal phase and the many-body localized regime. We substantiate this observation by introducing the Van Vleck perturbation theory into the field of many-body localization. The appropriateness of this method rests largely on the peculiar Hilbert-space structure enabled by the particles' Bose statistics. The situation is reversed in the lower-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, where the significant finite-size boundary drift pushes the putative many-body localized regime up to the greater disorder strengths. We utilize the algebraic projection method to make a connection linking the disordered Bose-Hubbard model in the lower-energy section to an intricate disordered spin chain model. This issue of the finite-size drift could hence be analogous to what happens in the disordered Heisenberg chain. Both trends might be traced back to the particles' intrinsic or emergent single-occupancy constraint like the spin-$1/2$, hard-core boson, or spinless fermion degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03712v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/q5l5-517x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134205(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Chen, Chun Chen, Xiaoqun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Josephson traveling-wave parametric amplifier based on low-intrinsic-loss coplanar lumped-element waveguide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07559v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a Josephson traveling-wave parametric amplifier (JTWPA) based on a low-loss coplanar lumped-element waveguide architecture. By employing open-stub capacitors and Manhattan-pattern junctions, our device achieves an insertion loss below 1~dB up to 12~GHz. We introduce windowed sinusoidal modulation for phase matching, demonstrating that a smooth transition in the impedance-modulation strength effectively suppresses intrinsic gain ripples. Using Tukey-windowed modulation with 8\% impedance variation, we achieve 20\text{--}23-dB~gain over 5-GHz bandwidth under ideal matching conditions. In a more practical circuit having impedance mismatches, the device maintains 17\text{--}20-dB gain over 4.8-GHz bandwidth with an added noise of 0.18~quanta above standard quantum limit at 20-dB gain and $-99$-dBm saturation power, while featuring zero to negative backward gain below the band-gap frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07559v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qhl6-cz2z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>C. W. Sandbo Chang, Arjan F. Van Loo, Chih-Chiao Hung, Yu Zhou, Christian Gnandt, Shuhei Tamate, Yasunobu Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Formal Verification of Quantum Error Correcting Programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07732v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum error correction (QEC) is fundamental for suppressing noise in quantum hardware and enabling fault-tolerant quantum computation. In this paper, we propose an efficient verification framework for QEC programs. We define an assertion logic and a program logic specifically crafted for QEC programs and establish a sound proof system. We then develop an efficient method for handling verification conditions (VCs) of QEC programs: for Pauli errors, the VCs are reduced to classical assertions that can be solved by SMT solvers, and for non-Pauli errors, we provide a heuristic algorithm. We formalize the proposed program logic in Coq proof assistant, making it a verified QEC verifier. Additionally, we implement an automated QEC verifier, Veri-QEC, for verifying various fault-tolerant scenarios. We demonstrate the efficiency and broad functionality of the framework by performing different verification tasks across various scenarios. Finally, we present a benchmark of 14 verified stabilizer codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07732v3</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3729293</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages, Volume 9, Issue PLDI (2025) 1068-1093</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qifan Huang, Li Zhou, Wang Fang, Mengyu Zhao, Mingsheng Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Investigation of a Bipartite Quench in a 1D Bose gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05839v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Long wavelength dynamics of 1D Bose gases with repulsive contact interactions can be captured by Generalized HydroDynamics (GHD) which predicts the evolution of the local rapidity distribution. The latter corresponds to the momentum distribution of quasiparticles, which have infinite lifetime owing to the integrability of the system. Here we experimentally investigate the dynamics for an initial situation that is the junction of two semi-infinite systems in different stationary states, a protocol referred to as `bipartite quench' protocol. More precisely we realise the particular case where one half of the system is the vacuum state. We show that the evolution of the boundary density profile exhibits ballistic dynamics obeying the Euler hydrodynamic scaling. The boundary profiles are similar to the ones predicted with zero-temperature GHD in the quasi-BEC regime, with deviations due to non-zero entropy effects. We show that this protocol, provided the boundary profile is measured with infinite precision, permits to reconstruct the rapidity distribution of the initial state. For our data, we extract the initial rapidity distribution by fitting the boundary profile and we use a 3-parameter ansatz that goes beyond the thermal assumption. Finally, we investigate the local rapidity distribution inside the boundary profile, which, according to GHD, presents, on one side, features of zero-entropy states. The measured distribution shows the asymmetry predicted by GHD, although unelucidated deviations remain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05839v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'ea Dubois, Guillaume Th\'em\`eze, J\'er\^ome Dubail, Isabelle Bouchoule</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pilot-waves and copilot-particles: A nonstochastic approach to objective wavefunction collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08168v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We seek an extension to Schrodinger's equation that incorporates the macroscopic measurement-induced wavefunction collapse phenomenon. We find that a suitable hybrid between two leading approaches, the Bohm-de Broglie pilot-wave and objective collapse theories, accomplishes this goal in a way that is consistent with Born's rule. Our theory posits that the Bohmian particle is guided by the wavefunction and, conversely, the wavefunction gradually localizes towards the particle's position. As long as the particle can visit any state, as in a typical microscopic system, the localization effect does not favor any particular quantum state and, on average, the usual Schrodinger-like time evolution results. However, when the wavefunction develops spatially well-separated lobes, as would happen during a macroscopic measurement, the Bohmian particle can remain trapped in one lobe, which causes the wavefunction to eventually localizes. This proposed loss of ergodicity mechanism recasts one of the foundational postulate of quantum mechanics as a emergent feature and has important implications regarding the feasibility of large-scale quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08168v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel van de Walle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuralized Fermionic Tensor Networks for Quantum Many-Body Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08329v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe a class of neuralized fermionic tensor network states (NN-fTNS) that introduce non-linearity into fermionic tensor networks through configuration-dependent neural network transformations of the local tensors. The construction uses the fTNS algebra to implement a natural fermionic sign structure and is compatible with standard tensor network algorithms, but gains enhanced expressivity through the neural network parametrization. Using the 1D and 2D Fermi-Hubbard models as benchmarks, we demonstrate that NN-fTNS achieve order of magnitude improvements in the ground-state energy compared to pure fTNS with the same bond dimension, and can be systematically improved through both the tensor network bond dimension and the neural network parametrization. Compared to existing fermionic neural quantum states (NQS) based on Slater determinants and Pfaffians, NN-fTNS offer a physically motivated alternative fermionic structure. Furthermore, compared to such states, NN-fTNS naturally exhibit improved computational scaling and we demonstrate a construction that achieves linear scaling with the lattice size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08329v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Jing Du, Ao Chen, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expansion dynamics of strongly correlated lattice bosons: A selfconsistent density-matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the spatio-temporal dynamics of interacting bosons on a two-dimensional Hubbard lattice in the strongly interacting regime, taking into account the dynamics of condensate amplitude as well as the direct transport of non-condensed fluctuations. To that end we develop a selfconsistent density-matrix approach which goes beyond the standard Gutzwiller mean-field theory. Starting from the Liouville-von-Neumann equation we derive a quantum master equation for the time evolution of the system's local density matrix at each lattice site, with a dynamical bath that represents the rest of the system. We apply this method to the expansion dynamics of an initially prepared cloud of interacting bosons in an optical lattice. We observe a ballistic expansion of the condensate, as expected, followed by slow, diffusive transport of the normal bosons. We discuss, in particular, the robustness of the Mott insulator phase as well as its melting due to incoherent transport. The method should be applicable to various models of lattice bosons in the strongly correlated regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09397v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bzvn-sp2h</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 043322 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julian Schwingel, Michael Turaev, Johann Kroha, Sayak Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Local Realism through Bell Tests at Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10979v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One of the most notable aspects of quantum systems is that their components can exhibit correlations much stronger than those allowed by classical physics. Two examples of quantum correlations are quantum entanglement and Bell nonlocality, but generally there is a hierarchy of many types of quantum correlations. Among these correlations, Bell nonlocality holds a special place because it plays a dual role in distinguishing theories where local realism is a valid description. A Bell test, which is a test of local realism, typically needs to be augmented with assumptions to address possible loopholes in the experimental setup. In this work, we study Bell tests in experiments in which the detector reports the correct outcome with a specified probability. This mirrors the situation at high-energy colliders, where particle spins are not measured directly but inferred from the angular distributions of their decay products. We show that, in this setup, a test of local realism is not possible. Quantum correlations, however, are still present, measurable, and informative in high-energy colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10979v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An accurate DFT-1/2 approach for shallow defect states: Efficient calculation of donor binding energies in silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14738v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of shallow-donor electron binding energies is critical for device modeling, dopant activation, and donor-based quantum technologies. Traditional beyond-DFT approaches (e.g., hybrid functionals, GW) are prohibitively expensive for the large supercells needed to capture the extended, hydrogenic wavefunctions, while semi-local DFT underestimates band gaps and suffers from delocalization errors. We present a simple, practical protocol for shallow donors based on the DFT-1/2 approximate quasiparticle correction that maintains the computational cost of standard DFT and enables supercells up to thousands of atoms. This approach provides a straightforward and reproducible workflow that delivers reliable donor binding energies with minimal computational overhead. Applied to group-V donors in Si, Si:X (X= P, As, Sb, Bi), the method yields binding energies in close agreement with experiment. We found that, for Si:Bi, it is essential to include spin-orbit coupling to achieve near-experimental values with a difference of only $\sim$ 4 meV. For arsenic, the method yields excellent agreement with experiment, with a difference of only ~0.3 meV. For antimony, the results match experiment to within ~5 meV, and for phosphorus, the deviation is within ~8 meV. Beyond its high accuracy, DFT-1/2 offers a significant practical advantage, providing a straightforward, reproducible, and transferable workflow that is less demanding than hybrid functional approaches while remaining fully generalizable to other shallow impurities in semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14738v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Claes, Bart Partoens, Dirk Lamoen, Marcelo Marques, Lara K. Teles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-group-invariant $D^{(2)}_{n+1}$ models: Bethe ansatz and finite-size spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00610v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the quantum integrable spin chain models associated with the Jimbo R-matrix based on the quantum affine algebra $D^{(2)}_{n+1}$, subject to quantum-group-invariant boundary conditions parameterized by two discrete variables $p=0,\dots, n$ and $\varepsilon = 0, 1$. We develop the analytical Bethe ansatz for the previously unexplored case $\varepsilon = 1$ with any $n$, and use it to investigate the effects of different boundary conditions on the finite-size spectrum of the quantum spin chain based on the rank-$2$ algebra $D^{(2)}_3$. Previous work on this model with periodic boundary conditions has shown that it is critical for the range of anisotropy parameters $0&lt;\gamma&lt;\pi/4$, where its scaling limit is described by a non-compact CFT with continuous degrees of freedom related to two copies of the 2D black hole sigma model. The scaling limit of the model with quantum-group-invariant boundary conditions depends on the parameter $\varepsilon$: similarly as in the rank-$1$ $D^{(2)}_2$ chain, we find that the symmetry of the lattice model is spontaneously broken, and the spectrum of conformal weights has both discrete and continuous components, for $\varepsilon=1$. For $p=1$, the latter coincides with that of the $D^{(2)}_2$ chain, which should correspond to a non-compact brane related to one black hole CFT in the presence of boundaries. For $\varepsilon=0$, the spectrum of conformal weights is purely discrete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00610v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Frahm, Sascha Gehrmann, Rafael I. Nepomechie, Ana L. Retore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal-Field--Driven Magnetoelectricity in the Triangular Quantum Magnet CeMgAl$_{11}$O$_{19}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08746v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report dielectric and magnetoelectric studies of single-crystalline \ce{CeMgAl11O19}, a Kramers triangular magnet embedded in a polarizable hexaaluminate lattice. In zero magnetic field, the permittivity $\varepsilon'(T)$ follows the Barrett law of a quantum paraelectric down to 25 K, below which a broad minimum develops near 3 K without evidence of static ferroelectric or magnetic order. Application of magnetic fields up to \SI{9}{\tesla} shifts this minimum to higher temperatures and broadens it, evidencing a tunable magnetoelectric response.The magnetoelectric coupling was characterized using results from magnetization measurements. The anomaly temperature $T^*$, extracted from the local minimum of $\varepsilon'(T)$, exhibits a linear dependence on the squared magnetization $M^2$, consistent with the biquadratic magnetoelectric coupling allowed in centrosymmetric systems. This magnetoelectric effect, mediated by spin-orbit-entangled Kramers doublets interacting with a frustrated antipolar liquid, establishes \ce{CeMgAl11O19} as a prototype for exploring quantum magnetoelectricity in frustrated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08746v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonu Kumar (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic, Adam Mickiewicz University, Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Department of Experimental Physics of Condensed Phase, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ga\"el Bastien (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Maxim Savinov (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague, Czech Republic), Petr Proschek (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Adam Eli\'a\v{s} (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Karol Za{\l}\k{e}ski (Adam Mickiewicz University, NanoBioMedical Centre, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ma{\l}gorzata \'Sliwi\'nska-Bartkowiak (Adam Mickiewicz University, Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Department of Experimental Physics of Condensed Phase, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ross H. Colman (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Stanislav Kamba (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague, Czech Republic)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
