<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 01:45:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical aspects of the decomposition of diagonal U(N) operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the decomposition of arbitrary diagonal operators into tensor and matrix products of smaller matrices, focusing on the analytic structure of the resulting formulas and their inherent symmetries. Diagrammatic representations are introduced, providing clear visualizations of the structure of these decompositions. We also discuss symmetries of the suggested decomposition. Methods and representations developed in this paper can be applied in different areas, including optimization of quantum computing algorithms, complex biological analysis, crystallography, optimization of AI models, and others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11735v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. M. Fedin, A. A. Morozov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Kernel Methods: Convergence Theory, Separation Bounds and Applications to Marketing Analytics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work studies the feasibility of applying quantum kernel methods to a real consumer classification task in the NISQ regime. We present a hybrid pipeline that combines a quantum-kernel Support Vector Machine (Q-SVM) with a quantum feature extraction module (QFE), and benchmark it against classical and quantum baselines in simulation and with limited shallow-depth hardware runs. With fixed hyperparameters, the proposed Q-SVM attains 0.7790 accuracy, 0.7647 precision, 0.8609 recall, 0.8100 F1, and 0.83 ROC AUC, exhibiting higher sensitivity while maintaining competitive precision relative to classical SVM. We interpret these results as an initial indicator and a concrete starting point for NISQ-era workflows and hardware integration, rather than a definitive benchmark. Methodologically, our design aligns with recent work that formalizes quantum-classical separations and verifies resources via XEB-style approaches, motivating shallow yet expressive quantum embeddings to achieve robust separability despite hardware noise constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11744v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura S\'aez-Ortu\~no, Santiago Forgas-Coll, Massimiliano Ferrara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back-reflection in dipole fields and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum reflection is a fascinating signature of the quantum vacuum that emerges from inhomogeneities in the electromagnetic fields. In pursuit of the prospective real-world implementation of quantum reflection in the back-reflection channel, we provide the first numerical estimates for the light-by-light scattering with dipole pulses, which are known to provide the tightest focusing of light possible. For an all-optical setup with a dipole pump and Gaussian probe of the same frequency, we find that the dominant signal signature is related mainly to the back-reflection channel from 4-wave mixing. Focusing on this, we study the particular case of a multiple focusing pulses configuration (belt configuration) as an approximation to the idealized dipole pulse. Using Bayesian optimization methods, we determine optimal parameters that maximize the detectability of a discernible back-reflection signal. Our study indicates that the optimization favors a three-beam collision setup, which we further investigate both numerically and analytically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11764v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksim Valialshchikov, Felix Karbstein, Daniel Seipt, Matt Zepf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact WKB method for radial Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit exact WKB quantization for radial Schr\"odinger problems from the modern resurgence perspective, with emphasis on how ``physically meaningful'' quantization paths should be chosen and interpreted. Using connection formulae at simple turning points and at regular singular points, we show that the nontrivial-cycle data give the spectrum. In particular, for the $3$-dimensional harmonic oscillator and the $3$-dimensional Coulomb potential, we explicitly compute a closed contour which starts at $+\infty$, bulges into the $r&lt;0$ sector to encircle the origin, and returns to $+\infty$. Also we propose that the appropriate slice of the closed path provides a physical local basis at $r=0$, which is used by an origin-to-$\infty$ open path. Our analysis clarifies, in radial settings, how mathematical monodromy data and physical boundary conditions dovetail, thereby addressing recent debates on path choices in resurgence-based quantization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11766v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Okuto Morikawa, Shoya Ogawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qiboml: towards the orchestration of quantum-classical machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11773v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Qiboml, an open-source software library for orchestrating quantum and classical components in hybrid machine learning workflows. Building on Qibo's quantum computing capabilities and integrating with popular machine learning frameworks such as TensorFlow and PyTorch, Qiboml enables the construction of quantum and hybrid models that can run on a broad range of backends: (i) multi-threaded CPUs, GPUs, and multi-GPU systems for simulation with statevector or tensor network methods; (ii) quantum processing units, both on-premise and through cloud providers. In this paper, we showcase its functionalities, including diverse simulation options, noise-aware simulations, and real-time error mitigation and calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11773v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Robbiati, Andrea Papaluca, Andrea Pasquale, Edoardo Pedicillo, Renato M. S. Farias, Alejandro Sopena, Mattia Robbiano, Ghaith Alramahi, Simone Bordoni, Alessandro Candido, Niccol\`o Laurora, Jogi Suda Neto, Yuanzheng Paul Tan, Michele Grossi, Stefano Carrazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum State-Aware Query Complexity: Krylov Compression and Polynomial Query Duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the minimal query complexity for preparing $f(H)\ket{\psi_0}$ is exactly the optimal polynomial approximation degree of $f$ in $L^2(\mu)$, where $\mu$ is the spectral measure of $(H,\ket{\psi_0})$. This state-aware perspective refines the worst-case bounds, unifies Krylov/Favard approximation with quantum queries, and explains how state-dependent spectral structure can yield substantial savings over uniform designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11786v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiran Adhikari Chhetriya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound on entanglement in neural quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational wavefunctions offer a practical route around the exponential complexity of many-body Hilbert spaces, but their expressive power is often sharply constrained. Matrix product states, for instance, are efficient but limited to area law entangled states. Neural quantum states (NQS) are widely believed to overcome such limitations, yet little is known about their fundamental constraints. Here we prove that feed-forward neural quantum states acting on $n$ spins with $k$ scalar nonlinearities, under certain analyticity assumptions, obey a bound on entanglement entropy for any subregion: $S \leq c k\log n$, for a constant $c$. This establishes an NQS analog of the area law constraint for matrix product states and rules out volume law entanglement for NQS with $O(1)$ nonlinearities. We demonstrate analytically and numerically that the scaling with $n$ is tight for a wide variety of NQS. Our work establishes a fundamental constraint on NQS that applies broadly across different network designs, while reinforcing their substantial expressive power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11797v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nisarga Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secret communication games and a hierarchy of quasiparticle statistics in 3 + 1D topological phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that a family of secret communication challenge games naturally define a hierarchy of emergent quasiparticle statistics in three-dimensional (3D) topological phases. The winning strategies exploit a special class of the recently proposed $R$-paraparticles to allow nonlocal secret communication between the two participating players. We first give a high-level, axiomatic description of emergent $R$-paraparticles, and show that any physical system hosting such particles admits a winning strategy. We then analyze the games using the categorical description of topological phases (where point-like excitations in 3D are described by symmetric fusion categories), and show that only $R$-paraparticles can win the 3D challenge in a noise-robust way, and the winning strategy is essentially unique. This analysis associates emergent $R$-paraparticles to deconfined gauge theories based on an exotic class of finite groups. Thus, even though this special class of $R$-paraparticles are fermions or bosons under the categorical classification, their exchange statistics can still have nontrivial physical consequences in the presence of appropriate defects, and the $R$-paraparticle language offers a more convenient description of the winning strategies. Finally, while a subclass of non-Abelian anyons can win the game in 2D, we introduce twisted variants that exclude anyons, thereby singling out $R$-paraparticles in 2D as well. Our results establish the secret communication challenge as a versatile diagnostic for both identifying and classifying exotic exchange statistics in topological quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11818v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian Realization of Quantum Dynamics on Embedded Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Floquet Hamiltonian of a quantum particle driven by a general time-periodic imaginary potential is exactly equivalent, at stroboscopic times, to the Hamiltonian of a free particle constrained to a curved Riemannian manifold with fixed embedding. We illustrate the construction for a sinusoidal drive and for the torus of revolution, and outline how the framework can guide experimental design of curved-space quantum dynamics. Our results unify non-Hermitian Floquet physics with spectral geometry and provide a general recipe for engineering quantum dynamics on embedded manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11845v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Alperin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal and efficient inference tools for field tracking with precessing spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precise, real-time monitoring of magnetic field evolution is important in applications including magnetic navigation and searches for physics beyond the standard model. One main field-monitoring technique, the spin-precession magnetometer (SPM), observes electron, nucleus, color center, or muon spins as they precess in response to their local magnetic field. Here, we study Bayesian signal-recovery methods for SPMs in the free-induction decay (FID) mode. In particular, we study tracking of field changes well within the coherence time of the spin system, and thus well beyond the response bandwidth, as in [Phys. Rev. Lett. 120, 040503 (2018)]. We derive the Bayesian Cram\'{e}r-Rao bound that dictates the ultimate precision in estimating the Larmor frequency, which we show to be attained by the computationally-expensive prediction error method (PEM). Relative to this benchmark, we show that the extended Kalman filter (EKF) and cubature Kalman filter (CKF) offer near-optimal tracking that is also computationally efficient, with the use of the latter giving better results only for large spin number. Focusing thus on the EKF, we show that it is sufficient to accurately track fluctuating and unknown transient signals. Our methods can be easily adapted to other types of sensors undergoing non-linear dissipative dynamics and experiencing intrinsic Gaussian-like stochastic noises.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11884v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaudia Dilcher, Piotr Bania, Diana Mendez-Avalos, Aleksandra Sierant, Morgan W. Mitchell, Jan Kolodynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-dimensional tunneling of the two-body bound state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider bound and scattering states of the one-dimensional dimer formed by two coupled non-identical atoms when one of them also interacts with the zero-range potential located at the origin. By calculating the dimer localized and scattering wave functions, we identify properties of the system without the two-body bound-state collapse. In general, we predict an enhancement of the dimer reflection compared to a single atom, except for a narrow region on the attractive side of the external potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11932v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Shypka, O. Hryhorchak, V. Pastukhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open Quantum Dynamics Theory for Coulomb Potentials: Hierarchical Equations of Motion for Atomic Orbitals (AO-HEOM)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the quantum dynamics of Coulomb potential systems in thermal baths. We study these systems within the framework of open quantum dynamics theory, focusing on preserving the rotational symmetry of the entire system, including the baths. Thus, we employ a three-dimensional rotationally invariant system-bath (3D-RISB) model to derive numerically ``exact'' hierarchical equations of motion for atomic orbitals (AO-HEOM) that enable a non-perturbative and non-Markovian treatment of system-bath interactions at finite temperatures. To assess the formalism, we calculated the linear absorption spectrum of an atomic system under isotropic thermal environment, with systematic variation of system-bath coupling strength and temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11981v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yankai Zhang, oshitaka Tanimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superradiance and Superabsorption Engine of $N$ Two-Level Systems: $N^{2}$-Power Scaling at Near-Unity Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a thermal engine that exploits the \emph{cooperative superradiance} and \emph{superabsorption} of a sample of \(N\) two-level atoms. This engine operates using a single cold reservoir via cycles of collective pumping followed by decay. Using an effective mean-field Hamiltonian to describe the many-body dynamics, we design optimized drive pulses that preserve adiabaticity and achieve an average power output scaling quadratically with the system size, \(P \propto N^2\). An experimentally measurable figure of merit demonstrates that the efficiency of this superengine can approach unity. The resulting analytical model, which yields a representative Hamiltonian for the sample within the mean-field formalism, is validated by numerical simulations. Our results pave the way for scalable and highly efficient quantum heat engines based on collective effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12017v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. F. Alves da Silva, H. Sanchez, M. A. Ponte, M. H. Y. Moussa, Norton G. de Almeida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing and Harnessing Correlations Featuring Independent Qubit Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a framework to characterize the correlations in qubit systems for Bell and prepare-and-measure scenarios with independent devices -- a typically non-convex problem. Based on this result, we introduce protocols for referring devices and detecting entanglement with correlation that are not necessarily extreme or nonlocal, as required by common linear approach. } Specifically, our correlation criterion, derived from uncertainty relation specific to qubit systems, can capture the non-convex nature of the set of correlations arising from Bell and prepare-and-measure scenarios, as demonstrated through concrete examples. Conversely, when given an observed correlation, our framework can refer potential measurements and quantum states -- which are sometimes uniquely determined -- even with correlations that are not extreme. This extends common protocols that merely verify devices using extreme correlations. We then enhance entanglement detection for qubit system by incorporating the inferred information in Navascu\'{e}s-Pironio-Ac\'{i}n (NPA) hierarchy, showing that some local correlations can also verify entanglement. Since the scenarios considered here are standard platforms for most quantum information protocols and device inference is a central issue in quantum information science, our methodology, which is well-suited to these tasks, may provide a foundation for a broad range of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12022v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang-Liang Sun, Xiang Zhou, Chengjie Zhang, Zizhu Wang, Yong-Shun Song, Sixia Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral analysis of hierarchical continuous-time quantum walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12043v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce hierarchical random walks at first. In this model, we use two types of random walkers, {global and local} walkers. The global walker chooses a local walker at every step, then the chosen local walker moves a single step. After that we construct the corresponding continuous-time quantum walks and discuss its spectral structures. Then we define multi-dimensional continuous-time quantum walk by taking a marginal distribution respect to the global walker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12043v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jir\^o Akahori, Yusuke Ide, Tomoki Kato, Norio Konno, Shuhei Mano, Akihiro Narimatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering atomic superradiance scaling in cavity QED system with collective and individual emission channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coherent emission of multiple atoms gives rise to superradiance, a cornerstone phenomenon in quantum optics with wide-ranging applications in quantum information processing and precision metrology. Despite its importance, how the superradiant scaling with respect to the number of participating atoms can be effectively controlled remains largely unexplored. In this work, we investigate a cavity-QED system and demonstrate that atom-photon coupling can significantly alter the emission behavior--suppressing the collective superradiant scaling while enhancing the scaling associated with individual atomic emissions. Our study provides a pathway toward controllable collective emission in state-of-the-art experimental platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12086v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijin Sun, Xiang Guo, Andreas Ruschhaupt, Zhihai Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital adiabatic evolution is universally accurate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Adiabatic evolution is a central paradigm in quantum physics. Digital simulations of adiabatic processes are generally viewed as costly, since algorithmic errors typically accumulate over the long evolution time, requiring exceptionally deep circuits to maintain accuracy. This work demonstrates that digital adiabatic evolution is intrinsically accurate and robust to simulation errors. We analyze two Hamiltonian simulation methods -- Trotterization and generalized quantum signal processing -- and prove that the simulation error does not increase with time. Numerical simulations of molecular systems and linear equations confirm the theory, revealing that digital adiabatic evolution is substantially more efficient than previously assumed. Remarkably, our estimation for the first-order Trotterization error can be 10^6 times tighter than previous analyses for the transverse field Ising model even with less than 6 qubits. The findings establish fundamental robustness of digital adiabatic evolution and provide a basis for accurate, efficient implementations on fault-tolerant -- and potentially near-term -- quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12237v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangyu Lu, Yifei Huang, Dong An, Qi Zhao, Dingshun Lv, Xiao Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster State Preparation with Randomization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12247v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum state preparation remains a dominant cost in many quantum algorithms. We introduce a randomized protocol that fundamentally improves the accuracy-cost trade-off for states with hierarchical amplitude structures, where amplitudes decay exponentially or by a power law with exponent greater than one. Rather than commonly employed deterministically truncating small amplitudes, we prepare an ensemble of simple circuits: each retains all large amplitudes while amplifying a single small one. We rigorously prove that the randomized ensemble achieves a quadratic improvement in trace-distance error over the deterministic truncation method. This quadratic scaling halves the number of encoded amplitudes for exponential decay and yields polynomial reductions for power-law decay, which directly translates to a reduction in circuit depth. Demonstrations on molecular wavefunctions (LiH), many-body ground states (transverse-field Ising), and machine-learning parameters (ResNet) validate the approach across diverse applications. The method broadens the class of states preparable on near-term and fault-tolerant quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12247v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Wang, Xiao-Ming Zhang, Xiao Yuan, Qi Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-efficiency and long-distance quantum memory-assisted device-independent quantum secret sharing with single photon sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12288v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum secret sharing (QSS) plays a critical role in building the distributed quantum networks. Device-independent (DI) QSS provides the highest security level for QSS. However, the photon transmission loss and extremely low multipartite entanglement generation rate largely limit DI QSS's secure photon transmission distance (less than 1 km) and practical key generation efficiency. To address the above drawbacks, we propose the quantum memory-assisted (QMA) DI QSS protocol based on single photon sources (SPSs). The single photons from the SPSs are used to construct long-distance multipartite entanglement channels with the help of the heralded architecture. The heralded architecture enables our protocol to have an infinite secure photon transmission distance in theory. The QMA technology can not only increase the multi-photon synchronization efficiency, but also optimize the photon transmittance to maximize the construction efficiency of the multipartite entanglement channels. Our protocol achieves the practical key generation efficiency seven orders of magnitude higher than that of the existing DI QSS protocols based on cascaded spontaneous parametric down-conversion sources and six orders of magnitude higher than that of the DI QSS based on SPSs without QMA. Our protocol has modular characteristics and is feasible under the current experimental technical conditions. Combining with the advanced random key generation basis strategy, the requirement on experimental devices can be effectively reduced. Our protocol is expected to promote the development of long-distance and high-efficiency DI quantum network in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12288v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Zhang, Jia-Wei Ying, Shi-Pu Gu, Xing-Fu Wang, Ming-Ming Du, Wei Zhong, Lan Zhou, Yu-Bo Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Vision Transformer and Quantum Convolutional Neural Network for Image Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning (QML) holds promise for computational advantage, yet progress on real-world tasks is hindered by classical preprocessing and noisy devices. We introduce ViT-QCNN-FT, a hybrid framework that integrates a fine-tuned Vision Transformer with a quantum convolutional neural network (QCNN) to compress high-dimensional images into features suited for noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. By systematically probing entanglement, we show that ansatzes with uniformly distributed entanglement entropy consistently deliver superior non-local feature fusion and state-of-the-art accuracy (99.77% on CIFAR-10). Surprisingly, quantum noise emerges as a double-edged factor: in some cases, it enhances accuracy (+2.71% under amplitude damping). Strikingly, substituting the QCNN with classical counterparts of equal parameter count leads to a dramatic 29.36% drop, providing unambiguous evidence of quantum advantage. Our study establishes a principled pathway for co-designing classical and quantum architectures, pointing toward practical QML capable of tackling complex, high-dimensional learning tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12291v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzhu Wang, Yun Shang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrological approach to the emergence of classical objectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a precise characterization of the onset of classicality that combines the formalism of quantum Darwinism with the tools from quantum metrology. We show that the quantum Fisher information provides a useful metric for assessing the rate at which classical objectivity emerges. Furthermore, our formalism allows us to explore how the choice of measurement impacts the precision with which an observer can determine the state of the system. For a paradigmatic example of the spin-star model, we demonstrate that optimal measurements lead to the emergence of classicality at an exponential rate. Although other measurements necessarily lead to slower emergence, we importantly show that suboptimal measurements can still saturate the Cram\'{e}r-Rao bound. By recasting emergent classicality as an information acquisition protocol, our framework provides a precise operational description of quantum Darwinism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12313v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Kiely, Diana A. Chisholm, Akram Touil, Sebastian Deffner, Gabriel Landi, Steve Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithms for QUBO problems Across Quantum Hardware Platforms: Performance Analysis, Challenges, and Strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12336v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computers are expected to offer significant advantages in solving complex optimization problems that are challenging for classical computers. Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problems represent an important class of problems with relevance in finance and logistics. The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is a prominent candidate for solving QUBO problems on near-term quantum devices. In this paper, we investigate the performance of both the standard QAOA and the adaptive derivative assembled problem tailored QAOA (ADAPT-QAOA) to solve QUBO problems of varying sizes and hardnesses with a focus on its practical applications in financial feature selection problems. Our main observation is that ADAPT-QAOA significantly outperforms QAOA with hard problems (trade-off parameter {\alpha} = 0.6) when comparing approximation ratio and time-to-solution. However, the standard QAOA remains efficient for simpler problems. Additionally, we investigate the practical feasibility and limitations of QAOA by scaling analysis based on the real-device calibration data for various hardware platforms. Our estimates indicate that standard QAOA implemented on superconducting quantum computers provides a shorter time-to-solution compared to trapped-ion devices. However, trapped-ion devices are expected to yield more favorable error rates. Our findings provide a comprehensive overview of the challenges, trade-offs, and strategies for deploying QAOA-based methods on near-term quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12336v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teemu Pihkakoski, Aravind Plathanam Babu, Pauli Taipale, Petri Liimatta, Matti Silveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snapshot renormalization group for quantum matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in quantum simulator experiments enable unprecedented access to quantum many-body states through snapshot measurements of individual many-body configurations. Here, we introduce an exact renormalization group (RG) transformation that can be directly applied to any such snapshot dataset. Our SnapshotRG operates in real space, but can also be directly translated to an RG in the abstract dataspace of measurement configurations, providing a framework for the characterization of quantum many-body systems on a more general level. We demonstrate that snapshot datasets in dataspace exhibit self-similarity at continuous phase transitions, providing an explanation for the recently observed scale-freeness of so-called wavefunction networks. As a consequence, scale invariance extends beyond traditional low-order correlation functions to encompass the full statistical structure of quantum states as contained in their snapshot datasets. Our SnapshotRG can be readily implemented with snapshot data generated by numerical method such as neural quantum states or any quantum simulation platform, offering a versatile tool for characterizing quantum phase transitions and critical phenomena in quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12415v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurin Brunner, Tobias Wiener, Tiago Mendes-Santos, Reyhaneh Khasseh, Markus Heyl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Guided Sampling for Quantum Circuit Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Translating a general quantum circuit on a specific hardware topology with a reduced set of available gates, also known as transpilation, comes with a substantial increase in the length of the equivalent circuit. Due to decoherence, the quality of the computational outcome can degrade seriously with increasing circuit length. Thus, there is major interest to reduce a quantum circuit to an equivalent circuit which is in its gate count as short as possible. One method to address efficient transpilation is based on approaches known from stochastic optimization, e.g. by using random sampling and token replacement strategies. Here, a core challenge is that these methods can suffer from sampling efficiency, causing long and energy consuming optimization time. As a remedy, we propose in this work 2D neural guided sampling. Thus, given a 2D representation of a quantum circuit, a neural network predicts groups of gates in the quantum circuit, which are likely reducible. Thus, it leads to a sampling prior which can heavily reduce the compute time for quantum circuit reduction. In several experiments, we demonstrate that our method is superior to results obtained from different qiskit or BQSKit optimization levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12430v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bodo Rosenhahn, Tobias J. Osborne, Christoph Hirche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental verification of multi-copy activation of genuine multipartite entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A central concept in quantum information processing is genuine multipartite entanglement (GME), a type of correlation beyond biseparability, that is, correlations that cannot be explained by statistical mixtures of partially separable states. GME is relevant for characterizing and benchmarking complex quantum systems, and it is an important resource for applications such as quantum communication. Remarkably, it has been found that GME can be activated from multiple copies of biseparable quantum states, which do not possess GME individually. Here, we experimentally demonstrate unambiguous evidence of such GME activation from two copies of a biseparable three-qubit state in a trapped-ion quantum processor. These results not only challenge notions of quantum resources but also highlight the potential of using multiple copies of quantum states to achieve tasks beyond the capabilities of the individual copies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12457v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert St\'arek, Tim Gollerthan, Olga Leskovjanov\'a, Michael Meth, Peter Tirler, Nicolai Friis, Martin Ringbauer, Ladislav Mi\v{s}ta Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The logic of quantum mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum logic program originated in a 1936 article by G. Birkhoff and J. von Neumann. This program is generally disregarded due to no-go theorems restricting the existence of the tensor product of elementary quantum logics and, above all, the impossibility of considering entangled states and Bell non-local states within the framework of these composite quantum logics. We revisit this study from the beginning and reverse the perspective. Here, the existence of a tensor product and a star involution are the only prerequisites for the definition of the state spaces. Surprisingly, the quantum logics constructed in this way turn out to have a close connection with irreducible Hilbert geometries, even though we did not impose this sort of structure ab initio. Endly, the existence of some basic quantum-like properties is explicitly proven in our framework : contextuality, no-broadcasting theorem, and Bell non-locality. These elements demonstrate that our quantum logic program is capable of achieving G. Birkhoff and J. von Neumann's initial ambition of founding quantum theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12502v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Buffenoir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of quantum information masking via machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, machine learning has been widely applied in the field of quantum information, notably in tasks such as entanglement detection, steering characterization, and nonlocality verification. However, few studies have focused on utilizing machine learning to detect quantum information masking. In this work, we investigate supervised machine learning for detecting quantum information masking in both pure and mixed qubit states. For pure qubit states, we randomly generate the corresponding density matrices and train an XGBoost model to detect quantum information masking. For mixed qubit states, we improve the XGBoost method by optimizing the selection of training samples. The experimental results demonstrate that our approach achieves higher classification accuracy. Furthermore, we analyze the area under the curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristic curve for this method, which further confirms its classification performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12507v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1555-6611/ae0df6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Laser Phys. 35 (2025) 105202</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Ao Mao, Lin Zhang, Bo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical analytical solutions of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis in a quantum billiard</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive semiclassical analytical solutions for both the diagonal and off-diagonal functions in the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH) in a quarter-stadium quantum billiard. For a representative observable, we obtain an explicit expression and an asymptotic closed-form solution that naturally separate into a local contribution and a phase-space correlation term. These analytical results predict the band structure of the observable matrix, including its bandwidth and scaling behavior. We further demonstrate that our analytical formula is equivalent to the prediction of Berry's conjecture. Supported by numerical evidence, we show that Berry's conjecture captures the energetic long-wavelength behavior in the space of eigenstates, while our analytical solution describes the asymptotic behavior of the f function in the semiclassical limit. Finally, by revealing the connection between the bandwidth scaling and the underlying classical dynamics, our results suggest that the ETH carries important physical implications in single-particle and few-body systems, where "thermalization" manifests as the loss of information about initial conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12517v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaoqi Ye, Chengkai Lin, Xiao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal approach to saddle-point methods in attosecond science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Light-matter interactions within the strong-field regime, where intense laser fields can ionise a target via tunnelling, give rise to fascinating phenomena such as the generation of high-order harmonic radiation (HHG). On the atomic scale, these strong-field processes are described in terms of highly-oscillatory time integrals which are often approximated using saddle-point methods. These methods simultaneously simplify the calculations and let us understand the physical processes in terms of semi-classical electron trajectories, or quantum orbits. However, applying saddle-point methods for HHG driven by polychromatic laser fields without clear dynamical symmetries has remained challenging. Here we introduce Picard-Lefschetz theory as a universal and robust link between the time integrals and the semi-classical trajectories. The continuous deformation of the integration contour towards so-called Lefschetz thimbles allows an exact evaluation of the integral, as well as the identification of relevant quantum orbits, for arbitrary driving fields. The latter is realised via the ``necklace algorithm'', a novel solution to the open problem of determining the relevance of saddle points for a two-dimensional integral, which we introduce here. We demonstrate the versatility and rigour of Picard-Lefschetz methods by studying Stokes transitions and spectral caustics arising in HHG driven by two-colour laser fields. For example, we showcase a quantum-orbit analysis of the colour switchover, which links the regime of perturbative two-colour fields with that of fully bichromatic driving fields. With this work, we set the foundation for a rigorous application of quantum-orbit based approaches in attosecond science that enables the interpretation of state-of-the-art experimental setups, and guides the design of future ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12545v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne Weber, Job Feldbrugge, Emilio Pisanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of the time-multiplexed SPDC source at 900-950 nm range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of quantum technology, single photons have emerged as a pivotal resource, prompting the development of heralded single photon sources (HSPS) with enhanced generation probability. The majority of such sources are based on spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC), but they exhibit a low single photon generation probability. The multiplexing principle (arXiv:quant-ph/0205103) has been proposed as a solution to this problem. This paper presents a demonstration of a time-multiplexed HSPS based on the SPDC process, including accurate calculations and modeling of key source characteristics, specifically purity and heralding efficiency. Furthermore, the paper provides an analysis and approximation of the probability of a single photon post-application of time multiplexing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12556v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. O. Gotovtsev, I. V. Dyakonov, O. V. Borzenkova, K. A. Taratorin, T. B. Dugarnimaev, A. A. Korneev, S. P. Kulik, S. S. Straupe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Copy Security in Unclonable Cryptography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unclonable cryptography leverages the quantum no-cloning principle to copy-protect cryptographic functionalities. While most existing works address the basic single-copy security, the stronger notion of multi-copy security remains largely unexplored.
  We introduce a generic compiler that upgrades collusion-resistant unclonable primitives to achieve multi-copy security, assuming only one-way functions. Using this framework, we obtain the first multi-copy secure constructions of public-key quantum money (termed quantum coins), single-decryptor encryption, unclonable encryption, and more. We also introduce an extended notion of quantum coins, called upgradable quantum coins, which allow weak (almost-public) verification under weaker assumptions and can be upgraded to full public verification under stronger assumptions by the bank simply publishing additional classical information.
  Along the way, we give a generic compiler that upgrades single-copy secure single-decryptor encryption to a collusion-resistant one, assuming the existence of functional encryption, and construct the first multi-challenge secure unclonable encryption scheme, which we believe are of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12626v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alper \c{C}akan, Vipul Goyal, Fuyuki Kitagawa, Ryo Nishimaki, Takashi Yamakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Network-Based Prediction of Cancer Driver Genes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identification of cancer driver genes is fundamental for the development of targeted therapeutic interventions. The integration of mutational profiles with protein-protein interaction (PPI) networks offers a promising avenue for their detection [ 1, 2], but scaling to large network datasets is computationally demanding. Quantum computing offers compact representations and potential complexity reductions. Motivated by the classical method of Gumpinger et al. [3], in this work we introduce a supervised quantum framework that combines mutation scores with network topology via a novel state preparation scheme, Quantum Multi-order Moment Embedding (QMME). QMME encodes low-order statistical moments over the mutation scores of a node's immediate and second-order neighbors, and encodes this information into quantum states. These are used as inputs to a kernel-based quantum binary classifier that discriminates known driver genes from others. Simulations on an empirical PPI network demonstrate competitive performance, with a 12.6% recall gain over a classical baseline. The pipeline performs explicit quantum state preparation and requires no classical training, enabling an efficient, nearly end-to-end quantum workflow. A brief complexity analysis suggests the approach could achieve a quantum speedup in network-based cancer gene prediction. This work underscores the potential of supervised quantum graph learning frameworks to advance biological discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12628v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patricia Marques, Andreas Wichert, Duarte Magano, Bruno Coutinho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Quantum Eigensolver Models of Molecular Quantum Dot Cellular Automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular quantum-dot Cellular Automata (QCA) may provide low-power, high-speed computational hardware for processing classical information. Simulation and modeling play an important role in the design of QCA circuits because fully-coherent models of QCA scale exponentially with the number of devices, and such models are severely limited in size. For larger circuits, approximations become necessary. In the era of fault-tolerant quantum computation, however, it may become possible to model large QCA circuits without such limitations. Presently, this work explores the use of the noisy-intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) method for estimating the ground state of QCA circuits. This is relevant because the computational result of a QCA calculation is encoded in the circuit's ground state. In this study, VQE is used to model logic circuits, including binary wires,
  inverters, and majority gates. VQE models are performed ideal simulators, noisy simulators, and actual quantum hardware. This study demonstrates that VQE may indeed be used to model molecular QCA circuits. It is observed that using modern NISQ hardware, results are still quite sensitive to noise, so measures should be taken to minimize noise. These include simplifying the ansatz circuit whenever possible, and using low-noise hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12656v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nischal Binod Gautam, Enrique P. Blair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Multimode Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill Codes with Noisy Auxiliary States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In order to achieve fault-tolerant quantum computing, we make use of quantum error correction schemes designed to protect the logical information of the system from decoherence. A promising way to preserve such information is to use the multimode Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) encoding, which encodes logical qubits into several harmonic oscillators. In this work, we focus on decoding the measurements obtained from Steane-type quantum error correction protocols for multimode GKP codes. We propose a decoder that considers the noise present on the auxiliary states, more specifically by tracking the correlations between errors on different modes spreading throughout the error-correction circuit. We show that leveraging the correlations between measurement results and the actual error affecting the multimode GKP state can decrease the logical error probability by at least an order of magnitude, yielding more robust quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12677v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc-Antoine Roy, Thomas Pousset, Baptiste Royer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Links Between Quantum Classification of Patterns of Boolean Functions and Hamming Distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article investigates the probabilistic relationship between quantum classification of Boolean functions and their Hamming distance. By integrating concepts from quantum computing, information theory, and combinatorics, we explore how Hamming distance serves as a metric for analyzing deviations in function classification. Our extensive experimental results confirm that the Hamming distance is a pivotal metric for validating nearest neighbors in the process of classifying random functions. One of the significant conclusions we arrived is that the successful classification probability decreases monotonically with the Hamming distance. However, key exceptions were found in specific classes, revealing intra-class heterogeneity. We have established that these deviations are not random but are systemic and predictable. Furthermore, we were able to quantify these irregularities, turning potential errors into manageable phenomena. The most important novelty of this work is the demarcation, for the first time to the best of our knowledge, of precise Hamming distance intervals for the classification probability. These intervals bound the possible values the probability can assume, and provide a new foundational tool for probabilistic assessment in quantum classification. Practitioners can now endorse classification results with high certainty or dismiss them with confidence. This framework can significantly enhance any quantum classification algorithm's reliability and decision-making capability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12736v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodore Andronikos, Constantinos Bitsakos, Konstantinos Nikas, Georgios I. Goumas, Nectarios Koziris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent Variational Principles for Hybrid Non-Unitary Dynamics: Application to Driven-Dissipative Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce time-dependent variational principles to study the non-unitary dynamics of open quantum many-body systems, including dynamics described by the full Lindblad master equation, the non-Hermitian dynamics corresponding to the no-click limit of the fully post-selected quantum trajectories, and the dynamics described by a hybrid Lindbladian with a control parameter $\alpha$ which interpolates between the full post-selection and averaging over all quantum trajectories. As an application we study the non-unitary dynamics of a lossy or driven-dissipative BCS superconductors, evolving in presence of two-body losses and two-body pumps. We show that the non-Hermitian limit acts as a singular limit of the hybrid dissipative dynamics, leading to a sharp modification of the universal approach to the driven-dissipative steady-states. By considering the dissipative dynamics with pair losses, we show that, as the non-Hermitian limit is approached, the density dynamics sharply evolves from a universal power-law to exponential decay that converges towards a quasi-steady plateau characterized by the freezing of the particle depletion due to pair losses. The reached quasi-stationary density increases as a function of the dissipation rate highlighting the emergence of a non-Hermitian Zeno effect in the lossy dynamics. For the driven-dissipative case, we show that, in the non-Hermitian limit, the system gets trapped into an effective negative temperature state, thus skipping the infinite temperature steady-state reached in the presence of finite contribution of the quantum jumps. We rationalize these findings in terms of the conservation of the length of the pseudospins which, in the non-Hermitian limit, suppresses the effective single-particle losses and pumps acting on the non-condensed particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12737v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Filice, Marco Schir\`o, Giacomo Mazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-induced entanglement in noisy 2D random Clifford circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study measurement-induced entanglement generated by column-by-column sampling of noisy 2D random Clifford circuits of size $N$ and depth $T$. Focusing on the operator entanglement $S_{\rm op}$ of the sampling-induced boundary state, first, we reproduce in the noiseless limit a finite-depth transition from area- to volume-law scaling. With on-site probablistic trace noise at any constant rate $p&gt;0$, the maximal $S_{\rm op}$ attained along the sampling trajectory obeys an area law in the boundary length and scales approximately linearly with $T/p$. By analyzing the spatial distribution of stabilizer generators, we observe exponential localization of stabilizer generators; this both accounts for the scaling of the maximal $S_{\rm op}$ and implies an exponential decay of conditional mutual information across buffered tripartitions, which we also confirm numerically. Together, these results indicate that constant local noise destroys long-range, volume-law measurement-induced entanglement in 2D random Clifford circuits. Finally, based on the observed scaling, we conjecture that a tensor-network-based algorithm can efficiently sample from noisy 2D random Clifford circuits (i) at sub-logarithmic depths $T = o(\log N)$ for any constant noise rate $p = \Omega(1)$, and (ii) at constant depths $T = O(1)$ for noise rates $p = \Omega(\log^{-1}N)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12743v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Yuan Wei, Jon Nelson, Joel Rajakumar, Esther Cruz, Alexey V. Gorshkov, Michael J. Gullans, Daniel Malz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contextuality-based quantum key distribution with deterministic single-photon sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12761v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photons are central to quantum technologies, with photonic qubits offering a promising platform for quantum communication. Semiconductor quantum dots stand out for their ability to generate single photons on demand, a key capability for enabling long-distance quantum networks. In this work, we utilize high-purity single-photon sources based on self-assembled InAs(Ga)As quantum dots as quantum information carriers. We demonstrate that such on-demand single photons can generate quantum contextuality. This capability enables a novel protocol for semi-device-independent quantum key distribution over free-space channels. Crucially, our method does not require ideal or perfectly projective measurements, opening a new pathway for robust and practical quantum communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12761v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Meng, Debashis Saha, Mikkel Thorbj{\o}rn Mikkelsen, Clara Henke, Ying Wang, Nikolai Bart, Arne Ludwig, Peter Lodahl, Ad\'an Cabello, Leonardo Midolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory-Protected Quantum Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel method that simultaneously isolates a quantum computer from decoherence and enables the controlled implementation of computational gates. We demonstrate a quantum computing model that utilizes a qubit's motion to protect it from decoherence. We model a qubit interacting with a quantum field via the standard light-matter interaction model: an Unruh-DeWitt detector, i.e., the qubit, follows a prescribed classical trajectory while interacting with a scalar quantum field. We switch off the rotating-wave terms, i.e., the resonant transitions, using the technique of acceleration-induced transparency which eliminates the dominant decoherence channels by controlling the qubit's trajectory. We are able to perform one-qubit gates by stimulating the counter-rotating wave terms (i.e., the non-resonant transitions) and two-qubit gates by extracting the entanglement from the quantum field prepared in a squeezed state. Finally, we discuss the fundamental limits on quantum error protection: on the trade-off between isolating a quantum computer from decoherence, and the speed with which entangling gates may be applied, comparable to the Eastin-Knill theorem for quantum error correction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12771v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barbara \v{S}oda, Pierre-Antoine Graham, T. Rick Perche, Gurpahul Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of Gaussian Boson Sampling on Planted Bipartite Clique Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate whether Gaussian Boson Sampling (GBS) can provide a computational advantage for solving the planted biclique problem, which is a graph problem widely believed to be classically hard when the planted structure is small. Although GBS has been heuristically and experimentally observed to favor sampling dense subgraphs, its theoretical performance on this classically hard problem remains largely unexplored. We focus on a natural statistic derived from GBS output: the frequency with which a node appears in GBS samples, referred to as the node weight. We rigorously analyze whether this signal is strong enough to distinguish planted biclique nodes from background nodes. Our analysis characterizes the distribution of node weights under GBS and quantifies the bias introduced by the planted structure. The results reveal a sharp limitation: when the planted biclique size falls within the conjectured hard regime, the natural fluctuations in node weights dominate the bias signal, making detection unreliable using simple ranking strategies. These findings provide the first rigorous evidence that planted biclique detection may remain computationally hard even under GBS-based quantum computing, and they motivate further investigation into more advanced GBS-based algorithms or other quantum approaches for this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12774v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Zhen Janice Chen, Laurent Massouli\'e, Don Towsley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of quantum processes: An operational framework for free energy and reversible athermality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the thermodynamics of quantum processes (quantum channels) by axiomatically introducing the free energy for channels, defined via the quantum relative entropy with an absolutely thermal channel whose fixed output is in equilibrium with a thermal reservoir. This definition finds strong support through its operational interpretations in designated quantum information and thermodynamic tasks. We construct a resource theory of athermality for quantum processes, where free operations are Gibbs preserving superchannels and golden units are unitary channels with respect to absolutely thermal channel having fully degenerate output Hamiltonian. We exactly characterize the one-shot distillation and formation of quantum channels using hypothesis-testing and max-relative entropy with respect to the absolutely thermal channel. These rates converge asymptotically to the channel free energy (up to a multiplicative factor of half the inverse temperature), establishing its operational meaning and proving the asymptotic reversibility of the athermality. We show the direct relation between the resource theory of athermality and quantum information tasks such as private randomness and purity distillation and thermodynamic tasks of erasure and work extraction. Our work connects the core thermodynamic concepts of free energy, energy, entropy, and maximal extractable work of quantum processes to their information processing capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12790v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Badhani, Dhanuja G S, Siddhartha Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prethermal gauge structure and surface growth in $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Universal aspects of thermalization in interacting many-body systems are typically challenging to derive microscopically, yet provide a powerful framework for understanding emergent phenomena. Here, we numerically study the mean-field dynamics of a $(2+1)$D spin system with thousands of spins and show that experimentally-feasible two-body Ising interactions can stabilize a prethermal $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge structure with dynamical matter, manifested by a gauge-invariant plateau with exponentially long lifetime. Eventually, the metastable prethermal $\mathbb{Z}_2$ gauge structure breaks down via a proliferation of Gauss' law defects, similar to bubble formation in false vacuum decay. In this regime, we discover spatio-temporal correlations described by a non-linear surface growth consistent with the $(1+1)$D Kardar-Parisi-Zhang (KPZ) universality class. We benchmark our results in small systems against semi-classical discrete time Wigner approximation (DTWA) and exact diagonalization (ED), where the breakdown of DTWA signals the emergence of an extensive number of local symmetries that strongly influence the thermalization pathway. Our model provides a testbed for quantum simulators and is directly implementable in large-scale arrays of Rydberg atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12800v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Homeier, Andrea Pizzi, Hongzheng Zhao, Jad C. Halimeh, Fabian Grusdt, Ana Maria Rey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetometry with Broadband Microwave Fields in Nitrogen-Vacancy Centers in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nitrogen vacancy (NV) centers in diamond are optically addressable and versatile light-matter interfaces with practical application in magnetic field sensing, offering the ability to operate at room temperature and reach sensitivities below pT/$\sqrt{\mathrm{Hz}}.$ We propose an approach to simultaneously probe all of the magnetically sensitive states using a broadband microwave field and demonstrate that it can be used to measure the external DC magnetic field strength with sensitivities below 1~nT/$\sqrt{\mathrm{Hz}}.$ We develop tools for analyzing the temporal signatures in the transmitted broadband microwaves to estimate the magnetic field, comparing maximum likelihood estimation based on minimizing the Kullback-Leibler divergence to various neural network models, and both methods independently reach practical sensitivities. These results are achieved without optimizing parameters such as the bandwidth, power, and shape of the probing microwave field such that, with further improvements, sensitivities down to $\mathrm{pT/\sqrt{Hz}}$ can be envisioned. Our results motivate novel implementations of NV-based magnetic sensors with the potential for vectorial magnetic field detection at 1-10 kHz update rates and improved sensitivities without requiring a bias magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11720v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arezoo Afshar, Andrew Proppe, Noah Lupu-Gladstein, Lilian Childress, Aaron Z. Goldberg, Khabat Heshami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Platinum Thin Films on the Photophysical and Quantum Properties of Near-Surface NV Centers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond are optically addressable spin defects with great potential for nanoscale quantum sensing. A key application of NV centers is the detection of external spins at the diamond surface. Among metals, platinum thin films - widely used in spintronics, catalysis and electrochemistry - provide a particularly interesting system for such studies. However, the interaction between NV centers and metals is known to affect their quantum sensing capabilities. In this work, we study five platinum-covered diamond samples containing shallow NVs created via nitrogen implantation with different energies (2.5-60 keV) and investigate the optical and quantum properties of NV ensembles beneath the metal films. We find a substantial reduction of the photoluminescence lifetime and a pronounced decrease of the NV$^{-}$ population for NV ensembles located near the platinum layer. As a result, optically detected magnetic resonance experiments could only be efficiently performed on diamonds implanted with at least 20 keV, where we observed a strong increase in the T$_{2}$ coherence time beneath the platinum thin films. Our study describes the various processes affecting NV centers near platinum films and provides guidance for the integration of thin metal films with near-surface NV centers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11721v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joachim P. Leibold (Department of Chemistry, School of Natural Sciences, Technical University of Munich, Garching, Germany), Lina M. Todenhagen (Walter Schottky Institute, Technical University of Munich, Garching, Germany), Matthias Althammer (Walther-Mei{\ss}ner-Institute, Bavarian Academy of Sciences and Humanities, Garching, Germany), Nikhita Khera (Department of Physics and Research Center OPTIMAS, RPTU Kaiserslautern Landau, Kaiserslautern, Germany), Elke Neu (Department of Physics and Research Center OPTIMAS, RPTU Kaiserslautern Landau, Kaiserslautern, Germany), Martin S. Brandt (Walter Schottky Institute, Technical University of Munich, Garching, Germany), Hans Huebl (Walther-Mei{\ss}ner-Institute, Bavarian Academy of Sciences and Humanities, Garching, Germany), Dominik B. Bucher (Department of Chemistry, School of Natural Sciences, Technical University of Munich, Garching, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Temperature Induced by Adopted Regular Universal Turing Machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11737v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that an effective temperature naturally emerges from the algorithmic structure of a regular universal Turing machine (UTM), without introducing any external physical parameter. In particular, the redundancy growth of the machine's wrapper language induces a Boltzmann--like exponential weighting over program lengths, yielding a canonical ensemble interpretation of algorithmic probability. This establishes a formal bridge between algorithmic information theory and statistical mechanics, in which the adopted UTM determines the intrinsic ``algorithmic temperature.'' We further show that this temperature approaches its maximal limit under the universal mixture (Solomonoff distribution), and discuss its epistemic meaning as the resolution level of an observer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11737v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Imafuku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution With(out) Time: Relational Holography &amp; BPS Complexity Growth in $\mathcal{N}=2$ Double-Scaled SYK</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11777v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: How do we describe non-trivial bulk measurements relative to an observer (i.e. relationally) when both the observer and the system it probes may/may not evolve in time? How can we interpret this holographically; particularly for zero-energy BPS states in supersymmetric theories? We address these questions, in the $\mathcal{N}=2$ double-scaled SYK model and its putative bulk dual by: (i) formulating a holographic procedure in the language of quantum reference frames to gravitationally dress bulk observables to ``clocks'' parametrized by both boundary time and R-charge; and (ii) proposing a \emph{new measure of Krylov complexity} with R-charge in the boundary theory that probes zero-energy BPS states. Holographically, this proposal reproduces a relational bulk observable, a BPS wormhole length. We contrast this to the Krylov complexity for Hartle-Hawking states with non-trivial time flow. The latter reproduces the same observable as for the bosonic DSSYK in the semiclassical limit, while its quantum fluctuations can capture supersymmetric corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11777v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio E. Aguilar-Gutierrez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Speed-up of Wave-like Dark Matter Searches with Entangled Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11795v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Qubit-based sensing platforms offer promising new directions for wave-like dark matter searches. Recent proposals demonstrate that entangled qubits can achieve quadratic scaling of the signal in the number of qubits. In this work we expand on these proposals to analyze the bandwidth and scan rate performance of entangled qubit protocols across different error regimes. We find that the phase-based readout of entangled protocols preserves the search bandwidth independent of qubit number, in contrast to power-based detection schemes, thereby achieving a genuine scan-rate advantage. We derive coherence time and error rate requirements for qubit systems to realize this advantage. Applying our analysis to dark photon searches, we find that entangled states of approximately 100 qubits can become competitive with benchmark photon-counting cavity experiments for masses $\gtrsim 30{-}40~\mu{\rm eV}$, provided sufficiently low error rates are achieved. The advantage increases at higher masses where cavity volume scaling becomes less favorable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11795v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arushi Bodas, Sohitri Ghosh, Roni Harnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbatively slow spread of quantum correlations in non-resonant systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strong disorder often has drastic consequences for quantum dynamics. This is best illustrated by the phenomenon of Anderson localization in non-interacting systems, where destructive quantum wave interference leads to the complete absence of particle and information transport over macroscopic distances. In this work, we investigate the extent to which strong disorder leads to provably slow dynamics in many-body quantum lattice models. We show that in any spatial dimension, strong disorder leads to a non-perturbatively small velocity for ballistic information transport under unitary quantum dynamics, almost surely in the thermodynamic limit, in every many-body state. In these models, we also prove the existence of a "prethermal many-body localized regime", where entanglement spreads logarithmically slowly, up to non-perturbatively long time scales. More generally, these conclusions hold for all models corresponding to quantum perturbations to a classical Hamiltonian obeying a simple non-resonant condition. Deterministic non-resonant models are found, including spin systems in strong incommensurate lattice potentials. Consequently, quantum dynamics in non-resonant potentials is asymptotically easier to simulate on both classical or quantum computers, compared to a generic many-body system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11831v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben T. McDonough, Marius Lemm, Andrew Lucas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General model and modulation strategies for Sagnac-based encoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent decades, there has been an increasing demand for faster modulation schemes. Electro-optic modulators are essential components in modern photonic systems, enabling high-speed control of light for applications ranging from telecommunications to quantum communication. Conventional inline and Mach-Zehnder modulators, while widely adopted, are limited by bias drift, high operating voltages, and polarization-mode dispersion. Sagnac loop-based modulators have recently emerged as a promising alternative, offering inherent stability against environmental fluctuations and eliminating the need for active bias control. In this work, we present a comprehensive model of the Sagnac modulator that captures both intensity and polarization modulation. We analyze the role of asymmetry in the loop, highlighting its impact on the achievable repetition rate, and propose modulation strategies to overcome these constraints. Finally, we investigate the symmetric Sagnac configuration and demonstrate practical techniques for achieving robust modulation while mitigating experimental challenges. Our results establish the Sagnac modulator as a versatile and stable platform for next-generation photonic and quantum communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11873v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Berra, Mat\'ias Rub\'en Bola\~nos, Alberto De Toni, Kannan Vijayadharan, Costantino Agnesi, Marco Avesani, Andrea Stanco, Paolo Villoresi, Giuseppe Vallone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopy of Sm$^{3+}$ Ions in the C$_{\rm s}$ Symmetry Centres of Hydrothermally Prepared K$_2$YF$_5$ Microcrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11934v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report on the synthesis and spectroscopic characterization of Sm$^{3+}$-doped K$_2$YF$_5$ microparticles. The particles were synthesized via the hydrothermal technique, yielding a particle size of approximately 20 $\mu$m in length. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and X-ray diffraction (XRD) analyses confirmed their orthorhombic crystal structure. A combination of absorption and laser excited fluorescence performed on samples cooled to 10~K, allow for the determination of {56} experimental crystal-field levels. A parametrised crystal-field analysis for Sm$^{3+}$ in the C$_{\rm s}$ point group symmetry centres of K$_2$YF$_5$ yields good approximation to the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11934v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.optmat.2025.117602</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Optical Materials 169,117602 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pakwan Chanprakhon, Michael F. Reid, and Jon-Paul R. Wells</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brillouin-Mandelstam Scattering-based Cooling of Traveling Acoustic Waves from Cryogenic Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12418v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal phonons are a major source of decoherence in quantum mechanical systems. Operating in the quantum ground state is therefore often an experimental prerequisite. Additionally to passive cooling in a cryogenic environment, active laser cooling enables the reduction of phonons at specific acoustic frequencies. Brillouin cooling has been used to show efficient reduction of the thermal phonon population in waveguides at GHz frequencies down to 74 K. In this letter, we demonstrate cooling of a 7.608 GHz acoustic mode by combining Brillouin active cooling with precooling from 77 K using liquid nitrogen. We show a 69 % reduction in the phonon population, resulting in a final temperature of 24.3 K, 50 K lower than previously reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12418v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lisa Fischer, Laura Bl\'azquez Mart\'inez, Robin Chenivi\`ere, Johann Troles, Birgit Stiller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green's function expansion for multiple coupled optical resonators with finite retardation using quasinormal modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12511v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electromagnetic Green's function is a crucial ingredient for the theoretical study of modern photonic quantum devices, but is often difficult or even impossible to calculate directly. We present a numerically efficient framework for calculating the scattered electromagnetic Green's function of a multi-cavity system with spatially separated open cavities (with arbitrary shape, dispersion and loss) and finite retardation times. The framework is based on a Dyson scattering equation that enables the construction of the Green's function from the quasinormal modes of the individual resonators within a few-mode approximation and a finite number of iteration steps without requiring nested integrals. The approach shows excellent agreement with the full numerical Green's function for the example of two coupled dipoles located in the gaps of two metal dimers serving as quasinormal mode cavities, and is easily extended to arbitrarily large separations and multiple cavities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12511v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Fuchs, Juanjuan Ren, Stephen Hughes, Marten Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GUPPY: Pythonic Quantum-Classical Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12582v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present ongoing work on Guppy, a domain-specific language embedded in Python that allows users to write high-level hybrid quantum programs with complex control flow in Pythonic syntax, aiming to run them on actual quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12582v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Koch, Alan Lawrence, Kartik Singhal, Seyon Sivarajah, Ross Duncan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum thermodynamics of Gross-Pitaevskii qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12599v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: What are the resources that can be leveraged for a thermodynamic device to exhibit genuine quantum advantage? Typically, the answer to this question is sought in quantum correlations. In the present work, we show that quantum Otto engines that operate with nonlinear qubits significantly outperform linear engines. To this end, we develop a comprehensive thermodynamic description of nonlinear qubits starting with identifying the proper thermodynamic equilibrium state. We then show that for ideal cycles as well as at maximum power the efficiency of the nonlinear engine is significantly higher. Interestingly, nonlinear dynamics can be thought of as an effective description of a correlated, complex quantum many body system. Hence, our findings corroborate common wisdom, while at the same time propose a new design of more efficient quantum engines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12599v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Deffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature and conditions for thermalization after canonical quenches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider quenches of a quantum system that is prepared in a canonical equilibrium state of one Hamiltonian and then evolves unitarily in time under a different Hamiltonian. Technically, our main result is a systematic expansion of the pre- and post-quench canonical ensembles in the quench strength. We first demonstrate how this can be used to predict the system's temperature after the quench from equilibrium properties at the pre-quench temperature. For a thermalizing post-quench system, it furthermore allows us to calculate equilibrium observable expectation values. Finally, in the presence of additional conserved quantities besides the Hamiltonian, we obtain a hierarchy of necessary conditions for thermalization towards the (post-quench) canonical ensemble. At first order, these thermalization conditions have a nice geometric interpretation in operator space with the canonical covariance as a semi-inner product: The quench operator (difference between post- and pre-quench Hamiltonians) and the conserved quantity must be orthogonal in the orthogonal complement of the post-quench Hamiltonian. We illustrate the results numerically for a variety of setups involving integrable and nonintegrable models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12696v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lennart Dabelow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical representation of local Clifford operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13304v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that every (single-qudit) Clifford operator maps the full set of generalized Pauli matrices (GPMs) to itself under unitary conjugation, which is an important quantum operation and plays a crucial role in quantum computation and information. However, in many quantum information processing tasks, it is required that a specific set of GPMs be mapped to another such set under conjugation, instead of the entire set. We formalize this by introducing local Clifford operator, which maps a given $n$-GPM set to another such set under unitary conjugation. We establish necessary and sufficient conditions for such an operator to transform a pair of GPMs, showing that these local Clifford operators admit a classical matrix representation, analogous to the classical (or symplectic) representation of standard (single-qudit) Clifford operators. Furthermore, we demonstrate that any local Clifford operator acting on an $n$-GPM ($n\geq 2$) set can be decomposed into a product of standard Clifford operators and a local Clifford operator acting on a pair of GPMs. This decomposition provides a complete classical characterization of unitary conjugation mappings between $n$-GPM sets. As a key application, we use this framework to address the local unitary equivalence (LU-equivalence) of sets of generalized Bell states (GBSs). We prove that the 31 equivalence classes of $4$-GBS sets in bipartite system $\mathbb{C}^{6}\otimes \mathbb{C}^{6}$ previously identified via Clifford operators are indeed distinct under LU-equivalence, confirming that this classification is complete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13304v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cai-Hong Wang, Jiang-Tao Yuan, Zhi-Hao Ma, Shao-Ming Fei, Shang-Quan Bu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient and exact noncommutative quantum Gibbs sampler</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Preparing thermal and ground states is an essential quantum algorithmic task for quantum simulation. In this work, we construct the first efficiently implementable and exactly detailed-balanced Lindbladian for Gibbs states of arbitrary noncommutative Hamiltonians. Our construction can also be regarded as a continuous-time quantum analog of the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm. To prepare the quantum Gibbs state, our algorithm invokes Hamiltonian simulation for a time proportional to the mixing time and the inverse temperature $\beta$, up to polylogarithmic factors. Moreover, the gate complexity reduces significantly for lattice Hamiltonians as the corresponding Lindblad operators are (quasi-) local (with radius $\sim\beta$) and only depend on local Hamiltonian patches. Meanwhile, purifying our Lindbladians yields a temperature-dependent family of frustration-free "parent Hamiltonians", prescribing an adiabatic path for the canonical purified Gibbs state (i.e., the Thermal Field Double state). These favorable features suggest that our construction serves as a quantum algorithmic counterpart to classical Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09207v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi-Fang Chen, Michael J. Kastoryano, Andr\'as Gily\'en</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Circuit Synthesis and Compilation Optimization: Overview and Prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00736v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum computing is a promising paradigm that may overcome the current computational power bottlenecks. The increasing maturity of quantum processors provides more possibilities for the development and implementation of quantum algorithms. As the crucial stages for quantum algorithm implementation, the logic circuit design and quantum compiling have also received significant attention, which covers key technologies, e.g., quantum logic circuit synthesis (also widely known as quantum architecture search) and optimization, as well as qubit mapping and routing. Recent studies suggest that the scale and precision of related algorithms are steadily increasing, especially with the integration of artificial intelligence methods. In this survey, we systematically review and summarize a vast body of literature, exploring the feasibility of an integrated design and optimization scheme that spans from the algorithmic level to quantum hardware, combining the steps of logic circuit design and compilation optimization. Leveraging the exceptional cognitive and learning capabilities of AI algorithms, it becomes more possible to reduce manual design costs, enhance the precision and efficiency of execution, and facilitate the implementation and validation of the superiority of quantum algorithms on hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00736v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ge Yan, Wenjie Wu, Yuheng Chen, Kaisen Pan, Xudong Lu, Zixiang Zhou, Yuhan Wang, Ruocheng Wang, Junchi Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-shot and measurement-based quantum error correction via fault complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Photonics provides a viable path to a scalable fault-tolerant quantum computer. The natural framework for this platform is measurement-based quantum computation, where fault-tolerant graph states supersede traditional quantum error-correcting codes. However, the existing formalism for foliation - the construction of fault-tolerant graph states - does not reveal how certain properties, such as single-shot error correction, manifest in the measurement-based setting. We introduce the fault complex, a representation of dynamic quantum error correction protocols particularly well-suited to describe foliation. Our approach enables precise computation of fault tolerance properties of foliated codes and provides insights into circuit-based quantum computation. Analyzing the fault complex leads to improved thresholds for three- and four-dimensional toric codes, a generalization of stability experiments, and the existence of single-shot lattice surgery with higher-dimensional topological codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12963v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/cjb4-l57n</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, L040401 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Timo Hillmann, Guillaume Dauphinais, Ilan Tzitrin, Michael Vasmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-shot distillation with constant overhead using catalysts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14547v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum resource distillation is a fundamental task in quantum information science and technology. Minimizing the overhead of distillation is crucial for the realization of quantum computation and other technologies. Here we explicitly demonstrate how, for general quantum resources, suitably designed quantum catalysts (i.e., auxiliary systems that remain unchanged before and after the process) enable distillation with constant overhead in the practical one-shot setting, thereby overcoming the established logarithmic lower bound for one-shot distillation overhead. In particular, for magic state distillation, our catalysis method paves a path for tackling the diverging batch size problem associated with code-based low-overhead protocols by enabling arbitrary reduction of the protocol size for any desired accuracy. Notably, this first yields constant-overhead magic state distillation methods with controllable protocol size. Furthermore, we demonstrate a tunable spacetime trade-off between overhead and success probability enabled by catalysts which offers significant versatility for practical implementation. Finally, we extend catalysis techniques to dynamical quantum resources and show that channel mutual information determines one-shot catalytic channel transformation, thereby advancing our understanding for both dynamical catalysis and information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14547v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Fang, Zi-Wen Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical simulation of circuits with realistic odd-dimensional Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13136v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Classically simulating circuits with bosonic codes is challenging due to the prohibitive cost of simulating quantum systems with many, possibly infinite, energy levels. We propose an algorithm to simulate circuits with encoded Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) states, specifically for odd-dimensional encoded qudits. Our approach is tailored to be especially effective in the most challenging but practically relevant regime, where the codeword states exhibit high (but finite) squeezing. Our algorithm leverages the Zak-Gross Wigner function introduced by J. Davis et al. [arXiv:2407.18394], which represents infinitely squeezed encoded stabilizer states positively. The runtime of the algorithm scales with the negativity of the Wigner function, allowing for efficient simulation of certain large-scale circuits - namely, input stabilizer GKP states undergoing generalized GKP-encoded Clifford operations followed by modular measurements - with a high degree of squeezing. For stabilizer GKP states exhibiting 12 dB of squeezing, our algorithm can simulate circuits with up to 1,000 modes with less than double the number of samples required for a single input mode, in stark contrast to existing simulators. Therefore, this approach holds significant potential for benchmarking early implementations of quantum computing architectures utilizing bosonic codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13136v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/xmtw-g54f</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 135, 010601 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cameron Calcluth, Oliver Hahn, Juani Bermejo-Vega, Alessandro Ferraro, Giulia Ferrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmon qutrit-based simulation of spin-1 AKLT systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19786v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Qutrit-based quantum circuits could help reduce the overall circuit depths, and hence the effect of noise, when the system of interest has a local dimension of three. Accessing second excited states in superconducting transmons provides a straightforward hardware realization of qutrits useful for such ternary encoding. In this work, we successfully calibrate microwave pulse gates to a low error rate to operate transmon qutrits. We use these qutrits to simulate one-dimensional spin-1 AKLT states (Affleck, Kennedy, Lieb, and Tasaki), which exhibit a multitude of interesting phenomena, such as topologically protected ground states, string order, and the existence of a robust Berry phase. We demonstrate the efficacy of qutrit-based simulation by preparing high-fidelity ground states of the AKLT Hamiltonian with open boundaries for various chain lengths. We then use ground state preparations of the perturbed AKLT Hamiltonian with periodic boundaries to calculate the Berry phase and illustrate non-trivial ground state topology. To establish the advantage of qutrits over qubits in the presence of noise, we present scalable methods for preparing the AKLT state and computing its Berry phase using tensor network simulations. Our work provides a pathway toward more general spin-1 physics simulations using transmon qutrits, with applications in chemistry, magnetism, and topological phases of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19786v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keerthi Kumaran, Faisal Alam, Norhan Eassa, Kaelyn Ferris, Xiao Xiao, Lukasz Cincio, Nicholas Bronn, Arnab Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The simplest 2D quantum walk detects chaoticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13900v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum walks are at present an active field of study in mathematics, with important applications in quantum information and statistical physics. In this paper, we determine the influence of basic chaotic features on the walker behavior. For this purpose, we consider an extremely simple model consisting of alternating one-dimensional walks along the two spatial coordinates in bidimensional closed domains (hard wall billiards). The chaotic or regular behavior induced by the boundary shape in the deterministic classical motion translates into chaotic signatures for the quantized problem, resulting in sharp differences in the spectral statistics and morphology of the eigenfunctions of the quantum walker. Indeed, we found for the Bunimovich stadium -- a chaotic billiard -- level statistics described by a Brody distribution with parameter $\delta \simeq 0.1$. This indicates a weak level repulsion, and also enhanced eigenfunction localization, with an average participation ratio (PR) $\simeq$ 1150) compared to the rectangular billiard (regular) case, where the average PR $\simeq$ 1500. Furthermore, scarring on unstable periodic orbits is observed. The fact that our simple model exhibits such key signatures of quantum chaos, e.g., non-Poissonian level statistics and scarring, that are sensitive to the underlying classical dynamics in the free particle billiard system is utterly surprising, especially when taking into account that quantum walks are diffusive models, which are not direct quantizations of a Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13900v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/math13193223</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mathematics 2025, 13(19), 3223</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>C. Alonso-Lobo, Gabriel G. Carlo, F. Borondo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-Enabled Nanoparticle Diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13821v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a scheme for generating high-mass quantum superposition states of an optically pre-cooled, levitated nanoparticle through electron diffraction at its sub-nanometer crystal lattice. When a single electron undergoes Bragg diffraction at a free-falling nanoparticle, momentum conservation implies that the superposition of Bragg momenta is imprinted onto the relative coordinate between electron and nanoparticle, which entangles their wavefunctions. By imaging the electron interferogram, one maps the nanoparticle state onto a superposition of Bragg momenta, as if it was diffracted by its own lattice. This results in a coherent momentum splitting approximately 1000 times greater than what is achievable with two-photon recoils in conventional standing-wave gratings. Self-interference of the nanoparticle can thus be observed within drastically shorter free-fall times in a time-domain Talbot interferometer configuration, significantly relaxing source requirements and alleviating decoherence from environmental factors such as residual gas and thermal radiation. Shorter interference times also allow for a recapture of the nanoparticle within its initial trapping volume, facilitating its reuse in many rapid experimental duty cycles. This opens new possibilities for experimental tests of macroscopic quantum effects within a transmission electron microscope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13821v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Nimmrichter, Dennis R\"atzel, Isobel C. Bicket, Michael S. Seifner, Philipp Haslinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superdiffusion resilience in Heisenberg Chains with 2D interactions on a quantum processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Observing superdiffusive scaling in the spin transport of the integrable 1D Heisenberg model is one of the key discoveries in non-equilibrium quantum many-body physics. Despite this remarkable theoretical development and the subsequent experimental observation of the phenomena in KCuF$_3$, real materials are often imperfect and contain integrability breaking interactions. Understanding the effect of such terms on the superdiffusion is crucial in identifying connections to such materials. Current quantum hardware has already ascertained its utility in studying such non-equilibrium phenomena by simulating the superdiffusion of the 1D Heisenberg model. In this work, we perform a quantum simulation of the superdiffusion breakdown by generalizing the superdiffusive Floquet-type 1D Heisenberg model to a general 2D model. We comprehensively study the effect of different 2D interactions on the superdiffusion breakdown by tuning up their strength from zero, corresponding to the 1D Heisenberg chain, to finite nonzero values. We observe that certain 2D interactions are more resilient against superdiffusion breakdown than others and that the $SU(2)$ preserving 2D interaction has the highest resilience among all the 2D interactions we study. Importantly, this observed resilience has direct implications for sustaining superdiffusive spin transport in two-dimensional lattices. We reason out the relative resilience against the superdiffusion breakdown through an analysis of the scattering coefficients off the 2D interaction in otherwise 1D chains. The relative resilience of different interaction types against superdiffusion breakdown was also captured in quantum hardware with remarkable accuracy, further establishing the current quantum hardware's applicability in simulating interesting non-equilibrium quantum many-body phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14371v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keerthi Kumaran, Manas Sajjan, Bibek Pokharel, Kevin Wang, Joe Gibbs, Jeffrey Cohn, Barbara Jones, Sarah Mostame, Sabre Kais, Arnab Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation-Driven Transition of Particles from Dispersive to Flat Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00796v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Flat bands (FBs) play a crucial role in condensed matter physics, offering an ideal platform to study strong correlation effects and enabling applications in diffraction-free photonics and quantum devices. However, the study and application of FB properties are susceptible to interference from dispersive bands. Here, we explore the impact of bond dissipation on systems hosting both flat and dispersive bands by calculating the steady-state density matrix. We demonstrate that bond dissipation can drive particles from dispersive bands into FBs and establish the general conditions for this phenomenon to occur. Our results demonstrate that dissipation can facilitate FB preparation, property measurement, and utilization. This opens a new avenue for exploring FB physics in open quantum systems, with potential implications for strongly correlated physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00796v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lyr8-n4r9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L161113 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yutao Hu, Chao Yang, Yucheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Phase Gates as Airy Transforms of the Wigner Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04851v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Low-order nonlinear phase gates allow the construction of versatile higher-order nonlinearities for bosonic systems and grant access to continuous variable quantum simulations of many unexplored aspects of nonlinear quantum dynamics. The resulting nonlinear transformations produce, even with small strength, multiple regions of negativity in the Wigner function and thus show an immediate departure from classical phase space. Towards the development of realistic, bounded versions of these gates we show that the action of a quartic-bounded cubic gate on an arbitrary multimode quantum state in phase space can be understood as an Airy transform of the Wigner function. This toolbox generalises the symplectic transformations associated with Gaussian operations and allows for the practical calculation, analysis and interpretation of explicit Wigner functions and the quantum non-Gaussian phenomena resulting from bounded nonlinear potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04851v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41534-025-01006-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Quantum Inf 11, 159 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Darren W. Moore, Radim Filip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R\'enyi security framework against coherent attacks applied to decoy-state QKD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12248v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a flexible and robust framework for finite-size security proofs of quantum key distribution (QKD) protocols under coherent attacks, applicable to both fixed- and variable-length protocols. Our approach achieves high finite-size key rates across a broad class of protocols while imposing minimal requirements. In particular, it eliminates the need for restrictive conditions such as limited repetition rates or the implementation of virtual tomography procedures. To achieve this goal, we introduce new numerical techniques for the evaluation of sandwiched conditional R\'enyi entropies. In doing so, we also find an alternative formulation of the "QKD cone" studied in previous work. We illustrate the versatility of our framework by applying it to several practically relevant protocols, including decoy-state protocols. Furthermore, we extend the analysis to accommodate realistic device imperfections, such as independent intensity and phase imperfections. Overall, our framework provides both greater scope of applicability and better key rates than existing techniques, especially for small block sizes, hence offering a scalable path toward secure quantum communication under realistic conditions</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12248v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lars Kamin, John Burniston, Ernest Y. -Z. Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast switching of telecom photon-number states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12376v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A crucial component of photonic quantum information processing platforms is the ability to modulate, route, convert, and switch quantum states of light noiselessly with low insertion loss. For instance, a high-speed, low-loss optical switch is crucial for scaling quantum photonic systems that rely on measurement-based feed-forward approaches. Such a device will also ideally be capable of operating on photon-number states, which can act as non-Gaussian resources. Here, we demonstrate ultrafast all-optical switching of heralded photon-number states, of up to 6 photons, using the optical Kerr effect in a single-mode fiber. A local birefringence is created by a high-intensity pump pulse at a center wavelength of 1030 nm which overlaps temporally with the 1550 nm photons in the fiber. A switching efficiency of $&gt;$99 % is reached with a resolution of 2.3 ps, an insertion loss of $2.27\pm0.08$ dB, and a signal-to-noise ratio of 32,000.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12376v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kate L. Fenwick, Fr\'ed\'eric Bouchard, Alicia Sit, Timothy Lee, Andrew H. Proppe, Guillaume Thekkadath, Duncan England, Philip J. Bustard, Jeff S. Lundeen, Benjamin J. Sussman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding across transversal Clifford gates in the surface code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13599v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transversal logical gates offer the opportunity for fast and low-noise logic, particularly when interspersed by a single round of parity check measurements of the underlying code. Using such circuits for the surface code requires decoding across logical gates, complicating the decoding task. We show how one can decode across an arbitrary sequence of transversal gates for the unrotated surface code, using a fast "logical observable" minimum-weight-perfect-matching (MWPM) based decoder, and benchmark its performance in Clifford circuits under circuit-level noise. We propose windowed logical observable matching decoders to address the problem of fully efficient decoding: our basic windowed decoder is computationally efficient under the restriction of quiescent (slow) resets. Our 'advanced' two-step windowed decoder can be computationally inefficient but allows fast resets. For both windowed decoders we identify errors which scale sublinearly in $d$ - depending on the structure of the circuit - which can lead to logical failure, and we propose methods to adapt the decoding to remove such failures. Our work highlights the complexity and interest in efficient decoding of fast logic for the surface code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13599v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Serra-Peralta, Mackenzie H. Shaw, Barbara M. Terhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum correlations versus spin magnitude: Transition to the classical limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04782v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum-classical transitions have long attracted much attention. We study such transitions in quantum spin-($j$,1/2) systems at thermal equilibrium. Unlike the previous work [Phys. Rev. A 73, 064302 (2006)], it is found that the threshold temperature of quantum entanglement decreases with increasing spin $j$ and completely disappears in the limit $j\to\infty$. In the ground state of systems with highly symmetric interactions, the discord-type quantum correlations can exist even for arbitrarily large spin. Such correlations turn out to be unstable and are destroyed by small perturbations that violate the symmetry of the Hamiltonian. The stable quantum correlations gradually degrade as the spin $j$ grows and eventually vanish when the classical limit is reached.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04782v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qxtm-gysy</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 042405 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Yurischev, E. I. Kuznetsova, Saeed Haddadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical-quantum systems breaking conservation laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15291v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Whether gravity must be quantized remains one of the biggest open problems in fundamental physics. Classical-quantum hybrid theories have recently attracted attention as a possible framework in which gravity is treated classically yet interacts consistently with quantum matter. Schemes based on completely positive dynamics satisfy most formal consistency requirements and enable a systematic treatment of quantum backreaction, but they also give rise to features that challenge conventional physical intuition, such as the breakdown of conservation laws. To illustrate this issue, we consider a qubit interacting with a classical particle and demonstrate that the corresponding hybrid system violates angular momentum conservation despite the rotational symmetry of the underlying equations of motion. This provides an explicit example of a fully closed, rotationally invariant classical-quantum system with completely positive dynamics that violates a conservation law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15291v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Hotta, Sebastian Murk, Daniel R. Terno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rabi transport and the other finite-size effects in one-dimensional discrete-time topological quantum walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19523v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates Rabi transport and finite-size effects in one-dimensional discrete-time topological quantum walks. We demonstrate the emergence of localized states at boundaries between topologically distinct phases and analyze how finite system sizes influence quantum walk dynamics. For finite lattices, we show that topology induces localized and bilocalized states, leading to Rabi-like transport as a result of degeneracy breaking due to finite-size effects. The study bridges the gap between topological protection and size-dependent dynamics, revealing transitions from ballistic motion to localized or oscillatory behavior based on the system's topological properties. Analytical and numerical methods are employed to explore the spectra and dynamics of quantum walks, highlighting the robustness of Rabi transport against disorder. The findings provide insights into controlled quantum transport and potential applications in quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19523v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Grudka, Marcin Karczewski, Pawe{\l} Kurzy\'nski, Tomasz P. Polak, Jan W\'ojcik, Antoni W\'ojcik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin Simulations Toolbox of the Nitrogen-Vacancy Center in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18759v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nitrogen-vacancy (NV) center in diamond is a crucial platform for quantum technologies, where its precise numerical modeling is indispensable for the continued advancement of the field. We present here a Python library for simulating the NV spin dynamics under general experimental conditions, i.e. a digital twin. Our library accounts for electromagnetic pulses and other environmental inputs, which are used to solve the system's time evolution, resulting in a physical output in the form of a quantum observable given by fluorescence. The simulation framework is based on a non-perturbative time-dependent Hamiltonian model, where the states initialization and readout are postulated from the interaction with optical fields. By eliminating oversimplifications such as the adoption of rotating frames for the microwave and radio frequency fields, our simulations reveal subtle dynamics emerging from realistic pulse constraints. The software is illustrated with three examples and validated by comparing the simulations with experimental reports, relevant to the fields of quantum computing (conditional logic gates), sensing (dynamical decoupling sequences with coupled spins) and networks (state teleportation). Overall, this digital twin delivers a robust numerical modeling of the NV spin dynamics, with simple and accessible usability, which can be used for a wide range of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18759v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Tsunaki, Anmol Singh, Sergei Trofimov, Boris Naydenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Krylov Subspace Diagonalization via Time Reversal Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22559v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Krylov quantum diagonalization methods have emerged as a promising use case for quantum computers. However, many existing implementations rely on controlled operations, which pose challenges to near-term quantum hardware. We introduce a novel protocol, termed Krylov Time Reversal (KTR), that circumvents these bottlenecks by leveraging time-reversal symmetry in Hamiltonian evolution. Using symmetric time dynamics, we show that it is possible to recover real-valued Krylov matrix elements, which significantly reduces the circuit depth and enhances compatibility with shallow quantum architectures. Furthermore, the protocol's structure indirectly reduces the total evolution time, benefiting both near-term and long-term architectures. We validate our method through numerical simulations on paradigmatic Hamiltonians exhibiting time-reversal symmetry, including the transverse-field Ising model and a lattice gauge theory, demonstrating accurate spectral estimation and favorable circuit constructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22559v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Mariella, Enrique Rico, Adam Byrne, Sergiy Zhuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapping an Atomic Ion using Time-Division Multiplexed Digital-to-Analog Converters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Independent control of numerous electrodes in quantum charge-coupled device architectures presents a significant challenge for wiring and hardware scalability. To address this issue, we demonstrate a voltage control method based on time-division multiplexing (TDM). This approach utilizes a single high-update-rate digital-to-analog converter (DAC) to sequentially generate control signals for multiple electrodes, thereby reducing both the number of required DACs and associated wiring. We experimentally validate this concept by developing a 10-channel system that operates with only two DACs. The developed TDM-based voltage control system is applied to a surface-electrode trap, where we successfully trap a single $^{40}\mathrm{Ca}^+$ ion and demonstrate a simple ion transport primitive. This approach offers a resource-efficient and scalable solution for advanced quantum computing systems based on trapped ions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04093v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryutaro Ohira, Masanari Miyamoto, Shinichi Morisaka, Ippei Nakamura, Atsushi Noguchi, Utako Tanaka, Takefumi Miyoshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum teleportation over thermal microwave network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14691v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum communication in the microwave regime is set to play an important role in distributed quantum computing and hybrid quantum networks. However, typical superconducting quantum circuits require millikelvin temperatures for operation, which poses a significant challenge for largescale microwave quantum networks. Here, we present a solution to this challenge by demonstrating the successful quantum teleportation of microwave coherent states between two spatially-separated dilution refrigerators over a thermal microwave channel in the temperature range up to $4$ K. We distribute two-mode squeezed states over this noisy channel and employ the resulting quantum entanglement for quantum teleportation of coherent states with fidelities of $72.3 \pm 0.5 ~\%$ at $1$ K and $59.9 \pm 2.5 \%$ at $4$ K, exceeding the no-cloning and classical communication thresholds, respectively. We successfully model the teleportation protocol using a Gaussian operator formalism that includes losses and noise. Our analysis shows that the teleportation infidelity mainly stems from a parasitic heating of the cold quantum nodes due to the hot network connection. These results demonstrate the experimental feasibility of distributed superconducting architectures and motivate further investigations of noisy quantum networks in various frequency regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14691v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. K. Yam, S. Gandorfer, F. Fesquet, M. Handschuh, K. E. Honasoge, A. Marx, R. Gross, K. G. Fedorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Simulations of Low Magic Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20252v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop classical simulation algorithms for adaptive quantum circuits that produce states with low levels of ``magic'' (i.e., non-stabilizerness). These algorithms are particularly well-suited to circuits with high rates of Pauli measurements, such as those encountered in quantum error correction and monitored quantum circuits. The measurements serve to limit the buildup of magic induced by non-Clifford operations arising from generic noise processes or unitary gates, respectively. Our algorithms also allow a systematic truncation procedure to achieve approximate simulation. To benchmark our approach, we study the dynamics of all-to-all monitored quantum circuits with a sub-extensive rate of T-gates per unit of circuit depth, where we can simulate previously inaccessible system sizes and depths. We characterize measurement-induced phase transitions in the output wavefunction, including in the entanglement, purification, and magic. We outline the utility of our algorithms to simulate dynamics with low magic and high entanglement, complementary to the leading matrix-product state approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20252v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kemal Aziz, Haining Pan, Michael J. Gullans, J. H. Pixley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Work Extraction from Finite-Time Closed Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20512v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Extracting useful work from quantum systems is a fundamental problem in quantum thermodynamics. In scenarios where rapid protocols are desired -- whether due to practical constraints or deliberate design choices -- a fundamental trade-off between power and efficiency is yet to be established. Here, we investigate the problem of finite-time optimal work extraction from closed quantum systems, subject to a constraint on the magnitude of the control Hamiltonian. We first reveal the trade-off relation between power and work under a general setup, stating that these fundamental performance metrics cannot be maximized simultaneously. We then introduce a general framework based on Lie algebras, which involves a wide range of control problems such as many-body control of the Heisenberg model and the SU(n)-Hubbard model. This framework enables us to reduce the optimal work extraction problem to an analytically or numerically efficiently tractable form. The resulting optimal protocol turns out to be remarkably simple: it suffices to use a time-independent control Hamiltonian in the interaction picture, determined by a nonlinear self-consistent equation. By exploiting the Lie-algebraic structure of the controllable terms, our approach is applicable to quantum many-body systems with an efficient numerical computation. Our results highlight the necessity of rapid protocols to achieve the maximum power and establish a theoretical framework for designing optimal work extraction protocols under realistic time constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20512v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoki Sugimoto, Takahiro Sagawa, Ryusuke Hamazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certification of energy-restricted entanglement depth with simple measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06726v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The certification of entanglement in multipartite scenarios is crucial for the advancement of quantum technologies, particularly for the realization of large-scale quantum networks. Here, we introduce a method to certify entanglement in ensembles of quantum states with limited energy based on a state discrimination game played by multiple distant and uncharacterized parties. This game exhibits a hierarchy in its optimal success probability, which depends strictly on the entanglement structure of the underlying ensemble. On the other hand, the game can be optimally won using a single, fixed measurement setting shared by all parties, regardless of the specific entanglement structure. We further demonstrate that both the performance and noise robustness of our method improve in the multipartite regime, scaling exponentially with the number of parties. Consequently, our approach enables the exclusion of entire separability classes, thereby certifying the depth of multipartite entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06726v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carles Roch I Carceller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Dynamics of High-Fidelity Two-Qubit Gates with Electrons on Helium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13946v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Systems of individual electrons electrostatically trapped on condensed noble gas surfaces have recently attracted considerable interest as potential platforms for quantum computing. The electrons form the qubits of the system, and the purity of the noble gas surface protects the relevant quantum properties of each electron. Previous work has indicated that manipulation of a confining double-well potential for electrons on superfluid helium can generate entanglement suitable for two-qubit gate operations. In this work, we incorporate a time-dependent tuning of the potential shape to further explore operation of two-qubit gates with the superfluid helium system. Through numerical time evolution, we show that fast, high-fidelity two-qubit gates can be achieved. In particular, we simulate operation of the $\sqrt{i\mathrm{SWAP}}$ and CZ gates and obtain fidelities of 0.999 and 0.996 with execution times of 2.9 ns and 9.4 ns, respectively. Furthermore, we examine the stability of these gate fidelities under non-ideal execution conditions, which reveals new properties to consider in the device design. With the insights gained from this work, we believe that an experimental realization of two-qubit gates using electrons on helium is feasible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13946v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oskar Leinonen, Jonas B. Flaten, Stian D. Bilek, {\O}yvind S. Sch{\o}yen, Morten Hjorth-Jensen, Niyaz R. Beysengulov, Zachary J. Stewart, Jared D. Weidman, Angela K. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric optimization for quantum communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15106v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Determining the ultimate limits of quantum communication, such as the quantum capacity of a channel and the distillable entanglement of a shared state, remains a central challenge in quantum information theory, primarily due to the phenomenon of superadditivity. This work develops Riemannian optimization methods to establish significantly tighter, computable two-sided bounds on these fundamental quantities. For upper bounds, our method systematically searches for state and channel extensions that minimize known information-theoretic bounds. We achieve this by parameterizing the space of all possible extensions as a Stiefel manifold, enabling a universal search that overcomes the limitations of ad-hoc constructions. Combined with an improved upper bound on the one-way distillable entanglement based on a refined continuity bound on quantum conditional entropy, our approach yields new state-of-the-art upper bounds on the quantum capacity of the qubit depolarizing channel for large values of the depolarizing parameter, strictly improving the previously best-known bounds. For lower bounds, we introduce Riemannian optimization methods to compute multi-shot coherent information. We establish lower bounds on the one-way distillable entanglement by parameterizing quantum instruments on the unitary manifold, and on the quantum capacity by parameterizing code states with a product of unitary manifolds. Numerical results for noisy entangled states and different channels demonstrate that our methods successfully unlock superadditive gains, improving previous results. Together, these findings establish Riemannian optimization as a principled and powerful tool for navigating the complex landscape of quantum communication limits. Furthermore, we prove that amortization does not enhance the channel coherent information, thereby closing a potential avenue for improving capacity lower bounds in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15106v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengkai Zhu, Hongyu Mao, Kun Fang, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability-Phase Mutual Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01104v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building on the geometric formulation of quantum mechanics, we develop a coherence theory for ensembles that exploits the probability-phase structure of the quantum state space. Standard coherence measures quantify superposition within density matrices but cannot distinguish ensembles that produce the same mixed state through different distributions of pure states. First, we introduce the probability-phase mutual information $I(P;\Phi)$, which measures statistical correlations between measurement-accessible probabilities and measurement-inaccessible phases across an ensemble. Then, we prove this satisfies the axioms of a coherence monotone, establishing it as a bona-fide measure of ensemble-level coherence. Eventually, through the definition of the \emph{coherence surplus} $\delta_{\mathcal{C}} \geq 0$, we show how ensemble coherence relates to, but exceeds, density-matrix coherence, thus quantifying structure lost in statistical averaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01104v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cameron Hahn, Nishan Ranabhat, Fabio Anza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital quantum simulation of many-body localization crossover in a disordered kicked Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01983v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simulating nonequilibrium dynamics of quantum many-body systems is one of the most promising applications of quantum computers. However, a faithful digital quantum simulation of the Hamiltonian evolution is very challenging in the present noisy quantum devices. Instead, nonequilibrium dynamics under the Floquet evolution realized by the Trotter decomposition of the Hamiltonian evolution with a large Trotter step size is considered to be a suitable problem for simulating in the present or near-term quantum devices. In this work, we propose simulating the many-body localization crossover as such a nonequilibrium problem in the disordered Floquet many-body systems. As a demonstration, we simulate the many-body localization crossover in a disordered kicked Ising model on a heavy-hex lattice using $60$ qubits from $156$ qubits available in the IBM Heron r2 superconducting qubit device named ibm\_fez. We compute out-of-time-ordered correlators as an indicator of the many-body localization crossover. From the late-time behavior of out-of-time-ordered correlators, we locate the quantum chaotic and many-body localized regimes as a function of the disorder strength. The validity of the results is confirmed by comparing two independent error mitigation methods, that is, the operator renormalization method and zero-noise extrapolation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01983v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Hayata, Kazuhiro Seki, Seiji Yunoki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The NPA hierarchy does not always attain the commuting operator value</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that it is undecidable to determine whether the commuting operator value of a nonlocal game is strictly greater than 1/2. As a corollary, there is a boolean constraint system (BCS) game for which the value of the Navascu\'es-Pironio-Ac\'in (NPA) hierarchy does not attain the commuting operator value at any finite level. Our contribution involves establishing a computable mapping from Turing machines to BCS nonlocal games in which the halting property of the machine is encoded as a decision problem for the commuting operator value of the game. Our techniques are algebraic and distinct from those used to establish MIP*=RE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04943v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Fanizza, Larissa Kroell, Arthur Mehta, Connor Paddock, Denis Rochette, William Slofstra, Yuming Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Limits on the Provable Consequences of Quantum Pseudorandomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05393v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There are various notions of quantum pseudorandomness, such as pseudorandom unitaries (PRUs), pseudorandom state generators (PRSGs) and pseudorandom function-like state generators (PRSFGs). Unlike the different notions of classical pseudorandomness, which are known to be existentially equivalent to each other, the relation between quantum pseudorandomness has yet to be fully established.
  We present some evidence suggesting that some quantum pseudorandomness is unlikely to be constructed from the others, or at least is hard to construct unless some conjectures are false. This indicates that quantum pseudorandomness could behave quite differently from classical pseudorandomness. We study new oracle worlds where one quantum pseudorandomness exists but another pseudorandomness does not under some assumptions or constraints, and provide potential directions to achieve the full black-box separation. More precisely:
  - We give a unitary oracle relative to which PRFSGs exist but PRUs without using ancilla do not. This can be extended to the general PRUs if we can prove a structural property of the PRU algorithm.
  - Assuming an isoperimetric inequality-style conjecture, we show a unitary oracle world where log-length output PRFSGs exist but proving the existence of quantum-computable pseudorandom generators (QPRGs) with negligible correctness error is as hard as proving that ${\sf BQP}\neq {\sf QCMA}$. This result suggests that the inverse-polynomial error in the state of the art construction of QPRGs from log-length PRSGs is inherent.
  - Assuming the same conjecture, we prove that some natural way of constructing super-log-length output PRSGs from log-length output PRFSGs is impossible. This partly complements the known hardness of shrinking the PRSG output lengths. Along the way, we also discuss other potential approaches to extend the PRSG output lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05393v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Bouaziz--Ermann, Minki Hhan, Garazi Muguruza, Quoc-Huy Vu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum $f$-divergences and Their Local Behaviour: An Analysis via Relative Expansion Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Any reasonable measure of distinguishability of quantum states must satisfy a data processing inequality, that is, it must not increase under the action of a quantum channel. We can ask about the proportion of information lost or preserved and this leads us to study contraction and expansion coefficients respectively, which can be combined into a single \emph{relative expansion coefficient}. We focus on two prominent families: (i) standard quantum $f$ divergences and (ii) their local (second-order) behaviour, which induces a monotone Riemannian semi-norm (that is linked to the $\chi^2$ divergence). Building on prior work, we identify new families of $f$ for which the global ($f$ divergence) and local (Riemannian) relative expansion coefficients coincide for every pair of channels, and we clarify how exceptional such exact coincidences are. Beyond equality, we introduce an \emph{equivalence} framework that transfers qualitative properties such as strict positivity uniformly across different relative expansion coefficients.
  Leveraging the link between equality in the data processing inequality (DPI) and channel reversibility, we apply our framework of relative expansion coefficients to approximate recoverability of quantum information. Using our relative expansion results for primitive channels, we prove a reverse quantum Markov convergence theorem, converting positive expansion coefficients into quantitative lower bounds on the convergence rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06183v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreyas Iyer, Peixue Wu, Paula Belzig, Graeme Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular interface for efficient optical readout of diamond quantum memory at cryogenic temperatures via single-mode optical fibers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07032v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficient quantum devices across various physical systems have been rapidly developed for entanglement-based quantum repeaters and spin-photon conversion; however, far less attention has been paid to standardizing platforms through quantum memory optical interfaces. We present a modular interface for color centers in diamond that is structurally isolated from device-and temperature-related variation. Despite a more than 100-fold reduction in confocal volume, we achieve highly efficient photon collection through single-mode optical fibers, including zero-phonon line spectroscopy, at both room and cryogenic temperatures. These results establish a standardized minimal NV-center-based platform and pave the way for construction of scalable quantum infrastructure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07032v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akira Kamimaki, Yuhei Sekiguchi, Daisuke Ito, Taichi Fujiwara, Toshiharu Makino, Hiromitsu Kato, Hideo Kosaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How hard is it to verify a classical shadow?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08515v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Classical shadows are succinct classical representations of quantum states which allow one to encode a set of properties P of a quantum state rho, while only requiring measurements on logarithmically many copies of rho in the size of P. In this work, we initiate the study of verification of classical shadows, denoted classical shadow validity (CSV), from the perspective of computational complexity, which asks: Given a classical shadow S, how hard is it to verify that S predicts the measurement statistics of a quantum state? We first show that even for the elegantly simple classical shadow protocol of [Huang, Kueng, Preskill, Nature Physics 2020] utilizing local Clifford measurements, CSV is QMA-complete. This hardness continues to hold for the high-dimensional extension of said protocol due to [Mao, Yi, and Zhu, PRL 2025]. In contrast, we show that for the HKP and MYZ protocols utilizing global Clifford measurements, CSV can be "dequantized" for low-rank observables, i.e., solved in randomized poly-time with standard sampling assumptions. Among other results, we also show that CSV for exponentially many observables is complete for a quantum generalization of the second level of the polynomial hierarchy, yielding the first natural complete problem for such a class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08515v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Karaiskos, Dorian Rudolph, Johannes Jakob Meyer, Jens Eisert, Sevag Gharibian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast CZ Gate via Energy-Level Engineering in Superconducting Qubits with a Tunable Coupler</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In superconducting quantum circuits, decoherence errors in qubits constitute a critical factor limiting quantum gate performance. To mitigate decoherence-induced gate infidelity, rapid implementation of quantum gates is essential. Here we propose a scheme for rapid controlled-Z (CZ) gate implementation through energy-level engineering, which leverages Rabi oscillations between the |11&gt; state and the superposition state in a tunable-coupler architecture. Numerical simulations achieved a 17 ns nonadiabatic CZ gate with fidelity over 99.99%. We further investigated the performance of the CZ gate in the presence of anharmonicity offsets. The results demonstrate that a high-fidelity CZ gate with an error rate below 10^-4 remains achievable even with finite anharmonicity variations. Furthermore, the detrimental impact of spectator qubits in different quantum states on the fidelity of CZ gate is effectively suppressed by incorporating a tunable coupler. This scheme exhibits potential for extending the circuit execution depth constrained by coherence time limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09461v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benzheng Yuan, Chaojie Zhang, Chuanbing Han, Shuya Wang, Peng Xu, Huihui Sun, Qing Mu, Lixin Wang, Bo Zhao, Weilong Wang, Zheng Shan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement detection in quantum materials with competing orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12931v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate entanglement detection in quantum materials through criteria based on the simultaneous suppression of collective matter excitations. Unlike other detection schemes, these criteria can be applied to continuous and unbounded variables. By considering a system of interacting dipoles on a lattice, we show the detection of collective entanglement arising from two different physical mechanisms, namely, the ferroelectric ordering and the dressing of matter degrees of freedom by light. In the latter case, the detection shows the formation of a collective entangled phase not directly related to spontaneous symmetry breaking. These results open a new perspective for the entanglement characterization of competing orders in quantum materials, and have direct application to quantum paraelectrics with large polariton splittings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12931v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L100302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L100302 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Mazza, Costantino Budroni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Phases of Many-Body Localized Systems: Beyond Eigenstate Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00825v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many-body localization (MBL) lends remarkable robustness to nonequilibrium phases of matter. Such phases can show topological and symmetry breaking order in their ground and excited states, but they may also belong to an anomalous localized topological phase (ALT phase). All eigenstates in an ALT phase are trivial, in that they can be deformed to product states, but the entire Hamiltonian cannot be deformed to a trivial localized model without going through a delocalization transition. Using a correspondence between MBL phases with short-ranged entanglement and locality preserving unitaries - called quantum cellular automata (QCA) - we reduce the classification of ALT phases to that of QCA. This method extends to periodically (Floquet) and quasiperiodically driven ALT phases, and captures anomalous Floquet phases within the same framework as static phases. We considerably develop the study of the topology of QCA, allowing us to classify static and driven ALT phases in low dimensions. The QCA framework further generalizes to include symmetry-enriched ALT phases (SALT phases) - which we also classify in low dimensions - and provides a large class of soluble models suitable for realization in quantum simulators. In systematizing the study of ALT phases, we both greatly extend the classification of interacting nonequilibrium systems and clarify a confusion in the literature which implicitly equates nontrivial Hamiltonians with nontrivial ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00825v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/77j6-g4jz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134206 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David M. Long, Dominic V. Else</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$m$-step rational extensions of the trigonometric Darboux-P\"{o}schl-Teller potential based on para-Jacobi polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05003v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A previous construction of regular rational extensions of the trigonometric Darboux-P\"oschl-Teller potential, obtained by one-step Darboux transformations using seed functions associated with the para-Jacobi polynomials of Calogero and Yi, is generalized by considering $m$-step Darboux transformations. As a result, some novel families of exceptional orthogonal polynomials depending on $m$ discrete parameters, as well as $m$ continuous real ones $\lambda_1$, $\lambda_2$, \ldots, $\lambda_m$, are obtained. The restrictions imposed on these parameters by the rational extensions regularity conditions are studied in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05003v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 66 (2025) 102101</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yves Grandati, Christiane Quesne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crosscap Quenches and Entanglement Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18610v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the mechanisms by which complex correlations emerge through the dynamics of quantum many-body systems remains a fundamental challenge in modern physics. To address this, quench dynamics starting from nonthermal states have been extensively studied, leading to significant progress. In this paper, we propose a novel quench protocol, termed the "crosscap quench", to investigate how highly structured thermal pure states relax into typical ones. We begin by analyzing conformal field theories (CFTs) and derive universal features in the time evolution of the entanglement entropy. Furthermore, leveraging the AdS/CFT correspondence, we study holographic CFTs, providing an analytically tractable example in chaotic CFTs. Finally, we validate these findings through numerical simulations in both nonintegrable and integrable quantum spin systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18610v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixia Wei, Yasushi Yoneta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable bi-frequency spinor modes as Dark Matter candidates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04027v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that spinor systems with scalar self-interaction, such as the Dirac--Klein--Gordon system with Yukawa coupling or the Soler model, generically have bi-frequency solitary wave solutions. We develop the approach to stability properties of such waves and use the radial reduction to show that indeed the (linear) stability is available for a wide range of parameters. We show that only bi-frequency modes can be dynamically stable and suggest that stable bi-frequency modes can serve as storages of the Dark Matter. The approach is based on linear stability results of one-frequency solitary waves in (3+1)D Soler model, which we obtain as a by-product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04027v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)082</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics 2025, article number 82 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Comech, Niranjana Kulkarni, Nabile Boussa\"id, Jes\'us Cuevas-Maraver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractal-enriched mobility edges and emergent quantum phases in Rydberg atomic arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07866v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Anderson localization describes disorder-induced phase transitions, distinguishing between localized and extended states. In quasiperiodic systems, a third multifractal state emerges, characterized by unique energy and wave functions. However, the corresponding multifractal-enriched mobility edges and three-state-coexisting quantum phases have yet to be experimentally detected. In this work, we propose exactly-solvable one-dimensional quasiperiodic lattice models that simultaneously host three-state-coexisting quantum phases, with their phase boundaries analytically derived via Avila's global theorem. Furthermore, we propose experimental protocols via Rydberg atom arrays to realize these states. Notably, we demonstrate a spectroscopic technique capable of measuring inverse participation ratios across real-space and dual-space domains, enabling simultaneous characterization of localized, extended, and multifractal quantum phases in systems with up to tens of qubits. Our work opens new avenues for the experimental exploration of Anderson localization and multifractal states in artificial quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07866v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-025-2774-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. China-Phys. Mech. Astron. 69, 217212 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shan-Zhong Li, Yi-Cai Zhang, Yucheng Wang, Shanchao Zhang, Shi-Liang Zhu, Zhi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global symmetries of quantum lattice models under non-invertible dualities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12514v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-invertible dualities/symmetries have become an important tool in the study of quantum field theories and quantum lattice models in recent years. One of the most studied examples is non-invertible dualities obtained by gauging a discrete group. When the physical system has more global symmetries than the gauged symmetry, it has not been thoroughly investigated how those global symmetries transform under non-invertible duality. In this paper, we study the change of global symmetries under non-invertible duality of gauging a discrete group $G$ in the context of (1+1)-dimensional quantum lattice models. We obtain the global symmetries of the dual model by focusing on different Hilbert space sectors determined by the $\mathrm{Rep}(G)$ symmetry. We provide general conjectures of global symmetries of the dual model forming an algebraic ring of the double cosets. We present concrete examples of the XXZ models and the duals, providing strong evidence for the conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12514v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhysCore.8.4.070</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. Core 8, 070 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Weiguang Cao, Yuan Miao, Masahito Yamazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metaplectic operators with quasi-diagonal kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05089v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Metaplectic operators form a relevant class of operators appearing in different applications, in the present work we study their Schwartz kernels. Namely, diagonality of a kernel is defined by imposing rapid off-diagonal decay conditions, and quasi-diagonality by imposing the same conditions on the smoothing of the kernel through convolution with the Gaussian. Kernels of metaplectic operators are not diagonal. Nevertheless, as we shall prove, they are quasi-diagonal under suitable conditions. Motivation for our study comes from problems in time-frequency analysis, that we discuss in the last section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05089v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Giacchi, Luigi Rodino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space-based cm/kg-scale Laser Interferometer for Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12899v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The experimental verification of the quantum nature of gravity represents a milestone in quantum gravity research. Recently, interest has grown for testing it via gravitationally induced entanglement (GIE). Here, we propose a space-based interferometer inspired by the LISA Pathfinder (LPF). Our design employs two kg-scale gold-platinum test masses which, unlike in the LPF, are surrounded by a shield below 1 K and positioned side-by-side with a centimeter-scale separation. This configuration enables the detection of GIE through simultaneous measurements of differential and common-mode motions. To estimate the integration time required for GIE detection, we simulate quantum measurements of these modes, considering noise sources such as gas damping, black-body radiation, and cosmic-ray collisions. Our results show that GIE can be demonstrated with a few modifications to the LPF setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12899v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nobuyuki Matsumoto, Katsuta Sakai, Kosei Hatakeyama, Kiwamu Izumi, Daisuke Miki, Satoshi Iso, Akira Matsumura, Kazuhiro Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the spatial distribution of k-vectors in situ with Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19157v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a novel method for mapping \textit{in situ} the spatial distribution of photon momentum across a laser beam using a Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC) as a moving probe. By displacing the BEC, we measure the photon recoil by atom interferometry at different positions in the laser beam and thus reconstruct a two-dimensional map of the local intensity and effective dispersion of the $k$ wave vector. Applied to a beam diffracted by a diaphragm, this method reveals a local \textit{extra recoil} effect, which exceeds the magnitude $h\nu/c$ of the individual plane-waves over which the beam can be decomposed. This method offers a new way to precisely characterize wavefront distortions and to evaluate one of the major systematic bias sources in quantum sensors based on atom interferometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19157v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Gaudout, Rayan Si-Ahmed, Cl\'ement Debavelaere, Menno Door, Pierre Clad\'e, Sa\"ida Guellati-Khelifa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric entanglers for non-invertible SPT phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04581v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been suggested that non-invertible symmetry protected topological phases (SPT), due to the lack of a stacking structure, do not have symmetric entanglers (globally symmetric finite-depth quantum circuits) connecting them. Using topological holography, we argue that a symmetric entangler should in fact exist for $1+1$d systems whenever the non-invertible symmetry has SPT phases connected by fixed-charge dualities (FCD). Moreover, we construct an explicit example of a symmetric entangler for the two SPT phases with $\mathrm{Rep}(A_4)$-symmetry, as a matrix product unitary (MPU).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04581v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minyoung You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Limited Acoustoelectric Amplification in a Piezoelectric-2DEG Heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09248v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a quantum mechanical description of phonon amplification in a heterostructure consisting of a two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) stacked on top of a piezoelectric material. An applied drift voltage effectively creates a population inversion in the momentum states of the 2DEG electrons, giving rise to spontaneous emission of phonons. Once an acoustic wave is launched, the pumped electrons release phonons via stimulated emission, returning to depleted ground states before being pumped back to the excited states. We show that whereas efficient amplification using a 1D electron gas requires the acoustic wavelength to roughly equal the average electron-electron spacing, a 2DEG enables efficient amplification for any wavelength greater than the average electron-electron spacing. We derive the imaginary and real parts of the 2DEG first-order acoustic susceptibility as functions of electronic drift velocity in specific limits and derive the gain per unit length for the signal and the quantum noise, with the gain matching the classical result in the short-electronic-lifetime (low-mobility) regime. Moreover, we analyze the gain clamping due to pump depletion and calculate the maximum achievable intensity. Our results provide a framework for designing novel acoustic devices including a quantum phononic laser and phase-insensitive quantum phononic amplifiers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09248v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Chatterjee, Daniel Soh, Matt Eichenfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
