<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 04:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating Interpretation Bias in Rock Records with Large Language Models: Insights from Paleoenvironmental Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The reconstruction of Earth's history faces significant challenges due to the nonunique interpretations often derived from rock records. The problem has long been recognized but there are no systematic solutions in practice. This study introduces an innovative approach that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) along with retrieval augmented generation and real-time search capabilities to counteract interpretation biases, thereby enhancing the accuracy and reliability of geological analyses. By applying this framework to sedimentology and paleogeography, we demonstrate its effectiveness in mitigating interpretations biases through the generation and evaluation of multiple hypotheses for the same data, which can effectively reduce human bias. Our research illuminates the transformative potential of LLMs in refining paleoenvironmental studies and extends their applicability across various sub-disciplines of Earth sciences, enabling a deeper and more accurate depiction of Earth's evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09977v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luoqi Wang, Haipeng Li, Linshu Hu, Jiarui Cai, Zhenhong Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a multi-physics multi-scale approach of deep geothermal exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A wide range of geophysical methods is used for the exploration of deep geothermal resources. It aimsat characterizing the deep fractured network and its capacity for fluid/heat extraction. This relieshowever on the capacity of geophysical techniques to 1) image the geometry of the fractured networkbut also 2) characterize the petro-physical properties of the fracture network and matrix. The challengeis however that the geophysical inverse problem is ill-posed and multi-scale.To overcome these challenges, we propose here to take a multi-physics and multi-scale approach of thegeophysical/petro-physical inverse problem. To do so, we are developing iteratively petro-physical andgeophysical models that can explain the observables at the different scales. In this paper, we report outthe results of the first iteration phase of this research project that consists in building an initial petrophysical model from well logs and prior geological knowledge, and single-domain inversion ofgeophysical data. We applied this methodology to the Upper Rhine Graben where a wealth ofknowledge and dataset on deep fractured formations are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10493v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3997/2214-4609.202321051</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Fourth EAGE Global Energy Transition Conference and Exhibition, Nov 2023, Paris, France. pp.1-5</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Darnet (BRGM), S. Vedrine (BRGM), F. Bretaudeau (BRGM), S. Marc (BRGM), L. Capar (BRGM), Joshua Pwavodi (ITES), G. Marquis (ITES), A. Montegud (CGG), J. Formento (CGG), V. Maurer (ES G\'eothermie), C. Glass (ES G\'eothermie), E. Delmais (ES G\'eothermie), A. Genter (ES G\'eothermie)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Operator-Based Proxy for Reservoir Simulations Considering Varying Well Settings, Locations, and Permeability Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09728v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating Darcy flows in porous media is fundamental to understand the future flow behavior of fluids in hydrocarbon and carbon storage reservoirs. Geological models of reservoirs are often associated with high uncertainly leading to many numerical simulations for history matching and production optimization. Machine learning models trained with simulation data can provide a faster alternative to traditional simulators. In this paper we present a single Fourier Neural Operator (FNO) surrogate that outperforms traditional reservoir simulators by the ability to predict pressures and saturations on varying permeability fields, well locations, well controls, and number of wells. The maximum-mean relative error of 95\% of pressure and saturation predictions is less than 5\%. This is achieved by employing a simple yet very effective data augmentation technique that reduces the dataset size by 75\% and reduces overfitting. Also, constructing the input tensor in a binary fashion enables predictions on unseen well locations, well controls, and number of wells. Such model can accelerate history matching and reservoir characterization procedures by several orders of magnitude. The ability to predict on new well locations, well controls, and number of wells enables highly efficient reservoir management and optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09728v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Badawi, Eduardo Gildin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axisymmetric displacement flows in fluid-driven fractures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10375v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Displacement flows are common in hydraulic fracturing, as fracking fluids of different composition are injected sequentially in the fracture. The injection of an immiscible fluid at the center of a liquid-filled fracture results in the growth of the fracture and the outward displacement of the interface between the two liquids. We study the dynamics of the fluid-driven fracture which is controlled by the competition between viscous, elastic, and toughness-related stresses. We use a model experiment to characterize the dynamics of the fracture for a range of mechanical properties of the fractured material and fracturing fluids. We form the liquid-filled pre-fracture in an elastic brittle matrix of gelatin. The displacing liquid is then injected. We record the radius and aperture of the fracture, and the position of the interface between the two liquids. In a typical experiment, the axisymmetric radial viscous flow is accommodated by the elastic deformation and fracturing of the matrix. We model the coupling between elastic deformation, viscous dissipation, and fracture propagation and recover the two fracturing regimes identified for single fluid injection. For the viscous-dominated and toughness-dominated regimes, we derive scaling equations that describe the crack growth due to a displacement flow and show the influence of the pre-existing fracture on the crack dynamics through a finite initial volume and an average viscosity of the fluid in the fracture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10375v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2022.954</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Fluid Mechanics. 2022;953:A36</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sri Savya Tanikella, Emilie Dressaire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of fluid-driven fractures in the viscous-dominated regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10384v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: During hydraulic fracturing, the injection of a pressurized fluid in a brittle elastic medium leads to the formation and growth of fluid-filled fractures. A disc-like or penny-shaped fracture grows radially from a point source during the injection of a viscous fluid at a constant flow rate. We report an experimental study on the dynamics of fractures propagating in the viscous regime. We measure the fracture aperture and radius over time for varying mechanical properties of the medium and fluid and different injection parameters. Our experiments show that the fracture continues to expand in an impermeable brittle matrix, even after the injection stops. {In the viscous regime, the fracture radius scales as $t^{4/9}$ during the injection. Post shut-in, the crack continues to propagate at a slower rate, which agrees well with the predictions of the scaling arguments, as the radius scales as $t^{1/9}$. The fracture finally reaches an equilibrium set by the toughness of the material.} The results provide insights into the propagation of hydraulic fractures in rocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10384v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1098/rspa.2022.0460</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. R. Soc. A.479: 20220460 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sri Savya Tanikella, Marie C Sigallon, Emilie Dressaire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting and Attributing Change in Climate and Complex Systems: Foundations, Green's Functions, and Nonlinear Fingerprints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.02628v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detection and attribution (D&amp;A) studies are cornerstones of climate science, providing crucial evidence for policy decisions. Their goal is to link observed climate change patterns to anthropogenic and natural drivers via the optimal fingerprinting method (OFM). We show that response theory for nonequilibrium systems offers the physical and dynamical basis for OFM, including the concept of causality used for attribution. Our framework clarifies the method's assumptions, advantages, and potential weaknesses. We use our theory to perform D&amp;A for prototypical climate change experiments performed on an energy balance model and on a low-resolution coupled climate model. We also explain the underpinnings of degenerate fingerprinting, which offers early warning indicators for tipping points. Finally, we extend the OFM to the nonlinear response regime. Our analysis shows that OFM has broad applicability across diverse stochastic systems influenced by time-dependent forcings, with potential relevance to ecosystems, quantitative social sciences, and finance, among others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.02628v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Lucarini, Micka\"el Chekroun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and stability of biomolecules in C-H-O-N fluids at extreme pressure-temperature conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04839v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: How life started on Earth is an unsolved mystery. There are various hypotheses for the location ranging from outer space to the seafloor, subseafloor or potentially deeper. Here, we applied extensive ab initio molecular dynamics (AIMD) simulations to study chemical reactions between NH3, H2O, H2, and CO at pressures (P) and temperatures (T) approximating the conditions of Earth's upper mantle (i.e. 10-13 GPa, 1000-1400 K). Contrary to the previous assumptions that larger organic molecules might readily disintegrate in aqueous solutions at extreme P-T conditions, we found that many organic compounds formed without any catalysts and persisted in C-H-O-N fluids under these extreme conditions, including glycine, ribose, urea, and uracil-like molecules. Particularly, our free energy calculations showed that the C-N bond is thermodynamically stable at 10 GPa and 1400 K. Moreover, while the pyranose (six-membered-ring) form of ribose is more stable than the furanose (five-membered-ring) form at ambient conditions, we observed the predominant formation of the five-membered-ring form of ribose at extreme conditions, which is consistent with the exclusive incorporation of \{beta}-D-ribofuranose in RNA. We have uncovered a previously unexplored pathway through which the building blocks of biomolecules may have originated in early Earth and other planets. Our findings contribute to an evolving understanding of the fundamental conditions necessary for life to arise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04839v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Li, Nore Stolte, Renbiao Tao, Dimitri A. Sverjensky, Isabelle Daniel, Ding Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
