<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 04:00:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Energy Balance of a Hydraulic Fracture at Depth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We detail the energy balance of a propagating hydraulic fracture. Using the linear hydraulic fracture model which combines lubrication flow and linear elastic fracture mechanics, we demonstrate how different propagation regimes are related to the dominance of a given term of the power balance of a growing hydraulic fracture. Taking an energy point of view allows us to offer a physical explanation of hydraulic fracture growth behaviours, such as, for example, the transition from viscosity to toughness dominated growth for a radial geometry, fracture propagation after the end of the injection or transition to self-buoyant elongated growth. We quantify the evolution of the different power terms for a series of numerical examples. We also discuss the order of magnitudes of the different terms for a industrial-like hydraulic fracturing treatment accounting for the additional dissipation in the injection line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05785v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Peruzzo, Andreas M\"ori, Brice Lecampion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-loop geothermal systems: Modeling and predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04716v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Geothermal energy is a sustainable baseload source recognized for its ability to provide clean energy on a large scale. Advanced Geothermal Systems (AGS) -- offer promising prototypes -- employ a closed-loop vascular layout that runs deep beneath the Earth's surface. A working fluid (e.g., water or supercritical carbon dioxide (sCO2)) circulates through the vasculature, entering the subsurface at the inlet and exiting at the outlet with an elevated temperature. For designing and performing cost-benefit analysis before deploying large-scale projects and maintaining efficiency while enabling real-time monitoring during the operational phase, modeling offers cost-effective solutions; often, it is the only available option for performance assessment. A knowledge gap exists due to the lack of a fast predictive modeling framework that considers the vascular intricacies, particularly the jumps in the solution fields across the channel. Noting that the channel diameter is considerably smaller in scale compared to the surrounding geological domain, we develop a reduced-order modeling (ROM) framework for closed-loop geothermal systems. This ROM incorporates the jump conditions and provides a quick and accurate prediction of the temperature field, including the outlet temperature, which directly correlates with the power production capacity and thermal draw-down. We demonstrate the predictive capabilities of the framework by establishing the uniqueness of the solutions and reporting representative numerical solutions. The modeling framework and the predictions reported in this paper benefit the closed-loop geothermal community, enabling them to determine the system's performance and optimal capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04716v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Adhikari, M. K. Mudunuru, K. B. Nakshatrala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microstructural and Micromechanical Evolution of Olivine Aggregates During Transient Creep</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04982v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To examine the microstructural evolution that occurs during transient creep, we deformed olivine aggregates to different strains that spanned the initial transient deformation. Two sets of samples with different initial grain sizes of 5 $\mu$m and 20 $\mu$m were deformed in torsion at T = 1523 K, P = 300 MPa, and a constant shear strain rate of 1.5 $\times$ 10$^{-4}$ s$^{-1}$. Both sets of samples experienced strain hardening during deformation. We characterized the microstructures at the end of each experiment using high-angular resolution electron backscatter diffraction (HR-EBSD) and dislocation decoration. In the coarse-grained samples, dislocation density increased from 1.5 $\times$ 10$^{11}$ m$^{-2}$ to 3.6 $\times$ 10$^{12}$ m$^{-2}$ with strain. Although the same final dislocation density was reached in the fine-grained samples, it did not vary significantly at small strains, potentially due to concurrent grain growth during deformation. In both sets of samples, HR-EBSD analysis revealed that intragranular stress heterogeneity increased in magnitude with strain and that elevated stresses are associated with regions of high geometrically necessary dislocation density. Further analysis of the stresses and their probability distributions indicate that the stresses are imparted by long-range elastic interactions among dislocations. These characteristics indicate that dislocation interactions were the primary cause of strain hardening during transient creep. A comparison of the results to predictions from three recent models reveals that the models do not correctly predict the evolution in stress and dislocation density with strain for our experiments due to a lack of previous such data in their calibrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04982v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harison S. Wiesman, Thomas Breithaupt, David Wallis, Lars N. Hansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling localized failure in geomaterials by large-deformation-plasticity periporomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large-deformation localized failure in geomaterials plays a crucial role in geohazards engineering. This article investigates shear bands and retrogressive failure of geomaterials through a recently formulated large-deformation-plasticity periporomechanics (PPM) paradigm. Periporomechanics is a nonlocal reformulation of classical poromechanics through the effective force and peridynamic state concepts. The nonlocal deformation gradient is multiplicatively decomposed into the elastic and plastic parts in this large-deformation PPM paradigm. The stabilized correspondence principle is adopted to implement a classical elastoplastic constitutive model into the new PPM paradigm. We have numerically implemented this large-deformation plasticity PPM paradigm through a Lagrangian meshfree method in space and an explicit Newmark scheme in time. The implemented PPM framework is used to model shear banding and retrogressive slope failure in porous media under dry conditions. The numerical results have demonstrated the efficacy and robustness of this new PPM paradigm for modeling shear banding and retrogressive failure involving large deformation in porous media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05129v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Song, Hossein Pashazad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential hybrid finite element and material point method to simulate slope failures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05185v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Numerical modeling of slope failures seeks to predict two key phenomena: the initiation of failure and the post-failure runout. Currently, most modeling methods for slope failure analysis excel at one of these two but are deficient in the other. For example, the Finite Element Method (FEM) models the initiation of instability well but quickly loses accuracy when modeling large deformations because of mesh distortion, restricting its ability to predict runout. Conversely, the Material Point Method (MPM) utilizes material points which move freely across a background grid, allowing for indefinite deformations without computational issues. However, MPM is restricted in its ability to model slope failure initiation due to limitations of the available boundary conditions and reduced accuracy of its stress distributions. The sequential hybridization of these two methods, initiating a model in FEM and then transferring to MPM, presents an opportunity to accurately capture both initiation and runout by a single model. The exact time for this transfer is not self-apparent, but it must be conducted after the initiation mechanism and before excessive mesh distortion. By simulating two granular column failures and two slope failures, we demonstrate the effectiveness of this hybrid FEM-MPM method and identify the appropriate time to transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05185v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.compgeo.2024.106525</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computers and Geotechnics (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Brent Sordo, Ellen Rathje, Krishna Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seismic monitoring using the telecom fiber network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Laser interferometry enables to remotely measure microscopical length changes of deployed telecommunication cables originating from earthquakes. Long range and compatibility with data traffic make it unique to the exploration of remote regions, as well as highly-populated areas where optical networks are pervasive, and its large-scale implementation is attractive for both Earth scientists and telecom operators. However, validation and modeling of its response and sensitivity are still at an early stage and suffer from lack of statistically-significant event catalogs and limited availability of co-located seismometers. We implemented laser interferometry on a land-based telecommunication cable and analyzed 1.5 years of continuous acquisition, with successful detections of events in a broad range of magnitudes, including very weak ones. By comparing fiber and seismometer recordings we determined relations between a cable's detection probability and the magnitude and distance of events, and showed that spectral analysis of recorded data allows considerations on the earthquake dynamics. Our results reveal that quantitative analysis is possible for this sensing technique and support the interpretation of data from the growing amount of interferometric deployments. We anticipate the high integration and scalability of laser interferometry into existing telecommunication grids to be useful for the daily seismicity monitoring, in perspective exploitable for civilian protection use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06203v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s43247-024-01338-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications Earth &amp; Environment 5, 178 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Simone Donadello, Cecilia Clivati, Aladino Govoni, Lucia Margheriti, Maurizio Vassallo, Daniele Brenda, Marianna Hovsepyan, Elio K. Bertacco, Roberto Concas, Filippo Levi, Alberto Mura, Andr\`e Herrero, Francesco Carpentieri, Davide Calonico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Directionality of Gravitational and Thermal Diffusive Transport in Geologic Fluid Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16659v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diffusive transport has implications for the long-term status of underground storage of hydrogen (H$_2$) fuel and carbon dioxide (CO$_2$), technologies which are being pursued to mitigate climate change and advance the energy transition. Once injected underground, CO$_2$ and H$_2$ will exist in multiphase fluid-water-rock systems: being partially-soluble, injected fluids can flow through the porous rack in a connected plume, become disconnected and trapped as ganglia surrounded by groundwater within the storage rock pore space, and also dissolve and migrate through the aqueous phase. Recent analyses have focused on the concentration gradients induced by differing capillary pressure between fluid ganglia which can drive diffusive transport ("Ostwald ripening"). However, studies have neglected or excessively simplified important factors; namely: the non-ideality of gases under geologic conditions, the opposing equilibrium state of dissolved CO$_2$ and H$_2$ driven by the partial molar density of dissolved solutes, and entropic and thermodiffusive effects resulting from geothermal gradients. We conduct an analysis from thermodynamic first principles and use this to provide numerical estimates at conditions relevant to underground storage reservoirs. We show that entropic contributions to the free energy are so significant as to cause a reversal in the direction of diffusive transport in systems with geothermal gradients. For CO$_2$, even geothermal gradients less than 10 C/km induce downwards diffusion at depths relevant to storage. Diffusive transport of H$_2$ is less affected, but still reverses direction under typical gradients. Contrary to previous studies, we find that in diffusion and convection will likely work in concert - both driving CO$_2$ downwards, and both driving H$_2$ upwards - for conditions representative of their respective storage reservoirs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16659v3</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Herring, Ruotong Huang, Adrian Sheppard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian geoacoustic inversion using mixture density network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.07902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2008.07902v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian geoacoustic inversion problems are conventionally solved by Markov chain Monte Carlo methods or its variants, which are computationally expensive. This paper extends the classic Bayesian geoacoustic inversion framework by deriving important geoacoustic statistics of Bayesian geoacoustic inversion from the multidimensional posterior probability density (PPD) using the mixture density network (MDN) theory. These statistics make it convenient to train the network directly on the whole parameter space and get the multidimensional PPD of model parameters. The present approach provides a much more efficient way to solve geoacoustic inversion problems in Bayesian inference framework. The network is trained on a simulated dataset of surface-wave dispersion curves with shear-wave velocities as labels and tested on both synthetic and real data cases. The results show that the network gives reliable predictions and has good generalization performance on unseen data. Once trained, the network can rapidly (within seconds) give a fully probabilistic solution which is comparable to Monte Carlo methods. It provides an promising approach for real-time inversion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2008.07902v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoli Wu, Jingya Zhang, Junqiang Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basal force fluctuations and granular rheology: Linking macroscopic descriptions of granular flows to bed forces with implications for monitoring signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10871v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Granular flows are ubiquitous in nature with single flows traversing a wide range of dynamic conditions from initiation to deposition. Many of these flows are responsible for significant hazards and have the ability to generate remotely detectable seismic signals. These signals provide a potential for real-time flow measurements from a safe distance. To fully realize the benefit of seismic measurements, basal granular forces must be linked to macroscopic internal flow dynamics across a wide range of flow conditions. We utilize discrete element simulations to observe dry and submerged granular flows under plane-shear and inclined flow configurations, relating bulk kinematics to basal force distributions. We find that force fluctuations scale with non-dimensional shear-rate ($I$), and this scaling tracks three flow regimes that can be described by $\mu(I)$ rheology, as well as a fourth regime that marks a `phase change' from a liquid-like to a gas-like state: (1) an unsteady particle rearrangement regime when $I&lt;10^{-3}$, where basal forces are dominated by low frequencies; (2) an intermediate regime when $10^{-3}&lt; I&lt;10^{-2}$, where basal forces start to become noise-like, (3) a transitional regime at $10^{-2}&lt;I&lt;10^{-1}$, where the increase in basal tractions with increasing shear-rates stalls as the granular bed dilates, partially destroying the contact network and memory stored in the particle contact network, and (4) a fully collisional regime when $I&gt;10^{-1}$, where the signal is nearly flat up to a cutoff frequency. This effort suggests that basal forces can be used to interpret complex granular processes in geophysical flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10871v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. J. Zrelak, Eric C. P. Breard, Josef Dufek</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
