<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 04:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Azimuthal imaging of rock fractures by incorporating single borehole radar and optical data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11350v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Single borehole radar detection suffers from azimuthal ambiguity, while borehole optical tests only provide information about the borehole wall. These limitations prevent either detection method from revealing the complete spatial patterns of rock fractures on their own. In this paper, we address these challenges by proposing a joint imaging method that combines the advantages of both borehole detection methods. Geological azimuthal parameters are extracted from optical images by fitting the fracture curves to sinusoidal functions. A 2D Kirchhoff time migration is then implemented using radar common offset gather. Up-dip and down-dip events are separated by the f-k transform or z-s transform, depending on their geometric relation. The complete fracture planes, including trend, dip angle, gap width, and extension length, are finally reconstructed in 3D space by mapping the migration profile using azimuthal information from optical images. The method is proven reliable and high-resolution through both numerical tests and real field data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11350v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Shen, Liu Liu, Shaojun Li, Zhenming Shi, Yiteng Wang, Ming Peng, Minzong Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Framework for Forward and Inverse Problems in Subsurface Imaging using Latent Space Translations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11247v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In subsurface imaging, learning the mapping from velocity maps to seismic waveforms (forward problem) and waveforms to velocity (inverse problem) is important for several applications. While traditional techniques for solving forward and inverse problems are computationally prohibitive, there is a growing interest in leveraging recent advances in deep learning to learn the mapping between velocity maps and seismic waveform images directly from data. Despite the variety of architectures explored in previous works, several open questions still remain unanswered such as the effect of latent space sizes, the importance of manifold learning, the complexity of translation models, and the value of jointly solving forward and inverse problems. We propose a unified framework to systematically characterize prior research in this area termed the Generalized Forward-Inverse (GFI) framework, building on the assumption of manifolds and latent space translations. We show that GFI encompasses previous works in deep learning for subsurface imaging, which can be viewed as specific instantiations of GFI. We also propose two new model architectures within the framework of GFI: Latent U-Net and Invertible X-Net, leveraging the power of U-Nets for domain translation and the ability of IU-Nets to simultaneously learn forward and inverse translations, respectively. We show that our proposed models achieve state-of-the-art (SOTA) performance for forward and inverse problems on a wide range of synthetic datasets, and also investigate their zero-shot effectiveness on two real-world-like datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11247v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naveen Gupta, Medha Sawhney, Arka Daw, Youzuo Lin, Anuj Karpatne</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
