<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 02:50:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neural machine translation of seismic waves for petrophysical inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective structural assessment of urban infrastructure is essential for sustainable land use and resilience to climate change and natural hazards. Seismic wave methods are widely applied in these areas for subsurface characterization and monitoring, yet they often rely on time-consuming inversion techniques that fall short in delivering comprehensive geological, hydrogeological, and geomechanical descriptions. Here, we explore the effectiveness of a passive seismic approach coupled with artificial intelligence (AI) for monitoring geological structures and hydrogeological conditions in the context of sinkhole hazard assessment. We introduce a deterministic petrophysical inversion technique based on a language model that decodes seismic wave velocity measurements to infer soil petrophysical and mechanical parameters as textual descriptions. Results successfully delineate 3D subsurface structures with their respective soil nature and mechanical characteristics, while accurately predicting daily water table levels. Validation demonstrates high accuracy, with a normalized root mean square error of 8%, closely rivaling with conventional stochastic seismic inversion methods, while delivering broader insights into subsurface conditions 2,000 times faster. These findings underscore the potential of advanced AI techniques to significantly enhance subsurface characterization across diverse scales, supporting decision-making for natural hazard mitigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13491v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Cunha Teixeira, Ludovic Bodet, Agn\`es Rivi\`ere, Santiago G. Solazzi, Am\'elie Hallier, Alexandrine Gesret, Sanae El Janyani, Marine Dangeard, Amine Dhemaied, Jos\'ephine Boisson Gaboriau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme firebrand transport by atmospheric waves in wildfires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13275v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In wildfires, burning pieces of ember-firebrands-are carried downstream by wind. At the time of landing, these firebrands can start secondary fires far away from the main burning unit. This phenomenon is called spotting and the secondary fires are referred to as spot fires. Here, we first present numerical evidence that atmospheric traveling waves can increase the spotting distance by at least an order of magnitude compared to unidirectional wind conditions. We then present theoretical results explaining this numerical observation. In particular, we show that the firebrand's motion can synchronize with the traveling wave, leading to a surf-like motion for some firebrand particles. This delays the firebrand's landing, making extreme spotting distances possible. This physical phenomena helps explain the discrepancy between previous theoretical estimates of maximum spotting distance and much larger spotting distances observed empirically. We derive new analytical expressions for the landing time and landing distance of the firebrands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13275v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Farazmand</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
