<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 01:38:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster analysis of earthquake hypocenters in Azerbaijan and surrounding territories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The research focuses on seismic events that occurred in Azerbaijan and adjacent territories, regions known for strong seismic activity. We analyze a catalog of recorded earthquakes between 2010 and 2023, extracting the locations of the earthquake hypocenters for study purposes. Using statistical methods and cluster analysis tools, we developed a procedure for partitioning hypocenter clusters. The procedure begins with estimates of the Morisita Index, which is suitable for preliminary assessments of the statistical properties of hypocenter sets. Analysis of the Morisita Index indicates that the spatial distribution of hypocenters is heterogeneous, containing denser domains referred to as clusters. The next stage involves identifying spatial clusters using the DBSCAN and HDBSCAN algorithms. Due to the strong dependence of results on the algorithm's parameters, we selected several partitions with 5-8 clusters that provided maximal or near-maximal Silhouette Index values. The final stage assesses the similarity of the resulting partitions, using the Adjusted Rand Index to identify partitions with a specified degree of similarity. The final set of partitions was compared to the fault network of the region. Based on the selected partition, the earthquake depth distributions were studied. Specifically, approximate probability density functions were constructed in the form of mixtures of normal distributions, leading to the identification of several bimodal distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22829v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergii Skurativskyi, Sergiy Mykulyak, Yuliya Semenova, Kateryna Skurativska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed conditional diffusion model for generalizable elastic wave-mode separation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional elastic wavefield separation methods, while accurate, often demand substantial computational resources, especially for large geological models or 3D scenarios. Purely data-driven neural network approaches can be more efficient, but may fail to generalize and maintain physical consistency due to the absence of explicit physical constraints. Here, we propose a physics-informed conditional diffusion model for elastic wavefield separation that seamlessly integrates domain-specific physics equations into both the training and inference stages of the reverse diffusion process. Conditioned on full elastic wavefields and subsurface P- and S-wave velocity profiles, our method directly predicts clean P-wave modes while enforcing Laplacian separation constraints through physics-guided loss and sampling corrections. Numerical experiments on diverse scenarios yield the separation results that closely match conventional numerical solutions but at a reduced cost, confirming the effectiveness and generalizability of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23007v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Cheng, Xinru Mu, Tariq Alkhalifah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Ionospheric Ray-Tracing: Advanced Electron Collision and Horizontal Gradient Modeling in the IONORT-ISP-WC System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.24098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This manuscript analyzes IONORT-ISP-WC, an advanced ionospheric ray-tracing tool improving HF radio wave propagation predictions. It significantly upgrades IONORT-ISP by integrating a double-exponential collision frequency model for the D-layer (primary HF absorption), extending the ISP 3-D electron density grid to 65 km, and increasing spatial resolution from 2{\deg} x 2{\deg} to 1{\deg} x 1{\deg}. A central focus is the detailed examination and local_ionort Fortran implementation of horizontal gradients in ionospheric electron density profiles. This reveals a robust framework for incorporating these gradients. Crucially, electx_grid now actively calculates horizontal gradients (previously commented), though full Taylor optimization is a high-priority future development to leverage the high-resolution grid for unparalleled accuracy. IONORT-ISP-WC underwent rigorous validation against observed and synthetic oblique ionograms (from IONORT-IRI-WC, based on the climatological IRI model). Results demonstrate its superior Maximum Usable Frequency (MUF) prediction accuracy. This underscores assimilative models' value in capturing dynamic ionospheric conditions, especially with meticulous horizontal gradient accounting. MUF prediction discrepancies are primarily attributed to real-time assimilation data limitations (availability, geographical distribution). This report positions IONORT-ISP-WC as a robust, reliable, cutting-edge operational tool for diverse space weather applications. It outlines crucial future developments: comprehensive validation of advanced horizontal gradient modeling and strategic enhancement of global data assimilation networks for higher accuracy and resilience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.24098v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Settimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Atmospheric Super-Resolution With Deep Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22780v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Score-based diffusion modeling is a generative machine learning algorithm that can be used to sample from complex distributions. They achieve this by learning a score function, i.e., the gradient of the log-probability density of the data, and reversing a noising process using the same. Once trained, score-based diffusion models not only generate new samples but also enable zero-shot conditioning of the generated samples on observed data. This promises a novel paradigm for data and model fusion, wherein the implicitly learned distributions of pretrained score-based diffusion models can be updated given the availability of online data in a Bayesian formulation. In this article, we apply such a concept to the super-resolution of a high-dimensional dynamical system, given the real-time availability of low-resolution and experimentally observed sparse sensor measurements from multimodal data. Additional analysis on how score-based sampling can be used for uncertainty estimates is also provided. Our experiments are performed for a super-resolution task that generates the ERA5 atmospheric dataset given sparse observations from a coarse-grained representation of the same and/or from unstructured experimental observations of the IGRA radiosonde dataset. We demonstrate accurate recovery of the high dimensional state given multiple sources of low-fidelity measurements. We also discover that the generative model can balance the influence of multiple dataset modalities during spatiotemporal reconstructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22780v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyajyoti Chakraborty, Haiwen Guan, Jason Stock, Troy Arcomano, Guido Cervone, Romit Maulik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Instabilities in Transient Landforms and Interconnected Ecosystems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many parts of the Earth system are thought to have multiple stable equilibrium states, with the potential for rapid and sometimes catastrophic shifts between them. The most common frameworks for analyzing stability changes, however, require stationary (trend- and seasonality-free) data, which necessitates error-prone data pre-processing. Here we propose a novel method of quantifying system stability based on eigenvalue tracking and Floquet Multipliers, which can be applied directly to diverse data without first removing trend and seasonality, and is robust to changing noise levels, as can be caused by merging signals from different sensors. We first demonstrate this approach with synthetic data and further show how glacier surge onset can be predicted from observed surface velocity time series. We then show that our method can be extended to analyze spatio-temporal data and illustrate this flexibility with remotely sensed Amazon rainforest vegetation productivity, highlighting the spatial patterns of whole-ecosystem destabilization. Our work applies critical slowing down theory to glacier dynamics for the first time, and provides a novel and flexible method to quantify the stability or resilience of a wide range of spatiotemporal systems, including climate subsystems, ecosystems, and transient landforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23946v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taylor Smith, Andreas Morr, Bodo Bookhagen, Niklas Boers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ocean-E2E: Hybrid Physics-Based and Data-Driven Global Forecasting of Extreme Marine Heatwaves with End-to-End Neural Assimilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22071v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work focuses on the end-to-end forecast of global extreme marine heatwaves (MHWs), which are unusually warm sea surface temperature events with profound impacts on marine ecosystems. Accurate prediction of extreme MHWs has significant scientific and financial worth. However, existing methods still have certain limitations, especially in the most extreme MHWs. In this study, to address these issues, based on the physical nature of MHWs, we created a novel hybrid data-driven and numerical MHWs forecast framework Ocean-E2E, which is capable of 40-day accurate MHW forecasting with end-to-end data assimilation. Our framework significantly improves the forecast ability of extreme MHWs by explicitly modeling the effect of oceanic mesoscale advection and air-sea interaction based on a differentiable dynamic kernel. Furthermore, Ocean-E2E is capable of end-to-end MHWs forecast and regional high-resolution prediction using neural data assimilation approaches, allowing our framework to operate completely independently of numerical models while demonstrating high assimilation stability and accuracy, outperforming the current state-of-the-art ocean numerical forecasting-assimilation models. Experimental results show that the proposed framework performs excellently on global-to-regional scales and short-to-long-term forecasts, especially in those most extreme MHWs. Overall, our model provides a framework for forecasting and understanding MHWs and other climate extremes. Our codes are available at https://github.com/ChiyodaMomo01/Ocean-E2E.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22071v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiqi Shu, Yuan Gao, Hao Wu, Ruijian Gou, Yanfei Xiang, Fan Xu, Qingsong Wen, Xian Wu, Xiaomeng Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
