<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 04:05:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A level-set structural approach for multi-physics joint inversion using full-waveform and gravity data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a level-set based structural approach for the joint inversion of full-waveform and gravity data. The joint inversion aims to integrate the strengths of full-waveform inversion for high resolution imaging and gravity inversion for detecting density contrasts over extensive regions. Although common studies typically only observe full-waveform inversion assisting gravity inversion, we propose three key points that enable gravity data to complement full-waveform data in the joint inversion. (i) Based on the well-posedness theorem, we consider a volume mass distribution where the density-contrast value is imposed as a priori information, ensuring that the gravity data provide meaningful information. (ii) We utilize a level-set formulation to characterize the shared interface of wave velocity and density functions, connecting multi-physics datasets via the structural similarity of their inversion parameters. (iii) We develop a balanced and decaying weight to regulate the influence of multi-physics datasets during joint inversion. This weight comprises a balanced part that accounts for the differing scales of full-waveform and gravity data, and a decaying part designed to effectively utilize the features and advantages of each dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06689v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Deng, Jianfeng Zhao, Wenbin Li, Jianwei Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven solar forecasting enables near-optimal economic decisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar energy adoption is critical to achieving net-zero emissions. However, it remains difficult for many industrial and commercial actors to decide on whether they should adopt distributed solar-battery systems, which is largely due to the unavailability of fast, low-cost, and high-resolution irradiance forecasts. Here, we present SunCastNet, a lightweight data-driven forecasting system that provides 0.05$^\circ$, 10-minute resolution predictions of surface solar radiation downwards (SSRD) up to 7 days ahead. SunCastNet, coupled with reinforcement learning (RL) for battery scheduling, reduces operational regret by 76--93\% compared to robust decision making (RDM). In 25-year investment backtests, it enables up to five of ten high-emitting industrial sectors per region to cross the commercial viability threshold of 12\% Internal Rate of Return (IRR). These results show that high-resolution, long-horizon solar forecasts can directly translate into measurable economic gains, supporting near-optimal energy operations and accelerating renewable deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06925v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixiang Dai, Minghao Yin, Xuanhong Chen, Alberto Carpentieri, Jussi Leinonen, Boris Bonev, Chengzhe Zhong, Thorsten Kurth, Jingan Sun, Ram Cherukuri, Yuzhou Zhang, Ruihua Zhang, Farah Hariri, Xiaodong Ding, Chuanxiang Zhu, Dake Zhang, Yaodan Cui, Yuxi Lu, Yue Song, Bin He, Jie Chen, Yixin Zhu, Chenheng Xu, Maofeng Liu, Zeyi Niu, Wanpeng Qi, Xu Shan, Siyuan Xian, Ning Lin, Kairui Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Boundary Conditions and Heating Modes on the Onset of Columnar Convection in Rotating Spherical Shells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06632v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the linear onset of thermal convection in rotating spherical shells with a focus on the influence of mechanical boundary conditions and thermal driving modes. Using a spectral method, we determine critical Rayleigh numbers, azimuthal wavenumbers, and oscillation frequencies over a wide range of Prandtl numbers and shell aspect ratios at moderate Ekman numbers. We show that the preferred boundary condition for convective onset depends systematically on both aspect ratio and Prandtl number: for sufficiently thick shells or for large $\text{Pr}$, the Ekman boundary layer at the outer boundary becomes destabilising, so that no-slip boundaries yield a lower $\text{Ra}_c$ than stress-free boundaries. Comparing differential and internal heating, we find that internal heating generally raises $\text{Ra}_c$, shifts the onset to larger wavenumbers and frequencies, and relocates the critical column away from the tangent cylinder. Mixed boundary conditions with no-slip on the inner boundary behave similarly to purely stress-free boundaries, confirming the dominant influence of the outer surface. These results demonstrate that boundary conditions and heating mechanisms play a central role in controlling the onset of convection and should be carefully considered in models of planetary and stellar interiors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06632v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/fluids10090237</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Seeley et al., Fluids (2025), 10(9), 237</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>William Seeley, Francesca Coke, Radostin Simitev, Robert Teed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DispFormer: A Pretrained Transformer Incorporating Physical Constraints for Dispersion Curve Inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04366v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Surface wave dispersion curve inversion is crucial for estimating subsurface shear-wave velocity (vs), yet traditional methods often face challenges related to computational cost, non-uniqueness, and sensitivity to initial models. While deep learning approaches show promise, many require large labeled datasets and struggle with real-world datasets, which often exhibit varying period ranges, missing values, and low signal-to-noise ratios. To address these limitations, this study introduces DispFormer, a transformer-based neural network for $v_s$ profile inversion from Rayleigh-wave phase and group dispersion curves. DispFormer processes dispersion data independently at each period, allowing it to handle varying lengths without requiring network modifications or strict alignment between training and testing datasets. A depth-aware training strategy is also introduced, incorporating physical constraints derived from the depth sensitivity of dispersion data. DispFormer is pre-trained on a global synthetic dataset and evaluated on two regional synthetic datasets using zero-shot and few-shot strategies. Results show that even without labeled data, the zero-shot DispFormer generates inversion profiles that outperform the interpolated reference model used as the pretraining target, providing a deployable initial model generator to assist traditional workflows. When partial labeled data available, the few-shot trained DispFormer surpasses traditional global search methods. Real-world tests further confirm that DispFormer generalizes well to dispersion data with varying lengths and achieves lower data residuals than reference models. These findings underscore the potential of DispFormer as a foundation model for dispersion curve inversion and demonstrate the advantages of integrating physics-informed deep learning into geophysical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04366v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1029/2025JH000648</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Liu, et al. (2025). Journal of Geophysical Research: Machine Learning and Computation, 2, e2025JH000648</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Feng Liu, Bao Deng, Rui Su, Lei Bai, Wanli Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Cubic Law and Darcy Fail: Bayesian Correction of Model Misspecification in Fracture Conductivities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20788v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Structural uncertainties and unresolved features in fault zones hinder the assessment of leakage risks in subsurface CO2 storage. Understanding multi-scale uncertainties in fracture network conductivity is crucial for mitigating risks and reliably modelling upscaled fault leakage rates. Conventional models, such as the Cubic Law, which is based on mechanical aperture measurements, often neglect fracture roughness, leading to model misspecifications and inaccurate conductivity estimates. Here, we develop a physics-informed, AI-driven correction of these model misspecifications by automatically integrating roughness effects and small-scale structural uncertainties. Using Bayesian inference combined with data-driven and geometric corrections, we reconstruct local hydraulic aperture fields that reliably estimate fracture conductivities. By leveraging interactions across scales, we improve upon traditional empirical corrections and provide a framework for propagating uncertainties from individual fractures to network scales. Our approach thereby supports robust calibration of conductivity ranges for fault leakage sensitivity analyses, offering a scalable solution for subsurface risk assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20788v3</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah Perez, Florian Doster, Julien Maes, Hannah Menke, Ahmed ElSheikh, Andreas Busch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise is All You Need: rethinking the value of noise on seismic denoising via diffusion models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03629v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce SeisDiff-denoNIA, a novel diffusion-based seismic denoising framework that trains directly on field noise, eliminating the reliance on synthetic datasets. Unlike conventional denoising methods that require clean signal labels, our approach leverages field noise extracted prior to first arrivals as training targets, allowing the diffusion model to explicitly learn the true noise distribution. The model demonstrates robust performance on field DAS-VSP data contaminated by different noise types, and significantly outperforms traditional signal-based diffusion models under low SNR conditions in synthetic tests. The results suggest that explicitly modeling noise is not only viable but advantageous for seismic denoising tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03629v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donglin Zhu, Peiyao Li, Ge Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
