<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 04:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Shear-enhanced permeability development of magma vesiculating in cylindrical conduits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: During magma vesiculation, permeability is established when growing bubbles begin to form connected networks, which allow fluids to percolate. This percolation threshold controls the relative rates between magma ascent and volatile exsolution, which in turn dictate eruptive style. Percolation is controlled primarily by total vesicularity and shear conditions. We performed vesiculation experiments on rhyolitic glass in a spatially confined, cylindrical, conduit-like geometry. The amount of shear experienced by the sample is controlled by varying the sample and confining diameters to allow for various degrees of free (isotropic) followed by confined (anisotropic) expansion. Pore anisotropy develops sub-parallel to the flow direction. We measure the total and connected porosity and permeability of the vesiculated samples. We observe two regimes of behavior for samples dominated by 1) isotropic expansion, in which the onset of percolation corresponds with the beginning of shear deformation and 2) anisotropic expansion which shows low percolation thresholds (&lt;20%) with a near-constant permeability even with increasing porosity. We find a good correlation between connected porosity and permeability, with distinct trends for sheared and unsheared samples. The development of anisotropy in vesiculating magmas is ubiquitous in magmatic networks and our data highlight the importance of considering the in situ shear conditions when investigating the percolation threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10103v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Birnbaum, J. Schauroth, J. Weaver, J. E. Kendrick, A. Lamur, Y. Lavall\'ee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the elementary theory of earthquake aftershocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The elementary theory of aftershocks, being relatively simple mathematically, belongs to the basics of earthquake physics. The paper briefly outlines the concepts and ideas of the theory, provides equations for the relaxation of the source after the main shock, and emphasizes the effectiveness of the theory in the search for new approaches to the processing and analysis of aftershock observation data. The main attention is paid to the discussion of two new results obtained on the basis of elementary theory. Firstly, a two-stage relaxation mode of the earthquake source was discovered. In the first stage, called the Omori epoch, the Omori law is strictly observed. The first stage ends with a bifurcation of the source, and the second stage of relaxation begins, during which the evolution of aftershocks proceeds chaotically. Secondly, within the framework of the elementary theory of aftershocks, a fundamentally new concept of the proper time of the source was introduced. Keywords: earthquake source, deactivation coefficient, Omori law, dynamic system, inverse problem, relaxation, proper time. The source proper time has proven useful in experimental studies of seismic activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10414v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Guglielmi, O. D. Zotov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling spontaneous ductile (viscous) strain localisation on Earth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01360v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A characteristic feature of the Earth is that diffuse thermal convection in the mantle produces localized deformation at the surface: Plate Tectonics. However, modelling this phenomenon remains a challenge, due to inability to simulate spontaneous strain localisation in the deep sections of the plates, where rocks deform by ductile processes and behave as highly viscous fluids. Analysis of shear zones - the main expression of strain localisation in nature - reveals that mechanical heterogeneity is key. Here we posit that the bottleneck for self-consistent generation of strain localisation in geodynamical models is poor representation of this heterogeneity and its evolution during deformation, in particular at small scales. To bypass this obstacle, we introduce a stochastic description of the mechanical properties of the rocks, which evolves as a function of the local work rate. This approach not only successfully generates steady-state shear zones from random rheological heterogeneity fields, but reproduces the full range of observations in nature and experiments. It allows defining the necessary conditions and a regime diagram for viscous strain localisation and quantifying the resulting bulk softening, paving the way for self-consistent modelling of the development of plate boundaries and initiation of Plate Tectonics on Earth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01360v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'ea Tommasi, Felipe S\'aez-Leiva, Michel Peyret, Riad Hassani, Maurine Montagnat</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
