<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 14:32:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions between syn-rift magmatism and tectonic extension at intermediate rifted margins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intermediate rifted margins exhibit neither seaward dipping reflectors nor exhumed mantle at the continent-ocean transition (COT). Instead, they transition into normal-thickness, magmatic Penrose-type oceanic crust, and thus diverge from the classic magma-rich and magma-poor end-member models. However, several intermediate margins, such as the South China Sea (SCS), display detachment faulting similar to magma-poor margins and magmatic underplating typical of magma-rich ones. How tectonics and magmatism interact in these intermediate environments is poorly understood. Here we use 2D numerical models to demonstrate that the elevated initial geotherm inherited from prior plate subduction in the SCS explains several key observations: an early phase of wide rifting, subsequent localization onto core complexes with substantial footwall magmatic intrusions, and eventual formation of normal igneous oceanic crust at break-up. Thermal weakening caused by syn-rift footwall magmatic intrusions facilitates lower crustal ductile flow, promoting the development of rolling-hinge type detachment faults and exhumation of core complexes. These structures are associated with accelerated tectonic subsidence, which is later moderated by detachment-related doming, as observed in the SCS. Normal-thickness oceanic crust occurs after break-up, even under ultra-slow extension rates used in our simulations, highlighting the importance of inheritance in determining margin architecture, the spatio-temporal distribution of syn-rift magmatism, and the nature of the COT. This behavior contrasts sharply with magma-poor margins, where a cooler lithosphere and similar ultra-slow extension produce no syn-rift magmatism, leading instead to crustal embrittlement, mantle serpentinization and exhumation at the COT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09366v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Yang, Marta Perez-Gussinye, Shaowen Liu, Javier Garcia-Pintado, Gudipati RaghuRam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining exoplanet interiors using observations of their atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astronomical surveys have identified numerous exoplanets with bulk compositions that are unlike the planets of the Solar System, including rocky super-Earths and gas-enveloped sub-Neptunes. Observing the atmospheres of these objects provides information on the geological processes that influence their climates and surfaces. In this Review, we summarize the current understanding of these planets, including insights into the interaction between the atmosphere and interior based on observations made with the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). We describe the expected climatic and interior planetary regimes for planets with different density and stellar flux and how those regimes might be observationally distinguished. We also identify the observational, experimental, and theoretical innovations that will be required to characterize Earth-like exoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08844v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/science.ads3360</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science 390, eads3360 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tim Lichtenberg, Oliver Shorttle, Johanna Teske, Eliza M. -R. Kempton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eastward Transients in the Dayside Ionosphere II: A Parallel-plate Capacitor-Like Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03174v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: During the 23 April 2023 geospace storm, we observed chorus wave-driven, energetic particle precipitation on closed magnetic field lines in the dayside magnetosphere. Simultaneously and in the ionosphere's bottom-side, we observed signatures of impact ionization and strong enhancements in the ionospheric electric field, via radar-detection of meter-scale turbulence, and with matching temporal characteristics as that of the magnetospheric observations. We detailed this in a companion paper. In the present article, we place those observations into context with the dayside ionosphere, and describe a remarkably similar event that took place during the May 2024 geospace superstorm. In both cases, fast, eastward-moving electric field structures were excited equatorward of the ionospheric cusp, on closed magnetic field-lines -- observations that challenge existing modes of explanation for electrodynamics in the cusp-region, where most such observations are interpreted in the context of poleward-moving auroral forms. Instead, primarily eastward-moving electric field structures were associated with turbulent Hall currents that are perhaps characteristically excited during geospace storms by wave-particle interactions near magnetospheric equator or by proton precipitation characteristics in the cusp, forming a `parallel-plate capacitor-like effect'. We propose that transient eastward electrodynamic bursts in the dayside ionosphere might be a common, albeit previously unresolved, feature of geomagnetic storms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03174v4</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3bzj-bsf8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 112 (2025), 045203</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Magnus F Ivarsen, Jean-Pierre St-Maurice, Glenn C Hussey, Kathryn McWilliams, Yaqi Jin, Devin R Huyghebaert, Yukinaga Miyashita, David Sibeck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Characteristic Signature of Magnetospheric Wave-Particle Interactions Found in the Turbulent E-region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04107v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Plasma waves in the magnetosphere scatter electrons, causing them to precipitate into Earth's atmosphere, imparting their temporal characteristics to diffuse auroras. In a case study of conjugate radar and satellite observations, we demonstrate a close and unprecedented association between enhanced electrostatic cyclotron harmonic wave activity in the magnetosphere and the appearance of meter-scale plasma turbulence a few seconds later in the lower ionosphere on nearby magnetic field lines. Such direct structuring of the ionosphere carries implications for our understanding of space weather.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04107v2</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.145201</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134 (2025), 145201</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Magnus F Ivarsen, Yukinaga Miyashita, Jean-Pierre St-Maurice, Glenn C Hussey, Brian Pitzel, Draven Galeschuk, Saif Marei, Richard B Horne, Yoshiya Kasahara, Shoya Matsuda, Satoshi Kasahara, Kunihiro Keika, Yoshizumi Miyoshi, Kazuhiro Yamamoto, Atsuki Shinbori, Devin R Huyghebaert, Ayako Matsuoka, Shoichiro Yokota, Fuminori Tsuchiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
