<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 02:38:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse-to-Fine Non-Rigid Registration for Side-Scan Sonar Mosaicking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Side-scan sonar mosaicking plays a crucial role in large-scale seabed mapping but is challenged by complex non-linear, spatially varying distortions due to diverse sonar acquisition conditions. Existing rigid or affine registration methods fail to model such complex deformations, whereas traditional non-rigid techniques tend to overfit and lack robustness in sparse-texture sonar data. To address these challenges, we propose a coarse-to-fine hierarchical non-rigid registration framework tailored for large-scale side-scan sonar images. Our method begins with a global Thin Plate Spline initialization from sparse correspondences, followed by superpixel-guided segmentation that partitions the image into structurally consistent patches preserving terrain integrity. Each patch is then refined by a pretrained SynthMorph network in an unsupervised manner, enabling dense and flexible alignment without task-specific training. Finally, a fusion strategy integrates both global and local deformations into a smooth, unified deformation field. Extensive quantitative and visual evaluations demonstrate that our approach significantly outperforms state-of-the-art rigid, classical non-rigid, and learning-based methods in accuracy, structural consistency, and deformation smoothness on the challenging sonar dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00052v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Can Lei, Nuno Gracias, Rafael Garcia, Hayat Rajani, Huigang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mount Rainier Elevation Survey 2024</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The elevation of Mount Rainier was last surveyed in 2010 by the Land Surveyors Association of Washington. More recent LiDAR data and observational reports have indicated that the historical highest point on the mountain, Columbia Crest, has lost a significant amount of elevation and may no longer be the highest point. This report documents the results of multiple ground surveys conducted in August and September 2024 to determine the current elevation of Columbia Crest and the current elevation and location of the summit of Mt Rainier. On August 28, 2024, a Promark 220 differential GPS unit was used to measure the elevation of Columbia Crest and the Southwest Rim, two recognized historical local maxima on the rim of the summit caldera. Columbia Crest is a year-round ice-capped locality, while the Southwest Rim melts to rock each summer. Measurements were corroborated with Abney level measurements and LiDAR data from 2007 and 2022. On September 21 and 22, 2024, additional ground measurements were taken with the Promark 220 of the Summit 2 USGS monument location and of the highest rock on the Southwest Rim. Additionally, the three USGS monuments lower on the mountain (Muir, McClure, and Paradise) were measured. These measurements were used to corroborate the summit measurements. Monument measurements were found to be consistent with 2010 measurements. Southwest Rim summit measurements were consistent from August and September. Columbia Crest, last measured at 14,411.0ft (NGVD29) in 1998, was measured to have lost 21.8ft of elevation. Now the ice-capped Columbia Crest is no longer the summit of Mt Rainier. The summit is now on the seasonally rocky Southwest Rim, next to the Summit 2 USGS monument location. (The physical monument was not located and has likely been stolen). The new summit elevation of Mount Rainier is 14,399.6ft +/-0.1ft NGVD29 (14,406.2ft +/-0.1ft NAVD88).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01130v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Gilbertson, Larry Signani, Kathryn Stanchak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slip, Differentiate, Observe: State and Parameter Estimation for Rate and State Friction from Noisy Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01705v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantifying frictional properties of interfaces remains a major challenge in both terrestrial and extraterrestrial geomechanics, where available samples, laboratory apparatuses, and geophysical observations are inherently limited. We introduce an analytic and numerical framework, grounded in nonlinear control theory, to infer the emergent frictional behavior of seismic faults. From noisy slip measurements, we first reconstruct the slip rate and frictional response in finite time using a Robust Exact Filtering Differentiator (REFD) that attenuates measurement noise. Building on these reconstructions, we design an exponentially convergent adaptive-gain observer that estimates the internal state variable and the key parameters (a - b) and dc of the rate-and-state friction (RSF) law, widely used in fault mechanics. Numerical experiments show that, in fast slip regimes where data are sufficiently rich, the method recovers RSF parameters with errors on the order of 20% and accurately tracks the RSF state variable despite noise contamination, whereas slowly varying sliding periods lack the observability required for reliable estimation. We also establish observability and identifiability conditions for the extended system, enabling the determination of additional parameters and outlining pathways for more advanced control-theoretic approaches to friction and state identification in fault systems. Although we apply the approach to a reduced spring-slider analogue, it improves on classical RSF calibration methods that depend on laboratory access to shear and normal stress. It also offers convergence guarantees and explicit error bounds, and it can further support model-based inversions that embed RSF in forward simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01705v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Michael Riley, Diego Guti\'errez-Oribio, Ioannis Stefanou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Granite sliding on granite: friction, wear rates, surface topography, and the scale-dependence of rate-state effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study tribological granite-granite contacts as a model for tectonic faulting, combining experiments, theory, and molecular dynamics simulations. The high friction in this system is not dominated by particulate wear or plowing, as frequently assumed, but by cold welding within plastically deformed asperity junctions. We base this conclusion on the observation that wear is repeatedly high after cleaning contacts but decreases as gouge accumulates, while friction shows the opposite trend. Moreover, adding water reduces wear by a factor of ten but barely decreases friction. Thermal and rate-dependent effects - central to most earthquake models-are negligible: friction remains unchanged between -40{\deg}C and 20{\deg}C, across abrupt velocity steps, and after hours of stationary contact. The absence of rate-state effects in our macroscopic samples is rationalized by the scale-dependence of pre-slip. The evolution of surface topography shows that quartz grains become locally smooth, with height spectra isotropic for wavelength below 10 microns but anisotropic at longer wavelengths, similar to natural faults. The resulting gouge particles have the usual characteristic sizes near 100 nm. Molecular dynamics simulations of a rigid, amorphous silica tip sliding on {\alpha}-quartz reproduce not only similar friction coefficients near unity but also other experimentally observed features, including stress-introduced transitions to phases observed in post-mortem faults, as well as theoretical estimates of local flash temperatures. Additionally, they reveal a marked decrease of interfacial shear strength above 600{\deg}C. The overall correspondence between experiments, simulations, theory, and field observations indicates that our model system captures essential aspects of rock friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01765v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey V. Sukhomlinov, Martin H. M\"user, B. N. J. Persson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Context-Fusion Attention (CFA) U-Net and Clustering for Robust Seismic Horizon Interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Interpreting seismic horizons is a critical task for characterizing subsurface structures in hydrocarbon exploration. Recent advances in deep learning, particularly U-Net-based architectures, have significantly improved automated horizon tracking. However, challenges remain in accurately segmenting complex geological features and interpolating horizons from sparse annotations. To address these issues, a hybrid framework is presented that integrates advanced U-Net variants with spatial clustering to enhance horizon continuity and geometric fidelity. The core contribution is the Context Fusion Attention (CFA) U-Net, a novel architecture that fuses spatial and Sobel-derived geometric features within attention gates to improve both precision and surface completeness. The performance of five architectures, the U-Net (Standard and compressed), U-Net++, Attention U-Net, and CFA U-Net, was systematically evaluated across various data sparsity regimes (10-, 20-, and 40-line spacing). This approach outperformed existing baselines, achieving state-of-the-art results on the Mexilhao field (Santos Basin, Brazil) dataset with a validation IoU of 0.881 and MAE of 2.49ms, and excellent surface coverage of 97.6% on the F3 Block of the North Sea dataset under sparse conditions. The framework further refines merged horizon predictions (inline and cross-line) using Density-Based Spatial Clustering of Applications with Noise (DBSCAN) to produce geologically plausible surfaces. The results demonstrate the advantages of hybrid methodologies and attention-based architectures enhanced with geometric context, providing a robust and generalizable solution for seismic interpretation in structurally complex and data-scarce environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00191v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Luis Lima de Jesus Silva, Joao Pedro Gomes, Paulo Roberto de Melo Barros Junior, Vitor Hugo Serravalle Reis Rodrigues, Alexsandro Guerra Cerqueira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routing-Method Effects on Distance, Time, Fuel, and Emissions in Europe-Asia Trade: A Comparison of the Suez, Cape, and Northern Sea Route Corridors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01076v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Growing interest in decarbonization and Arctic accessibility has renewed attention on Europe-Asia shipping corridors. The Northern Sea Route (NSR) is often portrayed as a 30-40% shortcut relative to Suez, with savings propagated to time, fuel, and CO2. The effect of enforcing sea-only feasibility on these baselines, and its downstream impact on time, fuel, and CO2, remains under-examined.
  We compare great-circle baselines with sea-only routes computed via A-star search (A*) on a 0.5-degree grid between Northern Europe and Northeast Asia across the Suez, Cape of Good Hope, and NSR corridors under three waypoint philosophies. Distances are mapped to voyage time using corridor-typical speeds and to fuel/CO2 using main- and auxiliary-engine accounting.
  Sea-only routing preserves the ranking NSR &lt; Suez &lt; Cape but compresses NSR's advantage once realistic speeds are applied. NSR remains shortest (about 8000-10000 nm versus 11000-12000 nm for Suez), yet typical durations differ modestly and fuel/CO2 savings over Suez are small and variant-dependent. Equal-speed tests restore geometric ordering, and endpoint sensitivity shows larger NSR gains for more northern East Asian ports.
  The framework provides a reproducible, corridor-agnostic benchmark for later integration of sea ice, weather, regulatory overlays, and AIS data in dynamic Arctic voyage planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01076v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdella Mohameda, Christian Hendricksb, Xiangyu Hua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting cement microstructure and mechanical properties in hydrating cement paste with a Phase-Field model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Predicting the evolving microstructure of hydrating cement is essential for understanding and modeling its mechanical property development. Physics-based continuum approaches offer a rigorous framework for capturing the thermodynamics of dissolution and precipitation processes at the microstructural scale. In this work, we present an adapted Phase-Field (PF) model for cement hydration that resolves key physical inconsistencies in existing PF formulations by introducing a revised free-energy potential and distinct equilibrium constants for clinker dissolution and hydrate precipitation. The resulting PF framework reproduces microstructural evolution, yielding realistic porosity levels and continuous phase boundaries in close agreement with experimental observations. The predicted hydrated microstructures are subsequently used in a computational homogenization scheme to evaluate the elastic response of the material. The PF-derived mechanical properties show good agreement with experimental trends, supporting the ability of the proposed framework to consistently link hydration chemistry, microstructure formation, and the resulting mechanical response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01407v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Sac-Morane, Katerina Ioannidou, Manolis Veveakis, Hadrien Rattez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Networks for Predicting Permeability Tensors of 2D Porous Media: Comparison of Convolution- and Transformer-based Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Permeability is a central concept in the macroscopic description of flow through porous media, with applications spanning from oil recovery to hydrology. Traditional methods for determining the permeability tensor involving flow simulations or experiments can be time consuming and resource-intensive, while analytical methods, e.g., based on the Kozeny-Carman equation, may be too simplistic for accurate prediction based on pore-scale features. In this work, we explore deep learning as a more efficient alternative for predicting the permeability tensor based on two-dimensional binary images of porous media, segmented into solid ($1$) and void ($0$) regions. We generate a dataset of 24,000 synthetic random periodic porous media samples with specified porosity and characteristic length scale. Using Lattice-Boltzmann simulations, we compute the permeability tensor for flow through these samples with values spanning three orders of magnitude. We evaluate three families of image-based deep learning models: ResNet (ResNet-$50$ and ResNet-$101$), Vision Transformers (ViT-T$16$ and ViT-S$16$) and ConvNeXt (Tiny and Small). To improve model generalisation, we employ techniques such as weight decay, learning rate scheduling, and data augmentation. The effect of data augmentation and dataset size on model performance is studied, and we find that they generally increase the accuracy of permeability predictions. We also show that ConvNeXt and ResNet converge faster than ViT and degrade in performance if trained for too long. ConvNeXt-Small achieved the highest $R^2$ score of $0.99460$ on $4,000$ unseen test samples. These findings underscore the potential to use image-based neural networks to predict permeability tensors accurately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01517v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sigurd Vargdal, Paula Reis, Henrik Andersen Sveinsson, Gaute Linga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth Matching Method Based on ShapeDTW for Oil-Based Mud Imager</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01611v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In well logging operations using the oil-based mud (OBM) microresistivity imager, which employs an interleaved design with upper and lower pad sets, depth misalignment issues persist between the pad images even after velocity correction. This paper presents a depth matching method for borehole images based on the Shape Dynamic Time Warping (ShapeDTW) algorithm. The method extracts local shape features to construct a morphologically sensitive distance matrix, better preserving structural similarity between sequences during alignment. We implement this by employing a combined feature set of the one-dimensional Histogram of Oriented Gradients (HOG1D) and the original signal as the shape descriptor. Field test examples demonstrate that our method achieves precise alignment for images with complex textures, depth shifts, or local scaling. Furthermore, it provides a flexible framework for feature extension, allowing the integration of other descriptors tailored to specific geological features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01611v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengfeng Li, Zhou Feng, Hongliang Wu, Hao Zhang, Han Tian, Peng Liu, Lixin Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of slow earthquake statistics in low-friction soft granular shear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01355v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Slow earthquakes differ from regular earthquakes in their slower moment release and size distribution dominated by smaller events. However, the physical origin of these slow earthquake statistics remains controversial. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate that their characteristics emerge from low-friction soft granular shear. To model slow-earthquake fault materials under hydrothermal conditions, we use a low-friction soft hydrogel particle layer floating on lubricating fluid and conduct stick-slip experiments. The observed slip events follow the same laws of both moment release rate and size distribution as with slow earthquakes, contrasting with frictional rigid granular shear. Slip size is determined by the competing effects of shear localization and pressure enhancement with decreasing porosity. These findings indicate that low friction and particle softness in sheared granular systems with sparse contact structures cause slow earthquake statistics, which may be driven by pore fluid dynamics and shear localization within hazardous fault zones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01355v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-65230-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16 (2024) 10236</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuto Sasaki, Hiroaki Katsuragi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided Unconditional and Conditional Generative Models for Super-Resolution and Inference of Quasi-Geostrophic Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00719v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Typically, numerical simulations of Earth systems are coarse, and Earth observations are sparse and gappy. We apply four generative diffusion modeling approaches to super-resolution and inference of forced two-dimensional quasi-geostrophic turbulence on the beta-plane from coarse, sparse, and gappy observations. Two guided approaches minimally adapt a pre-trained unconditional model: SDEdit modifies the initial condition, and Diffusion Posterior Sampling (DPS) modifies the reverse diffusion process score. Two conditional approaches, a vanilla variant and classifier-free guidance, require training with paired high-resolution and observation data. We consider multiple test cases spanning: two regimes, eddy and anisotropic-jet turbulence; two Reynolds numbers, 10^3 and 10^4; and two observation types, 4x coarse-resolution fields and coarse, sparse and gappy observations. Our comprehensive skill metrics include norms of the reconstructed vorticity fields, turbulence statistical quantities, and quantifications of the super-resolved probabilistic ensembles and their errors. We also study the sensitivity to tuning parameters such as guidance strength. Results show that the generated super-resolution fields of SDEdit are unphysical, while those of DPS are reasonable but with smoothed fine-scale features; however, neither of these lower-cost models propagates observational information effectively to unobserved regions. The two conditional models require re-training, but reconstruct missing fine-scale features, are cycle-consistent with observations, and predict correct turbulence statistics, including the tails. Further, their mean errors are highly correlated with and predictable from their ensemble standard deviations. Results highlight the tradeoffs between ease of implementation, fidelity (sharpness), and cycle-consistency of the diffusion models, and offer practical guidance for deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00719v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anantha Narayanan Suresh Babu, Akhil Sadam, Pierre F. J. Lermusiaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
