<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 04:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking CO$_2$ Storage Simulations: Results from the 11th Society of Petroleum Engineers Comparative Solution Project</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 11th Society of Petroleum Engineers Comparative Solution Project (shortened SPE11 herein) benchmarked simulation tools for geological carbon dioxide (CO$_2$) storage. A total of 45 groups from leading research institutions and industry across the globe signed up to participate, with 18 ultimately contributing valid results that were included in the comparative study reported here.
  This paper summarizes the SPE11. A comprehensive introduction and qualitative discussion of the submitted data are provided, together with an overview of online resources for accessing the full depth of data. A global metric for analyzing the relative distance between submissions is proposed and used to conduct a quantitative analysis of the submissions. This analysis attempts to statistically resolve the key aspects influencing the variability between submissions.
  The study shows that the major qualitative variation between the submitted results is related to thermal effects, dissolution-driven convective mixing, and resolution of facies discontinuities. Moreover, a strong dependence on grid resolution is observed across all three versions of the SPE11. However, our quantitative analysis suggests that the observed variations are predominantly influenced by factors not documented in the technical responses provided by the participants. We therefore identify that unreported variations due to human choices within the process of setting up, conducting, and reporting on the simulations underlying each SPE11 submission are at least as impactful as the computational choices reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15861v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan M. Nordbotten, Martin A. Fern{\o}, Bernd Flemisch, Anthony R. Kovscek, Knut-Andreas Lie, Jakub W. Both, Olav M{\o}yner, Tor Harald Sandve, Etienne Ahusborde, Sebastian Bauer, Zhangxing Chen, Holger Class, Chaojie Di, Didier Ding, David Element, Abbas Firoozabadi, Eric Flauraud, Jacques Franc, Firdovsi Gasanzade, Yousef Ghomian, Marie Ann Giddins, Christopher Green, Bruno R. B. Fernandes, George Hadjisotiriou, Glenn Hammond, Hai Huang, Dickson Kachuma, Michel Kern, Timo Koch, Prasanna Krishnamurthy, Kjetil Olsen Lye, David Landa-Marb\'an, Michael Nole, Paolo Orsini, Nicolas Ruby, Pablo Salinas, Mohammad Sayyafzadeh, Jakub Solovsk\'y, Jakob Torben, Adam Turner, Denis V. Voskov, Kai Wendel, AbdAllah A. Youssef</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earthquake Swarm Activity in the Tokara Islands (2025): Statistical Analysis Indicates Low Probability of Major Seismic Event</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Tokara Islands, a volcanic archipelago south of Japan's main islands, has experienced ongoing earthquake swarm activity in 2025, raising concerns about triggering the anticipated Nankai Trough earthquake. The Japan Meteorological Agency has dismissed this link, but the seismic activity's mechanisms remain unclear. This study uses Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) to examine the 2025 swarm's statistical properties and compare them with historical patterns. The 2025 swarm's frequency and magnitude distributions closely resemble those of 2021 swarms, which coincided with volcanic activity at Suwanose Island, 10 km from the epicentral region, suggesting a magma-seismicity link. Statistical analysis shows a low magnitude scale ({\sigma} = 0.37) and moderate mean magnitude ({\mu} = 2.8), consistent with magma-driven seismicity, unlike the higher {\sigma} (1.2) and {\mu} (3.6) before the 2011 Tohoku earthquake. The exponential distribution of earthquake intervals ({\lambda} = 1/0.19 hours) further supports magma-induced activity. These findings indicate localized volcanic processes, not precursors to major tectonic events like the Nankai Trough earthquake. Statistical seismology effectively distinguishes volcanic from tectonic seismic processes for hazard assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15872v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomokazu Konishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Semi-analytic but Biased Uncertainty Assessment Method using Sample Extensions, Analysed for Nonlinear Travel Time Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many geophysical problems can be cast as inverse problems that estimate a set of parameter values from observed data. Within a Bayesian framework, solutions to such problems are described probabilistically by the so-called posterior probability distribution functions (pdf's). To obtain robust inference results often requires millions of model parameter value samples to be drawn, and their simulation to be performed; this is a computationally expensive procedure. We investigate the concept of sample extensions as a means to improve efficiency when solving fully nonlinear inverse problems. A sample's extension is defined as the set of models or parameter values whose forward function values are directly accessible from a sample for which the forward function has already been evaluated, obviating the need for additional forward function evaluations. In a specific case of first-arrival travel time calculations used in seismic travel time tomography, we apply sample extensions to obtain a continuous region with non-zero hypervolume within parameter space, across all of which the forward function values are known given only a single forward simulation. We devise a deterministic sampling technique that identifies the most informative extensions by solving an optimisation problem. In an illustrative tomographic example that involves a single travel time datum, we find 51 optimal samples, and use them to construct an analytic approximation to the Bayesian posterior pdf. Additionally, we propose an extensions-based algorithm for real-world tomography scenarios and apply it to a synthetic 2D example. This study highlights two fundamental problems that make the method inefficient: (1) limited hypervolumes of extensions and (2) neglecting parameter correlations to simplify analytic calculations. Finding solutions to these problems defines possible directions for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16353v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuebin Zhao, Andrew Curtis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DASPack: Controlled Data Compression for Distributed Acoustic Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present DASPack, a high-performance, open-source compression tool specifically designed for distributed acoustic sensing (DAS) data. As DAS becomes a key technology for real-time, high-density, and long-range monitoring in fields such as geophysics, infrastructure surveillance, and environmental sensing, the volume of collected data is rapidly increasing. Large-scale DAS deployments already generate hundreds of terabytes and are expected to increase in the coming years, making long-term storage a major challenge. Despite this urgent need, few compression methods have proven to be both practical and scalable in real-world scenarios. DASPack is a fully operational solution that consistently outperforms existing techniques for DAS data. It enables both controlled lossy and lossless compression by allowing users to choose the maximum absolute difference per datum between the original and compressed data. The compression pipeline combines wavelet transforms, linear predictive coding, and entropy coding to optimise efficiency. Our method achieves up to 3x file size reductions for strain and strain rate data in lossless mode across diverse datasets. In lossy mode, compression improves to 6x with near-perfect signal fidelity, and up to 10x is reached with acceptable signal degradation. It delivers fast throughput (100-200 MB/s using a single-thread and up to 750 MB/s using 8-threads), enabling real-time deployment even under high data rates. We validated its performance on 15 datasets from a variety of acquisition environments, demonstrating its speed, robustness, and broad applicability. DASPack provides a practical foundation for long-term, sustainable DAS data management in large-scale monitoring networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16390v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleix Segui, Arantza Ugalde, Andreas Fichtner, Sergi Ventosa, Josep Ramon Morros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An effective physics-informed neural operator framework for predicting wavefields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16431v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving the wave equation is fundamental for geophysical applications. However, numerical solutions of the Helmholtz equation face significant computational and memory challenges. Therefore, we introduce a physics-informed convolutional neural operator (PICNO) to solve the Helmholtz equation efficiently. The PICNO takes both the background wavefield corresponding to a homogeneous medium and the velocity model as input function space, generating the scattered wavefield as the output function space. Our workflow integrates PDE constraints directly into the training process, enabling the neural operator to not only fit the available data but also capture the underlying physics governing wave phenomena. PICNO allows for high-resolution reasonably accurate predictions even with limited training samples, and it demonstrates significant improvements over a purely data-driven convolutional neural operator (CNO), particularly in predicting high-frequency wavefields. These features and improvements are important for waveform inversion down the road.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16431v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Ma, Tariq Alkhalifah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient mechanical evaluation of railway earthworks using a towed seismic array and Bayesian inference of MASW data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assessing Railway Earthworks (RE) requires non-destructive and time-efficient diagnostic tools. This study evaluates the relevance of shear-wave velocity ($V_s$) profiling using Multichannel Analysis of Surface Waves (MASW) for detecting Low Velocity Layers (LVLs) in disturbed RE zones. To enhance time-efficiency, a towed seismic setup (Landstreamer) was compared with a conventional one. Once qualified, the Landstreamer was deployed on the ballast for roll-along acquisition, showing greatly improved efficiency and good imaging capability. A probabilistic framework adopted in this study additionally enhances quantification of uncertainties and helps in interpretation of $V_s$ models, facilitating reliable decision-making in infrastructure management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16491v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Audrey Burzawa, Ludovic Bodet, Marine Dangeard, Brian Barrett, Daniel Byrne, Robert Whitehead, Corentin Chaptal, Jos\'e Cunha Teixeira, Julio Cardenas, Ramon Sanchez Gonzalez, Asger Eriksen, Amine Dhemaied</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EPBench: A Benchmark for Short-term Earthquake Prediction with Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15588v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Since the beginning of this century, the significant advancements in artificial intelligence and neural networks have offered the potential to bring new transformations to short-term earthquake prediction research. However, currently, there is no widely used benchmark for this task. To address this, we have built a new benchmark (EPBench), which is, to our knowledge, the first global regional-scale short-term earthquake prediction benchmark. Our benchmark comprises 924,472 earthquake records and 2959 multimodal earthquake records collected from seismic networks around the world. Each record includes basic information such as time, longitude and latitude, magnitude, while each multimodal record includes waveform and moment tensor information additionally, covering a time span from 1970 to 2021. To evaluate performance of models on this task, we have established a series of data partitions and evaluation methods tailored to the short-term earthquake prediction task. We also provide a variety of tools to assist future researchers in partitioning the data according to their geographical understanding. Our benchmark includes a variety of neural network models widely used for time series forecasting, as well as a statistical-based model currently employed by seismological bureaus in several countries. We hope this benchmark will serve as a guide to attract more researchers to explore new methods for addressing this task, which holds great significance for human existence. Code is available at https://github.com/CoderZY-X/EPBench</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15588v4</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyu Xu, Qingliang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
