<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 05:00:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Neutron Attenuation from Bulk Density and Moisture for Soil Carbon Measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inelastic neutron scattering (INS) enables rapid, non-destructive in situ measurements of soil elemental composition over large soil volumes. Standard INS yields bulk elemental concentrations, but spatially resolved measurements require techniques such as Associated Particle Imaging (API), which pairs neutron detection with coincident alpha detection to reconstruct the location of the neutron interaction. One of the unique advantages of API is its capability to measure all major soil components simultaneously, allowing for the estimation of both bulk density and water content directly from the measured neutron-induced gamma-ray spectra. Accurate interpretation of bulk INS-API data depends on correcting for both gamma-ray and neutron attenuation in soil. Although gamma attenuation can be calculated from known mass attenuation coefficient data and density, neutron attenuation is more complex, depending on neutron energy, soil composition, bulk density, and hydrogen content from water and organic matter. We use Monte Carlo simulations of soils with varied compositions, bulk densities, and water contents to model neutron attenuation and develop a simple predictive model requiring only dry bulk density and volumetric water content. We validate this model experimentally using an INS-API system with controlled soil columns, finding agreement within 10 percent at 30 cm depth. This approach enables practical, field-ready correction of INS-API measurements for neutron attenuation, laying the groundwork for a self-consistent measurement framework that can address the elemental composition of soil carbon assessments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09032v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Larsen, Valerie Smykalov, Cristina Castanha, Eoin Brodie, Mauricio Ayllon Unzueta, Bernhard Ludewigt, Arun Persaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variability in Performance of a Machine-Learning Seismicity Catalog: Central Italy, 2016-2017</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) catalogs contain many more earthquakes than routine catalogs, but their performance in phase picking and earthquake detection has not been fully evaluated. We develop station-level detection probabilities using logistic regression and combine them across a seismic network to compute spatial magnitude-of-completeness fields. We apply this approach to two catalogs from the 2016-2017 Central Italy sequence that were constructed from the same seismic network, one routine and one ML based. At the station level, the ML picker increases detection sensitivity by identifying smaller magnitude events and detecting earthquakes at greater distances. Spatially, the magnitude-of-completeness decreases substantially, with median values shifting from 1.6 to 0.5 for P waves and from 1.7 to 0.5 for S waves. However, the ML catalog also shows greater variability in station-level performance than the routine catalog. These results demonstrate that ML-based improvements in detectability are widespread but spatially non-uniform, highlighting their benefits, their limitations, and the potential for further improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09792v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaehong Chung, Yifan Yu, Lauro Chiaraluce, Maddalena Michele, Gregory C. Beroza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admissibility of Solitary Wave Modes in Long-Runout Debris Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09280v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Debris flows often exhibit coherent wave structures-shock-like roll waves on steeper slopes and weaker, more sinusoidal dispersive pulses on gentler slopes. Coarse-rich heads raise basal resistance, whereas fines-rich tails lower it; in gentle reaches, small-amplitude pulses can locally transport momentum across low-resistance segments. We focus on this gentle-slope, long-wave, low-amplitude regime, where the base-flow Froude number is order unity. In this limit, we obtain a Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) reduction from depth-averaged balances with frictional (Coulomb) and viscous-plastic basal options, using a curvature-type internal normal-stress closure in the long-wave small-k regime. Multiple-scale analysis yields effective nonlinear and dispersive coefficients. We also introduce a practical nonlinearity diagnostic that can be computed from observed crest speeds and flow thicknesses. When laboratory-frame crest celerity is available, we estimate an effective quadratic coefficient from the KdV speed-amplitude relation and report its ratio to the shallow-water reference. When only a depth-averaged first-surge speed and thickness are available, we use the same construction to form a velocity-based proxy and note its bias near zero. A Froude-slope diagram organizes published cases into a steep-slope roll-wave domain and a gentle-slope corridor where KdV pulses are admissible. Numerical solutions of the full depth-averaged model produce cnoidal and solitary waves that agree with the reduced KdV predictions within this corridor. We regard dispersive pulses as a regime-specific complement to roll-wave dynamics, offering a condition-dependent contribution to mobility on gentle reaches rather than a universal explanation for long runout.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09280v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6kxj-4vpg</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 112, 055112 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Louis-S. Bouchard, Seulgi Moon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Failure to track a stable AMOC state under rapid climate change</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) is a tipping element of the climate system. The current estimate of the global warming threshold for the onset of an AMOC collapse is +4C. However, such a threshold may not be meaningful because AMOC stability depends on the rate of radiative forcing and background climate state. Here, we identify an AMOC stabilising mechanism that operates on timescales longer than present-day radiative forcing increase. Slow forcing permits coherent adjustment of surface and interior ocean properties, supported by enhanced evaporation and reduced sea-ice extent, counteracting destabilising feedbacks. This mechanism is explicitly demonstrated in a slow CO2 increase experiment (+0.5 ppm/yr), in which the AMOC remains stable up to +5.5C of global warming. By contrast, under intermediate- and high-emission scenarios, the AMOC collapses at substantially lower warming levels (+2.2C and +2.8C, respectively). Our findings demonstrate the strong radiative forcing path dependence of AMOC tipping and imply that limiting the rate of radiative forcing is critical for reducing the near-term risk of an AMOC collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09964v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ren\'e M. van Westen, Reyk B\"orner, Henk A. Dijkstra</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
