<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 05:01:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Analysis of the Depth-Velocity Trade-off in Reflection Seismology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Seismic interpretation is strongly influenced by the relationship between subsurface layer depth and velocity. Small variations in these parameters can produce almost identical responses, characterizing the depth-velocity trade-off phenomenon. This work proposes a statistical and computational approach to evaluate the extent of this effect through Monte Carlo simulations involving thousands of synthetic models. The analysis consists of generating random depth-velocity pairs, computing travel times, and calculating the root mean square error (RMSE) relative to a reference model. The results show that multiple parameter combinations yield nearly indistinguishable travel times, confirming the existence of broad ambiguity regions. Finally, a two-layer geological velocity model is presented to illustrate the relationship between structure and velocity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04328v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael da Silva Garcia, Francisco Marcio Barboza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The heterogeneous near-surface velocity structure of a carbonate-hosted seismogenic fault zone and its dependence on the investigated length scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04717v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Field geological studies highlighted the heterogeneous structure of fault zones from the meter- to millimeter scale, but such internal variability is not generally resolved by seismological techniques due to spatial resolution limits. The near-surface velocity structure of the Vado di Corno seismogenic fault zone was quantified at different length scales, from laboratory measurements of ultrasonic velocities (few centimeters rock samples, 1 MHz source) to high-resolution first-arrival seismic tomography (spatial resolution to a few meters). The fault zone juxtaposed structural units with contrasting ultrasonic velocities. The fault core cataclastic units were slower compared to damage zone units. A negative correlation between ultrasonic velocity and porosity was observed, with dispersion in fault core units related to varying degree of textural maturity and pore space sealing by calcite. Low-velocity outliers in the damage zone were instead linked to microfracture networks with local cataclasis and partial calcite sealing. P-wave high-resolution seismic tomography imaged distinct fault-bounded rock bodies, matching the geometry and size of field-mapped structural units. At this length scale, relatively fast fault core units and low-strain damage zones contrasted with a very slow intensely fractured high-strain damage zone. The discrepancy between higher ultrasonic velocities and lower tomography-derived ones was reconciled through an effective medium approach considering the effect of meso-scale fractures in each unit. This revealed a heterogeneous fault zone velocity structure with different scaling among structural units. Lastly, the persistence of a thick compliant high-strain damage zone at shallow depth may significantly affect fault zone mechanics and the distribution of near-surface deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04717v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Fondriest, Thomas M. Mitchell, Maurizio Vassallo, Stephane Garambois, Giuseppe Di Giulio, Fabrizio Balsamo, Marta Pischiutta, Mai-Linh Doan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earthquakes and cluster dynamics during Interseismic phases between the Northern and Central Apennines (Italy)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the last thirty years, the Northern and Central Apennines (Italy) have been affected by three main destructive seismic sequences: the 1997 Colfiorito (three events $M_L &gt; 5.5$), the 2009 L'Aquila (one event $M_L &gt; 5.5$), and the 2016--2017 Amatrice--Visso--Norcia (three events $M_L &gt; 5.5$). Several studies have analysed the spatio-temporal evolution and processes driving each sequence, focusing mainly on the foreshock--mainshock--aftershock periods. Here, we focus on the 2018--2024 interseismic phase, aiming to unravel the long-term seismogenic behaviour of this region. We first relocated the earthquake catalogue and identified clusters through a declustering algorithm. During this phase, background seismicity and most clusters were arranged in a 2--3 km thick low-angle layer. We found that (i) most clusters were driven by aseismic processes, (ii) the depth of both clusters and the seismicity layer increased toward the southeast, (iii) the volume of clusters decreased toward the southeast, and (iv) the low-angle layer almost disappeared in the L'Aquila area. Comparing two interseismic phases (2011--2016 and 2018--2024), we found striking similarities, with events occurring at the same sites and characterized by both foreshock--mainshock--aftershock and swarm-like behaviour. In addition, the L'Aquila area was seismically more silent compared to the northern sites during both interseismic phases. We propose that these different long-term seismogenetic behaviours reflect variations in the structure and rheology of the upper crust from the Northern to the Central Apennines. This highlights the important role of structural inheritance in controlling how active deformation affects the interseismic period.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04829v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marion Baques, Piero Poli, Michele Fondriest</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
