<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.geo-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph</link>
    <description>physics.geo-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.geo-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 05:01:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Global River Forecasting with a Topology-Informed AI Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22293v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: River systems operate as inherently interconnected continuous networks, meaning river hydrodynamic simulation ought to be a systemic process. However, widespread hydrology data scarcity often restricts data-driven forecasting to isolated predictions. To achieve systemic simulation and reduce reliance on river observations, we present GraphRiverCast (GRC), a topology-informed AI foundation model designed to simulate multivariate river hydrodynamics in global river systems. GRC is capable of operating in a "ColdStart" mode, generating predictions without relying on historical river states for initialization. In 7-day global pseudo-hindcasts, GRC-ColdStart functions as a robust standalone simulator, achieving a Nash-Sutcliffe Efficiency (NSE) of approximately 0.82 without exhibiting the significant error accumulation typical of autoregressive paradigms. Ablation studies reveal that topological encoding serves as indispensable structural information in the absence of historical states, explicitly guiding hydraulic connectivity and network-scale mass redistribution to reconstruct flow dynamics. Furthermore, when adapted locally via a pre-training and fine-tuning strategy, GRC consistently outperforms physics-based and locally-trained AI baselines. Crucially, this superiority extends from gauged reaches to full river networks, underscoring the necessity of topology encoding and physics-based pre-training. Built on a physics-aligned neural operator architecture, GRC enables rapid and cross-scale adaptive simulation, establishing a collaborative paradigm bridging global hydrodynamic knowledge with local hydrological reality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22293v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hancheng Ren, Gang Zhao, Shuo Wang, Louise Slater, Dai Yamazaki, Shu Liu, Jingfang Fan, Shibo Cui, Ziming Yu, Shengyu Kang, Depeng Zuo, Dingzhi Peng, Zongxue Xu, Bo Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mimicking the earth core conditions with ultrafast laser materials interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrafast lasers create extreme, non-equilibrium thermodynamic conditions that can transiently reach pressures and temperatures comparable to interior core of the earth. Here we show that femtosecond excitation of amorphous silica-hafnia multilayer dielectrics drives the formation of high-pressure crystalline phases of silica including stishovite, seifertite, and the pyrite-type high density structure, within confined subsurface regions.Using TEM, SAED, and 4D-STEM, we directly map nanoscale phase evolution and identify crystalline motifs embedded inside laser generated blisters.Complementary molecular dynamics simualtions reveal the thermodynamic pathway underlying these transformations, where rapid electronic pressure initiates densification and octahedral coordination, followed by temperature driven crystallization and displacive transitions during ultrafast quenching. The resulting polymorphs reflects a dual-stage pathway inaccessible under equilibrium processing. Our results establish femtosecond laser excitation as a viable route to synthesize and stabilize ultrahigh-density high pressure silica phases under ambient conditions, without a diamond anvil cell, with implications for laser-damage mechanisms, high-energy-density materials, and planetary physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22460v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Yaseen Noor, Aram Yedigaryan, Gabriel Calderon, Arshak Tsaturyan, Elena Kanchan, Jinwoo Hwang, Carmen S. Menoni, Jean-Philippe Colombier, Enam Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Posterior Sampling for Seismic Data Recovery via Score-Based Generative Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01536v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Seismic data restoration is a fundamental task in seismic exploration, yet remains challenging under complex and unknown degradations. Traditional model-driven or task-specific learning methods often require retraining for each degradation type and fail to generalize effectively to unseen field data. In this work, we introduce an unsupervised Posterior Sampling Framework (PSF) built upon Score-based Generative Models (SGMs) for unified seismic data restoration. PSF leverages the pre-trained unconditional SGMs as a seismic-aware generative prior and derives a generalized conditional score function associated with the forward operator of each inverse problem. This enables posterior sampling across different seismic restoration tasks without retraining or supervision. Additionally, an adaptive noise-level estimation mechanism is incorporated to dynamically regulate the noise suppression strength during sampling, enhancing flexibility under varying signal-to-noise ratios and degradation conditions.Extensive experiments on seismic denoising, interpolation, compressed sensing, and deconvolution demonstrate that PSF delivers high-quality samples and exhibits robust generalization to out-of-distribution data. These results highlight the potential of SGMs as a universal prior for seismic inverse problems and establish PSF as a flexible framework for unsupervised posterior inference across diverse degradation scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01536v2</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuangji Meng, Jinghuai Gao, Zongben Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
