<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of Spectrum Sharing Algorithms for Networks with Heterogeneous Wireless Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As highlighted in the National Spectrum Strategy, Dynamic Spectrum Access (DSA) is key for enabling 6G networks to meet the increasing demand for spectrum from various, heterogeneous emerging applications. In this paper, we consider heterogeneous wireless networks with multiple 6G base stations (BS) and a limited number of frequency bands available for transmission. Each BS is associated with a geographical location, a coverage area, and a bandwidth requirement. We assume that clients/UEs are within the corresponding BS's coverage area. To avoid interference, we impose that BSs with overlapping coverage areas must use different frequency bands. We address the challenging problem of efficiently allocating contiguous frequency bands to BSs while avoiding interference. Specifically, we define performance metrics that capture the feasibility of the frequency allocation task, the number of BSs that can be allocated within the limited frequency bands, and the amount of resources utilized by the network. Then, we consider five different DSA algorithms that prioritize BSs based on different features - one of these algorithms is known in the graph theory literature as Welsh-Powell graph colouring algorithm - and compare their performance using extensive simulations. Our results show that DSA algorithms that attempt to maximize the chances of obtaining a feasible frequency allocation - which have been widely studied in the literature - tend to under-perform in all other metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17369v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankit Walishetti, Igor Kadota, Aidan Kim, Colin Ward, Eduardo Gutierrez, Randall Berry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hierarchical Gradient Tracking Algorithm for Mitigating Subnet-Drift in Fog Learning Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Federated learning (FL) encounters scalability challenges when implemented over fog networks that do not follow FL's conventional star topology architecture. Semi-decentralized FL (SD-FL) has proposed a solution for device-to-device (D2D) enabled networks that divides model cooperation into two stages: at the lower stage, D2D communications is employed for local model aggregations within subnetworks (subnets), while the upper stage handles device-server (DS) communications for global model aggregations. However, existing SD-FL schemes are based on gradient diversity assumptions that become performance bottlenecks as data distributions become more heterogeneous. In this work, we develop semi-decentralized gradient tracking (SD-GT), the first SD-FL methodology that removes the need for such assumptions by incorporating tracking terms into device updates for each communication layer. Our analytical characterization of SD-GT reveals upper bounds on convergence for non-convex, convex, and strongly-convex problems. We show how the bounds enable the development of an optimization algorithm that navigates the performance-efficiency trade-off by tuning subnet sampling rate and D2D rounds for each global training interval. Our subsequent numerical evaluations demonstrate that SD-GT obtains substantial improvements in trained model quality and communication cost relative to baselines in SD-FL and gradient tracking on several datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17430v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan Chen, Shiqiang Wang, Christopher G. Brinton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Resource Allocation for Multi-modal Semantic Communication in Mobile AIGC Networks: A Diffusion-based Game Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobile Artificial Intelligence-Generated Content (AIGC) networks enable massive users to obtain customized content generation services. However, users still need to download a large number of AIGC outputs from mobile AIGC service providers, which strains communication resources and increases the risk of transmission failures. Fortunately, Semantic Communication (SemCom) can improve transmission efficiency and reliability through semantic information processing. Moreover, recent advances in Generative Artificial Intelligence (GAI) further enhanced the effectiveness of SemCom through its powerful generative capabilities. However, how to strike a balance between high-quality content generation and the size of semantic information transmitted is a major challenge. In this paper, we propose a Generative Diffusion Model (GDM)-based multi-modal SemCom (GM-SemCom) framework. The framework improves the accuracy of information reconstruction by integrating GDMs and multi-modal semantic information and also adopts a controllable extraction module for efficient and controllable problems of unstable data recovery and slow decoding speed in GAI-enabled SemCom. Then, we introduce a novel metric called Age of Semantic Information (AoSI) based on the concept of Age of Information (AoI) to quantify the freshness of semantic information. To address the resource trading problem within the framework, we propose a Stackelberg game model, which integrates the AoSI with psychological factors to provide a comprehensive measure of user utility. Furthermore, we propose a GDM-based algorithm to solve the game under incomplete information. Compared with the traditional deep reinforcement learning algorithms, numerical results demonstrate that the proposed algorithm converges faster and is closer to the Stackelberg equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17506v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Liu, Ming Xiao, Jinbo Wen, Jiawen Kang, Ruichen Zhang, Tao Zhang, Dusit Niyato, Weiting Zhang, Ying Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Improved Beluga Whale Optimization Algorithm for Solving Localization Problem in Swarm Robotic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In Swarm Robotic Systems (SRSs), only a few robots are equipped with Global Positioning System (GPS) devices, known as anchors. A challenge lies in inferring the positions of other unknown robots based on the positions of anchors. Existing solutions estimate their positions using distance measurements between unknown robots and anchors. Based on existing solutions, this study proposes a novel meta-heuristic algorithm - Improved Beluga Whale Optimization Algorithm (IBWO) to address the localization problem of SRSs, focusing on enhancing the accuracy of localization results. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of this study. Specifically, we test the localization accuracy of robots under different proportions of anchors, different communication radius of robots, and different total number of robots. Compared to the traditional multilateration method and four other localization methods based on meta-heuristic algorithms, the localization accuracy of this method is consistently superior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17665v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuhao Teng, Qian Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation Pre-Offloading for MEC-Enabled Vehicular Networks via Trajectory Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Task offloading is of paramount importance to efficiently orchestrate vehicular wireless networks, necessitating the availability of information regarding the current network status and computational resources. However, due to the mobility of the vehicles and the limited computational resources for performing task offloading in near-real-time, such schemes may require high latency, thus, become even infeasible. To address this issue, in this paper, we present a Trajectory Prediction-based Pre-offloading Decision (TPPD) algorithm for analyzing the historical trajectories of vehicles to predict their future coordinates, thereby allowing for computational resource allocation in advance. We first utilize the Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) network model to predict each vehicle's movement trajectory. Then, based on the task requirements and the predicted trajectories, we devise a dynamic resource allocation algorithm using a Double Deep Q-Network (DDQN) that enables the edge server to minimize task processing delay, while ensuring effective utilization of the available computational resources. Our simulation results verify the effectiveness of the proposed approach, showcasing that, as compared with traditional real-time task offloading strategies, the proposed TPPD algorithm significantly reduces task processing delay while improving resource utilization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17681v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Zhang, Bo Yang, Zhiwen Yu, Xuelin Cao, George C. Alexandropoulos, Yan Zhang, Chau Yuen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying Privacy in 5G Stand Alone Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ensuring user privacy remains critical in mobile networks, particularly with the rise of connected devices and denser 5G infrastructure. Privacy concerns have persisted across 2G, 3G, and 4G/LTE networks. Recognizing these concerns, the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) has made privacy enhancements in 5G Release 15. However, the extent of operator adoption remains unclear, especially as most networks operate in 5G Non Stand Alone (NSA) mode, relying on 4G Core Networks. This study provides the first qualitative and experimental comparison between 5G NSA and Stand Alone (SA) in real operator networks, focusing on privacy enhancements addressing top eight pre-5G attacks based on recent academic literature. Additionally, it evaluates the privacy levels of OpenAirInterface (OAI), a leading open-source software for 5G, against real network deployments for the same attacks. The analysis reveals two new 5G privacy vulnerabilities, underscoring the need for further research and stricter standards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17700v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3636534.3690696</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stavros Eleftherakis, Timothy Otim, Giuseppe Santaromita, Almudena Diaz Zayas, Domenico Giustiniano, Nicolas Kourtellis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARS: Multi-radio Architecture with Radio Selection using Decision Trees for emerging mesoscale CPS/IoT applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18043v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IoT is rapidly growing from small-scale apps to large-scale apps. Small-scale apps employ short-range radios like Zigbee,BLE while large-scale apps employ long-range radios like LoRa,NB-IoT. The other upcoming category of apps like P2P energy-trade in smart homes are termed mesoscale IoT apps. There are no specialized radios for these apps. They either use short/long-range radios. To close this gap, we explored mesoscale apps using the COTS IoT radios available. Our qualitative analysis identifies Zigbee and LoRa as potential candidates. Our quantitative analysis on single and multi-hop topologies showed that Zigbee and LoRa achieve competitive throughput at a distance of 500-1200m from the gateway. A fundamental finding of these analyses is that a multi-radio system that can efficiently switch between Zigbee and LoRa performs better than the single-radio systems. However, instantaneously selecting and switching to a high-throughput radio during transmission is not trivial because of the erratic link quality dynamics. To address this issue, we developed MARS, that uses path quality metrics to instantaneously select the high-throughput radio during transmission. However, realizing MARS on resource-constrained end devices entails the challenge of obtaining instantaneous path-quality metrics. Traditional path quality estimation is not instantaneous due to propagation and queuing delays. We overcome this challenge by showing that collecting local path metrics as input to our decision trees provides sufficient information to instantaneously identify the high-throughput radio. The radio selector of MARS is powered by TAO-CART trees. The evaluation of MARS on a large-scale mesh topology at two different locations shows that MARS can efficiently identify and switch to the high-throughput radio during transmission, leading to an average throughput gain of 48.2% and 49.79% over its competitors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18043v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jothi Prasanna Shanmuga Sundaram, Arman Zharmagambetov, Magzhan Gabidolla, Miguel A. Carreira-Perpinan, Alberto Cerpa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-Air Deep Learning Integrated Semantic Inference Models for Enhanced Earth Observation Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15246v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Earth Observation (EO) systems play a crucial role in achieving Sustainable Development Goals by collecting and analyzing vital global data through satellite networks. These systems are essential for tasks like mapping, disaster monitoring, and resource management, but they face challenges in processing and transmitting large volumes of EO data, especially in specialized fields such as agriculture and real-time disaster response. Domain-adapted Large Language Models (LLMs) provide a promising solution by facilitating data fusion between extensive EO data and semantic EO data. By improving integration and interpretation of diverse datasets, LLMs address the challenges of processing specialized information in agriculture and disaster response applications. This fusion enhances the accuracy and relevance of transmitted data. This paper presents a framework for semantic communication in EO satellite networks, aimed at improving data transmission efficiency and overall system performance through cognitive processing techniques. The proposed system employs Discrete-Task-Oriented Source-Channel Coding (DT-JSCC) and Semantic Data Augmentation (SA) to focus on relevant information while minimizing communication overhead. By integrating cognitive semantic processing and inter-satellite links, the framework enhances the analysis and transmission of multispectral satellite imagery, improving object detection, pattern recognition, and real-time decision-making. The introduction of Cognitive Semantic Augmentation (CSA) allows satellites to process and transmit semantic information, boosting adaptability to changing environments and application needs. This end-to-end architecture is tailored for next-generation satellite networks, such as those supporting 6G, and demonstrates significant improvements in efficiency and accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15246v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-fu Chou, Vu Nguyen Ha, Prabhu Thiruvasagam, Thanh-Dung Le, Geoffrey Eappen, Ti Ti Nguyen, Luis M. Garces-Socarras, Jorge L. Gonzalez-Rios, Juan Carlos Merlano-Duncan, Symeon Chatzinotas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
