<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 01:37:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MLOPS in a multicloud environment: Typical Network Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As artificial intelligence, machine learning, and data science continue to drive the data-centric economy, the challenges of implementing machine learning on a single machine due to extensive data and computational needs have led to the adoption of cloud computing solutions. This research paper explores the design and implementation of a secure, cloud-native machine learning operations (MLOPS) pipeline that supports multi-cloud environments. The primary objective is to create a robust infrastructure that facilitates secure data collection, real-time model inference, and efficient management of the machine learning lifecycle. By leveraging cloud providers' capabilities, the solution aims to streamline the deployment and maintenance of machine learning models, ensuring high availability, scalability, and security. This paper details the network topology, problem description, business and technical requirements, trade-offs, and the provider selection process for achieving an optimal MLOPS environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20494v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyang Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A UAV-Enabled Time-Sensitive Data Collection Scheme for Grassland Monitoring Edge Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grassland monitoring is essential for the sustainable development of grassland resources. Traditional Internet of Things (IoT) devices generate critical ecological data, making data loss unacceptable, but the harsh environment complicates data collection. Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV) and mobile edge computing (MEC) offer efficient data collection solutions, enhancing performance on resource-limited mobile devices. In this context, this paper is the first to investigate a UAV-enabled time-sensitive data collection problem (TSDCMP) within grassland monitoring edge networks (GMENs). Unlike many existing data collection scenarios, this problem has three key challenges. First, the total amount of data collected depends significantly on the data collection duration and arrival time of UAV at each access point (AP). Second, the volume of data at different APs varies among regions due to differences in monitoring objects and vegetation coverage. Third, the service requests time and locations from APs are often not adjacent topologically. To address these issues, We formulate the TSDCMP for UAV-enabled GMENs as a mixed-integer programming model in a single trip. This model considers constraints such as the limited energy of UAV, the coupled routing and time scheduling, and the state of APs and UAV arrival time. Subsequently, we propose a novel cooperative heuristic algorithm based on temporal-spatial correlations (CHTSC) that integrates a modified dynamic programming (MDP) into an iterated local search to solve the TSDCMP for UAV-enabled GMENs. This approach fully takes into account the temporal and spatial relationships between consecutive service requests from APs. Systematic simulation studies demonstrate that the mixed-integer programming model effectively represents the TSDCMP within UAV-enabled GMENs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20585v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongbin Jiao, Zihao Wang, Wen Fan, Weibo Yang, Peng Yang, Zhanhuan Shang, Shi Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fully Open-Source End-to-End Private 5G Network over Unlicensed Frequency Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fifth generation of mobile networks (5G) represents the latest development in mobile communications. It has been designed to support several types of data traffic and to meet more performance requirements than ever before. These characteristics make 5G very attractive for current but also novel public and private industries and services. However, because of coverage, regulatory, business, and security reasons, many of these novel applications can only be deployed as part of a private network. The cost of licensed frequencies makes such approach prohibitive for many stakeholders, and therefore unlicensed frequency bands represent a more affordable option. Even so, private 5G networks for use in globally unlicensed frequency bands do not yet exist. In this paper we present the first end-to-end private 5G network operating in a globally unlicensed frequency band, using general purpose computers, open-source software and software-defined radio. We evidence its working and show that the choice of the hardware can significantly affect the performance of the network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20652v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faycal Bouhafs (University of New South Wales Canberra), Sayed Amir Hoseini (University of New South Wales Canberra), Syed Danial Ali Shah (University of New South Wales Canberra), Frank den Hartog (University of New South Wales Canberra, University of Canberra)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Optimization Framework for Channel Simulation-Based Base Station Placement and Transmission Power Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study proposes an adaptive experimental design framework for channel simulation-based base station (BS) design that supports joint optimization of transmission power and placement. We consider a system in which multiple transmitters provide wireless services over a shared frequency band. Our objective is to maximize the average throughput within an area of interest. System operators can design the system parameters prior to deployment by iterating through channel simulations and updating parameters. However, accurate channel simulations are computationally expensive, thus it is preferable to configure the system using a limited number of simulation iterations. We develop a solver for this problem based on Bayesian optimization (BO), a black-box optimization method. Numerical results demonstrate that our proposed framework can achieve 18-22% higher throughput performance compared to conventional placement and power optimization strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20778v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koya Sato, Katsuya Suto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Model (LLM)-enabled Graphs in Dynamic Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in generative artificial intelligence (AI), and particularly the integration of large language models (LLMs), have had considerable impact on multiple domains. Meanwhile, enhancing dynamic network performance is a crucial element in promoting technological advancement and meeting the growing demands of users in many applications areas involving networks. In this article, we explore an integration of LLMs and graphs in dynamic networks, focusing on potential applications and a practical study. Specifically, we first review essential technologies and applications of LLM-enabled graphs, followed by an exploration of their advantages in dynamic networking. Subsequently, we introduce and analyze LLM-enabled graphs and their applications in dynamic networks from the perspective of LLMs as different roles. On this basis, we propose a novel framework of LLM-enabled graphs for networking optimization, and then present a case study on UAV networking, concentrating on optimizing UAV trajectory and communication resource allocation to validate the effectiveness of the proposed framework. Finally, we outline several potential future extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20840v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geng Sun, Yixian Wang, Dusit Niyato, Jiacheng Wang, Xinying Wang, H. Vincent Poor, Khaled B. Letaief</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing 5G-Advanced Networks for Time-critical Applications: The Role of L4S</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As 5G networks strive to support advanced time-critical applications, such as immersive Extended Reality (XR), cloud gaming, and autonomous driving, the demand for Real-time Broadband Communication (RTBC) grows. In this article, we present the main mechanisms of Low Latency, Low Loss, and Scalable Throughput (L4S). Subsequently, we investigate the support and challenges of L4S technology in the latest 3GPP 5G-Advanced Release 18 (R18) standard. Our case study, using a prototype system for a real-time communication (RTC) application, demonstrates the superiority of L4S technology. The experimental results show that, compared with the GCC algorithm, the proposed L4S-GCC algorithm can reduce the stalling rate by 1.51%-2.80% and increase the bandwidth utilization by 11.4%-31.4%. The results emphasize the immense potential of L4S technology in enhancing transmission performance in time-critical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20852v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangjin Pan, Shugong Xu, Pin Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physically-consistent Multi-band Massive MIMO Systems: A Radio Resource Management Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20945v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive multiple-input multiple-output (mMIMO) antenna systems and inter-band carrier aggregation (CA)-enabled multi-band communication are two key technologies to achieve very high data rates in beyond fifth generation (B5G) wireless systems. We propose a joint optimization framework for such systems where the mMIMO antenna spacing selection, precoder optimization, optimum sub-carrier selection and optimum power allocation are carried out simultaneously. We harness the bandwidth gain existing in a tightly coupled base station mMIMO antenna system to avoid sophisticated, non-practical antenna systems for multi-band operation. In particular, we analyze a multi-band communication system using a circuit-theoretic model to consider physical characteristics of a tightly coupled antenna array, and formulate a joint optimization problem to maximize the sum-rate. As part of the optimization, we also propose a novel block iterative water-filling-based sub-carrier selection and power allocation optimization algorithm for the multi-band mMIMO system. A novel sub-carrier windowing-based sub-carrier selection scheme is also proposed which considers the physical constraints (hardware limitation) at the mobile user devices. We carryout the optimizations in two ways: (i) to optimize the antenna spacing selection in an offline manner, and (ii) to select antenna elements from a dense array dynamically. Via computer simulations, we illustrate superior bandwidth gains present in the tightly-coupled colinear and rectangular planar antenna arrays, compared to the loosely-coupled or tightly-coupled parallel arrays. We further show the optimum sum-rate performance of the proposed optimization-based framework under various power allocation schemes and various user capability scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20945v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuwan Balasuriya, Amine Mezghani, Ekram Hossain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models (LLMs) for Semantic Communication in Edge-based IoT Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the advent of Fifth Generation (5G) and Sixth Generation (6G) communication technologies, as well as the Internet of Things (IoT), semantic communication is gaining attention among researchers as current communication technologies are approaching Shannon's limit. On the other hand, Large Language Models (LLMs) can understand and generate human-like text, based on extensive training on diverse datasets with billions of parameters. Considering the recent near-source computational technologies like Edge, in this article, we give an overview of a framework along with its modules, where LLMs can be used under the umbrella of semantic communication at the network edge for efficient communication in IoT networks. Finally, we discuss a few applications and analyze the challenges and opportunities to develop such systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20970v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alakesh Kalita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resilient Entanglement Distribution in a Multihop Quantum Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The evolution of quantum networking requires architectures capable of dynamically reconfigurable entanglement distribution to meet diverse user needs and ensure tolerance against transmission disruptions. We introduce multihop quantum networks to improve network reach and resilience by enabling quantum communications across intermediate nodes, thus broadening network connectivity and increasing scalability. We present multihop two-qubit polarization-entanglement distribution within a quantum network at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory campus. Our system uses wavelength-selective switches for adaptive bandwidth management on a software-defined quantum network that integrates a quantum data plane with classical data and control planes, creating a flexible, reconfigurable mesh. Our network distributes entanglement across six nodes within three subnetworks, each located in a separate building, optimizing quantum state fidelity and transmission rate through adaptive resource management. Additionally, we demonstrate the network's resilience by implementing a link recovery approach that monitors and reroutes quantum resources to maintain service continuity despite link failures -- paving the way for scalable and reliable quantum networking infrastructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20443v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muneer Alshowkan, Joseph M. Lukens, Hsuan-Hao Lu, Nicholas A. Peters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Learning Based Collaborative Automatic Modulation Classification for Hierarchical Cognitive Radio Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20772v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In hierarchical cognitive radio networks, edge or cloud servers utilize the data collected by edge devices for modulation classification, which, however, is faced with problems of the computation load, transmission overhead, and data privacy. In this article, an edge learning (EL) based framework jointly mobilizing the edge device and the edge server for intelligent co-inference is proposed to realize the collaborative automatic modulation classification (C-AMC) between them. A spectrum semantic compression neural network is designed for the edge device to compress the collected raw data into a compact semantic embedding that is then sent to the edge server via the wireless channel. On the edge server side, a modulation classification neural network combining the bidirectional long-short term memory and attention structures is elaborated to determine the modulation type from the noisy semantic embedding. The C-AMC framework decently balances the computation resources of both sides while avoiding the high transmission overhead and data privacy leakage. Both the offline and online training procedures of the C-AMC framework are elaborated. The compression strategy of the C-AMC framework is also developed to further facilitate the deployment, especially for the resource-constrained edge device. Simulation results show the superiority of the EL-based C-AMC framework in terms of the classification accuracy, computational complexity, and the data compression rate as well as reveal useful insights paving the practical implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20772v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peihao Dong, Chaowei He, Shen Gao, Fuhui Zhou, Qihui Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Ultra-Reliable 6G: Transformer and Semantic Localization Empowered Robust Beamforming in Millimeter-Wave Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02000v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Advancements in 6G wireless technology have elevated the importance of beamforming, especially for attaining ultra-high data rates via millimeter-wave (mmWave) frequency deployment. Although promising, mmWave bands require substantial beam training to achieve precise beamforming. While initial deep learning models that use RGB camera images demonstrated promise in reducing beam training overhead, their performance suffers due to sensitivity to lighting and environmental variations. Due to this sensitivity, Quality of Service (QoS) fluctuates, eventually affecting the stability and dependability of networks in dynamic environments. This emphasizes a critical need for robust solutions. This paper proposes a robust beamforming technique to ensure consistent QoS under varying environmental conditions. An optimization problem has been formulated to maximize users' data rates. To solve the formulated NP-hard optimization problem, we decompose it into two subproblems: the semantic localization problem and the optimal beam selection problem. To solve the semantic localization problem, we propose a novel method that leverages the K-means clustering and YOLOv8 model. To solve the beam selection problem, we propose a novel lightweight hybrid architecture that combines a lightweight transformer with a CNN architecture through a weighted entropy mechanism. This hybrid architecture utilizes multimodal data sources to dynamically predict the optimal beams. A novel metric, Accuracy-Complexity Efficiency (ACE), has been proposed to quantify this. Six testing scenarios have been developed to evaluate the robustness of the proposed model. Finally, the simulation result demonstrates that the proposed model outperforms several state-of-the-art baselines regarding beam prediction accuracy, received power, and ACE in the developed test scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02000v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avi Deb Raha, Kitae Kim, Apurba Adhikary, Mrityunjoy Gain, Zhu Han, Choong Seon Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithm-Supervised Millimeter Wave Indoor Localization using Tiny Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01329v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quasi-optical propagation of millimeter-wave signals enables high-accuracy localization algorithms that employ geometric approaches or machine learning models. However, most algorithms require information on the indoor environment, may entail the collection of large training datasets, or bear an infeasible computational burden for commercial off-the-shelf (COTS) devices. In this work, we propose to use tiny neural networks (NNs) to learn the relationship between angle difference-of-arrival (ADoA) measurements and locations of a receiver in an indoor environment. To relieve training data collection efforts, we resort to a self-supervised approach by bootstrapping the training of our neural network through location estimates obtained from a state-of-the-art localization algorithm. We evaluate our scheme via mmWave measurements from indoor 60-GHz double-directional channel sounding. We process the measurements to yield dominant multipath components, use the corresponding angles to compute ADoA values, and finally obtain location fixes. Results show that the tiny NN achieves sub-meter errors in 74% of the cases, thus performing as good as or even better than the state-of-the-art algorithm, with significantly lower computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01329v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anish Shastri, Steve Blandino, Camillo Gentile, Chiehping Lai, Paolo Casari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Federated Learning for Wireless Networks: A Demonstration with Channel Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03088v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Federated learning (FL) offers a privacy-preserving collaborative approach for training models in wireless networks, with channel estimation emerging as a promising application. Despite extensive studies on FL-empowered channel estimation, the security concerns associated with FL require meticulous attention. In a scenario where small base stations (SBSs) serve as local models trained on cached data, and a macro base station (MBS) functions as the global model setting, an attacker can exploit the vulnerability of FL, launching attacks with various adversarial attacks or deployment tactics. In this paper, we analyze such vulnerabilities, corresponding solutions were brought forth, and validated through simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03088v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zexin Fang, Bin Han, Hans D. Schotten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive Indoor Localization Approach Using WiFi RSSI Fingerprinting with SLAM-Enabled Robotic Platform and Deep Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09242v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Indoor localization plays a vital role in the era of the IoT and robotics, with WiFi technology being a prominent choice due to its ubiquity. We present a method for creating WiFi fingerprinting datasets to enhance indoor localization systems and address the gap in WiFi fingerprinting dataset creation. We used the Simultaneous Localization And Mapping (SLAM) algorithm and employed a robotic platform to construct precise maps and localize robots in indoor environments. We developed software applications to facilitate data acquisition, fingerprinting dataset collection, and accurate ground truth map building. Subsequently, we aligned the spatial information generated via the SLAM with the WiFi scans to create a comprehensive WiFi fingerprinting dataset. The created dataset was used to train a deep neural network (DNN) for indoor localization, which can prove the usefulness of grid density. We conducted experimental validation within our office environment to demonstrate the proposed method's effectiveness, including a heatmap from the dataset showcasing the spatial distribution of WiFi signal strengths for the testing access points placed within the environment. Notably, our method offers distinct advantages over existing approaches as it eliminates the need for a predefined map of the environment, requires no preparatory steps, lessens human intervention, creates a denser fingerprinting dataset, and reduces the WiFi fingerprinting dataset creation time. Our method achieves 26% more accurate localization than the other methods and can create a six times denser fingerprinting dataset in one-third of the time compared to the traditional method. In summary, using WiFi RSSI Fingerprinting data surveyed by the SLAM-Enabled Robotic Platform, we can adapt our trained DNN model to indoor localization in any dynamic environment and enhance its scalability and applicability in real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09242v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Alireza Rahimi Azghadi, Atah Nuh Mih, Asfia Kawnine, Monica Wachowicz, Francis Palma, Hung Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F-KANs: Federated Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20100v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an innovative federated learning (FL) approach that utilizes Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs) for classification tasks. By utilizing the adaptive activation capabilities of KANs in a federated framework, we aim to improve classification capabilities while preserving privacy. The study evaluates the performance of federated KANs (F- KANs) compared to traditional Multi-Layer Perceptrons (MLPs) on classification task. The results show that the F-KANs model significantly outperforms the federated MLP model in terms of accuracy, precision, recall, F1 score and stability, and achieves better performance, paving the way for more efficient and privacy-preserving predictive analytics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20100v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Engin Zeydan, Cristian J. Vaca-Rubio, Luis Blanco, Roberto Pereira, Marius Caus, Abdullah Aydeger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
