<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 02:07:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Meta Learning Based Adaptive Cooperative Perception in Nonstationary Vehicular Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To accommodate high network dynamics in real-time cooperative perception (CP), reinforcement learning (RL) based adaptive CP schemes have been proposed, to allow adaptive switchings between CP and stand-alone perception modes among connected and autonomous vehicles. The traditional offline-training online-execution RL framework suffers from performance degradation under nonstationary network conditions. To achieve fast and efficient model adaptation, we formulate a set of Markov decision processes for adaptive CP decisions in each stationary local vehicular network (LVN). A meta RL solution is proposed, which trains a meta RL model that captures the general features among LVNs, thus facilitating fast model adaptation for each LVN with the meta RL model as an initial point. Simulation results show the superiority of meta RL in terms of the convergence speed without reward degradation. The impact of the customization level of meta models on the model adaptation performance has also been evaluated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01070v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaige Qu, Zixiong Qin, Weihua Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building a real-time physical layer labeled data logging facility for 6G research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work describes the architecture and vision of designing and implementing a new test infrastructure for 6G physical layer research at KU Leuven. The Testbed is designed for physical layer research and experimentation following several emerging trends, such as cell-free networking, integrated communication, sensing, open disaggregated Radio Access Networks, AI-Native design, and multiband operation. The software is almost entirely based on free and open-source software, making contributing and reusing any component easy. The open Testbed is designed to provide real-time and labeled data on all parts of the physical layer, from raw IQ data to synchronization statistics, channel state information, or symbol/bit/packet error rates. Real-time labeled datasets can be collected by synchronizing the physical layer data logging with a positioning and motion capture system. One of the main goals of the design is to make it open and accessible to external users remotely. Most tests and data captures can easily be automated, and experiment code can be remotely deployed using standard containers (e.g., Docker or Podman). Finally, the paper describes how the Testbed can be used for our research on joint communication and sensing, over-the-air synchronization, distributed processing, and AI in the loop.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01298v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franco Minucci, Raquel Marina Noguera Oishi, Haoqiu Xiong, Dieter Verbruggen, Cel Thys, Rizqi Hersyandika, Robbert Beerten, Achiel Colpaert, Vida Ranjbar, Sofie Pollin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Oriented Edge-Assisted Cooperative Data Compression, Communications and Computing for UGV-Enhanced Warehouse Logistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Only the chairs can edit This paper explores the growing need for task-oriented communications in warehouse logistics, where traditional communication Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)-such as latency, reliability, and throughput-often do not fully meet task requirements. As the complexity of data flow management in large-scale device networks increases, there is also a pressing need for innovative cross-system designs that balance data compression, communication, and computation. To address these challenges, we propose a task-oriented, edge-assisted framework for cooperative data compression, communication, and computing in Unmanned Ground Vehicle (UGV)-enhanced warehouse logistics. In this framework, two UGVs collaborate to transport cargo, with control functions-navigation for the front UGV and following/conveyance for the rear UGV-offloaded to the edge server to accommodate their limited on-board computing resources. We develop a Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL)-based two-stage point cloud data compression algorithm that dynamically and collaboratively adjusts compression ratios according to task requirements, significantly reducing communication overhead. System-level simulations of our UGV logistics prototype demonstrate the framework's effectiveness and its potential for swift real-world implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01515v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Yang (University of Glasgow, United Kingdom), Zhen Meng (University of Glasgow, United Kingdom), Xiangmin Xu (University of Glasgow, United Kingdom), Kan Chen (University of Glasgow, United Kingdom), Emma Liying Li (University of Glasgow, United Kingdom), Philip Guodong G. Zhao (University of Manchester, United Kingdom)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Sum Power Minimization for Cooperative Spectrum Sharing in Cognitive Radio Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter introduces weighted sum power (WSP), a new performance metric for wireless resource allocation during cooperative spectrum sharing in cognitive radio networks, where the primary and secondary nodes have different priorities and quality of service (QoS) requirements. Compared to using energy efficiency (EE) and weighted sum energy efficiency (WSEE) as performance metrics and optimization objectives of wireless resource allocation towards green communication, the linear character of WSP can reduce the complexity of optimization problems. Meanwhile, the weights assigned to different nodes are beneficial for managing their power budget. Using WSP as the optimization objective, a suboptimal resource allocation scheme is proposed, leveraging linear programming and Newton's method. Simulations verify that the proposed scheme provides near-optimal performance with low computation time. Furthermore, the initial approximate value selection in Newton's method is also optimized to accelerate the proposed scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01554v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI-Native Network Digital Twin for Intelligent Network Management in 6G</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As a pivotal virtualization technology, network digital twin is expected to accurately reflect real-time status and abstract features in the on-going sixth generation (6G) networks. In this article, we propose an artificial intelligence (AI)-native network digital twin framework for 6G networks to enable the synergy of AI and network digital twin, thereby facilitating intelligent network management. In the proposed framework, AI models are utilized to establish network digital twin models to facilitate network status prediction, network pattern abstraction, and network management decision-making. Furthermore, potential solutions are proposed for enhance the performance of network digital twin. Finally, a case study is presented, followed by a discussion of open research issues that are essential for AI-native network digital twin in 6G networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01584v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Wu, Xinyu Huangm, Tom H. Luan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAFE: Semantic Adaptive Feature Extraction with Rate Control for 6G Wireless Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most current Deep Learning-based Semantic Communication (DeepSC) systems are designed and trained exclusively for particular single-channel conditions, which restricts their adaptability and overall bandwidth utilization. To address this, we propose an innovative Semantic Adaptive Feature Extraction (SAFE) framework, which significantly improves bandwidth efficiency by allowing users to select different sub-semantic combinations based on their channel conditions. This paper also introduces three advanced learning algorithms to optimize the performance of SAFE framework as a whole. Through a series of simulation experiments, we demonstrate that the SAFE framework can effectively and adaptively extract and transmit semantics under different channel bandwidth conditions, of which effectiveness is verified through objective and subjective quality evaluations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01597v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuna Yan, Lixin Li, Xin Zhang, Wensheng Lin, Wenchi Cheng, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beamforming in Secure Integrated Sensing and Communication Systems with Antenna Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider joint antenna allocation and transmit beamforming design in secure integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) systems. A dual-function base station (DFBS) aims to securely deliver messages to a single-antenna receiver while detecting potential eavesdroppers. To prevent eavesdropping, we incorporate specialized sensing signals, intentionally reducing communication signal power toward suspicious targets to improve sensing. We prioritize minimizing the matching error between the transmitting and required beampatterns for sensing and communication. Our design optimizes antenna allocation and beamforming at the DFBS, meeting minimum secrecy rate and power constraints. We propose solvers based on alternating optimization for the non-convex design problem. Simulations show that the antenna allocation scheme significantly improves safety performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01603v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunxiang Shi, Lixin Li, Wensheng Lin, Wei Liang, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outage Probability Analysis for OTFS in Lossy Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper analyzes the outage probability of orthogonal time frequency space (OTFS) modulation under a lossy communication scenario. First of all, we introduce the channel model and the vector form representation of OTFS this paper uses. Then, we derive an exact expression of the OTFS outage probability in lossy communication scenarios, using Shannon's lossy source-channel separation theorem. Because the channel is time-varying, calculating the exact outage probability is computationally expensive. Therefore, this paper aims to derive a lower bound of the outage probability, which can relatively easily be calculated. Thus, given the distortion requirement and number of the resolvable paths, we can obtain a performance limit under the optimal condition as a reference. Finally, the experimental results of outage probability are obtained by Monte-Carlo method, and compared with the theoretical results calculated by the closed-from expression of the lower bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01564v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Zhang, Wensheng Lin, Lixin Li, Fucheng Yang, Zhu Han, Tad Matsumoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of End-to-End AoI in Edge-Enabled Vehicular Fog Systems: A Dueling-DQN Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02815v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In real-time status update services for the Internet of Things (IoT), the timely dissemination of information requiring timely updates is crucial to maintaining its relevance. Failing to keep up with these updates results in outdated information. The age of information (AoI) serves as a metric to quantify the freshness of information. The Existing works to optimize AoI primarily focus on the transmission time from the information source to the monitor, neglecting the transmission time from the monitor to the destination. This oversight significantly impacts information freshness and subsequently affects decision-making accuracy. To address this gap, we designed an edge-enabled vehicular fog system to lighten the computational burden on IoT devices. We examined how information transmission and request-response times influence end-to-end AoI. As a solution, we proposed Dueling-Deep Queue Network (dueling-DQN), a deep reinforcement learning (DRL)-based algorithm and compared its performance with DQN policy and analytical results. Our simulation results demonstrate that the proposed dueling-DQN algorithm outperforms both DQN and analytical methods, highlighting its effectiveness in improving real-time system information freshness. Considering the complete end-to-end transmission process, our optimization approach can improve decision-making performance and overall system efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02815v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seifu Birhanu Tadele, Binayak Kar, Frezer Guteta Wakgra, Asif Uddin Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
