<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Redundancy Transmission in UAV-Aided LoRa Networks Featuring Wake-Up Radios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09782v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a LoRa sensor network featuring a UAV-mounted gateway for collecting sensor data (messages). Wake-up radios (WuR) are employed to inform the sensors of the UAV's arrival. Building on an existing random access scheme for such setups, we propose and evaluate two redundancy transmission protocols for enhancing the reliability of the data transfer. One protocol employs fountain-coded transmissions, whereas the other performs message replication. Our results illustrate how redundancy transmission can be beneficial under the time constraints imposed by the UAV's limited hovering duration, and how node density, hovering time, and sensor energy budget impact the performance of the schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09782v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kushwanth Sistu, Siddhartha S. Borkotoky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Admission Control Algorithm for Isochronous and Asynchronous Traffic in IEEE 802.11ad MAC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to availability of large amount of bandwidth in the 60 GHz band and support of contention-free channel access called Service Period (SP), the IEEE 802.11ad/ay Wi-Fi standard is well suited for low latency and high data rate applications. IEEE 802.11ad supports two types of SP user traffic: isochronous and asynchronous. These user traffic need guaranteed SP duration before their respective deadlines. Hence, admission control plays an important role in an IEEE 802.11ad system. In an earlier work, we studied admission control and scheduling of isochronous and asynchronous traffic in an IEEE 802.11ad system, but we assumed the asynchronous requests to be periodic to keep the algorithm simple. That assumption resulted in overallocation of resource and potential degradation of performance. In this paper, we present an admission control algorithm which does not make such assumption and yet still maintains a linear run time complexity and allocates resources to the requests in a proportional fair manner. We provide arguments to establish correctness of the algorithm in terms of guaranteeing SP allocation to the requests before their respective deadlines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09819v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirudha Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Optimization of STAR-RIS Assisted SWIPT Communication Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simultaneous wireless information and power transfer (SWIPT) is an effective energy-saving technology, but its efficiency is hindered by environmental factors. The introduction of reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RIS) has alleviated this issue, although it still faces significant constraints due to geographical limitations. This paper proposes a scheme that employs a simultaneously transmitting and reflecting (STAR)-RIS to assist SWIPT. It can overcome this limitation, achieve higher degrees of freedom (DoF), and provide better quality of service (QoS) for users on both sides of the ground. Meanwhile, we have considered a hybrid device based on a power splitting, which is capable of both energy harvesting and information decoding. We have proposed an efficient alternating optimization (AO) method to optimize the phase and amplitude vectors for reflection and transmission, beamforming and the optimal power splitting ratio, achieving an optimal balance between data rate and energy efficiency. Finally, simulation results demonstrate that the sum rate of the proposed model is superior to traditional RIS and other benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09983v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junlong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NNCTC: Physical Layer Cross-Technology Communication via Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cross-technology communication(CTC) enables seamless interactions between diverse wireless technologies. Most existing work is based on reversing the transmission path to identify the appropriate payload to generate the waveform that the target devices can recognize. However, this method suffers from many limitations, including dependency on specific technologies and the necessity for intricate algorithms to mitigate distortion. In this work, we present NNCTC, a Neural-Network-based Cross-Technology Communication framework inspired by the adaptability of trainable neural models in wireless communications. By converting signal processing components within the CTC pipeline into neural models, the NNCTC is designed for end-to-end training without requiring labeled data. This enables the NNCTC system to autonomously derive the optimal CTC payload, which significantly eases the development complexity and showcases the scalability potential for various CTC links. Particularly, we construct a CTC system from Wi-Fi to ZigBee. The NNCTC system outperforms the well-recognized WEBee and WIDE design in error performance, achieving an average packet reception rate(PRR) of 92.3% and an average symbol error rate(SER) as low as 1.3%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10014v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Wang, Jiazhao Wang, Demin Gao, Wenchao Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Wireless Bad for Consensus in Blockchain?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper examines how wireless communication affects the performance of various blockchain consensus mechanisms, focusing on their scalability and decentralization. It introduces an analytical framework for quantifying these effects, backed by extensive simulations, underscoring its broad applicability to various consensus mechanisms despite wireless communication's unreliability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seungmo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RACH-less Handover with Early Timing Advance Acquisition for Outage Reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For fifth-generation (5G) and 5G-Advanced networks, outage reduction within the context of reliability is a key objective since outage denotes the time period when a user equipment (UE) cannot communicate with the network. Earlier studies have shown that in the experimental high mobility scenario considered, outage is dominated by the interruption time that stems from the random access channel (RACH)-based handover process from the serving cell to the target cell. A handover by itself is a necessary mobility process to prevent mobility failures and their associated outage. This paper proposes a RACH-less handover signaling scheme for the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) conditional handover (CHO) mechanism. The proposed scheme exploits the decoupling between the CHO preparation and execution phases to establish initial synchronization between the UE and the target cell through an early acquisition of the timing advance. This significantly curtails the RACH process and therefore the handover interruption time. Results based on a system-level simulation-based mobility study have shown that the proposed scheme significantly reduces the outage and its constituent handover interruption time relatively by 18.7% and 43.2%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10286v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhyal Bin Iqbal, Umur Karabulut, Ahmad Awada, Philipp Schulz, Gerhard P. Fettweis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NetBench: A Large-Scale and Comprehensive Network Traffic Benchmark Dataset for Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In computer networking, network traffic refers to the amount of data transmitted in the form of packets between internetworked computers or systems. Monitoring and analyzing network traffic is crucial for ensuring the performance, security, and reliability of a network. However, a significant challenge in network traffic analysis is to process diverse data packets including both ciphertext and plaintext. While many methods have been adopted to analyze network traffic, they often rely on different datasets for performance evaluation. This inconsistency results in substantial manual data processing efforts and unfair comparisons. Moreover, some data processing methods may cause data leakage due to improper separation of training and test data. To address these issues, we introduce NetBench, a large-scale and comprehensive benchmark dataset for assessing machine learning models, especially foundation models, in both traffic classification and generation tasks. NetBench is built upon seven publicly available datasets and encompasses a broad spectrum of 20 tasks, including 15 classification tasks and 5 generation tasks. Furthermore, we evaluate eight State-Of-The-Art (SOTA) classification models and two generative models using our benchmark. The results show that foundation models significantly outperform the traditional deep learning methods in traffic classification. We believe NetBench will facilitate fair comparisons among various approaches and advance the development of foundation models for network traffic. Our benchmark is available at https://github.com/WM-JayLab/NetBench.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10319v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Qian, Xiaochang Li, Qineng Wang, Gang Zhou, Huajie Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Jamming for Physical Layer Security Enhancement Using Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wireless data communications are always facing the risk of eavesdropping and interception. Conventional protection solutions which are based on encryption may not always be practical as is the case for wireless IoT networks or may soon become ineffective against quantum computers. In this regard, Physical Layer Security (PLS) presents a promising approach to secure wireless communications through the exploitation of the physical properties of the wireless channel. Cooperative Friendly Jamming (CFJ) is among the PLS techniques that have received attention in recent years. However, finding an optimal transmit power allocation that results in the highest secrecy is a complex problem that becomes more difficult to address as the size of the wireless network increases. In this paper, we propose an optimization approach to achieve CFJ in large Wi-Fi networks by using a Reinforcement Learning Algorithm. Obtained results show that our optimization approach offers better secrecy results and becomes more effective as the network size and the density of Wi-Fi access points increase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10342v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayed Amir Hoseini, Faycal Bouhafs, Neda Aboutorab, Parastoo Sadeghi, Frank den Hartog</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Energy-Efficient Ensemble Approach for Mitigating Data Incompleteness in IoT Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine Learning (ML) is becoming increasingly important for IoT-based applications. However, the dynamic and ad-hoc nature of many IoT ecosystems poses unique challenges to the efficacy of ML algorithms. One such challenge is data incompleteness, which is manifested as missing sensor readings. Many factors, including sensor failures and/or network disruption, can cause data incompleteness. Furthermore, most IoT systems are severely power-constrained. It is important that we build IoT-based ML systems that are robust against data incompleteness while simultaneously being energy efficient. This paper presents an empirical study of SECOE - a recent technique for alleviating data incompleteness in IoT - with respect to its energy bottlenecks. Towards addressing the energy bottlenecks of SECOE, we propose ENAMLE - a proactive, energy-aware technique for mitigating the impact of concurrent missing data. ENAMLE is unique in the sense that it builds an energy-aware ensemble of sub-models, each trained with a subset of sensors chosen carefully based on their correlations. Furthermore, at inference time, ENAMLE adaptively alters the number of the ensemble of models based on the amount of missing data rate and the energy-accuracy trade-off. ENAMLE's design includes several novel mechanisms for minimizing energy consumption while maintaining accuracy. We present extensive experimental studies on two distinct datasets that demonstrate the energy efficiency of ENAMLE and its ability to alleviate sensor failures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10371v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yousef AlShehri, Lakshmish Ramaswamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Adaptive Continuous Adversarial Training (ACAT) to Enhance ML Robustness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine Learning (ML) is susceptible to adversarial attacks that aim to trick ML models, making them produce faulty predictions. Adversarial training was found to increase the robustness of ML models against these attacks. However, in network and cybersecurity, obtaining labeled training and adversarial training data is challenging and costly. Furthermore, concept drift deepens the challenge, particularly in dynamic domains like network and cybersecurity, and requires various models to conduct periodic retraining. This letter introduces Adaptive Continuous Adversarial Training (ACAT) to continuously integrate adversarial training samples into the model during ongoing learning sessions, using real-world detected adversarial data, to enhance model resilience against evolving adversarial threats. ACAT is an adaptive defense mechanism that utilizes periodic retraining to effectively counter adversarial attacks while mitigating catastrophic forgetting. Our approach also reduces the total time required for adversarial sample detection, especially in environments such as network security where the rate of attacks could be very high. Traditional detection processes that involve two stages may result in lengthy procedures. Experimental results using a SPAM detection dataset demonstrate that with ACAT, the accuracy of the SPAM filter increased from 69% to over 88% after just three retraining sessions. Furthermore, ACAT outperforms conventional adversarial sample detectors, providing faster decision times, up to four times faster in some cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10461v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed elShehaby, Aditya Kotha, Ashraf Matrawy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Scheduling for 802.1Qbv Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN): A Systematic Review and Experimental Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16772v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) has been recognized as one of the key enabling technologies for Industry 4.0 and has been deployed in many mission- and safety-critical applications e.g., automotive and aerospace systems. Given the stringent real-time requirements of these applications, the Time-Aware Shaper (TAS) draws special attention among TSN's many traffic shapers due to its ability to achieve deterministic timing guarantees. Many scheduling methods for TAS shapers have been recently developed that claim to improve system schedulability. However, these scheduling methods have yet to be thoroughly evaluated, especially through experimental comparisons, to provide a systematical understanding of their performance using different evaluation metrics in diverse application scenarios. In this paper, we fill this gap by presenting a systematic review and experimental study on existing TAS-based scheduling methods for TSN. We first categorize the system models employed in these works along with the specific problems they aim to solve, and outline the fundamental considerations in the designs of TAS-based scheduling methods. We then perform an extensive evaluation on 17 representative solutions using both high-fidelity simulations and a real-life TSN testbed, and compare their performance under both synthetic scenarios and real-life industrial use cases. Through these experimental studies, we identify the limitations of individual scheduling methods and highlight several important findings. We expect this work will provide foundational knowledge and performance benchmarks needed for future studies on real-time TSN scheduling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16772v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanyu Xue, Tianyu Zhang, Yuanbin Zhou, Mark Nixon, Andrew Loveless, Song Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open, Programmable, Multi-vendor 5G O-RAN Testbed with NVIDIA ARC and OpenAirInterface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17062v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The transition of fifth generation (5G) cellular systems to softwarized, programmable, and intelligent networks depends on successfully enabling public and private 5G deployments that are (i) fully software-driven and (ii) with a performance at par with that of traditional monolithic systems. This requires hardware acceleration to scale the Physical (PHY) layer performance, end-to-end integration and testing, and careful planning of the Radio Frequency (RF) environment. In this paper, we describe how the X5G testbed at Northeastern University has addressed these challenges through the first 8-node network deployment of the NVIDIA Aerial RAN CoLab (ARC), with the Aerial Software Development Kit (SDK) for the PHY layer, accelerated on Graphics Processing Unit (GPU), and through its integration with higher layers from the OpenAirInterface (OAI) open-source project through the Small Cell Forum (SCF) Functional Application Platform Interface (FAPI). We discuss software integration, the network infrastructure, and a digital twin framework for RF planning. We then profile the performance with up to 4 Commercial Off-the-Shelf (COTS) smartphones for each base station with iPerf and video streaming applications, measuring a cell rate higher than 500 Mbps in downlink and 45 Mbps in uplink.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17062v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Villa, Imran Khan, Florian Kaltenberger, Nicholas Hedberg, Ruben Soares da Silva, Anupa Kelkar, Chris Dick, Stefano Basagni, Josep M. Jornet, Tommaso Melodia, Michele Polese, Dimitrios Koutsonikolas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
