<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models for Zero Touch Network Configuration Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Zero-touch Network &amp; Service Management (ZSM) paradigm, a direct response to the increasing complexity of communication networks, is a problem-solving approach. In this paper, taking advantage of recent advances in generative Artificial Intelligence, we introduce the Network ConFiguration Generator (LLM-NetCFG) that employs Large Language Model and architects ZSM configuration agents by Large Language Models. LLM-NetCFG can automatically generate configurations, verify them, and configure network devices based on intents expressed in natural language. We also show the automation and verification of network configurations with minimum human intervention. Moreover, we explore the opportunities and challenges of integrating LLM in functional areas of network management to fully achieve ZSM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13298v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar G. Lira, Oscar M. Caicedo, Nelson L. S. da Fonseca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demo: Generative Open xG Network Simulation with Multi-Agent LLM and ns-3 (GenOnet)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The move toward Sixth-Generation (6G) networks relies on open interfaces and protocols for seamless interoperability across devices, vendors, and technologies. In this context, open 6G development involves multiple disciplines and requires advanced simulation approaches for testing. In this demo paper, we propose a generative simulation approach based on a multi-agent Large Language Model (LLM) and Network Simulator 3 (ns-3), called Generative Open xG Network Simulation (GenOnet), to effectively generate, debug, execute, and interpret simulated Open Fifth-Generation (5G) environments. The first version of GenOnet application represents a specialized adaptation of the OpenAI GPT models. It incorporates supplementary tools, agents, 5G standards, and seamless integration with ns-3 simulation capabilities, supporting both C++ variants and Python implementations. This release complies with the latest Open Radio Access Network (O-RAN) and 3GPP standards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13781v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farhad Rezazadeh, Amir Ashtari Gargari, Sandra Lag\'en, Josep Mangues, Dusit Niyato, Lingjia Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LIMO: Load-balanced Offloading with MAPE and Particle Swarm Optimization in Mobile Fog Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14218v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fog computing is essentially the expansion of cloud computing towards the network edge, reducing user access time to computing resources and services. Various advantages attribute to fog computing, including reduced latency, and improved user experience. However, user mobility may limit the benefits of fog computing. The displacement of users from one location to another, may increase their distance from a fog server, leading into latency amplification. This would also increase the probability of over utilization of fog servers which are located in popular destinations of mobile edge devices. This creates an unbalanced network of fog devices failing to provide lower makespan and fewer cloud accesses. One solution to maintain latency within an acceptable range is the migration of fog tasks and preserve the distance between the edge devices and the available resources. Although some studies have focused on fog task migration, none of them have considered load balancing in fog nodes. Accordingly, this paper introduces LIMO; an allocation and migration strategy for establishing load balancing in fog networks based on the control loop MAPE (Monitor-Analyze-Plan-Execute) and the Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO) algorithm. The periodical migration of tasks for load balancing aims to enhance the system's efficiency. The performance of LIMO has been modeled and evaluated using the Mobfogsim toolkit. The results show that this technique outperforms the state-of-the-art in terms of network resource utilization with 10\% improvement. Furthermore, LIMO reduces the task migration to cloud by more than 15%, while it reduces the request response time by 18%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14218v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasaman Seraj, Soheil Fadaei, Bardia Safaei, Ali Javadi, Amir Mahdi Hosseini Monazzah, Ali Mohammad Afshin Hemmatyar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring GPU-to-GPU Communication: Insights into Supercomputer Interconnects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-GPU nodes are increasingly common in the rapidly evolving landscape of exascale supercomputers. On these systems, GPUs on the same node are connected through dedicated networks, with bandwidths up to a few terabits per second. However, gauging performance expectations and maximizing system efficiency is challenging due to different technologies, design options, and software layers. This paper comprehensively characterizes three supercomputers - Alps, Leonardo, and LUMI - each with a unique architecture and design. We focus on performance evaluation of intra-node and inter-node interconnects on up to 4096 GPUs, using a mix of intra-node and inter-node benchmarks. By analyzing its limitations and opportunities, we aim to offer practical guidance to researchers, system architects, and software developers dealing with multi-GPU supercomputing. Our results show that there is untapped bandwidth, and there are still many opportunities for optimization, ranging from network to software optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14090v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in Proceedings of The International Conference for High Performance Computing Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC '24) (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniele De Sensi, Lorenzo Pichetti, Flavio Vella, Tiziano De Matteis, Zebin Ren, Luigi Fusco, Matteo Turisini, Daniele Cesarini, Kurt Lust, Animesh Trivedi, Duncan Roweth, Filippo Spiga, Salvatore Di Girolamo, Torsten Hoefler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Learning and Computing over Space-Ground Integrated Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14116v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Space-ground integrated networks hold great promise for providing global connectivity, particularly in remote areas where large amounts of valuable data are generated by Internet of Things (IoT) devices, but lacking terrestrial communication infrastructure. The massive data is conventionally transferred to the cloud server for centralized artificial intelligence (AI) models training, raising huge communication overhead and privacy concerns. To address this, we propose a hierarchical learning and computing framework, which leverages the lowlatency characteristic of low-earth-orbit (LEO) satellites and the global coverage of geostationary-earth-orbit (GEO) satellites, to provide global aggregation services for locally trained models on ground IoT devices. Due to the time-varying nature of satellite network topology and the energy constraints of LEO satellites, efficiently aggregating the received local models from ground devices on LEO satellites is highly challenging. By leveraging the predictability of inter-satellite connectivity, modeling the space network as a directed graph, we formulate a network energy minimization problem for model aggregation, which turns out to be a Directed Steiner Tree (DST) problem. We propose a topologyaware energy-efficient routing (TAEER) algorithm to solve the DST problem by finding a minimum spanning arborescence on a substitute directed graph. Extensive simulations under realworld space-ground integrated network settings demonstrate that the proposed TAEER algorithm significantly reduces energy consumption and outperforms benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyang Zhu, Yuanming Shi, Yong Zhou, Chunxiao Jiang, Linling Kuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User-Access Point Association for High Density MIMO Wireless LANs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wireless local area network (WLAN) access points (APs) are being deployed in high density to improve coverage and throughput. The emerging multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) implementation for uplink (UL) transmissions promises high per-user throughput and improved aggregate network throughput. However, the high throughput potential of dense UL-MIMO WLAN is impaired by multiple access channel interference and high contention among densely distributed user stations (STAs). We investigate the problem of actualizing the throughput potential of UL-MIMO in high density WLANs via user-AP association. Since user-AP association influences interference and STA contention, a method to optimally distribute STAs among APs is proposed to maximize aggregate users' throughput utility. This problem is transformed into a graph matching problem with the throughput utility function as the graph edge weights. The graph matching problem is solved as a combinatorial problem using a modified classical Kuhn-Munkres algorithm. A dynamic implementation of the proposed algorithm is used to periodically update user-AP associations when there are changes in the network due to new entrants and/or user mobility. Simulated dense UL-MIMO WLAN scenarios reveal that the proposed scheme achieves an average of $36.9 \%$, $33.5 \%$, $20.4 \%$ and $11.3 \%$ gains over the default strongest signal first (SSF) association scheme used in conventional WLAN, Greedy [14], SmartAssoc [13] and best performance first (BPF) [5] algorithms, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14378v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phillip B. Oni, Steven D. Blostein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Power-Consumption Analysis for Different IPoWDM Network Architectures with ZR/ZR+ and Long-Haul Muxponders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We quantify and compare the power consumption of four IPoWDM transport network architectures employing ZR/ZR+ modules, considering different grooming, regeneration, and optical bypass capabilities. Results show that optical bypass is still the most power-efficient solution, reducing consumption by up to 30%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00643v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaolun Zhang, Annalisa Morea, Massimo Tornatore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cost and Power-Consumption Analysis for Power Profile Monitoring in Optical Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04977v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We quantify and benchmark cost and power consumption of power profile monitoring (PPM) in opaque and transparent IPoWDM networks, comparing it to current optical time-domain reflectometer (OTDR) technology. Results show PPM is preferable even when PPM module adds 80% (50%) cost (power) to one transponder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04977v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaolun Zhang, Patricia Layec, Annalisa Morea, Massimo Tornatore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictability of Performance in Communication Networks Under Markovian Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the emergence of time-critical applications in modern communication networks, there is a growing demand for proactive network adaptation and quality of service (QoS) prediction. However, a fundamental question remains largely unexplored: how can we quantify and achieve more predictable communication systems in terms of performance? To address this gap, this paper introduces a theoretical framework for defining and analyzing predictability in communication systems, with a focus on the impact of observations for performance forecasting. We establish a mathematical definition of predictability based on the total variation distance between forecast and marginal performance distributions. A system is deemed unpredictable when the forecast distribution, providing the most comprehensive characterization of future states using all accessible information, is indistinguishable from the marginal distribution, which depicts the system's behavior without any observational input. This framework is applied to multi-hop systems under Markovian conditions, with a detailed analysis of Geo/Geo/1 queuing models in both single-hop and multi-hop scenarios. We derive exact and approximate expressions for predictability in these systems, as well as upper bounds based on spectral analysis of the underlying Markov chains. Our results have implications for the design of efficient monitoring and prediction mechanisms in future communication networks aiming to provide deterministic services.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13196v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samie Mostafavi, Simon Egger, Gy\"orgy D\'an, James Gross</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
