<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 05:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>NeSt-VR: An Adaptive Bitrate Algorithm for Virtual Reality Streaming over Wi-Fi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-time interactive Virtual Reality (VR) streaming is a significantly challenging use case for Wi-Fi given its high throughput and low latency requirements, especially considering the constraints imposed by the possible presence of other users and the variability of the available bandwidth. Adaptive BitRate (ABR) algorithms dynamically adjust the encoded bitrate in response to varying network conditions to maintain smooth video playback. In this paper, we present the Network-aware Step-wise ABR algorithm for VR streaming (NeSt-VR), a configurable algorithm implemented in Air Light VR (ALVR), an open-source VR streaming solution. NeSt-VR effectively adjusts video bitrate based on real-time network metrics, such as frame delivery rate, network latency, and estimated available bandwidth, to guarantee user satisfaction. These metrics are part of a comprehensive set we integrated into ALVR to characterize network performance and support the decision-making process of any ABR algorithm, validated through extensive emulated experiments. NeSt-VR is evaluated in both single- and multi-user scenarios, including tests with network capacity fluctuations, user mobility, and co-channel interference. Our results demonstrate that NeSt-VR successfully manages Wi-Fi capacity fluctuations and enhances interactive VR streaming performance in both controlled experiments at UPF's lab and professional tests at CREW's facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14947v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Casasnovas, Ferran Maura, Isjtar Vandebroeck, Haryo Sukmawanto, Eric Joris, Boris Bellalta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficient Network Path Reconfiguration for Industrial Field Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15508v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy efficiency and reliability are vital design requirements of recent industrial networking solutions. Increased energy consumption, poor data access rates and unpredictable end-to-end data access latencies are catastrophic when transferring high volumes of critical industrial data in strict temporal deadlines. These requirements might become impossible to meet later on, due to node failures, or excessive degradation of the performance of wireless links. In this paper, we focus on maintaining the network functionality required by the industrial, best effort, low-latency applications after such events, by sacrificing latency guarantees to improve energy consumption and reliability. We avoid continuously recomputing the network configuration centrally, by designing an energy efficient, local and distributed path reconfiguration method. Specifically, given the operational parameters required by the applications, our method locally reconfigures the data distribution paths, when a network node fails. Additionally, our method also regulates the return to an operational state of nodes that have been offline in the past. We compare the performance of our method through simulations to the performance of other state of the art protocols and we demonstrate performance gains in terms of energy consumption, data delivery success rate, and in some cases, end-to-end data access latency. We conclude by providing some emerging key insights which can lead to further performance improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15508v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.comcom.2020.04.048</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computer Communications, Volume 158, 15 May 2020, Pages 1-9</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Theofanis P. Raptis, Andrea Passarella, Marco Conti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starlink in Northern Europe: A New Look at Stationary and In-motion Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starlink has introduced the Flat High Performance (FHP) terminal, specifically designed to support the vehicles and the vessels in motion as well as the high-demand stationary users. The research on FHP terminal throughput analysis remains limited, only a few existing studies evaluate FHP, focusing on the limited parameters and scenarios. This paper evaluates the FHP terminal's performance in Finland, Northern Europe. We examine round-trip time (RTT), uplink, and downlink throughput for both stationary and in-motion use. We measure network efficiency across six geographically diverse servers and get insights of network routing strategies. Our results show that Starlink provides high-speed, low-RTT connectivity, however, the throughput experiences fluctuations with slight degradation when in motion. Additionally, we compare Starlink and terrestrial network RTT and possible routing paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15552v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Asad Ullah, Antti Heikkinen, Mikko Uitto, Marko H\"oyhty\"a, Antti Anttonen, Konstantin Mikhaylov, Timo Lind</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Survey of Linear, Integer, and Mixed-Integer Programming Approaches for Optimizing Resource Allocation in 5G and Beyond Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The introduction of 5G networks has significantly advanced communication technology, offering faster speeds, lower latency, and greater capacity. This progress sets the stage for Beyond 5G (B5G) networks, which present new complexity and performance requirements challenges. Linear Programming (LP), Integer Linear Programming (ILP), and Mixed-Integer Linear Programming (MILP) models have been widely used to model the optimization of resource allocation problems in networks. This paper reviews 103 studies on resource allocation strategies in 5G and B5G, focusing specifically on optimization problems modelled as LP, ILP, and MILP. The selected studies are categorized based on network architectures, types of resource allocation problems, and specific objective functions and constraints. The review also discusses solution methods for NP-hard ILP and MILP problems by categorizing the solution methods into different categories. Additionally, emerging trends, such as integrating AI and machine learning with optimization models, are explored, suggesting promising future research directions in network optimization. The paper concludes that LP, ILP, and MILP models have been widely adopted across various network architectures, resource types, objective functions, and constraints and remain critical to optimizing next-generation networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15585v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naveed Ejaz, Salimur Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Internet Censorship and its Measurement: Methodology, Trends, and Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Internet censorship limits the access of nodes residing within a specific network environment to the public Internet, and vice versa. During the last decade, techniques for conducting Internet censorship have been developed further. Consequently, methodology for measuring Internet censorship had been improved as well. In this paper, we firstly provide a survey of Internet censorship techniques. Secondly, we survey censorship measurement methodology, including a coverage of available datasets. In cases where it is beneficial, we bridge the terminology and taxonomy of Internet censorship with related domains, namely traffic obfuscation and information hiding. We cover both, technical and human aspects, as well as recent trends, and challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14945v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steffen Wendzel, Simon Volpert, Sebastian Zillien, Julia Lenz, Philip R\"unz, Luca Caviglione</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Offload Rethinking by Cloud Assistance for Efficient Environmental Sound Recognition on LPWANs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15285v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning-based environmental sound recognition has emerged as a crucial method for ultra-low-power environmental monitoring in biological research and city-scale sensing systems. These systems usually operate under limited resources and are often powered by harvested energy in remote areas. Recent efforts in on-device sound recognition suffer from low accuracy due to resource constraints, whereas cloud offloading strategies are hindered by high communication costs. In this work, we introduce ORCA, a novel resource-efficient cloud-assisted environmental sound recognition system on batteryless devices operating over the Low-Power Wide-Area Networks (LPWANs), targeting wide-area audio sensing applications. We propose a cloud assistance strategy that remedies the low accuracy of on-device inference while minimizing the communication costs for cloud offloading. By leveraging a self-attention-based cloud sub-spectral feature selection method to facilitate efficient on-device inference, ORCA resolves three key challenges for resource-constrained cloud offloading over LPWANs: 1) high communication costs and low data rates, 2) dynamic wireless channel conditions, and 3) unreliable offloading. We implement ORCA on an energy-harvesting batteryless microcontroller and evaluate it in a real world urban sound testbed. Our results show that ORCA outperforms state-of-the-art methods by up to $80 \times$ in energy savings and $220 \times$ in latency reduction while maintaining comparable accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15285v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Zhang, Quanling Zhao, Run Wang, Shirley Bian, Onat Gungor, Flavio Ponzina, Tajana Rosing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Resource Optimization for ML-Based UAV Condition Monitoring with Vibration Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15491v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As smart cities begin to materialize, the role of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) and their reliability becomes increasingly important. One aspect of reliability relates to Condition Monitoring (CM), where Machine Learning (ML) models are leveraged to identify abnormal and adverse conditions. Given the resource-constrained nature of next-generation edge networks, the utilization of precious network resources must be minimized. This work explores the optimization of network resources for ML-based UAV CM frameworks. The developed framework uses experimental data and varies the feature extraction aggregation interval to optimize ML model selection. Additionally, by leveraging dimensionality reduction techniques, there is a 99.9% reduction in network resource consumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15491v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Gemayel, Dimitrios Michael Manias, Abdallah Shami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain-based Trust Management in Security Credential Management System for Vehicular Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15653v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cellular networking is advancing as a wireless technology to support diverse applications in vehicular communication, enabling vehicles to interact with various applications to enhance the driving experience, even when managed by different authorities. Security Credential Management System (SCMS) is the Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) for vehicular networking and the state-of-the-art distributed PKI to protect the privacy-preserving vehicular networking against an honest-but-curious authority using multiple authorities and to decentralize the trust management. We build a Blockchain-Based Trust Management (BBTM) to provide even greater decentralization and security. Specifically, BBTM uses the blockchain to 1) replace the existing Policy Generator (PG), 2) manage the policy of each authority in SCMS, 3) aggregate the Global Certificate Chain File (GCCF), and 4) provide greater accountability and transparency on the aforementioned functionalities. We implement BBTM on Hyperledger Fabric using a smart contract for experimentation and analyses. Our experiments show that BBTM is lightweight in processing, efficient management in the certificate chain and ledger size, supports a bandwidth of multiple transactions per second, and provides validated end-entities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15653v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>SangHyun Byun, Arijet Sarker, Sang-Yoon Chang, Jugal Kalita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Generative Semantic Communication for Multi-User Systems with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08765v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The surge in connected devices in 6G with typical complex tasks requiring multi-user cooperation, such as smart agriculture and smart cities, poses significant challenges to unsustainable traditional communication. Fortunately, the booming artificial intelligence technology and the growing computational power of devices offer a promising 6G enabler: semantic communication (SemCom). However, existing deep learning-based SemCom paradigms struggle to extend to multi-user scenarios due to its increasing model size with the growing number of users and its limited compatibility with complex communication environments. Consequently, to truly empower 6G networks with this critical technology, this article rethinks generative SemCom for multi-user system and proposes a novel framework called ``M-GSC" with the large language model (LLM) as the shared knowledge base (SKB). The LLM-based SKB plays three critical roles, that is, complex task decomposition, semantic representation specification, and semantic translation and mapping, for complex tasks, spawning a series of benefits such as semantic encoding standardization and semantic decoding personalization. Meanwhile, to enhance the performance of M-GSC framework, we highlight three optimization strategies unique to this framework: extending the LLM-based SKB into a multi-agent LLM system, offloading semantic encoding and decoding, and managing communication and computational resources. Finally, a case study is conducted to demonstrate the preliminary validation on the effectiveness of the M-GSC framework in terms of efficient decoding offloading.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08765v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanting Yang, Zehui Xiong, Shiwen Mao, Tony Q. S. Quek, Ping Zhang, Merouane Debbah, Rahim Tafazolli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SANDWICH: Towards an Offline, Differentiable, Fully-Trainable Wireless Neural Ray-Tracing Surrogate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08767v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Wireless ray-tracing (RT) is emerging as a key tool for three-dimensional (3D) wireless channel modeling, driven by advances in graphical rendering. Current approaches struggle to accurately model beyond 5G (B5G) network signaling, which often operates at higher frequencies and is more susceptible to environmental conditions and changes. Existing online learning solutions require real-time environmental supervision during training, which is both costly and incompatible with GPU-based processing. In response, we propose a novel approach that redefines ray trajectory generation as a sequential decision-making problem, leveraging generative models to jointly learn the optical, physical, and signal properties within each designated environment. Our work introduces the Scene-Aware Neural Decision Wireless Channel Raytracing Hierarchy (SANDWICH), an innovative offline, fully differentiable approach that can be trained entirely on GPUs. SANDWICH offers superior performance compared to existing online learning methods, outperforms the baseline by 4e^-2 radian in RT accuracy, and only fades 0.5 dB away from toplined channel gain estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08767v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Jin, Ali Maatouk, Sarunas Girdzijauskas, Shugong Xu, Leandros Tassiulas, Rex Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of the Received Power of Low-Power Networks Using Inertial Sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Low-power and cost-effective IoT sensing nodes enable scalable monitoring of different environments. Some of these environments impose rough and extreme operating conditions, requiring continuous adaptation and reconfiguration of physical and link layer parameters. In this paper, we closely investigate the stability of the wireless links established between nodes deployed on the surface of different water bodies and propose a model to predict the received power. Our model is based on Minimum Mean Square Estimation (MMSE) and relies on the statistics of received power and the motion the nodes experience during communication. One of the drawbacks of MMSE is its reliance on matrix inversion, which is at once computationally expensive and difficult to implement with resource constrained devices. We forgo this stage by estimating model parameters using the gradient-descent approach, which is much simpler to implement. The model achieves a prediction accuracy of 91% even with a small number of iterations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14107v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waltenegus Dargie, Christian Poellabauer, Abiy Tasissa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PP-MARL: Efficient Privacy-Preserving Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning for Cooperative Intelligence in Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.12064v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cooperative intelligence (CI) is expected to become an integral element in next-generation networks because it can aggregate the capabilities and intelligence of multiple devices. Multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) is a popular approach for achieving CI in communication problems by enabling effective collaboration among agents to address sequential problems. However, ensuring privacy protection for MARL is a challenging task because of the presence of heterogeneous agents that learn interdependently via sharing information. Implementing privacy protection techniques such as data encryption and federated learning to MARL introduces the notable overheads (e.g., computation and bandwidth). To overcome these challenges, we propose PP-MARL, an efficient privacy-preserving learning scheme for MARL. PP-MARL leverages homomorphic encryption (HE) and differential privacy (DP) to protect privacy, while introducing split learning to decrease overheads via reducing the volume of shared messages, and then improve efficiency. We apply and evaluate PP-MARL in two communication-related use cases. Simulation results reveal that PP-MARL can achieve efficient and reliable collaboration with 1.1-6 times better privacy protection and lower overheads (e.g., 84-91% reduction in bandwidth) than state-of-the-art approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.12064v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingting Yuan, Hwei-Ming Chung, Xiaoming Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
