<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 03:46:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AWARE: Evaluating PriorityFresh Caching for Offline Emergency Warning Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PriorityFresh is a semantic, actionability-first caching policy designed for offline emergency warning systems. Within the AWARE system's simulation environment, PriorityFresh optimizes which alerts to retain and surface under constrained connectivity. Experiments indicate improved actionability-first performance without harming efficiency. A separate Priority Forecasting model is used only to synthesize realistic alert sequences for controlled experiments and does not influence caching or push decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05022v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Melvin, N. Rich Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-link RTS/CTS for MLO mm-Wave WLANs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The directional RTS/CTS mechanism of mm-wave Wi-Fi hardly resolves the hidden terminal problem perfectly.This paper proposes cross-link RTS/CTS under multi-link operation (MLO) to address this problem and introduces a novel point process, named the generalized RTS/CTS hard-core process (G-HCP), to model the spatial transceiver relationships under the RTS/CTS mechanism, including the directional case and the omnidirectional case.Analytical expressions are derived for the intensity, the mean interference, an approximation of the success probability, and the expected number of hidden nodes for the directional RTS/CTS mechanism.Theoretical and numerical results demonstrate the performance difference between two RTS/CTS mechanisms.The cross-link RTS/CTS mechanism ensures higher link quality at the cost of reduced network throughput.In contrast, the directional RTS/CTS sacrifices the link quality for higher throughput.Our study reveals a fundamental trade-off between link reliability and network throughput, providing critical insights into the selection and optimization of RTS/CTS mechanisms in next-generation WLAN standards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05027v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoling Chen, Yi Zhong, Martin Haenggi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Injection-Throttling Mechanisms for Congestion Control for Data-center and Supercomputer Interconnects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past decade, Supercomputers and Data centers have evolved dramatically to cope with the increasing performance requirements of applications and services, such as scientific computing, generative AI, social networks or cloud services. This evolution have led these systems to incorporate high-speed networks using faster links, end nodes using multiple and dedicated accelerators, or a advancements in memory technologies to bridge the memory bottleneck. The interconnection network is a key element in these systems and it must be thoroughly designed so it is not the bottleneck of the entire system, bearing in mind the countless communication operations that generate current applications and services. Congestion is serious threat that spoils the interconnection network performance, and its effects are even more dramatic when looking at the traffic dynamics and bottlenecks generated by the communication operations mentioned above. In this vein, numerous congestion control (CC) techniques have been developed to address congestion negative effects. One popular example is Data Center Quantized Congestion Notification (DCQCN), which allows congestion detection at network switch buffers, then marking congesting packets and notifying about congestion to the sources, which finally apply injection throttling of those packets contributing to congestion. While DCQCN has been widely studied and improved, its main principles for congestion detection, notification and reaction remain largely unchanged, which is an important shortcoming considering congestion dynamics in current high-performance interconnection networks. In this paper, we revisit the DCQCN closed-loop mechanism and refine its design to leverage a more accurate congestion detection, signaling, and injection throttling, reducing control traffic overhead and avoiding unnecessary throttling of non-congesting flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05149v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristina Olmedilla, Jesus Escudero-Sahuquillo, Pedro J. Garcia, Francisco J. Quiles, Jose Duato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EPFL-REMNet: Efficient Personalized Federated Digital Twin Towards 6G Heterogeneous Radio Environme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio Environment Map (REM) is transitioning from 5G homogeneous environments to B5G/6G heterogeneous landscapes. However, standard Federated Learning (FL), a natural fit for this distributed task, struggles with performance degradation in accuracy and communication efficiency under the non-independent and identically distributed (Non-IID) data conditions inherent to these new environments. This paper proposes EPFL-REMNet, an efficient personalized federated framework for constructing a high-fidelity digital twin of the 6G heterogeneous radio environment. The proposed EPFL-REMNet employs a"shared backbone + lightweight personalized head" model, where only the compressed shared backbone is transmitted between the server and clients, while each client's personalized head is maintained locally. We tested EPFL-REMNet by constructing three distinct Non-IID scenarios (light, medium, and heavy) based on radio environment complexity, with data geographically partitioned across 90 clients. Experimental results demonstrate that EPFL-REMNet simultaneously achieves higher digital twin fidelity (accuracy) and lower uplink overhead across all Non-IID settings compared to standard FedAvg and recent state-of-the-art methods. Particularly, it significantly reduces performance disparities across datasets and improves local map accuracy for long-tail clients, enhancing the overall integrity of digital twin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05238v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peide Li, Liu Cao, Lyutianyang Zhang, Dongyu Wei, Ye Hu, Qipeng Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Formal Model for Path Set Attribute Calculation in Network Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In graph theory and its practical networking applications, e.g., telecommunications and transportation, the problem of finding paths has particular importance. Selecting paths requires giving scores to the alternative solutions to drive a choice. While previous studies have provided comprehensive evaluation of single-path solutions, the same level of detail is lacking when considering sets of paths. This paper emphasizes that the path characterization strongly depends on the properties under consideration. While property-based characterization is also valid for single paths, it becomes crucial to analyse multiple path sets. From the above consideration, this paper proposes a mathematical approach, defining a functional model that lends itself well to characterizing the path set in its general formulation. The paper shows how the functional model contextualizes specific attributes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05334v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Fiaschi, Carlo Vitucci, Thomas Westerb\"ack, Daniel Sundmark, Thomas Nolte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Squelch or not to Squelch: Enabling Improved Message Dissemination on the XRP Ledger</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the large increase in the adoption of blockchain technologies, their underlying peer-to-peer networks must also scale with the demand. In this context, previous works highlighted the importance of ensuring efficient and resilient communication for the underlying consensus and replication mechanisms. However, they were mainly focused on mainstream, Proof-of-Work-based Distributed Ledger Technologies like Bitcoin or Ethereum.
  In this paper, the problem is investigated in the context of consensus-validation based blockchains, like the XRP Ledger. The latter relies on a Federated Byzantine Agreement (FBA) consensus mechanism which is proven to have a good scalability in regards to transaction throughput. However, it is known that significant increases in the size of the XRP Ledger network would be challenging to achieve. The main reason is the flooding mechanism used to disseminate the messages related to the consensus protocol, which creates many duplicates in the network. Squelching is a recent solution proposed for limiting this duplication, however, it was never evaluated quantitatively in real-life scenarios involving the XRPL production network. In this paper, our aim is to assess this mechanism using a real-life controllable testbed and the XRPL production network, to assess its benefit and compare it to alternative solutions relying on Named Data Networking and on a gossip-based approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05362v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/NOMS59830.2024.10575886</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NOMS 2024-2024 IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium, Seoul, Korea, Republic of, 2024, pp. 1-7</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lucian Trestioreanu, Flaviene Scheidt, Wazen Shbair, Jerome Francois, Damien Magoni, Radu State</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scanning the IPv6 Internet Using Subnet-Router Anycast Probing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identifying active IPv6 addresses is challenging. Various methods emerged to master the measurement challenge in this huge address space, including hitlists, new probing techniques, and AI-generated target lists. In this paper, we apply active Subnet-Router anycast (SRA) probing, a commonly unused method to explore the IPv6 address space. We compare our results with lists of active IPv6 nodes obtained from prior methods and with random probing. Our findings indicate that probing an SRA address reveals on average 10% more router IP addresses than random probing and is far less affected by ICMP rate limiting. Compared to targeting router addresses directly, SRA probing discovers 80% more addresses. We conclude that SRA probing is an important addition to the IPv6 measurement toolbox and may improve the stability of results significantly. We also find evidence that some active scans can cause harmful conditions in current IPv6 deployments, which we started to fix in collaboration with network operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05423v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3768997</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the ACM on Networking (PACMNET) 3, CoNEXT4, Article 50 (December 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maynard Koch, Raphael Hiesgen, Marcin Nawrocki, Thomas C. Schmidt, Matthias W\"ahlisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bit-Flipping Attack Exploration and Countermeasure in 5G Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: 5G communication technology has become a vital component in a wide range of applications due to its unique advantages such as high data rate and low latency. While much of the existing research has focused on optimizing its efficiency and performance, security considerations have not received comparable attention, potentially leaving critical vulnerabilities unexplored. In this work, we investigate the vulnerability of 5G systems to bit-flipping attacks, which is an integrity attack where an adversary intercepts 5G network traffic and modifies specific fields of an encrypted message without decryption, thus mutating the message while remaining valid to the receiver. Notably, these attacks do not require the attacker to know the plaintext, and only the semantic meaning or position of certain fields would be enough to effect targeted modifications. We conduct our analysis on OpenAirInterface (OAI), an open-source 5G platform that follows the 3GPP Technical Specifications, to rigorously test the real-world feasibility and impact of bit-flipping attacks under current 5G encryption mechanisms. Finally, we propose a keystream-based shuffling defense mechanism to mitigate the effect of such attacks by raising the difficulty of manipulating specific encrypted fields, while introducing no additional communication overhead compared to the NAS Integrity Algorithm (NIA) in 5G. Our findings reveal that enhancements to 5G security are needed to better protect against attacks that alter data during transmission at the network level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joon Kim, Chengwei Duan, Sandip Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Secured Intent-Based Networking (sIBN) with Data-Driven Time-Aware Intrusion Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05133v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While Intent-Based Networking (IBN) promises operational efficiency through autonomous and abstraction-driven network management, a critical unaddressed issue lies in IBN's implicit trust in the integrity of intent ingested by the network. This inherent assumption of data reliability creates a blind spot exploitable by Man-in-the-Middle (MitM) attacks, where an adversary intercepts and alters intent before it is enacted, compelling the network to orchestrate malicious configurations. This study proposes a secured IBN (sIBN) system with data driven intrusion detection method designed to secure legitimate user intent from adversarial tampering. The proposed intent intrusion detection system uses a ML model applied for network behavioral anomaly detection to reveal temporal patterns of intent tampering. This is achieved by leveraging a set of original behavioral metrics and newly engineered time-aware features, with the model's hyperparameters fine-tuned through the randomized search cross-validation (RSCV) technique. Numerical results based on real-world data sets, show the effectiveness of sIBN, achieving the best performance across standard evaluation metrics, in both binary and multi classification tasks, while maintaining low error rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05133v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Urslla Uchechi Izuazu, Mounir Bensalem, Admela Jukan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SmartSecChain-SDN: A Blockchain-Integrated Intelligent Framework for Secure and Efficient Software-Defined Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05156v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With more and more existing networks being transformed to Software-Defined Networking (SDN), they need to be more secure and demand smarter ways of traffic control. This work, SmartSecChain-SDN, is a platform that combines machine learning based intrusion detection, blockchain-based storage of logs, and application-awareness-based priority in SDN networks. To detect network intrusions in a real-time, precision and low-false positives setup, the framework utilizes the application of advanced machine learning algorithms, namely Random Forest, XGBoost, CatBoost, and CNN-BiLSTM. SmartSecChain-SDN is based on the Hyperledger Fabric, which is a permissioned blockchain technology, to provide secure, scalable, and privacy-preserving storage and, thus, guarantee that the Intrusion Detection System (IDS) records cannot be altered and can be analyzed comprehensively. The system also has Quality of Service (QoS) rules and traffic shaping based on applications, which enables prioritization of critical services, such as VoIP, video conferencing, and business applications, as well as de-prioritization of non-essential traffic, such as downloads and updates. Mininet can simulate real-time SDN scenarios because it is used to prototype whole architectures. It is also compatible with controllers OpenDaylight and Ryu. It has tested the framework using the InSDN dataset and proved that it can identify different kinds of cyberattacks and handle bandwidth allocation efficiently under circumstances of resource constraints. SmartSecChain-SDN comprehensively addresses SDN system protection, securing and enhancing. The proposed study offers an innovative, extensible way to improve cybersecurity, regulatory compliance, and the administration of next-generation programmable networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05156v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.14445/23488549/IJECE-V12I10P117</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Azhar Hussain Mozumder, M. John Basha, Chayapathi A. R</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No One-Model-Fits-All: Uncovering Spatio-Temporal Forecasting Trade-offs with Graph Neural Networks and Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05179v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern IoT deployments for environmental sensing produce high volume spatiotemporal data to support downstream tasks such as forecasting, typically powered by machine learning models. While existing filtering and strategic deployment techniques optimize collected data volume at the edge, they overlook how variations in sampling frequencies and spatial coverage affect downstream model performance. In many forecasting models, incorporating data from additional sensors denoise predictions by providing broader spatial contexts. This interplay between sampling frequency, spatial coverage and different forecasting model architectures remain underexplored. This work presents a systematic study of forecasting models - classical models (VAR), neural networks (GRU, Transformer), spatio-temporal graph neural networks (STGNNs), and time series foundation models (TSFMs: Chronos Moirai, TimesFM) under varying spatial sensor nodes density and sampling intervals using real-world temperature data in a wireless sensor network. Our results show that STGNNs are effective when sensor deployments are sparse and sampling rate is moderate, leveraging spatial correlations via encoded graph structure to compensate for limited coverage. In contrast, TSFMs perform competitively at high frequencies but degrade when spatial coverage from neighboring sensors is reduced. Crucially, the multivariate TSFM Moirai outperforms all models by natively learning cross-sensor dependencies. These findings offer actionable insights for building efficient forecasting pipelines in spatio-temporal systems. All code for model configurations, training, dataset, and logs are open-sourced for reproducibility: https://github.com/UIUC-MONET-Projects/Benchmarking-Spatiotemporal-Forecast-Models</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05179v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ragini Gupta, Naman Raina, Bo Chen, Li Chen, Claudiu Danilov, Josh Eckhardt, Keyshla Bernard, Klara Nahrstedt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Taxonomy and Comparative Analysis of IPv4 Identifier Selection Correctness, Security, and Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06483v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The battle for a more secure Internet is waged on many fronts, including the most basic of networking protocols. Our focus is the IPv4 Identifier (IPID), an IPv4 header field as old as the Internet with an equally long history as an exploited side channel for scanning network properties, inferring off-path connections, and poisoning DNS caches. This article taxonomizes the 25-year history of IPID-based exploits and the corresponding changes to IPID selection methods. By mathematically analyzing these methods' correctness and security and empirically evaluating their performance, we reveal recommendations for best practice as well as shortcomings of current operating system implementations, emphasizing the value of systematic evaluations in network security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06483v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua J. Daymude, Antonio M. Espinoza, Holly Bergen, Benjamin Mixon-Baca, Jeffrey Knockel, Jedidiah R. Crandall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSRF: Complex-Valued 3D Gaussian Splatting for Efficient Radio-Frequency Data Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01826v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Synthesizing radio-frequency (RF) data given the transmitter and receiver positions, e.g., received signal strength indicator (RSSI), is critical for wireless networking and sensing applications, such as indoor localization. However, it remains challenging due to complex propagation interactions, including reflection, diffraction, and scattering. State-of-the-art neural radiance field (NeRF)-based methods achieve high-fidelity RF data synthesis but are limited by long training times and high inference latency. We introduce GSRF, a framework that extends 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) from the optical domain to the RF domain, enabling efficient RF data synthesis. GSRF realizes this adaptation through three key innovations: First, it introduces complex-valued 3D Gaussians with a hybrid Fourier-Legendre basis to model directional and phase-dependent radiance. Second, it employs orthographic splatting for efficient ray-Gaussian intersection identification. Third, it incorporates a complex-valued ray tracing algorithm, executed on RF-customized CUDA kernels and grounded in wavefront propagation principles, to synthesize RF data in real time. Evaluated across various RF technologies, GSRF preserves high-fidelity RF data synthesis while achieving significant improvements in training efficiency, shorter training time, and reduced inference latency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01826v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang Yang, Gaofeng Dong, Sijie Ji, Wan Du, Mani Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-Based Emulation of the Radio Resource Control Layer: Towards AI-Native RAN Protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16821v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Integrating Large AI Models (LAMs) into 6G mobile networks is a key enabler of the AI-Native Air Interface (AI-AI), where protocol intelligence must scale beyond handcrafted logic. This paper presents, to our knowledge, the first standards-compliant emulation of the Radio Resource Control (RRC) layer using a decoder-only LAM (LLAMA-class) fine-tuned with Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) on a multi-vendor corpus of real-world traces spanning both 5G and 4G systems. We treat RRC as a domain-specific language and construct a segmentation-safe, question--answer (Question-and-Answer (QA)) dataset that preserves Abstract Syntax Notation (ASN.1) structure through linearization prior to Byte Pair Encoding (BPE) tokenization. The proposed approach combines parameter-efficient adaptation with schema-bounded prompting to ensure syntactic and procedural fidelity. Evaluation introduces a standards-aware triad -- ASN.1 conformance, field-level coverage analysis, and uplink-to-downlink state-machine checks -- alongside semantic similarity and latency profiling across 120 configurations. On 30k 5G request--response pairs plus an additional 4.8k QA turns from 4G sessions, our 8B model achieves a median cosine similarity of 0.97, a 61% relative gain over a zero-shot baseline, while sustaining high conformance rates. These results demonstrate that LAMs, when augmented with protocol-aware reasoning, can directly orchestrate control-plane procedures, laying the foundation for the future Artificial Intelligence (AI)-native Radio Access Network (RAN).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16821v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziming Liu, Bryan Liu, Alvaro Valcarce, Xiaoli Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPS Spoofing Attacks on Automated Frequency Coordination System in Wi-Fi 6E and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02824v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The 6 GHz spectrum, recently opened for unlicensed use under Wi-Fi 6E and Wi-Fi 7, overlaps with frequencies used by mission-critical incumbent systems such as public safety communications and utility infrastructure. To prevent interference, the FCC mandates the use of Automated Frequency Coordination (AFC) systems, which assign safe frequency and power levels based on Wi-Fi Access Point (AP)-reported locations. In this work, we demonstrate that GPS-based location reporting, which Wi-Fi APs use, can be spoofed using inexpensive, off-the-shelf radio equipment. This enables attackers to manipulate AP behavior, gain unauthorized spectrum access, cause harmful interference, or disable APs entirely by spoofing them into foreign locations. We validate these attacks in a controlled lab setting against a commercial AP and evaluate a commercial AFC system under spoofed scenarios. Our findings highlight critical gaps in the security assumptions of AFC and motivate the need for stronger location integrity protections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02824v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilu Dong (The Pennsylvania State University), Tianchang Yang (The Pennsylvania State University), Arupjyoti Bhuyan (Idaho National Laboratory), Syed Rafiul Hussain (The Pennsylvania State University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Stage Automated Online Network Data Stream Analytics Framework for IIoT Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.01985v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Industry 5.0 aims at maximizing the collaboration between humans and machines. Machines are capable of automating repetitive jobs, while humans handle creative tasks. As a critical component of Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT) systems for service delivery, network data stream analytics often encounter concept drift issues due to dynamic IIoT environments, causing performance degradation and automation difficulties. In this paper, we propose a novel Multi-Stage Automated Network Analytics (MSANA) framework for concept drift adaptation in IIoT systems, consisting of dynamic data pre-processing, the proposed Drift-based Dynamic Feature Selection (DD-FS) method, dynamic model learning &amp; selection, and the proposed Window-based Performance Weighted Probability Averaging Ensemble (W-PWPAE) model. It is a complete automated data stream analytics framework that enables automatic, effective, and efficient data analytics for IIoT systems in Industry 5.0. Experimental results on two public IoT datasets demonstrate that the proposed framework outperforms state-of-the-art methods for IIoT data stream analytics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.01985v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TII.2022.3212003</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Li Yang, Abdallah Shami</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
