<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 04:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Active RIS Configuration and User Power Control for Localization: A Neuroevolution-Based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies user localization aided by a Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (RIS). A feedback link from the Base Station (BS) to the user is adopted to enable dynamic power control of the user pilot transmissions in the uplink. A novel multi-agent algorithm for the joint control of the RIS phase configuration and the user transmit power is presented, which is based on a hybrid approach integrating NeuroEvolution (NE) and supervised learning. The proposed scheme requires only single-bit feedback messages for the uplink power control, supports RIS elements with discrete responses, and is numerically shown to outperform fingerprinting, deep reinforcement learning baselines and backpropagation-based position estimators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13819v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Stamatelis, Hui Chen, Henk Wymeersch, George C. Alexandropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Wireless Sensor Networks for Real-Time Monitoring and Control of Industrial Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research proposes an extensive technique for monitoring and controlling the industrial parameters using Internet of Things (IoT) technology based on wireless communication. We proposed a system based on NRF transceivers to establish a strong Wireless Sensor Network (WSN), enabling transfer of real-time data from multiple sensors to a central setup that is driven by ARDUINO microcontrollers. Different key parameters, crucial for industrial setup such as temperature, humidity, soil moisture and fire detection, are monitored and displayed on an LCD screen, enabling factory administration to oversee the industrial operations remotely over the internet. Our proposed system bypasses the need for physical presence for monitoring by addressing the shortcomings of conventional wired communication systems. Other than monitoring, there is an additional feature to remotely control these parameters by controlling the speed of DC motors through online commands. Given the rising incidence of industrial fires over the worldwide between 2020 and 2024 due to an array of hazards, this system with dual functionality boosts the overall operational efficiency and safety. This overall integration of IoT and Wireless Sensor Network (WSN) reduces the potential risks linked with physical monitoring, providing rapid responses in emergency scenarios, including the activation of firefighting equipment. The results show that innovations in wireless communication perform an integral part in industrial process automation and safety, paving the way to more intelligent and responsive operating environments. Overall, this study highlights the potential for change of IoT-enabled systems to revolutionize monitoring and control in a variety of industrial applications, resulting in increased productivity and safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13820v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Junaid Asif, Shazia Saqib, Rana Fayyaz Ahmad, Hamza Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM Agent Communication Protocol (LACP) Requires Urgent Standardization: A Telecom-Inspired Protocol is Necessary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This position paper argues that the field of LLM agents requires a unified, telecom-inspired communication protocol to ensure safety, interoperability, and scalability, especially within the context of Next Generation (NextG) networks. Current ad-hoc communication methods are creating a fragmented ecosystem, reminiscent of the early "protocol wars" in networking, which stifles innovation and poses significant risks. Drawing inspiration from the layered, standardized protocols that underpin modern telecommunications, we propose the LLM-Agent Communication Protocol (LACP). LACP establishes a three-layer architecture designed to ensure semantic clarity in communication, transactional integrity for complex tasks, and robust, built-in security. In this position paper, we argue that adopting a principled, universal protocol is not merely beneficial but essential for realizing the potential of distributed AI. Such a standard is critical for ensuring that multi-agent systems can operate safely and reliably in the complex, real-time applications envisioned for 6G and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13821v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Li, Mengbing Liu, Chau Yuen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simulator for FANETs Using 5G Vehicle-to-Everything Communications and Named-Data Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a simulator designed for the validation, evaluation, and demonstration of flying adhoc networks (FANETs) using 5G vehicle-to-everything (V2X) communications and the named-data networking (NDN) paradigm. The simulator integrates the ns-3 network simulator and the Zenoh NDN protocol, enabling realistic testing of applications that involve the multi-hop communication among multiple unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13823v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/CAMAD62243.2024.10942683</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE 29th International Workshop on Computer Aided Modeling and Design of Communication Links and Networks (CAMAD), Athens, Greece, 2024, pp. 1-2</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Manuel R\'ua-Est\'evez, Alicia Meleiro-Est\'evez, Pablo Fondo-Ferreiro, Felipe Gil-Casti\~neira, Brais S\'anchez-Rama, Lois Gomez-Gonzalez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffLoc: Diffusion Model-Based High-Precision Positioning for 6G Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel framework for high-accuracy outdoor user equipment (UE) positioning that applies a conditional generative diffusion model directly to high-dimensional massive MIMO channel state information (CSI). Traditional fingerprinting methods struggle to scale to large, dynamic outdoor environments and require dense, impractical data surveys. To overcome these limitations, our approach learns a direct mapping from raw uplink Sounding Reference Signal (SRS) fingerprints to continuous geographic coordinates. We demonstrate that our DiffLoc framework achieves unprecedented sub-centimeter precision, with our best model (DiffLoc-CT) delivering 0.5 cm fusion accuracy and 1-2 cm single base station (BS) accuracy in a realistic, ray-traced Tokyo urban macro-cell environment. This represents an order-of-magnitude improvement over existing methods, including supervised regression approaches (over 10 m error) and grid-based fusion (3 m error). Our consistency training approach reduces inference time from 200 steps to just 2 steps while maintaining exceptional accuracy even for high-speed users (15-25 m/s) and unseen user trajectories, demonstrating the practical feasibility of our framework for real-time 6G applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14111v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taekyun Lee, Tommaso Balercia, Heasung Kim, Hyeji Kim, Jeffrey G. Andrews</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Latency Optimization for Dynamic 5G Mobile Radio Access Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 5G networks, base station (BS) disaggregation and new services present challenges in radio access network (RAN) configuration, particularly in meeting their bandwidth and latency constraints. The BS disaggregation is enabled by functional splitting (FS), which distributes the RAN functions in processing nodes and alleviates latency and bandwidth requirements in the fronthaul (FH). Besides network performance, energy consumption is a critical concern for mobile network operators (MNO), since RAN operation constitutes a major portion of their operational expenses (OPEX). RAN configuration optimization is essential to balance service performance with cost-effective energy consumption. In this paper, we propose a mixed-integer linear programming (MILP) model formulated with three objective functions: (i) minimizing fronthaul (FH) latency, (ii) minimizing energy consumption, and (iii) a bi-objective optimization that jointly balances both latency and energy consumption. The model determines the optimal FS option, RAN function placement, and routing for eMBB, URLLC, and mMTC slices. Although prior studies have addressed RAN configuration either from an energy minimization or latency reduction perspective, few have considered both aspects in realistic scenarios. Our evaluation spans different topologies, accounts for variations in aggregated gNB demand, explores diverse FS combinations, and incorporates Time Sensitive Networking (TSN) modeling for latency analysis, as it is also crucial in RAN performance. Given that MILP's execution time can be significant, we propose a heuristic algorithm that adheres to RAN constraints. Our results reveal a trade-off between latency and energy consumption, highlighting the need for dynamic RAN reconfiguration. These insights provide a foundation to optimize existing and future RAN deployments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14214v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriela N. Caspa H., Carlos A. Astudillo, Nelson L. S. da Fonseca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Extraction of Protocol State Machines from 3GPP Specifications with Domain-Informed Prompts and LLM Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobile telecommunication networks are foundational to global infrastructure and increasingly support critical sectors such as manufacturing, transportation, and healthcare. The security and reliability of these networks are essential, yet depend heavily on accurate modeling of underlying protocols through state machines. While most prior work constructs such models manually from 3GPP specifications, this process is labor-intensive, error-prone, and difficult to maintain due to the complexity and frequent updates of the specifications. Recent efforts using natural language processing have shown promise, but remain limited in handling the scale and intricacy of cellular protocols. In this work, we propose SpecGPT, a novel framework that leverages large language models (LLMs) to automatically extract protocol state machines from 3GPP documents. SpecGPT segments technical specifications into meaningful paragraphs, applies domain-informed prompting with chain-of-thought reasoning, and employs ensemble methods to enhance output reliability. We evaluate SpecGPT on three representative 5G protocols (NAS, NGAP, and PFCP) using manually annotated ground truth, and show that it outperforms existing approaches, demonstrating the effectiveness of LLMs for protocol modeling at scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14348v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miao Zhang, Runhan Feng, Hongbo Tang, Yu Zhao, Jie Yang, Hang Qiu, Qi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models for Real-World IoT Device Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid expansion of IoT devices has outpaced current identification methods, creating significant risks for security, privacy, and network accountability. These challenges are heightened in open-world environments, where traffic metadata is often incomplete, noisy, or intentionally obfuscated. We introduce a semantic inference pipeline that reframes device identification as a language modeling task over heterogeneous network metadata. To construct reliable supervision, we generate high-fidelity vendor labels for the IoT Inspector dataset, the largest real-world IoT traffic corpus, using an ensemble of large language models guided by mutual-information and entropy-based stability scores. We then instruction-tune a quantized LLaMA3.18B model with curriculum learning to support generalization under sparsity and long-tail vendor distributions. Our model achieves 98.25% top-1 accuracy and 90.73% macro accuracy across 2,015 vendors while maintaining resilience to missing fields, protocol drift, and adversarial manipulation. Evaluation on an independent IoT testbed, coupled with explanation quality and adversarial stress tests, demonstrates that instruction-tuned LLMs provide a scalable and interpretable foundation for real-world device identification at scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13817v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rameen Mahmood, Tousif Ahmed, Sai Teja Peddinti, Danny Yuxing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noisy Networks, Nosy Neighbors: Inferring Privacy Invasive Information from Encrypted Wireless Traffic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13822v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This thesis explores the extent to which passive observation of wireless traffic in a smart home environment can be used to infer privacy-invasive information about its inhabitants. Using a setup that mimics the capabilities of a nosy neighbor in an adjacent flat, we analyze raw 802.11 packets and Bluetooth Low Energy advertisemets. From this data, we identify devices, infer their activity states and approximate their location using RSSI-based trilateration. Despite the encrypted nature of the data, we demonstrate that it is possible to detect active periods of multimedia devices, infer common activities such as sleeping, working and consuming media, and even approximate the layout of the neighbor's apartment. Our results show that privacy risks in smart homes extend beyond traditional data breaches: a nosy neighbor behind the wall can gain privacy-invasive insights into the lives of their neighbors purely from encrypted network traffic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13822v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bartosz Burgiel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Layer Secret Sharing for Cross-Layer Attack Defense in 5G Networks: a COTS UE Demonstration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This demo presents the first implementation of multi-layer secret sharing on commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS) 5G user equipment (UE), operating without infrastructure modifications or pre-shared keys. Our XOR-based approach distributes secret shares across network operators and distributed relays, ensuring perfect recovery and data confidentiality even if one network operator and one relay are simultaneously lost (e.g., under denial of service (DoS) or unanticipated attacks).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13824v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wai Ming Chan, Remi Chou, Taejoon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millimeter Wave Inverse Pinhole Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13904v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Millimeter wave (mmWave) radars are popular for perception in vision-denied contexts due to their compact size. This paper explores emerging use-cases that involve static mount or momentarily-static compact radars, for example, a hovering drone. The key challenge with static compact radars is that their limited form-factor also limits their angular resolution. This paper presents Umbra, a mmWave high resolution imaging system, that introduces the concept of rotating mmWave "inverse pinholes" for angular resolution enhancement. We present the imaging system model, design, and evaluation of mmWave inverse pinholes. The inverse pinhole is attractive for its lightweight nature, which enables low-power rotation, upgrading static-mount radars. We also show how propellers in aerial vehicles act as natural inverse pinholes and can enjoy the benefits of high-resolution imaging even while they are momentarily static, e.g., hovering. Our evaluation shows Umbra resolving up to 2.5$^{\circ}$ with just a single antenna, a 5$\times$ improvement compared to 14$^{\circ}$ from a compact mmWave radar baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13904v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akarsh Prabhakara, Yawen Liu, Aswin C. Sankaranarayanan, Anthony Rowe, Swarun Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An LLM-Powered AI Agent Framework for Holistic IoT Traffic Interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13925v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Internet of Things (IoT) networks generate diverse and high-volume traffic that reflects both normal activity and potential threats. Deriving meaningful insight from such telemetry requires cross-layer interpretation of behaviors, protocols, and context rather than isolated detection. This work presents an LLM-powered AI agent framework that converts raw packet captures into structured and semantically enriched representations for interactive analysis. The framework integrates feature extraction, transformer-based anomaly detection, packet and flow summarization, threat intelligence enrichment, and retrieval-augmented question answering. An AI agent guided by a large language model performs reasoning over the indexed traffic artifacts, assembling evidence to produce accurate and human-readable interpretations. Experimental evaluation on multiple IoT captures and six open models shows that hybrid retrieval, which combines lexical and semantic search with reranking, substantially improves BLEU, ROUGE, METEOR, and BERTScore results compared with dense-only retrieval. System profiling further indicates low CPU, GPU, and memory overhead, demonstrating that the framework achieves holistic and efficient interpretation of IoT network traffic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13925v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Adu Worae, Spyridon Mastorakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Dynamic Handover via AI-assisted Signal Quality Prediction in 6G Multi-RAT Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14832v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The emerging paradigm of 6G multiple Radio Access Technology (multi-RAT) networks, where cellular and Wireless Fidelity (WiFi) transmitters coexist, requires mobility decisions that remain reliable under fast channel dynamics, interference, and heterogeneous coverage. Handover in multi-RAT deployments is still highly reactive and event-triggered, relying on instantaneous measurements and threshold events. This work proposes a Machine Learning (ML)-assisted Predictive Conditional Handover (P-CHO) framework based on a model-driven and short-horizon signal quality forecasts. We present a generalized P-CHO sequence workflow orchestrated by a RAT Steering Controller, which standardizes data collection, parallel per-RAT predictions, decision logic with hysteresis-based conditions, and CHO execution. Considering a realistic multi-RAT environment, we train RAT-aware Long Short Term Memory (LSTM) networks to forecast the signal quality indicators of mobile users along randomized trajectories. The proposed P-CHO models are trained and evaluated under different channel models for cellular and IEEE 802.11 WiFi integrated coverage. We study the impact of hyperparameter tuning of LSTM models under different system settings, and compare direct multi-step versus recursive P-CHO variants. Comparisons against baseline predictors are also carried out. Finally, the proposed P-CHO is tested under soft and hard handover settings, showing that hysteresis-enabled P-CHO scheme is able to reduce handover failures and ping-pong events. Overall, the proposed P-CHO framework can enable accurate, low-latency, and proactive handovers suitable for ML-assisted handover steering in 6G multi-RAT deployments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14832v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Lamprini A. Bartsioka, Anastasios Giannopoulos, Sotirios Spantideas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence-Aware Entangling and Swapping Strategy Optimization for Entanglement Routing in Quantum Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14912v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum teleportation enables high-security communications through end-to-end quantum entangled pairs. End-to-end entangled pairs are created by using swapping processes to consume short entangled pairs and generate long pairs. However, due to environmental interference, entangled pairs decohere over time, resulting in low fidelity. Thus, generating entangled pairs at the right time is crucial. Moreover, the swapping process also causes additional fidelity loss. To this end, this paper presents a short time slot protocol, where a time slot can only accommodate a process. It has a more flexible arrangement of entangling and swapping processes than the traditional long time slot protocol. It raises a new optimization problem TETRIS for finding strategies of entangling and swapping for each request to maximize the fidelity sum of all accepted requests. To solve the TETRIS, we design two novel algorithms with different optimization techniques. Finally, the simulation results manifest that our algorithms can outperform the existing methods by up to 60 ~ 78% in general, and by 20 ~ 75% even under low entangling probabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14912v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Min Huang, Cheng-Yang Cheng, Ming-Huang Chien, Jian-Jhih Kuo, Chih-Yu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: Adversarial Evasion Attacks Practicality in NIDS Domain and the Impact of Dynamic Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05494v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine Learning (ML) has become pervasive, and its deployment in Network Intrusion Detection Systems (NIDS) is inevitable due to its automated nature and high accuracy compared to traditional models in processing and classifying large volumes of data. However, ML has been found to have several flaws, most importantly, adversarial attacks, which aim to trick ML models into producing faulty predictions. While most adversarial attack research focuses on computer vision datasets, recent studies have explored the suitability of these attacks against ML-based network security entities, especially NIDS, due to the wide difference between different domains regarding the generation of adversarial attacks.
  To further explore the practicality of adversarial attacks against ML-based NIDS in-depth, this paper presents several key contributions: identifying numerous practicality issues for evasion adversarial attacks on ML-NIDS using an attack tree threat model, introducing a taxonomy of practicality issues associated with adversarial attacks against ML-based NIDS, identifying specific leaf nodes in our attack tree that demonstrate some practicality for real-world implementation and conducting a comprehensive review and exploration of these potentially viable attack approaches, and investigating how the dynamicity of real-world ML models affects evasion adversarial attacks against NIDS. Our experiments indicate that continuous re-training, even without adversarial training, can reduce the effectiveness of adversarial attacks. While adversarial attacks can compromise ML-based NIDSs, our aim is to highlight the significant gap between research and real-world practicality in this domain, which warrants attention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05494v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed elShehaby, Ashraf Matrawy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs' Suitability for Network Security: A Case Study of STRIDE Threat Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Artificial Intelligence (AI) is expected to be an integral part of next-generation AI-native 6G networks. With the prevalence of AI, researchers have identified numerous use cases of AI in network security. However, there are very few studies that analyze the suitability of Large Language Models (LLMs) in network security. To fill this gap, we examine the suitability of LLMs in network security, particularly with the case study of STRIDE threat modeling. We utilize four prompting techniques with five LLMs to perform STRIDE classification of 5G threats. From our evaluation results, we point out key findings and detailed insights along with the explanation of the possible underlying factors influencing the behavior of LLMs in the modeling of certain threats. The numerical results and the insights support the necessity for adjusting and fine-tuning LLMs for network security use cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04101v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>AbdulAziz AbdulGhaffar, Ashraf Matrawy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
