<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Routing for Large ML Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Training large language models (LLMs), and other large machine learning models, involves repeated communication of large volumes of data across a data center network. The communication patterns induced by these training process exhibit high regularity and persistence, giving rise to significant opportunities for optimizing the manner in which flows are routed across the network. We present an algorithmic framework for \textit{quantifying} network-wide efficiency in the context of training LLMs (and other large-scale ML models), and for periodically \textit{optimizing} routing with respect to this global metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05324v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofir Cohen, Jose Yallouz Michael Schapira, Shahar Belkar, Tal Mizrahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wi-Fi 6 Cross-Technology Interference Detection and Mitigation by OFDMA: an Experimental Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cross-Technology Interference (CTI) poses challenges for the performance and robustness of wireless networks. There are opportunities for better cooperation if the spectral occupation and technology of the interference can be detected. Namely, this information can help the Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiple Access (OFDMA) scheduler in IEEE 802.11ax (Wi-Fi 6) to efficiently allocate resources to multiple users inthe frequency domain. This work shows that a single Channel State Information (CSI) snapshot, which is used for packet demodulation in the receiver, is enough to detect and classify the type of CTI on low-cost Wi-Fi 6 hardware. We show the classification accuracy of a small Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) for different Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) and Signal-to-Interference Ratio (SIR) with simulated data, as well as using a wired and over-the-air test with a professional wireless connectivity tester, while running the inference on the low-cost device. Furthermore, we use openwifi, a full-stack Wi-Fi transceiver running on software-defined radio (SDR) available in the w-iLab.t testbed, as Access Point (AP) to implement a CTI-aware multi-user OFDMA scheduler when the clients send CTI detection feedback to the AP. We show experimentally that it can fully mitigate the 35% throughput loss caused by CTI when the AP applies the appropriate scheduling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05429v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thijs Havinga, Xianjun Jiao, Wei Liu, Baiheng Chen, Adnan Shahid, Ingrid Moerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RiLoCo: An ISAC-oriented AI Solution to Build RIS-empowered Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The advance towards 6G networks comes with the promise of unprecedented performance in sensing and communication capabilities. The feat of achieving those, while satisfying the ever-growing demands placed on wireless networks, promises revolutionary advancements in sensing and communication technologies. As 6G aims to cater to the growing demands of wireless network users, the implementation of intelligent and efficient solutions becomes essential. In particular, reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs), also known as Smart Surfaces, are envisioned as a transformative technology for future 6G networks. The performance of RISs when used to augment existing devices is nevertheless largely affected by their precise location. Suboptimal deployments are also costly to correct, negating their low-cost benefits. This paper investigates the topic of optimal RISs diffusion, taking into account the improvement they provide both for the sensing and communication capabilities of the infrastructure while working with other antennas and sensors. We develop a combined metric that takes into account the properties and location of the individual devices to compute the performance of the entire infrastructure. We then use it as a foundation to build a reinforcement learning architecture that solves the RIS deployment problem. Since our metric measures the surface where given localization thresholds are achieved and the communication coverage of the area of interest, the novel framework we provide is able to seamlessly balance sensing and communication, showing its performance gain against reference solutions, where it achieves simultaneously almost the reference performance for communication and the reference performance for localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05480v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Encinas-Lago, Vincenzo Sciancalepore, Henk Wymeersch, Marco Di Renzo, Xavier Costa-Perez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Simulator-centric Compositional Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04810v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article introduces a novel methodology, Network Simulator-centric Compositional Testing (NSCT), to enhance the verification of network protocols with a particular focus on time-varying network properties. NSCT follows a Model-Based Testing (MBT) approach. These approaches usually struggle to test and represent time-varying network properties. NSCT also aims to achieve more accurate and reproducible protocol testing. It is implemented using the Ivy tool and the Shadow network simulator. This enables online debugging of real protocol implementations. A case study on an implementation of QUIC (picoquic) is presented, revealing an error in its compliance with a time-varying specification. This error has subsequently been rectified, highlighting NSCT's effectiveness in uncovering and addressing real-world protocol implementation issues. The article underscores NSCT's potential in advancing protocol testing methodologies, offering a notable contribution to the field of network protocol verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04810v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-62645-6_10</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tom Rousseaux, Christophe Crochet, John Aoga, Axel Legay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small noise limits of Markov chains and the PageRank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We recall the classical formulation of PageRank as the stationary distribution of a singularly perturbed irreducible Markov chain that is not irreducible when the perturbation parameter goes to zero. Specifically, we use the Markov chain tree theorem to derive explicit expressions for the PageRank. This analysis leads to some surprising results. These results are then extended to a much more general class of perturbations that subsume personalized PageRank. We also give examples where even simpler formulas for PageRank are possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05137v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vivek S Borkar, S Sowmya, Raghavendra Tripathi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Layer-Optimized Link Selection for Hologram Video Streaming over Millimeter Wave Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Holographic-type communication brings an immersive tele-holography experience by delivering holographic contents to users. As the direct representation of holographic contents, hologram videos are naturally three-dimensional representation, which consist of a huge volume of data. Advanced multi-connectivity (MC) millimeter-wave (mmWave) networks are now available to transmit hologram videos by providing the necessary bandwidth. However, the existing link selection schemes in MC-based mmWave networks neglect the source content characteristics of hologram videos and the coordination among the parameters of different protocol layers in each link, leading to sub-optimal streaming performance. To address this issue, we propose a cross-layer-optimized link selection scheme for hologram video streaming over mmWave networks. This scheme optimizes link selection by jointly adjusting the video coding bitrate, the modulation and channel coding schemes (MCS), and link power allocation to minimize the end-to-end hologram distortion while guaranteeing the synchronization and quality balance between real and imaginary components of the hologram. Results show that the proposed scheme can effectively improve the hologram video streaming performance in terms of PSNR by 1.2dB to 6.4dB against the non-cross-layer scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05195v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Jiang, Yanwei Liu, Jinxia Liu, Antonios Argyriou, Yifei Chen, Wen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of 3D Terrestrial and Aerial Spectrum Sharing with Massive MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Connecting aerial and terrestrial users with a single base station (BS) is increasingly challenging due to the rising number of aerial users like unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs). Traditional BSs, designed with down-tilted beams, focus mainly on ground users, but massive MIMO (mMIMO) systems can significantly enhance coverage in low-altitude airspace. This paper analyzes how a mMIMO BS serves both aerial and terrestrial users in a 3D spectrum-sharing scheme. Using Semi-orthogonal User Selection (SUS) and random scheduling, we assess the spectral efficiency and performance limits of these systems. Results reveal that mMIMO effectively supports more terrestrial users, influenced by channel characteristics and user scheduling strategies, providing key insights for future 3D aerial-terrestrial networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05279v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achiel Colpaert, Zhuangzhuang Cui, Sofie Pollin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BSAC-CoEx: Coexistence of URLLC and Distributed Learning Services via Device Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.11805v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in distributed intelligence have driven impressive progress across a diverse range of applications, from industrial automation to autonomous transportation. Nevertheless, deploying distributed learning services over wireless networks poses numerous challenges. These arise from inherent uncertainties in wireless environments (e.g., random channel fluctuations), limited resources (e.g., bandwidth and transmit power), and the presence of coexisting services on the network. In this paper, we investigate a mixed service scenario wherein high-priority ultra-reliable low latency communication (URLLC) and low-priority distributed learning services run concurrently over a network. Utilizing device selection, we aim to minimize the convergence time of distributed learning while simultaneously fulfilling the requirements of the URLLC service. We formulate this problem as a Markov decision process and address it via BSAC-CoEx, a framework based on the branching soft actor-critic (BSAC) algorithm that determines each device's participation decision through distinct branches in the actor's neural network. We evaluate our solution with a realistic simulator that is compliant with 3GPP standards for factory automation use cases. Our simulation results confirm that our solution can significantly decrease the training delays of the distributed learning service while keeping the URLLC availability above its required threshold and close to the scenario where URLLC solely consumes all wireless resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.11805v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milad Ganjalizadeh, Hossein Shokri Ghadikolaei, Deniz G\"und\"uz, Marina Petrova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personalized Hierarchical Split Federated Learning in Wireless Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06042v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Extreme resource constraints make large-scale machine learning (ML) with distributed clients challenging in wireless networks. On the one hand, large-scale ML requires massive information exchange between clients and server(s). On the other hand, these clients have limited battery and computation powers that are often dedicated to operational computations. Split federated learning (SFL) is emerging as a potential solution to mitigate these challenges, by splitting the ML model into client-side and server-side model blocks, where only the client-side block is trained on the client device. However, practical applications require personalized models that are suitable for the client's personal task. Motivated by this, we propose a personalized hierarchical split federated learning (PHSFL) algorithm that is specially designed to achieve better personalization performance. More specially, owing to the fact that regardless of the severity of the statistical data distributions across the clients, many of the features have similar attributes, we only train the body part of the federated learning (FL) model while keeping the (randomly initialized) classifier frozen during the training phase. We first perform extensive theoretical analysis to understand the impact of model splitting and hierarchical model aggregations on the global model. Once the global model is trained, we fine-tune each client classifier to obtain the personalized models. Our empirical findings suggest that while the globally trained model with the untrained classifier performs quite similarly to other existing solutions, the fine-tuned models show significantly improved personalized performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06042v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md-Ferdous Pervej, Andreas F. Molisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
