<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Purification With Finite Latency Classical Communication in Quantum Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum networks rely on high fidelity entangled pairs distributed to nodes, but maintaining their fidelity is challenged by environmental decoherence during storage. Entanglement purification is used to restore fidelity, but the idle periods imposed by the associated classical communication delays counteract this goal by exposing the states to further decoherence. In this work, we analyze the practical viability of entanglement purification protocols (BBPSSW, DEJMPS), under non-instantaneous classical coordination over Internet protocol (IP) communications networks. We present a comprehensive performance evaluation of these protocols in various network conditions for a range of quantum memory technologies. We employ a microscopic Lindblad treatment of the underlying quantum dynamics, and use current-generation metropolitan IP network latency statistics and parameters drawn from quantum memory testbeds. In doing so we identify the regions in which entanglement purification succeeds and fails, delineated by break-even iso-fidelity contours in the phase space. We then determine the total number of entangled pairs required to complete a multi-round purification protocol, and the steady-state throughput of entangled pairs with purified fidelities that exceed application-specific thresholds. This provides latency budgets, memory quality targets, and resource-overhead estimates for deploying purification on current and near-future networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03667v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Vasan, Alexander Nico-Katz, Boulat A. Bash, Daniel C. Kilper, Marco Ruffini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drift Plus Optimistic Penalty -- A Learning Framework for Stochastic Network Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of joint routing and scheduling in queueing networks, where the edge transmission costs are unknown. At each time-slot, the network controller receives noisy observations of transmission costs only for those edges it selects for transmission. The network controller's objective is to make routing and scheduling decisions so that the total expected cost is minimized. This problem exhibits an exploration-exploitation trade-off, however, previous bandit-style solutions cannot be directly applied to this problem due to the queueing dynamics. In order to ensure network stability, the network controller needs to optimize throughput and cost simultaneously. We show that the best achievable cost is lower bounded by the solution to a static optimization problem, and develop a network control policy using techniques from Lyapunov drift-plus-penalty optimization and multi-arm bandits. We show that the policy achieves a sub-linear regret of order $O(\sqrt{T}\log T)$, as compared to the best policy that has complete knowledge of arrivals and costs. Finally, we evaluate the proposed policy using simulations and show that its regret is indeed sub-linear.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03762v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathwik Chadaga, Eytan Modiano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Versatile and Programmable UAV Platform for Radio Access Network and End-to-End Cellular Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a measurement platform to capture mobile network performance metrics including coverage and quality of service in regions where conventional coverage testing approaches are frequently time-intensive, labor-demanding, and occasionally hazardous. Traditionally, crowd-sourcing methods are used to collect cellular network performance metrics. However, these approaches are inadequate in rural areas due to low-density population, and difficult terrain. The platform described here is a UAV-based and is designed to investigate the mobile network performance through aerial operations and gather Radio Access Network (RAN) signal alongside end-to-end network performance metrics. Our platform gathers metrics through the integration of an onboard computation unit and commercial off-the-shelf cellular modem. The gathered data are subsequently analyzed and displayed using geospatial mapping utilities and statistical techniques to deliver key observations on cellular network performance. Experimental results showed that the received signal power improves at higher altitudes due to enhanced line-of-sight (LoS) conditions as expected. However, the signal quality degrades as a result of increased interference from neighboring cells. The analysis reveals that for most of the geographic area covered in the initial experiments the system maintained acceptable signal quality, with adequate throughput performance for both uplink and downlink communications, while maintaining satisfactory round-trip time characteristics. Notably, the experiment showed that a strong radio signal metric for a given cell does not necessarily translate to consistent spatial coverage across the tested region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03818v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sherwan Jalal Abdullah, Sravan Reddy Chintareddy, Victor S. Frost, Shawn Keshmiri, Morteza Hashemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indoor Positioning with Wi-Fi Location: A Survey of IEEE 802.11mc/az/bk Fine Timing Measurement Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Indoor positioning is an enabling technology for home, office, and industrial network users because it provides numerous information and communication technology (ICT) and Internet of things (IoT) functionalities such as indoor navigation, smart meter localization, asset tracking, support for emergency services, and detection of hazardous situations. The IEEE 802.11mc fine timing measurement (FTM) protocol (commercially known as Wi-Fi Location) has great potential to enable indoor positioning in future generation devices, primarily because of the high availability of Wi-Fi networks, FTM's high accuracy and device support. Furthermore, new FTM enhancements are available in the released (802.11az) and recently completed (802.11bk) amendments. Despite the multitude of literature reviews on indoor positioning, a survey dedicated to FTM and its recent enhancements has so far been lacking. We fill this gap by classifying and reviewing over 180 research papers related to the practical accuracy achieved with FTM, methods for improving its accuracy (also with machine learning), combining FTM with other indoor positioning systems, FTM-based applications, and security issues. Based on the conducted survey, we summarize the most important research achievements and formulate open areas for further research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Kosek-Szott, Szymon Szott, Wojciech Ciezobka, Maksymilian Wojnar, Krzysztof Rusek, Jonathan Segev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Task Offloading of Vehicular Edge Computing with Parallel Computation Queues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work considers a parallel task execution strategy in vehicular edge computing (VEC) networks, where edge servers are deployed along the roadside to process offloaded computational tasks of vehicular users. To minimize the overall waiting delay among vehicular users, a novel task offloading solution is implemented based on the network cooperation balancing resource under-utilization and load congestion. Dual evaluation through theoretical and numerical ways shows that the developed solution achieves a globally optimal delay reduction performance compared to existing methods, which is also approved by the feasibility test over a real-map virtual environment. The in-depth analysis reveals that predicting the instantaneous processing power of edge servers facilitates the identification of overloaded servers, which is critical for determining network delay. By considering discrete variables of the queue, the proposed technique's precise estimation can effectively address these combinatorial challenges to achieve optimal performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03935v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungho Cho, Sung Il Choi, Seung Hyun Oh, Ian P. Roberts, Sang Hyun Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Effect of an Extreme Weather Event on Telecommunications and Information Technology: Insights from 30 Days of Flooding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04219v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In May 2024, weeks of severe rainfall in Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil caused widespread damage to infrastructure, impacting over 400 cities and 2.3 million people. This study presents the construction of comprehensive telecommunications datasets during this climatic event, encompassing Internet measurements, fiber cut reports, and Internet Exchange routing data. By correlating network disruptions with hydrological and operational factors, the dataset offers insights into the resilience of fiber networks, data centers, and Internet traffic during critical events. For each scenario, we investigate failures related to the Information and Communication Technology infrastructure and highlight the challenges faced when its resilience is critically tested. Preliminary findings reveal trends in connectivity restoration, infrastructure vulnerabilities, and user behavior changes. These datasets and pre-analysis aim to support future research on disaster recovery strategies and the development of robust telecommunications systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04219v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-85960-1_12</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Leandro M\'arcio Bertholdo, Renan Barreto Paredes, Gabriela de Lima Marin, Cesar A. H. Loureiro, Milton Kaoru Kashiwakura Pedro de Botelho Marcos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Base Station Sleeping and Resource Allocation for Green Uplink Fully-Decoupled RAN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05517v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fully-decoupled radio access network (FD-RAN) is an innovative architecture designed for next-generation mobile communication networks, featuring decoupled control and data planes as well as separated uplink and downlink transmissions. To further enhance energy efficiency, this paper explores a green approach to FD-RAN by incorporating adaptive base station (BS) sleeping and resource allocation. First, we introduce a holistic power consumption model and formulate a energy efficiency maximization problem for FD-RAN, involving joint optimization of user equipment (UE) association, BS sleeping, and power control. Subsequently, the optimization problem is decomposed into two subproblems. The first subproblem, involving UE power control, is solved using a successive lower-bound maximization approach based on Dinkelbach's algorithm. The second subproblem, addressing UE association and BS sleeping, is tackled via a modified, low-complexity many-to-many swap matching algorithm. Extensive simulation results demonstrate the superior effectiveness of FD-RAN with our proposed algorithms, revealing the sources of energy efficiency gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05517v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Sun, Haibo Zhou, Kai Yu, Yunting Xu, Bo Qian, Lin X. Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MixNet: A Runtime Reconfigurable Optical-Electrical Fabric for Distributed Mixture-of-Experts Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03905v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mixture-of-Expert (MoE) models outperform conventional models by selectively activating different subnets, named experts, on a per-token basis. This gated computation generates dynamic communications that cannot be determined beforehand, challenging the existing GPU interconnects that remain static during the distributed training process. In this paper, we advocate for a first-of-its-kind system, called MixNet, that unlocks topology reconfiguration during distributed MoE training. Towards this vision, we first perform a production measurement study and show that the MoE dynamic communication pattern has strong locality, alleviating the requirement of global reconfiguration. Based on this, we design and implement a regionally reconfigurable high-bandwidth domain on top of existing electrical interconnects using optical circuit switching (OCS), achieving scalability while maintaining rapid adaptability. We have built a fully functional MixNet prototype with commodity hardware and a customized collective communication runtime that trains state-of-the-art MoE models with in-training topology reconfiguration across 32 A100 GPUs. Large-scale packet-level simulations show that MixNet delivers comparable performance as the non-blocking fat-tree fabric while boosting the training cost efficiency (e.g., performance per dollar) of four representative MoE models by 1.2x-1.5x and 1.9x-2.3x at 100 Gbps and 400 Gbps link bandwidths, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03905v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3718958.3750465</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the 2025 ACM SIGCOMM Conference</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xudong Liao, Yijun Sun, Han Tian, Xinchen Wan, Yilun Jin, Zilong Wang, Zhenghang Ren, Xinyang Huang, Wenxue Li, Kin Fai Tse, Zhizhen Zhong, Guyue Liu, Ying Zhang, Xiaofeng Ye, Yiming Zhang, Kai Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SmartFLow: A Communication-Efficient SDN Framework for Cross-Silo Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cross-silo Federated Learning (FL) enables multiple institutions to collaboratively train machine learning models while preserving data privacy. In such settings, clients repeatedly exchange model weights with a central server, making the overall training time highly sensitive to network performance. However, conventional routing methods often fail to prevent congestion, leading to increased communication latency and prolonged training. Software-Defined Networking (SDN), which provides centralized and programmable control over network resources, offers a promising way to address this limitation. To this end, we propose SmartFLow, an SDN-based framework designed to enhance communication efficiency in cross-silo FL. SmartFLow dynamically adjusts routing paths in response to changing network conditions, thereby reducing congestion and improving synchronization efficiency. Experimental results show that SmartFLow decreases parameter synchronization time by up to 47% compared to shortest-path routing and 41% compared to capacity-aware routing. Furthermore, it achieves these gains with minimal computational overhead and scales effectively to networks of up to 50 clients, demonstrating its practicality for real-world FL deployments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00603v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osama Abu Hamdan, Hao Che, Engin Arslan, Md Arifuzzaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLEET: A Federated Learning Emulation and Evaluation Testbed for Holistic Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00621v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Federated Learning (FL) presents a robust paradigm for privacy-preserving, decentralized machine learning. However, a significant gap persists between the theoretical design of FL algorithms and their practical performance, largely because existing evaluation tools often fail to model realistic operational conditions. Many testbeds oversimplify the critical dynamics among algorithmic efficiency, client-level heterogeneity, and continuously evolving network infrastructure. To address this challenge, we introduce the Federated Learning Emulation and Evaluation Testbed (FLEET). This comprehensive platform provides a scalable and configurable environment by integrating a versatile, framework-agnostic learning component with a high-fidelity network emulator. FLEET supports diverse machine learning frameworks, customizable real-world network topologies, and dynamic background traffic generation. The testbed collects holistic metrics that correlate algorithmic outcomes with detailed network statistics. By unifying the entire experiment configuration, FLEET enables researchers to systematically investigate how network constraints, such as limited bandwidth, high latency, and packet loss, affect the convergence and efficiency of FL algorithms. This work provides the research community with a robust tool to bridge the gap between algorithmic theory and real-world network conditions, promoting the holistic and reproducible evaluation of federated learning systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00621v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osama Abu Hamdan, Hao Che, Engin Arslan, Md Arifuzzaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Entanglement Routing for Satellite-Aerial-Terrestrial Quantum Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13517v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the era of 6G and beyond, space-aerial-terrestrial quantum networks (SATQNs) are shaping the future of the global-scale quantum Internet. This paper investigates the collaboration among satellite, aerial, and terrestrial quantum networks to efficiently transmit high-fidelity quantum entanglements over long distances. We begin with a comprehensive overview of existing satellite-, aerial-, and terrestrial-based quantum networks. Subsequently, we address the entanglement routing problem with the objective of maximizing quantum network throughput by jointly optimizing path selection and entanglement generation rates (PS-EGR). Given that the original problem is formulated as a mixed-integer linear programming (MILP) problem, which is inherently intractable, we propose a Benders' decomposition (BD)-based algorithm to solve the problem efficiently. Numerical results validate the effectiveness of the proposed PS-EGR scheme, offering valuable insights into various optimizable factors within the system. Finally, we discuss the current challenges and propose promising avenues for future research in SATQNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13517v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhang, Yanmin Gong, Lei Fan, Yu Wang, Zhu Han, Yuanxiong Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
