<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI</link>
    <description>cs.NI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 02:48:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Less is More: Optimizing Probe Selection Using Shared Latency Anomalies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Latency anomalies, defined as persistent or transient increases in round-trip time (RTT), are common in residential Internet performance. When multiple users observe anomalies to the same destination, this may reflect shared infrastructure, routing behavior, or congestion. Inferring such shared behavior is challenging because anomaly magnitudes vary widely across devices, even within the same ISP and geographic area, and detailed network topology information is often unavailable.
  We study whether devices experiencing a shared latency anomaly observe similar changes in RTT magnitude using a topology-agnostic approach. Using four months of high-frequency RTT measurements from 99 residential probes in Chicago, we detect shared anomalies and analyze their consistency in amplitude and duration without relying on traceroutes or explicit path information. Building on prior change-point detection techniques, we find that many shared anomalies exhibit similar amplitude across users, particularly within the same ISP.
  Motivated by this observation, we design a sampling algorithm that reduces redundancy by selecting representative devices under user-defined constraints. Our approach captures 95 percent of aggregate anomaly impact using fewer than half of the deployed probes. Compared to two baselines, it identifies significantly more unique anomalies at comparable coverage levels. We further show that geographic diversity remains important when selecting probes within a single ISP, even at city scale. Overall, our results demonstrate that anomaly amplitude and duration provide effective topology-independent signals for scalable monitoring, troubleshooting, and cost-efficient sampling in residential Internet measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03965v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taveesh Sharma, Andrew Chu, Paul Schmitt, Francesco Bronzino, Nick Feamster, Nicole Marwell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Tier UAV Edge Computing Towards Long-Term Energy Stability for Low Altitude Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The agile mobility of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) makes them ideal for low-altitude edge computing. This paper proposes a novel multi-tier UAV edge computing system where lightweight Low-Tier UAVs (L-UAVs) function as edge servers for vehicle users, supported by a powerful High-Tier UAV (H-UAV) acting as a backup server. The objective is to minimize task execution delays while ensuring the long-term energy stability of the L-UAVs, despite unknown future system states. To this end, the problem is decoupled using Lyapunov optimization, which adaptively balances the priorities of task delays and L-UAV energy cost based on their real-time energy states. An efficient vehicle to L-UAV matching scheme is designed, and the joint optimization problem for task assignment, computing resource allocation, and trajectory control of L-UAVs and H-UAV is then solved via a Block Coordinate Descent (BCD) algorithm. Simulation results demonstrate a reduction in L-UAV transmission energy of over 26% and superior L-UAV energy stability compared to existing benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04258v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufei Ye, Shijian Gao, Xinhu Zheng, Liuqing Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-Empowered Cooperative Content Caching in Vehicular Fog Caching-Assisted Platoon Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter proposes a novel three-tier content caching architecture for Vehicular Fog Caching (VFC)-assisted platoon, where the VFC is formed by the vehicles driving near the platoon. The system strategically coordinates storage across local platoon vehicles, dynamic VFC clusters, and cloud server (CS) to minimize content retrieval latency. To efficiently manage distributed storage, we integrate large language models (LLMs) for real-time and intelligent caching decisions. The proposed approach leverages LLMs' ability to process heterogeneous information, including user profiles, historical data, content characteristics, and dynamic system states. Through a designed prompting framework encoding task objectives and caching constraints, the LLMs formulate caching as a decision-making task, and our hierarchical deterministic caching mapping strategy enables adaptive requests prediction and precise content placement across three tiers without frequent retraining. Simulation results demonstrate the advantages of our proposed caching scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04471v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Tan, Qiong Wu, Pingyi Fan, Kezhi Wang, Nan Cheng, Wen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Mind World Model Inspired Network Digital Twin for Access Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Emerging networked systems such as industrial IoT and real-time cyber-physical infrastructures demand intelligent scheduling strategies capable of adapting to dynamic traffic, deadlines, and interference constraints. In this work, we present a novel Digital Twin-enabled scheduling framework inspired by Dual Mind World Model (DMWM) architecture, for learning-informed and imagination-driven network control. Unlike conventional rule-based or purely data-driven policies, the proposed DMWM combines short-horizon predictive planning with symbolic model-based rollout, enabling the scheduler to anticipate future network states and adjust transmission decisions accordingly. We implement the framework in a configurable simulation testbed and benchmark its performance against traditional heuristics and reinforcement learning baselines under varied traffic conditions. Our results show that DMWM achieves superior performance in bursty, interference-limited, and deadline-sensitive environments, while maintaining interpretability and sample efficiency. The proposed design bridges the gap between network-level reasoning and low-overhead learning, marking a step toward scalable and adaptive NDT-based network optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hrishikesh Dutta, Roberto Minerva, Noel Crespi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Dual Connectivity in 6G Leo Constellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dual connectivity (DC) has garnered significant attention in 5G evolution, allowing for enhancing throughput and reliability by leveraging the channel conditions of two paths. However, when the paths exhibit different delays, such as in terrestrial and non-terrestrial integrated networks with multi-orbit topologies or in networks characterized by frequent topology changes, like Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellite constellations with different elevation angles, traffic delivery may experience packet reordering or triggering congestion control mechanisms. Additionally, real-time traffic may experience packet drops if their arrival exceeds a play-out threshold. Different techniques have been proposed to address these issues, such as packet duplication, packet switching, and network coding for traffic scheduling in DC. However, if not accurately designed, these techniques can lead to resource waste, encoding/decoding delays, and computational overhead, undermining DC's intended benefits. This paper provides a mathematical framework for calculating the average end-to-end packet loss in case of a loss process modeled with a Discrete Markov Chain - typical of a wireless channel - when combining packet duplication and packet switching or when network coding is employed in DC. Such metrics help derive optimal policies with full knowledge of the underlying loss process to be compared to empirical models learned through Machine Learning algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04825v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achilles Machumilane, Alberto Gotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Availability Attacks Without an Adversary: Evidence from Enterprise LANs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04216v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Denial-of-Service (DoS) conditions in enterprise networks are commonly attributed to malicious actors. However, availability can also be compromised by benign non-malicious insider behavior. This paper presents an empirical study of a production enterprise LAN that demonstrates how routine docking and undocking of user endpoints repeatedly trigger rapid recalculations of the control plane of the Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol (RSTP) [1]. Although protocol-compliant and nonmalicious, these events introduce transient forwarding disruptions of approximately 2-4 seconds duration that degrade realtime streaming (voice and video) services while remaining largely undetected by conventional security monitoring. We map this phenomenon to the NIST and MITRE insider threat frameworks, characterizing it as an unintentional insider-driven availability breach, and demonstrate that explicit edge-port configuration effectively mitigates the condition without compromising loop prevention</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04216v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajendra Paudyal, Rajendra Upadhyay, Al Nahian Bin Emran, Lisa Donnan, Duminda Wijesekera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Oblivious Load-Balancing for Sparse Traffic in Large-Scale Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02537v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Oblivious load-balancing in networks involves routing traffic from sources to destinations using predetermined routes independent of the traffic, so that the maximum load on any link in the network is minimized. We investigate oblivious load-balancing schemes for a $N\times N$ torus network under sparse traffic where there are at most $k$ active source-destination pairs. We are motivated by the problem of load-balancing in large-scale LEO satellite networks, which can be modelled as a torus, where the traffic is known to be sparse and localized to certain hotspot areas. We formulate the problem as a linear program and show that no oblivious routing scheme can achieve a worst-case load lower than approximately $\frac{\sqrt{2k}}{4}$ when $1&lt;k \leq N^2/2$ and $\frac{N}{4}$ when $N^2/2\leq k\leq N^2$. Moreover, we demonstrate that the celebrated Valiant Load Balancing scheme is suboptimal under sparse traffic and construct an optimal oblivious load-balancing scheme that achieves the lower bound. Further, we discover a $\sqrt{2}$ multiplicative gap between the worst-case load of a non-oblivious routing and the worst-case load of any oblivious routing. The results can also be extended to general $N\times M$ tori with unequal link capacities along the vertical and horizontal directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02537v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rudrapatna Vallabh Ramakanth, Eytan Modiano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI-Powered CPS-Enabled Vulnerable-User-Aware Urban Transportation Digital Twin: Methods and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10396v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present methods and applications for the development of digital twins (DT) for urban traffic management. While the majority of studies on the DT focus on its ``eyes," which is the emerging sensing and perception like object detection and tracking, what really distinguishes the DT from a traditional simulator lies in its ``brain," the prediction and decision making capabilities of extracting patterns and making informed decisions from what has been seen and perceived. In order to add value to urban transportation management, DTs need to be powered by artificial intelligence and complement with low-latency high-bandwidth sensing and networking technologies, in other words, cyberphysical systems. This paper can be a pointer to help researchers and practitioners identify challenges and opportunities for the development of DTs; a bridge to initiate conversations across disciplines; and a road map to exploiting potentials of DTs for diverse urban transportation applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10396v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongjie Fu, Mehmet K. Turkcan, Mahshid Ghasemi, Zhaobin Mo, Chengbo Zang, Abhishek Adhikari, Zoran Kostic, Gil Zussman, Xuan Di</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic and Distributed Routing in IoT Networks based on Multi-Objective Q-Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00918v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: IoT networks often face conflicting routing goals such as maximizing packet delivery, minimizing delay, and conserving limited battery energy. These priorities can also change dynamically: for example, an emergency alert requires high reliability, while routine monitoring prioritizes energy efficiency to prolong network lifetime. Existing works, including many deep reinforcement learning approaches, are typically centralized and assume static objectives, making them slow to adapt when preferences shift. We propose a dynamic and fully distributed multi-objective Q-learning routing algorithm that learns multiple per-preference Q-tables in parallel and introduces a novel greedy interpolation policy to act near-optimally for unseen preferences without retraining or central coordination. A theoretical analysis further shows that the optimal value function is Lipschitz-continuous in the preference parameter, ensuring that the proposed greedy interpolation policy yields provably near-optimal behavior. Simulations show that our approach adapts in real time to shifting priorities and achieves up to 80-90\% lower energy consumption and more than 2-5x higher cumulative rewards and packet delivery compared to six baseline protocols, under dynamic and distributed settings. Sensitivity analysis across varying preference window lengths confirms that the proposed DPQ framework consistently achieves higher composite reward than all baseline methods, demonstrating robustness to changes in operating conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00918v4</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Vaishnav, Praveen Kumar Donta, Sindri Magn\'usson</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
