<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.NC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC</link>
    <description>q-bio.NC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 05:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric Enhancement of PerceptNet: A Human-Inspired Approach for Image Quality Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While deep learning models can learn human-like features at earlier levels, which suggests their utility in modeling human vision, few attempts exist to incorporate these features by design. Current approaches mostly optimize all parameters blindly, only constraining minor architectural aspects. This paper demonstrates how parametrizing neural network layers enables more biologically-plausible operations while reducing trainable parameters and improving interpretability. We constrain operations to functional forms present in human vision, optimizing only these functions' parameters rather than all convolutional tensor elements independently. We present two parametric model versions: one with hand-chosen biologically plausible parameters, and another fitted to human perception experimental data. We compare these with a non-parametric version. All models achieve comparable state-of-the-art results, with parametric versions showing orders of magnitude parameter reduction for minimal performance loss. The parametric models demonstrate improved interpretability and training behavior. Notably, the model fitted to human perception, despite biological initialization, converges to biologically incorrect results. This raises scientific questions and highlights the need for diverse evaluation methods to measure models' humanness, rather than assuming task performance correlates with human-like behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03210v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Vila-Tom\'as, Pablo Hern\'andez-C\'amara, Valero Laparra, Jes\'us Malo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Causal Models of Time-Varying Connectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel approach for modelling time-varying connectivity in neuroimaging data, focusing on the slow fluctuations in synaptic efficacy that mediate neuronal dynamics. Building on the framework of Dynamic Causal Modelling (DCM), we propose a method that incorporates temporal basis functions into neural models, allowing for the explicit representation of slow parameter changes. This approach balances expressivity and computational efficiency by modelling these fluctuations as a Gaussian process, offering a middle ground between existing methods that either strongly constrain or excessively relax parameter fluctuations. We validate the ensuing model through simulations and real data from an auditory roving oddball paradigm, demonstrating its potential to explain key aspects of brain dynamics. This work aims to equip researchers with a robust tool for investigating time-varying connectivity, particularly in the context of synaptic modulation and its role in both healthy and pathological brain function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16582v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan Medrano, Karl J. Friston, Peter Zeidman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Desynchronization Index: a New Approach for Exploring Complex Epileptogenic Networks in Stereoelectroencephalography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16347v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Stereoelectroencephalography (SEEG) is an invasive surgical procedure to record the electrical activities in cortical brain regions, aiming at identifying the Epileptogenic Zone (EZ) in patients with drug-resistant epilepsy. To improve the accuracy of the EZ definition, SEEG analysis can be supported by computational tools, among which the Epileptogenic Index (EI) represents the most common solution. However, the scientific community has still not found an agreement on which quantitative biomarkers can characterize the cortical sites within the EZ. In this work, we design a new algorithm, named Desynchronization Index (DI), to assist neurophysiologists in SEEG interpretation. Our algorithm estimates the effective connectivity between cortical sites and hypothesizes that the EZ is identified by those sites getting abnormally desynchronized from the network during the seizure generation. We test the proposed method over a SEEG dataset of 10 seizures, comparing its accuracy in terms of EZ definition against the EI algorithm and clinical ground truth. Our results indicate that the DI algorithm underscores specific connectivity dynamics that can hardly be identified with a pure visual analysis, increasing sensitivity in detecting epileptogenic cortical sites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16347v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Mason, Lorenzo Ferri, Lidia Di Vito, Lara Alvisi, Luca Zanuttini, Matteo Martinoni, Roberto Mai, Francesco Cardinale, Paolo Tinuper, Roberto Michelucci, Elena Pasini, Francesca Bisulli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplified derivations for high-dimensional convex learning problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Statistical physics provides tools for analyzing high-dimensional problems in machine learning and theoretical neuroscience. These calculations, particularly those using the replica method, often involve lengthy derivations that can obscure physical interpretation. We give concise, non-replica derivations of several key results and highlight their underlying similarities. Specifically, we introduce a cavity approach to analyzing high-dimensional learning problems and apply it to three cases: perceptron classification of points, perceptron classification of manifolds, and kernel ridge regression. These problems share a common structure -- a bipartite system of interacting feature and datum variables -- enabling a unified analysis. For perceptron-capacity problems, we identify a symmetry that allows derivation of correct capacities through a na\"ive method. These results match those obtained through the replica method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01110v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David G. Clark, Haim Sompolinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
