<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.NC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC</link>
    <description>q-bio.NC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 02:52:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Functions of Neurons in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The burgeoning growth of open-sourced vision-language models (VLMs) has catalyzed a plethora of applications across diverse domains. Ensuring the transparency and interpretability of these models is critical for fostering trustworthy and responsible AI systems. In this study, our objective is to delve into the internals of VLMs to interpret the functions of individual neurons. We observe the activations of neurons with respects to the input visual tokens and text tokens, and reveal some interesting findings. Particularly, we found that there are neurons responsible for only visual or text information, or both, respectively, which we refer to them as visual neurons, text neurons, and multi-modal neurons, respectively. We build a framework that automates the explanation of neurons with the assistant of GPT-4o. Meanwhile, for visual neurons, we propose an activation simulator to assess the reliability of the explanations for visual neurons. System statistical analyses on top of one representative VLM of LLaVA, uncover the behaviors/characteristics of different categories of neurons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18485v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Xu, Cuiling Lan, Xuejin Chen, Yan Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging Critical Gaps in Convergent Learning: How Representational Alignment Evolves Across Layers, Training, and Distribution Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding convergent learning -- the extent to which artificial and biological neural networks develop similar representations -- is crucial for neuroscience and AI, as it reveals shared learning principles and guides brain-like model design. While several studies have noted convergence in early and late layers of vision networks, key gaps remain. First, much existing work relies on a limited set of metrics, overlooking transformation invariances required for proper alignment. We compare three metrics that ignore specific irrelevant transformations: linear regression (ignoring affine transformations), Procrustes (ignoring rotations and reflections), and permutation/soft-matching (ignoring unit order). Notably, orthogonal transformations align representations nearly as effectively as more flexible linear ones, and although permutation scores are lower, they significantly exceed chance, indicating a robust representational basis. A second critical gap lies in understanding when alignment emerges during training. Contrary to expectations that convergence builds gradually with task-specific learning, our findings reveal that nearly all convergence occurs within the first epoch -- long before networks achieve optimal performance. This suggests that shared input statistics, architectural biases, or early training dynamics drive convergence rather than the final task solution. Finally, prior studies have not systematically examined how changes in input statistics affect alignment. Our work shows that out-of-distribution (OOD) inputs consistently amplify differences in later layers, while early layers remain aligned for both in-distribution and OOD inputs, suggesting that this alignment is driven by generalizable features stable across distribution shifts. These findings fill critical gaps in our understanding of representational convergence, with implications for neuroscience and AI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18710v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaitanya Kapoor, Sudhanshu Srivastava, Meenakshi Khosla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-related Potential driven Reinforcement Learning for adaptive Brain-Computer Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) provide alternative communication methods for individuals with motor disabilities by allowing control and interaction with external devices. Non-invasive BCIs, especially those using electroencephalography (EEG), are practical and safe for various applications. However, their performance is often hindered by EEG non-stationarities, caused by changing mental states or device characteristics like electrode impedance. This challenge has spurred research into adaptive BCIs that can handle such variations. In recent years, interest has grown in using error-related potentials (ErrPs) to enhance BCI performance. ErrPs, neural responses to errors, can be detected non-invasively and have been integrated into different BCI paradigms to improve performance through error correction or adaptation.
  This research introduces a novel adaptive ErrP-based BCI approach using reinforcement learning (RL). We demonstrate the feasibility of an RL-driven adaptive framework incorporating ErrPs and motor imagery. Utilizing two RL agents, the framework adapts dynamically to EEG non-stationarities. Validation was conducted using a publicly available motor imagery dataset and a fast-paced game designed to boost user engagement. Results show the framework's promise, with RL agents learning control policies from user interactions and achieving robust performance across datasets. However, a critical insight from the game-based protocol revealed that motor imagery in a high-speed interaction paradigm was largely ineffective for participants, highlighting task design limitations in real-time BCI applications. These findings underscore the potential of RL for adaptive BCIs while pointing out practical constraints related to task complexity and user responsiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18594v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aline Xavier Fid\^encio, Felix Gr\"un, Christian Klaes, Ioannis Iossifidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talking to the brain: Using Large Language Models as Proxies to Model Brain Semantic Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18725v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional psychological experiments utilizing naturalistic stimuli face challenges in manual annotation and ecological validity. To address this, we introduce a novel paradigm leveraging multimodal large language models (LLMs) as proxies to extract rich semantic information from naturalistic images through a Visual Question Answering (VQA) strategy for analyzing human visual semantic representation. LLM-derived representations successfully predict established neural activity patterns measured by fMRI (e.g., faces, buildings), validating its feasibility and revealing hierarchical semantic organization across cortical regions. A brain semantic network constructed from LLM-derived representations identifies meaningful clusters reflecting functional and contextual associations. This innovative methodology offers a powerful solution for investigating brain semantic organization with naturalistic stimuli, overcoming limitations of traditional annotation methods and paving the way for more ecologically valid explorations of human cognition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18725v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Liu, Ziyue Zhang, Jingxin Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeuroTree: Hierarchical Functional Brain Pathway Decoding for Mental Health Disorders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Analyzing functional brain networks using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) is crucial for understanding psychiatric disorders and addictive behaviors. While existing fMRI-based graph convolutional networks (GCNs) show considerable promise for feature extraction, they often fall short in characterizing complex relationships between brain regions and demographic factors and accounting for interpretable variables linked to psychiatric conditions. We propose NeuroTree to overcome these limitations, integrating a k-hop AGE-GCN with neural ordinary differential equations (ODEs). This framework leverages an attention mechanism to optimize functional connectivity (FC), thereby enhancing dynamic FC feature learning for brain disease classification. Furthermore, NeuroTree effectively decodes fMRI network features into tree structures, which improves the capture of high-order brain regional pathway features and enables the identification of hierarchical neural behavioral patterns essential for understanding disease-related brain subnetworks. Our empirical evaluations demonstrate that NeuroTree achieves state-of-the-art performance across two distinct mental disorder datasets and provides valuable insights into age-related deterioration patterns. These findings underscore the model's efficacy in predicting psychiatric disorders and elucidating their underlying neural mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18786v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-En Ding, Dongsheng Luo, Anna Zilverstand, Feng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero Echo Time Functional MRI in Humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19146v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivation: Conventional echo planar imaging(EPI) based functional MRI(fMRI) uses the BOLD contrast to map activity changes in human brains. Introducing an efficient ZTE sequence for functional brain mapping can help address limitations of EPI and demonstrate the feasibility of using T1 related changes as a surrogate marker of brain activity. Goals: To test and optimize ZTE sequence for fMRI. Methods: A ZTE sequence with radial inside out spokes was used to prepare a dynamic imaging protocol that matches conventional EPI time course. Temporal SNR and sensitivity to susceptibility differences of ZTE were evaluated and the sequence was benchmarked against BOLD EPI in a task based visual fMRI study with healthy volunteers at 3T. Results: Phantom measurements confirmed sensitivity of the ZTE protocol to the oxygen concentration. Functional activation in primary visual cortex could be detected using ZTE. Resting state networks could also be identified using independent component analysis. Discussion: ZTE-based fMRI is proposed for mapping functional activation in human brain. ZTE is robust against susceptibility artefacts and significantly reduces acoustic noise. Radial sampling pattern allows for high undersampling rates to increase temporal resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19146v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Caglar \"Ozen, Shuai Liu, Serhat Ilbey, Michael Bock, Uzay Emir, Yen-Yu Ian Shih</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Associative memory and dead neurons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In "Large Associative Memory Problem in Neurobiology and Machine Learning," Dmitry Krotov and John Hopfield introduced a general technique for the systematic construction of neural ordinary differential equations with non-increasing energy or Lyapunov function. We study this energy function and identify that it is vulnerable to the problem of dead neurons. Each point in the state space where the neuron dies is contained in a non-compact region with constant energy. In these flat regions, energy function alone does not completely determine all degrees of freedom and, as a consequence, can not be used to analyze stability or find steady states or basins of attraction. We perform a direct analysis of the dynamical system and show how to resolve problems caused by flat directions corresponding to dead neurons: (i) all information about the state vector at a fixed point can be extracted from the energy and Hessian matrix (of Lagrange function), (ii) it is enough to analyze stability in the range of Hessian matrix, (iii) if steady state touching flat region is stable the whole flat region is the basin of attraction. The analysis of the Hessian matrix can be complicated for realistic architectures, so we show that for a slightly altered dynamical system (with the same structure of steady states), one can derive a diverse family of Lyapunov functions that do not have flat regions corresponding to dead neurons. In addition, these energy functions allow one to use Lagrange functions with Hessian matrices that are not necessarily positive definite and even consider architectures with non-symmetric feedforward and feedback connections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13866v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Fanaskov, Ivan Oseledets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring stochastic low-rank recurrent neural networks from neural data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16749v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A central aim in computational neuroscience is to relate the activity of large populations of neurons to an underlying dynamical system. Models of these neural dynamics should ideally be both interpretable and fit the observed data well. Low-rank recurrent neural networks (RNNs) exhibit such interpretability by having tractable dynamics. However, it is unclear how to best fit low-rank RNNs to data consisting of noisy observations of an underlying stochastic system. Here, we propose to fit stochastic low-rank RNNs with variational sequential Monte Carlo methods. We validate our method on several datasets consisting of both continuous and spiking neural data, where we obtain lower dimensional latent dynamics than current state of the art methods. Additionally, for low-rank models with piecewise linear nonlinearities, we show how to efficiently identify all fixed points in polynomial rather than exponential cost in the number of units, making analysis of the inferred dynamics tractable for large RNNs. Our method both elucidates the dynamical systems underlying experimental recordings and provides a generative model whose trajectories match observed variability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16749v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Thirty-eighth Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matthijs Pals, A Erdem Sa\u{g}tekin, Felix Pei, Manuel Gloeckler, Jakob H Macke</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
