<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.NC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC</link>
    <description>q-bio.NC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 05:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Noumenal Labs White Paper: How To Build A Brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13161v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This white paper describes some of the design principles for artificial or machine intelligence that guide efforts at Noumenal Labs. These principles are drawn from both nature and from the means by which we come to represent and understand it. The end goal of research and development in this field should be to design machine intelligences that augment our understanding of the world and enhance our ability to act in it, without replacing us. In the first two sections, we examine the core motivation for our approach: resolving the grounding problem. We argue that the solution to the grounding problem rests in the design of models grounded in the world that we inhabit, not mere word models. A machine super intelligence that is capable of significantly enhancing our understanding of the human world must represent the world as we do and be capable of generating new knowledge, building on what we already know. In other words, it must be properly grounded and explicitly designed for rational, empirical inquiry, modeled after the scientific method. A primary implication of this design principle is that agents must be capable of engaging autonomously in causal physics discovery. We discuss the pragmatic implications of this approach, and in particular, the use cases in realistic 3D world modeling and multimodal, multidimensional time series analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13161v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxwell J. D. Ramstead, Candice Pattisapu, Jason Fox, Jeff Beck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic directed functional connectivity as a neural biomarker for objective motor skill assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Objective motor skill assessment plays a critical role in fields such as surgery, where proficiency is vital for certification and patient safety. Existing assessment methods, however, rely heavily on subjective human judgment, which introduces bias and limits reproducibility. While recent efforts have leveraged kinematic data and neural imaging to provide more objective evaluations, these approaches often overlook the dynamic neural mechanisms that differentiate expert and novice performance. This study proposes a novel method for motor skill assessment based on dynamic directed functional connectivity (dFC) as a neural biomarker. By using electroencephalography (EEG) to capture brain dynamics and employing an attention-based Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) model for non-linear Granger causality analysis, we compute dFC among key brain regions involved in psychomotor tasks. Coupled with hierarchical task analysis (HTA), our approach enables subtask-level evaluation of motor skills, offering detailed insights into neural coordination that underpins expert proficiency. A convolutional neural network (CNN) is then used to classify skill levels, achieving greater accuracy and specificity than established performance metrics in laparoscopic surgery. This methodology provides a reliable, objective framework for assessing motor skills, contributing to the development of tailored training protocols and enhancing the certification process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13362v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anil Kamat, Rahul Rahul, Anirban Dutta, Lora Cavuoto, Uwe Kruger, Harry Burke, Matthew Hackett, Jack Norfleet, Steven Schwaitzberg, Suvranu De</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LaVCa: LLM-assisted Visual Cortex Captioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the property of neural populations (or voxels) in the human brain can advance our comprehension of human perceptual and cognitive processing capabilities and contribute to developing brain-inspired computer models. Recent encoding models using deep neural networks (DNNs) have successfully predicted voxel-wise activity. However, interpreting the properties that explain voxel responses remains challenging because of the black-box nature of DNNs. As a solution, we propose LLM-assisted Visual Cortex Captioning (LaVCa), a data-driven approach that uses large language models (LLMs) to generate natural-language captions for images to which voxels are selective. By applying LaVCa for image-evoked brain activity, we demonstrate that LaVCa generates captions that describe voxel selectivity more accurately than the previously proposed method. Furthermore, the captions generated by LaVCa quantitatively capture more detailed properties than the existing method at both the inter-voxel and intra-voxel levels. Furthermore, a more detailed analysis of the voxel-specific properties generated by LaVCa reveals fine-grained functional differentiation within regions of interest (ROIs) in the visual cortex and voxels that simultaneously represent multiple distinct concepts. These findings offer profound insights into human visual representations by assigning detailed captions throughout the visual cortex while highlighting the potential of LLM-based methods in understanding brain representations. Please check out our webpage at https://sites.google.com/view/lavca-llm/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13606v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Matsuyama, Shinji Nishimoto, Yu Takagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term follow-up of DYT1 dystonia patients treated by deep brain stimulation: an open-label study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-term efficacy of internal globus pallidus (GPi) deep-brain stimulation (DBS) in DYT1 dystonia and disease progression under DBS was studied. Twenty-six patients of this open-label study were divided into two groups: (A) with single bilateral GPi lead, (B) with a second bilateral GPi lead implanted owning to subsequent worsening of symptomatology. Dystonia was assessed with the Burke Scale. Appearance of new symptoms and distribution according to body region were recorded. In the whole cohort, significant decreases in motor and disability subscores (P &lt; 0.0001) were observed at 1 year and maintained up to 10 years. Group B showed worsening of the symptoms. At 1 year, there were no significant differences between Groups A (without subsequent worsening) and B; at 5 years, a significant difference was found for motor and disability scores. Within Group B, four patients exhibited additional improvement after the second DBS surgery. In the 26 patients, significant difference (P = 0.001) was found between the number of body regions affected by dystonia preoperatively and over the whole follow-up. DBS efficacy in DYT1 dystonia can be maintained up to 10 years (two patients). New symptoms appear with long-term follow-up and may improve with additional leads in a subgroup of patients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13661v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/mds.22802</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mov Disord. 2010 Feb 15;25(3):289-99</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laura Cif, Xavier Vasques, Victoria Gonzalez, Patrice Ravel, Brigitte Biolsi, Gwenaelle Collod-Beroud, Sylvie Tuffery-Giraud, Hassan Elfertit, Mireille Claustres, Philippe Coubes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freezing of Gait as a Complication of Pallidal Deep Brain Stimulation in DYT- KMT2B Patients with Evidence of Striatonigral Degeneration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Background: Mutations in KMT2B are a recognized cause of early-onset complex dystonia, with deep brain stimulation (DBS) of the internal globus pallidus (GPi-DBS) being an effective treatment. However, gait impairment, particularly freezing of gait (FOG), remains a significant challenge in DYT-KMT2B patients post-DBS. Objectives: To characterize the emergence of FOG in DYT-KMT2B patients treated with GPi-DBS and explore potential underlying mechanisms, including striatonigral degeneration. Methods: Five patients (four females) with KMT2B-related dystonia and protein-truncating variants (PTVs) were retrospectively analyzed. Clinical progression, response to GPi-DBS, and the presence of FOG were documented. Dopaminergic function was assessed using DaTscan (SPECT for ^123I-ioflupane) in four patients. Results: FOG developed in all patients, with onset ranging from 1 to 15.5 years post-DBS. DaTscan abnormalities, indicative of bilateral striatal dopaminergic denervation, were observed in four cases. Prior to DBS, all patients exhibited dystonia unresponsive to L-dopa, and post-DBS, FOG remained refractory to dopaminergic treatment in most cases. Despite initial improvements in gait post-DBS, only one patient maintained independent ambulation at the last follow-up. Conclusions: FOG is an emerging complication in DYT-KMT2B patients with PTVs undergoing GPi-DBS, potentially linked to underlying striatonigral degeneration. The findings suggest a need for long-term motor surveillance and consideration of alternative therapeutic strategies, including dopaminergic trials, in this patient population. Further studies are required to elucidate the precise mechanisms driving DBS-related hypokinetic gait disturbances in DYT-KMT2B dystonia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13888v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/mdc3.13519</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mov Disord Clin Pract. 2022 Aug 9;9(7):992-996</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laura Cif, Diane Demailly, Xavier Vasques, Delphine de Verbizier, Philippe Coubes, Kathleen Gorman, Manju A Kurian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of the Primacy Effect in Structured State-Space Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Human and animal memory for sequentially presented items is well-documented to be more accurate for those at the beginning and end of a sequence, phenomena known as the primacy and recency effects, respectively. By contrast, artificial neural network (ANN) models are typically designed with a memory that decays monotonically over time. Accordingly, ANNs are expected to show the recency effect but not the primacy effect. Contrary to this theoretical expectation, however, the present study reveals a counterintuitive finding: a recently developed ANN architecture, called structured state-space models, exhibits the primacy effect when trained and evaluated on a synthetic task that mirrors psychological memory experiments. Given that this model was originally designed for recovering neuronal activity patterns observed in biological brains, this result provides a novel perspective on the psychological primacy effect while also posing a non-trivial puzzle for the current theories in machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13729v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Morita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of diverse (and advanced) cognitive abilities through adaptive fine-tuning of learning and chunking mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11201v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The evolution of cognition is frequently discussed as the evolution of cognitive abilities or the evolution of some neuronal structures in the brain. However, since such traits or abilities are often highly complex, understanding their evolution requires explaining how they could have gradually evolved through selection acting on heritable variations in simpler cognitive mechanisms. With this in mind, making use of a previously proposed theory, here we show how the evolution of cognitive abilities can be captured by the fine-tuning of basic learning mechanisms and, in particular, chunking mechanisms. We use the term chunking broadly for all types of non-elemental learning, claiming that the process by which elements are combined into chunks and associated with other chunks, or elements, is critical for what the brain can do, and that it must be fine-tuned to ecological conditions. We discuss the relevance of this approach to studies in animal cognition, using examples from animal foraging and decision-making, problem solving, and cognitive flexibility. Finally, we explain how even the apparent human-animal gap in sequence learning ability can be explained in terms of different fine-tunings of a similar chunking process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11201v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnon Lotem, Joseph Y. Halpern</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
