<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.NC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC</link>
    <description>q-bio.NC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.NC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 04:02:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Resonance Complexity Theory and the Architecture of Consciousness: A Field-Theoretic Model of Resonant Interference and Emergent Awareness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces Resonance Complexity Theory (RCT), which proposes that consciousness emerges from stable interference patterns of oscillatory neural activity. These patterns, shaped by recursive feedback and constructive interference, must exceed critical thresholds in complexity, coherence, gain, and fractal dimensionality to give rise to conscious experience. The resulting spatiotemporal attractors encode subjective awareness as dynamic resonance structures distributed across the neural field, enabling large-scale integration without symbolic representation or centralized control.
  To formalize this idea, we define the Complexity Index (CI), a composite metric that synthesizes four core properties of conscious systems: fractal dimensionality (D), signal gain (G), spatial coherence (C), and attractor dwell time (tau). These elements are combined multiplicatively to capture the emergence and persistence of structured, integrative neural states.
  To test the theory empirically, we developed a biologically inspired yet minimal neural field simulation composed of radial wave sources emitting across a continuous 2D space. The system exhibits recursive constructive interference, producing coherent, attractor-like excitation patterns without external input, regional coding, or imposed structure. These patterns meet the theoretical thresholds for CI and reflect the core dynamics predicted by RCT.
  The findings demonstrate that resonance-based attractors -- and by extension, consciousness-like dynamics -- can arise purely from the physics of wave interference. RCT thus offers a unified, dynamical framework for modeling awareness as an emergent property of organized complexity in oscillatory systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20580v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Arnold Bruna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing fMRI Data Acquisition for Decoding Natural Speech with Limited Participants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate optimal strategies for decoding perceived natural speech from fMRI data acquired from a limited number of participants. Leveraging Lebel et al. (2023)'s dataset of 8 participants, we first demonstrate the effectiveness of training deep neural networks to predict LLM-derived text representations from fMRI activity. Then, in this data regime, we observe that multi-subject training does not improve decoding accuracy compared to single-subject approach. Furthermore, training on similar or different stimuli across subjects has a negligible effect on decoding accuracy. Finally, we find that our decoders better model syntactic than semantic features, and that stories containing sentences with complex syntax or rich semantic content are more challenging to decode. While our results demonstrate the benefits of having extensive data per participant (deep phenotyping), they suggest that leveraging multi-subject for natural speech decoding likely requires deeper phenotyping or a substantially larger cohort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21304v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Jalouzot, Alexis Thual, Yair Lakretz, Christophe Pallier, Bertrand Thirion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic embedding of multilayer networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multilayer networks offer a powerful framework for modeling complex systems across diverse domains, effectively capturing multiple types of connections and interdependent subsystems commonly found in real world scenarios. To analyze these networks, embedding techniques that project nodes into a lower-dimensional geometric space are essential. This paper introduces a novel hyperbolic embedding framework that advances the state of the art in multilayer network analysis. Our method, which supports heterogeneous node sets across networks and inter-layer connections, generates layer-specific hyperbolic embeddings, enabling detailed intra-layer analysis and inter-layer comparisons, while simultaneously preserving the global multilayer structure within hyperbolic space, a capability that sets it apart from existing approaches, which typically rely on independent embedding of layers. Through experiments on synthetic multilayer stochastic block models, we demonstrate that our approach effectively preserves community structure, even when layers consist of different node sets. When applied to real brain networks, the method successfully clusters disease-related brain regions from different patients, outperforming layer-independent approaches and highlighting its relevance for comparative analysis. Overall, this work provides a robust tool for multilayer network analysis, enhancing interpretability and offering new insights into the structure and function of complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20378v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Guillemaud, Vera Dinkelacker, Mario Chavez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrainStratify: Coarse-to-Fine Disentanglement of Intracranial Neural Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20480v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Decoding speech directly from neural activity is a central goal in brain-computer interface (BCI) research. In recent years, exciting advances have been made through the growing use of intracranial field potential recordings, such as stereo-ElectroEncephaloGraphy (sEEG) and ElectroCorticoGraphy (ECoG). These neural signals capture rich population-level activity but present key challenges: (i) task-relevant neural signals are sparsely distributed across sEEG electrodes, and (ii) they are often entangled with task-irrelevant neural signals in both sEEG and ECoG. To address these challenges, we introduce a unified Coarse-to-Fine neural disentanglement framework, BrainStratify, which includes (i) identifying functional groups through spatial-context-guided temporal-spatial modeling, and (ii) disentangling distinct neural dynamics within the target functional group using Decoupled Product Quantization (DPQ). We evaluate BrainStratify on two open-source sEEG datasets and one (epidural) ECoG dataset, spanning tasks like vocal production and speech perception. Extensive experiments show that BrainStratify, as a unified framework for decoding speech from intracranial neural signals, significantly outperforms previous decoding methods. Overall, by combining data-driven stratification with neuroscience-inspired modularity, BrainStratify offers a robust and interpretable solution for speech decoding from intracranial recordings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20480v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Zheng, Hai-Teng Wang, Yi-Tao Jing, Pei-Yang Lin, Han-Qing Zhao, Wei Chen, Peng-Hu Wei, Yong-Zhi Shan, Guo-Guang Zhao, Yun-Zhe Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic embedding of brain networks can predict the surgery outcome in temporal lobe epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17820v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Epilepsy surgery, particularly for temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE), remains a vital treatment option for patients with drug-resistant seizures. However, accurately predicting surgical outcomes remains a significant challenge. This study introduces a novel biomarker derived from brain connectivity, analyzed using non-Euclidean network geometry, to predict the surgery outcome in TLE. Using structural and diffusion magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data from 51 patients, we examined differences in structural connectivity networks associated to surgical outcomes. Our approach uniquely utilized hyperbolic embeddings of pre- and post-surgery brain networks, successfully distinguishing patients with favorable outcomes from those with poor outcomes. Notably, the method identified regions in the contralateral hemisphere relative to the epileptogenic zone, whose connectivity patterns emerged as a potential biomarker for favorable surgical outcomes. The prediction model achieves an area under the curve (AUC) of 0.87 and a balanced accuracy of 0.81. These results underscore the predictive capability of our model and its effectiveness in individual outcome forecasting based on structural network changes. Our findings highlight the value of non-Euclidean representation of brain networks in gaining deeper insights into connectivity alterations in epilepsy, and advancing personalized prediction of surgical outcomes in TLE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17820v4</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Guillemaud, Alice Longhena, Louis Cousyn, Valerio Frazzini, Bertrand Mathon, Vincent Navarro, Mario Chavez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Optimized Convolutional Recurrent Networks Align with Tactile Processing in the Rodent Brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tactile sensing remains far less understood in neuroscience and less effective in artificial systems compared to more mature modalities such as vision and language. We bridge these gaps by introducing a novel Encoder-Attender-Decoder (EAD) framework to systematically explore the space of task-optimized temporal neural networks trained on realistic tactile input sequences from a customized rodent whisker-array simulator. We identify convolutional recurrent neural networks (ConvRNNs) as superior encoders to purely feedforward and state-space architectures for tactile categorization. Crucially, these ConvRNN-encoder-based EAD models achieve neural representations closely matching rodent somatosensory cortex, saturating the explainable neural variability and revealing a clear linear relationship between supervised categorization performance and neural alignment. Furthermore, contrastive self-supervised ConvRNN-encoder-based EADs, trained with tactile-specific augmentations, match supervised neural fits, serving as an ethologically-relevant, label-free proxy.
  For neuroscience, our findings highlight nonlinear recurrent processing as important for general-purpose tactile representations in somatosensory cortex, providing the first quantitative characterization of the underlying inductive biases in this system. For embodied AI, our results emphasize the importance of recurrent EAD architectures to handle realistic tactile inputs, along with tailored self-supervised learning methods for achieving robust tactile perception with the same type of sensors animals use to sense in unstructured environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18361v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trinity Chung, Yuchen Shen, Nathan C. L. Kong, Aran Nayebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spike-Adding Mechanisms in a Three-Timescale System: Insights from the FitzHugh-Nagumo Model with Periodic Forcing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00152v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the spike-adding mechanism in a class of three-dimensional fast-slow systems with three distinct timescales, inspired by the FitzHugh-Nagumo (FHN) model driven by periodic input. First, we numerically generate a spike-adding diagram for the FHN model by varying the frequency and amplitude of the input, revealing that as the frequency decreases and the amplitude increases, the number of spikes within each burst grows. We demonstrate that a similar spike-adding structure occurs in the more realistic, periodically forced Morris-Lecar neuronal model. Next, we apply methods from geometric singular perturbation theory to compute critical and super-critical manifolds of the fast-slow system. We use them to characterize the emergence of new burst-spikes in the FHN model, when the periodic forcing resembles a low frequency-band brain rhythm. We then describe how the uncovered spike-adding mechanism defines the boundaries that separate regions with different spike counts in the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00152v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pake Melland, Rodica Curtu, Zahra Aminzare</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
