<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 02:52:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hazards in Daily Life? Enabling Robots to Proactively Detect and Resolve Anomalies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existing household robots have made significant progress in performing routine tasks, such as cleaning floors or delivering objects. However, a key limitation of these robots is their inability to recognize potential problems or dangers in home environments. For example, a child may pick up and ingest medication that has fallen on the floor, posing a serious risk. We argue that household robots should proactively detect such hazards or anomalies within the home, and propose the task of anomaly scenario generation. We leverage foundational models instead of relying on manually labeled data to build simulated environments. Specifically, we introduce a multi-agent brainstorming approach, where agents collaborate and generate diverse scenarios covering household hazards, hygiene management, and child safety. These textual task descriptions are then integrated with designed 3D assets to simulate realistic environments. Within these constructed environments, the robotic agent learns the necessary skills to proactively discover and handle the proposed anomalies through task decomposition, and optimal learning approach selection. We demonstrate that our generated environment outperforms others in terms of task description and scene diversity, ultimately enabling robotic agents to better address potential household hazards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00781v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zirui Song, Guangxian Ouyang, Meng Fang, Hongbin Na, Zijing Shi, Zhenhao Chen, Yujie Fu, Zeyu Zhang, Shiyu Jiang, Miao Fang, Ling Chen, Xiuying Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IGOR: Image-GOal Representations are the Atomic Control Units for Foundation Models in Embodied AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce Image-GOal Representations (IGOR), aiming to learn a unified, semantically consistent action space across human and various robots. Through this unified latent action space, IGOR enables knowledge transfer among large-scale robot and human activity data. We achieve this by compressing visual changes between an initial image and its goal state into latent actions. IGOR allows us to generate latent action labels for internet-scale video data. This unified latent action space enables the training of foundation policy and world models across a wide variety of tasks performed by both robots and humans. We demonstrate that: (1) IGOR learns a semantically consistent action space for both human and robots, characterizing various possible motions of objects representing the physical interaction knowledge; (2) IGOR can "migrate" the movements of the object in the one video to other videos, even across human and robots, by jointly using the latent action model and world model; (3) IGOR can learn to align latent actions with natural language through the foundation policy model, and integrate latent actions with a low-level policy model to achieve effective robot control. We believe IGOR opens new possibilities for human-to-robot knowledge transfer and control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00785v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Chen, Junliang Guo, Tianyu He, Chuheng Zhang, Pushi Zhang, Derek Cathera Yang, Li Zhao, Jiang Bian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPOT: SE(3) Pose Trajectory Diffusion for Object-Centric Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce SPOT, an object-centric imitation learning framework. The key idea is to capture each task by an object-centric representation, specifically the SE(3) object pose trajectory relative to the target. This approach decouples embodiment actions from sensory inputs, facilitating learning from various demonstration types, including both action-based and action-less human hand demonstrations, as well as cross-embodiment generalization. Additionally, object pose trajectories inherently capture planning constraints from demonstrations without the need for manually crafted rules. To guide the robot in executing the task, the object trajectory is used to condition a diffusion policy. We show improvement compared to prior work on RLBench simulated tasks. In real-world evaluation, using only eight demonstrations shot on an iPhone, our approach completed all tasks while fully complying with task constraints. Project page: https://nvlabs.github.io/object_centric_diffusion</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00965v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Chun Hsu, Bowen Wen, Jie Xu, Yashraj Narang, Xiaolong Wang, Yuke Zhu, Joydeep Biswas, Stan Birchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Model-Based Step Adaptation for Push Recovery through Reinforcement Learning of Step Timing and Region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new approach to enhance the robustness of humanoid walking under strong perturbations, such as substantial pushes. Effective recovery from external disturbances requires bipedal robots to dynamically adjust their stepping strategies, including footstep positions and timing. Unlike most advanced walking controllers that restrict footstep locations to a predefined convex region, substantially limiting recoverable disturbances, our method leverages reinforcement learning to dynamically adjust the permissible footstep region, expanding it to a larger, effectively non-convex area and allowing cross-over stepping, which is crucial for counteracting large lateral pushes. Additionally, our method adapts footstep timing in real time to further extend the range of recoverable disturbances. Based on these adjustments, feasible footstep positions and DCM trajectory are planned by solving a QP. Finally, we employ a DCM controller and an inverse dynamics whole-body control framework to ensure the robot effectively follows the trajectory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Egle, Yashuai Yan, Dongheui Lee, Christian Ott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Learning-augmented Intention-aware Obstacle Avoidance of Autonomous Surface Vehicles in High-traffic Waters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01011v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper enhances the obstacle avoidance of Autonomous Surface Vehicles (ASVs) for safe navigation in high-traffic waters with an active state estimation of obstacle's passing intention and reducing its uncertainty. We introduce a topological modeling of passing intention of obstacles, which can be applied to varying encounter situations based on the inherent embedding of topological concepts in COLREGs. With a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) neural network, we classify the passing intention of obstacles. Then, for determining the ASV maneuver, we propose a multi-objective optimization framework including information gain about the passing obstacle intention and safety. We validate the proposed approach under extensive Monte Carlo simulations (2,400 runs) with a varying number of obstacles, dynamic properties, encounter situations, and different behavioral patterns of obstacles (cooperative, non-cooperative). We also present the results from a real marine accident case study as well as real-world experiments of a real ASV with environmental disturbances, showing successful collision avoidance with our strategy in real-time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01011v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingi Jeong, Arihant Chadda, Alberto Quattrini Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Reality Teleoperation Assistance for Direct Control of Humanoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Teleoperation plays a crucial role in enabling robot operations in challenging environments, yet existing limitations in effectiveness and accuracy necessitate the development of innovative strategies for improving teleoperated tasks. This article introduces a novel approach that utilizes mixed reality and assistive autonomy to enhance the efficiency and precision of humanoid robot teleoperation. By leveraging Probabilistic Movement Primitives, object detection, and Affordance Templates, the assistance combines user motion with autonomous capabilities, achieving task efficiency while maintaining human-like robot motion. Experiments and feasibility studies on the Nadia robot confirm the effectiveness of the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01014v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Penco, Kazuhiko Momose, Stephen McCrory, Dexton Anderson, Nicholas Kitchel, Duncan Calvert, Robert J. Griffin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AGISim, An Open Source Airborne Gimbal Mounted IMU Signal Simulator Considering Flight Dynamics Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01038v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we present more comprehensive evaluations on our airborne Gimbal mounted inertial measurement unit (IMU) signal simulator which also considers flight dynamic model (FDM). A flexible IMU signal simulator is an enabling tool in design, development, improvement, test and verification of aided inertial navigation systems (INS). Efforts by other researchers had been concentrated on simulation of the strapdown INS (SINS) with the IMU rigidly attached to the moving body frame. However custom airborne surveying/mapping applications that need pointing and stabilizing camera or any other surveying sensor, require mounting the IMU beside the sensor on a Gimbal onboard the airframe. Hence the proposed Gimbal mounted IMU signal simulator is of interest whilst itself requires further analysis and verifications. Extended evaluation results in terms of both unit tests and functional/integration tests (using aided inertial navigation algorithms with variable/dynamic lever arms), verifies the simulator and its applicability for the mentioned tasks. We have further packaged and published our MATLAB code for the proposed simulator as an open source GitHub repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01038v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alireza Kazemi, Reza Rohani Sarvestani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of Conservative Dynamical Systems Based on Stiffness Encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01120v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamical systems (DSs) provide a framework for high flexibility, robustness, and control reliability and are widely used in motion planning and physical human-robot interaction. The properties of the DS directly determine the robot's specific motion patterns and the performance of the closed-loop control system. In this paper, we establish a quantitative relationship between stiffness properties and DS. We propose a stiffness encoding framework to modulate DS properties by embedding specific stiffnesses. In particular, from the perspective of the closed-loop control system's passivity, a conservative DS is learned by encoding a conservative stiffness. The generated DS has a symmetric attraction behavior and a variable stiffness profile. The proposed method is applicable to demonstration trajectories belonging to different manifolds and types (e.g., closed and self-intersecting trajectories), and the closed-loop control system is always guaranteed to be passive in different cases. For controllers tracking the general DS, the passivity of the system needs to be guaranteed by the energy tank. We further propose a generic vector field decomposition strategy based on conservative stiffness, which effectively slows down the decay rate of energy in the energy tank and improves the stability margin of the control system. Finally, a series of simulations in various scenarios and experiments on planar and curved motion tasks demonstrate the validity of our theory and methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01120v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengyu Hou, Hanming Bai, Ye Ding, Han Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GarmentLab: A Unified Simulation and Benchmark for Garment Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Manipulating garments and fabrics has long been a critical endeavor in the development of home-assistant robots. However, due to complex dynamics and topological structures, garment manipulations pose significant challenges. Recent successes in reinforcement learning and vision-based methods offer promising avenues for learning garment manipulation. Nevertheless, these approaches are severely constrained by current benchmarks, which offer limited diversity of tasks and unrealistic simulation behavior. Therefore, we present GarmentLab, a content-rich benchmark and realistic simulation designed for deformable object and garment manipulation. Our benchmark encompasses a diverse range of garment types, robotic systems and manipulators. The abundant tasks in the benchmark further explores of the interactions between garments, deformable objects, rigid bodies, fluids, and human body. Moreover, by incorporating multiple simulation methods such as FEM and PBD, along with our proposed sim-to-real algorithms and real-world benchmark, we aim to significantly narrow the sim-to-real gap. We evaluate state-of-the-art vision methods, reinforcement learning, and imitation learning approaches on these tasks, highlighting the challenges faced by current algorithms, notably their limited generalization capabilities. Our proposed open-source environments and comprehensive analysis show promising boost to future research in garment manipulation by unlocking the full potential of these methods. We guarantee that we will open-source our code as soon as possible. You can watch the videos in supplementary files to learn more about the details of our work. Our project page is available at: https://garmentlab.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01200v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoran Lu, Ruihai Wu, Yitong Li, Sijie Li, Ziyu Zhu, Chuanruo Ning, Yan Shen, Longzan Luo, Yuanpei Chen, Hao Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Collaborative Navigation through Perception Fusion for Multi-Robots in Unknown Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For tasks conducted in unknown environments with efficiency requirements, real-time navigation of multi-robot systems remains challenging due to unfamiliarity with surroundings.In this paper, we propose a novel multi-robot collaborative planning method that leverages the perception of different robots to intelligently select search directions and improve planning efficiency. Specifically, a foundational planner is employed to ensure reliable exploration towards targets in unknown environments and we introduce Graph Attention Architecture with Information Gain Weight(GIWT) to synthesizes the information from the target robot and its teammates to facilitate effective navigation around obstacles.In GIWT, after regionally encoding the relative positions of the robots along with their perceptual features, we compute the shared attention scores and incorporate the information gain obtained from neighboring robots as a supplementary weight. We design a corresponding expert data generation scheme to simulate real-world decision-making conditions for network training. Simulation experiments and real robot tests demonstrates that the proposed method significantly improves efficiency and enables collaborative planning for multiple robots. Our method achieves approximately 82% accuracy on the expert dataset and reduces the average path length by about 8% and 6% across two types of tasks compared to the fundamental planner in ROS tests, and a path length reduction of over 6% in real-world experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01274v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingquan Lin, Weining Lu, Litong Meng, Chenxi Li, Bin Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Oriented Hierarchical Object Decomposition for Visuomotor Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Good pre-trained visual representations could enable robots to learn visuomotor policy efficiently. Still, existing representations take a one-size-fits-all-tasks approach that comes with two important drawbacks: (1) Being completely task-agnostic, these representations cannot effectively ignore any task-irrelevant information in the scene, and (2) They often lack the representational capacity to handle unconstrained/complex real-world scenes. Instead, we propose to train a large combinatorial family of representations organized by scene entities: objects and object parts. This hierarchical object decomposition for task-oriented representations (HODOR) permits selectively assembling different representations specific to each task while scaling in representational capacity with the complexity of the scene and the task. In our experiments, we find that HODOR outperforms prior pre-trained representations, both scene vector representations and object-centric representations, for sample-efficient imitation learning across 5 simulated and 5 real-world manipulation tasks. We further find that the invariances captured in HODOR are inherited into downstream policies, which can robustly generalize to out-of-distribution test conditions, permitting zero-shot skill chaining. Appendix, code, and videos: https://sites.google.com/view/hodor-corl24.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01284v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>CoRL 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jianing Qian, Yunshuang Li, Bernadette Bucher, Dinesh Jayaraman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control Strategies for Pursuit-Evasion Under Occlusion Using Visibility and Safety Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a control strategy for pursuit-evasion problems in environments with occlusions. We address the challenge of a mobile pursuer keeping a mobile evader within its field of view (FoV) despite line-of-sight obstructions. The signed distance function (SDF) of the FoV is used to formulate visibility as a control barrier function (CBF) constraint on the pursuer's control inputs. Similarly, obstacle avoidance is formulated as a CBF constraint based on the SDF of the obstacle set. While the visibility and safety CBFs are Lipschitz continuous, they are not differentiable everywhere, necessitating the use of generalized gradients. To achieve non-myopic pursuit, we generate reference control trajectories leading to evader visibility using a sampling-based kinodynamic planner. The pursuer then tracks this reference via convex optimization under the CBF constraints. We validate our approach in CARLA simulations and real-world robot experiments, demonstrating successful visibility maintenance using only onboard sensing, even under severe occlusions and dynamic evader movements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01321v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minnan Zhou, Mustafa Shaikh, Vatsalya Chaubey, Patrick Haggerty, Shumon Koga, Dimitra Panagou, Nikolay Atanasov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Domain Randomization in Training Diffusion Policies for Whole-Body Humanoid Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Humanoids have the potential to be the ideal embodiment in environments designed for humans. Thanks to the structural similarity to the human body, they benefit from rich sources of demonstration data, e.g., collected via teleoperation, motion capture, or even using videos of humans performing tasks. However, distilling a policy from demonstrations is still a challenging problem. While Diffusion Policies (DPs) have shown impressive results in robotic manipulation, their applicability to locomotion and humanoid control remains underexplored. In this paper, we investigate how dataset diversity and size affect the performance of DPs for humanoid whole-body control. In a simulated IsaacGym environment, we generate synthetic demonstrations by training Adversarial Motion Prior (AMP) agents under various Domain Randomization (DR) conditions, and we compare DPs fitted to datasets of different size and diversity. Our findings show that, although DPs can achieve stable walking behavior, successful training of locomotion policies requires significantly larger and more diverse datasets compared to manipulation tasks, even in simple scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01349v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Kaidanov, Firas Al-Hafez, Yusuf Suvari, Boris Belousov, Jan Peters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wallbounce : Push wall to navigate with Contact-Implicit MPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce a framework that enables highly maneuverable locomotion using non-periodic contacts. This task is challenging for traditional optimization and planning methods to handle due to difficulties in specifying contact mode sequences in real-time. To address this, we use a bi-level contact-implicit planner and hybrid model predictive controller to draft and execute a motion plan. We investigate how this method allows us to plan arm contact events on the shmoobot, a smaller ballbot, which uses an inverse mouse-ball drive to achieve dynamic balancing with a low number of actuators. Through multiple experiments we show how the arms allow for acceleration, deceleration and dynamic obstacle avoidance that are not achievable with the mouse-ball drive alone. This demonstrates how a holistic approach to locomotion can increase the control authority of unique robot morpohologies without additional hardware by leveraging robot arms that are typically used only for manipulation. Project website: https://cmushmoobot.github.io/Wallbounce</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01387v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaohan Liu, Cunxi Dai, John Z. Zhang, Arun Bishop, Zachary Manchester, Ralph Hollis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-Aware Trajectory Prediction for Safe Motion Planning in Autonomous Driving: A Transformer-Transfer Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A critical aspect of safe and efficient motion planning for autonomous vehicles (AVs) is to handle the complex and uncertain behavior of surrounding human-driven vehicles (HDVs). Despite intensive research on driver behavior prediction, existing approaches typically overlook the interactions between AVs and HDVs assuming that HDV trajectories are not affected by AV actions. To address this gap, we present a transformer-transfer learning-based interaction-aware trajectory predictor for safe motion planning of autonomous driving, focusing on a vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V) interaction scenario consisting of an AV and an HDV. Specifically, we construct a transformer-based interaction-aware trajectory predictor using widely available datasets of HDV trajectory data and further transfer the learned predictor using a small set of AV-HDV interaction data. Then, to better incorporate the proposed trajectory predictor into the motion planning module of AVs, we introduce an uncertainty quantification method to characterize the errors of the predictor, which are integrated into the path-planning process. Our experimental results demonstrate the value of explicitly considering interactions and handling uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01475v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhao Liang, Chaopeng Tan, Longhao Yan, Jingyuan Zhou, Guodong Yin, Kaidi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Failures in Robotics using Vision-Based Language Models (VLMs) and Behavior Trees (BT)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose an approach that combines Vision Language Models (VLMs) and Behavior Trees (BTs) to address failures in robotics. Current robotic systems can handle known failures with pre-existing recovery strategies, but they are often ill-equipped to manage unknown failures or anomalies. We introduce VLMs as a monitoring tool to detect and identify failures during task execution. Additionally, VLMs generate missing conditions or skill templates that are then incorporated into the BT, ensuring the system can autonomously address similar failures in future tasks. We validate our approach through simulations in several failure scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01568v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faseeh Ahmad, Jonathan Styrud, Volker Krueger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Aerial Transport System in Marine GNSS-Denied Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an autonomous aerial system specifically engineered for operation in challenging marine GNSS-denied environments, aimed at transporting small cargo from a target vessel. In these environments, characterized by weakly textured sea surfaces with few feature points, chaotic deck oscillations due to waves, and significant wind gusts, conventional navigation methods often prove inadequate. Leveraging the DJI M300 platform, our system is designed to autonomously navigate and transport cargo while overcoming these environmental challenges. In particular, this paper proposes an anchor-based localization method using ultrawideband (UWB) and QR codes facilities, which decouples the UAV's attitude from that of the moving landing platform, thus reducing control oscillations caused by platform movement. Additionally, a motor-driven attachment mechanism for cargo is designed, which enhances the UAV's field of view during descent and ensures a reliable attachment to the cargo upon landing. The system's reliability and effectiveness were progressively enhanced through multiple outdoor experimental iterations and were validated by the successful cargo transport during the 2024 Mohamed BinZayed International Robotics Challenge (MBZIRC2024) competition. Crucially, the system addresses uncertainties and interferences inherent in maritime transportation missions without prior knowledge of cargo locations on the deck and with strict limitations on intervention throughout the transportation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01603v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianjun Sun, Zhenwei Niu, Yihao Dong, Fenglin Zhang, Muhayy Ud Din, Lakmal Seneviratne, Defu Lin, Irfan Hussain, Shaoming He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Know Where You're Uncertain When Planning with Multimodal Foundation Models: A Formal Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multimodal foundation models offer a promising framework for robotic perception and planning by processing sensory inputs to generate actionable plans. However, addressing uncertainty in both perception (sensory interpretation) and decision-making (plan generation) remains a critical challenge for ensuring task reliability. We present a comprehensive framework to disentangle, quantify, and mitigate these two forms of uncertainty. We first introduce a framework for uncertainty disentanglement, isolating perception uncertainty arising from limitations in visual understanding and decision uncertainty relating to the robustness of generated plans.
  To quantify each type of uncertainty, we propose methods tailored to the unique properties of perception and decision-making: we use conformal prediction to calibrate perception uncertainty and introduce Formal-Methods-Driven Prediction (FMDP) to quantify decision uncertainty, leveraging formal verification techniques for theoretical guarantees. Building on this quantification, we implement two targeted intervention mechanisms: an active sensing process that dynamically re-observes high-uncertainty scenes to enhance visual input quality and an automated refinement procedure that fine-tunes the model on high-certainty data, improving its capability to meet task specifications. Empirical validation in real-world and simulated robotic tasks demonstrates that our uncertainty disentanglement framework reduces variability by up to 40% and enhances task success rates by 5% compared to baselines. These improvements are attributed to the combined effect of both interventions and highlight the importance of uncertainty disentanglement which facilitates targeted interventions that enhance the robustness and reliability of autonomous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01639v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neel P. Bhatt, Yunhao Yang, Rohan Siva, Daniel Milan, Ufuk Topcu, Zhangyang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Inverse Source Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reconstructing unknown external source functions is an important perception capability for a large range of robotics domains including manipulation, aerial, and underwater robotics. In this work, we propose a Physics-Informed Neural Network (PINN [1]) based approach for solving the inverse source problems in robotics, jointly identifying unknown source functions and the complete state of a system given partial and noisy observations. Our approach demonstrates several advantages over prior works (Finite Element Methods (FEM) and data-driven approaches): it offers flexibility in integrating diverse constraints and boundary conditions; eliminates the need for complex discretizations (e.g., meshing); easily accommodates gradients from real measurements; and does not limit performance based on the diversity and quality of training data. We validate our method across three simulation and real-world scenarios involving up to 4th order partial differential equations (PDEs), constraints such as Signorini and Dirichlet, and various regression losses including Chamfer distance and L2 norm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01665v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngsun Wi, Jayjun Lee, Miquel Oller, Nima Fazeli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Multi-Robot Coverage Path Planning on Grids with Path Deconfliction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Multi-Robot Coverage Path Planning (MCPP) on a 4-neighbor 2D grid G, which aims to compute paths for multiple robots to cover all cells of G. Traditional approaches are limited as they first compute coverage trees on a quadrant coarsened grid H and then employ the Spanning Tree Coverage (STC) paradigm to generate paths on G, making them inapplicable to grids with partially obstructed 2x2 blocks. To address this limitation, we reformulate the problem directly on G, revolutionizing grid-based MCPP solving and establishing new NP-hardness results. We introduce Extended-STC (ESTC), a novel paradigm that extends STC to ensure complete coverage with bounded suboptimality, even when H includes partially obstructed blocks. Furthermore, we present LS-MCPP, a new algorithmic framework that integrates ESTC with three novel types of neighborhood operators within a local search strategy to optimize coverage paths directly on G. Unlike prior grid-based MCPP work, our approach also incorporates a versatile post-processing procedure that applies Multi-Agent Path Finding (MAPF) techniques to MCPP for the first time, enabling a fusion of these two important fields in multi-robot coordination. This procedure effectively resolves inter-robot conflicts and accommodates turning costs by solving a MAPF variant, making our MCPP solutions more practical for real-world applications. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach significantly improves solution quality and efficiency, managing up to 100 robots on grids as large as 256x256 within minutes of runtime. Validation with physical robots confirms the feasibility of our solutions under real-world conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01707v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingtao Tang, Zining Mao, Hang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eurekaverse: Environment Curriculum Generation via Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent work has demonstrated that a promising strategy for teaching robots a wide range of complex skills is by training them on a curriculum of progressively more challenging environments. However, developing an effective curriculum of environment distributions currently requires significant expertise, which must be repeated for every new domain. Our key insight is that environments are often naturally represented as code. Thus, we probe whether effective environment curriculum design can be achieved and automated via code generation by large language models (LLM). In this paper, we introduce Eurekaverse, an unsupervised environment design algorithm that uses LLMs to sample progressively more challenging, diverse, and learnable environments for skill training. We validate Eurekaverse's effectiveness in the domain of quadrupedal parkour learning, in which a quadruped robot must traverse through a variety of obstacle courses. The automatic curriculum designed by Eurekaverse enables gradual learning of complex parkour skills in simulation and can successfully transfer to the real-world, outperforming manual training courses designed by humans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01775v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Liang, Sam Wang, Hung-Ju Wang, Osbert Bastani, Dinesh Jayaraman, Yecheng Jason Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Masking and Visual Feature Matching for Robust Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We are interested in long-term deployments of autonomous robots to aid astronauts with maintenance and monitoring operations in settings such as the International Space Station. Unfortunately, such environments tend to be highly dynamic and unstructured, and their frequent reconfiguration poses a challenge for robust long-term localization of robots. Many state-of-the-art visual feature-based localization algorithms are not robust towards spatial scene changes, and SLAM algorithms, while promising, cannot run within the low-compute budget available to space robots. To address this gap, we present a computationally efficient semantic masking approach for visual feature matching that improves the accuracy and robustness of visual localization systems during long-term deployment in changing environments. Our method introduces a lightweight check that enforces matches to be within long-term static objects and have consistent semantic classes. We evaluate this approach using both map-based relocalization and relative pose estimation and show that it improves Absolute Trajectory Error (ATE) and correct match ratios on the publicly available Astrobee dataset. While this approach was originally developed for microgravity robotic freeflyers, it can be applied to any visual feature matching pipeline to improve robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01804v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luisa Mao, Ryan Soussan, Brian Coltin, Trey Smith, Joydeep Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So You Think You Can Scale Up Autonomous Robot Data Collection?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A long-standing goal in robot learning is to develop methods for robots to acquire new skills autonomously. While reinforcement learning (RL) comes with the promise of enabling autonomous data collection, it remains challenging to scale in the real-world partly due to the significant effort required for environment design and instrumentation, including the need for designing reset functions or accurate success detectors. On the other hand, imitation learning (IL) methods require little to no environment design effort, but instead require significant human supervision in the form of collected demonstrations. To address these shortcomings, recent works in autonomous IL start with an initial seed dataset of human demonstrations that an autonomous policy can bootstrap from. While autonomous IL approaches come with the promise of addressing the challenges of autonomous RL as well as pure IL strategies, in this work, we posit that such techniques do not deliver on this promise and are still unable to scale up autonomous data collection in the real world. Through a series of real-world experiments, we demonstrate that these approaches, when scaled up to realistic settings, face much of the same scaling challenges as prior attempts in RL in terms of environment design. Further, we perform a rigorous study of autonomous IL methods across different data scales and 7 simulation and real-world tasks, and demonstrate that while autonomous data collection can modestly improve performance, simply collecting more human data often provides significantly more improvement. Our work suggests a negative result: that scaling up autonomous data collection for learning robot policies for real-world tasks is more challenging and impractical than what is suggested in prior work. We hope these insights about the core challenges of scaling up data collection help inform future efforts in autonomous learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01813v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvir Mirchandani, Suneel Belkhale, Joey Hejna, Evelyn Choi, Md Sazzad Islam, Dorsa Sadigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Social Robot Navigation with Integrated Motion Prediction and Trajectory Planning in Dynamic Human Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Navigating safely in dynamic human environments is crucial for mobile service robots, and social navigation is a key aspect of this process. In this paper, we proposed an integrative approach that combines motion prediction and trajectory planning to enable safe and socially-aware robot navigation. The main idea of the proposed method is to leverage the advantages of Socially Acceptable trajectory prediction and Timed Elastic Band (TEB) by incorporating human interactive information including position, orientation, and motion into the objective function of the TEB algorithms. In addition, we designed social constraints to ensure the safety of robot navigation. The proposed system is evaluated through physical simulation using both quantitative and qualitative metrics, demonstrating its superior performance in avoiding human and dynamic obstacles, thereby ensuring safe navigation. The implementations are open source at: \url{https://github.com/thanhnguyencanh/SGan-TEB.git}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01814v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh Nguyen Canh, Xiem HoangVan, Nak Young Chong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Integrating Semantic-aware Path Planning and Reliable Localization for UAV Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Localization is one of the most crucial tasks for Unmanned Aerial Vehicle systems (UAVs) directly impacting overall performance, which can be achieved with various sensors and applied to numerous tasks related to search and rescue operations, object tracking, construction, etc. However, due to the negative effects of challenging environments, UAVs may lose signals for localization. In this paper, we present an effective path-planning system leveraging semantic segmentation information to navigate around texture-less and problematic areas like lakes, oceans, and high-rise buildings using a monocular camera. We introduce a real-time semantic segmentation architecture and a novel keyframe decision pipeline to optimize image inputs based on pixel distribution, reducing processing time. A hierarchical planner based on the Dynamic Window Approach (DWA) algorithm, integrated with a cost map, is designed to facilitate efficient path planning. The system is implemented in a photo-realistic simulation environment using Unity, aligning with segmentation model parameters. Comprehensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations validate the effectiveness of our approach, showing significant improvements in the reliability and efficiency of UAV localization in challenging environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01816v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh Nguyen Canh, Huy-Hoang Ngo, Xiem HoangVan, Nak Young Chong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Trust Estimation in Human-Robot Collaboration Using Beta Reputation at Fine-grained Timescales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When interacting with each other, humans adjust their behavior based on perceived trust. However, to achieve similar adaptability, robots must accurately estimate human trust at sufficiently granular timescales during the human-robot collaboration task. A beta reputation is a popular way to formalize a mathematical estimation of human trust. However, it relies on binary performance, which updates trust estimations only after each task concludes. Additionally, manually crafting a reward function is the usual method of building a performance indicator, which is labor-intensive and time-consuming. These limitations prevent efficiently capturing continuous changes in trust at more granular timescales throughout the collaboration task. Therefore, this paper presents a new framework for the estimation of human trust using a beta reputation at fine-grained timescales. To achieve granularity in beta reputation, we utilize continuous reward values to update trust estimations at each timestep of a task. We construct a continuous reward function using maximum entropy optimization to eliminate the need for the laborious specification of a performance indicator. The proposed framework improves trust estimations by increasing accuracy, eliminating the need for manually crafting a reward function, and advancing toward developing more intelligent robots. The source code is publicly available. https://github.com/resuldagdanov/robot-learning-human-trust</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01866v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Resul Dagdanov, Milan Andrejevic, Dikai Liu, Chin-Teng Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traffic and Safety Rule Compliance of Humans in Diverse Driving Situations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing interest in autonomous driving systems has highlighted the need for an in-depth analysis of human driving behavior in diverse scenarios. Analyzing human data is crucial for developing autonomous systems that replicate safe driving practices and ensure seamless integration into human-dominated environments. This paper presents a comparative evaluation of human compliance with traffic and safety rules across multiple trajectory prediction datasets, including Argoverse 2, nuPlan, Lyft, and DeepUrban. By defining and leveraging existing safety and behavior-related metrics, such as time to collision, adherence to speed limits, and interactions with other traffic participants, we aim to provide a comprehensive understanding of each datasets strengths and limitations. Our analysis focuses on the distribution of data samples, identifying noise, outliers, and undesirable behaviors exhibited by human drivers in both the training and validation sets. The results underscore the need for applying robust filtering techniques to certain datasets due to high levels of noise and the presence of such undesirable behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01909v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Kurenkov, Sajad Marvi, Julian Schmidt, Christoph B. Rist, Alessandro Canevaro, Hang Yu, Julian Jordan, Georg Schildbach, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboCrowd: Scaling Robot Data Collection through Crowdsourcing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, imitation learning from large-scale human demonstrations has emerged as a promising paradigm for training robot policies. However, the burden of collecting large quantities of human demonstrations is significant in terms of collection time and the need for access to expert operators. We introduce a new data collection paradigm, RoboCrowd, which distributes the workload by utilizing crowdsourcing principles and incentive design. RoboCrowd helps enable scalable data collection and facilitates more efficient learning of robot policies. We build RoboCrowd on top of ALOHA (Zhao et al. 2023) -- a bimanual platform that supports data collection via puppeteering -- to explore the design space for crowdsourcing in-person demonstrations in a public environment. We propose three classes of incentive mechanisms to appeal to users' varying sources of motivation for interacting with the system: material rewards, intrinsic interest, and social comparison. We instantiate these incentives through tasks that include physical rewards, engaging or challenging manipulations, as well as gamification elements such as a leaderboard. We conduct a large-scale, two-week field experiment in which the platform is situated in a university cafe. We observe significant engagement with the system -- over 200 individuals independently volunteered to provide a total of over 800 interaction episodes. Our findings validate the proposed incentives as mechanisms for shaping users' data quantity and quality. Further, we demonstrate that the crowdsourced data can serve as useful pre-training data for policies fine-tuned on expert demonstrations -- boosting performance up to 20% compared to when this data is not available. These results suggest the potential for RoboCrowd to reduce the burden of robot data collection by carefully implementing crowdsourcing and incentive design principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01915v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvir Mirchandani, David D. Yuan, Kaylee Burns, Md Sazzad Islam, Tony Z. Zhao, Chelsea Finn, Dorsa Sadigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Polygonal Semantic Mapping for Humanoid Robot Stair Climbing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel algorithm for real-time planar semantic mapping tailored for humanoid robots navigating complex terrains such as staircases. Our method is adaptable to any odometry input and leverages GPU-accelerated processes for planar extraction, enabling the rapid generation of globally consistent semantic maps. We utilize an anisotropic diffusion filter on depth images to effectively minimize noise from gradient jumps while preserving essential edge details, enhancing normal vector images' accuracy and smoothness. Both the anisotropic diffusion and the RANSAC-based plane extraction processes are optimized for parallel processing on GPUs, significantly enhancing computational efficiency. Our approach achieves real-time performance, processing single frames at rates exceeding $30~Hz$, which facilitates detailed plane extraction and map management swiftly and efficiently. Extensive testing underscores the algorithm's capabilities in real-time scenarios and demonstrates its practical application in humanoid robot gait planning, significantly improving its ability to navigate dynamic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01919v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teng Bin, Jianming Yao, Tin Lun Lam, Tianwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brainbots as smart autonomous active particles with programmable motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an innovative robotic device designed to provide controlled motion for studying active matter. Motion is driven by an internal vibrator powered by a small rechargeable battery. The system integrates acoustic and magnetic sensors along with a programmable microcontroller. Unlike conventional vibrobots, the motor induces horizontal vibrations, resulting in cycloidal trajectories that have been characterized and optimized. Portions of these orbits can be utilized to create specific motion patterns. As a proof of concept, we demonstrate how this versatile system can be exploited to develop active particles with varying dynamics, ranging from ballistic motion to run-and-tumble diffusive behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01943v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Noirhomme, I. Mammadli, N. Vanesse, J. Pande, A. -S. Smith, N. Vandewalle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-CAS: A Realtime Vehicle Anti Collision System Using Vision Transformer on Multi-Camera Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a real-time Vehicle Collision Avoidance System (V-CAS) designed to enhance vehicle safety through adaptive braking based on environmental perception. V-CAS leverages the advanced vision-based transformer model RT-DETR, DeepSORT tracking, speed estimation, brake light detection, and an adaptive braking mechanism. It computes a composite collision risk score based on vehicles' relative accelerations, distances, and detected braking actions, using brake light signals and trajectory data from multiple camera streams to improve scene perception. Implemented on the Jetson Orin Nano, V-CAS enables real-time collision risk assessment and proactive mitigation through adaptive braking. A comprehensive training process was conducted on various datasets for comparative analysis, followed by fine-tuning the selected object detection model using transfer learning. The system's effectiveness was rigorously evaluated on the Car Crash Dataset (CCD) from YouTube and through real-time experiments, achieving over 98% accuracy with an average proactive alert time of 1.13 seconds. Results indicate significant improvements in object detection and tracking, enhancing collision avoidance compared to traditional single-camera methods. This research demonstrates the potential of low-cost, multi-camera embedded vision transformer systems to advance automotive safety through enhanced environmental perception and proactive collision avoidance mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01963v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Waqas Ashraf, Ali Hassan, Imad Ali Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reshaping UAV-Enabled Communications with Omnidirectional Multi-Rotor Aerial Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01985v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new class of Multi-Rotor Aerial Vehicles (MRAVs), known as omnidirectional MRAVs (o-MRAVs), has attracted significant interest in the robotics community. These MRAVs have the unique capability of independently controlling their 3D position and 3D orientation. In the context of aerial communication networks, this translates into the ability to control the position and orientation of the antenna mounted on the MRAV without any additional devices tasked for antenna orientation. This additional Degrees of Freedom (DoF) adds a new dimension to aerial communication systems, creating various research opportunities in communications-aware trajectory planning and positioning. This paper presents this new class of MRAVs and discusses use cases in areas such as physical layer security and optical communications. Furthermore, the benefits of these MRAVs are illustrated with realistic simulation scenarios. Finally, new research problems and opportunities introduced by this advanced robotics technology are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01985v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Bonilla Licea, Giuseppe Silano, Hajar El Hammouti, Mounir Ghogho, Martin Saska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Immediate Update Strategy of Multi-State Constraint Kalman Filter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The lightweight Multi-state Constraint Kalman Filter (MSCKF) has been well-known for its high efficiency, in which the delayed update has been usually adopted since its proposal. This work investigates the immediate update strategy of MSCKF based on timely reconstructed 3D feature points and measurement constraints. The differences between the delayed update and the immediate update are theoretically analyzed in detail. It is found that the immediate update helps construct more observation constraints and employ more filtering updates than the delayed update, which improves the linearization point of the measurement model and therefore enhances the estimation accuracy. Numerical simulations and experiments show that the immediate update strategy significantly enhances MSCKF even with a small amount of feature observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02028v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingchao Zhang, Wei Ouyang, Jiale Han, Qi Cai, Maoran Zhu, Yuanxin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Multi-robot Task Allocation for Long-Endurance Missions in Dynamic Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a framework for Multi-Robot Task Allocation (MRTA) in heterogeneous teams performing long-endurance missions in dynamic scenarios. Given the limited battery of robots, especially in the case of aerial vehicles, we allow for robot recharges and the possibility of fragmenting and/or relaying certain tasks. We also address tasks that must be performed by a coalition of robots in a coordinated manner. Given these features, we introduce a new class of heterogeneous MRTA problems which we analyze theoretically and optimally formulate as a Mixed-Integer Linear Program. We then contribute a heuristic algorithm to compute approximate solutions and integrate it into a mission planning and execution architecture capable of reacting to unexpected events by repairing or recomputing plans online. Our experimental results show the relevance of our newly formulated problem in a realistic use case for inspection with aerial robots. We assess the performance of our heuristic solver in comparison with other variants and with exact optimal solutions in small-scale scenarios. In addition, we evaluate the ability of our replanning framework to repair plans online.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02062v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alvaro Calvo, Jesus Capitan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-based Virtual Fixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Virtual fixtures assist human operators in teleoperation settings by constraining their actions. This extended abstract introduces a novel virtual fixture formulation \emph{on surfaces} for tactile robotics tasks. Unlike existing methods, our approach constrains the behavior based on the position on the surface and generalizes it over the surface by considering the distance (metric) on the surface. Our method works directly on possibly noisy and partial point clouds collected via a camera. Given a set of regions on the surface together with their desired behaviors, our method diffuses the behaviors across the entire surface by taking into account the surface geometry. We demonstrate our method's ability in two simulated experiments (i) to regulate contact force magnitude or tangential speed based on surface position and (ii) to guide the robot to targets while avoiding restricted regions defined on the surface. All source codes, experimental data, and videos are available as open access at https://sites.google.com/view/diffusion-virtual-fixtures</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02169v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cem Bilaloglu, Tobias L\"ow, Sylvain Calinon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Kinetic Energy through Control Barrier Functions: Analysis and Experimental Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the context of safety-critical control, we propose and analyse the use of Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) to limit the kinetic energy of torque-controlled robots. The proposed scheme is able to modify a nominal control action in a minimally invasive manner to achieve the desired kinetic energy limit. We show how this safety condition is achieved by appropriately injecting damping in the underlying robot dynamics independently of the nominal controller structure. We present an extensive experimental validation of the approach on a 7-Degree of Freedom (DoF) Franka Emika Panda robot. The results demonstrate that this approach provides an effective, minimally invasive safety layer that is straightforward to implement and is robust in real experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Califano, Daniel Logmans, Wesley Roozing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Touch-to-Touch Translation -- Learning the Mapping Between Heterogeneous Tactile Sensing Technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The use of data-driven techniques for tactile data processing and classification has recently increased. However, collecting tactile data is a time-expensive and sensor-specific procedure. Indeed, due to the lack of hardware standards in tactile sensing, data is required to be collected for each different sensor. This paper considers the problem of learning the mapping between two tactile sensor outputs with respect to the same physical stimulus -- we refer to this problem as touch-to-touch translation. In this respect, we proposed two data-driven approaches to address this task and we compared their performance. The first one exploits a generative model developed for image-to-image translation and adapted for this context. The second one uses a ResNet model trained to perform a regression task. We validated both methods using two completely different tactile sensors -- a camera-based, Digit and a capacitance-based, CySkin. In particular, we used Digit images to generate the corresponding CySkin data. We trained the models on a set of tactile features that can be found in common larger objects and we performed the testing on a previously unseen set of data. Experimental results show the possibility of translating Digit images into the CySkin output by preserving the contact shape and with an error of 15.18% in the magnitude of the sensor responses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02187v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Grella, Alessandro Albini, Giorgio Cannata, Perla Maiolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffSim2Real: Deploying Quadrupedal Locomotion Policies Purely Trained in Differentiable Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differentiable simulators provide analytic gradients, enabling more sample-efficient learning algorithms and paving the way for data intensive learning tasks such as learning from images. In this work, we demonstrate that locomotion policies trained with analytic gradients from a differentiable simulator can be successfully transferred to the real world. Typically, simulators that offer informative gradients lack the physical accuracy needed for sim-to-real transfer, and vice-versa. A key factor in our success is a smooth contact model that combines informative gradients with physical accuracy, ensuring effective transfer of learned behaviors. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time a real quadrupedal robot is able to locomote after training exclusively in a differentiable simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02189v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Bagajo, Clemens Schwarke, Victor Klemm, Ignat Georgiev, Jean-Pierre Sleiman, Jesus Tordesillas, Animesh Garg, Marco Hutter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DexHub and DART: Towards Internet Scale Robot Data Collection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quest to build a generalist robotic system is impeded by the scarcity of diverse and high-quality data. While real-world data collection effort exist, requirements for robot hardware, physical environment setups, and frequent resets significantly impede the scalability needed for modern learning frameworks. We introduce DART, a teleoperation platform designed for crowdsourcing that reimagines robotic data collection by leveraging cloud-based simulation and augmented reality (AR) to address many limitations of prior data collection efforts. Our user studies highlight that DART enables higher data collection throughput and lower physical fatigue compared to real-world teleoperation. We also demonstrate that policies trained using DART-collected datasets successfully transfer to reality and are robust to unseen visual disturbances. All data collected through DART is automatically stored in our cloud-hosted database, DexHub, which will be made publicly available upon curation, paving the path for DexHub to become an ever-growing data hub for robot learning. Videos are available at: https://dexhub.ai/project</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02214v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Younghyo Park, Jagdeep Singh Bhatia, Lars Ankile, Pulkit Agrawal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Aware Coverage Planning for Heterogeneous Multi-Robot System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a distributed control law for a heterogeneous multi-robot coverage problem, where the robots could have different energy characteristics, such as capacity and depletion rates, due to their varying sizes, speeds, capabilities, and payloads. Existing energy-aware coverage control laws consider capacity differences but assume the battery depletion rate to be the same for all robots. In realistic scenarios, however, some robots can consume energy much faster than other robots; for instance, UAVs hover at different altitudes, and these changes could be dynamically updated based on their assigned tasks. Robots' energy capacities and depletion rates need to be considered to maximize the performance of a multi-robot system. To this end, we propose a new energy-aware controller based on Lloyd's algorithm to adapt the weights of the robots based on their energy dynamics and divide the area of interest among the robots accordingly. The controller is theoretically analyzed and extensively evaluated through simulations and real-world demonstrations in multiple realistic scenarios and compared with three baseline control laws to validate its performance and efficacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02230v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiman Munir, Ayan Dutta, Ramviyas Parasuraman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kilovolt Pyroelectric Voltage Generation and Electrostatic Actuation With Fluidic Heating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integrated micro power generators are crucial components for micro robotic platforms to demonstrate untethered operation and to achieve autonomy. Current micro robotic electrostatic actuators typically require hundreds to thousands of voltages to output sufficient work. Pyroelectricity is one such source of high voltages that can be scaled to small form factors. This paper demonstrates a distributed pyroelectric high voltage generation mechanism to power kV actuators using alternating exposure of crystals to hot and cold water (300C to 900C water temperature). Using this fluidic temperature control, a pyroelectrically generated voltage of 2470 V was delivered to a 2 pF storage capacitor yielding a 6.10 {\mu}J stored energy. A maximum energy of 17.46 {\mu}J was delivered to a 47 pF capacitor at 861 V. The recirculating water can be used to heat a distributed array of converters to generate electricity in distant robotic actuator sections. The development of this distributed system would enable untethered micro-robot to be operated with a flexible body and free of battery recharging, which advances its applications in the real world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02295v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.31438/trf.hh2022.16</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Di Ni, Ved Gund, Landon Ivy, Amit Lal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of Nanorobots with Artificial Intelligence and Reinforcement Learning for Advanced Cancer Cell Detection and Tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanorobots are a promising development in targeted drug delivery and the treatment of neurological disorders, with potential for crossing the blood-brain barrier (BBB). These small devices leverage advancements in nanotechnology and bioengineering for precise navigation and targeted payload delivery, particularly for conditions like brain tumors, Alzheimer's disease, and Parkinson's disease. Recent progress in artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) has improved the navigation and effectiveness of nanorobots, allowing them to detect and interact with cancer cells through biomarker analysis. This study presents a new reinforcement learning (RL) framework for optimizing nanorobot navigation in complex biological environments, focusing on cancer cell detection by analyzing the concentration gradients of surrounding biomarkers. We utilize a computer simulation model to explore the behavior of nanorobots in a three-dimensional space with cancer cells and biological barriers. The proposed method uses Q-learning to refine movement strategies based on real-time biomarker concentration data, enabling nanorobots to autonomously navigate to cancerous tissues for targeted drug delivery. This research lays the groundwork for future laboratory experiments and clinical applications, with implications for personalized medicine and less invasive cancer treatments. The integration of intelligent nanorobots could revolutionize therapeutic strategies, reducing side effects and enhancing treatment effectiveness for cancer patients. Further research will investigate the practical deployment of these technologies in medical settings, aiming to unlock the full potential of nanorobotics in healthcare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02345v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahab Kavousinejad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeeR-VLA: Dynamic Inference of Multimodal Large Language Models for Efficient Robot Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: MLLMs have demonstrated remarkable comprehension and reasoning capabilities with complex language and visual data. These advances have spurred the vision of establishing a generalist robotic MLLM proficient in understanding complex human instructions and accomplishing various embodied tasks. However, developing MLLMs for real-world robots is challenging due to the typically limited computation and memory capacities available on robotic platforms. In contrast, the inference of MLLMs involves storing billions of parameters and performing tremendous computation, imposing significant hardware demands. In our paper, we propose a Dynamic Early-Exit Framework for Robotic Vision-Language-Action Model (DeeR-VLA, or simply DeeR) that automatically adjusts the size of the activated MLLM based on each situation at hand. The approach leverages a multi-exit architecture in MLLMs, which allows the model to terminate processing once a proper size of the model has been activated for a specific situation, thus avoiding further redundant computation. Additionally, we develop novel algorithms that establish early-termination criteria for DeeR, conditioned on predefined demands such as average computational cost (i.e., power consumption), as well as peak computational consumption (i.e., latency) and GPU memory usage. These enhancements ensure that DeeR operates efficiently under varying resource constraints while maintaining competitive performance. On the CALVIN robot manipulation benchmark, DeeR demonstrates significant reductions in computational costs of LLM by 5.2-6.5x and GPU memory of LLM by 2-6x without compromising performance. Code and checkpoints are available at https://github.com/yueyang130/DeeR-VLA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02359v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Yue, Yulin Wang, Bingyi Kang, Yizeng Han, Shenzhi Wang, Shiji Song, Jiashi Feng, Gao Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry PhenoSet: A Phenology-based Dataset for Automated Growth Detection and Yield Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The future of the agriculture industry is intertwined with automation. Accurate fruit detection, yield estimation, and harvest time estimation are crucial for optimizing agricultural practices. These tasks can be carried out by robots to reduce labour costs and improve the efficiency of the process. To do so, deep learning models should be trained to perform knowledge-based tasks, which outlines the importance of contributing valuable data to the literature. In this paper, we introduce Raspberry PhenoSet, a phenology-based dataset designed for detecting and segmenting raspberry fruit across seven developmental stages. To the best of our knowledge, Raspberry PhenoSet is the first fruit dataset to integrate biology-based classification with fruit detection tasks, offering valuable insights for yield estimation and precise harvest timing. This dataset contains 1,853 high-resolution images, the highest quality in the literature, captured under controlled artificial lighting in a vertical farm. The dataset has a total of 6,907 instances of mask annotations, manually labelled to reflect the seven phenology stages. We have also benchmarked Raspberry PhenoSet using several state-of-the-art deep learning models, including YOLOv8, YOLOv10, RT-DETR, and Mask R-CNN, to provide a comprehensive evaluation of their performance on the dataset. Our results highlight the challenges of distinguishing subtle phenology stages and underscore the potential of Raspberry PhenoSet for both deep learning model development and practical robotic applications in agriculture, particularly in yield prediction and supply chain management. The dataset and the trained models are publicly available for future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00967v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parham Jafary, Anna Bazangeya, Michelle Pham, Lesley G. Campbell, Sajad Saeedi, Kourosh Zareinia, Habiba Bougherara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AquaFuse: Waterbody Fusion for Physics Guided View Synthesis of Underwater Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01119v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the idea of AquaFuse, a physics-based method for synthesizing waterbody properties in underwater imagery. We formulate a closed-form solution for waterbody fusion that facilitates realistic data augmentation and geometrically consistent underwater scene rendering. AquaFuse leverages the physical characteristics of light propagation underwater to synthesize the waterbody from one scene to the object contents of another. Unlike data-driven style transfer, AquaFuse preserves the depth consistency and object geometry in an input scene. We validate this unique feature by comprehensive experiments over diverse underwater scenes. We find that the AquaFused images preserve over 94% depth consistency and 90-95% structural similarity of the input scenes. We also demonstrate that it generates accurate 3D view synthesis by preserving object geometry while adapting to the inherent waterbody fusion process. AquaFuse opens up a new research direction in data augmentation by geometry-preserving style transfer for underwater imaging and robot vision applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01119v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Abu Bakr Siddique, Jiayi Wu, Ioannis Rekleitis, Md Jahidul Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MonoPlane: Exploiting Monocular Geometric Cues for Generalizable 3D Plane Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a generalizable 3D plane detection and reconstruction framework named MonoPlane. Unlike previous robust estimator-based works (which require multiple images or RGB-D input) and learning-based works (which suffer from domain shift), MonoPlane combines the best of two worlds and establishes a plane reconstruction pipeline based on monocular geometric cues, resulting in accurate, robust and scalable 3D plane detection and reconstruction in the wild. Specifically, we first leverage large-scale pre-trained neural networks to obtain the depth and surface normals from a single image. These monocular geometric cues are then incorporated into a proximity-guided RANSAC framework to sequentially fit each plane instance. We exploit effective 3D point proximity and model such proximity via a graph within RANSAC to guide the plane fitting from noisy monocular depths, followed by image-level multi-plane joint optimization to improve the consistency among all plane instances. We further design a simple but effective pipeline to extend this single-view solution to sparse-view 3D plane reconstruction. Extensive experiments on a list of datasets demonstrate our superior zero-shot generalizability over baselines, achieving state-of-the-art plane reconstruction performance in a transferring setting. Our code is available at https://github.com/thuzhaowang/MonoPlane .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01226v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Zhao, Jiachen Liu, Sheng Zhang, Yishu Li, Sili Chen, Sharon X Huang, Yong-Jin Liu, Hengkai Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotational Odometry using Ultra Low Resolution Thermal Cameras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This letter provides what is, to the best of our knowledge, a first study on the applicability of ultra-low-resolution thermal cameras for providing rotational odometry measurements to navigational devices such as rovers and drones. Our use of an ultra-low-resolution thermal camera instead of other modalities such as an RGB camera is motivated by its robustness to lighting conditions, while being one order of magnitude less cost-expensive compared to higher-resolution thermal cameras. After setting up a custom data acquisition system and acquiring thermal camera data together with its associated rotational speed label, we train a small 4-layer Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) for regressing the rotational speed from the thermal data. Experiments and ablation studies are conducted for determining the impact of thermal camera resolution and the number of successive frames on the CNN estimation precision. Finally, our novel dataset for the study of low-resolution thermal odometry is openly released with the hope of benefiting future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01227v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Safa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed-Integer MPC-Based Motion Planning Using Hybrid Zonotopes with Tight Relaxations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous vehicle (AV) motion planning problems often involve non-convex constraints, which present a major barrier to applying model predictive control (MPC) in real time on embedded hardware. This paper presents an approach for efficiently solving mixed-integer MPC motion planning problems using a hybrid zonotope representation of the obstacle-free space. The MPC optimization problem is formulated as a multi-stage mixed-integer quadratic program (MIQP) using a hybrid zonotope representation of the non-convex constraints. Risk-aware planning is supported by assigning costs to different regions of the obstacle-free space within the MPC cost function. A multi-stage MIQP solver is presented that exploits the structure of the hybrid zonotope constraints. For some hybrid zonotope representations, it is shown that the convex relaxation is tight, i.e., equal to the convex hull. In conjunction with logical constraints derived from the AV motion planning context, this property is leveraged to generate tight quadratic program (QP) sub-problems within a branch-and-bound mixed-integer solver. The hybrid zonotope structure is further leveraged to reduce the number of matrix factorizations that need to be computed within the QP sub-problems. Simulation studies are presented for obstacle-avoidance and risk-aware motion planning problems using polytopic maps and occupancy grids. In most cases, the proposed solver finds the optimal solution an order of magnitude faster than a state-of-the-art commercial solver. Processor-in-the-loop studies demonstrate the utility of the solver for real-time implementations on embedded hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01286v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua A. Robbins, Jacob A. Siefert, Sean Brennan, Herschel C. Pangborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Receding Hamiltonian-Informed Optimal Neural Control and State Estimation for Closed-Loop Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01297v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper formalizes Hamiltonian-Informed Optimal Neural (Hion) controllers, a novel class of neural network-based controllers for dynamical systems and explicit non-linear model predictive control. Hion controllers estimate future states and compute optimal control inputs using Pontryagin's Maximum Principle. The proposed framework allows for customization of transient behavior, addressing limitations of existing methods. The Taylored Multi-Faceted Approach for Neural ODE and Optimal Control (T-mano) architecture facilitates training and ensures accurate state estimation. Optimal control strategies are demonstrated for both linear and non-linear dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01297v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josue N. Rivera, Dengfeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use Digital Twins to Support Fault Diagnosis From System-level Condition-monitoring Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01360v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep learning models have created great opportunities for data-driven fault diagnosis but they require large amount of labeled failure data for training. In this paper, we propose to use a digital twin to support developing data-driven fault diagnosis model to reduce the amount of failure data used in the training process. The developed fault diagnosis models are also able to diagnose component-level failures based on system-level condition-monitoring data. The proposed framework is evaluated on a real-world robot system. The results showed that the deep learning model trained by digital twins is able to diagnose the locations and modes of 9 faults/failure from $4$ different motors. However, the performance of the model trained by a digital twin can still be improved, especially when the digital twin model has some discrepancy with the real system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01360v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Killian Mc Court, Xavier Mc Court, Shijia Du, Zhiguo Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Edges of Latent State Clusters for Goal-Conditioned Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exploring unknown environments efficiently is a fundamental challenge in unsupervised goal-conditioned reinforcement learning. While selecting exploratory goals at the frontier of previously explored states is an effective strategy, the policy during training may still have limited capability of reaching rare goals on the frontier, resulting in reduced exploratory behavior. We propose "Cluster Edge Exploration" ($CE^2$), a new goal-directed exploration algorithm that when choosing goals in sparsely explored areas of the state space gives priority to goal states that remain accessible to the agent. The key idea is clustering to group states that are easily reachable from one another by the current policy under training in a latent space and traversing to states holding significant exploration potential on the boundary of these clusters before doing exploratory behavior. In challenging robotics environments including navigating a maze with a multi-legged ant robot, manipulating objects with a robot arm on a cluttered tabletop, and rotating objects in the palm of an anthropomorphic robotic hand, $CE^2$ demonstrates superior efficiency in exploration compared to baseline methods and ablations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01396v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanlin Duan, Guofeng Cui, He Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GITSR: Graph Interaction Transformer-based Scene Representation for Multi Vehicle Collaborative Decision-making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we propose GITSR, an effective framework for Graph Interaction Transformer-based Scene Representation for multi-vehicle collaborative decision-making in intelligent transportation system. In the context of mixed traffic where Connected Automated Vehicles (CAVs) and Human Driving Vehicles (HDVs) coexist, in order to enhance the understanding of the environment by CAVs to improve decision-making capabilities, this framework focuses on efficient scene representation and the modeling of spatial interaction behaviors of traffic states. We first extract features of the driving environment based on the background of intelligent networking. Subsequently, the local scene representation, which is based on the agent-centric and dynamic occupation grid, is calculated by the Transformer module. Besides, feasible region of the map is captured through the multi-head attention mechanism to reduce the collision of vehicles. Notably, spatial interaction behaviors, based on motion information, are modeled as graph structures and extracted via Graph Neural Network (GNN). Ultimately, the collaborative decision-making among multiple vehicles is formulated as a Markov Decision Process (MDP), with driving actions output by Reinforcement Learning (RL) algorithms. Our algorithmic validation is executed within the extremely challenging scenario of highway off-ramp task, thereby substantiating the superiority of agent-centric approach to scene representation. Simulation results demonstrate that the GITSR method can not only effectively capture scene representation but also extract spatial interaction data, outperforming the baseline method across various comparative metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Hu, Lijun Zhang, Dejian Meng, Ye Han, Lisha Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Probabilistic Formulation of LiDAR Mapping with Neural Radiance Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01725v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we reexamine the process through which a Neural Radiance Field (NeRF) can be trained to produce novel LiDAR views of a scene. Unlike image applications where camera pixels integrate light over time, LiDAR pulses arrive at specific times. As such, multiple LiDAR returns are possible for any given detector and the classification of these returns is inherently probabilistic. Applying a traditional NeRF training routine can result in the network learning phantom surfaces in free space between conflicting range measurements, similar to how floater aberrations may be produced by an image model. We show that by formulating loss as an integral of probability (rather than as an integral of optical density) the network can learn multiple peaks for a given ray, allowing the sampling of first, nth, or strongest returns from a single output channel. Code is available at https://github.com/mcdermatt/PLINK</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01725v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew McDermott, Jason Rife</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Human-AI Cooperation: An Inclusive Embodied Social Intelligence Challenge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01796v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce Constrained Human-AI Cooperation (CHAIC), an inclusive embodied social intelligence challenge designed to test social perception and cooperation in embodied agents. In CHAIC, the goal is for an embodied agent equipped with egocentric observations to assist a human who may be operating under physical constraints -- e.g., unable to reach high places or confined to a wheelchair -- in performing common household or outdoor tasks as efficiently as possible. To achieve this, a successful helper must: (1) infer the human's intents and constraints by following the human and observing their behaviors (social perception), and (2) make a cooperative plan tailored to the human partner to solve the task as quickly as possible, working together as a team (cooperative planning). To benchmark this challenge, we create four new agents with real physical constraints and eight long-horizon tasks featuring both indoor and outdoor scenes with various constraints, emergency events, and potential risks. We benchmark planning- and learning-based baselines on the challenge and introduce a new method that leverages large language models and behavior modeling. Empirical evaluations demonstrate the effectiveness of our benchmark in enabling systematic assessment of key aspects of machine social intelligence. Our benchmark and code are publicly available at https://github.com/UMass-Foundation-Model/CHAIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01796v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weihua Du, Qiushi Lyu, Jiaming Shan, Zhenting Qi, Hongxin Zhang, Sunli Chen, Andi Peng, Tianmin Shu, Kwonjoon Lee, Behzad Dariush, Chuang Gan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ManiBox: Enhancing Spatial Grasping Generalization via Scalable Simulation Data Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01850v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning a precise robotic grasping policy is crucial for embodied agents operating in complex real-world manipulation tasks. Despite significant advancements, most models still struggle with accurate spatial positioning of objects to be grasped. We first show that this spatial generalization challenge stems primarily from the extensive data requirements for adequate spatial understanding. However, collecting such data with real robots is prohibitively expensive, and relying on simulation data often leads to visual generalization gaps upon deployment. To overcome these challenges, we then focus on state-based policy generalization and present \textbf{ManiBox}, a novel bounding-box-guided manipulation method built on a simulation-based teacher-student framework. The teacher policy efficiently generates scalable simulation data using bounding boxes, which are proven to uniquely determine the objects' spatial positions. The student policy then utilizes these low-dimensional spatial states to enable zero-shot transfer to real robots. Through comprehensive evaluations in simulated and real-world environments, ManiBox demonstrates a marked improvement in spatial grasping generalization and adaptability to diverse objects and backgrounds. Further, our empirical study into scaling laws for policy performance indicates that spatial volume generalization scales positively with data volume. For a certain level of spatial volume, the success rate of grasping empirically follows Michaelis-Menten kinetics relative to data volume, showing a saturation effect as data increases. Our videos and code are available in https://thkkk.github.io/manibox.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01850v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengkai Tan, Xuezhou Xu, Chengyang Ying, Xinyi Mao, Songming Liu, Xingxing Zhang, Hang Su, Jun Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Realistic Cinema: The State of the Art in Mechatronics for Modern Animatronic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02102v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The pursuit of realism in cinema has driven significant advancements in animatronics, where the integration of mechatronics, a multidisciplinary field that combines mechanical engineering, electronics, and computer science, plays a pivotal role in enhancing the functionality and realism of animatronics. This interdisciplinary approach facilitates smoother characters movements and enhances the sophistication of behaviors in animatronic creatures, thereby increasing their realism. This article examines the most recent developments in mechatronic technology and their significant impact on the art and engineering of animatronics in the filmmaking. It explores the sophisticated integration of system components and analyzes how these enhancements foster complexity and integration, crucial for achieving unprecedented levels of realism in modern cinema. Further, the article delves into in-depth case studies of well-known movie characters, demonstrating the practical applicability of these state-of-the-art mechatronic solutions in creating compelling, lifelike cinematic experiences. This paper aims to bridge the gap between the technical aspects of mechatronics and the creative demands of the film industry, ultimately contributing to the ongoing evolution of cinematic realism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02102v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riham M. Hilal, Haitham El-Hussieny, Ayman A. Nada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Multiple Initial Solutions to Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sequentially solving similar optimization problems under strict runtime constraints is essential for many applications, such as robot control, autonomous driving, and portfolio management. The performance of local optimization methods in these settings is sensitive to the initial solution: poor initialization can lead to slow convergence or suboptimal solutions. To address this challenge, we propose learning to predict \emph{multiple} diverse initial solutions given parameters that define the problem instance. We introduce two strategies for utilizing multiple initial solutions: (i) a single-optimizer approach, where the most promising initial solution is chosen using a selection function, and (ii) a multiple-optimizers approach, where several optimizers, potentially run in parallel, are each initialized with a different solution, with the best solution chosen afterward. We validate our method on three optimal control benchmark tasks: cart-pole, reacher, and autonomous driving, using different optimizers: DDP, MPPI, and iLQR. We find significant and consistent improvement with our method across all evaluation settings and demonstrate that it efficiently scales with the number of initial solutions required. The code is available at $\href{https://github.com/EladSharony/miso}{\tt{https://github.com/EladSharony/miso}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02158v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elad Sharony, Heng Yang, Tong Che, Marco Pavone, Shie Mannor, Peter Karkus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Length Image Tokenization via Recurrent Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02393v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Current vision systems typically assign fixed-length representations to images, regardless of the information content. This contrasts with human intelligence - and even large language models - which allocate varying representational capacities based on entropy, context and familiarity. Inspired by this, we propose an approach to learn variable-length token representations for 2D images. Our encoder-decoder architecture recursively processes 2D image tokens, distilling them into 1D latent tokens over multiple iterations of recurrent rollouts. Each iteration refines the 2D tokens, updates the existing 1D latent tokens, and adaptively increases representational capacity by adding new tokens. This enables compression of images into a variable number of tokens, ranging from 32 to 256. We validate our tokenizer using reconstruction loss and FID metrics, demonstrating that token count aligns with image entropy, familiarity and downstream task requirements. Recurrent token processing with increasing representational capacity in each iteration shows signs of token specialization, revealing potential for object / part discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02393v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Duggal, Phillip Isola, Antonio Torralba, William T. Freeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural-Rendezvous: Provably Robust Guidance and Control to Encounter Interstellar Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.04883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.04883v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Interstellar objects (ISOs) are likely representatives of primitive materials invaluable in understanding exoplanetary star systems. Due to their poorly constrained orbits with generally high inclinations and relative velocities, however, exploring ISOs with conventional human-in-the-loop approaches is significantly challenging. This paper presents Neural-Rendezvous -- a deep learning-based guidance and control framework for encountering fast-moving objects, including ISOs, robustly, accurately, and autonomously in real time. It uses pointwise minimum norm tracking control on top of a guidance policy modeled by a spectrally-normalized deep neural network, where its hyperparameters are tuned with a loss function directly penalizing the MPC state trajectory tracking error. We show that Neural-Rendezvous provides a high probability exponential bound on the expected spacecraft delivery error, the proof of which leverages stochastic incremental stability analysis. In particular, it is used to construct a non-negative function with a supermartingale property, explicitly accounting for the ISO state uncertainty and the local nature of nonlinear state estimation guarantees. In numerical simulations, Neural-Rendezvous is demonstrated to satisfy the expected error bound for 100 ISO candidates. This performance is also empirically validated using our spacecraft simulator and in high-conflict and distributed UAV swarm reconfiguration with up to 20 UAVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.04883v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2514/1.G007671</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyasu Tsukamoto, Soon-Jo Chung, Yashwanth Kumar Nakka, Benjamin Donitz, Declan Mages, Michel Ingham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin-Enhanced Wireless Indoor Navigation: Achieving Efficient Environment Sensing with Zero-Shot Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.06766v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Millimeter-wave (mmWave) communication is a vital component of future generations of mobile networks, offering not only high data rates but also precise beams, making it ideal for indoor navigation in complex environments. However, the challenges of multipath propagation and noisy signal measurements in indoor spaces complicate the use of mmWave signals for navigation tasks. Traditional physics-based methods, such as following the angle of arrival (AoA), often fall short in complex scenarios, highlighting the need for more sophisticated approaches. Digital twins, as virtual replicas of physical environments, offer a powerful tool for simulating and optimizing mmWave signal propagation in such settings. By creating detailed, physics-based models of real-world spaces, digital twins enable the training of machine learning algorithms in virtual environments, reducing the costs and limitations of physical testing. Despite their advantages, current machine learning models trained in digital twins often overfit specific virtual environments and require costly retraining when applied to new scenarios. In this paper, we propose a Physics-Informed Reinforcement Learning (PIRL) approach that leverages the physical insights provided by digital twins to shape the reinforcement learning (RL) reward function. By integrating physics-based metrics such as signal strength, AoA, and path reflections into the learning process, PIRL enables efficient learning and improved generalization to new environments without retraining. Our experiments demonstrate that the proposed PIRL, supported by digital twin simulations, outperforms traditional heuristics and standard RL models, achieving zero-shot generalization in unseen environments and offering a cost-effective, scalable solution for wireless indoor navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.06766v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Li, Haozhe Lei, Hao Guo, Mingsheng Yin, Yaqi Hu, Quanyan Zhu, Sundeep Rangan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MPCGPU: Real-Time Nonlinear Model Predictive Control through Preconditioned Conjugate Gradient on the GPU</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08079v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear Model Predictive Control (NMPC) is a state-of-the-art approach for locomotion and manipulation which leverages trajectory optimization at each control step. While the performance of this approach is computationally bounded, implementations of direct trajectory optimization that use iterative methods to solve the underlying moderately-large and sparse linear systems, are a natural fit for parallel hardware acceleration. In this work, we introduce MPCGPU, a GPU-accelerated, real-time NMPC solver that leverages an accelerated preconditioned conjugate gradient (PCG) linear system solver at its core. We show that MPCGPU increases the scalability and real-time performance of NMPC, solving larger problems, at faster rates. In particular, for tracking tasks using the Kuka IIWA manipulator, MPCGPU is able to scale to kilohertz control rates with trajectories as long as 512 knot points. This is driven by a custom PCG solver which outperforms state-of-the-art, CPU-based, linear system solvers by at least 10x for a majority of solves and 3.6x on average.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08079v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA57147.2024.10611212</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Emre Adabag, Miloni Atal, William Gerard, Brian Plancher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RaLF: Flow-based Global and Metric Radar Localization in LiDAR Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09875v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Localization is paramount for autonomous robots. While camera and LiDAR-based approaches have been extensively investigated, they are affected by adverse illumination and weather conditions. Therefore, radar sensors have recently gained attention due to their intrinsic robustness to such conditions. In this paper, we propose RaLF, a novel deep neural network-based approach for localizing radar scans in a LiDAR map of the environment, by jointly learning to address both place recognition and metric localization. RaLF is composed of radar and LiDAR feature encoders, a place recognition head that generates global descriptors, and a metric localization head that predicts the 3-DoF transformation between the radar scan and the map. We tackle the place recognition task by learning a shared embedding space between the two modalities via cross-modal metric learning. Additionally, we perform metric localization by predicting pixel-level flow vectors that align the query radar scan with the LiDAR map. We extensively evaluate our approach on multiple real-world driving datasets and show that RaLF achieves state-of-the-art performance for both place recognition and metric localization. Moreover, we demonstrate that our approach can effectively generalize to different cities and sensor setups than the ones used during training. We make the code and trained models publicly available at http://ralf.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09875v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA57147.2024.10610626</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abhijeet Nayak, Daniele Cattaneo, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Human Impressions of Robot Performance During Navigation Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human impressions of robot performance are often measured through surveys. As a more scalable and cost-effective alternative, we investigate the possibility of predicting people's impressions of robot behavior using non-verbal behavioral cues and machine learning techniques. To this end, we first contribute the SEAN TOGETHER Dataset consisting of observations of an interaction between a person and a mobile robot in a VR simulation, together with impressions of robot performance provided by users on a 5-point scale. Second, we contribute analyses of how well humans and supervised learning techniques can predict perceived robot performance based on different observation types (like facial expression features, and features that describe the navigation behavior of the robot and pedestrians). Our results suggest that facial expressions alone provide useful information about human impressions of robot performance; but in the navigation scenarios that we considered, reasoning about spatial features in context is critical for the prediction task. Also, supervised learning techniques showed promise because they outperformed humans' predictions of robot performance in most cases. Further, when predicting robot performance as a binary classification task on unseen users' data, the F1 Score of machine learning models more than doubled in comparison to predicting performance on a 5-point scale. This suggested that the models can have good generalization capabilities, although they are better at telling the directionality of robot performance than predicting exact performance ratings. Based on our findings in simulation, we conducted a real-world demonstration in which a mobile robot uses a machine learning model to predict how a human that follows it perceives it. Finally, we discuss the implications of our results for implementing such supervised learning models in real-world navigation scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11590v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiping Zhang, Nathan Tsoi, Mofeed Nagib, Booyeon Choi, Jie Tan, Hao-Tien Lewis Chiang, Marynel V\'azquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-density Electromyography for Effective Gesture-based Control of Physically Assistive Mobile Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07745v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-density electromyography (HDEMG) can detect myoelectric activity as control inputs to a variety of electronically-controlled devices. Furthermore, HDEMG sensors may be built into a variety of clothing, allowing for a non-intrusive myoelectric interface that is integrated into a user's routine. In our work, we introduce an easily-producible HDEMG device that interfaces with the control of a mobile manipulator to perform a range of household and physically assistive tasks. Mobile manipulators can operate throughout the home and are applicable for a spectrum of assistive and daily tasks in the home. We evaluate the use of real-time myoelectric gesture recognition using our device to enable precise control over the intricate mobility and manipulation functionalities of an 8 degree-of-freedom mobile manipulator. Our evaluation, involving 13 participants engaging in challenging self-care and household activities, demonstrates the potential of our wearable HDEMG system to control a mobile manipulator in the home.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07745v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jehan Yang, Kent Shibata, Douglas Weber, Zackory Erickson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Tissue Traction Using Miniature Force-Sensing Forceps for Minimally Invasive Surgery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13957v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A common limitation of autonomous tissue manipulation in robotic minimally invasive surgery (MIS) is the absence of force sensing and control at the tool level. Recently, our team has developed miniature force-sensing forceps that can simultaneously measure the grasping and pulling forces during tissue manipulation. Based on this design, here we further present a method to automate tissue traction that comprises grasping and pulling stages. During this process, the grasping and pulling forces can be controlled either separately or simultaneously through force decoupling. The force controller is built upon a static model of tissue manipulation, considering the interaction between the force-sensing forceps and soft tissue. The efficacy of this force control approach is validated through a series of experiments comparing targeted, estimated, and actual reference forces. To verify the feasibility of the proposed method in surgical applications, various tissue resections are conducted on ex vivo tissues employing a dual-arm robotic setup. Finally, we discuss the benefits of multi-force control in tissue traction, evidenced through comparative analyses of various ex vivo tissue resections with and without the proposed method, and the potential generalization with traction on different tissues. The results affirm the feasibility of implementing automatic tissue traction using miniature forceps with multi-force control, suggesting its potential to promote autonomous MIS. A video demonstrating the experiments can be found at https://youtu.be/f5gXuXe67Ak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13957v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TRO.2024.3486177</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tangyou Liu, Xiaoyi Wang, Jay Katupitiya, Jiaole Wang, Liao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tactile Ergodic Coverage on Curved Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04862v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we present a feedback control method for tactile coverage tasks, such as cleaning or surface inspection. These tasks are challenging to plan due to complex continuous physical interactions. In these tasks, the coverage target and progress can be easily measured using a camera and encoded in a point cloud. We propose an ergodic coverage method that operates directly on point clouds, guiding the robot to spend more time on regions requiring more coverage. For robot control and contact behavior, we use geometric algebra to formulate a task-space impedance controller that tracks a line while simultaneously exerting a desired force along that line. We evaluate the performance of our method in kinematic simulations and demonstrate its applicability in real-world experiments on kitchenware. Our source codes, experimental data, and videos are available as open access at https://sites.google.com/view/tactile-ergodic-control/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04862v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cem Bilaloglu, Tobias L\"ow, Sylvain Calinon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4CNet: A Diffusion Approach to Map Prediction for Decentralized Multi-robot Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17904v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mobile robots in unknown cluttered environments with irregularly shaped obstacles often face sensing, energy, and communication challenges which directly affect their ability to explore these environments. In this paper, we introduce a novel deep learning architecture, Confidence-Aware Contrastive Conditional Consistency Model (4CNet), for robot map prediction during decentralized, resource-limited multi-robot exploration. 4CNet uniquely incorporates: 1) a conditional consistency model for map prediction in unstructured unknown regions, 2) a contrastive map-trajectory pretraining framework for a trajectory encoder that extracts spatial information from the trajectories of nearby robots during map prediction, and 3) a confidence network to measure the uncertainty of map prediction for effective exploration under resource constraints. We incorporate 4CNet within our proposed robot exploration with map prediction architecture, 4CNet-E. We then conduct extensive comparison studies with 4CNet-E and state-of-the-art heuristic and learning methods to investigate both map prediction and exploration performance in environments consisting of irregularly shaped obstacles and uneven terrain. Results showed that 4CNet-E obtained statistically significant higher prediction accuracy and area coverage with varying environment sizes, number of robots, energy budgets, and communication limitations. Hardware experiments were performed and validated the applicability and generalizability of 4CNet-E in both unstructured indoor and real natural outdoor environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17904v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Hao Tan, Siddarth Narasimhan, Goldie Nejat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Strategy Nash Equilibrium for Crowd Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01537v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robots navigating in crowded areas should negotiate free space with humans rather than fully controlling collision avoidance, as this can lead to freezing behavior. Game theory provides a framework for the robot to reason about potential cooperation from humans for collision avoidance during path planning. In particular, the mixed strategy Nash equilibrium captures the negotiation behavior under uncertainty, making it well suited for crowd navigation. However, computing the mixed strategy Nash equilibrium is often prohibitively expensive for real-time decision-making. In this paper, we propose an iterative Bayesian update scheme over probability distributions of trajectories. The algorithm simultaneously generates a stochastic plan for the robot and probabilistic predictions of other pedestrians' paths. We prove that the proposed algorithm is equivalent to solving a mixed strategy game for crowd navigation, and the algorithm guarantees the recovery of the global Nash equilibrium of the game. We name our algorithm Bayesian Recursive Nash Equilibrium (BRNE) and develop a real-time model prediction crowd navigation framework. Since BRNE is not solving a general-purpose mixed strategy Nash equilibrium but a tailored formula specifically for crowd navigation, it can compute the solution in real-time on a low-power embedded computer. We evaluate BRNE in both simulated environments and real-world pedestrian datasets. BRNE consistently outperforms non-learning and learning-based methods regarding safety and navigation efficiency. It also reaches human-level crowd navigation performance in the pedestrian dataset benchmark. Lastly, we demonstrate the practicality of our algorithm with real humans on an untethered quadruped robot with fully onboard perception and computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01537v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max M. Sun, Francesca Baldini, Katie Hughes, Peter Trautman, Todd Murphey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Fiber Optic Bundles to Miniaturize Vision-Based Tactile Sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05500v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vision-based tactile sensors have recently become popular due to their combination of low cost, very high spatial resolution, and ease of integration using widely available miniature cameras. The associated field of view and focal length, however, are difficult to package in a human-sized finger. In this paper we employ optical fiber bundles to achieve a form factor that, at 15 mm diameter, is smaller than an average human fingertip. The electronics and camera are also located remotely, further reducing package size. The sensor achieves a spatial resolution of 0.22 mm and a minimum force resolution 5 mN for normal and shear contact forces. With these attributes, the DIGIT Pinki sensor is suitable for applications such as robotic and teleoperated digital palpation. We demonstrate its utility for palpation of the prostate gland and show that it can achieve clinically relevant discrimination of prostate stiffness for phantom and ex vivo tissue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05500v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Di, Zdravko Dugonjic, Will Fu, Tingfan Wu, Romeo Mercado, Kevin Sawyer, Victoria Rose Most, Gregg Kammerer, Stefanie Speidel, Richard E. Fan, Geoffrey Sonn, Mark R. Cutkosky, Mike Lambeta, Roberto Calandra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoLD: Robot Latent Diffusion for Multi-task Policy Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07312v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modeling generalized robot control policies poses ongoing challenges for language-guided robot manipulation tasks. Existing methods often struggle to efficiently utilize cross-dataset resources or rely on resource-intensive vision-language models, thus limiting their multi-task performance and practical applications. In this study, we propose a novel approach that decouples robot action trajectory encoding and control policy generation by leveraging latent action trajectory spaces, enhancing the generalization ability of policy generation on multi-task manipulation tasks. First, we pre-train a task-agnostic auto-encoder to project an action trajectory of several frames accompanied with observations into a latent action trajectory space on large-scale datasets collected with multiple embodiments in various environments. Then we propose learning a diffusion model based on the latent action trajectory space to generate actions of next steps. Through experiments on two widely used benchmarks, results demonstrate that our proposed method outperforms baselines by 7%-29% in terms of average success rate across eight tasks. Our method can consistently benefit from pre-training while baselines cannot. Our method is more than two times faster than our baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07312v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhui Tan, Bei Liu, Junbo Zhang, Ruihua Song, Jianlong Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MSI-NeRF: Linking Omni-Depth with View Synthesis through Multi-Sphere Image aided Generalizable Neural Radiance Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10840v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Panoramic observation using fisheye cameras is significant in virtual reality (VR) and robot perception. However, panoramic images synthesized by traditional methods lack depth information and can only provide three degrees-of-freedom (3DoF) rotation rendering in VR applications. To fully preserve and exploit the parallax information within the original fisheye cameras, we introduce MSI-NeRF, which combines deep learning omnidirectional depth estimation and novel view synthesis. We construct a multi-sphere image as a cost volume through feature extraction and warping of the input images. We further build an implicit radiance field using spatial points and interpolated 3D feature vectors as input, which can simultaneously realize omnidirectional depth estimation and 6DoF view synthesis. Leveraging the knowledge from depth estimation task, our method can learn scene appearance by source view supervision only. It does not require novel target views and can be trained conveniently on existing panorama depth estimation datasets. Our network has the generalization ability to reconstruct unknown scenes efficiently using only four images. Experimental results show that our method outperforms existing methods in both depth estimation and novel view synthesis tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10840v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongyu Yan, Guanyu Huang, Fengyu Quan, Haoyao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Whole-Body Control for Legged Loco-Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16967v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of mobile manipulation using legged robots equipped with an arm, namely legged loco-manipulation. The robot legs, while usually utilized for mobility, offer an opportunity to amplify the manipulation capabilities by conducting whole-body control. That is, the robot can control the legs and the arm at the same time to extend its workspace. We propose a framework that can conduct the whole-body control autonomously with visual observations. Our approach, namely Visual Whole-Body Control(VBC), is composed of a low-level policy using all degrees of freedom to track the body velocities along with the end-effector position, and a high-level policy proposing the velocities and end-effector position based on visual inputs. We train both levels of policies in simulation and perform Sim2Real transfer for real robot deployment. We perform extensive experiments and show significant improvements over baselines in picking up diverse objects in different configurations (heights, locations, orientations) and environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16967v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghuan Liu, Zixuan Chen, Xuxin Cheng, Yandong Ji, Ri-Zhao Qiu, Ruihan Yang, Xiaolong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aerial Robots Carrying Flexible Cables: Dynamic Shape Optimal Control via Spectral Method Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we present a model-based optimal boundary control design for an aerial robotic system composed of a quadrotor carrying a flexible cable. The whole system is modeled by partial differential equations (PDEs) combined with boundary conditions described by ordinary differential equations (ODEs). The proper orthogonal decomposition (POD) method is adopted to project the original infinite-dimensional system on a finite low-dimensional space spanned by orthogonal basis functions. Based on such a reduced order model, nonlinear model predictive control (NMPC) is implemented online to realize both position and shape trajectory tracking of the flexible cable in an optimal predictive fashion. The proposed POD-based reduced modeling and optimal control paradigms are verified in simulation using an accurate high-dimensional FDM-based model and experimentally using a real quadrotor and a cable. The results show the viability of the POD-based predictive control approach (allowing closing the control loop on the full system state) and its superior performance compared to an optimally tuned PID controller (allowing closing the control loop on the quadrotor state only).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17565v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaolei Shen, Antonio Franchi, Chiara Gabellieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-world Instance-specific Image Goal Navigation: Bridging Domain Gaps via Contrastive Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09645v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Improving instance-specific image goal navigation (InstanceImageNav), which locates the identical object in a real-world environment from a query image, is essential for robotic systems to assist users in finding desired objects. The challenge lies in the domain gap between low-quality images observed by the moving robot, characterized by motion blur and low-resolution, and high-quality query images provided by the user. Such domain gaps could significantly reduce the task success rate but have not been the focus of previous work. To address this, we propose a novel method called Few-shot Cross-quality Instance-aware Adaptation (CrossIA), which employs contrastive learning with an instance classifier to align features between massive low- and few high-quality images. This approach effectively reduces the domain gap by bringing the latent representations of cross-quality images closer on an instance basis. Additionally, the system integrates an object image collection with a pre-trained deblurring model to enhance the observed image quality. Our method fine-tunes the SimSiam model, pre-trained on ImageNet, using CrossIA. We evaluated our method's effectiveness through an InstanceImageNav task with 20 different types of instances, where the robot identifies the same instance in a real-world environment as a high-quality query image. Our experiments showed that our method improves the task success rate by up to three times compared to the baseline, a conventional approach based on SuperGlue. These findings highlight the potential of leveraging contrastive learning and image enhancement techniques to bridge the domain gap and improve object localization in robotic applications. The project website is https://emergentsystemlabstudent.github.io/DomainBridgingNav/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09645v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taichi Sakaguchi, Akira Taniguchi, Yoshinobu Hagiwara, Lotfi El Hafi, Shoichi Hasegawa, Tadahiro Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Target-Less Camera-LiDAR Calibration From Motion and Deep Point Correspondences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17298v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sensor setups of robotic platforms commonly include both camera and LiDAR as they provide complementary information. However, fusing these two modalities typically requires a highly accurate calibration between them. In this paper, we propose MDPCalib which is a novel method for camera-LiDAR calibration that requires neither human supervision nor any specific target objects. Instead, we utilize sensor motion estimates from visual and LiDAR odometry as well as deep learning-based 2D-pixel-to-3D-point correspondences that are obtained without in-domain retraining. We represent camera-LiDAR calibration as an optimization problem and minimize the costs induced by constraints from sensor motion and point correspondences. In extensive experiments, we demonstrate that our approach yields highly accurate extrinsic calibration parameters and is robust to random initialization. Additionally, our approach generalizes to a wide range of sensor setups, which we demonstrate by employing it on various robotic platforms including a self-driving perception car, a quadruped robot, and a UAV. To make our calibration method publicly accessible, we release the code on our project website at http://calibration.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17298v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3468090</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 9, no. 11, pp. 9978-9985, November 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K\"ursat Petek, Niclas V\"odisch, Johannes Meyer, Daniele Cattaneo, Abhinav Valada, Wolfram Burgard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnyRotate: Gravity-Invariant In-Hand Object Rotation with Sim-to-Real Touch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07391v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human hands are capable of in-hand manipulation in the presence of different hand motions. For a robot hand, harnessing rich tactile information to achieve this level of dexterity still remains a significant challenge. In this paper, we present AnyRotate, a system for gravity-invariant multi-axis in-hand object rotation using dense featured sim-to-real touch. We tackle this problem by training a dense tactile policy in simulation and present a sim-to-real method for rich tactile sensing to achieve zero-shot policy transfer. Our formulation allows the training of a unified policy to rotate unseen objects about arbitrary rotation axes in any hand direction. In our experiments, we highlight the benefit of capturing detailed contact information when handling objects of varying properties. Interestingly, we found rich multi-fingered tactile sensing can detect unstable grasps and provide a reactive behavior that improves the robustness of the policy. The project website can be found at https://maxyang27896.github.io/anyrotate/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07391v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Yang, Chenghua Lu, Alex Church, Yijiong Lin, Chris Ford, Haoran Li, Efi Psomopoulou, David A. W. Barton, Nathan F. Lepora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ManiWAV: Learning Robot Manipulation from In-the-Wild Audio-Visual Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19464v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Audio signals provide rich information for the robot interaction and object properties through contact. This information can surprisingly ease the learning of contact-rich robot manipulation skills, especially when the visual information alone is ambiguous or incomplete. However, the usage of audio data in robot manipulation has been constrained to teleoperated demonstrations collected by either attaching a microphone to the robot or object, which significantly limits its usage in robot learning pipelines. In this work, we introduce ManiWAV: an 'ear-in-hand' data collection device to collect in-the-wild human demonstrations with synchronous audio and visual feedback, and a corresponding policy interface to learn robot manipulation policy directly from the demonstrations. We demonstrate the capabilities of our system through four contact-rich manipulation tasks that require either passively sensing the contact events and modes, or actively sensing the object surface materials and states. In addition, we show that our system can generalize to unseen in-the-wild environments by learning from diverse in-the-wild human demonstrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19464v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyi Liu, Cheng Chi, Eric Cousineau, Naveen Kuppuswamy, Benjamin Burchfiel, Shuran Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pr\"avention und Beseitigung von Fehlerursachen im Kontext von unbemannten Fahrzeugen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02876v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mobile robots, becoming increasingly autonomous, are capable of operating in diverse and unknown environments. This flexibility allows them to fulfill goals independently and adapting their actions dynamically without rigidly predefined control codes. However, their autonomous behavior complicates guaranteeing safety and reliability due to the limited influence of a human operator to accurately supervise and verify each robot's actions. To ensure autonomous mobile robot's safety and reliability, which are aspects of dependability, methods are needed both in the planning and execution of missions for autonomous mobile robots. In this article, a twofold approach is presented that ensures fault removal in the context of mission planning and fault prevention during mission execution for autonomous mobile robots. First, the approach consists of a concept based on formal verification applied during the planning phase of missions. Second, the approach consists of a rule-based concept applied during mission execution. A use case applying the approach is presented, discussing how the two concepts complement each other and what contribution they make to certain aspects of dependability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02876v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aron Schnakenbeck, Christoph Sieber, Luis Miguel Vieira da Silva, Felix Gehlhoff, Alexander Fay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplification of Robotic System Model Analysis by Petri Net Meta-Model Property Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06454v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a simplification of robotic system model analysis due to the transfer of Robotic System Hierarchical Petri Net (RSHPN) meta-model properties onto the model of a designed system. Key contributions include: 1) analysis of RSHPN meta-model properties; 2) decomposition of RSHPN analysis into analysis of individual Petri nets, thus the reduction of state space explosion; and 3) transfer of RSHPN meta-model properties onto the produced models, hence elimination of the need for full re-analysis of the RSHPN model when creating new robotic systems. Only task-dependent parts of the model need to be analyzed. This approach streamlines the analysis thus reducing the design time. Moreover, it produces a specification which is a solid foundation for the implementation of the system. The obtained results highlight the potential of Petri nets as a valuable formal framework for analyzing robotic system properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06454v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksym Figat, Cezary Zieli\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RobotKeyframing: Learning Locomotion with High-Level Objectives via Mixture of Dense and Sparse Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11562v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel learning-based control framework that uses keyframing to incorporate high-level objectives in natural locomotion for legged robots. These high-level objectives are specified as a variable number of partial or complete pose targets that are spaced arbitrarily in time. Our proposed framework utilizes a multi-critic reinforcement learning algorithm to effectively handle the mixture of dense and sparse rewards. Additionally, it employs a transformer-based encoder to accommodate a variable number of input targets, each associated with specific time-to-arrivals. Throughout simulation and hardware experiments, we demonstrate that our framework can effectively satisfy the target keyframe sequence at the required times. In the experiments, the multi-critic method significantly reduces the effort of hyperparameter tuning compared to the standard single-critic alternative. Moreover, the proposed transformer-based architecture enables robots to anticipate future goals, which results in quantitative improvements in their ability to reach their targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11562v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Zargarbashi, Jin Cheng, Dongho Kang, Robert Sumner, Stelian Coros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Imitation to Refinement -- Residual RL for Precise Assembly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16677v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in behavior cloning (BC), like action-chunking and diffusion, have led to impressive progress. Still, imitation alone remains insufficient for tasks requiring reliable and precise movements, such as aligning and inserting objects. Our key insight is that chunked BC policies function as trajectory planners, enabling long-horizon tasks. Conversely, as they execute action chunks open-loop, they lack the fine-grained reactivity necessary for reliable execution. Further, we find that the performance of BC policies saturates despite increasing data. Reinforcement learning (RL) is a natural way to overcome this, but it is not straightforward to apply directly to action-chunked models like diffusion policies. We present a simple yet effective method, ResiP (Residual for Precise Manipulation), that sidesteps these challenges by augmenting a frozen, chunked BC model with a fully closed-loop residual policy trained with RL. The residual policy is trained via on-policy RL, addressing distribution shifts and introducing reactivity without altering the BC trajectory planner. Evaluation on high-precision manipulation tasks demonstrates strong performance of ResiP over BC methods and direct RL fine-tuning. Videos, code, and data are available at \url{https://residual-assembly.github.io}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16677v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lars Ankile, Anthony Simeonov, Idan Shenfeld, Marcel Torne, Pulkit Agrawal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaLoco: Universal Quadrupedal Locomotion with Meta-Reinforcement Learning and Motion Imitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work presents a meta-reinforcement learning approach to develop a universal locomotion control policy capable of zero-shot generalization across diverse quadrupedal platforms. The proposed method trains an RL agent equipped with a memory unit to imitate reference motions using a small set of procedurally generated quadruped robots. Through comprehensive simulation and real-world hardware experiments, we demonstrate the efficacy of our approach in achieving locomotion across various robots without requiring robot-specific fine-tuning. Furthermore, we highlight the critical role of the memory unit in enabling generalization, facilitating rapid adaptation to changes in the robot properties, and improving sample efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17502v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Zargarbashi, Fabrizio Di Giuro, Jin Cheng, Dongho Kang, Bhavya Sukhija, Stelian Coros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SuperVINS: A Real-Time Visual-Inertial SLAM Framework for Challenging Imaging Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21348v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The traditional visual-inertial SLAM system often struggles with stability under low-light or motion-blur conditions, leading to potential lost of trajectory tracking. High accuracy and robustness are essential for the long-term and stable localization capabilities of SLAM systems. Addressing the challenges of enhancing robustness and accuracy in visual-inertial SLAM, this paper propose SuperVINS, a real-time visual-inertial SLAM framework designed for challenging imaging conditions. In contrast to geometric modeling, deep learning features are capable of fully leveraging the implicit information present in images, which is often not captured by geometric features. Therefore, SuperVINS, developed as an enhancement of VINS-Fusion, integrates the deep learning neural network model SuperPoint for feature point extraction and loop closure detection. At the same time, a deep learning neural network LightGlue model for associating feature points is integrated in front-end feature matching. A feature matching enhancement strategy based on the RANSAC algorithm is proposed. The system is allowed to set different masks and RANSAC thresholds for various environments, thereby balancing computational cost and localization accuracy. Additionally, it allows for flexible training of specific SuperPoint bag of words tailored for loop closure detection in particular environments. The system enables real-time localization and mapping. Experimental validation on the well-known EuRoC dataset demonstrates that SuperVINS is comparable to other visual-inertial SLAM system in accuracy and robustness across the most challenging sequences. This paper analyzes the advantages of SuperVINS in terms of accuracy, real-time performance, and robustness. To facilitate knowledge exchange within the field, we have made the code for this paper publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21348v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongkun Luo, Yang Liu, Chi Guo, Zengke Li, Weiwei Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context-Aware Replanning with Pre-explored Semantic Map for Object Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04837v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pre-explored Semantic Maps, constructed through prior exploration using visual language models (VLMs), have proven effective as foundational elements for training-free robotic applications. However, existing approaches assume the map's accuracy and do not provide effective mechanisms for revising decisions based on incorrect maps. To address this, we introduce Context-Aware Replanning (CARe), which estimates map uncertainty through confidence scores and multi-view consistency, enabling the agent to revise erroneous decisions stemming from inaccurate maps without requiring additional labels. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed method by integrating it with two modern mapping backbones, VLMaps and OpenMask3D, and observe significant performance improvements in object navigation tasks. More details can be found on the project page: https://care-maps.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04837v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Chen Ko, Hung-Ting Su, Ching-Yuan Chen, Jia-Fong Yeh, Min Sun, Winston H. Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perceptive Pedipulation with Local Obstacle Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07195v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pedipulation leverages the feet of legged robots for mobile manipulation, eliminating the need for dedicated robotic arms. While previous works have showcased blind and task-specific pedipulation skills, they fail to account for static and dynamic obstacles in the environment. To address this limitation, we introduce a reinforcement learning-based approach to train a whole-body obstacle-aware policy that tracks foot position commands while simultaneously avoiding obstacles. Despite training the policy in only five different static scenarios in simulation, we show that it generalizes to unknown environments with different numbers and types of obstacles. We analyze the performance of our method through a set of simulation experiments and successfully deploy the learned policy on the ANYmal quadruped, demonstrating its capability to follow foot commands while navigating around static and dynamic obstacles. Videos of the experiments are available at sites.google.com/leggedrobotics.com/perceptive-pedipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07195v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Stolle, Philip Arm, Mayank Mittal, Marco Hutter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MapEx: Indoor Structure Exploration with Probabilistic Information Gain from Global Map Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exploration is a critical challenge in robotics, centered on understanding unknown environments. In this work, we focus on robots exploring structured indoor environments which are often predictable and composed of repeating patterns. Most existing approaches, such as conventional frontier approaches, have difficulty leveraging the predictability and explore with simple heuristics such as `closest first'. Recent works use deep learning techniques to predict unknown regions of the map, using these predictions for information gain calculation. However, these approaches are often sensitive to the predicted map quality or do not reason over sensor coverage. To overcome these issues, our key insight is to jointly reason over what the robot can observe and its uncertainty to calculate probabilistic information gain. We introduce MapEx, a new exploration framework that uses predicted maps to form probabilistic sensor model for information gain estimation. MapEx generates multiple predicted maps based on observed information, and takes into consideration both the computed variances of predicted maps and estimated visible area to estimate the information gain of a given viewpoint. Experiments on the real-world KTH dataset showed on average 12.4% improvement than representative map-prediction based exploration and 25.4% improvement than nearest frontier approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15590v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cherie Ho, Seungchan Kim, Brady Moon, Aditya Parandekar, Narek Harutyunyan, Chen Wang, Katia Sycara, Graeme Best, Sebastian Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distance-based Multiple Non-cooperative Ground Target Encirclement for Complex Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15840v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a comprehensive strategy for complex multi-target-multi-drone encirclement in an obstacle-rich and GPS-denied environment, motivated by practical scenarios such as pursuing vehicles or humans in urban canyons. The drones have omnidirectional range sensors that can robustly detect ground targets and obtain noisy relative distances. After each drone task is assigned, a novel distance-based target state estimator (DTSE) is proposed by estimating the measurement output noise variance and utilizing the Kalman filter. By integrating anti-synchronization techniques and pseudo-force functions, an acceleration controller enables two tasking drones to cooperatively encircle a target from opposing positions while navigating obstacles. The algorithms effectiveness for the discrete-time double-integrator system is established theoretically, particularly regarding observability. Moreover, the versatility of the algorithm is showcased in aerial-to-ground scenarios, supported by compelling simulation results. Experimental validation demonstrates the effectiveness of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15840v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fen Liu, Shenghai Yuan, Kun Cao, Wei Meng, Lihua Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DualAD: Dual-Layer Planning for Reasoning in Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18053v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel autonomous driving framework, DualAD, designed to imitate human reasoning during driving. DualAD comprises two layers: a rule-based motion planner at the bottom layer that handles routine driving tasks requiring minimal reasoning, and an upper layer featuring a rule-based text encoder that converts driving scenarios from absolute states into text description. This text is then processed by a large language model (LLM) to make driving decisions. The upper layer intervenes in the bottom layer's decisions when potential danger is detected, mimicking human reasoning in critical situations. Closed-loop experiments demonstrate that DualAD, using a zero-shot pre-trained model, significantly outperforms rule-based motion planners that lack reasoning abilities. Our experiments also highlight the effectiveness of the text encoder, which considerably enhances the model's scenario understanding. Additionally, the integrated DualAD model improves with stronger LLMs, indicating the framework's potential for further enhancement. Code and benchmarks are available at github.com/TUM-AVS/DualAD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18053v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dingrui Wang, Marc Kaufeld, Johannes Betz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Robust Quadruped Robot with Twisting Waist for Flexible Motions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The waist plays a crucial role in the agile movement of many animals in nature. It provides the torso with additional degrees of freedom and flexibility, inspiring researchers to incorporate this biological feature into robotic structures to enhance robot locomotion. This paper presents a cost-effective and low-complexity waist mechanism integrated into the structure of the open-source robot solo8, adding a new degree of freedom (DOF) to its torso. We refer to this novel robot as solo9. Additionally, we propose a full-body control method for the waist-equipped quadruped robot based on generative adversarial imitation learning (GAIL). During training, the discriminator is used as input for iterative optimization of the policy and dataset, enabling solo9 to achieve flexible steering maneuvers across various gaits. Extensive tests of solo9's steering capabilities, terrain adaptability, and robustness are conducted in both simulation and real-world scenarios, with detailed comparisons to solo8 and solo12, demonstrating the effectiveness of the control algorithm and the advantages of the waist mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05884v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quancheng Qian, Xiaoyi Wei, Zonghao Zhang, Jiaxin Tu, Yueqi Zhang, Taixian Hou, Xiaofei Gao, Peng Zhai, Lihua Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Transfer from Simple to Complex: A Safe and Efficient Reinforcement Learning Framework for Autonomous Driving Decision-Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14468v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A safe and efficient decision-making system is crucial for autonomous vehicles. However, the complexity of driving environments limits the effectiveness of many rule-based and machine learning approaches. Reinforcement Learning (RL), with its robust self-learning capabilities and environmental adaptability, offers a promising solution to these challenges. Nevertheless, safety and efficiency concerns during training hinder its widespread application. To address these concerns, we propose a novel RL framework, Simple to Complex Collaborative Decision (S2CD). First, we rapidly train the teacher model in a lightweight simulation environment. In the more complex and realistic environment, teacher intervenes when the student agent exhibits suboptimal behavior by assessing actions' value to avert dangers. We also introduce an RL algorithm called Adaptive Clipping Proximal Policy Optimization Plus, which combines samples from both teacher and student policies and employs dynamic clipping strategies based on sample importance. This approach improves sample efficiency while effectively alleviating data imbalance. Additionally, we employ the Kullback-Leibler divergence as a policy constraint, transforming it into an unconstrained problem with the Lagrangian method to accelerate the student's learning. Finally, a gradual weaning strategy ensures that the student learns to explore independently over time, overcoming the teacher's limitations and maximizing performance. Simulation experiments in highway lane-change scenarios show that the S2CD framework enhances learning efficiency, reduces training costs, and significantly improves safety compared to state-of-the-art algorithms. This framework also ensures effective knowledge transfer between teacher and student models, even with suboptimal teachers, the student achieves superior performance, demonstrating the robustness and effectiveness of S2CD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14468v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongliang Zhou, Jiakun Huang, Mingjun Li, Hepeng Li, Haotian Cao, Xiaolin Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caging in Time: A Framework for Robust Object Manipulation under Uncertainties and Limited Robot Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16481v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Real-world object manipulation has been commonly challenged by physical uncertainties and perception limitations. Being an effective strategy, while caging configuration-based manipulation frameworks have successfully provided robust solutions, they are not broadly applicable due to their strict requirements on the availability of multiple robots, widely distributed contacts, or specific geometries of the robots or the objects. To this end, this work proposes a novel concept, termed Caging in Time, to allow caging configurations to be formed even if there is just one robot engaged in a task. This novel concept can be explained by an insight that even if a caging configuration is needed to constrain the motion of an object, only a small portion of the cage is actively manipulating at a time. As such, we can switch the configuration of the robot strategically so that by collapsing its configuration in time, we will see a cage formed and its necessary portion active whenever needed. We instantiate our Caging in Time theory on challenging quasistatic and dynamic manipulation tasks, showing that Caging in Time can be achieved in general state spaces including geometry-based and energy-based spaces. With extensive experiments, we show robust and accurate manipulation, in an open-loop manner, without requiring detailed knowledge of the object geometry or physical properties, nor realtime accurate feedback on the manipulation states. In addition to being an effective and robust open-loop manipulation solution, the proposed theory can be a supplementary strategy to other manipulation systems affected by uncertain or limited robot perception.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16481v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaotian Wang, Kejia Ren, Andrew S. Morgan, Kaiyu Hang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generic approach for reactive stateful mitigation of application failures in distributed robotics systems deployed with Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18825v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Offloading computationally expensive algorithms to the edge or even cloud offers an attractive option to tackle limitations regarding on-board computational and energy resources of robotic systems. In cloud-native applications deployed with the container management system Kubernetes (K8s), one key problem is ensuring resilience against various types of failures. However, complex robotic systems interacting with the physical world pose a very specific set of challenges and requirements that are not yet covered by failure mitigation approaches from the cloud-native domain. In this paper, we therefore propose a novel approach for robotic system monitoring and stateful, reactive failure mitigation for distributed robotic systems deployed using Kubernetes (K8s) and the Robot Operating System (ROS2). By employing the generic substrate of Behaviour Trees, our approach can be applied to any robotic workload and supports arbitrarily complex monitoring and failure mitigation strategies. We demonstrate the effectiveness and application-agnosticism of our approach on two example applications, namely Autonomous Mobile Robot (AMR) navigation and robotic manipulation in a simulated environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18825v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Mirus, Frederik Pasch, Nikhil Singhal, Kay-Ulrich Scholl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Degree of Flowability for Virtual Tubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22031v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the rapid development of robotics swarm technology, there are more tasks that require the swarm to pass through complicated environments safely and efficiently. Virtual tube technology is a novel way to achieve this goal. Virtual tubes are free spaces connecting two places that provide safety boundaries and direction of motion for swarm robotics. How to determine the design quality of a virtual tube is a fundamental problem. For such a purpose, this paper presents a degree of flowability (DOF) for two-dimensional virtual tubes according to a minimum energy principle. After that, methods to calculate DOF are proposed with a feasibility analysis. Simulations of swarm robotics in different kinds of two-dimensional virtual tubes are performed to demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed method of calculating DOF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22031v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Quan, Shuhan Huang, Kai-Yuan Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPTR: Gaussian Process Trajectory Representation for Continuous-Time Motion Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22931v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Continuous-time trajectory representation has gained significant popularity in recent years, as it offers an elegant formulation that allows the fusion of a larger number of sensors and sensing modalities, overcoming limitations of traditional discrete-time frameworks. To bolster the adoption of the continuous-time paradigm, we propose a so-called Gaussian Process Trajectory Representation (GPTR) framework for continuous-time motion estimation (CTME) tasks. Our approach stands out by employing a third-order random jerk model, featuring closed-form expressions for both rotational and translational state derivatives. This model provides smooth, continuous trajectory representations that are crucial for precise estimation of complex motion. To support the wider robotics and computer vision communities, we have made the source code for GPTR available as a light-weight header-only library. This format was chosen for its ease of integration, allowing developers to incorporate GPTR into existing systems without needing extensive code modifications. Moreover, we also provide a set of optimization examples with LiDAR, camera, IMU, UWB factors, and closed-form analytical Jacobians under the proposed GP framework. Our experiments demonstrate the efficacy and efficiency of GP-based trajectory representation in various motion estimation tasks, and the examples can serve as the prototype to help researchers quickly develop future applications such as batch optimization, calibration, sensor fusion, trajectory planning, etc., with continuous-time trajectory representation. Our project is accessible at https://github.com/brytsknguyen/gptr .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22931v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thien-Minh Nguyen, Ziyu Cao, Kailai Li, Shenghai Yuan, Lihua Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FilMBot: A High-Speed Soft Parallel Robotic Micromanipulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23059v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Soft robotic manipulators are generally slow despite their great adaptability, resilience, and compliance. This limitation also extends to current soft robotic micromanipulators. Here, we introduce FilMBot, a 3-DOF film-based, electromagnetically actuated, soft kinematic robotic micromanipulator achieving speeds up to 2117 $\deg$/s and 2456 $\deg$/s in $\alpha$ and $\beta$ angular motions, with corresponding linear velocities of 1.61 m/s and 1.92 m/s using a 4-cm needle end-effector, and 1.57 m/s along the Z axis. The robot can reach ~1.50 m/s in path-following tasks, operates at frequencies up to 30 Hz, and remains functional up to 50 Hz. It demonstrates high precision (~6.3 $\mu$m, or ~0.05% of its workspace) in small path-following tasks. The novel combination of the low-stiffness soft kinematic film structure and strong electromagnetic actuation in FilMBot opens new avenues for soft robotics. Furthermore, its simple construction and inexpensive, readily accessible components could broaden the application of micromanipulators beyond current academic and professional users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23059v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangkun Yu, Houari Bettahar, Hakan Kandemir, Quan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast and Model Based Approach for Evaluating Task-Competence of Antagonistic Continuum Arms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00241v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Soft robot arms have made significant progress towards completing human-scale tasks, but designing arms for tasks with specific load and workspace requirements remains difficult. A key challenge is the lack of model-based design tools, forcing advancement to occur through empirical iteration and observation. Existing models are focused on control and rely on parameter fits, which means they cannot provide general conclusions about the mapping between design and performance or the influence of factors outside the fitting data. As a first step toward model-based design tools, we introduce a novel method of analyzing whether a proposed arm design can complete desired tasks. Our method is informative, interpretable, and fast; it provides novel metrics for quantifying a proposed arm design's ability to perform a task, it yields a graphical interpretation of performance through segment forces, and computing it is over 80x faster than optimization based methods. Our formulation focuses on antagonistic, pneumatically-driven soft arms. We demonstrate our approach through example analysis, and also through consideration of antagonistic vs non-antagonistic designs. Our method enables fast, direct and task-specific comparison of these two architectures, and provides a new visualization of the comparative mechanics. While only a first step, the proposed approach will support advancement of model-based design tools, leading to highly capable soft arms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00241v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bill Fan, Jacob Roulier, Gina Olson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoJoin: Efficient Adversarial Training against Gradient-Free Perturbations for Robust Maneuvering via Denoising Autoencoder and Joint Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.10933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.10933v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the growing use of machine learning algorithms and ubiquitous sensors, many `perception-to-control' systems are being developed and deployed. To ensure their trustworthiness, improving their robustness through adversarial training is one potential approach. We propose a gradient-free adversarial training technique, named AutoJoin, to effectively and efficiently produce robust models for image-based maneuvering. Compared to other state-of-the-art methods with testing on over 5M images, AutoJoin achieves significant performance increases up to the 40% range against perturbations while improving on clean performance up to 300%. AutoJoin is also highly efficient, saving up to 86% time per training epoch and 90% training data over other state-of-the-art techniques. The core idea of AutoJoin is to use a decoder attachment to the original regression model creating a denoising autoencoder within the architecture. This architecture allows the tasks `maneuvering' and `denoising sensor input' to be jointly learnt and reinforce each other's performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.10933v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Villarreal, Bibek Poudel, Ryan Wickman, Yu Shen, Weizi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision probability reduction method for tracking control in automatic docking / berthing using reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.06415v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Automation of berthing maneuvers in shipping is a pressing issue as the berthing maneuver is one of the most stressful tasks seafarers undertake. Berthing control problems are often tackled via tracking a predefined trajectory or path. Maintaining a tracking error of zero under an uncertain environment is impossible; the tracking controller is nonetheless required to bring vessels close to desired berths. The tracking controller must prioritize the avoidance of tracking errors that may cause collisions with obstacles. This paper proposes a training method based on reinforcement learning for a trajectory tracking controller that reduces the probability of collisions with static obstacles. Via numerical simulations, we show that the proposed method reduces the probability of collisions during berthing maneuvers. Furthermore, this paper shows the tracking performance in a model experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.06415v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00773-023-00962-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kouki Wakita, Youhei Akimoto, Dimas M. Rachman, Yoshiki Miyauchi, Umeda Naoya, Atsuo Maki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Control and Coordinate Mixed Traffic Through Robot Vehicles at Complex and Unsignalized Intersections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.05294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.05294v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Intersections are essential road infrastructures for traffic in modern metropolises. However, they can also be the bottleneck of traffic flows as a result of traffic incidents or the absence of traffic coordination mechanisms such as traffic lights. Recently, various control and coordination mechanisms that are beyond traditional control methods have been proposed to improve the efficiency of intersection traffic by leveraging the ability of autonomous vehicles. Amongst these methods, the control of foreseeable mixed traffic that consists of human-driven vehicles (HVs) and robot vehicles (RVs) has emerged. We propose a decentralized multi-agent reinforcement learning approach for the control and coordination of mixed traffic by RVs at real-world, complex intersections -- an open challenge to date. We design comprehensive experiments to evaluate the effectiveness, robustness, generalizablility, and adaptability of our approach. In particular, our method can prevent congestion formation via merely 5% RVs under a real-world traffic demand of 700 vehicles per hour. In contrast, without RVs, congestion will form when the traffic demand reaches as low as 200 vehicles per hour. Moreover, when the RV penetration rate exceeds 60%, our method starts to outperform traffic signal control in terms of the average waiting time of all vehicles. Our method is not only robust against blackout events, sudden RV percentage drops, and V2V communication error, but also enjoys excellent generalizablility, evidenced by its successful deployment in five unseen intersections. Lastly, our method performs well under various traffic rules, demonstrating its adaptability to diverse scenarios. Videos and code of our work are available at https://sites.google.com/view/mixedtrafficcontrol</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.05294v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1177/02783649241284069</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dawei Wang, Weizi Li, Lei Zhu, Jia Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Quantization-Aware Training for 6D Object Pose Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06753v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Edge applications, such as collaborative robotics and spacecraft rendezvous, demand efficient 6D object pose estimation on resource-constrained embedded platforms. Existing 6D pose estimation networks are often too large for such deployments, necessitating compression while maintaining reliable performance. To address this challenge, we introduce Modular Quantization-Aware Training (MQAT), an adaptive and mixed-precision quantization-aware training strategy that exploits the modular structure of modern 6D pose estimation architectures. MQAT guides a systematic gradated modular quantization sequence and determines module-specific bit precisions, leading to quantized models that outperform those produced by state-of-the-art uniform and mixed-precision quantization techniques. Our experiments showcase the generality of MQAT across datasets, architectures, and quantization algorithms. Remarkably, MQAT-trained quantized models achieve a significant accuracy boost (&gt;7%) over the baseline full-precision network while reducing model size by a factor of 4x or more. Our project website is at: https://saqibjaved1.github.io/MQAT_/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06753v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saqib Javed, Chengkun Li, Andrew Price, Yinlin Hu, Mathieu Salzmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PVPUFormer: Probabilistic Visual Prompt Unified Transformer for Interactive Image Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.06656v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Integration of diverse visual prompts like clicks, scribbles, and boxes in interactive image segmentation significantly facilitates users' interaction as well as improves interaction efficiency. However, existing studies primarily encode the position or pixel regions of prompts without considering the contextual areas around them, resulting in insufficient prompt feedback, which is not conducive to performance acceleration. To tackle this problem, this paper proposes a simple yet effective Probabilistic Visual Prompt Unified Transformer (PVPUFormer) for interactive image segmentation, which allows users to flexibly input diverse visual prompts with the probabilistic prompt encoding and feature post-processing to excavate sufficient and robust prompt features for performance boosting. Specifically, we first propose a Probabilistic Prompt-unified Encoder (PPuE) to generate a unified one-dimensional vector by exploring both prompt and non-prompt contextual information, offering richer feedback cues to accelerate performance improvement. On this basis, we further present a Prompt-to-Pixel Contrastive (P$^2$C) loss to accurately align both prompt and pixel features, bridging the representation gap between them to offer consistent feature representations for mask prediction. Moreover, our approach designs a Dual-cross Merging Attention (DMA) module to implement bidirectional feature interaction between image and prompt features, generating notable features for performance improvement. A comprehensive variety of experiments on several challenging datasets demonstrates that the proposed components achieve consistent improvements, yielding state-of-the-art interactive segmentation performance. Our code is available at https://github.com/XuZhang1211/PVPUFormer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.06656v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Zhang, Kailun Yang, Jiacheng Lin, Jin Yuan, Zhiyong Li, Shutao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-Aware Vision-and-Language Navigation: Bridging Simulation to Reality with Dynamic Human Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19236v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vision-and-Language Navigation (VLN) aims to develop embodied agents that navigate based on human instructions. However, current VLN frameworks often rely on static environments and optimal expert supervision, limiting their real-world applicability. To address this, we introduce Human-Aware Vision-and-Language Navigation (HA-VLN), extending traditional VLN by incorporating dynamic human activities and relaxing key assumptions. We propose the Human-Aware 3D (HA3D) simulator, which combines dynamic human activities with the Matterport3D dataset, and the Human-Aware Room-to-Room (HA-R2R) dataset, extending R2R with human activity descriptions. To tackle HA-VLN challenges, we present the Expert-Supervised Cross-Modal (VLN-CM) and Non-Expert-Supervised Decision Transformer (VLN-DT) agents, utilizing cross-modal fusion and diverse training strategies for effective navigation in dynamic human environments. A comprehensive evaluation, including metrics considering human activities, and systematic analysis of HA-VLN's unique challenges, underscores the need for further research to enhance HA-VLN agents' real-world robustness and adaptability. Ultimately, this work provides benchmarks and insights for future research on embodied AI and Sim2Real transfer, paving the way for more realistic and applicable VLN systems in human-populated environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19236v3</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng Li, Minghan Li, Zhi-Qi Cheng, Yifei Dong, Yuxuan Zhou, Jun-Yan He, Qi Dai, Teruko Mitamura, Alexander G. Hauptmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomy-Aware Continual Semantic Segmentation in Hyperbolic Spaces for Open-World Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18145v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Semantic segmentation models are typically trained on a fixed set of classes, limiting their applicability in open-world scenarios. Class-incremental semantic segmentation aims to update models with emerging new classes while preventing catastrophic forgetting of previously learned ones. However, existing methods impose strict rigidity on old classes, reducing their effectiveness in learning new incremental classes. In this work, we propose Taxonomy-Oriented Poincar\'e-regularized Incremental-Class Segmentation (TOPICS) that learns feature embeddings in hyperbolic space following explicit taxonomy-tree structures. This supervision provides plasticity for old classes, updating ancestors based on new classes while integrating new classes at fitting positions. Additionally, we maintain implicit class relational constraints on the geometric basis of the Poincar\'e ball. This ensures that the latent space can continuously adapt to new constraints while maintaining a robust structure to combat catastrophic forgetting. We also establish eight realistic incremental learning protocols for autonomous driving scenarios, where novel classes can originate from known classes or the background. Extensive evaluations of TOPICS on the Cityscapes and Mapillary Vistas 2.0 benchmarks demonstrate that it achieves state-of-the-art performance. We make the code and trained models publicly available at http://topics.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18145v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Hindel, Daniele Cattaneo, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BodySLAM: A Generalized Monocular Visual SLAM Framework for Surgical Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03078v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Endoscopic surgery relies on two-dimensional views, posing challenges for surgeons in depth perception and instrument manipulation. While Monocular Visual Simultaneous Localization and Mapping (MVSLAM) has emerged as a promising solution, its implementation in endoscopic procedures faces significant challenges due to hardware limitations, such as the use of a monocular camera and the absence of odometry sensors. This study presents BodySLAM, a robust deep learning-based MVSLAM approach that addresses these challenges through three key components: CycleVO, a novel unsupervised monocular pose estimation module; the integration of the state-of-the-art Zoe architecture for monocular depth estimation; and a 3D reconstruction module creating a coherent surgical map. The approach is rigorously evaluated using three publicly available datasets (Hamlyn, EndoSLAM, and SCARED) spanning laparoscopy, gastroscopy, and colonoscopy scenarios, and benchmarked against four state-of-the-art methods. Results demonstrate that CycleVO exhibited competitive performance with the lowest inference time among pose estimation methods, while maintaining robust generalization capabilities, whereas Zoe significantly outperformed existing algorithms for depth estimation in endoscopy. BodySLAM's strong performance across diverse endoscopic scenarios demonstrates its potential as a viable MVSLAM solution for endoscopic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03078v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Manni (Research Unit of Computer Systems and Bioinformatics Department of Engineering Universit\`a Campus Bio-Medico di Roma, Unit of Advanced Robotics and Human-Centred Technologies Department of Engineering Universit\`a Campus Bio-Medico di Roma), C. Lauretti (Unit of Advanced Robotics and Human-Centred Technologies Department of Engineering Universit\`a Campus Bio-Medico di Roma), F. Prata (Department of Urology Fondazione Policlinico Universitario Campus Bio-Medico), R. Papalia (Department of Urology Fondazione Policlinico Universitario Campus Bio-Medico), L. Zollo (Unit of Advanced Robotics and Human-Centred Technologies Department of Engineering Universit\`a Campus Bio-Medico di Roma), P. Soda (Research Unit of Computer Systems and Bioinformatics Department of Engineering Universit\`a Campus Bio-Medico di Roma)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assigning Credit with Partial Reward Decoupling in Multi-Agent Proximal Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04295v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multi-agent proximal policy optimization (MAPPO) has recently demonstrated state-of-the-art performance on challenging multi-agent reinforcement learning tasks. However, MAPPO still struggles with the credit assignment problem, wherein the sheer difficulty in ascribing credit to individual agents' actions scales poorly with team size. In this paper, we propose a multi-agent reinforcement learning algorithm that adapts recent developments in credit assignment to improve upon MAPPO. Our approach leverages partial reward decoupling (PRD), which uses a learned attention mechanism to estimate which of a particular agent's teammates are relevant to its learning updates. We use this estimate to dynamically decompose large groups of agents into smaller, more manageable subgroups. We empirically demonstrate that our approach, PRD-MAPPO, decouples agents from teammates that do not influence their expected future reward, thereby streamlining credit assignment. We additionally show that PRD-MAPPO yields significantly higher data efficiency and asymptotic performance compared to both MAPPO and other state-of-the-art methods across several multi-agent tasks, including StarCraft II. Finally, we propose a version of PRD-MAPPO that is applicable to \textit{shared} reward settings, where PRD was previously not applicable, and empirically show that this also leads to performance improvements over MAPPO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04295v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Kapoor, Benjamin Freed, Howie Choset, Jeff Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Agent Interface: Benchmarking LLMs for Embodied Decision Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07166v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We aim to evaluate Large Language Models (LLMs) for embodied decision making. While a significant body of work has been leveraging LLMs for decision making in embodied environments, we still lack a systematic understanding of their performance because they are usually applied in different domains, for different purposes, and built based on different inputs and outputs. Furthermore, existing evaluations tend to rely solely on a final success rate, making it difficult to pinpoint what ability is missing in LLMs and where the problem lies, which in turn blocks embodied agents from leveraging LLMs effectively and selectively. To address these limitations, we propose a generalized interface (Embodied Agent Interface) that supports the formalization of various types of tasks and input-output specifications of LLM-based modules. Specifically, it allows us to unify 1) a broad set of embodied decision-making tasks involving both state and temporally extended goals, 2) four commonly-used LLM-based modules for decision making: goal interpretation, subgoal decomposition, action sequencing, and transition modeling, and 3) a collection of fine-grained metrics which break down evaluation into various types of errors, such as hallucination errors, affordance errors, various types of planning errors, etc. Overall, our benchmark offers a comprehensive assessment of LLMs' performance for different subtasks, pinpointing the strengths and weaknesses in LLM-powered embodied AI systems, and providing insights for effective and selective use of LLMs in embodied decision making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07166v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manling Li, Shiyu Zhao, Qineng Wang, Kangrui Wang, Yu Zhou, Sanjana Srivastava, Cem Gokmen, Tony Lee, Li Erran Li, Ruohan Zhang, Weiyu Liu, Percy Liang, Li Fei-Fei, Jiayuan Mao, Jiajun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robot Policy Learning with Temporal Optimal Transport Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reward specification is one of the most tricky problems in Reinforcement Learning, which usually requires tedious hand engineering in practice. One promising approach to tackle this challenge is to adopt existing expert video demonstrations for policy learning. Some recent work investigates how to learn robot policies from only a single/few expert video demonstrations. For example, reward labeling via Optimal Transport (OT) has been shown to be an effective strategy to generate a proxy reward by measuring the alignment between the robot trajectory and the expert demonstrations. However, previous work mostly overlooks that the OT reward is invariant to temporal order information, which could bring extra noise to the reward signal. To address this issue, in this paper, we introduce the Temporal Optimal Transport (TemporalOT) reward to incorporate temporal order information for learning a more accurate OT-based proxy reward. Extensive experiments on the Meta-world benchmark tasks validate the efficacy of the proposed method. Code is available at: https://github.com/fuyw/TemporalOT</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21795v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuwei Fu, Haichao Zhang, Di Wu, Wei Xu, Benoit Boulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S3PT: Scene Semantics and Structure Guided Clustering to Boost Self-Supervised Pre-Training for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23085v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent self-supervised clustering-based pre-training techniques like DINO and Cribo have shown impressive results for downstream detection and segmentation tasks. However, real-world applications such as autonomous driving face challenges with imbalanced object class and size distributions and complex scene geometries. In this paper, we propose S3PT a novel scene semantics and structure guided clustering to provide more scene-consistent objectives for self-supervised training. Specifically, our contributions are threefold: First, we incorporate semantic distribution consistent clustering to encourage better representation of rare classes such as motorcycles or animals. Second, we introduce object diversity consistent spatial clustering, to handle imbalanced and diverse object sizes, ranging from large background areas to small objects such as pedestrians and traffic signs. Third, we propose a depth-guided spatial clustering to regularize learning based on geometric information of the scene, thus further refining region separation on the feature level. Our learned representations significantly improve performance in downstream semantic segmentation and 3D object detection tasks on the nuScenes, nuImages, and Cityscapes datasets and show promising domain translation properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23085v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej K. Wozniak, Hariprasath Govindarajan, Marvin Klingner, Camille Maurice, B Ravi Kiran, Senthil Yogamani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMMA: End-to-End Multimodal Model for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23262v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce EMMA, an End-to-end Multimodal Model for Autonomous driving. Built on a multi-modal large language model foundation, EMMA directly maps raw camera sensor data into various driving-specific outputs, including planner trajectories, perception objects, and road graph elements. EMMA maximizes the utility of world knowledge from the pre-trained large language models, by representing all non-sensor inputs (e.g. navigation instructions and ego vehicle status) and outputs (e.g. trajectories and 3D locations) as natural language text. This approach allows EMMA to jointly process various driving tasks in a unified language space, and generate the outputs for each task using task-specific prompts. Empirically, we demonstrate EMMA's effectiveness by achieving state-of-the-art performance in motion planning on nuScenes as well as competitive results on the Waymo Open Motion Dataset (WOMD). EMMA also yields competitive results for camera-primary 3D object detection on the Waymo Open Dataset (WOD). We show that co-training EMMA with planner trajectories, object detection, and road graph tasks yields improvements across all three domains, highlighting EMMA's potential as a generalist model for autonomous driving applications. However, EMMA also exhibits certain limitations: it can process only a small amount of image frames, does not incorporate accurate 3D sensing modalities like LiDAR or radar and is computationally expensive. We hope that our results will inspire further research to mitigate these issues and to further evolve the state of the art in autonomous driving model architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23262v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jyh-Jing Hwang, Runsheng Xu, Hubert Lin, Wei-Chih Hung, Jingwei Ji, Kristy Choi, Di Huang, Tong He, Paul Covington, Benjamin Sapp, Yin Zhou, James Guo, Dragomir Anguelov, Mingxing Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\pi_0$: A Vision-Language-Action Flow Model for General Robot Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Robot learning holds tremendous promise to unlock the full potential of flexible, general, and dexterous robot systems, as well as to address some of the deepest questions in artificial intelligence. However, bringing robot learning to the level of generality required for effective real-world systems faces major obstacles in terms of data, generalization, and robustness. In this paper, we discuss how generalist robot policies (i.e., robot foundation models) can address these challenges, and how we can design effective generalist robot policies for complex and highly dexterous tasks. We propose a novel flow matching architecture built on top of a pre-trained vision-language model (VLM) to inherit Internet-scale semantic knowledge. We then discuss how this model can be trained on a large and diverse dataset from multiple dexterous robot platforms, including single-arm robots, dual-arm robots, and mobile manipulators. We evaluate our model in terms of its ability to perform tasks in zero shot after pre-training, follow language instructions from people and from a high-level VLM policy, and its ability to acquire new skills via fine-tuning. Our results cover a wide variety of tasks, such as laundry folding, table cleaning, and assembling boxes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Black, Noah Brown, Danny Driess, Adnan Esmail, Michael Equi, Chelsea Finn, Niccolo Fusai, Lachy Groom, Karol Hausman, Brian Ichter, Szymon Jakubczak, Tim Jones, Liyiming Ke, Sergey Levine, Adrian Li-Bell, Mohith Mothukuri, Suraj Nair, Karl Pertsch, Lucy Xiaoyang Shi, James Tanner, Quan Vuong, Anna Walling, Haohuan Wang, Ury Zhilinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Equivariant Pose Regression via Direct Wigner-D Harmonics Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00543v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Determining the 3D orientations of an object in an image, known as single-image pose estimation, is a crucial task in 3D vision applications. Existing methods typically learn 3D rotations parametrized in the spatial domain using Euler angles or quaternions, but these representations often introduce discontinuities and singularities. SO(3)-equivariant networks enable the structured capture of pose patterns with data-efficient learning, but the parametrizations in spatial domain are incompatible with their architecture, particularly spherical CNNs, which operate in the frequency domain to enhance computational efficiency. To overcome these issues, we propose a frequency-domain approach that directly predicts Wigner-D coefficients for 3D rotation regression, aligning with the operations of spherical CNNs. Our SO(3)-equivariant pose harmonics predictor overcomes the limitations of spatial parameterizations, ensuring consistent pose estimation under arbitrary rotations. Trained with a frequency-domain regression loss, our method achieves state-of-the-art results on benchmarks such as ModelNet10-SO(3) and PASCAL3D+, with significant improvements in accuracy, robustness, and data efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00543v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jongmin Lee, Minsu Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
