<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 04:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MorphoMove: Bi-Modal Path Planner with MPC-based Path Follower for Multi-Limb Morphogenetic UAV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper discusses developments for a multi-limb morphogenetic UAV, MorphoGear, that is capable of both aerial flight and ground locomotion. A hybrid path planning algorithm based on A* strategy has been developed enabling seamless transition between air-to-ground navigation modes, thereby enhancing robot's mobility in complex environments. Moreover, precise path following is achieved during ground locomotion with a Model Predictive Control (MPC) architecture for its novel walking behaviour. Experimental validation was conducted in the Unity simulation environment utilizing Python scripts to compute control values. The algorithms' performance is validated by the Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) of 0.91 cm and a maximum error of 1.85 cm, as demonstrated by the results. These developments highlight the adaptability of MorphoGear in navigation through cluttered environments, establishing it as a usable tool in autonomous exploration, both aerial and ground-based.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09625v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Ahsan Mustafa, Yasheerah Yaqoot, Mikhail Martynov, Sausar Karaf, Dzmitry Tsetserukou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VDB-GPDF: Online Gaussian Process Distance Field with VDB Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robots reason about the environment through dedicated representations. Popular choices for dense representations exploit Truncated Signed Distance Functions (TSDF) and Octree data structures. However, TSDF is a projective signed distance obtained directly from depth measurements that overestimates the Euclidean distance. Octrees, despite being memory efficient, require tree traversal and can lead to increased runtime in large scenarios. Other representations based on Gaussian Process (GP) distance fields are appealing due to their probabilistic and continuous nature, but the computational complexity is a concern. In this paper, we present an online efficient mapping framework that seamlessly couples GP distance fields and the fast-access VDB data structure. This framework incrementally builds the Euclidean distance field and fuses other surface properties, like intensity or colour, into a global scene representation that can cater for large-scale scenarios. The key aspect is a latent Local GP Signed Distance Field (L-GPDF) contained in a local VDB structure that allows fast queries of the Euclidean distance, surface properties and their uncertainties for arbitrary points in the field of view. Probabilistic fusion is then performed by merging the inferred values of these points into a global VDB structure that is efficiently maintained over time. After fusion, the surface mesh is recovered, and a global GP Signed Distance Field (G-GPDF) is generated and made available for downstream applications to query accurate distance and gradients. A comparison with the state-of-the-art frameworks shows superior efficiency and accuracy of the inferred distance field and comparable reconstruction performance. The accompanying code will be publicly available. https://github.com/UTS-RI/VDB_GPDF</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09649v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lan Wu, Cedric Le Gentil, Teresa Vidal-Calleja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ballad of the Bots: Sonification Using Cognitive Metaphor to Support Immersed Teleoperation of Robot Teams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As an embodied and spatial medium, virtual reality is proving an attractive proposition for robot teleoperation in hazardous environments. This paper examines a nuclear decommissioning scenario in which a simulated team of semi-autonomous robots are used to characterise a chamber within a virtual nuclear facility. This study examines the potential utility and impact of sonification as a means of communicating salient operator data in such an environment. However, the question of what sound should be used and how it can be applied in different applications is far from resolved. This paper explores and compares two sonification design approaches. The first is inspired by the theory of cognitive metaphor to create sonifications that align with socially acquired contextual and ecological understanding of the application domain. The second adopts a computationalist approach using auditory mappings that are commonplace in the literature. The results suggest that the computationalist approach outperforms the cognitive metaphor approach in terms of predictability and mental workload. However, qualitative data analysis demonstrates that the cognitive metaphor approach resulted in sounds that were more intuitive, and were better implemented for spatialisation of data sources and data legibility when there was more than one sound source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09673v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/frvir.2024.1404865</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Joe Simmons, Paul Bremner, Thomas J Mitchell, Alison Bown, Verity McIntosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language-Augmented Symbolic Planner for Open-World Task Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Enabling robotic agents to perform complex long-horizon tasks has been a long-standing goal in robotics and artificial intelligence (AI). Despite the potential shown by large language models (LLMs), their planning capabilities remain limited to short-horizon tasks and they are unable to replace the symbolic planning approach. Symbolic planners, on the other hand, may encounter execution errors due to their common assumption of complete domain knowledge which is hard to manually prepare for an open-world setting. In this paper, we introduce a Language-Augmented Symbolic Planner (LASP) that integrates pre-trained LLMs to enable conventional symbolic planners to operate in an open-world environment where only incomplete knowledge of action preconditions, objects, and properties is initially available. In case of execution errors, LASP can utilize the LLM to diagnose the cause of the error based on the observation and interact with the environment to incrementally build up its knowledge base necessary for accomplishing the given tasks. Experiments demonstrate that LASP is proficient in solving planning problems in the open-world setting, performing well even in situations where there are multiple gaps in the knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09792v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanqi Chen, Lei Yang, Ruixing Jia, Zhe Hu, Yizhou Chen, Wei Zhang, Wenping Wang, Jia Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Predictive Path Integral Control for Agile Unmanned Aerial Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a control architecture for real-time and onboard control of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) in environments with obstacles using the Model Predictive Path Integral (MPPI) methodology. MPPI allows the use of the full nonlinear model of UAV dynamics and a more general cost function at the cost of a high computational demand. To run the controller in real-time, the sampling-based optimization is performed in parallel on a graphics processing unit onboard the UAV. We propose an approach to the simulation of the nonlinear system which respects low-level constraints, while also able to dynamically handle obstacle avoidance, and prove that our methods are able to run in real-time without the need for external computers. The MPPI controller is compared to MPC and SE(3) controllers on the reference tracking task, showing a comparable performance. We demonstrate the viability of the proposed method in multiple simulation and real-world experiments, tracking a reference at up to 44 km/h and acceleration close to 20 m/s^2, while still being able to avoid obstacles. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first method to demonstrate an MPPI-based approach in real flight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09812v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Minarik, Robert Penicka, Vojtech Vonasek, Martin Saska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLMPC: Vision-Language Model Predictive Control for Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although Model Predictive Control (MPC) can effectively predict the future states of a system and thus is widely used in robotic manipulation tasks, it does not have the capability of environmental perception, leading to the failure in some complex scenarios. To address this issue, we introduce Vision-Language Model Predictive Control (VLMPC), a robotic manipulation framework which takes advantage of the powerful perception capability of vision language model (VLM) and integrates it with MPC. Specifically, we propose a conditional action sampling module which takes as input a goal image or a language instruction and leverages VLM to sample a set of candidate action sequences. Then, a lightweight action-conditioned video prediction model is designed to generate a set of future frames conditioned on the candidate action sequences. VLMPC produces the optimal action sequence with the assistance of VLM through a hierarchical cost function that formulates both pixel-level and knowledge-level consistence between the current observation and the goal image. We demonstrate that VLMPC outperforms the state-of-the-art methods on public benchmarks. More importantly, our method showcases excellent performance in various real-world tasks of robotic manipulation. Code is available at~\url{https://github.com/PPjmchen/VLMPC}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09829v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wentao Zhao, Jiaming Chen, Ziyu Meng, Donghui Mao, Ran Song, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniRace: 6D Hand Pose Estimation for Intuitive Guidance of Racing Drone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the OmniRace approach to controlling a racing drone with 6-degree of freedom (DoF) hand pose estimation and gesture recognition. To our knowledge, it is the first-ever technology that allows for low-level control of high-speed drones using gestures. OmniRace employs a gesture interface based on computer vision and a deep neural network to estimate a 6-DoF hand pose. The advanced machine learning algorithm robustly interprets human gestures, allowing users to control drone motion intuitively. Real-time control of a racing drone demonstrates the effectiveness of the system, validating its potential to revolutionize drone racing and other applications. Experimental results conducted in the Gazebo simulation environment revealed that OmniRace allows the users to complite the UAV race track significantly (by 25.1%) faster and to decrease the length of the test drone path (from 102.9 to 83.7 m). Users preferred the gesture interface for attractiveness (1.57 UEQ score), hedonic quality (1.56 UEQ score), and lower perceived temporal demand (32.0 score in NASA-TLX), while noting the high efficiency (0.75 UEQ score) and low physical demand (19.0 score in NASA-TLX) of the baseline remote controller. The deep neural network attains an average accuracy of 99.75% when applied to both normalized datasets and raw datasets. OmniRace can potentially change the way humans interact with and navigate racing drones in dynamic and complex environments. The source code is available at https://github.com/SerValera/OmniRace.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09841v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerii Serpiva, Aleksey Fedoseev, Sausar Karaf, Ali Alridha Abdulkarim, Dzmitry Tsetserukou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speech-Guided Sequential Planning for Autonomous Navigation using Large Language Model Meta AI 3 (Llama3)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In social robotics, a pivotal focus is enabling robots to engage with humans in a more natural and seamless manner. The emergence of advanced large language models (LLMs) such as Generative Pre-trained Transformers (GPTs) and autoregressive models like Large Language Model Meta AI (Llamas) has driven significant advancements in integrating natural language understanding capabilities into social robots. This paper presents a system for speech-guided sequential planning in autonomous navigation, utilizing Llama3 and the Robot Operating System~(ROS). The proposed system involves using Llama3 to interpret voice commands, extracting essential details through parsing, and decoding these commands into sequential actions for tasks. Such sequential planning is essential in various domains, particularly in the pickup and delivery of an object. Once a sequential navigation task is evaluated, we employ DRL-VO, a learning-based control policy that allows a robot to autonomously navigate through social spaces with static infrastructure and (crowds of) people. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the system in simulation experiment using Turtlebot 2 in ROS1 and Turtlebot 3 in ROS2. We conduct hardware trials using a Clearpath Robotics Jackal UGV, highlighting its potential for real-world deployment in scenarios requiring flexible and interactive robotic behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09890v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alkesh K. Srivastava, Philip Dames</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DexGrasp-Diffusion: Diffusion-based Unified Functional Grasp Synthesis Pipeline for Multi-Dexterous Robotic Hands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The versatility and adaptability of human grasping catalyze advancing dexterous robotic manipulation. While significant strides have been made in dexterous grasp generation, current research endeavors pivot towards optimizing object manipulation while ensuring functional integrity, emphasizing the synthesis of functional grasps following desired affordance instructions. This paper addresses the challenge of synthesizing functional grasps tailored to diverse dexterous robotic hands by proposing DexGrasp-Diffusion, an end-to-end modularized diffusion-based pipeline. DexGrasp-Diffusion integrates MultiHandDiffuser, a novel unified data-driven diffusion model for multi-dexterous hands grasp estimation, with DexDiscriminator, which employs a Physics Discriminator and a Functional Discriminator with open-vocabulary setting to filter physically plausible functional grasps based on object affordances. The experimental evaluation conducted on the MultiDex dataset provides substantiating evidence supporting the superior performance of MultiHandDiffuser over the baseline model in terms of success rate, grasp diversity, and collision depth. Moreover, we demonstrate the capacity of DexGrasp-Diffusion to reliably generate functional grasps for household objects aligned with specific affordance instructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09899v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengshen Zhang, Lei Zhou, Chenchen Liu, Zhiyang Liu, Chengran Yuan, Sheng Guo, Ruiteng Zhao, Marcelo H. Ang Jr., Francis EH Tay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Air-Ground Collaboration with SPOMP: Semantic Panoramic Online Mapping and Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mapping and navigation have gone hand-in-hand since long before robots existed. Maps are a key form of communication, allowing someone who has never been somewhere to nonetheless navigate that area successfully. In the context of multi-robot systems, the maps and information that flow between robots are necessary for effective collaboration, whether those robots are operating concurrently, sequentially, or completely asynchronously. In this paper, we argue that maps must go beyond encoding purely geometric or visual information to enable increasingly complex autonomy, particularly between robots. We propose a framework for multi-robot autonomy, focusing in particular on air and ground robots operating in outdoor 2.5D environments. We show that semantic maps can enable the specification, planning, and execution of complex collaborative missions, including localization in GPS-denied settings. A distinguishing characteristic of this work is that we strongly emphasize field experiments and testing, and by doing so demonstrate that these ideas can work at scale in the real world. We also perform extensive simulation experiments to validate our ideas at even larger scales. We believe these experiments and the experimental results constitute a significant step forward toward advancing the state-of-the-art of large-scale, collaborative multi-robot systems operating with real communication, navigation, and perception constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09902v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TFR.2024.3424748</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Field Robotics (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ian D. Miller, Fernando Cladera, Trey Smith, Camillo Jose Taylor, Vijay Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Dynamic Systems through Neural Network Learning: A Robust Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Point-to-point and periodic motions are ubiquitous in the world of robotics. To master these motions, Autonomous Dynamic System (DS) based algorithms are fundamental in the domain of Learning from Demonstration (LfD). However, these algorithms face the significant challenge of balancing precision in learning with the maintenance of system stability. This paper addresses this challenge by presenting a novel ADS algorithm that leverages neural network technology. The proposed algorithm is designed to distill essential knowledge from demonstration data, ensuring stability during the learning of both point-to-point and periodic motions. For point-to-point motions, a neural Lyapunov function is proposed to align with the provided demonstrations. In the case of periodic motions, the neural Lyapunov function is used with the transversal contraction to ensure that all generated motions converge to a stable limit cycle. The model utilizes a streamlined neural network architecture, adept at achieving dual objectives: optimizing learning accuracy while maintaining global stability. To thoroughly assess the efficacy of the proposed algorithm, rigorous evaluations are conducted using the LASA dataset and a manually designed dataset. These assessments were complemented by empirical validation through robotic experiments, providing robust evidence of the algorithm's performance</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09984v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhang, Haoyu Zhang, Yongxiang Zou, Houcheng Li, Long Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Is More Influential Than Haptic Information During Reinforcement Learning of Object Manipulation Against Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning to lift and rotate objects with the fingertips is necessary for autonomous in-hand dexterous manipulation. In our study, we explore the impact of various factors on successful learning strategies for this task. Specifically, we investigate the role of curriculum learning and haptic feedback in enabling the learning of dexterous manipulation. Using model-free Reinforcement Learning, we compare different curricula and two haptic information modalities (No-tactile vs. 3D-force sensing) for lifting and rotating a ball against gravity with a three-fingered simulated robotic hand with no visual input. Note that our best results were obtained when we used a novel curriculum-based learning rate scheduler, which adjusts the linearly-decaying learning rate when the reward is changed as it accelerates convergence to higher rewards. Our findings demonstrate that the choice of curriculum greatly biases the acquisition of different features of dexterous manipulation. Surprisingly, successful learning can be achieved even in the absence of tactile feedback, challenging conventional assumptions about the necessity of haptic information for dexterous manipulation tasks. We demonstrate the generalizability of our results to balls of different weights and sizes, underscoring the robustness of our learning approach. This work, therefore, emphasizes the importance of the choice curriculum and challenges long-held notions about the need for tactile information to autonomously learn in-hand dexterous manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09986v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pegah Ojaghi, Romina Mir, Ali Marjaninejad, Andrew Erwin, Michael Wehner, Francisco J Valero-Cueva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-Horizon Planning for Multi-Agent Robots in Partially Observable Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability of Language Models (LMs) to understand natural language makes them a powerful tool for parsing human instructions into task plans for autonomous robots. Unlike traditional planning methods that rely on domain-specific knowledge and handcrafted rules, LMs generalize from diverse data and adapt to various tasks with minimal tuning, acting as a compressed knowledge base. However, LMs in their standard form face challenges with long-horizon tasks, particularly in partially observable multi-agent settings. We propose an LM-based Long-Horizon Planner for Multi-Agent Robotics (LLaMAR), a cognitive architecture for planning that achieves state-of-the-art results in long-horizon tasks within partially observable environments. LLaMAR employs a plan-act-correct-verify framework, allowing self-correction from action execution feedback without relying on oracles or simulators. Additionally, we present MAP-THOR, a comprehensive test suite encompassing household tasks of varying complexity within the AI2-THOR environment. Experiments show that LLaMAR achieves a 30% higher success rate compared to other state-of-the-art LM-based multi-agent planners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10031v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Nayak, Adelmo Morrison Orozco, Marina Ten Have, Vittal Thirumalai, Jackson Zhang, Darren Chen, Aditya Kapoor, Eric Robinson, Karthik Gopalakrishnan, James Harrison, Brian Ichter, Anuj Mahajan, Hamsa Balakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WING: Wheel-Inertial Neural Odometry with Ground Manifold Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose an interoceptive-only odometry system for ground robots with neural network processing and soft constraints based on the assumption of a globally continuous ground manifold. Exteroceptive sensors such as cameras, GPS and LiDAR may encounter difficulties in scenarios with poor illumination, indoor environments, dusty areas and straight tunnels. Therefore, improving the pose estimation accuracy only using interoceptive sensors is important to enhance the reliability of navigation system even in degrading scenarios mentioned above. However, interoceptive sensors like IMU and wheel encoders suffer from large drift due to noisy measurements. To overcome these challenges, the proposed system trains deep neural networks to correct the measurements from IMU and wheel encoders, while considering their uncertainty. Moreover, because ground robots can only travel on the ground, we model the ground surface as a globally continuous manifold using a dual cubic B-spline manifold to further improve the estimation accuracy by this soft constraint. A novel space-based sliding-window filtering framework is proposed to fully exploit the $C^2$ continuity of ground manifold soft constraints and fuse all the information from raw measurements and neural networks in a yaw-independent attitude convention. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our proposed approach can outperform state-of-the-art learning-based interoceptive-only odometry methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10101v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenxing Jiang, Kunyi Zhang, Sheng Yang, Shaojie Shen, Chao Xu, Fei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Model Predictive Control with Data-driven Error Model for Quadrupedal Locomotion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Model Predictive Control (MPC) relies heavily on the robot model for its control law. However, a gap always exists between the reduced-order control model with uncertainties and the real robot, which degrades its performance. To address this issue, we propose the controller of integrating a data-driven error model into traditional MPC for quadruped robots. Our approach leverages real-world data from sensors to compensate for defects in the control model. Specifically, we employ the Autoregressive Moving Average Vector (ARMAV) model to construct the state error model of the quadruped robot using data. The predicted state errors are then used to adjust the predicted future robot states generated by MPC. By such an approach, our proposed controller can provide more accurate inputs to the system, enabling it to achieve desired states even in the presence of model parameter inaccuracies or disturbances. The proposed controller exhibits the capability to partially eliminate the disparity between the model and the real-world robot, thereby enhancing the locomotion performance of quadruped robots. We validate our proposed method through simulations and real-world experimental trials on a large-size quadruped robot that involves carrying a 20 kg un-modeled payload (84% of body weight).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10124v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanqi Zeng, Hongbo Zhang, Linzhu Yue, Zhitao Song, Linwei Zhang, Yun-Hui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ODD: Omni Differential Drive for Simultaneous Reconfiguration and Omnidirectional Mobility of Wheeled Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wheeled robots are highly efficient in human living environments. However, conventional wheeled designs, with their limited degrees of freedom and constraints in robot configuration, struggle to simultaneously achieve stability, passability, and agility due to varying footprint needs. This paper proposes a novel robot drive model inspired by human movements, termed as the Omni Differential Drive (ODD). The ODD model innovatively utilizes a lateral differential drive to adjust wheel spacing without adding additional actuators to the existing omnidirectional drive. This approach enables wheeled robots to achieve both simultaneous reconfiguration and omnidirectional mobility. To validate the feasibility of the ODD model, a functional prototype was developed, followed by comprehensive kinematic analyses. Control systems for self-balancing and motion control were designed and implemented. Experimental validations confirmed the feasibility of the ODD mechanism and the effectiveness of the control strategies. The results underline the potential of this innovative drive system to enhance the mobility and adaptability of robotic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10127v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Zhao, Peijia Xie, Max Q. -H. Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programming Manipulators by Instructions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an instructions-based approach for robot programming where the programmer interacts with the robot by issuing simple commands in a scripting language, like python. Internally, these commands make use of pre-programmed motion and manipulation skills coordinated by a behaviour tree task controller. A knowledge graph keeps track of the state of the robot and the environment and of all the instructions given to the robot by the programmer. This allows to easily transform sequences of instructions into new skills that can be reused in the same or in other tasks. An advantage of this approach is that the programmer does not need to be located physically next to the robot, but can work remotely, either with a physical robot or with a digital twin. To demonstrate the concept, we show an interactive simulation of a robot manipulator in a pick and place scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10133v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael de la Guardia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning-Based Model Matching in COBRA, a Slithering Snake Robot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work employs a reinforcement learning-based model identification method aimed at enhancing the accuracy of the dynamics for our snake robot, called COBRA. Leveraging gradient information and iterative optimization, the proposed approach refines the parameters of COBRA's dynamical model such as coefficient of friction and actuator parameters using experimental and simulated data. Experimental validation on the hardware platform demonstrates the efficacy of the proposed approach, highlighting its potential to address sim-to-real gap in robot implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10300v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harin Kumar Nallaguntla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Foundation Models Enable Simultaneous Geometry and Pose Estimation of Grasped Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Humans have the remarkable ability to use held objects as tools to interact with their environment. For this to occur, humans internally estimate how hand movements affect the object's movement. We wish to endow robots with this capability. We contribute methodology to jointly estimate the geometry and pose of objects grasped by a robot, from RGB images captured by an external camera. Notably, our method transforms the estimated geometry into the robot's coordinate frame, while not requiring the extrinsic parameters of the external camera to be calibrated. Our approach leverages 3D foundation models, large models pre-trained on huge datasets for 3D vision tasks, to produce initial estimates of the in-hand object. These initial estimations do not have physically correct scales and are in the camera's frame. Then, we formulate, and efficiently solve, a coordinate-alignment problem to recover accurate scales, along with a transformation of the objects to the coordinate frame of the robot. Forward kinematics mappings can subsequently be defined from the manipulator's joint angles to specified points on the object. These mappings enable the estimation of points on the held object at arbitrary configurations, enabling robot motion to be designed with respect to coordinates on the grasped objects. We empirically evaluate our approach on a robot manipulator holding a diverse set of real-world objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10331v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiming Zhi, Haozhan Tang, Tianyi Zhang, Matthew Johnson-Roberson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affordance-Guided Reinforcement Learning via Visual Prompting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robots equipped with reinforcement learning (RL) have the potential to learn a wide range of skills solely from a reward signal. However, obtaining a robust and dense reward signal for general manipulation tasks remains a challenge. Existing learning-based approaches require significant data, such as demonstrations or examples of success and failure, to learn task-specific reward functions. Recently, there is also a growing adoption of large multi-modal foundation models for robotics. These models can perform visual reasoning in physical contexts and generate coarse robot motions for various manipulation tasks. Motivated by this range of capability, in this work, we propose and study rewards shaped by vision-language models (VLMs). State-of-the-art VLMs have demonstrated an impressive ability to reason about affordances through keypoints in zero-shot, and we leverage this to define dense rewards for robotic learning. On a real-world manipulation task specified by natural language description, we find that these rewards improve the sample efficiency of autonomous RL and enable successful completion of the task in 20K online finetuning steps. Additionally, we demonstrate the robustness of the approach to reductions in the number of in-domain demonstrations used for pretraining, reaching comparable performance in 35K online finetuning steps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10341v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivia Y. Lee, Annie Xie, Kuan Fang, Karl Pertsch, Chelsea Finn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GLIM: 3D Range-Inertial Localization and Mapping with GPU-Accelerated Scan Matching Factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article presents GLIM, a 3D range-inertial localization and mapping framework with GPU-accelerated scan matching factors. The odometry estimation module of GLIM employs a combination of fixed-lag smoothing and keyframe-based point cloud matching that makes it possible to deal with a few seconds of completely degenerated range data while efficiently reducing trajectory estimation drift. It also incorporates multi-camera visual feature constraints in a tightly coupled way to further improve the stability and accuracy. The global trajectory optimization module directly minimizes the registration errors between submaps over the entire map. This approach enables us to accurately constrain the relative pose between submaps with a small overlap. Although both the odometry estimation and global trajectory optimization algorithms require much more computation than existing methods, we show that they can be run in real-time due to the careful design of the registration error evaluation algorithm and the entire system to fully leverage GPU parallel processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10344v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.robot.2024.104750</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kenji Koide, Masashi Yokozuka, Shuji Oishi, Atsuhiko Banno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UMI on Legs: Making Manipulation Policies Mobile with Manipulation-Centric Whole-body Controllers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce UMI-on-Legs, a new framework that combines real-world and simulation data for quadruped manipulation systems. We scale task-centric data collection in the real world using a hand-held gripper (UMI), providing a cheap way to demonstrate task-relevant manipulation skills without a robot. Simultaneously, we scale robot-centric data in simulation by training whole-body controller for task-tracking without task simulation setups. The interface between these two policies is end-effector trajectories in the task frame, inferred by the manipulation policy and passed to the whole-body controller for tracking. We evaluate UMI-on-Legs on prehensile, non-prehensile, and dynamic manipulation tasks, and report over 70% success rate on all tasks. Lastly, we demonstrate the zero-shot cross-embodiment deployment of a pre-trained manipulation policy checkpoint from prior work, originally intended for a fixed-base robot arm, on our quadruped system. We believe this framework provides a scalable path towards learning expressive manipulation skills on dynamic robot embodiments. Please checkout our website for robot videos, code, and data: https://umi-on-legs.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10353v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huy Ha, Yihuai Gao, Zipeng Fu, Jie Tan, Shuran Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication- and Computation-Efficient Distributed Decision-Making in Multi-Robot Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a distributed coordination paradigm that enables scalable and near-optimal joint motion planning among multiple robots. Our coordination paradigm contrasts with current paradigms that are either near-optimal but impractical for replanning times or real-time but offer no near-optimality guarantees. We are motivated by the future of collaborative mobile autonomy, where distributed teams of robots will coordinate via vehicle-to-vehicle (v2v) communication to execute information-heavy tasks like mapping, surveillance, and target tracking. To enable rapid distributed coordination, we must curtail the explosion of information-sharing across the network, thus limiting robot coordination. However, this can lead to suboptimal plans, causing overlapping trajectories instead of complementary ones. We make theoretical and algorithmic contributions to balance the trade-off between decision speed and optimality. We introduce tools for distributed submodular optimization, a diminishing returns property in information-gathering tasks. Theoretically, we analyze how local network topology affects near-optimality at the global level. Algorithmically, we provide a communication- and computation-efficient coordination algorithm for agents to balance the trade-off. Our algorithm is up to two orders faster than competitive near-optimal algorithms. In simulations of surveillance tasks with up to 45 robots, it enables real-time planning at the order of 1 Hz with superior coverage performance. To enable the simulations, we provide a high-fidelity simulator that extends AirSim by integrating a collaborative autonomy pipeline and simulating v2v communication delays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10382v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zirui Xu, Sandilya Sai Garimella, Vasileios Tzoumas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Represent Surroundings, Anticipate Motion and Take Informed Actions in Unstructured Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contemporary robots have become exceptionally skilled at achieving specific tasks in structured environments. However, they often fail when faced with the limitless permutations of real-world unstructured environments. This motivates robotics methods which learn from experience, rather than follow a pre-defined set of rules. In this thesis, we present a range of learning-based methods aimed at enabling robots, operating in dynamic and unstructured environments, to better understand their surroundings, anticipate the actions of others, and take informed actions accordingly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10383v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiming Zhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Rapid Turning, Aerial Reorientation, and Balancing using Manipulator as a Tail</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this research, we investigated the innovative use of a manipulator as a tail in quadruped robots to augment their physical capabilities. Previous studies have primarily focused on enhancing various abilities by attaching robotic tails that function solely as tails on quadruped robots. While these tails improve the performance of the robots, they come with several disadvantages, such as increased overall weight and higher costs. To mitigate these limitations, we propose the use of a 6-DoF manipulator as a tail, allowing it to serve both as a tail and as a manipulator. To control this highly complex robot, we developed a controller based on reinforcement learning for the robot equipped with the manipulator. Our experimental results demonstrate that robots equipped with a manipulator outperform those without a manipulator in tasks such as rapid turning, aerial reorientation, and balancing. These results indicate that the manipulator can improve the agility and stability of quadruped robots, similar to a tail, in addition to its manipulation capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10420v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Insung Yang, Jemin Hwangbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Social Cost Functions for Human-Aware Path Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving social acceptance is one of the main goals of Social Robotic Navigation. Despite this topic has received increasing interest in recent years, most of the research has focused on driving the robotic agent along obstacle-free trajectories, planning around estimates of future human motion to respect personal distances and optimize navigation. However, social interactions in everyday life are also dictated by norms that do not strictly depend on movement, such as when standing at the end of a queue rather than cutting it. In this paper, we propose a novel method to recognize common social scenarios and modify a traditional planner's cost function to adapt to them. This solution enables the robot to carry out different social navigation behaviors that would not arise otherwise, maintaining the robustness of traditional navigation. Our approach allows the robot to learn different social norms with a single learned model, rather than having different modules for each task. As a proof of concept, we consider the tasks of queuing and respect interaction spaces of groups of people talking to one another, but the method can be extended to other human activities that do not involve motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10547v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Eirale, Matteo Leonetti, Marcello Chiaberge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Peg-in-Hole Assembly of Tightly Coupled Multi-manipulator Using Learning-based Visual Servo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multiple peg-in-hole assembly is one of the fundamental tasks in robotic assembly. In the multiple peg-in-hole task for large-sized parts, it is challenging for a single manipulator to simultaneously align multiple distant pegs and holes, necessitating tightly coupled multi-manipulator systems. For such Multi-manipulator Multiple Peg-in-Hole (MMPiH) tasks, we proposes a collaborative visual servo control framework that uses only the monocular in-hand cameras of each manipulator to reduce positioning errors. Initially, we train a state classification neural network and a positioning neural network. The former is used to divide the states of peg and hole in the image into three categories: obscured, separated and overlapped, while the latter determines the position of the peg and hole in the image. Based on these findings, we propose a method to integrate the visual features of multiple manipulators using virtual forces, which can naturally combine with the cooperative controller of the multi-manipulator system. To generalize our approach to holes of different appearances, we varied the appearance of the holes during the dataset generation process. The results confirm that by considering the appearance of the holes, classification accuracy and positioning precision can be improved. Finally, the results show that our method achieves an 85% success rate in dual-manipulator dual peg-in-hole tasks with a clearance of 0.2 mm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10570v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Zhang, Chengchao Bai, Jifeng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-tactile manipulation to collect household waste in outdoor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a perception system applied to robotic manipulation, that is able to assist in navigation, household waste classification and collection in outdoor environments. This system is made up of optical tactile sensors, RGBD cameras and a LiDAR. These sensors are integrated on a mobile platform with a robot manipulator and a robotic gripper. Our system is divided in three software modules, two of them are vision-based and the last one is tactile-based. The vision-based modules use CNNs to localize and recognize solid household waste, together with the grasping points estimation. The tactile-based module, which also uses CNNs and image processing, adjusts the gripper opening to control the grasping from touch data. Our proposal achieves localization errors around 6 %, a recognition accuracy of 98% and ensures the grasping stability the 91% of the attempts. The sum of runtimes of the three modules is less than 750 ms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10606v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4995/riai.2022.18534</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Revista Iberoamericana de Autom\'atica e Inform\'atica Industrial (RIAI), Volume 20, Article number 2, 2022, Pages 163-174</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julio Casta\~no-Amor\'os, Ignacio de Loyola P\'aez-Ubieta, Pablo Gil, Santiago Timoteo Puente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk-aware Trajectory Prediction by Incorporating Spatio-temporal Traffic Interaction Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To operate in open-ended environments where humans interact in complex, diverse ways, autonomous robots must learn to predict their behaviour, especially when that behavior is potentially dangerous to other agents or to the robot. However, reducing the risk of accidents requires prior knowledge of where potential collisions may occur and how. Therefore, we propose to gain this information by analyzing locations and speeds that commonly correspond to high-risk interactions within the dataset, and use it within training to generate better predictions in high risk situations. Through these location-based and speed-based re-weighting techniques, we achieve improved overall performance, as measured by most-likely FDE and KDE, as well as improved performance on high-speed vehicles, and vehicles within high-risk locations.
  2023 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10639v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2023 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2023 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2024 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Divya Thuremella, Lewis Ince, Lars Kunze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back to Newton's Laws: Learning Vision-based Agile Flight via Differentiable Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Swarm navigation in cluttered environments is a grand challenge in robotics. This work combines deep learning with first-principle physics through differentiable simulation to enable autonomous navigation of multiple aerial robots through complex environments at high speed. Our approach optimizes a neural network control policy directly by backpropagating loss gradients through the robot simulation using a simple point-mass physics model and a depth rendering engine. Despite this simplicity, our method excels in challenging tasks for both multi-agent and single-agent applications with zero-shot sim-to-real transfer. In multi-agent scenarios, our system demonstrates self-organized behavior, enabling autonomous coordination without communication or centralized planning - an achievement not seen in existing traditional or learning-based methods. In single-agent scenarios, our system achieves a 90% success rate in navigating through complex environments, significantly surpassing the 60% success rate of the previous state-of-the-art approach. Our system can operate without state estimation and adapt to dynamic obstacles. In real-world forest environments, it navigates at speeds up to 20 m/s, doubling the speed of previous imitation learning-based solutions. Notably, all these capabilities are deployed on a budget-friendly $21 computer, costing less than 5% of a GPU-equipped board used in existing systems. Video demonstrations are available at https://youtu.be/LKg9hJqc2cc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10648v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuang Zhang, Yu Hu, Yunlong Song, Danping Zhou, Weiyao Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HPHS: Hierarchical Planning based on Hybrid Frontier Sampling for Unknown Environments Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10660v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapid sampling from the environment to acquire available frontier points and timely incorporating them into subsequent planning to reduce fragmented regions are critical to improve the efficiency of autonomous exploration. We propose HPHS, a fast and effective method for the autonomous exploration of unknown environments. In this work, we efficiently sample frontier points directly from the LiDAR data and the local map around the robot, while exploiting a hierarchical planning strategy to provide the robot with a global perspective. The hierarchical planning framework divides the updated environment into multiple subregions and arranges the order of access to them by considering the overall revenue of the global path. The combination of the hybrid frontier sampling method and hierarchical planning strategy reduces the complexity of the planning problem and mitigates the issue of region remnants during the exploration process. Detailed simulation and real-world experiments demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of our approach in various aspects. The source code will be released to benefit the further research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10660v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Long, Ying Li, Chenming Wu, Bin Xu, Wei Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Estimate the Pose of a Peer Robot in a Camera Image by Predicting the States of its LEDs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of training a fully convolutional network to estimate the relative 6D pose of a robot given a camera image, when the robot is equipped with independent controllable LEDs placed in different parts of its body. The training data is composed by few (or zero) images labeled with a ground truth relative pose and many images labeled only with the true state (\textsc{on} or \textsc{off}) of each of the peer LEDs. The former data is expensive to acquire, requiring external infrastructure for tracking the two robots; the latter is cheap as it can be acquired by two unsupervised robots moving randomly and toggling their LEDs while sharing the true LED states via radio. Training with the latter dataset on estimating the LEDs' state of the peer robot (\emph{pretext task}) promotes learning the relative localization task (\emph{end task}). Experiments on real-world data acquired by two autonomous wheeled robots show that a model trained only on the pretext task successfully learns to localize a peer robot on the image plane; fine-tuning such model on the end task with few labeled images yields statistically significant improvements in 6D relative pose estimation with respect to baselines that do not use pretext-task pre-training, and alternative approaches. Estimating the state of multiple independent LEDs promotes learning to estimate relative heading. The approach works even when a large fraction of training images do not include the peer robot and generalizes well to unseen environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10661v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Carlotti, Mirko Nava, Alessandro Giusti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling 3D Reasoning with LMMs to Large Robot Mission Environments Using Datagraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the challenge of scaling Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) to expansive 3D environments. Solving this open problem is especially relevant for robot deployment in many first-responder scenarios, such as search-and-rescue missions that cover vast spaces. The use of LMMs in these settings is currently hampered by the strict context windows that limit the LMM's input size. We therefore introduce a novel approach that utilizes a datagraph structure, which allows the LMM to iteratively query smaller sections of a large environment. Using the datagraph in conjunction with graph traversal algorithms, we can prioritize the most relevant locations to the query, thereby improving the scalability of 3D scene language tasks. We illustrate the datagraph using 3D scenes, but these can be easily substituted by other dense modalities that represent the environment, such as pointclouds or Gaussian splats. We demonstrate the potential to use the datagraph for two 3D scene language task use cases, in a search-and-rescue mission example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10743v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. J. Meijer, A. C. Kemmeren, E. H. J. Riemens, J. E. Fransman, M. van Bekkum, G. J. Burghouts, J. D. van Mil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LVCP: LiDAR-Vision Tightly Coupled Collaborative Real-time Relative Positioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10782v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In air-ground collaboration scenarios without GPS and prior maps, the relative positioning of drones and unmanned ground vehicles (UGVs) has always been a challenge. For a drone equipped with monocular camera and an UGV equipped with LiDAR as an external sensor, we propose a robust and real-time relative pose estimation method (LVCP) based on the tight coupling of vision and LiDAR point cloud information, which does not require prior information such as maps or precise initial poses. Given that large-scale point clouds generated by 3D sensors has more accurate spatial geometric information than the feature point cloud generated by image, we utilize LiDAR point clouds to correct the drift in visual-inertial odometry (VIO) when the camera undergoes significant shaking or the IMU has a low signal-to-noise ratio. To achieve this, we propose a novel coarse-to-fine framework for LiDAR-vision collaborative localization. In this framework, we construct point-plane association based on spatial geometric information, and innovatively construct a point-aided Bundle Adjustment (BA) problem as the backend to simultaneously estimate the relative pose of the camera and LiDAR and correct the VIO drift. In this process, we propose a particle swarm optimization (PSO) based sampling algorithm to complete the coarse estimation of the current camera-LiDAR pose. In this process, the initial pose of the camera used for sampling is obtained based on VIO propagation, and the valid feature-plane association number (VFPN) is used to trigger PSO-sampling process. Additionally, we propose a method that combines Structure from Motion (SFM) and multi-level sampling to initialize the algorithm, addressing the challenge of lacking initial values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10782v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuozhu Jian, Qixuan Li, Shengtao Zheng, Xueqian Wang, Xinlei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tailoring Solution Accuracy for Fast Whole-body Model Predictive Control of Legged Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thanks to recent advancements in accelerating non-linear model predictive control (NMPC), it is now feasible to deploy whole-body NMPC at real-time rates for humanoid robots. However, enforcing inequality constraints in real time for such high-dimensional systems remains challenging due to the need for additional iterations. This paper presents an implementation of whole-body NMPC for legged robots that provides low-accuracy solutions to NMPC with general equality and inequality constraints. Instead of aiming for highly accurate optimal solutions, we leverage the alternating direction method of multipliers to rapidly provide low-accuracy solutions to quadratic programming subproblems. Our extensive simulation results indicate that real robots often cannot benefit from highly accurate solutions due to dynamics discretization errors, inertial modeling errors and delays. We incorporate control barrier functions (CBFs) at the initial timestep of the NMPC for the self-collision constraints, resulting in up to a 26-fold reduction in the number of self-collisions without adding computational burden. The controller is reliably deployed on hardware at 90 Hz for a problem involving 32 timesteps, 2004 variables, and 3768 constraints. The NMPC delivers sufficiently accurate solutions, enabling the MIT Humanoid to plan complex crossed-leg and arm motions that enhance stability when walking and recovering from significant disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10789v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Khazoom, Seungwoo Hong, Matthew Chignoli, Elijah Stanger-Jones, Sangbae Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AirNeRF: 3D Reconstruction of Human with Drone and NeRF for Future Communication Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the rapidly evolving landscape of digital content creation, the demand for fast, convenient, and autonomous methods of crafting detailed 3D reconstructions of humans has grown significantly. Addressing this pressing need, our AirNeRF system presents an innovative pathway to the creation of a realistic 3D human avatar. Our approach leverages Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF) with an automated drone-based video capturing method. The acquired data provides a swift and precise way to create high-quality human body reconstructions following several stages of our system. The rigged mesh derived from our system proves to be an excellent foundation for free-view synthesis of dynamic humans, particularly well-suited for the immersive experiences within gaming and virtual reality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10865v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Kotcov, Maria Dronova, Vladislav Cheremnykh, Sausar Karaf, Dzmitry Tsetserukou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A BlueROV2-based platform for underwater mapping experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a low-cost laboratory platform for development and validation of underwater mapping techniques, using the BlueROV2 Remotely Operated Vehicle (ROV). Both the ROV and the objects to be mapped are placed in a pool that is imaged via an overhead camera. In our prototype mapping application, the ROV's pose is found using extended Kalman filtering on measurements from the overhead camera, inertial, and pressure sensors; while objects are detected with a deep neural network in the ROV camera stream. Validation experiments are performed for pose estimation, detection, and mapping. The litter detection dataset and code are made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tudor Alinei-Poiana, David Rete, Davian Martinovici, Vicu-Mihalis Maer, Lucian Busoniu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRUtopia: Dream General Robots in a City at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent works have been exploring the scaling laws in the field of Embodied AI. Given the prohibitive costs of collecting real-world data, we believe the Simulation-to-Real (Sim2Real) paradigm is a crucial step for scaling the learning of embodied models. This paper introduces project GRUtopia, the first simulated interactive 3D society designed for various robots. It features several advancements: (a) The scene dataset, GRScenes, includes 100k interactive, finely annotated scenes, which can be freely combined into city-scale environments. In contrast to previous works mainly focusing on home, GRScenes covers 89 diverse scene categories, bridging the gap of service-oriented environments where general robots would be initially deployed. (b) GRResidents, a Large Language Model (LLM) driven Non-Player Character (NPC) system that is responsible for social interaction, task generation, and task assignment, thus simulating social scenarios for embodied AI applications. (c) The benchmark, GRBench, supports various robots but focuses on legged robots as primary agents and poses moderately challenging tasks involving Object Loco-Navigation, Social Loco-Navigation, and Loco-Manipulation. We hope that this work can alleviate the scarcity of high-quality data in this field and provide a more comprehensive assessment of Embodied AI research. The project is available at https://github.com/OpenRobotLab/GRUtopia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10943v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanqing Wang, Jiahe Chen, Wensi Huang, Qingwei Ben, Tai Wang, Boyu Mi, Tao Huang, Siheng Zhao, Yilun Chen, Sizhe Yang, Peizhou Cao, Wenye Yu, Zichao Ye, Jialun Li, Junfeng Long, Zirui Wang, Huiling Wang, Ying Zhao, Zhongying Tu, Yu Qiao, Dahua Lin, Jiangmiao Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified theory and statistical learning approach for traffic conflict detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study proposes a unified theory and statistical learning approach for traffic conflict detection, addressing the long-existing call for a consistent and comprehensive methodology to evaluate the collision risk emerged in road user interactions. The proposed theory assumes a context-dependent probabilistic collision risk and frames conflict detection as estimating the risk by statistical learning from observed proximities and contextual variables. Three primary tasks are integrated: representing interaction context from selected observables, inferring proximity distributions in different contexts, and applying extreme value theory to relate conflict intensity with conflict probability. As a result, this methodology is adaptable to various road users and interaction scenarios, enhancing its applicability without the need for pre-labelled conflict data. Demonstration experiments are executed using real-world trajectory data, with the unified metric trained on lane-changing interactions on German highways and applied to near-crash events from the 100-Car Naturalistic Driving Study in the U.S. The experiments demonstrate the methodology's ability to provide effective collision warnings, generalise across different datasets and traffic environments, cover a broad range of conflicts, and deliver a long-tailed distribution of conflict intensity. This study contributes to traffic safety by offering a consistent and explainable methodology for conflict detection applicable across various scenarios. Its societal implications include enhanced safety evaluations of traffic infrastructures, more effective collision warning systems for autonomous and driving assistance systems, and a deeper understanding of road user behaviour in different traffic conditions, contributing to a potential reduction in accident rates and improving overall traffic safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10959v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiru Jiao, Simeon C. Calvert, Sander van Cranenburgh, Hans van Lint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of Autonomous Driving Image Detection Based on RFAConv and Triplet Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09530v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: YOLOv8 plays a crucial role in the realm of autonomous driving, owing to its high-speed target detection, precise identification and positioning, and versatile compatibility across multiple platforms. By processing video streams or images in real-time, YOLOv8 rapidly and accurately identifies obstacles such as vehicles and pedestrians on roadways, offering essential visual data for autonomous driving systems. Moreover, YOLOv8 supports various tasks including instance segmentation, image classification, and attitude estimation, thereby providing comprehensive visual perception for autonomous driving, ultimately enhancing driving safety and efficiency. Recognizing the significance of object detection in autonomous driving scenarios and the challenges faced by existing methods, this paper proposes a holistic approach to enhance the YOLOv8 model. The study introduces two pivotal modifications: the C2f_RFAConv module and the Triplet Attention mechanism. Firstly, the proposed modifications are elaborated upon in the methodological section. The C2f_RFAConv module replaces the original module to enhance feature extraction efficiency, while the Triplet Attention mechanism enhances feature focus. Subsequently, the experimental procedure delineates the training and evaluation process, encompassing training the original YOLOv8, integrating modified modules, and assessing performance improvements using metrics and PR curves. The results demonstrate the efficacy of the modifications, with the improved YOLOv8 model exhibiting significant performance enhancements, including increased MAP values and improvements in PR curves. Lastly, the analysis section elucidates the results and attributes the performance improvements to the introduced modules. C2f_RFAConv enhances feature extraction efficiency, while Triplet Attention improves feature focus for enhanced target detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09530v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhipeng Ling, Qi Xin, Yiyu Lin, Guangze Su, Zuwei Shui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability in Reinforcement Learning: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09645v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent literature has proposed approaches that learn control policies with high performance while maintaining safety guarantees. Synthesizing Hamilton-Jacobi (HJ) reachable sets has become an effective tool for verifying safety and supervising the training of reinforcement learning-based control policies for complex, high-dimensional systems. Previously, HJ reachability was limited to verifying low-dimensional dynamical systems -- this is because the computational complexity of the dynamic programming approach it relied on grows exponentially with the number of system states. To address this limitation, in recent years, there have been methods that compute the reachability value function simultaneously with learning control policies to scale HJ reachability analysis while still maintaining a reliable estimate of the true reachable set. These HJ reachability approximations are used to improve the safety, and even reward performance, of learned control policies and can solve challenging tasks such as those with dynamic obstacles and/or with lidar-based or vision-based observations. In this survey paper, we review the recent developments in the field of HJ reachability estimation in reinforcement learning that would provide a foundational basis for further research into reliability in high-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09645v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milan Ganai, Sicun Gao, Sylvia Herbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLOVER: Context-aware Long-term Object Viewpoint- and Environment- Invariant Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09718v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many applications, robots can benefit from object-level understanding of their environments, including the ability to distinguish object instances and re-identify previously seen instances. Object re-identification is challenging across different viewpoints and in scenes with significant appearance variation arising from weather or lighting changes. Most works on object re-identification focus on specific classes; approaches that address general object re-identification require foreground segmentation and have limited consideration of challenges such as occlusions, outdoor scenes, and illumination changes. To address this problem, we introduce CODa Re-ID: an in-the-wild object re-identification dataset containing 1,037,814 observations of 557 objects of 8 classes under diverse lighting conditions and viewpoints. Further, we propose CLOVER, a representation learning method for object observations that can distinguish between static object instances. Our results show that CLOVER achieves superior performance in static object re-identification under varying lighting conditions and viewpoint changes, and can generalize to unseen instances and classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09718v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongmyeong Lee, Amanda Adkins, Joydeep Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAPiD-Seg: Range-Aware Pointwise Distance Distribution Networks for 3D LiDAR Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: 3D point clouds play a pivotal role in outdoor scene perception, especially in the context of autonomous driving. Recent advancements in 3D LiDAR segmentation often focus intensely on the spatial positioning and distribution of points for accurate segmentation. However, these methods, while robust in variable conditions, encounter challenges due to sole reliance on coordinates and point intensity, leading to poor isometric invariance and suboptimal segmentation. To tackle this challenge, our work introduces Range-Aware Pointwise Distance Distribution (RAPiD) features and the associated RAPiD-Seg architecture. Our RAPiD features exhibit rigid transformation invariance and effectively adapt to variations in point density, with a design focus on capturing the localized geometry of neighboring structures. They utilize inherent LiDAR isotropic radiation and semantic categorization for enhanced local representation and computational efficiency, while incorporating a 4D distance metric that integrates geometric and surface material reflectivity for improved semantic segmentation. To effectively embed high-dimensional RAPiD features, we propose a double-nested autoencoder structure with a novel class-aware embedding objective to encode high-dimensional features into manageable voxel-wise embeddings. Additionally, we propose RAPiD-Seg which incorporates a channel-wise attention fusion and two effective RAPiD-Seg variants, further optimizing the embedding for enhanced performance and generalization. Our method outperforms contemporary LiDAR segmentation work in terms of mIoU on SemanticKITTI (76.1) and nuScenes (83.6) datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10159v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Conf. Comput. Vis. (ECCV 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Li Li, Hubert P. H. Shum, Toby P. Breckon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Reward Shaping for Multi-Agent Pathfinding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10403v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The primary objective of Multi-Agent Pathfinding (MAPF) is to plan efficient and conflict-free paths for all agents. Traditional multi-agent path planning algorithms struggle to achieve efficient distributed path planning for multiple agents. In contrast, Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning (MARL) has been demonstrated as an effective approach to achieve this objective. By modeling the MAPF problem as a MARL problem, agents can achieve efficient path planning and collision avoidance through distributed strategies under partial observation. However, MARL strategies often lack cooperation among agents due to the absence of global information, which subsequently leads to reduced MAPF efficiency. To address this challenge, this letter introduces a unique reward shaping technique based on Independent Q-Learning (IQL). The aim of this method is to evaluate the influence of one agent on its neighbors and integrate such an interaction into the reward function, leading to active cooperation among agents. This reward shaping method facilitates cooperation among agents while operating in a distributed manner. The proposed approach has been evaluated through experiments across various scenarios with different scales and agent counts. The results are compared with those from other state-of-the-art (SOTA) planners. The evidence suggests that the approach proposed in this letter parallels other planners in numerous aspects, and outperforms them in scenarios featuring a large number of agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10403v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Song, Ronghao Zheng, Senlin Zhang, Meiqin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion-prior Contrast Maximization for Dense Continuous-Time Motion Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Current optical flow and point-tracking methods rely heavily on synthetic datasets. Event cameras are novel vision sensors with advantages in challenging visual conditions, but state-of-the-art frame-based methods cannot be easily adapted to event data due to the limitations of current event simulators. We introduce a novel self-supervised loss combining the Contrast Maximization framework with a non-linear motion prior in the form of pixel-level trajectories and propose an efficient solution to solve the high-dimensional assignment problem between non-linear trajectories and events. Their effectiveness is demonstrated in two scenarios: In dense continuous-time motion estimation, our method improves the zero-shot performance of a synthetically trained model on the real-world dataset EVIMO2 by 29%. In optical flow estimation, our method elevates a simple UNet to achieve state-of-the-art performance among self-supervised methods on the DSEC optical flow benchmark. Our code is available at https://github.com/tub-rip/MotionPriorCMax.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10802v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), Milan, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Friedhelm Hamann, Ziyun Wang, Ioannis Asmanis, Kenneth Chaney, Guillermo Gallego, Kostas Daniilidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory Tracking for Unmanned Aerial Vehicles in 3D Spaces under Motion Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10837v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article presents a three-dimensional nonlinear trajectory tracking control strategy for unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) in the presence of spatial constraints. As opposed to many existing control strategies, which do not consider spatial constraints, the proposed strategy considers spatial constraints on each degree of freedom movement of the UAV. Such consideration makes the design appealing for many practical applications, such as pipeline inspection, boundary tracking, etc. The proposed design accounts for the limited information about the inertia matrix, thereby affirming its inherent robustness against unmodeled dynamics and other imperfections. We rigorously show that the UAV will converge to its desired path by maintaining bounded position, orientation, and linear and angular speeds. Finally, we demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed strategy through various numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10837v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurabh Kumar, Shashi Ranjan Kumar, Abhinav Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Reinforcement Learning using Distributional Representation for Trustworthy Quadrotor UAV Tracking Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.11694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.11694v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simultaneously accurate and reliable tracking control for quadrotors in complex dynamic environments is challenging. As aerodynamics derived from drag forces and moment variations are chaotic and difficult to precisely identify, most current quadrotor tracking systems treat them as simple `disturbances' in conventional control approaches. We propose a novel, interpretable trajectory tracker integrating a Distributional Reinforcement Learning disturbance estimator for unknown aerodynamic effects with a Stochastic Model Predictive Controller (SMPC). The proposed estimator `Constrained Distributional Reinforced disturbance estimator' (ConsDRED) accurately identifies uncertainties between true and estimated values of aerodynamic effects. Simplified Affine Disturbance Feedback is used for control parameterization to guarantee convexity, which we then integrate with a SMPC. We theoretically guarantee that ConsDRED achieves at least an optimal global convergence rate and a certain sublinear rate if constraints are violated with an error decreases as the width and the layer of neural network increase. To demonstrate practicality, we show convergent training in simulation and real-world experiments, and empirically verify that ConsDRED is less sensitive to hyperparameter settings compared with canonical constrained RL approaches. We demonstrate our system improves accumulative tracking errors by at least 70% compared with the recent art. Importantly, the proposed framework, ConsDRED-SMPC, balances the tradeoff between pursuing high performance and obeying conservative constraints for practical implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.11694v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanran Wang, David Boyle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HACMan: Learning Hybrid Actor-Critic Maps for 6D Non-Prehensile Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03942v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Manipulating objects without grasping them is an essential component of human dexterity, referred to as non-prehensile manipulation. Non-prehensile manipulation may enable more complex interactions with the objects, but also presents challenges in reasoning about gripper-object interactions. In this work, we introduce Hybrid Actor-Critic Maps for Manipulation (HACMan), a reinforcement learning approach for 6D non-prehensile manipulation of objects using point cloud observations. HACMan proposes a temporally-abstracted and spatially-grounded object-centric action representation that consists of selecting a contact location from the object point cloud and a set of motion parameters describing how the robot will move after making contact. We modify an existing off-policy RL algorithm to learn in this hybrid discrete-continuous action representation. We evaluate HACMan on a 6D object pose alignment task in both simulation and in the real world. On the hardest version of our task, with randomized initial poses, randomized 6D goals, and diverse object categories, our policy demonstrates strong generalization to unseen object categories without a performance drop, achieving an 89% success rate on unseen objects in simulation and 50% success rate with zero-shot transfer in the real world. Compared to alternative action representations, HACMan achieves a success rate more than three times higher than the best baseline. With zero-shot sim2real transfer, our policy can successfully manipulate unseen objects in the real world for challenging non-planar goals, using dynamic and contact-rich non-prehensile skills. Videos can be found on the project website: https://hacman-2023.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03942v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxuan Zhou, Bowen Jiang, Fan Yang, Chris Paxton, David Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Motion Planning as Gaussian Variational Inference: Theory and Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel formulation for motion planning under uncertainties based on variational inference where the optimal motion plan is modeled as a posterior distribution. We propose a Gaussian variational inference-based framework, termed Gaussian Variational Inference Motion Planning (GVI-MP), to approximate this posterior by a Gaussian distribution over the trajectories. We show that the GVI-MP framework is dual to a special class of stochastic control problems and brings robustness into the decision-making in motion planning. We develop two algorithms to numerically solve this variational inference and the equivalent control formulations for motion planning. The first algorithm uses a natural gradient paradigm to iteratively update a Gaussian proposal distribution on the sparse motion planning factor graph. We propose a second algorithm, the Proximal Covariance Steering Motion Planner (PCS-MP), to solve the same inference problem in its stochastic control form with an additional terminal constraint. We leverage a proximal gradient paradigm where, at each iteration, we quadratically approximate nonlinear state costs and solve a linear covariance steering problem in closed form. The efficacy of the proposed algorithms is demonstrated through extensive experiments on various robot models. An implementation is provided in https://github.com/hzyu17/VIMP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14985v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongzhe Yu, Yongxin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Reality Environment and High-Dimensional Continuification Control for Swarm Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01573v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many new methodologies for the control of large-scale multi-agent systems are based on macroscopic representations of the emerging system dynamics, in the form of continuum approximations of large ensembles. These techniques, that are developed in the limit case of an infinite number of agents, are usually validated only through numerical simulations. In this paper, we introduce a mixed reality set-up for testing swarm robotics techniques, focusing on the macroscopic collective motion of robotic swarms. This hybrid apparatus combines both real differential drive robots and virtual agents to create a heterogeneous swarm of tunable size. We also extend continuification-based control methods for swarms to higher dimensions, and assess experimentally their validity in the new platform. Our study demonstrates the effectiveness of the platform for conducting large-scale swarm robotics experiments, and it contributes new theoretical insights into control algorithms exploiting continuification approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01573v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gian Carlo Maffettone, Lorenzo Liguori, Eduardo Palermo, Mario di Bernardo, Maurizio Porfiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do we learn from a large-scale study of pre-trained visual representations in sim and real environments?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02219v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a large empirical investigation on the use of pre-trained visual representations (PVRs) for training downstream policies that execute real-world tasks. Our study involves five different PVRs, each trained for five distinct manipulation or indoor navigation tasks. We performed this evaluation using three different robots and two different policy learning paradigms. From this effort, we can arrive at three insights: 1) the performance trends of PVRs in the simulation are generally indicative of their trends in the real world, 2) the use of PVRs enables a first-of-its-kind result with indoor ImageNav (zero-shot transfer to a held-out scene in the real world), and 3) the benefits from variations in PVRs, primarily data-augmentation and fine-tuning, also transfer to the real-world performance. See project website for additional details and visuals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02219v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sneha Silwal, Karmesh Yadav, Tingfan Wu, Jay Vakil, Arjun Majumdar, Sergio Arnaud, Claire Chen, Vincent-Pierre Berges, Dhruv Batra, Aravind Rajeswaran, Mrinal Kalakrishnan, Franziska Meier, Oleksandr Maksymets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning in a Safety-Embedded MDP with Trajectory Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Safe Reinforcement Learning (RL) plays an important role in applying RL algorithms to safety-critical real-world applications, addressing the trade-off between maximizing rewards and adhering to safety constraints. This work introduces a novel approach that combines RL with trajectory optimization to manage this trade-off effectively. Our approach embeds safety constraints within the action space of a modified Markov Decision Process (MDP). The RL agent produces a sequence of actions that are transformed into safe trajectories by a trajectory optimizer, thereby effectively ensuring safety and increasing training stability. This novel approach excels in its performance on challenging Safety Gym tasks, achieving significantly higher rewards and near-zero safety violations during inference. The method's real-world applicability is demonstrated through a safe and effective deployment in a real robot task of box-pushing around obstacles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06903v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Yang, Wenxuan Zhou, Zuxin Liu, Ding Zhao, David Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-Aware Planning for Heterogeneous Robot Teams using Dynamic Topological Graphs and Mixed-Integer Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multi-robot planning and coordination in uncertain environments is a fundamental computational challenge, since the belief space increases exponentially with the number of robots. In this paper, we address the problem of planning in uncertain environments with a heterogeneous robot team comprised of fast scout vehicles for information gathering and more risk-averse carrier robots from which the scout vehicles are deployed. To overcome the computational challenges associated with multi-robot motion planning in the presence of environmental uncertainty, we represent the environment and operational scenario using a topological graph, where the edge weight distributions vary with the state of the robot team on the graph. While this belief space representation still scales exponentially with the number of robots, we formulate a computationally efficient mixed-integer program which is capable of generating optimal multi-robot plans in seconds. We evaluate our approach in a representative scenario where the robot team must move through an environment while minimizing detection by observers in positions that are uncertain to the robot team. We demonstrate that our approach is sufficiently computationally tractable for real-time re-planning in changing environments, can improve performance in the presence of imperfect information, and can be adjusted to accommodate different risk profiles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08396v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cora A. Dimmig, Kevin C. Wolfe, Marin Kobilarov, Joseph Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Aquatic Soft Robots with Elastic Instability Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14119v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sinusoidal undulation has long been considered the most successful swimming pattern for fish and bionic aquatic robots [1]. However, a swimming pattern generated by the hair clip mechanism (HCM, part iii, Figure 1A) [2]~[5] may challenge this knowledge. HCM is an in-plane prestressed bi-stable mechanism that stores elastic energy and releases the stored energy quickly via its snap-through buckling. When used for fish robots, the HCM functions as the fish body and creates unique swimming patterns that we term HCM undulation. With the same energy consumption [3], HCM fish outperforms the traditionally designed soft fish with a two-fold increase in cruising speed. We reproduce this phenomenon in a single-link simulation with Aquarium [6]. HCM undulation generates an average propulsion of 16.7 N/m, 2-3 times larger than the reference undulation (6.78 N/m), sine pattern (5.34 N/m/s), and cambering sine pattern (6.36 N/m), and achieves an efficiency close to the sine pattern. These results can aid in developing fish robots and faster swimming patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14119v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zechen Xiong, Suyu Luohong, Jeong Hun Lee, Hod Lipson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H3-Mapping: Quasi-Heterogeneous Feature Grids for Real-time Dense Mapping Using Hierarchical Hybrid Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10821v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, implicit online dense mapping methods have achieved high-quality reconstruction results, showcasing great potential in robotics, AR/VR, and digital twins applications. However, existing methods struggle with slow texture modeling which limits their real-time performance. To address these limitations, we propose a NeRF-based dense mapping method that enables faster and higher-quality reconstruction. To improve texture modeling, we introduce quasi-heterogeneous feature grids, which inherit the fast querying ability of uniform feature grids while adapting to varying levels of texture complexity. Besides, we present a gradient-aided coverage-maximizing strategy for keyframe selection that enables the selected keyframes to exhibit a closer focus on rich-textured regions and a broader scope for weak-textured areas. Experimental results demonstrate that our method surpasses existing NeRF-based approaches in texture fidelity, geometry accuracy, and time consumption. The code for our method will be available at: https://github.com/SYSU-STAR/H3-Mapping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10821v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenxing Jiang, Yiming Luo, Boyu Zhou, Shaojie Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Doppler Velocity Measurements Useful for Spinning Radar Odometry?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01537v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spinning, frequency-modulated continuous-wave (FMCW) radars with 360 degree coverage have been gaining popularity for autonomous-vehicle navigation. However, unlike 'fixed' automotive radar, commercially available spinning radar systems typically do not produce radial velocities due to the lack of repeated measurements in the same direction and the fundamental hardware setup. To make these radial velocities observable, we modified the firmware of a commercial spinning radar to use triangular frequency modulation. In this paper, we develop a novel way to use this modulation to extract radial Doppler velocity measurements from single raw radar intensity scans without any required data association. We show that these noisy, error-prone measurements contain enough information to provide good ego-velocity estimates, and incorporate these estimates into different modern odometry pipelines. We extensively evaluate the pipelines on over 110 km of driving data in progressively more geometrically challenging autonomous-driving environments. We show that Doppler velocity measurements improve odometry in well-defined geometric conditions and enable it to continue functioning even in severely geometrically degenerate environments, such as long tunnels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01537v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniil Lisus, Keenan Burnett, David J. Yoon, Richard Poulton, John Marshall, Timothy D. Barfoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained 6-DoF Grasp Generation on Complex Shapes for Improved Dual-Arm Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficiently generating grasp poses tailored to specific regions of an object is vital for various robotic manipulation tasks, especially in a dual-arm setup. This scenario presents a significant challenge due to the complex geometries involved, requiring a deep understanding of the local geometry to generate grasps efficiently on the specified constrained regions. Existing methods only explore settings involving table-top/small objects and require augmented datasets to train, limiting their performance on complex objects. We propose CGDF: Constrained Grasp Diffusion Fields, a diffusion-based grasp generative model that generalizes to objects with arbitrary geometries, as well as generates dense grasps on the target regions. CGDF uses a part-guided diffusion approach that enables it to get high sample efficiency in constrained grasping without explicitly training on massive constraint-augmented datasets. We provide qualitative and quantitative comparisons using analytical metrics and in simulation, in both unconstrained and constrained settings to show that our method can generalize to generate stable grasps on complex objects, especially useful for dual-arm manipulation settings, while existing methods struggle to do so.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04643v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Singh, Sanket Kalwar, Md Faizal Karim, Bipasha Sen, Nagamanikandan Govindan, Srinath Sridhar, K Madhava Krishna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CEAR: Comprehensive Event Camera Dataset for Rapid Perception of Agile Quadruped Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04698v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When legged robots perform agile movements, traditional RGB cameras often produce blurred images, posing a challenge for rapid perception. Event cameras have emerged as a promising solution for capturing rapid perception and coping with challenging lighting conditions thanks to their low latency, high temporal resolution, and high dynamic range. However, integrating event cameras into agile-legged robots is still largely unexplored. Notably, no dataset including event cameras has yet been developed for the context of agile quadruped robots. To bridge this gap, we introduce CEAR, a dataset comprising data from an event camera, an RGB-D camera, an IMU, a LiDAR, and joint encoders, all mounted on a dynamic quadruped, Mini Cheetah robot. This comprehensive dataset features more than 100 sequences from real-world environments, encompassing various indoor and outdoor environments, different lighting conditions, a range of robot gaits (e.g., trotting, bounding, pronking), as well as acrobatic movements like backflip. To our knowledge, this is the first event camera dataset capturing the dynamic and diverse quadruped robot motions under various setups, developed to advance research in rapid perception for quadruped robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04698v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3426373</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Robot and Automation Letters, June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shifan Zhu, Zixun Xiong, Donghyun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Cross-hand Policies for High-DOF Reaching and Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09150v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reaching-and-grasping is a fundamental skill for robotic manipulation, but existing methods usually train models on a specific gripper and cannot be reused on another gripper. In this paper, we propose a novel method that can learn a unified policy model that can be easily transferred to different dexterous grippers. Our method consists of two stages: a gripper-agnostic policy model that predicts the displacements of pre-defined key points on the gripper, and a gripper-specific adaptation model that translates these displacements into adjustments for controlling the grippers' joints. The gripper state and interactions with objects are captured at the finger level using robust geometric representations, integrated with a transformer-based network to address variations in gripper morphology and geometry. In the experiments, we evaluate our method on several dexterous grippers and diverse objects, and the result shows that our method significantly outperforms the baseline methods. Pioneering the transfer of grasp policies across dexterous grippers, our method effectively demonstrates its potential for learning generalizable and transferable manipulation skills for various robotic hands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09150v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qijin She, Shishun Zhang, Yunfan Ye, Ruizhen Hu, Kai Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating 6-D Trajectories for Omnidirectional Multirotor Aerial Vehicles in Cluttered Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As fully-actuated systems, omnidirectional multirotor aerial vehicles (OMAVs) have more flexible maneuverability and advantages in aggressive flight in cluttered environments than traditional underactuated MAVs. %Due to the high dimensionality of configuration space, making the designed trajectory generation algorithm efficient is challenging. This paper aims to achieve safe flight of OMAVs in cluttered environments. Considering existing static obstacles, an efficient optimization-based framework is proposed to generate 6-D $SE(3)$ trajectories for OMAVs. Given the kinodynamic constraints and the 3D collision-free region represented by a series of intersecting convex polyhedra, the proposed method finally generates a safe and dynamically feasible 6-D trajectory. First, we parameterize the vehicle's attitude into a free 3D vector using stereographic projection to eliminate the constraints inherent in the $SO(3)$ manifold, while the complete $SE(3)$ trajectory is represented as a 6-D polynomial in time without inherent constraints. The vehicle's shape is modeled as a cuboid attached to the body frame to achieve whole-body collision evaluation. Then, we formulate the origin trajectory generation problem as a constrained optimization problem. The original constrained problem is finally transformed into an unconstrained one that can be solved efficiently. To verify the proposed framework's performance, simulations and real-world experiments based on a tilt-rotor hexarotor aerial vehicle are carried out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10392v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peiyan Liu, Yuanzhe Shen, Yueqian Liu, Fengyu Quan, Can Wang, Haoyao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadruped robot traversing 3D complex environments with limited perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18225v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Traversing 3-D complex environments has always been a significant challenge for legged locomotion. Existing methods typically rely on external sensors such as vision and lidar to preemptively react to obstacles by acquiring environmental information. However, in scenarios like nighttime or dense forests, external sensors often fail to function properly, necessitating robots to rely on proprioceptive sensors to perceive diverse obstacles in the environment and respond promptly. This task is undeniably challenging. Our research finds that methods based on collision detection can enhance a robot's perception of environmental obstacles. In this work, we propose an end-to-end learning-based quadruped robot motion controller that relies solely on proprioceptive sensing. This controller can accurately detect, localize, and agilely respond to collisions in unknown and complex 3D environments, thereby improving the robot's traversability in complex environments. We demonstrate in both simulation and real-world experiments that our method enables quadruped robots to successfully traverse challenging obstacles in various complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18225v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Cheng, Hang Liu, Guoping Pan, Linqi Ye, Houde Liu, Bin Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passive Obstacle Aware Control to Follow Desired Velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05669v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Evaluating and updating the obstacle avoidance velocity for an autonomous robot in real-time ensures robustness against noise and disturbances. A passive damping controller can obtain the desired motion with a torque-controlled robot, which remains compliant and ensures a safe response to external perturbations. Here, we propose a novel approach for designing the passive control policy. Our algorithm complies with obstacle-free zones while transitioning to increased damping near obstacles to ensure collision avoidance. This approach ensures stability across diverse scenarios, effectively mitigating disturbances. Validation on a 7DoF robot arm demonstrates superior collision rejection capabilities compared to the baseline, underlining its practicality for real-world applications. Our obstacle-aware damping controller represents a substantial advancement in secure robot control within complex and uncertain environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05669v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Huber, Thibaud Trinca, Jean-Jacques Slotine, Aude Billard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-Modeling in Sequential Decision-Making: An Analysis through the Lens of Human-Aware AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07773v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: "Human-aware" has become a popular keyword used to describe a particular class of AI systems that are designed to work and interact with humans. While there exists a surprising level of consistency among the works that use the label human-aware, the term itself mostly remains poorly understood. In this work, we retroactively try to provide an account of what constitutes a human-aware AI system. We see that human-aware AI is a design oriented paradigm, one that focuses on the need for modeling the humans it may interact with. Additionally, we see that this paradigm offers us intuitive dimensions to understand and categorize the kinds of interactions these systems might have with humans. We show the pedagogical value of these dimensions by using them as a tool to understand and review the current landscape of work related to human-AI systems that purport some form of human modeling. To fit the scope of a workshop paper, we specifically narrowed our review to papers that deal with sequential decision-making and were published in a major AI conference in the last three years. Our analysis helps identify the space of potential research problems that are currently being overlooked. We perform additional analysis on the degree to which these works make explicit reference to results from social science and whether they actually perform user-studies to validate their systems. We also provide an accounting of the various AI methods used by these works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07773v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Tulli, Stylianos Loukas Vasileiou, Sarath Sreedharan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auto-Multilift: Distributed Learning and Control for Cooperative Load Transportation With Quadrotors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Designing motion control and planning algorithms for multilift systems remains challenging due to the complexities of dynamics, collision avoidance, actuator limits, and scalability. Existing methods that use optimization and distributed techniques effectively address these constraints and scalability issues. However, they often require substantial manual tuning, leading to suboptimal performance. This paper proposes Auto-Multilift, a novel framework that automates the tuning of model predictive controllers (MPCs) for multilift systems. We model the MPC cost functions with deep neural networks (DNNs), enabling fast online adaptation to various scenarios. We develop a distributed policy gradient algorithm to train these DNNs efficiently in a closed-loop manner. Central to our algorithm is distributed sensitivity propagation, which is built on fully exploiting the unique dynamic couplings within the multilift system. It parallelizes gradient computation across quadrotors and focuses on actual system state sensitivities relative to key MPC parameters. Extensive simulations demonstrate favorable scalability to a large number of quadrotors. Our method outperforms a state-of-the-art open-loop MPC tuning approach by effectively learning adaptive MPCs from trajectory tracking errors. It also excels in learning an adaptive reference for reconfiguring the system when traversing multiple narrow slots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04858v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingheng Wang, Rui Huang, Kuankuan Sima, Lin Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboGolf: Mastering Real-World Minigolf with a Reflective Multi-Modality Vision-Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10157v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Minigolf, a game with countless court layouts, and complex ball motion, constitutes a compelling real-world testbed for the study of embodied intelligence. As it not only challenges spatial and kinodynamic reasoning but also requires reflective and corrective capacities to address erroneously designed courses. We introduce RoboGolf, a VLM-based framework that perceives dual-camera visual inputs with nested VLM-empowered closed-loop control and reflective equilibrium loop. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of RoboGolf on challenging minigolf courts including those that are impossible to finish.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10157v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hantao Zhou, Tianying Ji, Lukas Sommerhalder, Michael Goerner, Norman Hendrich, Jianwei Zhang, Fuchun Sun, Huazhe Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transferable Tactile Transformers for Representation Learning Across Diverse Sensors and Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13640v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents T3: Transferable Tactile Transformers, a framework for tactile representation learning that scales across multi-sensors and multi-tasks. T3 is designed to overcome the contemporary issue that camera-based tactile sensing is extremely heterogeneous, i.e. sensors are built into different form factors, and existing datasets were collected for disparate tasks. T3 captures the shared latent information across different sensor-task pairings by constructing a shared trunk transformer with sensor-specific encoders and task-specific decoders. The pre-training of T3 utilizes a novel Foundation Tactile (FoTa) dataset, which is aggregated from several open-sourced datasets and it contains over 3 million data points gathered from 13 sensors and 11 tasks. FoTa is the largest and most diverse dataset in tactile sensing to date and it is made publicly available in a unified format. Across various sensors and tasks, experiments show that T3 pre-trained with FoTa achieved zero-shot transferability in certain sensor-task pairings, can be further fine-tuned with small amounts of domain-specific data, and its performance scales with bigger network sizes. T3 is also effective as a tactile encoder for long horizon contact-rich manipulation. Results from sub-millimeter multi-pin electronics insertion tasks show that T3 achieved a task success rate 25% higher than that of policies trained with tactile encoders trained from scratch, or 53% higher than without tactile sensing. Data, code, and model checkpoints are open-sourced at https://t3.alanz.info.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13640v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialiang Zhao, Yuxiang Ma, Lirui Wang, Edward H. Adelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Open-World Grasping with Large Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18722v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability to grasp objects in-the-wild from open-ended language instructions constitutes a fundamental challenge in robotics. An open-world grasping system should be able to combine high-level contextual with low-level physical-geometric reasoning in order to be applicable in arbitrary scenarios. Recent works exploit the web-scale knowledge inherent in large language models (LLMs) to plan and reason in robotic context, but rely on external vision and action models to ground such knowledge into the environment and parameterize actuation. This setup suffers from two major bottlenecks: a) the LLM's reasoning capacity is constrained by the quality of visual grounding, and b) LLMs do not contain low-level spatial understanding of the world, which is essential for grasping in contact-rich scenarios. In this work we demonstrate that modern vision-language models (VLMs) are capable of tackling such limitations, as they are implicitly grounded and can jointly reason about semantics and geometry. We propose OWG, an open-world grasping pipeline that combines VLMs with segmentation and grasp synthesis models to unlock grounded world understanding in three stages: open-ended referring segmentation, grounded grasp planning and grasp ranking via contact reasoning, all of which can be applied zero-shot via suitable visual prompting mechanisms. We conduct extensive evaluation in cluttered indoor scene datasets to showcase OWG's robustness in grounding from open-ended language, as well as open-world robotic grasping experiments in both simulation and hardware that demonstrate superior performance compared to previous supervised and zero-shot LLM-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18722v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Tziafas, Hamidreza Kasaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifelong Robot Library Learning: Bootstrapping Composable and Generalizable Skills for Embodied Control with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18746v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have emerged as a new paradigm for embodied reasoning and control, most recently by generating robot policy code that utilizes a custom library of vision and control primitive skills. However, prior arts fix their skills library and steer the LLM with carefully hand-crafted prompt engineering, limiting the agent to a stationary range of addressable tasks. In this work, we introduce LRLL, an LLM-based lifelong learning agent that continuously grows the robot skill library to tackle manipulation tasks of ever-growing complexity. LRLL achieves this with four novel contributions: 1) a soft memory module that allows dynamic storage and retrieval of past experiences to serve as context, 2) a self-guided exploration policy that proposes new tasks in simulation, 3) a skill abstractor that distills recent experiences into new library skills, and 4) a lifelong learning algorithm for enabling human users to bootstrap new skills with minimal online interaction. LRLL continuously transfers knowledge from the memory to the library, building composable, general and interpretable policies, while bypassing gradient-based optimization, thus relieving the learner from catastrophic forgetting. Empirical evaluation in a simulated tabletop environment shows that LRLL outperforms end-to-end and vanilla LLM approaches in the lifelong setup while learning skills that are transferable to the real world. Project material will become available at the webpage https://gtziafas.github.io/LRLL_project.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18746v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Tziafas, Hamidreza Kasaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Policy Learning for Multi-UAV Collision Avoidance with Causal Feature Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04056v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In unseen and complex outdoor environments, collision avoidance navigation for unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) swarms presents a challenging problem. It requires UAVs to navigate through various obstacles and complex backgrounds. Existing collision avoidance navigation methods based on deep reinforcement learning show promising performance but suffer from poor generalization abilities, resulting in performance degradation in unseen environments. To address this issue, we investigate the cause of weak generalization ability in DRL and propose a novel causal feature selection module. This module can be integrated into the policy network and effectively filters out non-causal factors in representations, thereby reducing the influence of spurious correlations between non-causal factors and action predictions. Experimental results demonstrate that our proposed method can achieve robust navigation performance and effective collision avoidance especially in scenarios with unseen backgrounds and obstacles, which significantly outperforms existing state-of-the-art algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04056v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiafan Zhuang, Gaofei Han, Zihao Xia, Boxi Wang, Wenji Li, Dongliang Wang, Zhifeng Hao, Ruichu Cai, Zhun Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision Avoidance for Multiple UAVs in Unknown Scenarios with Causal Representation Disentanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04064v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deep reinforcement learning (DRL) has achieved remarkable progress in online path planning tasks for multi-UAV systems. However, existing DRL-based methods often suffer from performance degradation when tackling unseen scenarios, since the non-causal factors in visual representations adversely affect policy learning. To address this issue, we propose a novel representation learning approach, \ie, causal representation disentanglement, which can identify the causal and non-causal factors in representations. After that, we only pass causal factors for subsequent policy learning and thus explicitly eliminate the influence of non-causal factors, which effectively improves the generalization ability of DRL models. Experimental results show that our proposed method can achieve robust navigation performance and effective collision avoidance especially in unseen scenarios, which significantly outperforms existing SOTA algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04064v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiafan Zhuang, Zihao Xia, Gaofei Han, Boxi Wang, Wenji Li, Dongliang Wang, Zhifeng Hao, Ruichu Cai, Zhun Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Neurosymbolic Approach to Adaptive Feature Extraction in SLAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06889v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomous robots, autonomous vehicles, and humans wearing mixed-reality headsets require accurate and reliable tracking services for safety-critical applications in dynamically changing real-world environments. However, the existing tracking approaches, such as Simultaneous Localization and Mapping (SLAM), do not adapt well to environmental changes and boundary conditions despite extensive manual tuning. On the other hand, while deep learning-based approaches can better adapt to environmental changes, they typically demand substantial data for training and often lack flexibility in adapting to new domains. To solve this problem, we propose leveraging the neurosymbolic program synthesis approach to construct adaptable SLAM pipelines that integrate the domain knowledge from traditional SLAM approaches while leveraging data to learn complex relationships. While the approach can synthesize end-to-end SLAM pipelines, we focus on synthesizing the feature extraction module. We first devise a domain-specific language (DSL) that can encapsulate domain knowledge on the important attributes for feature extraction and the real-world performance of various feature extractors. Our neurosymbolic architecture then undertakes adaptive feature extraction, optimizing parameters via learning while employing symbolic reasoning to select the most suitable feature extractor. Our evaluations demonstrate that our approach, neurosymbolic Feature EXtraction (nFEX), yields higher-quality features. It also reduces the pose error observed for the state-of-the-art baseline feature extractors ORB and SIFT by up to 90% and up to 66%, respectively, thereby enhancing the system's efficiency and adaptability to novel environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06889v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yasra Chandio, Momin A. Khan, Khotso Selialia, Luis Garcia, Joseph DeGol, Fatima M. Anwar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision and Tactile Robotic System to Grasp Litter in Outdoor Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08575v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The accumulation of litter is increasing in many places and is consequently becoming a problem that must be dealt with. In this paper, we present a manipulator robotic system to collect litter in outdoor environments. This system has three functionalities. Firstly, it uses colour images to detect and recognise litter comprising different materials. Secondly, depth data are combined with pixels of waste objects to compute a 3D location and segment three-dimensional point clouds of the litter items in the scene. The grasp in 3 Degrees of Freedom (DoFs) is then estimated for a robot arm with a gripper for the segmented cloud of each instance of waste. Finally, two tactile-based algorithms are implemented and then employed in order to provide the gripper with a sense of touch. This work uses two low-cost visual-based tactile sensors at the fingertips. One of them addresses the detection of contact (which is obtained from tactile images) between the gripper and solid waste, while another has been designed to detect slippage in order to prevent the objects grasped from falling. Our proposal was successfully tested by carrying out extensive experimentation with different objects varying in size, texture, geometry and materials in different outdoor environments (a tiled pavement, a surface of stone/soil, and grass). Our system achieved an average score of 94% for the detection and Collection Success Rate (CSR) as regards its overall performance, and of 80% for the collection of items of litter at the first attempt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08575v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10846-023-01930-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Intelligent &amp; Robotic Systems (JINT), Volume 109, Article number 36, 2023, Pages 1-24</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio de Loyola P\'aez-Ubieta, Julio Casta\~no-Amor\'os, Santiago T. Puente, Pablo Gil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robotic Control via Embodied Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A key limitation of learned robot control policies is their inability to generalize outside their training data. Recent works on vision-language-action models (VLAs) have shown that the use of large, internet pre-trained vision-language models as the backbone of learned robot policies can substantially improve their robustness and generalization ability. Yet, one of the most exciting capabilities of large vision-language models in other domains is their ability to reason iteratively through complex problems. Can that same capability be brought into robotics to allow policies to improve performance by reasoning about a given task before acting? Naive use of "chain-of-thought" (CoT) style prompting is significantly less effective with standard VLAs because of the relatively simple training examples that are available to them. Additionally, purely semantic reasoning about sub-tasks, as is common in regular CoT, is insufficient for robot policies that need to ground their reasoning in sensory observations and the robot state. To this end, we introduce Embodied Chain-of-Thought Reasoning (ECoT) for VLAs, in which we train VLAs to perform multiple steps of reasoning about plans, sub-tasks, motions, and visually grounded features like object bounding boxes and end effector positions, before predicting the robot action. We design a scalable pipeline for generating synthetic training data for ECoT on large robot datasets. We demonstrate, that ECoT increases the absolute success rate of OpenVLA, the current strongest open-source VLA policy, by 28% across challenging generalization tasks, without any additional robot training data. Additionally, ECoT makes it easier for humans to interpret a policy's failures and correct its behavior using natural language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08693v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Zawalski, William Chen, Karl Pertsch, Oier Mees, Chelsea Finn, Sergey Levine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tightly-Coupled LiDAR-IMU-Wheel Odometry with an Online Neural Kinematic Model Learning via Factor Graph Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Environments lacking geometric features (e.g., tunnels and long straight corridors) are challenging for LiDAR-based odometry algorithms because LiDAR point clouds degenerate in such environments. For wheeled robots, a wheel kinematic model (i.e., wheel odometry) can improve the reliability of the odometry estimation. However, the kinematic model suffers from complex motions (e.g., wheel slippage, lateral movement) in the case of skid-steering robots particularly because this robot model rotates by skidding its wheels. Furthermore, these errors change nonlinearly when the wheel slippage is large (e.g., drifting) and are subject to terrain-dependent parameters. To simultaneously tackle point cloud degeneration and the kinematic model errors, we developed a LiDAR-IMU-wheel odometry algorithm incorporating online training of a neural network that learns the kinematic model of wheeled robots with nonlinearity. We propose to train the neural network online on a factor graph along with robot states, allowing the learning-based kinematic model to adapt to the current terrain condition. The proposed method jointly solves online training of the neural network and LiDARIMUwheel odometry on a unified factor graph to retain the consistency of all those constraints. Through experiments, we first verified that the proposed network adapted to a changing environment, resulting in an accurate odometry estimation across different environments.We then confirmed that the proposed odometry estimation algorithm was robust against point cloud degeneration and nonlinearity (e.g., large wheel slippage by drifting) of the kinematic model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08907v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taku Okawara, Kenji Koide, Shuji Oishi, Masashi Yokozuka, Atsuhiko Banno, Kentaro Uno, Kazuya Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proto-CLIP: Vision-Language Prototypical Network for Few-Shot Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03073v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel framework for few-shot learning by leveraging large-scale vision-language models such as CLIP. Motivated by unimodal prototypical networks for few-shot learning, we introduce Proto-CLIP which utilizes image prototypes and text prototypes for few-shot learning. Specifically, Proto-CLIP adapts the image and text encoder embeddings from CLIP in a joint fashion using few-shot examples. The embeddings from the two encoders are used to compute the respective prototypes of image classes for classification. During adaptation, we propose aligning the image and text prototypes of the corresponding classes. Such alignment is beneficial for few-shot classification due to the reinforced contributions from both types of prototypes. Proto-CLIP has both training-free and fine-tuned variants. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our method by conducting experiments on benchmark datasets for few-shot learning, as well as in the real world for robot perception. The project page is available at https://irvlutd.github.io/Proto-CLIP</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03073v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jishnu Jaykumar P, Kamalesh Palanisamy, Yu-Wei Chao, Xinya Du, Yu Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robotic Manipulation Datasets for Offline Compositional Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07091v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Offline reinforcement learning (RL) is a promising direction that allows RL agents to pre-train on large datasets, avoiding the recurrence of expensive data collection. To advance the field, it is crucial to generate large-scale datasets. Compositional RL is particularly appealing for generating such large datasets, since 1)~it permits creating many tasks from few components, 2)~the task structure may enable trained agents to solve new tasks by combining relevant learned components, and 3)~the compositional dimensions provide a notion of task relatedness. This paper provides four offline RL datasets for simulated robotic manipulation created using the $256$ tasks from CompoSuite [Mendez at al., 2022a]. Each dataset is collected from an agent with a different degree of performance, and consists of $256$ million transitions. We provide training and evaluation settings for assessing an agent's ability to learn compositional task policies. Our benchmarking experiments show that current offline RL methods can learn the training tasks to some extent and that compositional methods outperform non-compositional methods. Yet current methods are unable to extract the compositional structure to generalize to unseen tasks, highlighting a need for future research in offline compositional RL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07091v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcel Hussing, Jorge A. Mendez, Anisha Singrodia, Cassandra Kent, Eric Eaton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PCR-99: A Practical Method for Point Cloud Registration with 99% Outliers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16598v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a robust method for point cloud registration that can handle both unknown scales and extreme outlier ratios. Our method, dubbed PCR-99, uses a deterministic 3-point sampling approach with two novel mechanisms that significantly boost the speed: (1) an improved ordering of the samples based on pairwise scale consistency, prioritizing the point correspondences that are more likely to be inliers, and (2) an efficient outlier rejection scheme based on triplet scale consistency, prescreening bad samples and reducing the number of hypotheses to be tested. Our evaluation shows that, up to 98% outlier ratio, the proposed method achieves comparable performance to the state of the art. At 99% outlier ratio, however, it outperforms the state of the art for both known-scale and unknown-scale problems. Especially for the latter, we observe a clear superiority in terms of robustness and speed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16598v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seong Hun Lee, Javier Civera, Patrick Vandewalle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set-membership target search and tracking within an unknown cluttered area using cooperating UAVs equipped with vision systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15113v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of target search and tracking using a fleet of cooperating UAVs evolving in some unknown region of interest containing an a priori unknown number of moving ground targets. Each drone is equipped with an embedded Computer Vision System (CVS), providing an image with labeled pixels and a depth map of the observed part of its environment. Moreover, a box containing the corresponding pixels in the image frame is available when a UAV identifies a target. Hypotheses regarding information provided by the pixel classification, depth map construction, and target identification algorithms are proposed to allow its exploitation by set-membership approaches. A set-membership target location estimator is developed using the information provided by the CVS. Each UAV evaluates sets guaranteed to contain the location of the identified targets and a set possibly containing the locations of targets still to be identified. Then, each UAV uses these sets to search and track targets cooperatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15113v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Zagar, Luc Meyer, Michel Kieffer, H\'el\`eene Piet-Lahanier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Advantage-Guided Policy Regularization for Offline Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19909v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In offline reinforcement learning, the challenge of out-of-distribution (OOD) is pronounced. To address this, existing methods often constrain the learned policy through policy regularization. However, these methods often suffer from the issue of unnecessary conservativeness, hampering policy improvement. This occurs due to the indiscriminate use of all actions from the behavior policy that generates the offline dataset as constraints. The problem becomes particularly noticeable when the quality of the dataset is suboptimal. Thus, we propose Adaptive Advantage-guided Policy Regularization (A2PR), obtaining high-advantage actions from an augmented behavior policy combined with VAE to guide the learned policy. A2PR can select high-advantage actions that differ from those present in the dataset, while still effectively maintaining conservatism from OOD actions. This is achieved by harnessing the VAE capacity to generate samples matching the distribution of the data points. We theoretically prove that the improvement of the behavior policy is guaranteed. Besides, it effectively mitigates value overestimation with a bounded performance gap. Empirically, we conduct a series of experiments on the D4RL benchmark, where A2PR demonstrates state-of-the-art performance. Furthermore, experimental results on additional suboptimal mixed datasets reveal that A2PR exhibits superior performance. Code is available at https://github.com/ltlhuuu/A2PR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19909v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tenglong Liu, Yang Li, Yixing Lan, Hao Gao, Wei Pan, Xin Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Feature Distillation with Object-Centric Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18742v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Grounding natural language to the physical world is a ubiquitous topic with a wide range of applications in computer vision and robotics. Recently, 2D vision-language models such as CLIP have been widely popularized, due to their impressive capabilities for open-vocabulary grounding in 2D images. Recent works aim to elevate 2D CLIP features to 3D via feature distillation, but either learn neural fields that are scene-specific and hence lack generalization, or focus on indoor room scan data that require access to multiple camera views, which is not practical in robot manipulation scenarios. Additionally, related methods typically fuse features at pixel-level and assume that all camera views are equally informative. In this work, we show that this approach leads to sub-optimal 3D features, both in terms of grounding accuracy, as well as segmentation crispness. To alleviate this, we propose a multi-view feature fusion strategy that employs object-centric priors to eliminate uninformative views based on semantic information, and fuse features at object-level via instance segmentation masks. To distill our object-centric 3D features, we generate a large-scale synthetic multi-view dataset of cluttered tabletop scenes, spawning 15k scenes from over 3300 unique object instances, which we make publicly available. We show that our method reconstructs 3D CLIP features with improved grounding capacity and spatial consistency, while doing so from single-view RGB-D, thus departing from the assumption of multiple camera views at test time. Finally, we show that our approach can generalize to novel tabletop domains and be re-purposed for 3D instance segmentation without fine-tuning, and demonstrate its utility for language-guided robotic grasping in clutter</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18742v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Tziafas, Yucheng Xu, Zhibin Li, Hamidreza Kasaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Backstepping and Non-singular Sliding Mode Control for Quadrotor UAVs with Unknown Time-varying Uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07175v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel quaternion-based nonsingular control system for underactuated vertical-take-off and landing (VTOL) Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs). Position and attitude tracking is challenging regarding singularity and accuracy. Quaternion-based Adaptive Backstepping Control (QABC) is developed to tackle the underactuated issues of UAV control systems in a cascaded way. Leveraging the virtual control (auxiliary control) developed in the QABC, desired attitude components and required thrust are produced. Afterwards, we propose Quaternion-based Sliding Mode Control (QASMC) to enhance the stability and mitigate chattering issues. The sliding surface is modified to avoid singularity compared to conventional SMC. To improve the robustness of controllers, the control parameters are updated using adaptation laws. Furthermore, the asymptotic stability of translational and rotational dynamics is guaranteed by utilizing Lyapunov stability and Barbalet Lemma. Finally, the comprehensive comparison results are provided to verify the effectiveness of the proposed controllers in the presence of unknown time-varying parameter uncertainties and significant initial errors. Keywords: Non-singular Sliding Mode Control, Adaptive Backstepping Control, Unit-quaternion, Drones, Unmanned Aerial Vehicles, Asymptotic Stability, Position and Orientation Control</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07175v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arezo Shevidi, Hashim A. Hashim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
