<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 02:27:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Learning-based Detection of GPS Spoofing Attack for Quadrotors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Safety-critical cyber-physical systems (CPS), such as quadrotor UAVs, are particularly prone to cyber attacks, which can result in significant consequences if not detected promptly and accurately. During outdoor operations, the nonlinear dynamics of UAV systems, combined with non-Gaussian noise, pose challenges to the effectiveness of conventional statistical and machine learning methods. To overcome these limitations, we present QUADFormer, an advanced attack detection framework for quadrotor UAVs leveraging a transformer-based architecture. This framework features a residue generator that produces sequences sensitive to anomalies, which are then analyzed by the transformer to capture statistical patterns for detection and classification. Furthermore, an alert mechanism ensures UAVs can operate safely even when under attack. Extensive simulations and experimental evaluations highlight that QUADFormer outperforms existing state-of-the-art techniques in detection accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07597v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengyu Wang, Zhaohua Yang, Jialu Li, Ling Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Contact Grasping of Soft Tissue with Complex Geometry using a Vortex Gripper</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Soft tissue manipulation is an integral aspect of most surgical procedures; however, the vast majority of surgical graspers used today are made of hard materials, such as metals or hard plastics. Furthermore, these graspers predominately function by pinching tissue between two hard objects as a method for tissue manipulation. As such, the potential to apply too much force during contact, and thus damage tissue, is inherently high. As an alternative approach, gaspers developed using a pneumatic vortex could potentially levitate soft tissue, enabling manipulation with low or even no contact force. In this paper, we present the design and well as a full factorial study of the force characteristics of the vortex gripper grasping soft surfaces with four common shapes, with convex and concave curvature, and ranging over 10 different radii of curvature, for a total of 40 unique surfaces. By changing the parameters of the nozzle elements in the design of the gripper, it was possible to investigate the influence of the mass flow parameters of the vortex gripper on the lifting force for all of these different soft surfaces. An $\pmb{ex}$ $\pmb{vivo}$ experiment was conducted on grasping biological tissues and soft balls of various shapes to show the advantages and disadvantages of the proposed technology. The obtained results allowed us to find limitations in the use of vortex technology and the following stages of its improvement for medical use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07832v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Mykhailyshyn, Ann Majewicz Fey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Guide Dog: Egocentric Path Prediction on Smartphone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces AI Guide Dog (AIGD), a lightweight egocentric navigation assistance system for visually impaired individuals, designed for real-time deployment on smartphones. AIGD addresses key challenges in blind navigation by employing a vision-only, multi-label classification approach to predict directional commands, ensuring safe traversal across diverse environments. We propose a novel technique to enable goal-based outdoor navigation by integrating GPS signals and high-level directions, while also addressing uncertain multi-path predictions for destination-free indoor navigation. Our generalized model is the first navigation assistance system to handle both goal-oriented and exploratory navigation scenarios across indoor and outdoor settings, establishing a new state-of-the-art in blind navigation. We present methods, datasets, evaluations, and deployment insights to encourage further innovations in assistive navigation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07957v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aishwarya Jadhav, Jeffery Cao, Abhishree Shetty, Urvashi Priyam Kumar, Aditi Sharma, Ben Sukboontip, Jayant Sravan Tamarapalli, Jingyi Zhang, Anirudh Koul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHEQ-ing the Box: Safe Variable Impedance Learning for Robotic Polishing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07985v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic systems are increasingly employed for industrial automation, with contact-rich tasks like polishing requiring dexterity and compliant behaviour. These tasks are difficult to model, making classical control challenging. Deep reinforcement learning (RL) offers a promising solution by enabling the learning of models and control policies directly from data. However, its application to real-world problems is limited by data inefficiency and unsafe exploration. Adaptive hybrid RL methods blend classical control and RL adaptively, combining the strengths of both: structure from control and learning from RL. This has led to improvements in data efficiency and exploration safety. However, their potential for hardware applications remains underexplored, with no evaluations on physical systems to date. Such evaluations are critical to fully assess the practicality and effectiveness of these methods in real-world settings. This work presents an experimental demonstration of the hybrid RL algorithm CHEQ for robotic polishing with variable impedance, a task requiring precise force and velocity tracking. In simulation, we show that variable impedance enhances polishing performance. We compare standalone RL with adaptive hybrid RL, demonstrating that CHEQ achieves effective learning while adhering to safety constraints. On hardware, CHEQ achieves effective polishing behaviour, requiring only eight hours of training and incurring just five failures. These results highlight the potential of adaptive hybrid RL for real-world, contact-rich tasks trained directly on hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07985v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Cramer, Lukas J\"aschke, Sebastian Trimpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HydroelasticTouch: Simulation of Tactile Sensors with Hydroelastic Contact Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thanks to recent advancements in the development of inexpensive, high-resolution tactile sensors, touch sensing has become popular in contact-rich robotic manipulation tasks. With the surge of data-driven methods and their requirement for substantial datasets, several methods of simulating tactile sensors have emerged in the tactile research community to overcome real-world data collection limitations. These simulation approaches can be split into two main categories: fast but inaccurate (soft) point-contact models and slow but accurate finite element modeling. In this work, we present a novel approach to simulating pressure-based tactile sensors using the hydroelastic contact model, which provides a high degree of physical realism at a reasonable computational cost. This model produces smooth contact forces for soft-to-soft and soft-to-rigid contacts along even non-convex contact surfaces. Pressure values are approximated at each point of the contact surface and can be integrated to calculate sensor outputs. We validate our models' capacity to synthesize real-world tactile data by conducting zero-shot sim-to-real transfer of a model for object state estimation. Our simulation is available as a plug-in to our open-source, MuJoCo-based simulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08077v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David P. Leins, Florian Patzelt, Robert Haschke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Action Based Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Objective Compatible Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) has shown excellent performance in solving decision-making and control problems of autonomous driving, which is increasingly applied in diverse driving scenarios. However, driving is a multi-attribute problem, leading to challenges in achieving multi-objective compatibility for current RL methods, especially in both policy execution and policy iteration. On the one hand, the common action space structure with single action type limits driving flexibility or results in large behavior fluctuations during policy execution. On the other hand, the multi-attribute weighted single reward function result in the agent's disproportionate attention to certain objectives during policy iterations. To this end, we propose a Multi-objective Ensemble-Critic reinforcement learning method with Hybrid Parametrized Action for multi-objective compatible autonomous driving. Specifically, a parameterized action space is constructed to generate hybrid driving actions, combining both abstract guidance and concrete control commands. A multi-objective critics architecture is constructed considering multiple attribute rewards, to ensure simultaneously focusing on different driving objectives. Additionally, uncertainty-based exploration strategy is introduced to help the agent faster approach viable driving policy. The experimental results in both the simulated traffic environment and the HighD dataset demonstrate that our method can achieve multi-objective compatible autonomous driving in terms of driving efficiency, action consistency, and safety. It enhances the general performance of the driving while significantly increasing training efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08096v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guizhe Jin, Zhuoren Li, Bo Leng, Wei Han, Lu Xiong, Chen Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven Spatial Classification using Multi-Arm Bandits for Monitoring with Energy-Constrained Mobile Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the spatial classification problem for monitoring using data collected by a coordinated team of mobile robots. Such classification problems arise in several applications including search-and-rescue and precision agriculture. Specifically, we want to classify the regions of a search environment into interesting and uninteresting as quickly as possible using a team of mobile sensors and mobile charging stations. We develop a data-driven strategy that accommodates the noise in sensed data and the limited energy capacity of the sensors, and generates collision-free motion plans for the team. We propose a bi-level approach, where a high-level planner leverages a multi-armed bandit framework to determine the potential regions of interest for the drones to visit next based on the data collected online. Then, a low-level path planner based on integer programming coordinates the paths for the team to visit the target regions subject to the physical constraints. We characterize several theoretical properties of the proposed approach, including anytime guarantees and task completion time. We show the efficacy of our approach in simulation, and further validate these observations in physical experiments using mobile robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoshan Lin, Siddharth Nayak, Stefano Di Cairano, Abraham P. Vinod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FDPP: Fine-tune Diffusion Policy with Human Preference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08259v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Imitation learning from human demonstrations enables robots to perform complex manipulation tasks and has recently witnessed huge success. However, these techniques often struggle to adapt behavior to new preferences or changes in the environment. To address these limitations, we propose Fine-tuning Diffusion Policy with Human Preference (FDPP). FDPP learns a reward function through preference-based learning. This reward is then used to fine-tune the pre-trained policy with reinforcement learning (RL), resulting in alignment of pre-trained policy with new human preferences while still solving the original task. Our experiments across various robotic tasks and preferences demonstrate that FDPP effectively customizes policy behavior without compromising performance. Additionally, we show that incorporating Kullback-Leibler (KL) regularization during fine-tuning prevents over-fitting and helps maintain the competencies of the initial policy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08259v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Chen, Devesh K. Jha, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Diego Romeres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VINGS-Mono: Visual-Inertial Gaussian Splatting Monocular SLAM in Large Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: VINGS-Mono is a monocular (inertial) Gaussian Splatting (GS) SLAM framework designed for large scenes. The framework comprises four main components: VIO Front End, 2D Gaussian Map, NVS Loop Closure, and Dynamic Eraser. In the VIO Front End, RGB frames are processed through dense bundle adjustment and uncertainty estimation to extract scene geometry and poses. Based on this output, the mapping module incrementally constructs and maintains a 2D Gaussian map. Key components of the 2D Gaussian Map include a Sample-based Rasterizer, Score Manager, and Pose Refinement, which collectively improve mapping speed and localization accuracy. This enables the SLAM system to handle large-scale urban environments with up to 50 million Gaussian ellipsoids. To ensure global consistency in large-scale scenes, we design a Loop Closure module, which innovatively leverages the Novel View Synthesis (NVS) capabilities of Gaussian Splatting for loop closure detection and correction of the Gaussian map. Additionally, we propose a Dynamic Eraser to address the inevitable presence of dynamic objects in real-world outdoor scenes. Extensive evaluations in indoor and outdoor environments demonstrate that our approach achieves localization performance on par with Visual-Inertial Odometry while surpassing recent GS/NeRF SLAM methods. It also significantly outperforms all existing methods in terms of mapping and rendering quality. Furthermore, we developed a mobile app and verified that our framework can generate high-quality Gaussian maps in real time using only a smartphone camera and a low-frequency IMU sensor. To the best of our knowledge, VINGS-Mono is the first monocular Gaussian SLAM method capable of operating in outdoor environments and supporting kilometer-scale large scenes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08286v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Wu, Zicheng Zhang, Muer Tie, Ziqing Ai, Zhongxue Gan, Wenchao Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Electrochemistry Platform with Real-Time Normality Testing of Voltammetry Measurements Using ML</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07705v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electrochemistry workflows utilize various instruments and computing systems to execute workflows consisting of electrocatalyst synthesis, testing and evaluation tasks. The heterogeneity of the software and hardware of these ecosystems makes it challenging to orchestrate a complete workflow from production to characterization by automating its tasks. We propose an autonomous electrochemistry computing platform for a multi-site ecosystem that provides the services for remote experiment steering, real-time measurement transfer, and AI/ML-driven analytics. We describe the integration of a mobile robot and synthesis workstation into the ecosystem by developing custom hub-networks and software modules to support remote operations over the ecosystem's wireless and wired networks. We describe a workflow task for generating I-V voltammetry measurements using a potentiostat, and a machine learning framework to ensure their normality by detecting abnormal conditions such as disconnected electrodes. We study a number of machine learning methods for the underlying detection problem, including smooth, non-smooth, structural and statistical methods, and their fusers. We present experimental results to illustrate the effectiveness of this platform, and also validate the proposed ML method by deriving its rigorous generalization equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07705v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/e-Science62913.2024.10678672</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anees Al-Najjar, Nageswara S. V. Rao, Craig A. Bridges, Sheng Dai, Alex Walters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Human-Hand Segmentation on In-Distribution and Out-of-Distribution Data in Human-Robot Interactions Using a Deep Ensemble Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07713v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reliable detection and segmentation of human hands are critical for enhancing safety and facilitating advanced interactions in human-robot collaboration. Current research predominantly evaluates hand segmentation under in-distribution (ID) data, which reflects the training data of deep learning (DL) models. However, this approach fails to address out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios that often arise in real-world human-robot interactions. In this study, we present a novel approach by evaluating the performance of pre-trained DL models under both ID data and more challenging OOD scenarios. To mimic realistic industrial scenarios, we designed a diverse dataset featuring simple and cluttered backgrounds with industrial tools, varying numbers of hands (0 to 4), and hands with and without gloves. For OOD scenarios, we incorporated unique and rare conditions such as finger-crossing gestures and motion blur from fast-moving hands, addressing both epistemic and aleatoric uncertainties. To ensure multiple point of views (PoVs), we utilized both egocentric cameras, mounted on the operator's head, and static cameras to capture RGB images of human-robot interactions. This approach allowed us to account for multiple camera perspectives while also evaluating the performance of models trained on existing egocentric datasets as well as static-camera datasets. For segmentation, we used a deep ensemble model composed of UNet and RefineNet as base learners. Performance evaluation was conducted using segmentation metrics and uncertainty quantification via predictive entropy. Results revealed that models trained on industrial datasets outperformed those trained on non-industrial datasets, highlighting the importance of context-specific training. Although all models struggled with OOD scenarios, those trained on industrial datasets demonstrated significantly better generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07713v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Jalayer, Yuxin Chen, Masoud Jalayer, Carlotta Orsenigo, Masayoshi Tomizuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Infrastructure LiDAR Placement with Realistic LiDAR Simulation Library</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.15975v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, Vehicle-to-Everything(V2X) cooperative perception has attracted increasing attention. Infrastructure sensors play a critical role in this research field; however, how to find the optimal placement of infrastructure sensors is rarely studied. In this paper, we investigate the problem of infrastructure sensor placement and propose a pipeline that can efficiently and effectively find optimal installation positions for infrastructure sensors in a realistic simulated environment. To better simulate and evaluate LiDAR placement, we establish a Realistic LiDAR Simulation library that can simulate the unique characteristics of different popular LiDARs and produce high-fidelity LiDAR point clouds in the CARLA simulator. Through simulating point cloud data in different LiDAR placements, we can evaluate the perception accuracy of these placements using multiple detection models. Then, we analyze the correlation between the point cloud distribution and perception accuracy by calculating the density and uniformity of regions of interest. Experiments show that when using the same number and type of LiDAR, the placement scheme optimized by our proposed method improves the average precision by 15%, compared with the conventional placement scheme in the standard lane scene. We also analyze the correlation between perception performance in the region of interest and LiDAR point cloud distribution and validate that density and uniformity can be indicators of performance. Both the RLS Library and related code will be released at https://github.com/PJLab-ADG/PCSim.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.15975v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA48891.2023.10161027</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Cai, Wentao Jiang, Runsheng Xu, Wenquan Zhao, Jiaqi Ma, Si Liu, Yikang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tactile-based Exploration, Mapping and Navigation with Collision-Resilient Aerial Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.17217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.17217v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article introduces XPLORER, a passive deformable UAV with a spring-augmented chassis and proprioceptive state awareness, designed to endure collisions and maintain smooth contact. We develop a fast-converging external force estimation algorithm for XPLORER that leverages onboard sensors and proprioceptive data for contact and collision detection. Using this force information, we propose four motion primitives, including three novel tactile-based primitives: tactile-traversal, tactile-turning, and ricocheting-to aid XPLORER in navigating unknown environments. These primitives are synthesized autonomously in real-time to enable efficient exploration and navigation by leveraging collisions and contacts. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach, highlighting the potential of passive deformable UAVs for contact-rich real-world tasks such as non-destructive inspection, surveillance and mapping, and pursuit/evasion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.17217v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karishma Patnaik, Aravind Adhith Pandian Saravanakumaran, Wenlong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Mixed-Integer Conic Program for the Moving-Target Traveling Salesman Problem based on a Graph of Convex Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04917v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new formulation that finds the optimum for the Moving-Target Traveling Salesman Problem (MT-TSP), which seeks to find a shortest path for an agent, that starts at a depot, visits a set of moving targets exactly once within their assigned time-windows, and returns to the depot. The formulation relies on the key idea that when the targets move along lines, their trajectories become convex sets within the space-time coordinate system. The problem then reduces to finding the shortest path within a graph of convex sets, subject to some speed constraints. We compare our formulation with the current state-of-the-art Mixed Integer Conic Program (MICP) solver for the MT-TSP. The experimental results show that our formulation outperforms the MICP for instances with up to 20 targets, with up to two orders of magnitude reduction in runtime, and up to a 60\% tighter optimality gap. We also show that the solution cost from the convex relaxation of our formulation provides significantly tighter lower bounds for the MT-TSP than the ones from the MICP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04917v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/IROS58592.2024.10802374</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>"A Mixed-Integer Conic Program for the Moving-Target Traveling Salesman Problem based on a Graph of Convex Sets," 2024 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), 2024, pp. 8847-8853</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Allen George Philip, Zhongqiang Ren, Sivakumar Rathinam, Howie Choset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DIDLM: A SLAM Dataset for Difficult Scenarios Featuring Infrared, Depth Cameras, LIDAR, 4D Radar, and Others under Adverse Weather, Low Light Conditions, and Rough Roads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09622v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Adverse weather conditions, low-light environments, and bumpy road surfaces pose significant challenges to SLAM in robotic navigation and autonomous driving. Existing datasets in this field predominantly rely on single sensors or combinations of LiDAR, cameras, and IMUs. However, 4D millimeter-wave radar demonstrates robustness in adverse weather, infrared cameras excel in capturing details under low-light conditions, and depth images provide richer spatial information. Multi-sensor fusion methods also show potential for better adaptation to bumpy roads. Despite some SLAM studies incorporating these sensors and conditions, there remains a lack of comprehensive datasets addressing low-light environments and bumpy road conditions, or featuring a sufficiently diverse range of sensor data. In this study, we introduce a multi-sensor dataset covering challenging scenarios such as snowy weather, rainy weather, nighttime conditions, speed bumps, and rough terrains. The dataset includes rarely utilized sensors for extreme conditions, such as 4D millimeter-wave radar, infrared cameras, and depth cameras, alongside 3D LiDAR, RGB cameras, GPS, and IMU. It supports both autonomous driving and ground robot applications and provides reliable GPS/INS ground truth data, covering structured and semi-structured terrains. We evaluated various SLAM algorithms using this dataset, including RGB images, infrared images, depth images, LiDAR, and 4D millimeter-wave radar. The dataset spans a total of 18.5 km, 69 minutes, and approximately 660 GB, offering a valuable resource for advancing SLAM research under complex and extreme conditions. Our dataset is available at https://github.com/GongWeiSheng/DIDLM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09622v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weisheng Gong, Kaijie Su, Qingyong Li, Chen He, Tong Wu, Z. Jane Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Chordal Sparsity for Fast Global Optimality with Application to Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02365v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, many estimation problems in robotics have been shown to be solvable to global optimality using their semidefinite relaxations. However, the runtime complexity of off-the-shelf semidefinite programming (SDP) solvers is up to cubic in problem size, which inhibits real-time solutions of problems involving large state dimensions. We show that for a large class of problems, namely those with chordal sparsity, we can reduce the complexity of these solvers to linear in problem size. In particular, we show how to replace the large positive-semidefinite variable with a number of smaller interconnected ones using the well-known chordal decomposition. This formulation also allows for the straightforward application of the alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM), which can exploit parallelism for increased scalability. We show for two example problems in simulation that the chordal solvers provide a significant speed-up over standard SDP solvers, and that global optimality is crucial in the absence of good initializations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02365v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederike D\"umbgen, Connor Holmes, Timothy D. Barfoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perception Matters: Enhancing Embodied AI with Uncertainty-Aware Semantic Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02297v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Embodied AI has made significant progress acting in unexplored environments. However, tasks such as object search have largely focused on efficient policy learning. In this work, we identify several gaps in current search methods: They largely focus on dated perception models, neglect temporal aggregation, and transfer from ground truth directly to noisy perception at test time, without accounting for the resulting overconfidence in the perceived state. We address the identified problems through calibrated perception probabilities and uncertainty across aggregation and found decisions, thereby adapting the models for sequential tasks. The resulting methods can be directly integrated with pretrained models across a wide family of existing search approaches at no additional training cost. We perform extensive evaluations of aggregation methods across both different semantic perception models and policies, confirming the importance of calibrated uncertainties in both the aggregation and found decisions. We make the code and trained models available at https://semantic-search.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02297v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the International Symposium on Robotics Research (ISRR), 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sai Prasanna, Daniel Honerkamp, Kshitij Sirohi, Tim Welschehold, Wolfram Burgard, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Aerial Robot Inspection Challenge: A Benchmark for Heterogeneous Multi-UAV Planning and Lessons Learned</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06566v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose the Cooperative Aerial Robot Inspection Challenge (CARIC), a simulation-based benchmark for motion planning algorithms in heterogeneous multi-UAV systems. CARIC features UAV teams with complementary sensors, realistic constraints, and evaluation metrics prioritizing inspection quality and efficiency. It offers a ready-to-use perception-control software stack and diverse scenarios to support the development and evaluation of task allocation and motion planning algorithms. Competitions using CARIC were held at IEEE CDC 2023 and the IROS 2024 Workshop on Multi-Robot Perception and Navigation, attracting innovative solutions from research teams worldwide. This paper examines the top three teams from CDC 2023, analyzing their exploration, inspection, and task allocation strategies while drawing insights into their performance across scenarios. The results highlight the task's complexity and suggest promising directions for future research in cooperative multi-UAV systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06566v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muqing Cao, Thien-Minh Nguyen, Shenghai Yuan, Andreas Anastasiou, Angelos Zacharia, Savvas Papaioannou, Panayiotis Kolios, Christos G. Panayiotou, Marios M. Polycarpou, Xinhang Xu, Mingjie Zhang, Fei Gao, Boyu Zhou, Ben M. Chen, Lihua Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cost-Effective Robotic Handwriting System with AI Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a cost-effective robotic handwriting system designed to replicate human-like handwriting with high precision. Combining a Raspberry Pi Pico microcontroller, 3D-printed components, and a machine learning-based handwriting generation model implemented via TensorFlow, the system converts user-supplied text into realistic stroke trajectories. By leveraging lightweight 3D-printed materials and efficient mechanical designs, the system achieves a total hardware cost of approximately \$56, significantly undercutting commercial alternatives. Experimental evaluations demonstrate handwriting precision within $\pm$0.3 millimeters and a writing speed of approximately 200 mm/min, positioning the system as a viable solution for educational, research, and assistive applications. This study seeks to lower the barriers to personalized handwriting technologies, making them accessible to a broader audience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06783v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LISAT63094.2024.10807994</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE Long Island Systems, Applications and Technology Conference (LISAT), pages 1-6, November 2024, Holtsville, NY, USA</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tianyi Huang, Richard Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GazeGrasp: DNN-Driven Robotic Grasping with Wearable Eye-Gaze Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07255v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present GazeGrasp, a gaze-based manipulation system enabling individuals with motor impairments to control collaborative robots using eye-gaze. The system employs an ESP32 CAM for eye tracking, MediaPipe for gaze detection, and YOLOv8 for object localization, integrated with a Universal Robot UR10 for manipulation tasks. After user-specific calibration, the system allows intuitive object selection with a magnetic snapping effect and robot control via eye gestures. Experimental evaluation involving 13 participants demonstrated that the magnetic snapping effect significantly reduced gaze alignment time, improving task efficiency by 31%. GazeGrasp provides a robust, hands-free interface for assistive robotics, enhancing accessibility and autonomy for users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07255v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Issatay Tokmurziyev, Miguel Altamirano Cabrera, Luis Moreno, Muhammad Haris Khan, Dzmitry Tsetserukou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenSafe: A Generalizable Safety Enhancer for Safe Reinforcement Learning Algorithms Based on Reduced Order Markov Decision Process Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03912v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Safe Reinforcement Learning (SRL) aims to realize a safe learning process for Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) algorithms by incorporating safety constraints. However, the efficacy of SRL approaches often relies on accurate function approximations, which are notably challenging to achieve in the early learning stages due to data insufficiency. To address this issue, we introduce in this work a novel Generalizable Safety enhancer (GenSafe) that is able to overcome the challenge of data insufficiency and enhance the performance of SRL approaches. Leveraging model order reduction techniques, we first propose an innovative method to construct a Reduced Order Markov Decision Process (ROMDP) as a low-dimensional approximator of the original safety constraints. Then, by solving the reformulated ROMDP-based constraints, GenSafe refines the actions of the agent to increase the possibility of constraint satisfaction. Essentially, GenSafe acts as an additional safety layer for SRL algorithms. We evaluate GenSafe on multiple SRL approaches and benchmark problems. The results demonstrate its capability to improve safety performance, especially in the early learning phases, while maintaining satisfactory task performance. Our proposed GenSafe not only offers a novel measure to augment existing SRL methods but also shows broad compatibility with various SRL algorithms, making it applicable to a wide range of systems and SRL problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03912v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TNNLS.2024.3496492</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhehua Zhou, Xuan Xie, Jiayang Song, Zhan Shu, Lei Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FaVoR: Features via Voxel Rendering for Camera Relocalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07571v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Camera relocalization methods range from dense image alignment to direct camera pose regression from a query image. Among these, sparse feature matching stands out as an efficient, versatile, and generally lightweight approach with numerous applications. However, feature-based methods often struggle with significant viewpoint and appearance changes, leading to matching failures and inaccurate pose estimates. To overcome this limitation, we propose a novel approach that leverages a globally sparse yet locally dense 3D representation of 2D features. By tracking and triangulating landmarks over a sequence of frames, we construct a sparse voxel map optimized to render image patch descriptors observed during tracking. Given an initial pose estimate, we first synthesize descriptors from the voxels using volumetric rendering and then perform feature matching to estimate the camera pose. This methodology enables the generation of descriptors for unseen views, enhancing robustness to view changes. We extensively evaluate our method on the 7-Scenes and Cambridge Landmarks datasets. Our results show that our method significantly outperforms existing state-of-the-art feature representation techniques in indoor environments, achieving up to a 39% improvement in median translation error. Additionally, our approach yields comparable results to other methods for outdoor scenarios while maintaining lower memory and computational costs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07571v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Polizzi, Marco Cannici, Davide Scaramuzza, Jonathan Kelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Reflections on a Dynamic 2D Eye Model Improve Spatial Reference Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07344v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The visible orientation of human eyes creates some transparency about people's spatial attention and other mental states. This leads to a dual role for the eyes as a means of sensing and communication. Accordingly, artificial eye models are being explored as communication media in human-machine interaction scenarios. One challenge in the use of eye models for communication consists of resolving spatial reference ambiguities, especially for screen-based models. Here, we introduce an approach for overcoming this challenge through the introduction of reflection-like features that are contingent on artificial eye movements. We conducted a user study with 30 participants in which participants had to use spatial references provided by dynamic eye models to advance in a fast-paced group interaction task. Compared to a non-reflective eye model and a pure reflection mode, their combination in the new approach resulted in a higher identification accuracy and user experience, suggesting a synergistic benefit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07344v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matti Kr\"uger, Yutaka Oshima, Yu Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vid2Sim: Realistic and Interactive Simulation from Video for Urban Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06693v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Sim-to-real gap has long posed a significant challenge for robot learning in simulation, preventing the deployment of learned models in the real world. Previous work has primarily focused on domain randomization and system identification to mitigate this gap. However, these methods are often limited by the inherent constraints of the simulation and graphics engines. In this work, we propose Vid2Sim, a novel framework that effectively bridges the sim2real gap through a scalable and cost-efficient real2sim pipeline for neural 3D scene reconstruction and simulation. Given a monocular video as input, Vid2Sim can generate photorealistic and physically interactable 3D simulation environments to enable the reinforcement learning of visual navigation agents in complex urban environments. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Vid2Sim significantly improves the performance of urban navigation in the digital twins and real world by 31.2% and 68.3% in success rate compared with agents trained with prior simulation methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06693v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyang Xie, Zhizheng Liu, Zhenghao Peng, Wayne Wu, Bolei Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of Artificial Intelligence Methods for Lead Time Prediction in Non-Cycled Areas of Automotive Production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07317v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The present study examines the effectiveness of applying Artificial Intelligence methods in an automotive production environment to predict unknown lead times in a non-cycle-controlled production area. Data structures are analyzed to identify contextual features and then preprocessed using one-hot encoding. Methods selection focuses on supervised machine learning techniques. In supervised learning methods, regression and classification methods are evaluated. Continuous regression based on target size distribution is not feasible. Classification methods analysis shows that Ensemble Learning and Support Vector Machines are the most suitable. Preliminary study results indicate that gradient boosting algorithms LightGBM, XGBoost, and CatBoost yield the best results. After further testing and extensive hyperparameter optimization, the final method choice is the LightGBM algorithm. Depending on feature availability and prediction interval granularity, relative prediction accuracies of up to 90% can be achieved. Further tests highlight the importance of periodic retraining of AI models to accurately represent complex production processes using the database. The research demonstrates that AI methods can be effectively applied to highly variable production data, adding business value by providing an additional metric for various control tasks while outperforming current non AI-based systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07317v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cornelius Hake, Jonas Weigele, Frederik Reichert, Christian Friedrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
