<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 01:38:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>SCOUT: A Lightweight Framework for Scenario Coverage Assessment in Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assessing scenario coverage is crucial for evaluating the robustness of autonomous agents, yet existing methods rely on expensive human annotations or computationally intensive Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs). These approaches are impractical for large-scale deployment due to cost and efficiency constraints. To address these shortcomings, we propose SCOUT (Scenario Coverage Oversight and Understanding Tool), a lightweight surrogate model designed to predict scenario coverage labels directly from an agent's latent sensor representations. SCOUT is trained through a distillation process, learning to approximate LVLM-generated coverage labels while eliminating the need for continuous LVLM inference or human annotation. By leveraging precomputed perception features, SCOUT avoids redundant computations and enables fast, scalable scenario coverage estimation. We evaluate our method across a large dataset of real-life autonomous navigation scenarios, demonstrating that it maintains high accuracy while significantly reducing computational cost. Our results show that SCOUT provides an effective and practical alternative for large-scale coverage analysis. While its performance depends on the quality of LVLM-generated training labels, SCOUT represents a major step toward efficient scenario coverage oversight in autonomous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24949v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anil Yildiz, Sarah M. Thornton, Carl Hildebrandt, Sreeja Roy-Singh, Mykel J. Kochenderfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth path planning with safety margins using Piece-Wise Bezier curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a computationally efficient quadratic programming (QP) approach for generating smooth, $C^1$ continuous paths for mobile robots using piece-wise quadratic Bezier (PWB) curves. Our method explicitly incorporates safety margins within a structured optimization framework, balancing trajectory smoothness and robustness with manageable numerical complexity suitable for real-time and embedded applications. Comparative simulations demonstrate clear advantages over traditional piece-wise linear (PWL) path planning methods, showing reduced trajectory deviations, enhanced robustness, and improved overall path quality. These benefits are validated through simulations using a Pure-Pursuit controller in representative scenarios, highlighting the practical effectiveness and scalability of our approach for safe navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24972v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ETFA65518.2025.11205537</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 IEEE 30th International Conference on Emerging Technologies and Factory Automation (ETFA), Porto, Portugal, 2025, pp. 1-4</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Iancu Andrei, Marius Kloetzer, Cristian Mahulea, Catalin Dosoftei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect Mitigation for Robot Arm-based Additive Manufacturing Utilizing Intelligent Control and IOT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24994v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an integrated robotic fused deposition modeling additive manufacturing system featuring closed-loop thermal control and intelligent in-situ defect correction using a 6-degree of freedom robotic arm and an Oak-D camera. The robot arm end effector was modified to mount an E3D hotend thermally regulated by an IoT microcontroller, enabling precise temperature control through real-time feedback. Filament extrusion system was synchronized with robotic motion, coordinated via ROS2, ensuring consistent deposition along complex trajectories. A vision system based on OpenCV detects layer-wise defects position, commanding autonomous re-extrusion at identified sites. Experimental validation demonstrated successful defect mitigation in printing operations. The integrated system effectively addresses challenges real-time quality assurance. Inverse kinematics were used for motion planning, while homography transformations corrected camera perspectives for accurate defect localization. The intelligent system successfully mitigated surface anomalies without interrupting the print process. By combining real-time thermal regulation, motion control, and intelligent defect detection &amp; correction, this architecture establishes a scalable and adaptive robotic additive manufacturing framework suitable for aerospace, biomedical, and industrial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24994v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matsive Ali, Blake Gassen, Sen Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable predictive processing framework for multitask caregiving robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid aging of societies is intensifying demand for autonomous care robots; however, most existing systems are task-specific and rely on handcrafted preprocessing, limiting their ability to generalize across diverse scenarios. A prevailing theory in cognitive neuroscience proposes that the human brain operates through hierarchical predictive processing, which underlies flexible cognition and behavior by integrating multimodal sensory signals. Inspired by this principle, we introduce a hierarchical multimodal recurrent neural network grounded in predictive processing under the free-energy principle, capable of directly integrating over 30,000-dimensional visuo-proprioceptive inputs without dimensionality reduction. The model was able to learn two representative caregiving tasks, rigid-body repositioning and flexible-towel wiping, without task-specific feature engineering. We demonstrate three key properties: (i) self-organization of hierarchical latent dynamics that regulate task transitions, capture variability in uncertainty, and infer occluded states; (ii) robustness to degraded vision through visuo-proprioceptive integration; and (iii) asymmetric interference in multitask learning, where the more variable wiping task had little influence on repositioning, whereas learning the repositioning task led to a modest reduction in wiping performance, while the model maintained overall robustness. Although the evaluation was limited to simulation, these results establish predictive processing as a universal and scalable computational principle, pointing toward robust, flexible, and autonomous caregiving robots while offering theoretical insight into the human brain's ability to achieve flexible adaptation in uncertain real-world environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25053v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayato Idei, Tamon Miyake, Tetsuya Ogata, Yuichi Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Invasive Calibration Of A Stewart Platform By Photogrammetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate calibration of a Stewart platform is important for their precise and efficient operation. However, the calibration of these platforms using forward kinematics is a challenge for researchers because forward kinematics normally generates multiple feasible and unfeasible solutions for any pose of the moving platform. The complex kinematic relations among the six actuator paths connecting the fixed base to the moving platform further compound the difficulty in establishing a straightforward and efficient calibration method. The authors developed a new forward kinematics-based calibration method using Denavit-Hartenberg convention and used the Stewart platform Tiger 66.1 developed in their lab for experimenting with the photogrammetry-based calibration strategies described in this paper. This system became operational upon completion of construction, marking its inaugural use. The authors used their calibration model for estimating the errors in the system and adopted three compensation options or strategies as per Least Square method to improve the accuracy of the system. These strategies leveraged a high-resolution digital camera and off-the-shelf software to capture the poses of the moving platform's center. This process is non-invasive and does not need any additional equipment to be attached to the hexapod or any alteration of the hexapod hardware. This photogrammetry-based calibration process involves multiple high-resolution images from different angles to measure the position and orientation of the platform center in the three-dimensional space. The Target poses and Actual poses are then compared, and the error compensations are estimated using the Least-Squared methods to calculate the Predicted poses. Results from each of the three compensation approaches demonstrated noticeable enhancements in platform pose accuracies, suggesting room for further improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25072v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00170-024-13485-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sourabh Karmakar, Cameron J. Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-Shift Theory and Its Applications in Swarm Robotics: A New Way to Enhance the Efficiency of Multi-Robot Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Swarms evolving from collective behaviors among multiple individuals are commonly seen in nature, which enables biological systems to exhibit more efficient and robust collaboration. Creating similar swarm intelligence in engineered robots poses challenges to the design of collaborative algorithms that can be programmed at large scales. The assignment-based method has played an eminent role for a very long time in solving collaboration problems of robot swarms. However, it faces fundamental limitations in terms of efficiency and robustness due to its unscalability to swarm variants. This article presents a tutorial review on recent advances in assignment-free collaboration of robot swarms, focusing on the problem of shape formation. A key theoretical component is the recently developed \emph{mean-shift exploration} strategy, which improves the collaboration efficiency of large-scale swarms by dozens of times. Further, the efficiency improvement is more significant as the swarm scale increases. Finally, this article discusses three important applications of the mean-shift exploration strategy, including precise shape formation, area coverage formation, and maneuvering formation, as well as their corresponding industrial scenarios in smart warehousing, area exploration, and cargo transportation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25086v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guibin Sun, Jinhu L\"u, Kexin Liu, Zhenqian Wang, Guanrong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NanoVLA: Routing Decoupled Vision-Language Understanding for Nano-sized Generalist Robotic Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-language-action (VLA) models have significantly advanced robotic manipulation by integrating vision-language models (VLMs), and action decoders into a unified architecture. However, their deployment on resource-constrained edge devices, such as mobile robots or embedded systems (e.g., Jetson Orin Nano), remains challenging due to high computational demands, especially in real-world scenarios where power, latency, and computational resources are critical. To close this gap, we introduce Nano-scale Vision-Language Action (NanoVLA), a family of lightweight VLA architectures that achieve high performance with minimal resources. Our core innovations include: (1) vision-language decoupling that moves conventional early vision and language inputs fusion in VLM to late stage, achieving better performance while enabling caching and reduce inference overhead and latency; (2) long-short action chunking to ensure smooth, coherent multi-step planning without sacrificing real-time responsiveness; (3) dynamic routing that adaptively assigns lightweight or heavy backbones based on task complexity, further optimizing inference efficiency. Experimental results on several benchmarks, as well as real-world deployments, demonstrate that NanoVLA achieves up to 52x faster inference on edge devices compared to previous state-of-the-art VLA models, with 98% less parameters while maintaining or surpassing their task accuracy and generalization. Ablation studies confirm that our decoupling strategy preserves cross-task transferability, and the routing module enhances cost-performance trade-offs, enabling practical, high-precision robotic manipulation on resource-constrained hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25122v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahong Chen, Jing Wang, Long Chen, Chuwei Cai, Jinghui Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Spatial-Aware Manipulation Ordering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Manipulation in cluttered environments is challenging due to spatial dependencies among objects, where an improper manipulation order can cause collisions or blocked access. Existing approaches often overlook these spatial relationships, limiting their flexibility and scalability. To address these limitations, we propose OrderMind, a unified spatial-aware manipulation ordering framework that directly learns object manipulation priorities based on spatial context. Our architecture integrates a spatial context encoder with a temporal priority structuring module. We construct a spatial graph using k-Nearest Neighbors to aggregate geometric information from the local layout and encode both object-object and object-manipulator interactions to support accurate manipulation ordering in real-time. To generate physically and semantically plausible supervision signals, we introduce a spatial prior labeling method that guides a vision-language model to produce reasonable manipulation orders for distillation. We evaluate OrderMind on our Manipulation Ordering Benchmark, comprising 163,222 samples of varying difficulty. Extensive experiments in both simulation and real-world environments demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms prior approaches in effectiveness and efficiency, enabling robust manipulation in cluttered scenes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25138v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Yan, Zhiyuan Zhou, Xin Gao, Guanghao Li, Shenglin Li, Jiaqi Chen, Qunyan Pu, Jian Pu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoraNav: Adaptive UAV Task-Centric Navigation via Zeroshot VLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interpreting visual observations and natural language instructions for complex task execution remains a key challenge in robotics and AI. Despite recent advances, language-driven navigation is still difficult, particularly for UAVs in small-scale 3D environments. Existing Vision-Language Navigation (VLN) approaches are mostly designed for ground robots and struggle to generalize to aerial tasks that require full 3D spatial reasoning. The emergence of large Vision-Language Models (VLMs), such as GPT and Claude, enables zero-shot semantic reasoning from visual and textual inputs. However, these models lack spatial grounding and are not directly applicable to navigation. To address these limitations, SoraNav is introduced, an adaptive UAV navigation framework that integrates zero-shot VLM reasoning with geometry-aware decision-making. Geometric priors are incorporated into image annotations to constrain the VLM action space and improve decision quality. A hybrid switching strategy leverages navigation history to alternate between VLM reasoning and geometry-based exploration, mitigating dead-ends and redundant revisits. A PX4-based hardware-software platform, comprising both a digital twin and a physical micro-UAV, enables reproducible evaluation. Experimental results show that in 2.5D scenarios, our method improves Success Rate (SR) by 25.7% and Success weighted by Path Length (SPL) by 17%. In 3D scenarios, it improves SR by 29.5% and SPL by 18.5% relative to the baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25191v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongyu Song, Rishabh Dev Yadav, Cheng Guo, Wei Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoadSens-4M: A Multimodal Smartphone &amp; Camera Dataset for Holistic Road-way Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25211v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It's important to monitor road issues such as bumps and potholes to enhance safety and improve road conditions. Smartphones are equipped with various built-in sensors that offer a cost-effective and straightforward way to assess road quality. However, progress in this area has been slow due to the lack of high-quality, standardized datasets. This paper discusses a new dataset created by a mobile app that collects sensor data from devices like GPS, accelerometers, gyroscopes, magnetometers, gravity sensors, and orientation sensors. This dataset is one of the few that integrates Geographic Information System (GIS) data with weather information and video footage of road conditions, providing a comprehensive understanding of road issues with geographic context. The dataset allows for a clearer analysis of road conditions by compiling essential data, including vehicle speed, acceleration, rotation rates, and magnetic field intensity, along with the visual and spatial context provided by GIS, weather, and video data. Its goal is to provide funding for initiatives that enhance traffic management, infrastructure development, road safety, and urban planning. Additionally, the dataset will be publicly accessible to promote further research and innovation in smart transportation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25211v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amith Khandakar, David Michelson, Shaikh Golam Rabbani, Fariya Bintay Shafi, Md. Faysal Ahamed, Khondokar Radwanur Rahman, Md Abidur Rahman, Md. Fahmidun Nabi, Mohamed Arselene Ayari, Khaled Khan, Ponnuthurai Nagaratnam Suganthan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Vision Servoing with Depp Alignment and GRU-Based Occlusion Recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-based control systems, such as image-based visual servoing (IBVS), have been extensively explored for precise robot manipulation. A persistent challenge, however, is maintaining robust target tracking under partial or full occlusions. Classical methods like Lucas-Kanade (LK) offer lightweight tracking but are fragile to occlusion and drift, while deep learning-based approaches often require continuous visibility and intensive computation. To address these gaps, we propose a hybrid visual tracking framework that bridges advanced perception with real-time servo control. First, a fast global template matcher constrains the pose search region; next, a deep-feature Lucas-Kanade module operating on early VGG layers refines alignment to sub-pixel accuracy (&lt;2px); then, a lightweight residual regressor corrects local misalignments caused by texture degradation or partial occlusion. When visual confidence falls below a threshold, a GRU-based predictor seamlessly extrapolates pose updates from recent motion history. Crucially, the pipeline's final outputs-translation, rotation, and scale deltas-are packaged as direct control signals for 30Hz image-based servo loops. Evaluated on handheld video sequences with up to 90% occlusion, our system sustains under 2px tracking error, demonstrating the robustness and low-latency precision essential for reliable real-world robot vision applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25233v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jee Won Lee, Hansol Lim, Sooyeun Yang, Jongseong Brad Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-shot Humanoid Whole-body Motion Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Whole-body humanoid motion represents a cornerstone challenge in robotics, integrating balance, coordination, and adaptability to enable human-like behaviors. However, existing methods typically require multiple training samples per motion category, rendering the collection of high-quality human motion datasets both labor-intensive and costly. To address this, we propose a novel approach that trains effective humanoid motion policies using only a single non-walking target motion sample alongside readily available walking motions. The core idea lies in leveraging order-preserving optimal transport to compute distances between walking and non-walking sequences, followed by interpolation along geodesics to generate new intermediate pose skeletons, which are then optimized for collision-free configurations and retargeted to the humanoid before integration into a simulated environment for policy training via reinforcement learning. Experimental evaluations on the CMU MoCap dataset demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms baselines, achieving superior performance across metrics. Code will be released upon acceptance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25241v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Huang, Geeta Chandra Raju Bethala, Shuaihang Yuan, Congcong Wen, Anthony Tzes, Yi Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Optimal Transport of Loosely Placed Liquid Filled Cups along Prescribed Paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Handling loosely placed objects with robotic manipulators is a difficult task from the point of view of trajectory planning and control. This becomes even more challenging when the object to be handled is a container filled with liquid. This paper addresses the task of transporting a liquid-filled cup placed on a tray along a prescribed path in shortest time. The objective is to minimize swapping, thus avoiding spillage of the fluid. To this end, the sloshing dynamics is incorporated into the dynamic model used within the optimal control problem formulation. The optimization problem is solved using a direct multiple shooting approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25255v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-59257-7_41</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Service and Industrial Robotics. RAAD 2024. Mechanisms and Machine Science, vol. 157, pp. 411-419</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Zauner, Hubert Gattringer, Andreas Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SynHLMA:Synthesizing Hand Language Manipulation for Articulated Object with Discrete Human Object Interaction Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generating hand grasps with language instructions is a widely studied topic that benefits from embodied AI and VR/AR applications. While transferring into hand articulatied object interaction (HAOI), the hand grasps synthesis requires not only object functionality but also long-term manipulation sequence along the object deformation. This paper proposes a novel HAOI sequence generation framework SynHLMA, to synthesize hand language manipulation for articulated objects. Given a complete point cloud of an articulated object, we utilize a discrete HAOI representation to model each hand object interaction frame. Along with the natural language embeddings, the representations are trained by an HAOI manipulation language model to align the grasping process with its language description in a shared representation space. A joint-aware loss is employed to ensure hand grasps follow the dynamic variations of articulated object joints. In this way, our SynHLMA achieves three typical hand manipulation tasks for articulated objects of HAOI generation, HAOI prediction and HAOI interpolation. We evaluate SynHLMA on our built HAOI-lang dataset and experimental results demonstrate the superior hand grasp sequence generation performance comparing with state-of-the-art. We also show a robotics grasp application that enables dexterous grasps execution from imitation learning using the manipulation sequence provided by our SynHLMA. Our codes and datasets will be made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25268v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang zhi, Yuyan Liu, Liu Liu, Li Zhang, Ruixuan Lu, Dan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of Implicit-Explicit Control Based Amphibious Centipede-Type Robot and Evaluation of its Mobile Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-legged mobile robots possess high mobility performance in rough terrain environments, stemming from their high postural stability, joint flexibility, and the redundancy provided by multiple legs. In prior research on navigating between different environments such as land and water, the primary strategy employed involves switching to a controller that generates an appropriate gait for the new environment upon entering it. However, designing appropriate gaits for each complex and diverse environment and accurately determining controller switching for each environment is challenging. Therefore, this research develops a centipede-type mobile robot that navigates both aquatic and terrestrial environments with a simple, unified control scheme, based on the implicit-explicit control philosophy and by ingeniously designing the robot's body structure. In this research, we developed the robot featuring flexible joints and left and right legs on each body segment and focused on the leg structure which has extensive contact with the environment. This paper evaluates the locomotion performance on land and water using the three developed leg structures, using the robot's leg slip rate and actuator energy consumption as evaluation metrics. The experimental results confirmed the existence of an appropriate leg structure capable of navigating both aquatic and terrestrial environments under identical control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25280v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Tsunoda, Seiya Yamamoto, Kazuki Ito, Runze Xiao, Keisuke Naniwa, Koichi Osuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An approach for combining transparency and motion assistance of a lower body exoskeleton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, an approach for gait assistance with a lower body exoskeleton is described. Two concepts, transparency and motion assistance, are combined. The transparent mode, where the system is following the user's free motion with a minimum of perceived interaction forces, is realized by exploiting the gear backlash of the actuation units. During walking a superimposed assistance mode applies an additional torque guiding the legs to their estimated future position. The concept of adaptive oscillators is utilized to learn the quasi-periodic signals typical for locomotion. First experiments showed promising results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-32606-6_28</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Service and Industrial Robotics. RAAD 2023. Mechanisms and Machine Science, vol 135</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Ziegler, Bernhard Rameder, Hubert Gattringer, Andreas Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Robot Calibration Using a Calibration Plate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper a new method for geometric robot calibration is introduced, which uses a calibration plate with precisely known distances between its measuring points. The relative measurement between two points on the calibration plate is used to determine predefined error parameters of the system. In comparison to conventional measurement methods, like laser tracker or motion capture systems, the calibration plate provides a more mechanically robust and cheaper alternative, which is furthermore easier to transport due to its small size. The calibration method, the plate design, the mathematical description of the error system as well as the identification of the parameters are described in detail. For identifying the error parameters, the least squares method and a constrained optimization problem are used. The functionality of this method was demonstrated in experiments that led to promising results, correlated with one of a laser tracker calibration. The modeling and identification of the error parameters is done for a gantry machine, but is not restricted to that type of robot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25338v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-59257-7_31</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Service and Industrial Robotics. RAAD 2024. Mechanisms and Machine Science, vol. 157, May 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernhard Rameder, Hubert Gattringer, Andreas Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Legal and Logical Specifications in Perception, Prediction, and Planning for Automated Driving: A Survey of Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This survey provides an analysis of current methodologies integrating legal and logical specifications into the perception, prediction, and planning modules of automated driving systems. We systematically explore techniques ranging from logic-based frameworks to computational legal reasoning approaches, emphasizing their capability to ensure regulatory compliance and interpretability in dynamic and uncertain driving environments. A central finding is that significant challenges arise at the intersection of perceptual reliability, legal compliance, and decision-making justifiability. To systematically analyze these challenges, we introduce a taxonomy categorizing existing approaches by their theoretical foundations, architectural implementations, and validation strategies. We particularly focus on methods that address perceptual uncertainty and incorporate explicit legal norms, facilitating decisions that are both technically robust and legally defensible. The review covers neural-symbolic integration methods for perception, logic-driven rule representation, and norm-aware prediction strategies, all contributing toward transparent and accountable autonomous vehicle operation. We highlight critical open questions and practical trade-offs that must be addressed, offering multidisciplinary insights from engineering, logic, and law to guide future developments in legally compliant autonomous driving systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25386v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kumar Manas, Mert Keser, Alois Knoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sim-to-Real Gentle Manipulation of Deformable and Fragile Objects with Stress-Guided Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic manipulation of deformable and fragile objects presents significant challenges, as excessive stress can lead to irreversible damage to the object. While existing solutions rely on accurate object models or specialized sensors and grippers, this adds complexity and often lacks generalization. To address this problem, we present a vision-based reinforcement learning approach that incorporates a stress-penalized reward to discourage damage to the object explicitly. In addition, to bootstrap learning, we incorporate offline demonstrations as well as a designed curriculum progressing from rigid proxies to deformables. We evaluate the proposed method in both simulated and real-world scenarios, showing that the policy learned in simulation can be transferred to the real world in a zero-shot manner, performing tasks such as picking up and pushing tofu. Our results show that the learned policies exhibit a damage-aware, gentle manipulation behavior, demonstrating their effectiveness by decreasing the stress applied to fragile objects by 36.5% while achieving the task goals, compared to vanilla RL policies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25405v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kei Ikemura, Yifei Dong, David Blanco-Mulero, Alberta Longhini, Li Chen, Florian T. Pokorny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the Right Problem with Multi-Robot Formations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Formation control simplifies minimizing multi-robot cost functions by encoding a cost function as a shape the robots maintain. However, by reducing complex cost functions to formations, discrepancies arise between maintaining the shape and minimizing the original cost function. For example, a Diamond or Box formation shape is often used for protecting all members of the formation. When more information about the surrounding environment becomes available, a static shape often no longer minimizes the original protection cost. We propose a formation planner to reduce mismatch between a formation and the cost function while still leveraging efficient formation controllers. Our formation planner is a two-step optimization problem that identifies desired relative robot positions. We first solve a constrained problem to estimate non-linear and non-differentiable costs with a weighted sum of surrogate cost functions. We theoretically analyze this problem and identify situations where weights do not need to be updated. The weighted, surrogate cost function is then minimized using relative positions between robots. The desired relative positions are realized using a non-cooperative formation controller derived from Lyapunov's direct approach. We then demonstrate the efficacy of this approach for military-like costs such as protection and obstacle avoidance. In simulations, we show a formation planner can reduce a single cost by over 75%. When minimizing a variety of cost functions simultaneously, using a formation planner with adaptive weights can reduce the cost by 20-40%. Formation planning provides better performance by minimizing a surrogate cost function that closely approximates the original cost function instead of relying on a shape abstraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25422v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaz Cornwall, Jeremy P. Bos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining Moving Mass Actuators and Manoeuvring Models for Underwater Vehicles: A Lagrangian Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a Newton-Euler formulation of the equations of motion for underwater vehicles with an interntal moving mass actuator. Furthermore, the moving mass dynamics are expressed as an extension to the manoeuvring model for underwater vehicles, originally introduced by Fossen (1991). The influence of the moving mass is described in body-frame and included as states in both an additional kinematic equation and as part of the coupled rigid-body kinetics of the underwater vehicle. The Coriolis-centripetal effects are derived from Kirchhoff's equations and the hydrostatics are derived using first principals. The proposed Newton-Euler model is validated through simulation and compared with the traditional Hamiltonian internal moving mass actuator formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25479v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander B. Rambech, Ivar B. Saksvik, Vahid Hassani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Octopus-like Reaching Motion: A Perspective Inspired by Whipping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The stereotypical reaching motion of the octopus arm has drawn growing attention for its efficient control of a highly deformable body. Previous studies suggest that its characteristic bend propagation may share underlying principles with the dynamics of a whip. This work investigates whether whip-like passive dynamics in water can reproduce the kinematic features observed in biological reaching and their similarities and differences. Platform-based whipping tests were performed in water and air while systematically varying material stiffness and driving speed. Image-based quantification revealed that the Ecoflex Gel 2 arm driven at 150 rpm (motor speed) reproduced curvature propagation similar to that observed in octopus reaching. However, its bend-point velocity decreased monotonically rather than exhibiting the biological bell-shaped profile, confirming that the octopus reaching movement is not merely a passive whipping behavior. The absence of propagation in air further highlights the critical role of the surrounding medium in forming octopus-like reaching motion. This study provides a new perspective for understand biological reaching movement, and offers a potential platform for future hydrodynamic research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25520v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengyao Zhang, Yiyuan Zhang, Chenrui Zhang, Yiming Li, Wenci Xin, Yuliang Liufu, Hong Wei Ng, Cecilia Laschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using VLM Reasoning to Constrain Task and Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In task and motion planning, high-level task planning is done over an abstraction of the world to enable efficient search in long-horizon robotics problems. However, the feasibility of these task-level plans relies on the downward refinability of the abstraction into continuous motion. When a domain's refinability is poor, task-level plans that appear valid may ultimately fail during motion planning, requiring replanning and resulting in slower overall performance. Prior works mitigate this by encoding refinement issues as constraints to prune infeasible task plans. However, these approaches only add constraints upon refinement failure, expending significant search effort on infeasible branches. We propose VIZ-COAST, a method of leveraging the common-sense spatial reasoning of large pretrained Vision-Language Models to identify issues with downward refinement a priori, bypassing the need to fix these failures during planning. Experiments on two challenging TAMP domains show that our approach is able to extract plausible constraints from images and domain descriptions, drastically reducing planning times and, in some cases, eliminating downward refinement failures altogether, generalizing to a diverse range of instances from the broader domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25548v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muyang Yan, Miras Mengdibayev, Ardon Floros, Weihang Guo, Lydia E. Kavraki, Zachary Kingston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Plan &amp; Schedule with Reinforcement-Learned Bimanual Robot Skills</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-horizon contact-rich bimanual manipulation presents a significant challenge, requiring complex coordination involving a mixture of parallel execution and sequential collaboration between arms. In this paper, we introduce a hierarchical framework that frames this challenge as an integrated skill planning &amp; scheduling problem, going beyond purely sequential decision-making to support simultaneous skill invocation. Our approach is built upon a library of single-arm and bimanual primitive skills, each trained using Reinforcement Learning (RL) in GPU-accelerated simulation. We then train a Transformer-based planner on a dataset of skill compositions to act as a high-level scheduler, simultaneously predicting the discrete schedule of skills as well as their continuous parameters. We demonstrate that our method achieves higher success rates on complex, contact-rich tasks than end-to-end RL approaches and produces more efficient, coordinated behaviors than traditional sequential-only planners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25634v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weikang Wan, Fabio Ramos, Xuning Yang, Caelan Garrett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision avoidance and path finding in a robotic mobile fulfillment system using multi-objective meta-heuristics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-Agent Path Finding (MAPF) has gained significant attention, with most research focusing on minimizing collisions and travel time. This paper also considers energy consumption in the path planning of automated guided vehicles (AGVs). It addresses two main challenges: i) resolving collisions between AGVs and ii) assigning tasks to AGVs. We propose a new collision avoidance strategy that takes both energy use and travel time into account. For task assignment, we present two multi-objective algorithms: Non-Dominated Sorting Genetic Algorithm (NSGA) and Adaptive Large Neighborhood Search (ALNS). Comparative evaluations show that these proposed methods perform better than existing approaches in both collision avoidance and task assignment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25650v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Kokhahi, Mary Kurz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robotic Assistant: Completing Collaborative Tasks with Dexterous Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We adapt a pre-trained Vision-Language-Action (VLA) model (Open-VLA) for dexterous human-robot collaboration with minimal language prompting. Our approach adds (i) FiLM conditioning to visual backbones for task-aware perception, (ii) an auxiliary intent head that predicts collaborator hand pose and target cues, and (iii) action-space post-processing that predicts compact deltas (position/rotation) and PCA-reduced finger joints before mapping to full commands. Using a multi-view, teleoperated Franka and Mimic-hand dataset augmented with MediaPipe hand poses, we demonstrate that delta actions are well-behaved and that four principal components explain ~96% of hand-joint variance. Ablations identify action post-processing as the primary performance driver; auxiliary intent helps, FiLM is mixed, and a directional motion loss is detrimental. A real-time stack (~0.3 s latency on one RTX 4090) composes "pick-up" and "pass" into a long-horizon behavior. We surface "trainer overfitting" to specific demonstrators as the key limitation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25713v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boshi An, Chenyu Yang, Robert Katzschmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Humanoid Visual-Tactile-Action Dataset for Contact-Rich Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contact-rich manipulation has become increasingly important in robot learning. However, previous studies on robot learning datasets have focused on rigid objects and underrepresented the diversity of pressure conditions for real-world manipulation. To address this gap, we present a humanoid visual-tactile-action dataset designed for manipulating deformable soft objects. The dataset was collected via teleoperation using a humanoid robot equipped with dexterous hands, capturing multi-modal interactions under varying pressure conditions. This work also motivates future research on models with advanced optimization strategies capable of effectively leveraging the complexity and diversity of tactile signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25725v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eunju Kwon, Seungwon Oh, In-Chang Baek, Yucheon Park, Gyungbo Kim, JaeYoung Moon, Yunho Choi, Kyung-Joong Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Collapse of Steered Vine Robots Under Their Own Weight</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Soft, vine-inspired growing robots that move by eversion are highly mobile in confined environments, but, when faced with gaps in the environment, they may collapse under their own weight while navigating a desired path. In this work, we present a comprehensive collapse model that can predict the collapse length of steered robots in any shape using true shape information and tail tension. We validate this model by collapsing several unsteered robots without true shape information. The model accurately predicts the trends of those experiments. We then attempt to collapse a robot steered with a single actuator at different orientations. Our models accurately predict collapse when it occurs. Finally, we demonstrate how this could be used in the field by having a robot attempt a gap-crossing task with and without inflating its actuators. The robot needs its actuators inflated to cross the gap without collapsing, which our model supports. Our model has been specifically tested on straight and series pouch motor-actuated robots made of non-stretchable material, but it could be applied to other robot variations. This work enables us to model the robot's collapse behavior in any open environment and understand the parameters it needs to succeed in 3D navigation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25727v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ciera McFarland, Margaret McGuinness</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GET-USE: Learning Generalized Tool Usage for Bimanual Mobile Manipulation via Simulated Embodiment Extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to use random objects as tools in a generalizable manner is a missing piece in robots' intelligence today to boost their versatility and problem-solving capabilities. State-of-the-art robotic tool usage methods focused on procedurally generating or crowd-sourcing datasets of tools for a task to learn how to grasp and manipulate them for that task. However, these methods assume that only one object is provided and that it is possible, with the correct grasp, to perform the task; they are not capable of identifying, grasping, and using the best object for a task when many are available, especially when the optimal tool is absent. In this work, we propose GeT-USE, a two-step procedure that learns to perform real-robot generalized tool usage by learning first to extend the robot's embodiment in simulation and then transferring the learned strategies to real-robot visuomotor policies. Our key insight is that by exploring a robot's embodiment extensions (i.e., building new end-effectors) in simulation, the robot can identify the general tool geometries most beneficial for a task. This learned geometric knowledge can then be distilled to perform generalized tool usage tasks by selecting and using the best available real-world object as tool. On a real robot with 22 degrees of freedom (DOFs), GeT-USE outperforms state-of-the-art methods by 30-60% success rates across three vision-based bimanual mobile manipulation tool-usage tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25754v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bohan Wu, Paul de La Sayette, Li Fei-Fei, Roberto Mart\'in-Mart\'in</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STITCH 2.0: Extending Augmented Suturing with EKF Needle Estimation and Thread Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surgical suturing is a high-precision task that impacts patient healing and scarring. Suturing skill varies widely between surgeons, highlighting the need for robot assistance. Previous robot suturing works, such as STITCH 1.0 [1], struggle to fully close wounds due to inaccurate needle tracking and poor thread management. To address these challenges, we present STITCH 2.0, an elevated augmented dexterity pipeline with seven improvements including: improved EKF needle pose estimation, new thread untangling methods, and an automated 3D suture alignment algorithm. Experimental results over 15 trials find that STITCH 2.0 on average achieves 74.4% wound closure with 4.87 sutures per trial, representing 66% more sutures in 38% less time compared to the previous baseline. When two human interventions are allowed, STITCH 2.0 averages six sutures with 100% wound closure rate. Project website: https://stitch-2.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25768v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2025.3625503</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kush Hari, Ziyang Chen, Hansoul Kim, Ken Goldberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DrivingScene: A Multi-Task Online Feed-Forward 3D Gaussian Splatting Method for Dynamic Driving Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Real-time, high-fidelity reconstruction of dynamic driving scenes is challenged by complex dynamics and sparse views, with prior methods struggling to balance quality and efficiency. We propose DrivingScene, an online, feed-forward framework that reconstructs 4D dynamic scenes from only two consecutive surround-view images. Our key innovation is a lightweight residual flow network that predicts the non-rigid motion of dynamic objects per camera on top of a learned static scene prior, explicitly modeling dynamics via scene flow. We also introduce a coarse-to-fine training paradigm that circumvents the instabilities common to end-to-end approaches. Experiments on nuScenes dataset show our image-only method simultaneously generates high-quality depth, scene flow, and 3D Gaussian point clouds online, significantly outperforming state-of-the-art methods in both dynamic reconstruction and novel view synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24734v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qirui Hou, Wenzhang Sun, Chang Zeng, Chunfeng Wang, Hao Li, Jianxun Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point-level Uncertainty Evaluation of Mobile Laser Scanning Point Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reliable quantification of uncertainty in Mobile Laser Scanning (MLS) point clouds is essential for ensuring the accuracy and credibility of downstream applications such as 3D mapping, modeling, and change analysis. Traditional backward uncertainty modeling heavily rely on high-precision reference data, which are often costly or infeasible to obtain at large scales. To address this issue, this study proposes a machine learning-based framework for point-level uncertainty evaluation that learns the relationship between local geometric features and point-level errors. The framework is implemented using two ensemble learning models, Random Forest (RF) and XGBoost, which are trained and validated on a spatially partitioned real-world dataset to avoid data leakage. Experimental results demonstrate that both models can effectively capture the nonlinear relationships between geometric characteristics and uncertainty, achieving mean ROC-AUC values above 0.87. The analysis further reveals that geometric features describing elevation variation, point density, and local structural complexity play a dominant role in predicting uncertainty. The proposed framework offers a data-driven perspective of uncertainty evaluation, providing a scalable and adaptable foundation for future quality control and error analysis of large-scale point clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24773v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyang Xu, Olaf Wysocki, Christoph Holst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Efficient Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24795v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vision-Language-Action models (VLAs) represent a significant frontier in embodied intelligence, aiming to bridge digital knowledge with physical-world interaction. While these models have demonstrated remarkable generalist capabilities, their deployment is severely hampered by the substantial computational and data requirements inherent to their underlying large-scale foundation models. Motivated by the urgent need to address these challenges, this survey presents the first comprehensive review of Efficient Vision-Language-Action models (Efficient VLAs) across the entire data-model-training process. Specifically, we introduce a unified taxonomy to systematically organize the disparate efforts in this domain, categorizing current techniques into three core pillars: (1) Efficient Model Design, focusing on efficient architectures and model compression; (2) Efficient Training, which reduces computational burdens during model learning; and (3) Efficient Data Collection, which addresses the bottlenecks in acquiring and utilizing robotic data. Through a critical review of state-of-the-art methods within this framework, this survey not only establishes a foundational reference for the community but also summarizes representative applications, delineates key challenges, and charts a roadmap for future research. We maintain a continuously updated project page to track our latest developments: https://evla-survey.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24795v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoshu Yu, Bo Wang, Pengpeng Zeng, Haonan Zhang, Ji Zhang, Lianli Gao, Jingkuan Song, Nicu Sebe, Heng Tao Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Clearly and Deeply: An RGBD Imaging Approach with a Bio-inspired Monocentric Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25314v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Achieving high-fidelity, compact RGBD imaging presents a dual challenge: conventional compact optics struggle with RGB sharpness across the entire depth-of-field, while software-only Monocular Depth Estimation (MDE) is an ill-posed problem reliant on unreliable semantic priors. While deep optics with elements like DOEs can encode depth, they introduce trade-offs in fabrication complexity and chromatic aberrations, compromising simplicity. To address this, we first introduce a novel bio-inspired all-spherical monocentric lens, around which we build the Bionic Monocentric Imaging (BMI) framework, a holistic co-design. This optical design naturally encodes depth into its depth-varying Point Spread Functions (PSFs) without requiring complex diffractive or freeform elements. We establish a rigorous physically-based forward model to generate a synthetic dataset by precisely simulating the optical degradation process. This simulation pipeline is co-designed with a dual-head, multi-scale reconstruction network that employs a shared encoder to jointly recover a high-fidelity All-in-Focus (AiF) image and a precise depth map from a single coded capture. Extensive experiments validate the state-of-the-art performance of the proposed framework. In depth estimation, the method attains an Abs Rel of 0.026 and an RMSE of 0.130, markedly outperforming leading software-only approaches and other deep optics systems. For image restoration, the system achieves an SSIM of 0.960 and a perceptual LPIPS score of 0.082, thereby confirming a superior balance between image fidelity and depth accuracy. This study illustrates that the integration of bio-inspired, fully spherical optics with a joint reconstruction algorithm constitutes an effective strategy for addressing the intrinsic challenges in high-performance compact RGBD imaging. Source code will be publicly available at https://github.com/ZongxiYu-ZJU/BMI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25314v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongxi Yu, Xiaolong Qian, Shaohua Gao, Qi Jiang, Yao Gao, Kailun Yang, Kaiwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPADE: Sparsity Adaptive Depth Estimator for Zero-Shot, Real-Time, Monocular Depth Estimation in Underwater Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Underwater infrastructure requires frequent inspection and maintenance due to harsh marine conditions. Current reliance on human divers or remotely operated vehicles is limited by perceptual and operational challenges, especially around complex structures or in turbid water. Enhancing the spatial awareness of underwater vehicles is key to reducing piloting risks and enabling greater autonomy. To address these challenges, we present SPADE: SParsity Adaptive Depth Estimator, a monocular depth estimation pipeline that combines pre-trained relative depth estimator with sparse depth priors to produce dense, metric scale depth maps. Our two-stage approach first scales the relative depth map with the sparse depth points, then refines the final metric prediction with our proposed Cascade Conv-Deformable Transformer blocks. Our approach achieves improved accuracy and generalisation over state-of-the-art baselines and runs efficiently at over 15 FPS on embedded hardware, promising to support practical underwater inspection and intervention. This work has been submitted to IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering Special Issue of AUV 2026.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25463v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongjie Zhang, Gideon Billings, Stefan B. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating Social Awareness into Control of Unknown Multi-Agent Systems: A Real-Time Spatiotemporal Tubes Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25597v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a decentralized control framework that incorporates social awareness into multi-agent systems with unknown dynamics to achieve prescribed-time reach-avoid-stay tasks in dynamic environments. Each agent is assigned a social awareness index that quantifies its level of cooperation or self-interest, allowing heterogeneous social behaviors within the system. Building on the spatiotemporal tube (STT) framework, we propose a real-time STT framework that synthesizes tubes online for each agent while capturing its social interactions with others. A closed-form, approximation-free control law is derived to ensure that each agent remains within its evolving STT, thereby avoiding dynamic obstacles while also preventing inter-agent collisions in a socially aware manner, and reaching the target within a prescribed time. The proposed approach provides formal guarantees on safety and timing, and is computationally lightweight, model-free, and robust to unknown disturbances. The effectiveness and scalability of the framework are validated through simulation and hardware experiments on a 2D omnidirectional</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25597v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddhartha Upadhyay, Ratnangshu Das, Pushpak Jagtap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Blind Your VLA: Aligning Visual Representations for OOD Generalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The growing success of Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models stems from the promise that pretrained Vision-Language Models (VLMs) can endow agents with transferable world knowledge and vision-language (VL) grounding, laying a foundation for action models with broader generalization. Yet when these VLMs are adapted to the action modality, it remains unclear to what extent their original VL representations and knowledge are preserved. In this work, we conduct a systematic study of representation retention during VLA fine-tuning, showing that naive action fine-tuning leads to degradation of visual representations. To characterize and measure these effects, we probe VLA's hidden representations and analyze attention maps, further, we design a set of targeted tasks and methods that contrast VLA models with their counterpart VLMs, isolating changes in VL capabilities induced by action fine-tuning. We further evaluate a range of strategies for aligning visual representations and introduce a simple yet effective method that mitigates degradation and yields improved generalization to out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios. Taken together, our analysis clarifies the trade-off between action fine-tuning and the degradation of VL representations and highlights practical approaches to recover inherited VL capabilities. Code is publicly available: https://blind-vla-paper.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25616v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Kachaev, Mikhail Kolosov, Daniil Zelezetsky, Alexey K. Kovalev, Aleksandr I. Panov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-robot Motion Planning based on Nets-within-Nets Modeling and Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.08772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.08772v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper focuses on designing motion plans for a heterogeneous team of robots that must cooperate to fulfill a global mission. Robots move in an environment that contains some regions of interest, while the specification for the entire team can include avoidance, visits, or sequencing of these regions of interest. The mission is expressed in terms of a Petri net corresponding to an automaton, while each robot is also modeled by a state machine Petri net. The current work brings about the following contributions with respect to existing solutions for related problems. First, we propose a novel model, denoted High-Level robot team Petri Net (HLrtPN) system, to incorporate the specification and robot models into the Nets-within-Nets paradigm. A guard function, named Global Enabling Function, is designed to synchronize the firing of transitions so that robot motions do not violate the specification. Then, the solution is found by simulating the HLrtPN system in a specific software tool that accommodates Nets-within-Nets. Illustrative examples based on Linear Temporal Logic missions support the computational feasibility of the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.08772v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sofia Hustiu, Joaquin Ezpeleta, Cristian Mahulea, Marius Kloetzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAT-RRT: Motion Planning that Admits Contact One Link at a Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06210v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current motion planning approaches rely on binary collision checking to evaluate the validity of a state and thereby dictate where the robot is allowed to move. This approach leaves little room for robots to engage in contact with an object, as is often necessary when operating in densely cluttered spaces. In this work, we propose an alternative method that considers contact states as high-cost states that the robot should avoid but can traverse if necessary to complete a task. More specifically, we introduce Contact Admissible Transition-based Rapidly exploring Random Trees (CAT-RRT), a planner that uses a novel per-link cost heuristic to find a path by traversing high-cost obstacle regions. Through extensive testing, we find that state-of-the-art optimization planners tend to over-explore low-cost states, which leads to slow and inefficient convergence to contact regions. Conversely, CAT-RRT searches both low and high-cost regions simultaneously with an adaptive thresholding mechanism carried out at each robot link. This leads to paths with a balance between efficiency, path length, and contact cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06210v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/IROS55552.2023.10341668</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nataliya Nechyporenko, Caleb Escobedo, Shreyas Kadekodi, Alessandro Roncone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Kinematic Synthesis and Prototype Development of Knee Exoskeleton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02635v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The range of rotation (RoR) in a knee exoskeleton is a critical factor in rehabilitation, as it directly influences joint mobility, muscle activation, and recovery outcomes. A well-designed RoR ensures that patients achieve near-natural knee kinematics, which is essential for restoring gait patterns and preventing compensatory movements. This paper presents optimal design of one degree of freedom knee exoskeleton. In kinematic analysis, the existing design being represented by nonlinear and nonconvex mathematical functions. To obtain feasible and optimum measurement of the links of knee exoskeleton, an optimization problem is formulated based on the kinematic analysis and average human's leg measurement. The optimized solution increases the range of motion of knee exoskeleton during sit to stand motion by $24 \%$ as compared with inspired design. Furthermore, misalignment study is conducted by comparing the trajectory of human's knee and exoskeleton's knee during sit to stand motion. The joint movement is calculated using marker and camera system. Finally, a prototype of the knee joint exoskeleton is being developed based on optimal dimensions which validate the maximum range of motion achieved during simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02635v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashank Mani Gautam, Ekta Singla, Ashish Singla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Federated Deep Reinforcement Learning for Privacy-Preserving Robotic-Assisted Surgery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12153v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The integration of Reinforcement Learning (RL) into robotic-assisted surgery (RAS) holds significant promise for advancing surgical precision, adaptability, and autonomous decision-making. However, the development of robust RL models in clinical settings is hindered by key challenges, including stringent patient data privacy regulations, limited access to diverse surgical datasets, and high procedural variability. To address these limitations, this paper presents a Federated Deep Reinforcement Learning (FDRL) framework that enables decentralized training of RL models across multiple healthcare institutions without exposing sensitive patient information. A central innovation of the proposed framework is its dynamic policy adaptation mechanism, which allows surgical robots to select and tailor patient-specific policies in real-time, thereby ensuring personalized and Optimised interventions. To uphold rigorous privacy standards while facilitating collaborative learning, the FDRL framework incorporates secure aggregation, differential privacy, and homomorphic encryption techniques. Experimental results demonstrate a 60\% reduction in privacy leakage compared to conventional methods, with surgical precision maintained within a 1.5\% margin of a centralized baseline. This work establishes a foundational approach for adaptive, secure, and patient-centric AI-driven surgical robotics, offering a pathway toward clinical translation and scalable deployment across diverse healthcare environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12153v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE ICDCS 2025 45th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems. Workshop on Federated and Privacy Preserving AI in Biomedical Applications (FPPAI), Glasgow, United Kingdom</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sana Hafeez, Sundas Rafat Mulkana, Muhammad Ali Imran, Michele Sevegnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Path Planning and Task Allocation Algorithm for Boolean Specifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04881v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel path-planning and task assignment algorithm for multi-robot systems that should fulfill a global Boolean specification. The proposed method is based on Integer Linear Programming (ILP) formulations, which are combined with structural insights from Petri nets to improve scalability and computational efficiency. By proving that the \emph{constraint matrix} is totally unimodular (TU) for certain classes of problems, the ILP formulation can be relaxed into a Linear Programming (LP) problem without losing the integrality of the solution. This relaxation eliminates complex combinatorial techniques, significantly reducing computational overhead and thus ensuring scalability for large-scale systems. Using the approach proposed in this paper, we can solve path-planning problems for teams made up to 500 robots. The method guarantees computational tractability, handles collision avoidance and reduces computational demands through iterative LP optimization techniques. Case studies demonstrate the efficiency of the algorithm in generating scalable, collision-free paths for large robot teams navigating in complex environments. While the conservative nature of collision avoidance introduces additional constraints, and thus, computational requirements, the solution remains practical and impactful for diverse applications. The algorithm is particularly applicable to real-world scenarios, including warehouse logistics where autonomous robots must efficiently coordinate tasks or search-and-rescue operations in various environments. This work contributes both theoretically and practically to scalable multi-robot path planning and task allocation, offering an efficient framework for coordinating autonomous agents in shared environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04881v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioana Hustiu, Roozbeh Abolpour, Cristian Mahulea, Marius Kloetzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboCerebra: A Large-scale Benchmark for Long-horizon Robotic Manipulation Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06677v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in vision-language models (VLMs) have enabled instruction-conditioned robotic systems with improved generalization. However, most existing work focuses on reactive System 1 policies, underutilizing VLMs' strengths in semantic reasoning and long-horizon planning. These System 2 capabilities-characterized by deliberative, goal-directed thinking-remain under explored due to the limited temporal scale and structural complexity of current benchmarks. To address this gap, we introduce RoboCerebra, a benchmark for evaluating high-level reasoning in long-horizon robotic manipulation. RoboCerebra includes: (1) a large-scale simulation dataset with extended task horizons and diverse subtask sequences in household environments; (2) a hierarchical framework combining a high-level VLM planner with a low-level vision-language-action (VLA) controller; and (3) an evaluation protocol targeting planning, reflection, and memory through structured System 1-System 2 interaction. The dataset is constructed via a top-down pipeline, where GPT generates task instructions and decomposes them into subtask sequences. Human operators execute the subtasks in simulation, yielding high-quality trajectories with dynamic object variations. Compared to prior benchmarks, RoboCerebra features significantly longer action sequences and denser annotations. We further benchmark state-of-the-art VLMs as System 2 modules and analyze their performance across key cognitive dimensions, advancing the development of more capable and generalizable robotic planners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06677v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songhao Han, Boxiang Qiu, Yue Liao, Siyuan Huang, Chen Gao, Shuicheng Yan, Si Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Adaptation for Flying Quadrotors in Tight Formations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17488v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The task of flying in tight formations is challenging for teams of quadrotors because the complex aerodynamic wake interactions can destabilize individual team members as well as the team. Furthermore, these aerodynamic effects are highly nonlinear and fast-paced, making them difficult to model and predict. To overcome these challenges, we present L1 KNODE-DW MPC, an adaptive, mixed expert learning based control framework that allows individual quadrotors to accurately track trajectories while adapting to time-varying aerodynamic interactions during formation flights. We evaluate L1 KNODE-DW MPC in two different three-quadrotor formations and show that it outperforms several MPC baselines. Our results show that the proposed framework is capable of enabling the three-quadrotor team to remain vertically aligned in close proximity throughout the flight. These findings show that the L1 adaptive module compensates for unmodeled disturbances most effectively when paired with an accurate dynamics model. A video showcasing our framework and the physical experiments is available here: https://youtu.be/9QX1Q5Ut9Rs</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17488v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-An Hsieh, Kong Yao Chee, M. Ani Hsieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EquiContact: A Hierarchical SE(3) Vision-to-Force Equivariant Policy for Spatially Generalizable Contact-rich Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10961v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a framework for learning vision-based robotic policies for contact-rich manipulation tasks that generalize spatially across task configurations. We focus on achieving robust spatial generalization of the policy for the peg-in-hole (PiH) task trained from a small number of demonstrations. We propose EquiContact, a hierarchical policy composed of a high-level vision planner (Diffusion Equivariant Descriptor Field, Diff-EDF) and a novel low-level compliant visuomotor policy (Geometric Compliant ACT, G-CompACT). G-CompACT operates using only localized observations (geometrically consistent error vectors (GCEV), force-torque readings, and wrist-mounted RGB images) and produces actions defined in the end-effector frame. Through these design choices, we show that the entire EquiContact pipeline is SE(3)-equivariant, from perception to force control. We also outline three key components for spatially generalizable contact-rich policies: compliance, localized policies, and induced equivariance. Real-world experiments on PiH, screwing, and surface wiping tasks demonstrate a near-perfect success rate and robust generalization to unseen spatial configurations, validating the proposed framework and principles. The experimental videos can be found on the project website: https://sites.google.com/berkeley.edu/equicontact</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10961v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joohwan Seo, Arvind Kruthiventy, Soomi Lee, Megan Teng, Xiang Zhang, Seoyeon Choi, Jongeun Choi, Roberto Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control Modes of Teleoperated Surgical Robotic System's Tools in Ophthalmic Surgery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13654v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The introduction of a teleoperated surgical robotic system designed for minimally invasive procedures enables the emulation of two distinct control modes through a dedicated input device of the surgical console: (1) Inside Control Mode, which emulates tool manipulation near the distal end as if the surgeon was holding the tip of the instrument inside the patient's body; (2) Outside Control Mode, which emulates manipulation near the proximal end as if the surgeon was holding the tool externally. The aim of this research is to compare the surgeon's performance on these two modes of operation along with various scaling factors in a simulated vitreoretinal surgical setting. The console of Intraocular Robotic Interventional Surgical System (IRISS) was utilized but the surgical robot itself and the human eye anatomy was simulated by a virtual environment projected microscope view of an intraocular setup to a VR headset. Five experienced vitreoretinal surgeons and five subjects with no surgical experience used the system to perform four fundamental tool/tissue tasks common to vitreoretinal surgery: touch and reset; grasp and drop; inject; circular tracking. Results indicate that Inside Control outperforms Outside Control across multiple tasks and metrics. Higher scaling factors generally performed better, particularly for reducing trajectory errors and tissue damage. This improvement suggests that larger scaling factors enable more precise control, making them the preferred option for fine manipulation. However, completion time was not consistently reduced across all conditions, indicating that surgeons need to balance speed and accuracy based on surgical requirements. By optimizing control dynamics and user interface, robotic teleoperation has the potential to reduce complications, enhance dexterity, and expand the accessibility of high precision procedures to a broader range of practitioners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13654v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TMRB.2025.3604102</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Haoran Wang, Yasamin Foroutani, Matthew Nepo, Mercedes Rodriguez, Ji Ma, Jean-Pierre Hubschman, Tsu-Chin Tsao, Jacob Rosen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Machine Learning and Grover's Algorithm for Quantum Optimization of Robotic Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07216v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Optimizing high-degree of freedom robotic manipulators requires searching complex, high-dimensional configuration spaces, a task that is computationally challenging for classical methods. This paper introduces a quantum native framework that integrates quantum machine learning with Grover's algorithm to solve kinematic optimization problems efficiently. A parameterized quantum circuit is trained to approximate the forward kinematics model, which then constructs an oracle to identify optimal configurations. Grover's algorithm leverages this oracle to provide a quadratic reduction in search complexity. Demonstrated on simulated 1-DoF, 2-DoF, and dual-arm manipulator tasks, the method achieves significant speedups-up to 93x over classical optimizers like Nelder Mead as problem dimensionality increases. This work establishes a foundational, quantum-native framework for robot kinematic optimization, effectively bridging quantum computing and robotics problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07216v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2025.3627071</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hassen Nigatu, Shi Gaokun, Li Jituo, Wang Jin, Lu Guodong, Howard Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomy and Trends in Reinforcement Learning for Robotics and Control Systems: A Structured Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21758v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reinforcement learning (RL) has become a foundational approach for enabling intelligent robotic behavior in dynamic and uncertain environments. This work presents an in-depth review of RL principles, advanced deep reinforcement learning (DRL) algorithms, and their integration into robotic and control systems. Beginning with the formalism of Markov Decision Processes (MDPs), the study outlines essential elements of the agent-environment interaction and explores core algorithmic strategies including actor-critic methods, value-based learning, and policy gradients. Emphasis is placed on modern DRL techniques such as DDPG, TD3, PPO, and SAC, which have shown promise in solving high-dimensional, continuous control tasks. A structured taxonomy is introduced to categorize RL applications across domains such as locomotion, manipulation, multi-agent coordination, and human-robot interaction, along with training methodologies and deployment readiness levels. The review synthesizes recent research efforts, highlighting technical trends, design patterns, and the growing maturity of RL in real-world robotics. Overall, this work aims to bridge theoretical advances with practical implementations, providing a consolidated perspective on the evolving role of RL in autonomous robotic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21758v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kumater Ter, Ore-Ofe Ajayi, Daniel Udekwe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboOmni: Proactive Robot Manipulation in Omni-modal Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have driven rapid progress in Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models for robotic manipulation. Although effective in many scenarios, current approaches largely rely on explicit instructions, whereas in real-world interactions, humans rarely issue instructions directly. Effective collaboration requires robots to infer user intentions proactively. In this work, we introduce cross-modal contextual instructions, a new setting where intent is derived from spoken dialogue, environmental sounds, and visual cues rather than explicit commands. To address this new setting, we present RoboOmni, a Perceiver-Thinker-Talker-Executor framework based on end-to-end omni-modal LLMs that unifies intention recognition, interaction confirmation, and action execution. RoboOmni fuses auditory and visual signals spatiotemporally for robust intention recognition, while supporting direct speech interaction. To address the absence of training data for proactive intention recognition in robotic manipulation, we build OmniAction, comprising 140k episodes, 5k+ speakers, 2.4k event sounds, 640 backgrounds, and six contextual instruction types. Experiments in simulation and real-world settings show that RoboOmni surpasses text- and ASR-based baselines in success rate, inference speed, intention recognition, and proactive assistance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23763v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyin Wang, Jinlan Fu, Feihong Liu, Xinzhe He, Huangxuan Wu, Junhao Shi, Kexin Huang, Zhaoye Fei, Jingjing Gong, Zuxuan Wu, Yugang Jiang, See-Kiong Ng, Tat-Seng Chua, Xipeng Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SNN-Based Online Learning of Concepts and Action Laws in an Open World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12308v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the architecture of a fully autonomous, bio-inspired cognitive agent built around a spiking neural network (SNN) implementing the agent's semantic memory. This agent explores its universe and learns concepts of objects/situations and of its own actions in a one-shot manner. While object/situation concepts are unary, action concepts are triples made up of an initial situation, a motor activity, and an outcome. They embody the agent's knowledge of its universe's action laws. Both kinds of concepts have different degrees of generality. To make decisions the agent queries its semantic memory for the expected outcomes of envisaged actions and chooses the action to take on the basis of these predictions. Our experiments show that the agent handles new situations by appealing to previously learned general concepts and rapidly modifies its concepts to adapt to environment changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12308v4</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christel Grimaud (IRIT-LILaC), Dominique Longin (IRIT-LILaC), Andreas Herzig (IRIT-LILaC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redistributing Rewards Across Time and Agents for Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04864v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Credit assignmen, disentangling each agent's contribution to a shared reward, is a critical challenge in cooperative multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL). To be effective, credit assignment methods must preserve the environment's optimal policy. Some recent approaches attempt this by enforcing return equivalence, where the sum of distributed rewards must equal the team reward. However, their guarantees are conditional on a learned model's regression accuracy, making them unreliable in practice. We introduce Temporal-Agent Reward Redistribution (TAR$^2$), an approach that decouples credit modeling from this constraint. A neural network learns unnormalized contribution scores, while a separate, deterministic normalization step enforces return equivalence by construction. We demonstrate that this method is equivalent to a valid Potential-Based Reward Shaping (PBRS), which guarantees the optimal policy is preserved regardless of model accuracy. Empirically, on challenging SMACLite and Google Research Football (GRF) benchmarks, TAR$^2$ accelerates learning and achieves higher final performance than strong baselines. These results establish our method as an effective solution for the agent-temporal credit assignment problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04864v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Kapoor, Kale-ab Tessera, Mayank Baranwal, Harshad Khadilkar, Jan Peters, Stefano Albrecht, Mingfei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ES-HPC-MPC: Exponentially Stable Hybrid Perception Constrained MPC for Quadrotor with Suspended Payloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08841v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aerial transportation using quadrotors with cable-suspended payloads holds great potential for applications in disaster response, logistics, and infrastructure maintenance. However, their hybrid and underactuated dynamics pose significant control and perception challenges. Traditional approaches often assume a taut cable condition, limiting their effectiveness in real-world applications where slack-to-taut transitions occur due to disturbances. We introduce ES-HPC-MPC, a model predictive control framework that enforces exponential stability and perception-constrained control under hybrid dynamics.
  Our method leverages Exponentially Stabilizing Control Lyapunov Functions (ES-CLFs) to enforce stability during the tasks and Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) to maintain the payload within the onboard camera's field of view (FoV). We validate our method through both simulation and real-world experiments, demonstrating stable trajectory tracking and reliable payload perception. We validate that our method maintains stability and satisfies perception constraints while tracking dynamically infeasible trajectories and when the system is subjected to hybrid mode transitions caused by unexpected disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08841v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis F. Recalde, Mrunal Sarvaiya, Giuseppe Loianno, Guanrui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Driver Behaviour Using External Observation Techniques for Autonomous Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09349v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Road traffic accidents remain a significant global concern, with human error, particularly distracted and impaired driving, among the leading causes. This study introduces a novel driver behaviour classification system that uses external observation techniques to detect indicators of distraction and impairment. The proposed framework employs advanced computer vision methodologies, including real-time object tracking, lateral displacement analysis, and lane position monitoring. The system identifies unsafe driving behaviours such as excessive lateral movement and erratic trajectory patterns by implementing the YOLO object detection model and custom lane estimation algorithms. Unlike systems reliant on inter-vehicular communication, this vision-based approach enables behavioural analysis of non-connected vehicles. Experimental evaluations on diverse video datasets demonstrate the framework's reliability and adaptability across varying road and environmental conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09349v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Nell, Shane Gilroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-Regularized Riccati Recursions for Interior-Point Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16370v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive closed-form extensions of Riccati's recursions (both sequential and parallel) for solving dual-regularized LQR problems. We show how these methods can be used to solve general constrained, non-convex, discrete-time optimal control problems via a regularized interior point method, while guaranteeing that each step is a descent direction of an Augmented Barrier-Lagrangian merit function. We provide MIT-licensed implementations of our methods in C++ and JAX.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16370v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Sousa-Pinto, Dominique Orban</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
