<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Jump Point Search Pathfinding in 4-connected Grids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work introduces JPS4, a novel pathfinding algorithm for 4-connected grid maps. JPS4 builds upon the Jump Point Search (JPS8) algorithm, originally designed for 8-connected environments. To achieve efficient pathfinding on 4-connected grids, JPS4 employs a canonical ordering and a successor function that enable online graph pruning. This reduces the search space by minimizing unnecessary node expansions.
  The core concept of JPS4 as well as JPS8 lies in the utilization of jump points. Strategically placed at obstacle corners, jump points prevent the search from overlooking crucial sections of the state space. They essentially reinitialize the canonical ordering, allowing exploration beyond obstacles. This mechanism ensures JPS4 finds optimal paths even in complex environments.
  The paper further explores the optimality of JPS4 and compares its performance against the established A* algorithm on various grid maps. Benchmarking results demonstrate that JPS4 significantly outperforms A* in scenarios with high obstacle density. However, A* remains more efficient on open maps. Overall, JPS4 presents itself as a promising alternative to A* for pathfinding on 4-connected grids, particularly applicable in video game development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14816v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Baum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-conditioned Energy-based Annealed Rewards (NEAR): A Generative Framework for Imitation Learning from Observation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new imitation learning framework based on energy-based generative models capable of learning complex, physics-dependent, robot motion policies through state-only expert motion trajectories. Our algorithm, called Noise-conditioned Energy-based Annealed Rewards (NEAR), constructs several perturbed versions of the expert's motion data distribution and learns smooth, and well-defined representations of the data distribution's energy function using denoising score matching. We propose to use these learnt energy functions as reward functions to learn imitation policies via reinforcement learning. We also present a strategy to gradually switch between the learnt energy functions, ensuring that the learnt rewards are always well-defined in the manifold of policy-generated samples. We evaluate our algorithm on complex humanoid tasks such as locomotion and martial arts and compare it with state-only adversarial imitation learning algorithms like Adversarial Motion Priors (AMP). Our framework sidesteps the optimisation challenges of adversarial imitation learning techniques and produces results comparable to AMP in several quantitative metrics across multiple imitation settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14856v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anish Abhijit Diwan, Julen Urain, Jens Kober, Jan Peters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Binding Foundation Model for Material Property Recognition via Tactile Sequence Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14934v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robots engaged in complex manipulation tasks require robust material property recognition to ensure adaptability and precision. Traditionally, visual data has been the primary source for object perception; however, it often proves insufficient in scenarios where visibility is obstructed or detailed observation is needed. This gap highlights the necessity of tactile sensing as a complementary or primary input for material recognition. Tactile data becomes particularly essential in contact-rich, small-scale manipulations where subtle deformations and surface interactions cannot be accurately captured by vision alone. This letter presents a novel approach leveraging a temporal binding foundation model for tactile sequence understanding to enhance material property recognition. By processing tactile sensor data with a temporal focus, the proposed system captures the sequential nature of tactile interactions, similar to human fingertip perception. Additionally, this letter demonstrates that, through tailored and specific design, the foundation model can more effectively capture temporal information embedded in tactile sequences, advancing material property understanding. Experimental results validate the model's capability to capture these temporal patterns, confirming its utility for material property recognition in visually restricted scenarios. This work underscores the necessity of embedding advanced tactile data processing frameworks within robotic systems to achieve truly embodied and responsive manipulation capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14934v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengxu You, Tianyu Zhou, Jing Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force-Based Robotic Imitation Learning: A Two-Phase Approach for Construction Assembly Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The drive for efficiency and safety in construction has boosted the role of robotics and automation. However, complex tasks like welding and pipe insertion pose challenges due to their need for precise adaptive force control, which complicates robotic training. This paper proposes a two-phase system to improve robot learning, integrating human-derived force feedback. The first phase captures real-time data from operators using a robot arm linked with a virtual simulator via ROS-Sharp. In the second phase, this feedback is converted into robotic motion instructions, using a generative approach to incorporate force feedback into the learning process. This method's effectiveness is demonstrated through improved task completion times and success rates. The framework simulates realistic force-based interactions, enhancing the training data's quality for precise robotic manipulation in construction tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14942v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengxu You, Yang Ye, Tianyu Zhou, Jing Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Atomic Skill Library Construction Method for Data-Efficient Embodied Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Embodied manipulation is a fundamental ability in the realm of embodied artificial intelligence. Although current embodied manipulation models show certain generalizations in specific settings, they struggle in new environments and tasks due to the complexity and diversity of real-world scenarios. The traditional end-to-end data collection and training manner leads to significant data demands, which we call ``data explosion''. To address the issue, we introduce a three-wheeled data-driven method to build an atomic skill library. We divide tasks into subtasks using the Vision-Language Planning (VLP). Then, atomic skill definitions are formed by abstracting the subtasks. Finally, an atomic skill library is constructed via data collection and Vision-Language-Action (VLA) fine-tuning. As the atomic skill library expands dynamically with the three-wheel update strategy, the range of tasks it can cover grows naturally. In this way, our method shifts focus from end-to-end tasks to atomic skills, significantly reducing data costs while maintaining high performance and enabling efficient adaptation to new tasks. Extensive experiments in real-world settings demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15068v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongjiang Li, Bo Peng, Chang Li, Ning Qiao, Qi Zheng, Lei Sun, Yusen Qin, Bangguo Li, Yifeng Luan, Yibing Zhan, Mingang Sun, Tong Xu, Lusong Li, Hui Shen, Xiaodong He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding via Gaze: Gaze-based Task Decomposition for Imitation Learning of Robot Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In imitation learning for robotic manipulation, decomposing object manipulation tasks into multiple semantic actions is essential. This decomposition enables the reuse of learned skills in varying contexts and the combination of acquired skills to perform novel tasks, rather than merely replicating demonstrated motions. Gaze, an evolutionary tool for understanding ongoing events, plays a critical role in human object manipulation, where it strongly correlates with motion planning. In this study, we propose a simple yet robust task decomposition method based on gaze transitions. We hypothesize that an imitation agent's gaze control, fixating on specific landmarks and transitioning between them, naturally segments demonstrated manipulations into sub-tasks. Notably, our method achieves consistent task decomposition across all demonstrations, which is desirable in contexts such as machine learning. Using teleoperation, a common modality in imitation learning for robotic manipulation, we collected demonstration data for various tasks, applied our segmentation method, and evaluated the characteristics and consistency of the resulting sub-tasks. Furthermore, through extensive testing across a wide range of hyperparameter variations, we demonstrated that the proposed method possesses the robustness necessary for application to different robotic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15071v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Takizawa, Yoshiyuki Ohmura, Yasuo Kuniyoshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact-resistant, autonomous robots inspired by tensegrity architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Future robots will navigate perilous, remote environments with resilience and autonomy. Researchers have proposed building robots with compliant bodies to enhance robustness, but this approach often sacrifices the autonomous capabilities expected of rigid robots. Inspired by tensegrity architecture, we introduce a tensegrity robot -- a hybrid robot made from rigid struts and elastic tendons -- that demonstrates the advantages of compliance and the autonomy necessary for task performance. This robot boasts impact resistance and autonomy in a field environment and additional advances in the state of the art, including surviving harsh impacts from drops (at least 5.7 m), accurately reconstructing its shape and orientation using on-board sensors, achieving high locomotion speeds (18 bar lengths per minute), and climbing the steepest incline of any tensegrity robot (28 degrees). We characterize the robot's locomotion on unstructured terrain, showcase its autonomous capabilities in navigation tasks, and demonstrate its robustness by rolling it off a cliff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15078v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William R. Johnson III, Xiaonan Huang, Shiyang Lu, Kun Wang, Joran W. Booth, Kostas Bekris, Rebecca Kramer-Bottiglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Conscious Service Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning's success in perception, natural language processing, etc. inspires hopes for advancements in autonomous robotics. However, real-world robotics face challenges like variability, high-dimensional state spaces, non-linear dependencies, and partial observability. A key issue is non-stationarity of robots, environments, and tasks, leading to performance drops with out-of-distribution data. Unlike current machine learning models, humans adapt quickly to changes and new tasks due to a cognitive architecture that enables systematic generalization and meta-cognition. Human brain's System 1 handles routine tasks unconsciously, while System 2 manages complex tasks consciously, facilitating flexible problem-solving and self-monitoring. For robots to achieve human-like learning and reasoning, they need to integrate causal models, working memory, planning, and metacognitive processing. By incorporating human cognition insights, the next generation of service robots will handle novel situations and monitor themselves to avoid risks and mitigate errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15198v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Behnke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-shot Robotic Manipulation with Language-guided Instruction and Formal Task Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic manipulation is often challenging due to the long-horizon tasks and the complex object relationships. A common solution is to develop a task and motion planning framework that integrates planning for high-level task and low-level motion. Recently, inspired by the powerful reasoning ability of Large Language Models (LLMs), LLM-based planning approaches have achieved remarkable progress. However, these methods still heavily rely on expert-specific knowledge, often generating invalid plans for unseen and unfamiliar tasks. To address this issue, we propose an innovative language-guided symbolic task planning (LM-SymOpt) framework with optimization. It is the first expert-free planning framework since we combine the world knowledge from LLMs with formal reasoning, resulting in improved generalization capability to new tasks. Specifically, differ to most existing work, our LM-SymOpt employs LLMs to translate natural language instructions into symbolic representations, thereby representing actions as high-level symbols and reducing the search space for planning. Next, after evaluating the action probability of completing the task using LLMs, a weighted random sampling method is introduced to generate candidate plans. Their feasibility is assessed through symbolic reasoning and their cost efficiency is then evaluated using trajectory optimization for selecting the optimal planning. Our experimental results show that LM-SymOpt outperforms existing LLM-based planning approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15214v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junfeng Tang, Zihan Ye, Yuping Yan, Ziqi Zheng, Ting Gao, Yaochu Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe and Agile Transportation of Cable-Suspended Payload via Multiple Aerial Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transporting a heavy payload using multiple aerial robots (MARs) is an efficient manner to extend the load capacity of a single aerial robot. However, existing schemes for the multiple aerial robots transportation system (MARTS) still lack the capability to generate a collision-free and dynamically feasible trajectory in real-time and further track an agile trajectory especially when there are no sensors available to measure the states of payload and cable. Therefore, they are limited to low-agility transportation in simple environments. To bridge the gap, we propose complete planning and control schemes for the MARTS, achieving safe and agile aerial transportation (SAAT) of a cable-suspended payload in complex environments. Flatness maps for the aerial robot considering the complete kinematical constraint and the dynamical coupling between each aerial robot and payload are derived. To improve the responsiveness for the generation of the safe, dynamically feasible, and agile trajectory in complex environments, a real-time spatio-temporal trajectory planning scheme is proposed for the MARTS. Besides, we break away from the reliance on the state measurement for both the payload and cable, as well as the closed-loop control for the payload, and propose a fully distributed control scheme to track the agile trajectory that is robust against imprecise payload mass and non-point mass payload. The proposed schemes are extensively validated through benchmark comparisons, ablation studies, and simulations. Finally, extensive real-world experiments are conducted on a MARTS integrated by three aerial robots with onboard computers and sensors. The result validates the efficiency and robustness of our proposed schemes for SAAT in complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15272v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongchao Wang, Junjie Wang, Xiaobin Zhou, Tiankai Yang, Chao Xu, Fei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAVbot: An Autonomous Target Tracking Micro-Robot with Frequency Actuation Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic autonomy at centimeter scale requires compact and miniaturization-friendly actuation integrated with sensing and neural network processing assembly within a tiny form factor. Applications of such systems have witnessed significant advancements in recent years in fields such as healthcare, manufacturing, and post-disaster rescue. The system design at this scale puts stringent constraints on power consumption for both the sensory front-end and actuation back-end and the weight of the electronic assembly for robust operation. In this paper, we introduce FAVbot, the first autonomous mobile micro-robotic system integrated with a novel actuation mechanism and convolutional neural network (CNN) based computer vision - all integrated within a compact 3-cm form factor. The novel actuation mechanism utilizes mechanical resonance phenomenon to achieve frequency-controlled steering with a single piezoelectric actuator. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of FAVbot's frequency-controlled actuation, which offers a diverse selection of resonance modes with different motion characteristics. The actuation system is complemented with the vision front-end where a camera along with a microcontroller supports object detection for closed-loop control and autonomous target tracking. This enables adaptive navigation in dynamic environments. This work contributes to the evolving landscape of neural network-enabled micro-robotic systems showing the smallest autonomous robot built using controllable multi-directional single-actuator mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15426v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhijian Hao, Ashwin Lele, Yan Fang, Arijit Raychowdhury, Azadeh Ansari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the Potential of iMarkers: Invisible Fiducial Markers for Advanced Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15505v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fiducial markers are widely used in various robotics tasks, facilitating enhanced navigation, object recognition, and scene understanding. Despite their advantages for robots and Augmented Reality (AR) applications, they often disrupt the visual aesthetics of environments because they are visible to humans, making them unsuitable for non-intrusive use cases. To address this gap, this paper presents "iMarkers"-innovative, unobtrusive fiducial markers detectable exclusively by robots equipped with specialized sensors. These markers offer high flexibility in production, allowing customization of their visibility range and encoding algorithms to suit various demands. The paper also introduces the hardware designs and software algorithms developed for detecting iMarkers, highlighting their adaptability and robustness in the detection and recognition stages. Various evaluations have demonstrated the effectiveness of iMarkers compared to conventional (printed) and blended fiducial markers and confirmed their applicability in diverse robotics scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15505v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Tourani, Deniz Isinsu Avsar, Hriday Bavle, Jose Luis Sanchez-Lopez, Jan Lagerwall, Holger Voos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-Based Planning for Autonomous Driving with Flexible Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving human-like driving behaviors in complex open-world environments is a critical challenge in autonomous driving. Contemporary learning-based planning approaches such as imitation learning methods often struggle to balance competing objectives and lack of safety assurance,due to limited adaptability and inadequacy in learning complex multi-modal behaviors commonly exhibited in human planning, not to mention their strong reliance on the fallback strategy with predefined rules. We propose a novel transformer-based Diffusion Planner for closed-loop planning, which can effectively model multi-modal driving behavior and ensure trajectory quality without any rule-based refinement. Our model supports joint modeling of both prediction and planning tasks under the same architecture, enabling cooperative behaviors between vehicles. Moreover, by learning the gradient of the trajectory score function and employing a flexible classifier guidance mechanism, Diffusion Planner effectively achieves safe and adaptable planning behaviors. Evaluations on the large-scale real-world autonomous planning benchmark nuPlan and our newly collected 200-hour delivery-vehicle driving dataset demonstrate that Diffusion Planner achieves state-of-the-art closed-loop performance with robust transferability in diverse driving styles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15564v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinan Zheng, Ruiming Liang, Kexin Zheng, Jinliang Zheng, Liyuan Mao, Jianxiong Li, Weihao Gu, Rui Ai, Shengbo Eben Li, Xianyuan Zhan, Jingjing Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Your Learned Constraint is Secretly a Backward Reachable Tube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inverse Constraint Learning (ICL) is the problem of inferring constraints from safe (i.e., constraint-satisfying) demonstrations. The hope is that these inferred constraints can then be used downstream to search for safe policies for new tasks and, potentially, under different dynamics. Our paper explores the question of what mathematical entity ICL recovers. Somewhat surprisingly, we show that both in theory and in practice, ICL recovers the set of states where failure is inevitable, rather than the set of states where failure has already happened. In the language of safe control, this means we recover a backwards reachable tube (BRT) rather than a failure set. In contrast to the failure set, the BRT depends on the dynamics of the data collection system. We discuss the implications of the dynamics-conditionedness of the recovered constraint on both the sample-efficiency of policy search and the transferability of learned constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15618v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamad Qadri, Gokul Swamy, Jonathan Francis, Michael Kaess, Andrea Bajcsy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AirIO: Learning Inertial Odometry with Enhanced IMU Feature Observability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inertial odometry (IO) using only Inertial Measurement Units (IMUs) offers a lightweight and cost-effective solution for Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV) applications, yet existing learning-based IO models often fail to generalize to UAVs due to the highly dynamic and non-linear-flight patterns that differ from pedestrian motion. In this work, we identify that the conventional practice of transforming raw IMU data to global coordinates undermines the observability of critical kinematic information in UAVs. By preserving the body-frame representation, our method achieves substantial performance improvements, with a 66.7% average increase in accuracy across three datasets. Furthermore, explicitly encoding attitude information into the motion network results in an additional 23.8% improvement over prior results. Combined with a data-driven IMU correction model (AirIMU) and an uncertainty-aware Extended Kalman Filter (EKF), our approach ensures robust state estimation under aggressive UAV maneuvers without relying on external sensors or control inputs. Notably, our method also demonstrates strong generalizability to unseen data not included in the training set, underscoring its potential for real-world UAV applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15659v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuheng Qiu, Can Xu, Yutian Chen, Shibo Zhao, Junyi Geng, Sebastian Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-State LQR Formulation for Quadrotor UAV Trajectory Tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article presents an error-state Linear Quadratic Regulator (LQR) formulation for robust trajectory tracking in quadrotor Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs). The proposed approach leverages error-state dynamics and employs exponential coordinates to represent orientation errors, enabling a linearized system representation for real-time control. The control strategy integrates an LQR-based full-state feedback controller for trajectory tracking, combined with a cascaded bodyrate controller to handle actuator dynamics. Detailed derivations of the error-state dynamics, the linearization process, and the controller design are provided, highlighting the applicability of the method for precise and stable quadrotor control in dynamic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15768v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micah Reich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Horizon-based Asteroid Navigation With Observability-constrained Maneuvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Asteroid exploration is a pertinent challenge due to the varying complexity of their dynamical environments, shape and communication delays due to distance. Thus, autonomous navigation methods are continually being developed and improved in current research to enable their safe exploration. These methods often involve using horizon-based Optical Navigation (OpNav) to determine the spacecraft's location, which is reliant on the visibility of the horizon. It is critical to ensure the reliability of this measurement such that the spacecraft may maintain an accurate state estimate throughout its mission. This paper presents an algorithm that generates control maneuvers for spacecraft to follow trajectories that allow continuously usable optical measurements to maintain system observability for safe navigation. This algorithm improves upon existing asteroid navigation capabilities by allowing the safe and robust autonomous targeting of various trajectories and orbits at a wide range of distances within optical measurement range. It is adaptable to different asteroid scenarios. Overall, the approach develops an all-encompassing system that simulates the asteroid dynamics, synthetic image generation, edge detection, horizon-based OpNav, filtering and observability-enhancing control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15806v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Arjun Anibha, Kenshiro Oguri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpatialVLA: Exploring Spatial Representations for Visual-Language-Action Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15830v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we claim that spatial understanding is the keypoint in robot manipulation, and propose SpatialVLA to explore effective spatial representations for the robot foundation model. Specifically, we introduce Ego3D Position Encoding to inject 3D information into the input observations of the visual-language-action model, and propose Adaptive Action Grids to represent spatial robot movement actions with adaptive discretized action grids, facilitating learning generalizable and transferrable spatial action knowledge for cross-robot control. SpatialVLA is first pre-trained on top of a vision-language model with 1.1 Million real-world robot episodes, to learn a generalist manipulation policy across multiple robot environments and tasks. After pre-training, SpatialVLA is directly applied to perform numerous tasks in a zero-shot manner. The superior results in both simulation and real-world robots demonstrate its advantage of inferring complex robot motion trajectories and its strong in-domain multi-task generalization ability. We further show the proposed Adaptive Action Grids offer a new and effective way to fine-tune the pre-trained SpatialVLA model for new simulation and real-world setups, where the pre-learned action grids are re-discretized to capture robot-specific spatial action movements of new setups. The superior results from extensive evaluations demonstrate the exceptional in-distribution generalization and out-of-distribution adaptation capability, highlighting the crucial benefit of the proposed spatial-aware representations for generalist robot policy learning. All the details and codes will be open-sourced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15830v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Delin Qu, Haoming Song, Qizhi Chen, Yuanqi Yao, Xinyi Ye, Yan Ding, Zhigang Wang, JiaYuan Gu, Bin Zhao, Dong Wang, Xuelong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Mobile Robot Path Planning via LLM-Based Dynamic Waypoint Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobile robot path planning in complex environments remains a significant challenge, especially in achieving efficient, safe and robust paths. The traditional path planning techniques like DRL models typically trained for a given configuration of the starting point and target positions, these models only perform well when these conditions are satisfied. In this paper, we proposed a novel path planning framework that embeds Large Language Models to empower mobile robots with the capability of dynamically interpreting natural language commands and autonomously generating efficient, collision-free navigation paths. The proposed framework uses LLMs to translate high-level user inputs into actionable waypoints while dynamically adjusting paths in response to obstacles. We experimentally evaluated our proposed LLM-based approach across three different environments of progressive complexity, showing the robustness of our approach with llama3.1 model that outperformed other LLM models in path planning time, waypoint generation success rate, and collision avoidance. This underlines the promising contribution of LLMs for enhancing the capability of mobile robots, especially when their operation involves complex decisions in large and complex environments. Our framework has provided safer, more reliable navigation systems and opened a new direction for the future research. The source code of this work is publicly available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Taha Tariq, Congqing Wang, Yasir Hussain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Underactuated dexterous robotic grasping with reconfigurable passive joints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel reconfigurable passive joint (RP-joint), which has been implemented and tested on an underactuated three-finger robotic gripper. RP-joint has no actuation, but instead it is lightweight and compact. It can be easily reconfigured by applying external forces and locked to perform complex dexterous manipulation tasks, but only after tension is applied to the connected tendon. Additionally, we present an approach that allows learning dexterous grasps from single examples with underactuated grippers and automatically configures the RP-joints for dexterous manipulation. This is enhanced by integrating kinaesthetic contact optimization, which improves grasp performance even further. The proposed RP-joint gripper and grasp planner have been tested on over 370 grasps executed on 42 IKEA objects and on the YCB object dataset, achieving grasping success rates of 80% and 87%, on IKEA and YCB, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16006v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3497714</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 10, no. 1, pp. 48-55, Jan. 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marek Kopicki, Sainul Islam Ansary, Simone Tolomei, Franco Angelini, Manolo Garabini, Piotr Skrzypczy\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Reconstruction of non-visible surfaces of objects from a Single Depth View -- Comparative Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scene and object reconstruction is an important problem in robotics, in particular in planning collision-free trajectories or in object manipulation. This paper compares two strategies for the reconstruction of nonvisible parts of the object surface from a single RGB-D camera view. The first method, named DeepSDF predicts the Signed Distance Transform to the object surface for a given point in 3D space. The second method, named MirrorNet reconstructs the occluded objects' parts by generating images from the other side of the observed object. Experiments performed with objects from the ShapeNet dataset, show that the view-dependent MirrorNet is faster and has smaller reconstruction errors in most categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16101v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.34658/9788366741928.1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rafa{\l} Staszak, Piotr Micha{\l}ek, Jakub Chudzi\'nski, Marek Kopicki, Dominik Belter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An FPGA-Based Neuro-Fuzzy Sensor for Personalized Driving Assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advanced driving-assistance systems (ADAS) are intended to automatize driver tasks, as well as improve driving and vehicle safety. This work proposes an intelligent neuro-fuzzy sensor for driving style (DS) recognition, suitable for ADAS enhancement. The development of the driving style intelligent sensor uses naturalistic driving data from the SHRP2 study, which includes data from a CAN bus, inertial measurement unit, and front radar. The system has been successfully implemented using a field-programmable gate array (FPGA) device of the Xilinx Zynq programmable system-on-chip (PSoC). It can mimic the typical timing parameters of a group of drivers as well as tune these typical parameters to model individual DSs. The neuro-fuzzy intelligent sensor provides high-speed real-time active ADAS implementation and is able to personalize its behavior into safe margins without driver intervention. In particular, the personalization procedure of the time headway (THW) parameter for an ACC in steady car following was developed, achieving a performance of 0.53 microseconds. This performance fulfilled the requirements of cutting-edge active ADAS specifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16212v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/s19184011</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sensors 2019, 19(18), 4011</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\'Oscar Mata-Carballeira, Jon Guti\'errez-Zaballa, In\'es del Campo, Victoria Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Mathematical and System-Level Analysis of Autonomous Vehicle Timelines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14819v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fully autonomous vehicles (AVs) continue to spark immense global interest, yet predictions on when they will operate safely and broadly remain heavily debated. This paper synthesizes two distinct research traditions: computational complexity and algorithmic constraints versus reliability growth modeling and real-world testing to form an integrated, quantitative timeline for future AV deployment. We propose a mathematical framework that unifies NP-hard multi-agent path planning analyses, high-performance computing (HPC) projections, and extensive Crow-AMSAA reliability growth calculations, factoring in operational design domain (ODD) variations, severity, and partial vs. full domain restrictions. Through category-specific case studies (e.g., consumer automotive, robo-taxis, highway trucking, industrial and defense applications), we show how combining HPC limitations, safety demonstration requirements, production/regulatory hurdles, and parallel/serial test strategies can push out the horizon for universal Level 5 deployment by up to several decades. Conversely, more constrained ODDs; like fenced industrial sites or specialized defense operations; may see autonomy reach commercial viability in the near-to-medium term. Our findings illustrate that while targeted domains can achieve automated service sooner, widespread driverless vehicles handling every environment remain far from realized. This paper thus offers a unique and rigorous perspective on why AV timelines extend well beyond short-term optimism, underscoring how each dimension of complexity and reliability imposes its own multi-year delays. By quantifying these constraints and exploring potential accelerators (e.g., advanced AI hardware, infrastructure up-grades), we provide a structured baseline for researchers, policymakers, and industry stakeholders to more accurately map their expectations and investments in AV technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14819v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Perrone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A causal learning approach to in-orbit inertial parameter estimation for multi-payload deployers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper discusses an approach to inertial parameter estimation for the case of cargo carrying spacecraft that is based on causal learning, i.e. learning from the responses of the spacecraft, under actuation. Different spacecraft configurations (inertial parameter sets) are simulated under different actuation profiles, in order to produce an optimised time-series clustering classifier that can be used to distinguish between them. The actuation is comprised of finite sequences of constant inputs that are applied in order, based on typical actuators available. By learning from the system's responses across multiple input sequences, and then applying measures of time-series similarity and F1-score, an optimal actuation sequence can be chosen either for one specific system configuration or for the overall set of possible configurations. This allows for both estimation of the inertial parameter set without any prior knowledge of state, as well as validation of transitions between different configurations after a deployment event. The optimisation of the actuation sequence is handled by a reinforcement learning model that uses the proximal policy optimisation (PPO) algorithm, by repeatedly trying different sequences and evaluating the impact on classifier performance according to a multi-objective metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14824v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Platanitis, Miguel Arana-Catania, Saurabh Upadhyay, Leonard Felicetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensive Exploration in Complex Traffic Scenarios using Hierarchical Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14992v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Developing an automated driving system capable of navigating complex traffic environments remains a formidable challenge. Unlike rule-based or supervised learning-based methods, Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) based controllers eliminate the need for domain-specific knowledge and datasets, thus providing adaptability to various scenarios. Nonetheless, a common limitation of existing studies on DRL-based controllers is their focus on driving scenarios with simple traffic patterns, which hinders their capability to effectively handle complex driving environments with delayed, long-term rewards, thus compromising the generalizability of their findings. In response to these limitations, our research introduces a pioneering hierarchical framework that efficiently decomposes intricate decision-making problems into manageable and interpretable subtasks. We adopt a two step training process that trains the high-level controller and low-level controller separately. The high-level controller exhibits an enhanced exploration potential with long-term delayed rewards, and the low-level controller provides longitudinal and lateral control ability using short-term instantaneous rewards. Through simulation experiments, we demonstrate the superiority of our hierarchical controller in managing complex highway driving situations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14992v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihao Zhang, Ekim Yurtsever, Keith A. Redmill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Forward Invariant Sets from Neural Network-Based Control Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15189v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Training Neural Networks (NNs) to serve as Barrier Functions (BFs) is a popular way to improve the safety of autonomous dynamical systems. Despite significant practical success, these methods are not generally guaranteed to produce true BFs in a provable sense, which undermines their intended use as safety certificates. In this paper, we consider the problem of formally certifying a learned NN as a BF with respect to state avoidance for an autonomous system: viz. computing a region of the state space on which the candidate NN is provably a BF. In particular, we propose a sound algorithm that efficiently produces such a certificate set for a shallow NN. Our algorithm combines two novel approaches: it first uses NN reachability tools to identify a subset of states for which the output of the NN does not increase along system trajectories; then, it uses a novel enumeration algorithm for hyperplane arrangements to find the intersection of the NN's zero-sub-level set with the first set of states. In this way, our algorithm soundly finds a subset of states on which the NN is certified as a BF. We further demonstrate the effectiveness of our algorithm at certifying for real-world NNs as BFs in two case studies. We complemented these with scalability experiments that demonstrate the efficiency of our algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15189v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Goli Vaisi, James Ferlez, Yasser Shoukry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-attacker: Enhancing Closed-loop Adversarial Scenario Generation for Autonomous Driving with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15850v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ensuring and improving the safety of autonomous driving systems (ADS) is crucial for the deployment of highly automated vehicles, especially in safety-critical events. To address the rarity issue, adversarial scenario generation methods are developed, in which behaviors of traffic participants are manipulated to induce safety-critical events. However, existing methods still face two limitations. First, identification of the adversarial participant directly impacts the effectiveness of the generation. However, the complexity of real-world scenarios, with numerous participants and diverse behaviors, makes identification challenging. Second, the potential of generated safety-critical scenarios to continuously improve ADS performance remains underexplored. To address these issues, we propose LLM-attacker: a closed-loop adversarial scenario generation framework leveraging large language models (LLMs). Specifically, multiple LLM agents are designed and coordinated to identify optimal attackers. Then, the trajectories of the attackers are optimized to generate adversarial scenarios. These scenarios are iteratively refined based on the performance of ADS, forming a feedback loop to improve ADS. Experimental results show that LLM-attacker can create more dangerous scenarios than other methods, and the ADS trained with it achieves a collision rate half that of training with normal scenarios. This indicates the ability of LLM-attacker to test and enhance the safety and robustness of ADS. Video demonstrations are provided at: https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Zv4V3iG7825oyiKbUwS2Y-rR0DQIE1ZA/view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15850v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuewen Mei, Tong Nie, Jian Sun, Ye Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Structural-RNN for Robot Crowd Navigation with Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.04820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2011.04820v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Safe and efficient navigation through human crowds is an essential capability for mobile robots. Previous work on robot crowd navigation assumes that the dynamics of all agents are known and well-defined. In addition, the performance of previous methods deteriorates in partially observable environments and environments with dense crowds. To tackle these problems, we propose decentralized structural-Recurrent Neural Network (DS-RNN), a novel network that reasons about spatial and temporal relationships for robot decision making in crowd navigation. We train our network with model-free deep reinforcement learning without any expert supervision. We demonstrate that our model outperforms previous methods in challenging crowd navigation scenarios. We successfully transfer the policy learned in the simulator to a real-world TurtleBot 2i. For more information, please visit the project website at https://sites.google.com/view/crowdnav-ds-rnn/home.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2011.04820v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuijing Liu, Peixin Chang, Weihang Liang, Neeloy Chakraborty, Katherine Driggs-Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective Intelligence for 2D Push Manipulations with Mobile Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.15136v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While natural systems often present collective intelligence that allows them to self-organize and adapt to changes, the equivalent is missing in most artificial systems. We explore the possibility of such a system in the context of cooperative 2D push manipulations using mobile robots. Although conventional works demonstrate potential solutions for the problem in restricted settings, they have computational and learning difficulties. More importantly, these systems do not possess the ability to adapt when facing environmental changes. In this work, we show that by distilling a planner derived from a differentiable soft-body physics simulator into an attention-based neural network, our multi-robot push manipulation system achieves better performance than baselines. In addition, our system also generalizes to configurations not seen during training and is able to adapt toward task completions when external turbulence and environmental changes are applied. Supplementary videos can be found on our project website: https://sites.google.com/view/ciom/home</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.15136v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Kuroki, Tatsuya Matsushima, Jumpei Arima, Hiroki Furuta, Yutaka Matsuo, Shixiang Shane Gu, Yujin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Model Predictive Covariance Steering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.00398v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes Distributed Model Predictive Covariance Steering (DiMPCS) for multi-agent control under stochastic uncertainty. The scope of our approach is to blend covariance steering theory, distributed optimization and model predictive control (MPC) into a single framework that is safe, scalable and decentralized. Initially, we pose a problem formulation that uses the Wasserstein distance to steer the state distributions of a multi-agent system to desired targets, and probabilistic constraints to ensure safety. We then transform this problem into a finite-dimensional optimization one by utilizing a disturbance feedback policy parametrization for covariance steering and a tractable approximation of the safety constraints. To solve the latter problem, we derive a decentralized consensus-based algorithm using the Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers. This method is then extended to a receding horizon form, which yields the proposed DiMPCS algorithm. Simulation experiments on a variety of multi-robot tasks with up to hundreds of robots demonstrate the effectiveness of DiMPCS. The superior scalability and performance of the proposed method is also highlighted through a comparison against related stochastic MPC approaches. Finally, hardware results on a multi-robot platform also verify the applicability of DiMPCS on real systems. A video with all results is available in https://youtu.be/tzWqOzuj2kQ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.00398v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/IROS58592.2024.10802104</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Augustinos D. Saravanos, Isin M. Balci, Efstathios Bakolas, Evangelos A. Theodorou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenDOM: Generalizable One-shot Deformable Object Manipulation with Parameter-Aware Policy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09051v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Due to the inherent uncertainty in their deformability during motion, previous methods in deformable object manipulation, such as rope and cloth, often required hundreds of real-world demonstrations to train a manipulation policy for each object, which hinders their applications in our ever-changing world. To address this issue, we introduce GenDOM, a framework that allows the manipulation policy to handle different deformable objects with only a single real-world demonstration. To achieve this, we augment the policy by conditioning it on deformable object parameters and training it with a diverse range of simulated deformable objects so that the policy can adjust actions based on different object parameters. At the time of inference, given a new object, GenDOM can estimate the deformable object parameters with only a single real-world demonstration by minimizing the disparity between the grid density of point clouds of real-world demonstrations and simulations in a differentiable physics simulator. Empirical validations on both simulated and real-world object manipulation setups clearly show that our method can manipulate different objects with a single demonstration and significantly outperforms the baseline in both environments (a 62% improvement for in-domain ropes and a 15% improvement for out-of-distribution ropes in simulation, as well as a 26% improvement for ropes and a 50% improvement for cloths in the real world), demonstrating the effectiveness of our approach in one-shot deformable object manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09051v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Kuroki, Jiaxian Guo, Tatsuya Matsushima, Takuya Okubo, Masato Kobayashi, Yuya Ikeda, Ryosuke Takanami, Paul Yoo, Yutaka Matsuo, Yusuke Iwasawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal and Force-Matched Imitation Learning with a See-Through Visuotactile Sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01248v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Contact-rich tasks continue to present many challenges for robotic manipulation. In this work, we leverage a multimodal visuotactile sensor within the framework of imitation learning (IL) to perform contact-rich tasks that involve relative motion (e.g., slipping and sliding) between the end-effector and the manipulated object. We introduce two algorithmic contributions, tactile force matching and learned mode switching, as complimentary methods for improving IL. Tactile force matching enhances kinesthetic teaching by reading approximate forces during the demonstration and generating an adapted robot trajectory that recreates the recorded forces. Learned mode switching uses IL to couple visual and tactile sensor modes with the learned motion policy, simplifying the transition from reaching to contacting. We perform robotic manipulation experiments on four door-opening tasks with a variety of observation and algorithm configurations to study the utility of multimodal visuotactile sensing and our proposed improvements. Our results show that the inclusion of force matching raises average policy success rates by 62.5%, visuotactile mode switching by 30.3%, and visuotactile data as a policy input by 42.5%, emphasizing the value of see-through tactile sensing for IL, both for data collection to allow force matching, and for policy execution to enable accurate task feedback. Project site: https://papers.starslab.ca/sts-il/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01248v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TRO.2024.3521864</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Robotics (T-RO), Vol. 41, pp. 946-959, Jan. 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Trevor Ablett, Oliver Limoyo, Adam Sigal, Affan Jilani, Jonathan Kelly, Kaleem Siddiqi, Francois Hogan, Gregory Dudek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Behavior Retrieval: Retrieval-Augmented Policy Training for Cooperative Push Manipulation by Mobile Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02008v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Due to the complex interactions between agents, learning multi-agent control policy often requires a prohibited amount of data. This paper aims to enable multi-agent systems to effectively utilize past memories to adapt to novel collaborative tasks in a data-efficient fashion. We propose the Multi-Agent Coordination Skill Database, a repository for storing a collection of coordinated behaviors associated with key vectors distinctive to them. Our Transformer-based skill encoder effectively captures spatio-temporal interactions that contribute to coordination and provides a unique skill representation for each coordinated behavior. By leveraging only a small number of demonstrations of the target task, the database enables us to train the policy using a dataset augmented with the retrieved demonstrations. Experimental evaluations demonstrate that our method achieves a significantly higher success rate in push manipulation tasks compared with baseline methods like few-shot imitation learning. Furthermore, we validate the effectiveness of our retrieve-and-learn framework in a real environment using a team of wheeled robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02008v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Kuroki, Mai Nishimura, Tadashi Kozuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Scaling Laws in Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14005v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neural scaling laws have driven significant advancements in machine learning, particularly in domains like language modeling and computer vision. However, the exploration of neural scaling laws within robotics has remained relatively underexplored, despite the growing adoption of foundation models in this field. This paper represents the first comprehensive study to quantify neural scaling laws for Robot Foundation Models (RFMs) and Large Language Models (LLMs) in robotics tasks. Through a meta-analysis of 327 research papers, we investigate how data size, model size, and compute resources influence downstream performance across a diverse set of robotic tasks. Consistent with previous scaling law research, our results reveal that the performance of robotic models improves with increased resources, following a power-law relationship. Promisingly, the improvement in robotic task performance scales notably faster than language tasks. This suggests that, while performance on downstream robotic tasks today is often moderate-to-poor, increased data and compute are likely to signficantly improve performance in the future. Also consistent with previous scaling law research, we also observe the emergence of new robot capabilities as models scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14005v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Sartor, Neil Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensor-Based Distributionally Robust Control for Safe Robot Navigation in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18251v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel method for mobile robot navigation in dynamic, unknown environments, leveraging onboard sensing and distributionally robust optimization to impose probabilistic safety constraints. Our method introduces a distributionally robust control barrier function (DR-CBF) that directly integrates noisy sensor measurements and state estimates to define safety constraints. This approach is applicable to a wide range of control-affine dynamics, generalizable to robots with complex geometries, and capable of operating at real-time control frequencies. Coupled with a control Lyapunov function (CLF) for path following, the proposed CLF-DR-CBF control synthesis method achieves safe, robust, and efficient navigation in challenging environments. We demonstrate the effectiveness and robustness of our approach for safe autonomous navigation under uncertainty in simulations and real-world experiments with differential-drive robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18251v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kehan Long, Yinzhuang Yi, Zhirui Dai, Sylvia Herbert, Jorge Cort\'es, Nikolay Atanasov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imperative Learning: A Self-supervised Neuro-Symbolic Learning Framework for Robot Autonomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16087v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Data-driven methods such as reinforcement and imitation learning have achieved remarkable success in robot autonomy. However, their data-centric nature still hinders them from generalizing well to ever-changing environments. Moreover, collecting large datasets for robotic tasks is often impractical and expensive. To overcome these challenges, we introduce a new self-supervised neuro-symbolic (NeSy) computational framework, imperative learning (IL), for robot autonomy, leveraging the generalization abilities of symbolic reasoning. The framework of IL consists of three primary components: a neural module, a reasoning engine, and a memory system. We formulate IL as a special bilevel optimization (BLO), which enables reciprocal learning over the three modules. This overcomes the label-intensive obstacles associated with data-driven approaches and takes advantage of symbolic reasoning concerning logical reasoning, physical principles, geometric analysis, etc. We discuss several optimization techniques for IL and verify their effectiveness in five distinct robot autonomy tasks including path planning, rule induction, optimal control, visual odometry, and multi-robot routing. Through various experiments, we show that IL can significantly enhance robot autonomy capabilities and we anticipate that it will catalyze further research across diverse domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16087v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Wang, Kaiyi Ji, Junyi Geng, Zhongqiang Ren, Taimeng Fu, Fan Yang, Yifan Guo, Haonan He, Xiangyu Chen, Zitong Zhan, Qiwei Du, Shaoshu Su, Bowen Li, Yuheng Qiu, Yi Du, Qihang Li, Yifan Yang, Xiao Lin, Zhipeng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Assessment of Lidar Odometry Frameworks: A Case Study at the Australian Botanic Garden Mount Annan</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16931v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomous vehicles are being tested in diverse environments worldwide. However, a notable gap exists in evaluating datasets representing natural, unstructured environments such as forests or gardens. To address this, we present a study on localisation at the Australian Botanic Garden Mount Annan. This area encompasses open grassy areas, paved pathways, and densely vegetated sections with trees and other objects. The dataset was recorded using a 128-beam LiDAR sensor and GPS and IMU readings to track the ego-vehicle. This paper evaluates the performance of two state-of-the-art LiDARinertial odometry frameworks, COIN-LIO and LIO-SAM, on this dataset. We analyse trajectory estimates in both horizontal and vertical dimensions and assess relative translation and yaw errors over varying distances. Our findings reveal that while both frameworks perform adequately in the vertical plane, COINLIO demonstrates superior accuracy in the horizontal plane, particularly over extended trajectories. In contrast, LIO-SAM shows increased drift and yaw errors over longer distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16931v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Mourad Ouazghire, Julie Stephany Berrio, Mao Shan, Stewart Worrall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>{\lambda}: A Benchmark for Data-Efficiency in Long-Horizon Indoor Mobile Manipulation Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05313v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficiently learning and executing long-horizon mobile manipulation (MoMa) tasks is crucial for advancing robotics in household and workplace settings. However, current MoMa models are data-inefficient, underscoring the need for improved models that require realistic-sized benchmarks to evaluate their efficiency, which do not exist. To address this, we introduce the LAMBDA ({\lambda}) benchmark (Long-horizon Actions for Mobile-manipulation Benchmarking of Directed Activities), which evaluates the data efficiency of models on language-conditioned, long-horizon, multi-room, multi-floor, pick-and-place tasks using a dataset of manageable size, more feasible for collection. The benchmark includes 571 human-collected demonstrations that provide realism and diversity in simulated and real-world settings. Unlike planner-generated data, these trajectories offer natural variability and replay-verifiability, ensuring robust learning and evaluation. We benchmark several models, including learning-based models and a neuro-symbolic modular approach combining foundation models with task and motion planning. Learning-based models show suboptimal success rates, even when leveraging pretrained weights, underscoring significant data inefficiencies. However, the neuro-symbolic approach performs significantly better while being more data efficient. Findings highlight the need for more data-efficient learning-based MoMa approaches. {\lambda} addresses this gap by serving as a key benchmark for evaluating the data efficiency of those future models in handling household robotics tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05313v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Jaafar, Shreyas Sundara Raman, Yichen Wei, Sudarshan Harithas, Sofia Juliani, Anneke Wernerfelt, Benedict Quartey, Ifrah Idrees, Jason Xinyu Liu, Stefanie Tellex</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TelePreview: A User-Friendly Teleoperation System with Virtual Arm Assistance for Enhanced Effectiveness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13548v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Teleoperation provides an effective way to collect robot data, which is crucial for learning from demonstrations. In this field, teleoperation faces several key challenges: user-friendliness for new users, safety assurance, and transferability across different platforms. While collecting real robot dexterous manipulation data by teleoperation to train robots has shown impressive results on diverse tasks, due to the morphological differences between human and robot hands, it is not only hard for new users to understand the action mapping but also raises potential safety concerns during operation. To address these limitations, we introduce TelePreview. This teleoperation system offers real-time visual feedback on robot actions based on human user inputs, with a total hardware cost of less than $1,000. TelePreview allows the user to see a virtual robot that represents the outcome of the user's next movement. By enabling flexible switching between command visualization and actual execution, this system helps new users learn how to demonstrate quickly and safely. We demonstrate that it outperforms other teleoperation systems across five tasks, emphasize its ease of use, and highlight its straightforward deployment across diverse robotic platforms. We release our code and a deployment document on our website https://nus-lins-lab.github.io/telepreview/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13548v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingxiang Guo, Jiayu Luo, Zhenyu Wei, Yiwen Hou, Zhixuan Xu, Xiaoyi Lin, Chongkai Gao, Lin Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLIM: Sim-to-Real Legged Instructive Manipulation via Long-Horizon Visuomotor Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09905v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a low-cost legged mobile manipulation system that solves long-horizon real-world tasks, trained by reinforcement learning purely in simulation. This system is made possible by 1) a hierarchical design of a high-level policy for visual-mobile manipulation following instructions and a low-level policy for quadruped movement and limb control, 2) a progressive exploration and learning approach that leverages privileged task decomposition information to train the teacher policy for long-horizon tasks, which will guide an imitation-based student policy for efficient training of the high-level visuomotor policy, and 3) a suite of techniques for minimizing sim-to-real gaps.
  In contrast to previous approaches that use high-end equipment, our system demonstrates effective performance with more accessible hardware - specifically, a Unitree Go1 quadruped, a WidowX250S arm, and a single wrist-mounted RGB camera - despite the increased challenges of sim-to-real transfer. When fully trained in simulation, a single policy autonomously solves long-horizon tasks such as search, move, grasp, and drop-into, achieving nearly 80% success. This performance is comparable to that of expert human teleoperation on the same tasks but significantly more efficient, operating at about 1.5x the speed. The sim-to-real transfer is fluid across diverse indoor and outdoor scenes under varying lighting conditions. Finally, we discuss the key techniques that enable the entire pipeline, including efficient RL training and sim-to-real, to work effectively for legged mobile manipulation, and present their ablation results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09905v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haichao Zhang, Haonan Yu, Le Zhao, Andrew Choi, Qinxun Bai, Break Yang, Wei Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-Lidar Map Alignment for Infrastructure Inspections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14486v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Routine and repetitive infrastructure inspections present safety, efficiency, and consistency challenges as they are performed manually, often in challenging or hazardous environments. They can also introduce subjectivity and errors into the process, resulting in undesirable outcomes. Simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM) presents an opportunity to generate high-quality 3D maps that can be used to extract accurate and objective inspection data. Yet, many SLAM algorithms are limited in their ability to align 3D maps from repeated inspections in GPS-denied settings automatically. This limitation hinders practical long-term asset health assessments by requiring tedious manual alignment for data association across scans from previous inspections. This paper introduces a versatile map alignment algorithm leveraging both visual and lidar data for improved place recognition robustness and presents an infrastructure-focused dataset tailored for consecutive inspections. By detaching map alignment from SLAM, our approach enhances infrastructure inspection pipelines, supports monitoring asset degradation over time, and invigorates SLAM research by permitting exploration beyond existing multi-session SLAM algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14486v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jake McLaughlin, Nicholas Charron, Sriram Narasimhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenORM: Generalizable One-shot Rope Manipulation with Parameter-Aware Policy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09872v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to the inherent uncertainty in their deformability during motion, previous methods in rope manipulation often require hundreds of real-world demonstrations to train a manipulation policy for each rope, even for simple tasks such as rope goal reaching, which hinder their applications in our ever-changing world. To address this issue, we introduce GenORM, a framework that allows the manipulation policy to handle different deformable ropes with a single real-world demonstration. To achieve this, we augment the policy by conditioning it on deformable rope parameters and training it with a diverse range of simulated deformable ropes so that the policy can adjust actions based on different rope parameters. At the time of inference, given a new rope, GenORM estimates the deformable rope parameters by minimizing the disparity between the grid density of point clouds of real-world demonstrations and simulations. With the help of a differentiable physics simulator, we require only a single real-world demonstration. Empirical validations on both simulated and real-world rope manipulation setups clearly show that our method can manipulate different ropes with a single demonstration and significantly outperforms the baseline in both environments (62% improvement in in-domain ropes, and 15% improvement in out-of-distribution ropes in simulation, 26% improvement in real-world), demonstrating the effectiveness of our approach in one-shot rope manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09872v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Kuroki, Jiaxian Guo, Tatsuya Matsushima, Takuya Okubo, Masato Kobayashi, Yuya Ikeda, Ryosuke Takanami, Paul Yoo, Yutaka Matsuo, Yusuke Iwasawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Segmentation Dataset for Reinforced Concrete Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09372v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper provides a dataset of 14,805 RGB images with segmentation labels for autonomous robotic inspection of reinforced concrete defects. Baselines for the YOLOv8L-seg, DeepLabV3, and U-Net segmentation models are established. Labelling inconsistencies are addressed statistically, and their influence on model performance is analyzed. An error identification tool is employed to examine the error modes of the models. The paper demonstrates that YOLOv8L-seg performs best, achieving a validation mIOU score of up to 0.59. Label inconsistencies were found to have a negligible effect on model performance, while the inclusion of more data improved the performance. False negatives were identified as the primary failure mode. The results highlight the importance of data availability for the performance of deep learning-based models. The lack of publicly available data is identified as a significant contributor to false negatives. To address this, the paper advocates for an increased open-source approach within the construction community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09372v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Schmidt, Lazaros Nalpantidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Robust Spacecraft Trajectory Optimization via Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05585v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Future multi-spacecraft missions require robust autonomous trajectory optimization capabilities to ensure safe and efficient rendezvous operations. This capability hinges on solving non-convex optimal control problems in real-time, although traditional iterative methods such as sequential convex programming impose significant computational challenges. To mitigate this burden, the Autonomous Rendezvous Transformer (ART) introduced a generative model trained to provide near-optimal initial guesses. This approach provides convergence to better local optima (e.g., fuel optimality), improves feasibility rates, and results in faster convergence speed of optimization algorithms through warm-starting. This work extends the capabilities of ART to address robust chance-constrained optimal control problems. Specifically, ART is applied to challenging rendezvous scenarios in Low Earth Orbit (LEO), ensuring fault-tolerant behavior under uncertainty. Through extensive experimentation, the proposed warm-starting strategy is shown to consistently produce high-quality reference trajectories, achieving up to 30\% cost improvement and 50\% reduction in infeasible cases compared to conventional methods, demonstrating robust performance across multiple state representations. Additionally, a post hoc evaluation framework is proposed to assess the quality of generated trajectories and mitigate runtime failures, marking an initial step toward the reliable deployment of AI-driven solutions in safety-critical autonomous systems such as spacecraft.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05585v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Takubo, Tommaso Guffanti, Daniele Gammelli, Marco Pavone, Simone D'Amico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal DLT-based Solutions for the Perspective-n-Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a modified normalized direct linear transform (DLT) algorithm for solving the perspective-n-point (PnP) problem with much better behavior than the conventional DLT. The modification consists of analytically weighting the different measurements in the linear system with a negligible increase in computational load. Our approach exhibits clear improvements -- in both performance and runtime -- when compared to popular methods such as EPnP, CPnP, RPnP, and OPnP. Our new non-iterative solution approaches that of the true optimal found via Gauss-Newton optimization, but at a fraction of the computational cost. Our optimal DLT (oDLT) implementation, as well as the experiments, are released in open source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S\'ebastien Henry, John A. Christian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SNN-Based Online Learning of Concepts and Action Laws in an Open World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12308v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the architecture of a fully autonomous, bio-inspired cognitive agent built around a spiking neural network (SNN) implementing the agent's semantic memory. The agent explores its universe and learns concepts of objects/situations and of its own actions in a one-shot manner. While object/situation concepts are unary, action concepts are triples made up of an initial situation, a motor activity, and an outcome. They embody the agent's knowledge of its universe's actions laws. Both kinds of concepts have different degrees of generality. To make decisions the agent queries its semantic memory for the expected outcomes of envisaged actions and chooses the action to take on the basis of these predictions. Our experiments show that the agent handles new situations by appealing to previously learned general concepts and rapidly modifies its concepts to adapt to environment changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12308v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christel Grimaud (IRIT-LILaC), Dominique Longin (IRIT-LILaC), Andreas Herzig (IRIT-LILaC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Fault Tolerance Strategy for Abrupt Reachability Constraint Changes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01831v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When a system's constraints change abruptly, the system's reachability safety does no longer sustain. Thus, the system can reach a forbidden/dangerous value. Conventional remedy practically involves online controller redesign (OCR) to re-establish the reachability's compliance with the new constraints, which, however, is usually too slow. There is a need for an online strategy capable of managing runtime changes in reachability constraints. However, to the best of the authors' knowledge, this topic has not been addressed in the existing literature. In this paper, we propose a fast fault tolerance strategy to recover the system's reachability safety in runtime. Instead of redesigning the system's controller, we propose to change the system's reference state to modify the system's reachability to comply with the new constraints. We frame the reference state search as an optimization problem and employ the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) method as well as the Interior Point Method (IPM) based Newton's method (as a fallback for the KKT method) for fast solution derivation. The optimization also allows more future fault tolerance. Numerical simulations demonstrate that our method outperforms the conventional OCR method in terms of computational efficiency and success rate. Specifically, the results show that the proposed method finds a solution $10^{2}$ (with the IPM based Newton's method) $\sim 10^{4}$ (with the KKT method) times faster than the OCR method. Additionally, the improvement rate of the success rate of our method over the OCR method is $40.81\%$ without considering the deadline of run time. The success rate remains at $49.44\%$ for the proposed method, while it becomes $0\%$ for the OCR method when a deadline of $1.5 \; seconds$ is imposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01831v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henghua Shen, Qixin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuIP: Experimental design for expensive simulators with many Qualitative factors via Integer Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14616v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The need to explore and/or optimize expensive simulators with many qualitative factors arises in broad scientific and engineering problems. Our motivating application lies in path planning - the exploration of feasible paths for navigation, which plays an important role in robotics, surgical planning and assembly planning. Here, the feasibility of a path is evaluated via expensive virtual experiments, and its parameter space is typically discrete and high-dimensional. A carefully selected experimental design is thus essential for timely decision-making. We propose here a novel framework, called QuIP, for experimental design of Qualitative factors via Integer Programming under a Gaussian process surrogate model with an exchangeable covariance function. For initial design, we show that its asymptotic D-optimal design can be formulated as a variant of the well-known assignment problem in operations research, which can be efficiently solved to global optimality using state-of-the-art integer programming solvers. For sequential design (specifically, for active learning or black-box optimization), we show that its design criterion can similarly be formulated as an assignment problem, thus enabling efficient and reliable optimization with existing solvers. We then demonstrate the effectiveness of QuIP over existing methods in a suite of path planning experiments and an application to rover trajectory optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14616v2</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Chun Liu, Simon Mak</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
