<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 02:54:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Diverse Controllable Diffusion Policy with Signal Temporal Logic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generating realistic simulations is critical for autonomous system applications such as self-driving and human-robot interactions. However, driving simulators nowadays still have difficulty in generating controllable, diverse, and rule-compliant behaviors for road participants: Rule-based models cannot produce diverse behaviors and require careful tuning, whereas learning-based methods imitate the policy from data but are not designed to follow the rules explicitly. Besides, the real-world datasets are by nature "single-outcome", making the learning method hard to generate diverse behaviors. In this paper, we leverage Signal Temporal Logic (STL) and Diffusion Models to learn controllable, diverse, and rule-aware policy. We first calibrate the STL on the real-world data, then generate diverse synthetic data using trajectory optimization, and finally learn the rectified diffusion policy on the augmented dataset. We test on the NuScenes dataset and our approach can achieve the most diverse rule-compliant trajectories compared to other baselines, with a runtime 1/17X to the second-best approach. In the closed-loop testing, our approach reaches the highest diversity, rule satisfaction rate, and the least collision rate. Our method can generate varied characteristics conditional on different STL parameters in testing. A case study on human-robot encounter scenarios shows our approach can generate diverse and closed-to-oracle trajectories. The annotation tool, augmented dataset, and code are available at https://github.com/mengyuest/pSTL-diffusion-policy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02924v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3444668</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 9, no. 10, pp. 8354-8361, Oct. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yue Meng, Chuchu fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reliable and Efficient Multi-Agent Coordination via Graph Neural Network Variational Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-agent coordination is crucial for reliable multi-robot navigation in shared spaces such as automated warehouses. In regions of dense robot traffic, local coordination methods may fail to find a deadlock-free solution. In these scenarios, it is appropriate to let a central unit generate a global schedule that decides the passing order of robots. However, the runtime of such centralized coordination methods increases significantly with the problem scale. In this paper, we propose to leverage Graph Neural Network Variational Autoencoders (GNN-VAE) to solve the multi-agent coordination problem at scale faster than through centralized optimization. We formulate the coordination problem as a graph problem and collect ground truth data using a Mixed-Integer Linear Program (MILP) solver. During training, our learning framework encodes good quality solutions of the graph problem into a latent space. At inference time, solution samples are decoded from the sampled latent variables, and the lowest-cost sample is selected for coordination. Finally, the feasible proposal with the highest performance index is selected for the deployment. By construction, our GNN-VAE framework returns solutions that always respect the constraints of the considered coordination problem. Numerical results show that our approach trained on small-scale problems can achieve high-quality solutions even for large-scale problems with 250 robots, being much faster than other baselines. Project page: https://mengyuest.github.io/gnn-vae-coord</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02954v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Meng, Nathalie Majcherczyk, Wenliang Liu, Scott Kiesel, Chuchu Fan, Federico Pecora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monocular visual simultaneous localization and mapping: (r)evolution from geometry to deep learning-based pipelines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the rise of deep learning, there is a fundamental change in visual SLAM algorithms toward developing different modules trained as end-to-end pipelines. However, regardless of the implementation domain, visual SLAM's performance is subject to diverse environmental challenges, such as dynamic elements in outdoor environments, harsh imaging conditions in underwater environments, or blurriness in high-speed setups. These environmental challenges need to be identified to study the real-world viability of SLAM implementations. Motivated by the aforementioned challenges, this paper surveys the current state of visual SLAM algorithms according to the two main frameworks: geometry-based and learning-based SLAM. First, we introduce a general formulation of the SLAM pipeline that includes most of the implementations in the literature. Second, those implementations are classified and surveyed for geometry and learning-based SLAM. After that, environment-specific challenges are formulated to enable experimental evaluation of the resilience of different visual SLAM classes to varying imaging conditions. We address two significant issues in surveying visual SLAM, providing (1) a consistent classification of visual SLAM pipelines and (2) a robust evaluation of their performance under different deployment conditions. Finally, we give our take on future opportunities for visual SLAM implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02955v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAI.2023.3321032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Artificial Intelligence 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Olaya Alvarez-Tunon, Yury Brodskiy, Erdal Kayacan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAILGUN: A Unified Convolutional Policy for Multi-Agent Path Finding Across Different Environments and Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-Agent Path Finding (MAPF), which focuses on finding collision-free paths for multiple robots, is crucial for applications ranging from aerial swarms to warehouse automation. Solving MAPF is NP-hard so learning-based approaches for MAPF have gained attention, particularly those leveraging deep neural networks. Nonetheless, despite the community's continued efforts, all learning-based MAPF planners still rely on decentralized planning due to variability in the number of agents and map sizes. We have developed the first centralized learning-based policy for MAPF problem called RAILGUN. RAILGUN is not an agent-based policy but a map-based policy. By leveraging a CNN-based architecture, RAILGUN can generalize across different maps and handle any number of agents. We collect trajectories from rule-based methods to train our model in a supervised way. In experiments, RAILGUN outperforms most baseline methods and demonstrates great zero-shot generalization capabilities on various tasks, maps and agent numbers that were not seen in the training dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02992v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yimin Tang, Xiao Xiong, Jingyi Xi, Jiaoyang Li, Erdem B{\i}y{\i}k, Sven Koenig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ArticuBot: Learning Universal Articulated Object Manipulation Policy via Large Scale Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents ArticuBot, in which a single learned policy enables a robotics system to open diverse categories of unseen articulated objects in the real world. This task has long been challenging for robotics due to the large variations in the geometry, size, and articulation types of such objects. Our system, Articubot, consists of three parts: generating a large number of demonstrations in physics-based simulation, distilling all generated demonstrations into a point cloud-based neural policy via imitation learning, and performing zero-shot sim2real transfer to real robotics systems. Utilizing sampling-based grasping and motion planning, our demonstration generalization pipeline is fast and effective, generating a total of 42.3k demonstrations over 322 training articulated objects. For policy learning, we propose a novel hierarchical policy representation, in which the high-level policy learns the sub-goal for the end-effector, and the low-level policy learns how to move the end-effector conditioned on the predicted goal. We demonstrate that this hierarchical approach achieves much better object-level generalization compared to the non-hierarchical version. We further propose a novel weighted displacement model for the high-level policy that grounds the prediction into the existing 3D structure of the scene, outperforming alternative policy representations. We show that our learned policy can zero-shot transfer to three different real robot settings: a fixed table-top Franka arm across two different labs, and an X-Arm on a mobile base, opening multiple unseen articulated objects across two labs, real lounges, and kitchens. Videos and code can be found on our project website: https://articubot.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03045v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufei Wang, Ziyu Wang, Mino Nakura, Pratik Bhowal, Chia-Liang Kuo, Yi-Ting Chen, Zackory Erickson, David Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physically-Feasible Reactive Synthesis for Terrain-Adaptive Locomotion via Trajectory Optimization and Symbolic Repair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an integrated planning framework for quadrupedal locomotion over dynamically changing, unforeseen terrains. Existing approaches either rely on heuristics for instantaneous foothold selection--compromising safety and versatility--or solve expensive trajectory optimization problems with complex terrain features and long time horizons. In contrast, our framework leverages reactive synthesis to generate correct-by-construction controllers at the symbolic level, and mixed-integer convex programming (MICP) for dynamic and physically feasible footstep planning for each symbolic transition. We use a high-level manager to reduce the large state space in synthesis by incorporating local environment information, improving synthesis scalability. To handle specifications that cannot be met due to dynamic infeasibility, and to minimize costly MICP solves, we leverage a symbolic repair process to generate only necessary symbolic transitions. During online execution, re-running the MICP with real-world terrain data, along with runtime symbolic repair, bridges the gap between offline synthesis and online execution. We demonstrate, in simulation, our framework's capabilities to discover missing locomotion skills and react promptly in safety-critical environments, such as scattered stepping stones and rebars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03071v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Zhou, Qian Meng, Hadas Kress-Gazit, Ye Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BEVDriver: Leveraging BEV Maps in LLMs for Robust Closed-Loop Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03074v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous driving has the potential to set the stage for more efficient future mobility, requiring the research domain to establish trust through safe, reliable and transparent driving. Large Language Models (LLMs) possess reasoning capabilities and natural language understanding, presenting the potential to serve as generalized decision-makers for ego-motion planning that can interact with humans and navigate environments designed for human drivers. While this research avenue is promising, current autonomous driving approaches are challenged by combining 3D spatial grounding and the reasoning and language capabilities of LLMs. We introduce BEVDriver, an LLM-based model for end-to-end closed-loop driving in CARLA that utilizes latent BEV features as perception input. BEVDriver includes a BEV encoder to efficiently process multi-view images and 3D LiDAR point clouds. Within a common latent space, the BEV features are propagated through a Q-Former to align with natural language instructions and passed to the LLM that predicts and plans precise future trajectories while considering navigation instructions and critical scenarios. On the LangAuto benchmark, our model reaches up to 18.9% higher performance on the Driving Score compared to SoTA methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03074v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Winter, Mark Azer, Fabian B. Flohr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MochiSwarm: A testbed for robotic blimps in realistic environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Testing aerial robots in tasks such as pickup-and-delivery and surveillance significantly benefits from high energy efficiency and scalability of the deployed robotic system. This paper presents MochiSwarm, an open-source testbed of light-weight robotic blimps, ready for multi-robot operation without external localization. We introduce the system design in hardware, software, and perception, which capitalizes on modularity, low cost, and light weight. The hardware allows for rapid modification, which enables the integration of additional sensors to enhance autonomy for different scenarios. The software framework supports different actuation models and communication between the base station and multiple blimps. The detachable perception module allows independent blimps to perform tasks that involve detection and autonomous actuation. We showcase a differential-drive module as an example, of which the autonomy is enabled by visual servoing using the perception module. A case study of pickup-and-delivery tasks with up to 12 blimps highlights the autonomy of the MochiSwarm without external infrastructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03077v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Xu, Thong Vu, Diego S. D'Antonio, David Salda\~na</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AirExo-2: Scaling up Generalizable Robotic Imitation Learning with Low-Cost Exoskeletons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scaling up imitation learning for real-world applications requires efficient and cost-effective demonstration collection methods. Current teleoperation approaches, though effective, are expensive and inefficient due to the dependency on physical robot platforms. Alternative data sources like in-the-wild demonstrations can eliminate the need for physical robots and offer more scalable solutions. However, existing in-the-wild data collection devices have limitations: handheld devices offer restricted in-hand camera observation, while whole-body devices often require fine-tuning with robot data due to action inaccuracies. In this paper, we propose AirExo-2, a low-cost exoskeleton system for large-scale in-the-wild demonstration collection. By introducing the demonstration adaptor to transform the collected in-the-wild demonstrations into pseudo-robot demonstrations, our system addresses key challenges in utilizing in-the-wild demonstrations for downstream imitation learning in real-world environments. Additionally, we present RISE-2, a generalizable policy that integrates 2D and 3D perceptions, outperforming previous imitation learning policies in both in-domain and out-of-domain tasks, even with limited demonstrations. By leveraging in-the-wild demonstrations collected and transformed by the AirExo-2 system, without the need for additional robot demonstrations, RISE-2 achieves comparable or superior performance to policies trained with teleoperated data, highlighting the potential of AirExo-2 for scalable and generalizable imitation learning. Project page: https://airexo.tech/airexo2</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongjie Fang, Chenxi Wang, Yiming Wang, Jingjing Chen, Shangning Xia, Jun Lv, Zihao He, Xiyan Yi, Yunhan Guo, Xinyu Zhan, Lixin Yang, Weiming Wang, Cewu Lu, Hao-Shu Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Car-STAGE: Automated framework for large-scale high-dimensional simulated time-series data generation based on user-defined criteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03100v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generating large-scale sensing datasets through photo-realistic simulation is an important aspect of many robotics applications such as autonomous driving. In this paper, we consider the problem of synchronous data collection from the open-source CARLA simulator using multiple sensors attached to vehicle based on user-defined criteria. We propose a novel, one-step framework that we refer to as Car-STAGE, based on CARLA simulator, to generate data using a graphical user interface (GUI) defining configuration parameters to data collection without any user intervention. This framework can utilize the user-defined configuration parameters such as choice of maps, number and configurations of sensors, environmental and lighting conditions etc. to run the simulation in the background, collecting high-dimensional sensor data from diverse sensors such as RGB Camera, LiDAR, Radar, Depth Camera, IMU Sensor, GNSS Sensor, Semantic Segmentation Camera, Instance Segmentation Camera, and Optical Flow Camera along with the ground-truths of the individual actors and storing the sensor data as well as ground-truth labels in a local or cloud-based database. The framework uses multiple threads where a main thread runs the server, a worker thread deals with queue and frame number and the rest of the threads processes the sensor data. The other way we derive speed up over the native implementation is by memory mapping the raw binary data into the disk and then converting the data into known formats at the end of data collection. We show that using these techniques, we gain a significant speed up over frames, under an increasing set of sensors and over the number of spawned objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03100v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asma A. Almutairi, David J. LeBlanc, Arpan Kusari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Shake the Wheel: Momentum-Aware Planning in End-to-End Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03125v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: End-to-end autonomous driving frameworks enable seamless integration of perception and planning but often rely on one-shot trajectory prediction, which may lead to unstable control and vulnerability to occlusions in single-frame perception. To address this, we propose the Momentum-Aware Driving (MomAD) framework, which introduces trajectory momentum and perception momentum to stabilize and refine trajectory predictions. MomAD comprises two core components: (1) Topological Trajectory Matching (TTM) employs Hausdorff Distance to select the optimal planning query that aligns with prior paths to ensure coherence;(2) Momentum Planning Interactor (MPI) cross-attends the selected planning query with historical queries to expand static and dynamic perception files. This enriched query, in turn, helps regenerate long-horizon trajectory and reduce collision risks. To mitigate noise arising from dynamic environments and detection errors, we introduce robust instance denoising during training, enabling the planning model to focus on critical signals and improve its robustness. We also propose a novel Trajectory Prediction Consistency (TPC) metric to quantitatively assess planning stability. Experiments on the nuScenes dataset demonstrate that MomAD achieves superior long-term consistency (&gt;=3s) compared to SOTA methods. Moreover, evaluations on the curated Turning-nuScenes shows that MomAD reduces the collision rate by 26% and improves TPC by 0.97m (33.45%) over a 6s prediction horizon, while closedloop on Bench2Drive demonstrates an up to 16.3% improvement in success rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03125v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziying Song, Caiyan Jia, Lin Liu, Hongyu Pan, Yongchang Zhang, Junming Wang, Xingyu Zhang, Shaoqing Xu, Lei Yang, Yadan Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causality-Based Reinforcement Learning Method for Multi-Stage Robotic Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep reinforcement learning has made significant strides in various robotic tasks. However, employing deep reinforcement learning methods to tackle multi-stage tasks still a challenge. Reinforcement learning algorithms often encounter issues such as redundant exploration, getting stuck in dead ends, and progress reversal in multi-stage tasks. To address this, we propose a method that integrates causal relationships with reinforcement learning for multi-stage tasks. Our approach enables robots to automatically discover the causal relationships between their actions and the rewards of the tasks and constructs the action space using only causal actions, thereby reducing redundant exploration and progress reversal. By integrating correct causal relationships using the causal policy gradient method into the learning process, our approach can enhance the performance of reinforcement learning algorithms in multi-stage robotic tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03145v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiechao Deng, Ning Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Certifiably Correct Range-Aided SLAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM) algorithms are necessary for safety-critical autonomous navigation. In the communication-constrained multi-agent setting, navigation systems increasingly use point-to-point range sensors as they afford measurements with low bandwidth requirements and known data association. The state estimation problem for these systems takes the form of range-aided (RA) SLAM. However, distributed algorithms for solving the RA-SLAM problem lack formal guarantees on the quality of the returned estimate. To this end, we present the first distributed algorithm for RA-SLAM that can efficiently recover certifiably globally optimal solutions. Our algorithm, distributed certifiably correct RA-SLAM (DCORA), achieves this via the Riemannian Staircase method, where computational procedures developed for distributed certifiably correct pose graph optimization are generalized to the RA-SLAM problem. We demonstrate DCORA's efficacy on real-world multi-agent datasets by achieving absolute trajectory errors comparable to those of a state-of-the-art centralized certifiably correct RA-SLAM algorithm. Additionally, we perform a parametric study on the structure of the RA-SLAM problem using synthetic data, revealing how common parameters affect DCORA's performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03192v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Thoms, Alan Papalia, Jared Velasquez, David M. Rosen, Sriram Narasimhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Escaping: End-to-End Reinforcement Learning for Robot Navigation in Narrow Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous navigation is a fundamental task for robot vacuum cleaners in indoor environments. Since their core function is to clean entire areas, robots inevitably encounter dead zones in cluttered and narrow scenarios. Existing planning methods often fail to escape due to complex environmental constraints, high-dimensional search spaces, and high difficulty maneuvers. To address these challenges, this paper proposes an embodied escaping model that leverages reinforcement learning-based policy with an efficient action mask for dead zone escaping. To alleviate the issue of the sparse reward in training, we introduce a hybrid training policy that improves learning efficiency. In handling redundant and ineffective action options, we design a novel action representation to reshape the discrete action space with a uniform turning radius. Furthermore, we develop an action mask strategy to select valid action quickly, balancing precision and efficiency. In real-world experiments, our robot is equipped with a Lidar, IMU, and two-wheel encoders. Extensive quantitative and qualitative experiments across varying difficulty levels demonstrate that our robot can consistently escape from challenging dead zones. Moreover, our approach significantly outperforms compared path planning and reinforcement learning methods in terms of success rate and collision avoidance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03208v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Zheng, Jiale Zhang, Mingyang Jiang, Peiyuan Liu, Danni Liu, Tong Qin, Ming Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenGV 2.0: Motion prior-assisted calibration and SLAM with vehicle-mounted surround-view systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present paper proposes optimization-based solutions to visual SLAM with a vehicle-mounted surround-view camera system. Owing to their original use-case, such systems often only contain a single camera facing into either direction and very limited overlap between fields of view. Our novelty consist of three optimization modules targeting at practical online calibration of exterior orientations from simple two-view geometry, reliable front-end initialization of relative displacements, and accurate back-end optimization using a continuous-time trajectory model. The commonality between the proposed modules is given by the fact that all three of them exploit motion priors that are related to the inherent non-holonomic characteristics of passenger vehicle motion. In contrast to prior related art, the proposed modules furthermore excel in terms of bypassing partial unobservabilities in the transformation variables that commonly occur for Ackermann-motion. As a further contribution, the modules are built into a novel surround-view camera SLAM system that specifically targets deployment on Ackermann vehicles operating in urban environments. All modules are studied in the context of in-depth ablation studies, and the practical validity of the entire framework is supported by a successful application to challenging, large-scale publicly available online datasets. Note that upon acceptance, the entire framework is scheduled for open-source release as part of an extension of the OpenGV library.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03230v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Huang, Yifu Wang, Si'ao Zhang, Zhirui Wang, Zhanpeng Ouyang, Zhenghua Yu, Laurent Kneip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Gesture Recognition in spHRI: Leveraging Fabric-Based Tactile Sensing on Humanoid Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Humans are able to convey different messages using only touch. Equipping robots with the ability to understand social touch adds another modality in which humans and robots can communicate. In this paper, we present a social gesture recognition system using a fabric-based, large-scale tactile sensor integrated onto the arms of a humanoid robot. We built a social gesture dataset using multiple participants and extracted temporal features for classification. By collecting real-world data on a humanoid robot, our system provides valuable insights into human-robot social touch, further advancing the development of spHRI systems for more natural and effective communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03234v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dakarai Crowder, Kojo Vandyck, Xiping Sun, James McCann, Wenzhen Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STORM: Spatial-Temporal Iterative Optimization for Reliable Multicopter Trajectory Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient and safe trajectory planning plays a critical role in the application of quadrotor unmanned aerial vehicles. Currently, the inherent trade-off between constraint compliance and computational efficiency enhancement in UAV trajectory optimization problems has not been sufficiently addressed. To enhance the performance of UAV trajectory optimization, we propose a spatial-temporal iterative optimization framework. Firstly, B-splines are utilized to represent UAV trajectories, with rigorous safety assurance achieved through strict enforcement of constraints on control points. Subsequently, a set of QP-LP subproblems via spatial-temporal decoupling and constraint linearization is derived. Finally, an iterative optimization strategy incorporating guidance gradients is employed to obtain high-performance UAV trajectories in different scenarios. Both simulation and real-world experimental results validate the efficiency and high-performance of the proposed optimization framework in generating safe and fast trajectories. Our source codes will be released for community reference at https://hitsz-mas.github.io/STORM</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03252v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhao Zhang, Zhexuan Zhou, Wenlong Xia, Youmin Gong, Jie Mei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCORE: Saturated Consensus Relocalization in Semantic Line Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is the arxiv version for our paper submitted to IEEE/RSJ IROS 2025. We propose a scene-agnostic and light-weight visual relocalization framework that leverages semantically labeled 3D lines as a compact map representation. In our framework, the robot localizes itself by capturing a single image, extracting 2D lines, associating them with semantically similar 3D lines in the map, and solving a robust perspective-n-line problem. To address the extremely high outlier ratios~(exceeding 99.5\%) caused by one-to-many ambiguities in semantic matching, we introduce the Saturated Consensus Maximization~(Sat-CM) formulation, which enables accurate pose estimation when the classic Consensus Maximization framework fails. We further propose a fast global solver to the formulated Sat-CM problems, leveraging rigorous interval analysis results to ensure both accuracy and computational efficiency. Additionally, we develop a pipeline for constructing semantic 3D line maps using posed depth images. To validate the effectiveness of our framework, which integrates our innovations in robust estimation and practical engineering insights, we conduct extensive experiments on the ScanNet++ dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03254v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haodong Jiang, Xiang Zheng, Yanglin Zhang, Qingcheng Zeng, Yiqian Li, Ziyang Hong, Junfeng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory Prediction for Autonomous Driving: Progress, Limitations, and Future Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the potential for autonomous vehicles to be integrated on a large scale into modern traffic systems continues to grow, ensuring safe navigation in dynamic environments is crucial for smooth integration. To guarantee safety and prevent collisions, autonomous vehicles must be capable of accurately predicting the trajectories of surrounding traffic agents. Over the past decade, significant efforts from both academia and industry have been dedicated to designing solutions for precise trajectory forecasting. These efforts have produced a diverse range of approaches, raising questions about the differences between these methods and whether trajectory prediction challenges have been fully addressed. This paper reviews a substantial portion of recent trajectory prediction methods and devises a taxonomy to classify existing solutions. A general overview of the prediction pipeline is also provided, covering input and output modalities, modeling features, and prediction paradigms discussed in the literature. In addition, the paper discusses active research areas within trajectory prediction, addresses the posed research questions, and highlights the remaining research gaps and challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03262v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nadya Abdel Madjid, Abdulrahman Ahmad, Murad Mebrahtu, Yousef Babaa, Abdelmoamen Nasser, Sumbal Malik, Bilal Hassan, Naoufel Werghi, Jorge Dias, Majid Khonji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervised Visual Docking Network for Unmanned Surface Vehicles Using Auto-labeling in Real-world Water Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unmanned Surface Vehicles (USVs) are increasingly applied to water operations such as environmental monitoring and river-map modeling. It faces a significant challenge in achieving precise autonomous docking at ports or stations, still relying on remote human control or external positioning systems for accuracy and safety which limits the full potential of human-out-of-loop deployment for USVs.This paper introduces a novel supervised learning pipeline with the auto-labeling technique for USVs autonomous visual docking. Firstly, we designed an auto-labeling data collection pipeline that appends relative pose and image pair to the dataset. This step does not require conventional manual labeling for supervised learning. Secondly, the Neural Dock Pose Estimator (NDPE) is proposed to achieve relative dock pose prediction without the need for hand-crafted feature engineering, camera calibration, and peripheral markers. Moreover, The NDPE can accurately predict the relative dock pose in real-world water environments, facilitating the implementation of Position-Based Visual Servo (PBVS) and low-level motion controllers for efficient and autonomous docking.Experiments show that the NDPE is robust to the disturbance of the distance and the USV velocity. The effectiveness of our proposed solution is tested and validated in real-world water environments, reflecting its capability to handle real-world autonomous docking tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03282v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijie Chu, Ziniu Wu, Yong Yue, Eng Gee Lim, Paolo Paoletti, Xiaohui Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Intelligence: A Survey of Google OR-Tools and Machine Learning for Global Path Planning in Autonomous Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We offer a new in-depth investigation of global path planning (GPP) for unmanned ground vehicles, an autonomous mining sampling robot named ROMIE. GPP is essential for ROMIE's optimal performance, which is translated into solving the traveling salesman problem, a complex graph theory challenge that is crucial for determining the most effective route to cover all sampling locations in a mining field. This problem is central to enhancing ROMIE's operational efficiency and competitiveness against human labor by optimizing cost and time. The primary aim of this research is to advance GPP by developing, evaluating, and improving a cost-efficient software and web application. We delve into an extensive comparison and analysis of Google operations research (OR)-Tools optimization algorithms. Our study is driven by the goal of applying and testing the limits of OR-Tools capabilities by integrating Reinforcement Learning techniques for the first time. This enables us to compare these methods with OR-Tools, assessing their computational effectiveness and real-world application efficiency. Our analysis seeks to provide insights into the effectiveness and practical application of each technique. Our findings indicate that Q-Learning stands out as the optimal strategy, demonstrating superior efficiency by deviating only 1.2% on average from the optimal solutions across our datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03338v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/aisy.202300840</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Benoit, Pedram Asef</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Sparse Odometry with Continuous 3D Gaussian Maps for Indoor Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate localization is essential for robotics and augmented reality applications such as autonomous navigation. Vision-based methods combining prior maps aim to integrate LiDAR-level accuracy with camera cost efficiency for robust pose estimation. Existing approaches, however, often depend on unreliable interpolation procedures when associating discrete point cloud maps with dense image pixels, which inevitably introduces depth errors and degrades pose estimation accuracy. We propose a monocular visual odometry framework utilizing a continuous 3D Gaussian map, which directly assigns geometrically consistent depth values to all extracted high-gradient points without interpolation. Evaluations on two public datasets demonstrate superior tracking accuracy compared to existing methods. We have released the source code of this work for the development of the community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03373v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Deng, Fengtian Lang, Zikang Yuan, Xin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REACT: Real-time Efficient Attribute Clustering and Transfer for Updatable 3D Scene Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern-day autonomous robots need high-level map representations to perform sophisticated tasks. Recently, 3D scene graphs (3DSGs) have emerged as a promising alternative to traditional grid maps, blending efficient memory use and rich feature representation. However, most efforts to apply them have been limited to static worlds. This work introduces REACT, a framework that efficiently performs real-time attribute clustering and transfer to relocalize object nodes in a 3DSG. REACT employs a novel method for comparing object instances using an embedding model trained on triplet loss, facilitating instance clustering and matching. Experimental results demonstrate that REACT is able to relocalize objects while maintaining computational efficiency. The REACT framework's source code will be available as an open-source project, promoting further advancements in reusable and updatable 3DSGs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03412v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phuoc Nguyen, Francesco Verdoja, Ville Kyrki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tiny Lidars for Manipulator Self-Awareness: Sensor Characterization and Initial Localization Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For several tasks, ranging from manipulation to inspection, it is beneficial for robots to localize a target object in their surroundings. In this paper, we propose an approach that utilizes coarse point clouds obtained from miniaturized VL53L5CX Time-of-Flight (ToF) sensors (tiny lidars) to localize a target object in the robot's workspace. We first conduct an experimental campaign to calibrate the dependency of sensor readings on relative range and orientation to targets. We then propose a probabilistic sensor model that is validated in an object pose estimation task using a Particle Filter (PF). The results show that the proposed sensor model improves the performance of the localization of the target object with respect to two baselines: one that assumes measurements are free from uncertainty and one in which the confidence is provided by the sensor datasheet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03449v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giammarco Caroleo, Alessandro Albini, Daniele De Martini, Timothy D. Barfoot, Perla Maiolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Artificial Intelligence in Robotic Manipulation: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This survey provides a comprehensive review on recent advancements of generative learning models in robotic manipulation, addressing key challenges in the field. Robotic manipulation faces critical bottlenecks, including significant challenges in insufficient data and inefficient data acquisition, long-horizon and complex task planning, and the multi-modality reasoning ability for robust policy learning performance across diverse environments. To tackle these challenges, this survey introduces several generative model paradigms, including Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), Variational Autoencoders (VAEs), diffusion models, probabilistic flow models, and autoregressive models, highlighting their strengths and limitations. The applications of these models are categorized into three hierarchical layers: the Foundation Layer, focusing on data generation and reward generation; the Intermediate Layer, covering language, code, visual, and state generation; and the Policy Layer, emphasizing grasp generation and trajectory generation. Each layer is explored in detail, along with notable works that have advanced the state of the art. Finally, the survey outlines future research directions and challenges, emphasizing the need for improved efficiency in data utilization, better handling of long-horizon tasks, and enhanced generalization across diverse robotic scenarios. All the related resources, including research papers, open-source data, and projects, are collected for the community in https://github.com/GAI4Manipulation/AwesomeGAIManipulation</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03464v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Zhang, Peng Yun, Jun Cen, Junhao Cai, Didi Zhu, Hangjie Yuan, Chao Zhao, Tao Feng, Michael Yu Wang, Qifeng Chen, Jia Pan, Bo Yang, Hua Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Control of Diverse Skills in Quadruped Robots Without Complete Expert Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning diverse skills for quadruped robots presents significant challenges, such as mastering complex transitions between different skills and handling tasks of varying difficulty. Existing imitation learning methods, while successful, rely on expensive datasets to reproduce expert behaviors. Inspired by introspective learning, we propose Progressive Adversarial Self-Imitation Skill Transition (PASIST), a novel method that eliminates the need for complete expert datasets. PASIST autonomously explores and selects high-quality trajectories based on predefined target poses instead of demonstrations, leveraging the Generative Adversarial Self-Imitation Learning (GASIL) framework. To further enhance learning, We develop a skill selection module to mitigate mode collapse by balancing the weights of skills with varying levels of difficulty. Through these methods, PASIST is able to reproduce skills corresponding to the target pose while achieving smooth and natural transitions between them. Evaluations on both simulation platforms and the Solo 8 robot confirm the effectiveness of PASIST, offering an efficient alternative to expert-driven learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03476v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxin Tu, Xiaoyi Wei, Yueqi Zhang, Taixian Hou, Xiaofei Gao, Zhiyan Dong, Peng Zhai, Lihua Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SafeVLA: Towards Safety Alignment of Vision-Language-Action Model via Safe Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-language-action models (VLAs) have shown great potential as generalist robot policies. However, these models pose urgent safety challenges during deployment, including the risk of physical harm to the environment, the robot itself, and humans. How can safety be explicitly incorporated into VLAs? In this work, we propose SafeVLA, a novel algorithm designed to integrate safety into VLAs, ensuring the protection of the environment, robot hardware and humans in real-world settings. SafeVLA effectively balances safety and task performance by employing large-scale constrained learning within simulated environments. We demonstrate that SafeVLA outperforms the current state-of-the-art method in both safety and task performance, achieving average improvements of 83.58% and 3.85%, respectively, in simulation. By prioritizing safety, our approach eliminates high-risk behaviors and reduces the upper bound of unsafe behaviors to 1/35 of that in the current state-of-the-art, thereby significantly mitigating long-tail risks. Furthermore, the learned safety constraints generalize to diverse, unseen scenarios, including multiple out-of-distribution perturbations and tasks. Our data, models and newly proposed benchmark environment are available at https://sites.google.com/view/pku-safevla.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03480v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Borong Zhang, Yuhao Zhang, Jiaming Ji, Yingshan Lei, Josef Dai, Yuanpei Chen, Yaodong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coordinated Trajectories for Non-stop Flying Carriers Holding a Cable-Suspended Load</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multirotor UAVs have been typically considered for aerial manipulation, but their scarce endurance prevents long-lasting manipulation tasks. This work demonstrates that the non-stop flights of three or more carriers are compatible with holding a constant pose of a cable-suspended load, thus potentially enabling aerial manipulation with energy-efficient non-stop carriers. It also presents an algorithm for generating the coordinated non-stop trajectories. The proposed method builds upon two pillars: (1)~the choice of $n$ special linearly independent directions of internal forces within the $3n-6$-dimensional nullspace of the grasp matrix of the load, chosen as the edges of a Hamiltonian cycle on the graph that connects the cable attachment points on the load. Adjacent pairs of directions are used to generate $n$ forces evolving on distinct 2D affine subspaces, despite the attachment points being generically in 3D; (2)~the construction of elliptical trajectories within these subspaces by mapping, through appropriate graph coloring, each edge of the Hamiltonian cycle to a periodic coordinate while ensuring that no adjacent coordinates exhibit simultaneous zero derivatives. Combined with conditions for load statics and attachment point positions, these choices ensure that each of the $n$ force trajectories projects onto the corresponding cable constraint sphere with non-zero tangential velocity, enabling perpetual motion of the carriers while the load is still. The theoretical findings are validated through simulations and laboratory experiments with non-stopping multirotor UAVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03481v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Gabellieri, Antonio Franchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Benchmark for Optimal Multi-Modal Multi-Robot Multi-Goal Path Planning with Given Robot Assignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03509v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many industrial robotics applications, multiple robots are working in a shared workspace to complete a set of tasks as quickly as possible. Such settings can be treated as multi-modal multi-robot multi-goal path planning problems, where each robot has to reach an ordered sequence of goals. Existing approaches to this type of problem solve this using prioritization or assume synchronous completion of tasks, and are thus neither optimal nor complete. We formalize this problem as a single path planning problem and introduce a benchmark encompassing a diverse range of problem instances including scenarios with various robots, planning horizons, and collaborative tasks such as handovers. Along with the benchmark, we adapt an RRT* and a PRM* planner to serve as a baseline for the planning problems. Both planners work in the composite space of all robots and introduce the required changes to work in our setting. Unlike existing approaches, our planner and formulation is not restricted to discretized 2D workspaces, supports a changing environment, and works for heterogeneous robot teams over multiple modes with different constraints, and multiple goals. Videos and code for the benchmark and the planners is available at https://vhartman.github.io/mrmg-planning/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03509v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentin N. Hartmann, Tirza Heinle, Stelian Coros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeuGrasp: Generalizable Neural Surface Reconstruction with Background Priors for Material-Agnostic Object Grasp Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic grasping in scenes with transparent and specular objects presents great challenges for methods relying on accurate depth information. In this paper, we introduce NeuGrasp, a neural surface reconstruction method that leverages background priors for material-agnostic grasp detection. NeuGrasp integrates transformers and global prior volumes to aggregate multi-view features with spatial encoding, enabling robust surface reconstruction in narrow and sparse viewing conditions. By focusing on foreground objects through residual feature enhancement and refining spatial perception with an occupancy-prior volume, NeuGrasp excels in handling objects with transparent and specular surfaces. Extensive experiments in both simulated and real-world scenarios show that NeuGrasp outperforms state-of-the-art methods in grasping while maintaining comparable reconstruction quality. More details are available at https://neugrasp.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03511v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingyu Fan, Yinghao Cai, Chao Li, Wenzhe He, Xudong Zheng, Tao Lu, Bin Liang, Shuo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Olympus: A Jumping Quadruped for Planetary Exploration Utilizing Reinforcement Learning for In-Flight Attitude Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exploring planetary bodies with lower gravity, such as the moon and Mars, allows legged robots to utilize jumping as an efficient form of locomotion thus giving them a valuable advantage over traditional rovers for exploration. Motivated by this fact, this paper presents the design, simulation, and learning-based "in-flight" attitude control of Olympus, a jumping legged robot tailored to the gravity of Mars. First, the design requirements are outlined followed by detailing how simulation enabled optimizing the robot's design - from its legs to the overall configuration - towards high vertical jumping, forward jumping distance, and in-flight attitude reorientation. Subsequently, the reinforcement learning policy used to track desired in-flight attitude maneuvers is presented. Successfully crossing the sim2real gap, extensive experimental studies of attitude reorientation tests are demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03574v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J{\o}rgen Anker Olsen, Grzegorz Malczyk, Kostas Alexis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generative System for Robot-to-Human Handovers: from Intent Inference to Spatial Configuration Imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel system for robot-to-human object handover that emulates human coworker interactions. Unlike most existing studies that focus primarily on grasping strategies and motion planning, our system focus on 1. inferring human handover intents, 2. imagining spatial handover configuration. The first one integrates multimodal perception-combining visual and verbal cues-to infer human intent. The second one using a diffusion-based model to generate the handover configuration, involving the spacial relationship among robot's gripper, the object, and the human hand, thereby mimicking the cognitive process of motor imagery. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach effectively interprets human cues and achieves fluent, human-like handovers, offering a promising solution for collaborative robotics. Code, videos, and data are available at: https://i3handover.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03579v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanxin Zhang, Abdulqader Dhafer, Zhou Daniel Hao, Hongbiao Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TeraSim: Uncovering Unknown Unsafe Events for Autonomous Vehicles through Generative Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03629v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traffic simulation is essential for autonomous vehicle (AV) development, enabling comprehensive safety evaluation across diverse driving conditions. However, traditional rule-based simulators struggle to capture complex human interactions, while data-driven approaches often fail to maintain long-term behavioral realism or generate diverse safety-critical events. To address these challenges, we propose TeraSim, an open-source, high-fidelity traffic simulation platform designed to uncover unknown unsafe events and efficiently estimate AV statistical performance metrics, such as crash rates. TeraSim is designed for seamless integration with third-party physics simulators and standalone AV stacks, to construct a complete AV simulation system. Experimental results demonstrate its effectiveness in generating diverse safety-critical events involving both static and dynamic agents, identifying hidden deficiencies in AV systems, and enabling statistical performance evaluation. These findings highlight TeraSim's potential as a practical tool for AV safety assessment, benefiting researchers, developers, and policymakers. The code is available at https://github.com/mcity/TeraSim.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03629v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haowei Sun, Xintao Yan, Zhijie Qiao, Haojie Zhu, Yihao Sun, Jiawei Wang, Shengyin Shen, Darian Hogue, Rajanikant Ananta, Derek Johnson, Greg Stevens, Greg McGuire, Yifan Wei, Wei Zheng, Yong Sun, Yasuo Fukai, Henry X. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion Planning and Control with Unknown Nonlinear Dynamics through Predicted Reachability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous motion planning under unknown nonlinear dynamics presents significant challenges. An agent needs to continuously explore the system dynamics to acquire its properties, such as reachability, in order to guide system navigation adaptively. In this paper, we propose a hybrid planning-control framework designed to compute a feasible trajectory toward a target. Our approach involves partitioning the state space and approximating the system by a piecewise affine (PWA) system with constrained control inputs. By abstracting the PWA system into a directed weighted graph, we incrementally update the existence of its edges via affine system identification and reach control theory, introducing a predictive reachability condition by exploiting prior information of the unknown dynamics. Heuristic weights are assigned to edges based on whether their existence is certain or remains indeterminate. Consequently, we propose a framework that adaptively collects and analyzes data during mission execution, continually updates the predictive graph, and synthesizes a controller online based on the graph search outcomes. We demonstrate the efficacy of our approach through simulation scenarios involving a mobile robot operating in unknown terrains, with its unknown dynamics abstracted as a single integrator model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03633v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiquan Zhang, Gokul Puthumanaillam, Manav Vora, Melkior Ornik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Negative Damping Control for User-Dependent Multi-Terrain Walking Assistance with a Hip Exoskeleton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03662v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hip exoskeletons are known for their versatility in assisting users across varied scenarios. However, current assistive strategies often lack the flexibility to accommodate for individual walking patterns and adapt to diverse locomotion environments. In this work, we present a novel control strategy that adapts the mechanical impedance of the human-exoskeleton system. We design the hip assistive torques as an adaptive virtual negative damping, which is able to inject energy into the system while allowing the users to remain in control and contribute voluntarily to the movements. Experiments with five healthy subjects demonstrate that our controller reduces the metabolic cost of walking compared to free walking (average reduction of 7.2%), and it preserves the lower-limbs kinematics. Additionally, our method achieves minimal power losses from the exoskeleton across the entire gait cycle (less than 2% negative mechanical power out of the total power), ensuring synchronized action with the users' movements. Moreover, we use Bayesian Optimization to adapt the assistance strength and allow for seamless adaptation and transitions across multi-terrain environments. Our strategy achieves efficient power transmission under all conditions. Our approach demonstrates an individualized, adaptable, and straightforward controller for hip exoskeletons, advancing the development of viable, adaptive, and user-dependent control laws.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03662v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 IEEE International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Ramella, Auke Ijspeert, Mohamed Bouri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curating Demonstrations using Online Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many robot demonstration datasets contain heterogeneous demonstrations of varying quality. This heterogeneity may benefit policy pre-training, but can hinder robot performance when used with a final imitation learning objective. In particular, some strategies in the data may be less reliable than others or may be underrepresented in the data, leading to poor performance when such strategies are sampled at test time. Moreover, such unreliable or underrepresented strategies can be difficult even for people to discern, and sifting through demonstration datasets is time-consuming and costly. On the other hand, policy performance when trained on such demonstrations can reflect the reliability of different strategies. We thus propose for robots to self-curate based on online robot experience (Demo-SCORE). More specifically, we train and cross-validate a classifier to discern successful policy roll-outs from unsuccessful ones and use the classifier to filter heterogeneous demonstration datasets. Our experiments in simulation and the real world show that Demo-SCORE can effectively identify suboptimal demonstrations without manual curation. Notably, Demo-SCORE achieves over 15-35% higher absolute success rate in the resulting policy compared to the base policy trained with all original demonstrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03707v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annie S. Chen, Alec M. Lessing, Yuejiang Liu, Chelsea Finn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OTTER: A Vision-Language-Action Model with Text-Aware Visual Feature Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models aim to predict robotic actions based on visual observations and language instructions. Existing approaches require fine-tuning pre-trained visionlanguage models (VLMs) as visual and language features are independently fed into downstream policies, degrading the pre-trained semantic alignments. We propose OTTER, a novel VLA architecture that leverages these existing alignments through explicit, text-aware visual feature extraction. Instead of processing all visual features, OTTER selectively extracts and passes only task-relevant visual features that are semantically aligned with the language instruction to the policy transformer. This allows OTTER to keep the pre-trained vision-language encoders frozen. Thereby, OTTER preserves and utilizes the rich semantic understanding learned from large-scale pre-training, enabling strong zero-shot generalization capabilities. In simulation and real-world experiments, OTTER significantly outperforms existing VLA models, demonstrating strong zeroshot generalization to novel objects and environments. Video, code, checkpoints, and dataset: https://ottervla.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03734v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huang Huang, Fangchen Liu, Letian Fu, Tingfan Wu, Mustafa Mukadam, Jitendra Malik, Ken Goldberg, Pieter Abbeel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Robust Multi-UAV Collaboration: MARL with Noise-Resilient Communication and Attention Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficient path planning for unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) is crucial in remote sensing and information collection. As task scales expand, the cooperative deployment of multiple UAVs significantly improves information collection efficiency. However, collaborative communication and decision-making for multiple UAVs remain major challenges in path planning, especially in noisy environments. To efficiently accomplish complex information collection tasks in 3D space and address robust communication issues, we propose a multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) framework for UAV path planning based on the Counterfactual Multi-Agent Policy Gradients (COMA) algorithm. The framework incorporates attention mechanism-based UAV communication protocol and training-deployment system, significantly improving communication robustness and individual decision-making capabilities in noisy conditions. Experiments conducted on both synthetic and real-world datasets demonstrate that our method outperforms existing algorithms in terms of path planning efficiency and robustness, especially in noisy environments, achieving a 78\% improvement in entropy reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02913v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilin Zhao, Chishui Chen, Haotian Shi, Jiale Chen, Xuanlin Yue, Zhejian Yang, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monocular Person Localization under Camera Ego-motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02916v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Localizing a person from a moving monocular camera is critical for Human-Robot Interaction (HRI). To estimate the 3D human position from a 2D image, existing methods either depend on the geometric assumption of a fixed camera or use a position regression model trained on datasets containing little camera ego-motion. These methods are vulnerable to fierce camera ego-motion, resulting in inaccurate person localization. We consider person localization as a part of a pose estimation problem. By representing a human with a four-point model, our method jointly estimates the 2D camera attitude and the person's 3D location through optimization. Evaluations on both public datasets and real robot experiments demonstrate our method outperforms baselines in person localization accuracy. Our method is further implemented into a person-following system and deployed on an agile quadruped robot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02916v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhan, Hanjing Ye, Hong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Step Deep Koopman Network (MDK-Net) for Vehicle Control in Frenet Frame</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The highly nonlinear dynamics of vehicles present a major challenge for the practical implementation of optimal and Model Predictive Control (MPC) approaches in path planning and following. Koopman operator theory offers a global linear representation of nonlinear dynamical systems, making it a promising framework for optimization-based vehicle control. This paper introduces a novel deep learning-based Koopman modeling approach that employs deep neural networks to capture the full vehicle dynamics-from pedal and steering inputs to chassis states-within a curvilinear Frenet frame. The superior accuracy of the Koopman model compared to identified linear models is shown for a double lane change maneuver. Furthermore, it is shown that an MPC controller deploying the Koopman model provides significantly improved performance while maintaining computational efficiency comparable to a linear MPC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03002v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Abtahi, Mahdis Rabbani, Armin Abdolmohammadi, Shima Nazari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpiritSight Agent: Advanced GUI Agent with One Look</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graphical User Interface (GUI) agents show amazing abilities in assisting human-computer interaction, automating human user's navigation on digital devices. An ideal GUI agent is expected to achieve high accuracy, low latency, and compatibility for different GUI platforms. Recent vision-based approaches have shown promise by leveraging advanced Vision Language Models (VLMs). While they generally meet the requirements of compatibility and low latency, these vision-based GUI agents tend to have low accuracy due to their limitations in element grounding. To address this issue, we propose $\textbf{SpiritSight}$, a vision-based, end-to-end GUI agent that excels in GUI navigation tasks across various GUI platforms. First, we create a multi-level, large-scale, high-quality GUI dataset called $\textbf{GUI-Lasagne}$ using scalable methods, empowering SpiritSight with robust GUI understanding and grounding capabilities. Second, we introduce the $\textbf{Universal Block Parsing (UBP)}$ method to resolve the ambiguity problem in dynamic high-resolution of visual inputs, further enhancing SpiritSight's ability to ground GUI objects. Through these efforts, SpiritSight agent outperforms other advanced methods on diverse GUI benchmarks, demonstrating its superior capability and compatibility in GUI navigation tasks. Models are available at $\href{https://huggingface.co/SenseLLM/SpiritSight-Agent-8B}{this\ URL}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03196v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Huang, Ziming Cheng, Junting Pan, Zhaohui Hou, Mingjie Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transformer-Based Spatio-Temporal Association of Apple Fruitlets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03200v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a transformer-based method to spatio-temporally associate apple fruitlets in stereo-images collected on different days and from different camera poses. State-of-the-art association methods in agriculture are dedicated towards matching larger crops using either high-resolution point clouds or temporally stable features, which are both difficult to obtain for smaller fruit in the field. To address these challenges, we propose a transformer-based architecture that encodes the shape and position of each fruitlet, and propagates and refines these features through a series of transformer encoder layers with alternating self and cross-attention. We demonstrate that our method is able to achieve an F1-score of 92.4% on data collected in a commercial apple orchard and outperforms all baselines and ablations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03200v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Freeman, George Kantor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Human Localization and Trajectory Prediction with Monocular Vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03535v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conventional human trajectory prediction models rely on clean curated data, requiring specialized equipment or manual labeling, which is often impractical for robotic applications. The existing predictors tend to overfit to clean observation affecting their robustness when used with noisy inputs. In this work, we propose MonoTransmotion (MT), a Transformer-based framework that uses only a monocular camera to jointly solve localization and prediction tasks. Our framework has two main modules: Bird's Eye View (BEV) localization and trajectory prediction. The BEV localization module estimates the position of a person using 2D human poses, enhanced by a novel directional loss for smoother sequential localizations. The trajectory prediction module predicts future motion from these estimates. We show that by jointly training both tasks with our unified framework, our method is more robust in real-world scenarios made of noisy inputs. We validate our MT network on both curated and non-curated datasets. On the curated dataset, MT achieves around 12% improvement over baseline models on BEV localization and trajectory prediction. On real-world non-curated dataset, experimental results indicate that MT maintains similar performance levels, highlighting its robustness and generalization capability. The code is available at https://github.com/vita-epfl/MonoTransmotion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03535v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Chien Luan, Yang Gao, Celine Demonsant, Alexandre Alahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Afford-X: Generalizable and Slim Affordance Reasoning for Task-oriented Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Object affordance reasoning, the ability to infer object functionalities based on physical properties, is fundamental for task-oriented planning and activities in both humans and Artificial Intelligence (AI). This capability, required for planning and executing daily activities in a task-oriented manner, relies on commonsense knowledge of object physics and functionalities, extending beyond simple object recognition. Current computational models for affordance reasoning from perception lack generalizability, limiting their applicability in novel scenarios. Meanwhile, comprehensive Large Language Models (LLMs) with emerging reasoning capabilities are challenging to deploy on local devices for task-oriented manipulations. Here, we introduce LVIS-Aff, a large-scale dataset comprising 1,496 tasks and 119k images, designed to enhance the generalizability of affordance reasoning from perception. Utilizing this dataset, we develop Afford-X, an end-to-end trainable affordance reasoning model that incorporates Verb Attention and Bi-Fusion modules to improve multi-modal understanding. This model achieves up to a 12.1% performance improvement over the best-reported results from non-LLM methods, while also demonstrating a 1.2% enhancement compared to our previous conference paper. Additionally, it maintains a compact 187M parameter size and infers nearly 50 times faster than the GPT-4V API. Our work demonstrates the potential for efficient, generalizable affordance reasoning models that can be deployed on local devices for task-oriented manipulations. We showcase Afford-X's effectiveness in enabling task-oriented manipulations for robots across various tasks and environments, underscoring its efficiency and broad implications for advancing robotics and AI systems in real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaomeng Zhu, Yuyang Li, Leiyao Cui, Pengfei Li, Huan-ang Gao, Yixin Zhu, Hao Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REGRACE: A Robust and Efficient Graph-based Re-localization Algorithm using Consistency Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03599v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Loop closures are essential for correcting odometry drift and creating consistent maps, especially in the context of large-scale navigation. Current methods using dense point clouds for accurate place recognition do not scale well due to computationally expensive scan-to-scan comparisons. Alternative object-centric approaches are more efficient but often struggle with sensitivity to viewpoint variation. In this work, we introduce REGRACE, a novel approach that addresses these challenges of scalability and perspective difference in re-localization by using LiDAR-based submaps. We introduce rotation-invariant features for each labeled object and enhance them with neighborhood context through a graph neural network. To identify potential revisits, we employ a scalable bag-of-words approach, pooling one learned global feature per submap. Additionally, we define a revisit with geometrical consistency cues rather than embedding distance, allowing us to recognize far-away loop closures. Our evaluations demonstrate that REGRACE achieves similar results compared to state-of-the-art place recognition and registration baselines while being twice as fast.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03599v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D\'ebora N. P. Oliveira, Joshua Knights, Sebasti\'an Barbas Laina, Simon Boche, Wolfram Burgard, Stefan Leutenegger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active 6D Pose Estimation for Textureless Objects using Multi-View RGB Frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Estimating the 6D pose of textureless objects from RBG images is an important problem in robotics. Due to appearance ambiguities, rotational symmetries, and severe occlusions, single-view based 6D pose estimators are still unable to handle a wide range of objects, motivating research towards multi-view pose estimation and next-best-view prediction that addresses these limitations. In this work, we propose a comprehensive active perception framework for estimating the 6D poses of textureless objects using only RGB images. Our approach is built upon a key idea: decoupling the 6D pose estimation into a sequential two-step process can greatly improve both accuracy and efficiency. First, we estimate the 3D translation of each object, resolving scale and depth ambiguities inherent to RGB images. These estimates are then used to simplify the subsequent task of determining the 3D orientation, which we achieve through canonical scale template matching. Building on this formulation, we then introduce an active perception strategy that predicts the next best camera viewpoint to capture an RGB image, effectively reducing object pose uncertainty and enhancing pose accuracy. We evaluate our method on the public ROBI dataset as well as on a transparent object dataset that we created. When evaluated using the same camera viewpoints, our multi-view pose estimation significantly outperforms state-of-the-art approaches. Furthermore, by leveraging our next-best-view strategy, our method achieves high object pose accuracy with substantially fewer viewpoints than heuristic-based policies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03726v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Yang, Wenjie Xue, Sahar Ghavidel, Steven L. Waslander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Feeling of Success: Does Touch Sensing Help Predict Grasp Outcomes?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.05512</link>
      <description>arXiv:1710.05512v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A successful grasp requires careful balancing of the contact forces. Deducing whether a particular grasp will be successful from indirect measurements, such as vision, is therefore quite challenging, and direct sensing of contacts through touch sensing provides an appealing avenue toward more successful and consistent robotic grasping. However, in order to fully evaluate the value of touch sensing for grasp outcome prediction, we must understand how touch sensing can influence outcome prediction accuracy when combined with other modalities. Doing so using conventional model-based techniques is exceptionally difficult. In this work, we investigate the question of whether touch sensing aids in predicting grasp outcomes within a multimodal sensing framework that combines vision and touch. To that end, we collected more than 9,000 grasping trials using a two-finger gripper equipped with GelSight high-resolution tactile sensors on each finger, and evaluated visuo-tactile deep neural network models to directly predict grasp outcomes from either modality individually, and from both modalities together. Our experimental results indicate that incorporating tactile readings substantially improve grasping performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1710.05512v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Calandra, Andrew Owens, Manu Upadhyaya, Wenzhen Yuan, Justin Lin, Edward H. Adelson, Sergey Levine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Impedance Control on SE(3) for Robotic Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07945v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: After its introduction, impedance control has been utilized as a primary control scheme for robotic manipulation tasks that involve interaction with unknown environments. While impedance control has been extensively studied, the geometric structure of SE(3) for the robotic manipulator itself and its use in formulating a robotic task has not been adequately addressed. In this paper, we propose a differential geometric approach to impedance control. Given a left-invariant error metric in SE(3), the corresponding error vectors in position and velocity are first derived. We then propose the impedance control schemes that adequately account for the geometric structure of the manipulator in SE(3) based on a left-invariant potential function. The closed-loop stabilities for the proposed control schemes are verified using Lyapunov function-based analysis. The proposed control design clearly outperformed a conventional impedance control approach when tracking challenging trajectory profiles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07945v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ifacol.2023.10.1581</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Joohwan Seo, Nikhil Potu Surya Prakash, Alexander Rose, Jongeun Choi, Roberto Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Robots to Build Simulations of Themselves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12151v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emergence of vision catalysed a pivotal evolutionary advancement, enabling organisms not only to perceive but also to interact intelligently with their environment. This transformation is mirrored by the evolution of robotic systems, where the ability to leverage vision to simulate and predict their own dynamics marks a leap towards autonomy and self-awareness. Humans utilize vision to record experiences and internally simulate potential actions. For example, we can imagine that, if we stand up and raise our arms, the body will form a T shape without physical movement. Similarly, simulation allows robots to plan and predict the outcomes of potential actions without execution. Here we introduce a self-supervised learning framework to enable robots to model and predict their morphology, kinematics and motor control using only brief raw video data, eliminating the need for extensive real-world data collection and kinematic priors. By observing their own movements, akin to humans watching their reflection in a mirror, robots learn an ability to simulate themselves and predict their spatial motion for various tasks. Our results demonstrate that this self-learned simulation not only enables accurate motion planning but also allows the robot to detect abnormalities and recover from damage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12151v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42256-025-01006-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Teaching robots to build simulations of themselves. Nat Mach Intell (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuhang Hu, Jiong Lin, Hod Lipson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StableLego: Stability Analysis of Block Stacking Assembly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10711v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Structural stability is a necessary condition for successful construction of an assembly. However, designing a stable assembly requires a non-trivial effort since a slight variation in the design could significantly affect the structural stability. To address the challenge, this paper studies the stability of assembly structures, in particular, block stacking assembly. The paper proposes a new optimization formulation, which optimizes over force balancing equations, for inferring the structural stability of 3D block stacking structures. The proposed stability analysis is verified on hand-crafted Lego examples. The experiment results demonstrate that the proposed method can correctly predict whether the structure is stable. In addition, it outperforms the existing methods since it can accurately locate the weakest parts in the design, and more importantly, solve any given assembly structures. To further validate the proposed method, we provide \textit{StableLego}: a comprehensive dataset including 50k+ 3D objects with their Lego layouts. We test the proposed stability analysis and include the stability inference for each corresponding object in StableLego. Our code and the dataset are available at https://github.com/intelligent-control-lab/StableLego.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10711v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 9, no. 11, pp. 9383-9390, Nov. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ruixuan Liu, Kangle Deng, Ziwei Wang, Changliu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Goal-Directed Object Pushing in Cluttered Scenes with Location-Based Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17667v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In complex scenarios where typical pick-and-place techniques are insufficient, often non-prehensile manipulation can ensure that a robot is able to fulfill its task. However, non-prehensile manipulation is challenging due to its underactuated nature with hybrid-dynamics, where a robot needs to reason about an object's long-term behavior and contact-switching, while being robust to contact uncertainty. The presence of clutter in the workspace further complicates this task, introducing the need to include more advanced spatial analysis to avoid unwanted collisions. Building upon prior work on reinforcement learning with multimodal categorical exploration for planar pushing, we propose to incorporate location-based attention to enable robust manipulation in cluttered scenes. Unlike previous approaches addressing this obstacle avoiding pushing task, our framework requires no predefined global paths and considers the desired target orientation of the manipulated object. Experimental results in simulation as well as with a real KUKA iiwa robot arm demonstrate that our learned policy manipulates objects successfully while avoiding collisions through complex obstacle configurations, including dynamic obstacles, to reach the desired target pose.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17667v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nils Dengler, Juan Del Aguila Ferrandis, Jo\~ao Moura, Sethu Vijayakumar, Maren Bennewitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Energy Regularization for Autonomous Gait Transition and Energy-Efficient Quadruped Locomotion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20001v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In reinforcement learning for legged robot locomotion, crafting effective reward strategies is crucial. Pre-defined gait patterns and complex reward systems are widely used to stabilize policy training. Drawing from the natural locomotion behaviors of humans and animals, which adapt their gaits to minimize energy consumption, we propose a simplified, energy-centric reward strategy to foster the development of energy-efficient locomotion across various speeds in quadruped robots. By implementing an adaptive energy reward function and adjusting the weights based on velocity, we demonstrate that our approach enables ANYmal-C and Unitree Go1 robots to autonomously select appropriate gaits, such as four-beat walking at lower speeds and trotting at higher speeds, resulting in improved energy efficiency and stable velocity tracking compared to previous methods using complex reward designs and prior gait knowledge. The effectiveness of our policy is validated through simulations in the IsaacGym simulation environment and on real robots, demonstrating its potential to facilitate stable and adaptive locomotion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20001v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICRA 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Liang, Lingfeng Sun, Xinghao Zhu, Bike Zhang, Ziyin Xiong, Yixiao Wang, Chenran Li, Koushil Sreenath, Masayoshi Tomizuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZeroCAP: Zero-Shot Multi-Robot Context Aware Pattern Formation via Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02318v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Incorporating language comprehension into robotic operations unlocks significant advancements in robotics, but also presents distinct challenges, particularly in executing spatially oriented tasks like pattern formation. This paper introduces ZeroCAP, a novel system that integrates large language models with multi-robot systems for zero-shot context aware pattern formation. Grounded in the principles of language-conditioned robotics, ZeroCAP leverages the interpretative power of language models to translate natural language instructions into actionable robotic configurations. This approach combines the synergy of vision-language models, cutting-edge segmentation techniques and shape descriptors, enabling the realization of complex, context-driven pattern formations in the realm of multi robot coordination. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate the systems proficiency in executing complex context aware pattern formations across a spectrum of tasks, from surrounding and caging objects to infilling regions. This not only validates the system's capability to interpret and implement intricate context-driven tasks but also underscores its adaptability and effectiveness across varied environments and scenarios. The experimental videos and additional information about this work can be found at https://sites.google.com/view/zerocap/home.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02318v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishnunandan L. N. Venkatesh, Byung-Cheol Min</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARS548_ros. An ARS 548 RDI radar driver for ROS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04589v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ARS 548 RDI Radar is a premium model of the fifth generation of 77 GHz long range radar sensors with new RF antenna arrays, which offer digital beam forming. This radar measures independently the distance, speed and angle of objects without any reflectors in one measurement cycle based on Pulse Compression with New Frequency Modulation. Unfortunately, to the best of our knowledge, there are no open source drivers available for Linux systems to enable users to analyze the data acquired by the sensor. In this paper, we present a driver that can interpret the data from the ARS 548 RDI sensor and make it available over the Robot Operating System versions 1 and 2 (ROS and ROS2). Thus, these data can be stored, represented, and analyzed using the powerful tools offered by ROS. Besides, our driver offers advanced object features provided by the sensor, such as relative estimated velocity and acceleration of each object, its orientation and angular velocity. We focus on the configuration of the sensor and the use of our driver including its filtering and representation tools. Besides, we offer a video tutorial to help in its configuration process. Finally, a dataset acquired with this sensor and an Ouster OS1-32 LiDAR sensor, to have baseline measurements, is available, so that the user can check the correctness of our driver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04589v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Fern\'andez-Calatayud, Luc\'ia Coto-Elena, David Alejo, Jos\'e J. Carpio-Jim\'enez, Fernando Caballero, Luis Merino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affordance-Guided Reinforcement Learning via Visual Prompting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10341v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robots equipped with reinforcement learning (RL) have the potential to learn a wide range of skills solely from a reward signal. However, obtaining a robust and dense reward signal for general manipulation tasks remains a challenge. Existing learning-based approaches require significant data, such as human demonstrations of success and failure, to learn task-specific reward functions. Recently, there is also a growing adoption of large multi-modal foundation models for robotics that can perform visual reasoning in physical contexts and generate coarse robot motions for manipulation tasks. Motivated by this range of capability, in this work, we present Keypoint-based Affordance Guidance for Improvements (KAGI), a method leveraging rewards shaped by vision-language models (VLMs) for autonomous RL. State-of-the-art VLMs have demonstrated impressive reasoning about affordances through keypoints in zero-shot, and we use these to define dense rewards that guide autonomous robotic learning. On real-world manipulation tasks specified by natural language descriptions, KAGI improves the sample efficiency of autonomous RL and enables successful task completion in 30K online fine-tuning steps. Additionally, we demonstrate the robustness of KAGI to reductions in the number of in-domain demonstrations used for pre-training, reaching similar performance in 45K online fine-tuning steps. Project website: https://sites.google.com/view/affordance-guided-rl</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10341v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivia Y. Lee, Annie Xie, Kuan Fang, Karl Pertsch, Chelsea Finn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-Shot Imitation under Mismatched Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06615v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human demonstrations as prompts are a powerful way to program robots to do long-horizon manipulation tasks. However, translating these demonstrations into robot-executable actions presents significant challenges due to execution mismatches in movement styles and physical capabilities. Existing methods either depend on human-robot paired data, which is infeasible to scale, or rely heavily on frame-level visual similarities that often break down in practice. To address these challenges, we propose RHyME, a novel framework that automatically aligns human and robot task executions using optimal transport costs. Given long-horizon robot demonstrations, RHyME synthesizes semantically equivalent human videos by retrieving and composing short-horizon human clips. This approach facilitates effective policy training without the need for paired data. RHyME successfully imitates a range of cross-embodiment demonstrators, both in simulation and with a real human hand, achieving over 50\% increase in task success compared to previous methods. We release our code and datasets at https://portal-cornell.github.io/rhyme/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06615v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kushal Kedia, Prithwish Dan, Angela Chao, Maximus Adrian Pace, Sanjiban Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Optimal Experimental Design for Robot Kinematic Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10802v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a Bayesian optimal experimental design for robot kinematic calibration on ${\mathbb{S}^3 \!\times\! \mathbb{R}^3}$. Our method builds upon a Gaussian process approach that incorporates a geometry-aware kernel based on Riemannian Mat\'ern kernels over ${\mathbb{S}^3}$. To learn the forward kinematics errors via Bayesian optimization with a Gaussian process, we define a geodesic distance-based objective function. Pointwise values of this function are sampled via noisy measurements taken using fiducial markers on the end-effector using a camera and computed pose with the nominal kinematics. The corrected Denavit-Hartenberg parameters are obtained using an efficient quadratic program that operates on the collected data sets. The effectiveness of the proposed method is demonstrated via simulations and calibration experiments on NASA's ocean world lander autonomy testbed (OWLAT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10802v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ersin Das, Thomas Touma, Joel W. Burdick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GND: Global Navigation Dataset with Multi-Modal Perception and Multi-Category Traversability in Outdoor Campus Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14262v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Navigating large-scale outdoor environments requires complex reasoning in terms of geometric structures, environmental semantics, and terrain characteristics, which are typically captured by onboard sensors such as LiDAR and cameras. While current mobile robots can navigate such environments using pre-defined, high-precision maps based on hand-crafted rules catered for the specific environment, they lack commonsense reasoning capabilities that most humans possess when navigating unknown outdoor spaces. To address this gap, we introduce the Global Navigation Dataset (GND), a large-scale dataset that integrates multi-modal sensory data, including 3D LiDAR point clouds and RGB and 360-degree images, as well as multi-category traversability maps (pedestrian walkways, vehicle roadways, stairs, off-road terrain, and obstacles) from ten university campuses. These environments encompass a variety of parks, urban settings, elevation changes, and campus layouts of different scales. The dataset covers approximately 2.7km2 and includes at least 350 buildings in total. We also present a set of novel applications of GND to showcase its utility to enable global robot navigation, such as map-based global navigation, mapless navigation, and global place recognition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14262v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Liang, Dibyendu Das, Daeun Song, Md Nahid Hasan Shuvo, Mohammad Durrani, Karthik Taranath, Ivan Penskiy, Dinesh Manocha, Xuesu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DROP: Dexterous Reorientation via Online Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14562v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Achieving human-like dexterity is a longstanding challenge in robotics, in part due to the complexity of planning and control for contact-rich systems. In reinforcement learning (RL), one popular approach has been to use massively-parallelized, domain-randomized simulations to learn a policy offline over a vast array of contact conditions, allowing robust sim-to-real transfer. Inspired by recent advances in real-time parallel simulation, this work considers instead the viability of online planning methods for contact-rich manipulation by studying the well-known in-hand cube reorientation task. We propose a simple architecture that employs a sampling-based predictive controller and vision-based pose estimator to search for contact-rich control actions online. We conduct thorough experiments to assess the real-world performance of our method, architectural design choices, and key factors for robustness, demonstrating that our simple sampling-based approach achieves performance comparable to prior RL-based works. Supplemental material: https://caltech-amber.github.io/drop.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14562v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert H. Li, Preston Culbertson, Vince Kurtz, Aaron D. Ames</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CushionCatch: A Compliant Catching Mechanism for Mobile Manipulators via Combined Optimization and Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14754v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Catching flying objects with a cushioning process is a skill commonly performed by humans, yet it remains a significant challenge for robots. In this paper, we present a framework that combines optimization and learning to achieve compliant catching on mobile manipulators (CCMM). First, we propose a high-level capture planner for mobile manipulators (MM) that calculates the optimal capture point and joint configuration. Next, the pre-catching (PRC) planner ensures the robot reaches the target joint configuration as quickly as possible. To learn compliant catching strategies, we propose a network that leverages the strengths of LSTM for capturing temporal dependencies and positional encoding for spatial context (P-LSTM). This network is designed to effectively learn compliant strategies from human demonstrations. Following this, the post-catching (POC) planner tracks the compliant sequence output by the P-LSTM while avoiding potential collisions due to structural differences between humans and robots. We validate the CCMM framework through both simulated and real-world ball-catching scenarios, achieving a success rate of 98.70% in simulation, 92.59% in real-world tests, and a 28.7% reduction in impact torques. The open source code will be released for the reference of the community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14754v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingjie Chen, Keyu Fan, Qi Yang, Yi Cheng, Houde Liu, Kangkang Dong, Chongkun Xia, Liang Han, Bin Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Planning for Multi-UAV Pursuit-Evasion in Unknown Environments Using Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15866v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multi-UAV pursuit-evasion, where pursuers aim to capture evaders, poses a key challenge for UAV swarm intelligence. Multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) has demonstrated potential in modeling cooperative behaviors, but most RL-based approaches remain constrained to simplified simulations with limited dynamics or fixed scenarios. Previous attempts to deploy RL policy to real-world pursuit-evasion are largely restricted to two-dimensional scenarios, such as ground vehicles or UAVs at fixed altitudes. In this paper, we address multi-UAV pursuit-evasion by considering UAV dynamics and physical constraints. We introduce an evader prediction-enhanced network to tackle partial observability in cooperative strategy learning. Additionally, we propose an adaptive environment generator within MARL training, enabling higher exploration efficiency and better policy generalization across diverse scenarios. Simulations show our method significantly outperforms all baselines in challenging scenarios, generalizing to unseen scenarios with a 100% capture rate. Finally, we derive a feasible policy via a two-stage reward refinement and deploy the policy on real quadrotors in a zero-shot manner. To our knowledge, this is the first work to derive and deploy an RL-based policy using collective thrust and body rates control commands for multi-UAV pursuit-evasion in unknown environments. The open-source code and videos are available at https://sites.google.com/view/pursuit-evasion-rl.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15866v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayu Chen, Chao Yu, Guosheng Li, Wenhao Tang, Shilong Ji, Xinyi Yang, Botian Xu, Huazhong Yang, Yu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tiny Robotics Dataset and Benchmark for Continual Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16215v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Detecting objects in mobile robotics is crucial for numerous applications, from autonomous navigation to inspection. However, robots often need to operate in different domains from those they were trained in, requiring them to adjust to these changes. Tiny mobile robots, subject to size, power, and computational constraints, encounter even more difficulties in running and adapting these algorithms. Such adaptability, though, is crucial for real-world deployment, where robots must operate effectively in dynamic and unpredictable settings. In this work, we introduce a novel benchmark to evaluate the continual learning capabilities of object detection systems in tiny robotic platforms. Our contributions include: (i) Tiny Robotics Object Detection~(TiROD), a comprehensive dataset collected using the onboard camera of a small mobile robot, designed to test object detectors across various domains and classes; (ii) a benchmark of different continual learning strategies on this dataset using NanoDet, a lightweight object detector. Our results highlight key challenges in developing robust and efficient continual learning strategies for object detectors in tiny robotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16215v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Pasti, Riccardo De Monte, Davide Dalle Pezze, Gian Antonio Susto, Nicola Bellotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dashing for the Golden Snitch: Multi-Drone Time-Optimal Motion Planning with Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent innovations in autonomous drones have facilitated time-optimal flight in single-drone configurations, and enhanced maneuverability in multi-drone systems by applying optimal control and learning-based methods. However, few studies have achieved time-optimal motion planning for multi-drone systems, particularly during highly agile maneuvers or in dynamic scenarios. This paper presents a decentralized policy network using multi-agent reinforcement learning for time-optimal multi-drone flight. To strike a balance between flight efficiency and collision avoidance, we introduce a soft collision-free mechanism inspired by optimization-based methods. By customizing PPO in a centralized training, decentralized execution (CTDE) fashion, we unlock higher efficiency and stability in training while ensuring lightweight implementation. Extensive simulations show that, despite slight performance trade-offs compared to single-drone systems, our multi-drone approach maintains near-time-optimal performance with a low collision rate. Real-world experiments validate our method, with two quadrotors using the same network as in simulation achieving a maximum speed of 13.65 m/s and a maximum body rate of 13.4 rad/s in a 5.5 m * 5.5 m * 2.0 m space across various tracks, relying entirely on onboard computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16720v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xian Wang, Jin Zhou, Yuanli Feng, Jiahao Mei, Jiming Chen, Shuo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Submap-based Autonomous MAV Exploration using Visual-Inertial SLAM Configurable for LiDARs or Depth Cameras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16972v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomous exploration of unknown space is an essential component for the deployment of mobile robots in the real world. Safe navigation is crucial for all robotics applications and requires accurate and consistent maps of the robot's surroundings. To achieve full autonomy and allow deployment in a wide variety of environments, the robot must rely on on-board state estimation which is prone to drift over time. We propose a Micro Aerial Vehicle (MAV) exploration framework based on local submaps to allow retaining global consistency by applying loop-closure corrections to the relative submap poses. To enable large-scale exploration we efficiently compute global, environment-wide frontiers from the local submap frontiers and use a sampling-based next-best-view exploration planner. Our method seamlessly supports using either a LiDAR sensor or a depth camera, making it suitable for different kinds of MAV platforms. We perform comparative evaluations in simulation against a state-of-the-art submap-based exploration framework to showcase the efficiency and reconstruction quality of our approach. Finally, we demonstrate the applicability of our method to real-world MAVs, one equipped with a LiDAR and the other with a depth camera. Video available at https://youtu.be/Uf5fwmYcuq4 .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16972v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sotiris Papatheodorou, Simon Boche, Sebasti\'an Barbas Laina, Stefan Leutenegger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HARMONIC: Cognitive and Control Collaboration in Human-Robotic Teams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18047v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces HARMONIC, a cognitive-robotic architecture that integrates the OntoAgent cognitive framework with general-purpose robot control systems applied to human-robot teaming (HRT). We also present a cognitive strategy for robots that incorporates metacognition, natural language communication, and explainability capabilities required for collaborative partnerships in HRT. Through simulation experiments involving a joint search task performed by a heterogeneous team of a UGV, a drone, and a human operator, we demonstrate the system's ability to coordinate actions between robots with heterogeneous capabilities, adapt to complex scenarios, and facilitate natural human-robot communication. Evaluation results show that robots using the OntoAgent architecture within the HARMONIC framework can reason about plans, goals, and team member attitudes while providing clear explanations for their decisions, which are essential prerequisites for realistic human-robot teaming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18047v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Oruganti, Sergei Nirenburg, Marjorie McShane, Jesse English, Michael K. Roberts, Christian Arndt, Sahithi Kamireddy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative motion planning for multi-manipulator systems through Reinforcement Learning and Dynamic Movement Primitives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00757v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robotic tasks often require multiple manipulators to enhance task efficiency and speed, but this increases complexity in terms of collaboration, collision avoidance, and the expanded state-action space. To address these challenges, we propose a multi-level approach combining Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Dynamic Movement Primitives (DMP) to generate adaptive, real-time trajectories for new tasks in dynamic environments using a demonstration library. This method ensures collision-free trajectory generation and efficient collaborative motion planning. We validate the approach through experiments in the PyBullet simulation environment with UR5e robotic manipulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00757v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Singh, Tian Xu, Qing Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LocoVR: Multiuser Indoor Locomotion Dataset in Virtual Reality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06437v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding human locomotion is crucial for AI agents such as robots, particularly in complex indoor home environments. Modeling human trajectories in these spaces requires insight into how individuals maneuver around physical obstacles and manage social navigation dynamics. These dynamics include subtle behaviors influenced by proxemics - the social use of space, such as stepping aside to allow others to pass or choosing longer routes to avoid collisions. Previous research has developed datasets of human motion in indoor scenes, but these are often limited in scale and lack the nuanced social navigation dynamics common in home environments. To address this, we present LocoVR, a dataset of 7000+ two-person trajectories captured in virtual reality from over 130 different indoor home environments. LocoVR provides accurate trajectory data and precise spatial information, along with rich examples of socially-motivated movement behaviors. For example, the dataset captures instances of individuals navigating around each other in narrow spaces, adjusting paths to respect personal boundaries in living areas, and coordinating movements in high-traffic zones like entryways and kitchens. Our evaluation shows that LocoVR significantly enhances model performance in three practical indoor tasks utilizing human trajectories, and demonstrates predicting socially-aware navigation patterns in home environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06437v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kojiro Takeyama, Yimeng Liu, Misha Sra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Maximal Safe Sets Using Hypernetworks for MPC-based Local Trajectory Planning in Unknown Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20267v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel learning-based approach for online estimation of maximal safe sets for local trajectory planning in unknown static environments. The neural representation of a set is used as the terminal set constraint for a model predictive control (MPC) local planner, resulting in improved recursive feasibility and safety. To achieve real-time performance and desired generalization properties, we employ the idea of hypernetworks. We use the Hamilton-Jacobi (HJ) reachability analysis as the source of supervision during the training process, allowing us to consider general nonlinear dynamics and arbitrary constraints. The proposed method is extensively evaluated against relevant baselines in simulations for different environments and robot dynamics. The results show a success rate increase of up to 52 \% compared to the best baseline while maintaining comparable execution speed. Additionally, we deploy our proposed method, NTC-MPC, on a physical robot and demonstrate its ability to safely avoid obstacles in scenarios where the baselines fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20267v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bojan Deraji\'c, Mohamed-Khalil Bouzidi, Sebastian Bernhard, Wolfgang H\"onig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLIP-RT: Learning Language-Conditioned Robotic Policies from Natural Language Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00508v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Teaching robots desired skills in real-world environments remains challenging, especially for non-experts. A key bottleneck is that collecting robotic data often requires expertise or specialized hardware, limiting accessibility and scalability. We posit that natural language offers an intuitive and accessible interface for robot learning. To this end, we study two aspects: (1) enabling non-experts to collect robotic data through natural language supervision (e.g., "move the arm to the right") and (2) learning robotic policies directly from this supervision. Specifically, we introduce a data collection framework that collects robot demonstrations based on natural language supervision and further augments these demonstrations. We then present CLIP-RT, a vision-language-action (VLA) model that learns language-conditioned visuomotor policies from this supervision. CLIP-RT adapts the pretrained CLIP models and learns to predict language-based motion primitives via contrastive imitation learning. We train CLIP-RT on the Open X-Embodiment dataset and finetune it on in-domain data collected by our framework to learn diverse skills. CLIP-RT demonstrates strong capabilities in learning novel manipulation skills, outperforming the state-of-the-art model, OpenVLA (7B parameters), by 24% in average success rates, while using 7x fewer parameters (1B). We further observe that CLIP-RT shows significant improvements in few-shot generalization. Finally, through collaboration with humans or large pretrained models, we demonstrate that CLIP-RT can further improve its generalization on challenging robotic tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00508v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gi-Cheon Kang, Junghyun Kim, Kyuhwan Shim, Jun Ki Lee, Byoung-Tak Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint-repositionable Inner-wireless Planar Snake Robot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13916v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bio-inspired multi-joint snake robots offer the advantages of terrain adaptability due to their limbless structure and high flexibility. However, a series of dozens of motor units in typical multiple-joint snake robots results in a heavy body structure and hundreds of watts of high power consumption. This paper presents a joint-repositionable, inner-wireless snake robot that enables multi-joint-like locomotion using a low-powered underactuated mechanism. The snake robot, consisting of a series of flexible passive links, can dynamically change its joint coupling configuration by repositioning motor-driven joint units along rack gears inside the robot. Additionally, a soft robot skin wirelessly powers the internal joint units, avoiding the risk of wire tangling and disconnection caused by the movable joint units. The combination of the joint-repositionable mechanism and the wireless-charging-enabled soft skin achieves a high degree of bending, along with a lightweight structure of 1.3 kg and energy-efficient wireless power transmission of 7.6 watts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13916v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayato Kanada, Ryo Takahashi, Keito Hayashi, Ryusuke Hosaka, Wakako Yukita, Yasutaka Nakashima, Tomoyuki Yokota, Takao Someya, Mitsuhiro Kamezaki, Yoshihiro Kawahara, Motoji Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DMVC-Tracker: Distributed Multi-Agent Trajectory Planning for Target Tracking Using Dynamic Buffered Voronoi and Inter-Visibility Cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18086v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This letter presents a distributed trajectory planning method for multi-agent aerial tracking. The proposed method uses a Dynamic Buffered Voronoi Cell (DBVC) and a Dynamic Inter-Visibility Cell (DIVC) to formulate the distributed trajectory generation. Specifically, the DBVC and the DIVC are time-variant spaces that prevent mutual collisions and occlusions among agents, while enabling them to maintain suitable distances from the moving target. We combine the DBVC and the DIVC with an efficient Bernstein polynomial motion primitive-based tracking generation method, which has been refined into a less conservative approach than in our previous work. The proposed algorithm can compute each agent's trajectory within several milliseconds on an Intel i7 desktop. We validate the tracking performance in challenging scenarios, including environments with dozens of obstacles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18086v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunwoo Lee, Jungwon Park, H. Jin Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Multi-Robot Semantic Navigation Through Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Score Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18292v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding how humans cooperatively utilize semantic knowledge to explore unfamiliar environments and decide on navigation directions is critical for house service multi-robot systems. Previous methods primarily focused on single-robot centralized planning strategies, which severely limited exploration efficiency. Recent research has considered decentralized planning strategies for multiple robots, assigning separate planning models to each robot, but these approaches often overlook communication costs. In this work, we propose Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Co-Navigation (MCoCoNav), a modular approach that utilizes multimodal Chain-of-Thought to plan collaborative semantic navigation for multiple robots. MCoCoNav combines visual perception with Vision Language Models (VLMs) to evaluate exploration value through probabilistic scoring, thus reducing time costs and achieving stable outputs. Additionally, a global semantic map is used as a communication bridge, minimizing communication overhead while integrating observational results. Guided by scores that reflect exploration trends, robots utilize this map to assess whether to explore new frontier points or revisit history nodes. Experiments on HM3D_v0.2 and MP3D demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. Our code is available at https://github.com/FrankZxShen/MCoCoNav.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18292v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixuan Shen, Haonan Luo, Kexun Chen, Fengmao Lv, Tianrui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Constitutional Filter: Bayesian Estimation of Compliant Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18347v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Predicting agents impacted by legal policies, physical limitations, and operational preferences is inherently difficult. In recent years, neuro-symbolic methods have emerged, integrating machine learning and symbolic reasoning models into end-to-end learnable systems. Hereby, a promising avenue for expressing high-level constraints over multi-modal input data in robotics has opened up. This work introduces an approach for Bayesian estimation of agents expected to comply with a human-interpretable neuro-symbolic model we call its Constitution. Hence, we present the Constitutional Filter (CoFi), leading to improved tracking of agents by leveraging expert knowledge, incorporating deep learning architectures, and accounting for environmental uncertainties. CoFi extends the general, recursive Bayesian estimation setting, ensuring compatibility with a vast landscape of established techniques such as Particle Filters. To underpin the advantages of CoFi, we evaluate its performance on real-world marine traffic data. Beyond improved performance, we show how CoFi can learn to trust and adapt to the level of compliance of an agent, recovering baseline performance even if the assumed Constitution clashes with reality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18347v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Kohaut, Felix Divo, Benedict Flade, Devendra Singh Dhami, Julian Eggert, Kristian Kersting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learn from the Past: Language-conditioned Object Rearrangement with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18516v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Object manipulation for rearrangement into a specific goal state is a significant task for collaborative robots. Accurately determining object placement is a key challenge, as misalignment can increase task complexity and the risk of collisions, affecting the efficiency of the rearrangement process. Most current methods heavily rely on pre-collected datasets to train the model for predicting the goal position. As a result, these methods are restricted to specific instructions, which limits their broader applicability and generalisation. In this paper, we propose a framework of flexible language-conditioned object rearrangement based on the Large Language Model (LLM). Our approach mimics human reasoning by making use of successful past experiences as a reference to infer the best strategies to achieve a current desired goal position. Based on LLM's strong natural language comprehension and inference ability, our method generalises to handle various everyday objects and free-form language instructions in a zero-shot manner. Experimental results demonstrate that our methods can effectively execute the robotic rearrangement tasks, even those involving long sequences of orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18516v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanqun Cao, Ryan Mckenna, Erich Graf, John Oyekan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VL-Nav: Real-time Vision-Language Navigation with Spatial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00931v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vision-language navigation in unknown environments is crucial for mobile robots. In scenarios such as household assistance and rescue, mobile robots need to understand a human command, such as "find a person wearing black". We present a novel vision-language navigation (VL-Nav) system that integrates efficient spatial reasoning on low-power robots. Unlike prior methods that rely on a single image-level feature similarity to guide a robot, our method integrates pixel-wise vision-language features with curiosity-driven exploration. This approach enables robust navigation to human-instructed instances across diverse environments. We deploy VL-Nav on a four-wheel mobile robot and evaluate its performance through comprehensive navigation tasks in both indoor and outdoor environments, spanning different scales and semantic complexities. Remarkably, VL-Nav operates at a real-time frequency of 30 Hz with a Jetson Orin NX, highlighting its ability to conduct efficient vision-language navigation. Results show that VL-Nav achieves an overall success rate of 86.3%, outperforming previous methods by 44.15%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00931v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Du, Taimeng Fu, Zhuoqun Chen, Bowen Li, Shaoshu Su, Zhipeng Zhao, Chen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Object Weight in Handovers: Inspiring Robotic Grip Release and Motion from Human Handovers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17834v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work explores the effect of object weight on human motion and grip release during handovers to enhance the naturalness, safety, and efficiency of robot-human interactions. We introduce adaptive robotic strategies based on the analysis of human handover behavior with varying object weights. The key contributions of this work includes the development of an adaptive grip-release strategy for robots, a detailed analysis of how object weight influences human motion to guide robotic motion adaptations, and the creation of handover-datasets incorporating various object weights, including the YCB handover dataset. By aligning robotic grip release and motion with human behavior, this work aims to improve robot-human handovers for different weighted objects. We also evaluate these human-inspired adaptive robotic strategies in robot-to-human handovers to assess their effectiveness and performance and demonstrate that they outperform the baseline approaches in terms of naturalness, efficiency, and user perception.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17834v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parag Khanna, M{\aa}rten Bj\"orkman, Christian Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CarPlanner: Consistent Auto-regressive Trajectory Planning for Large-scale Reinforcement Learning in Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19908v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Trajectory planning is vital for autonomous driving, ensuring safe and efficient navigation in complex environments. While recent learning-based methods, particularly reinforcement learning (RL), have shown promise in specific scenarios, RL planners struggle with training inefficiencies and managing large-scale, real-world driving scenarios. In this paper, we introduce \textbf{CarPlanner}, a \textbf{C}onsistent \textbf{a}uto-\textbf{r}egressive \textbf{Planner} that uses RL to generate multi-modal trajectories. The auto-regressive structure enables efficient large-scale RL training, while the incorporation of consistency ensures stable policy learning by maintaining coherent temporal consistency across time steps. Moreover, CarPlanner employs a generation-selection framework with an expert-guided reward function and an invariant-view module, simplifying RL training and enhancing policy performance. Extensive analysis demonstrates that our proposed RL framework effectively addresses the challenges of training efficiency and performance enhancement, positioning CarPlanner as a promising solution for trajectory planning in autonomous driving. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to demonstrate that the RL-based planner can surpass both IL- and rule-based state-of-the-arts (SOTAs) on the challenging large-scale real-world dataset nuPlan. Our proposed CarPlanner surpasses RL-, IL-, and rule-based SOTA approaches within this demanding dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19908v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongkun Zhang, Jiaming Liang, Ke Guo, Sha Lu, Qi Wang, Rong Xiong, Zhenwei Miao, Yue Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DexGraspVLA: A Vision-Language-Action Framework Towards General Dexterous Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20900v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dexterous grasping remains a fundamental yet challenging problem in robotics. A general-purpose robot must be capable of grasping diverse objects in arbitrary scenarios. However, existing research typically relies on specific assumptions, such as single-object settings or limited environments, leading to constrained generalization. Our solution is DexGraspVLA, a hierarchical framework that utilizes a pre-trained Vision-Language model as the high-level task planner and learns a diffusion-based policy as the low-level Action controller. The key insight lies in iteratively transforming diverse language and visual inputs into domain-invariant representations, where imitation learning can be effectively applied due to the alleviation of domain shift. Thus, it enables robust generalization across a wide range of real-world scenarios. Notably, our method achieves a 90+% success rate under thousands of unseen object, lighting, and background combinations in a ``zero-shot'' environment. Empirical analysis further confirms the consistency of internal model behavior across environmental variations, thereby validating our design and explaining its generalization performance. We hope our work can be a step forward in achieving general dexterous grasping. Our demo and code can be found at https://dexgraspvla.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20900v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Zhong, Xuchuan Huang, Ruochong Li, Ceyao Zhang, Yitao Liang, Yaodong Yang, Yuanpei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Magnetic-Actuated Vision-Based Whisker Array for Contact Perception and Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tactile sensing and the manipulation of delicate objects are critical challenges in robotics. This study presents a vision-based magnetic-actuated whisker array sensor that integrates these functions. The sensor features eight whiskers arranged circularly, supported by an elastomer membrane and actuated by electromagnets and permanent magnets. A camera tracks whisker movements, enabling high-resolution tactile feedback. The sensor's performance was evaluated through object classification and grasping experiments. In the classification experiment, the sensor approached objects from four directions and accurately identified five distinct objects with a classification accuracy of 99.17% using a Multi-Layer Perceptron model. In the grasping experiment, the sensor tested configurations of eight, four, and two whiskers, achieving the highest success rate of 87% with eight whiskers. These results highlight the sensor's potential for precise tactile sensing and reliable manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00133v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixian Hu, Juan Wachs, Yu She</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floorplan-SLAM: A Real-Time, High-Accuracy, and Long-Term Multi-Session Point-Plane SLAM for Efficient Floorplan Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00397v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Floorplan reconstruction provides structural priors essential for reliable indoor robot navigation and high-level scene understanding. However, existing approaches either require time-consuming offline processing with a complete map, or rely on expensive sensors and substantial computational resources. To address the problems, we propose Floorplan-SLAM, which incorporates floorplan reconstruction tightly into a multi-session SLAM system by seamlessly interacting with plane extraction, pose estimation, and back-end optimization, achieving real-time, high-accuracy, and long-term floorplan reconstruction using only a stereo camera. Specifically, we present a robust plane extraction algorithm that operates in a compact plane parameter space and leverages spatially complementary features to accurately detect planar structures, even in weakly textured scenes. Furthermore, we propose a floorplan reconstruction module tightly coupled with the SLAM system, which uses continuously optimized plane landmarks and poses to formulate and solve a novel optimization problem, thereby enabling real-time incremental floorplan reconstruction. Note that by leveraging the map merging capability of multi-session SLAM, our method supports long-term floorplan reconstruction across multiple sessions without redundant data collection. Experiments on the VECtor and the self-collected datasets indicate that Floorplan-SLAM significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in terms of plane extraction robustness, pose estimation accuracy, and floorplan reconstruction fidelity and speed, achieving real-time performance at 25-45 FPS without GPU acceleration, which reduces the floorplan reconstruction time for a 1000 square meters scene from over 10 hours to just 9.44 minutes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00397v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haolin Wang, Zeren Lv, Hao Wei, Haijiang Zhu, Yihong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Perceptive Humanoid Locomotion over Challenging Terrain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00692v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Humanoid robots are engineered to navigate terrains akin to those encountered by humans, which necessitates human-like locomotion and perceptual abilities. Currently, the most reliable controllers for humanoid motion rely exclusively on proprioception, a reliance that becomes both dangerous and unreliable when coping with rugged terrain. Although the integration of height maps into perception can enable proactive gait planning, robust utilization of this information remains a significant challenge, especially when exteroceptive perception is noisy. To surmount these challenges, we propose a solution based on a teacher-student distillation framework. In this paradigm, an oracle policy accesses noise-free data to establish an optimal reference policy, while the student policy not only imitates the teacher's actions but also simultaneously trains a world model with a variational information bottleneck for sensor denoising and state estimation. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that our approach markedly enhances performance in scenarios characterized by unreliable terrain estimations. Moreover, we conducted rigorous testing in both challenging urban settings and off-road environments, the model successfully traverse 2 km of varied terrain without external intervention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00692v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wandong Sun, Baoshi Cao, Long Chen, Yongbo Su, Yang Liu, Zongwu Xie, Hong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Trajectory Planning for Cooperative Manipulation with Multiple Quadrotors Using Control Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01096v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel trajectory planning algorithm for cooperative manipulation with multiple quadrotors using control barrier functions (CBFs). Our approach addresses the complex dynamics of a system in which a team of quadrotors transports and manipulates a cable-suspended rigid-body payload in environments cluttered with obstacles. The proposed algorithm ensures obstacle avoidance for the entire system, including the quadrotors, cables, and the payload in all six degrees of freedom (DoF). We introduce the use of CBFs to enable safe and smooth maneuvers, effectively navigating through cluttered environments while accommodating the system's nonlinear dynamics. To simplify complex constraints, the system components are modeled as convex polytopes, and the Duality theorem is employed to reduce the computational complexity of the optimization problem. We validate the performance of our planning approach both in simulation and real-world environments using multiple quadrotors. The results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach in achieving obstacle avoidance and safe trajectory generation for cooperative transportation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01096v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Pallar, Guanrui Li, Mrunal Sarvaiya, Giuseppe Loianno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Action Tokenizer Matters in In-Context Imitation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01206v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In-context imitation learning (ICIL) is a new paradigm that enables robots to generalize from demonstrations to unseen tasks without retraining. A well-structured action representation is the key to capturing demonstration information effectively, yet action tokenizer (the process of discretizing and encoding actions) remains largely unexplored in ICIL. In this work, we first systematically evaluate existing action tokenizer methods in ICIL and reveal a critical limitation: while they effectively encode action trajectories, they fail to preserve temporal smoothness, which is crucial for stable robotic execution. To address this, we propose LipVQ-VAE, a variational autoencoder that enforces the Lipschitz condition in the latent action space via weight normalization. By propagating smoothness constraints from raw action inputs to a quantized latent codebook, LipVQ-VAE generates more stable and smoother actions. When integrating into ICIL, LipVQ-VAE improves performance by more than 5.3% in high-fidelity simulators, with real-world experiments confirming its ability to produce smoother, more reliable trajectories. Code and checkpoints will be released.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01206v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>An Dinh Vuong, Minh Nhat Vu, Dong An, Ian Reid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perceptual Motor Learning with Active Inference Framework for Robust Lateral Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01676v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel Perceptual Motor Learning (PML) framework integrated with Active Inference (AIF) to enhance lateral control in Highly Automated Vehicles (HAVs). PML, inspired by human motor learning, emphasizes the seamless integration of perception and action, enabling efficient decision-making in dynamic environments. Traditional autonomous driving approaches--including modular pipelines, imitation learning, and reinforcement learning--struggle with adaptability, generalization, and computational efficiency. In contrast, PML with AIF leverages a generative model to minimize prediction error ("surprise") and actively shape vehicle control based on learned perceptual-motor representations. Our approach unifies deep learning with active inference principles, allowing HAVs to perform lane-keeping maneuvers with minimal data and without extensive retraining across different environments. Extensive experiments in the CARLA simulator demonstrate that PML with AIF enhances adaptability without increasing computational overhead while achieving performance comparable to conventional methods. These findings highlight the potential of PML-driven active inference as a robust alternative for real-world autonomous driving applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01676v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elahe Delavari, John Moore, Junho Hong, Jaerock Kwon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SEB-Naver: A SE(2)-based Local Navigation Framework for Car-like Robots on Uneven Terrain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02412v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomous navigation of car-like robots on uneven terrain poses unique challenges compared to flat terrain, particularly in traversability assessment and terrain-associated kinematic modelling for motion planning. This paper introduces SEB-Naver, a novel SE(2)-based local navigation framework designed to overcome these challenges. First, we propose an efficient traversability assessment method for SE(2) grids, leveraging GPU parallel computing to enable real-time updates and maintenance of local maps. Second, inspired by differential flatness, we present an optimization-based trajectory planning method that integrates terrain-associated kinematic models, significantly improving both planning efficiency and trajectory quality. Finally, we unify these components into SEB-Naver, achieving real-time terrain assessment and trajectory optimization. Extensive simulations and real-world experiments demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of our approach. The code is at https://github.com/ZJU-FAST-Lab/seb_naver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02412v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoying Li, Long Xu, Xiaolin Huang, Donglai Xue, Zhihao Zhang, Zhichao Han, Chao Xu, Yanjun Cao, Fei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integral Forms in Matrix Lie Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02820v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Matrix Lie groups provide a language for describing motion in such fields as robotics, computer vision, and graphics. When using these tools, we are often faced with turning infinite-series expressions into more compact finite series (e.g., the Euler-Rodriques formula), which can sometimes be onerous. In this paper, we identify some useful integral forms in matrix Lie group expressions that offer a more streamlined pathway for computing compact analytic results. Moreover, we present some recursive structures in these integral forms that show many of these expressions are interrelated. Key to our approach is that we are able to apply the minimal polynomial for a Lie algebra quite early in the process to keep expressions compact throughout the derivations. With the series approach, the minimal polynomial is usually applied at the end, making it hard to recognize common analytic expressions in the result. We show that our integral method can reproduce several series-derived results from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02820v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy D Barfoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adapting Pre-Trained Vision Models for Novel Instance Detection and Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17859v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Novel Instance Detection and Segmentation (NIDS) aims at detecting and segmenting novel object instances given a few examples of each instance. We propose a unified, simple, yet effective framework (NIDS-Net) comprising object proposal generation, embedding creation for both instance templates and proposal regions, and embedding matching for instance label assignment. Leveraging recent advancements in large vision methods, we utilize Grounding DINO and Segment Anything Model (SAM) to obtain object proposals with accurate bounding boxes and masks. Central to our approach is the generation of high-quality instance embeddings. We utilized foreground feature averages of patch embeddings from the DINOv2 ViT backbone, followed by refinement through a weight adapter mechanism that we introduce.
  We show experimentally that our weight adapter can adjust the embeddings locally within their feature space and effectively limit overfitting in the few-shot setting. Furthermore, the weight adapter optimizes weights to enhance the distinctiveness of instance embeddings during similarity computation. This methodology enables a straightforward matching strategy that results in significant performance gains. Our framework surpasses current state-of-the-art methods, demonstrating notable improvements in four detection datasets. In the segmentation tasks on seven core datasets of the BOP challenge, our method outperforms the leading published RGB methods and remains competitive with the best RGB-D method. We have also verified our method using real-world images from a Fetch robot and a RealSense camera. Project Page: https://irvlutd.github.io/NIDSNet/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17859v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangxiao Lu, Jishnu Jaykumar P, Yunhui Guo, Nicholas Ruozzi, Yu Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSCPR: Cross-Source-Context Indoor RGB-D Place Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17457v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend our previous work, PoCo, and present a new algorithm, Cross-Source-Context Place Recognition (CSCPR), for RGB-D indoor place recognition that integrates global retrieval and reranking into an end-to-end model and keeps the consistency of using Context-of-Clusters (CoCs) for feature processing. Unlike prior approaches that primarily focus on the RGB domain for place recognition reranking, CSCPR is designed to handle the RGB-D data. We apply the CoCs to handle cross-sourced and cross-scaled RGB-D point clouds and introduce two novel modules for reranking: the Self-Context Cluster (SCC) and the Cross Source Context Cluster (CSCC), which enhance feature representation and match query-database pairs based on local features, respectively. We also release two new datasets, ScanNetIPR and ARKitIPR. Our experiments demonstrate that CSCPR significantly outperforms state-of-the-art models on these datasets by at least 29.27% in Recall@1 on the ScanNet-PR dataset and 43.24% in the new datasets. Code and datasets will be released.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17457v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Liang, Zhuo Deng, Zheming Zhou, Min Sun, Omid Ghasemalizadeh, Cheng-Hao Kuo, Arnie Sen, Dinesh Manocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ODYSSEE: Oyster Detection Yielded by Sensor Systems on Edge Electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07003v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Oysters are a vital keystone species in coastal ecosystems, providing significant economic, environmental, and cultural benefits. As the importance of oysters grows, so does the relevance of autonomous systems for their detection and monitoring. However, current monitoring strategies often rely on destructive methods. While manual identification of oysters from video footage is non-destructive, it is time-consuming, requires expert input, and is further complicated by the challenges of the underwater environment.
  To address these challenges, we propose a novel pipeline using stable diffusion to augment a collected real dataset with realistic synthetic data. This method enhances the dataset used to train a YOLOv10-based vision model. The model is then deployed and tested on an edge platform in underwater robotics, achieving a state-of-the-art 0.657 mAP@50 for oyster detection on the Aqua2 platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07003v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaomin Lin, Vivek Mange, Arjun Suresh, Bernhard Neuberger, Aadi Palnitkar, Brendan Campbell, Alan Williams, Kleio Baxevani, Jeremy Mallette, Alhim Vera, Markus Vincze, Ioannis Rekleitis, Herbert G. Tanner, Yiannis Aloimonos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSplatLoc: Grounding Keypoint Descriptors into 3D Gaussian Splatting for Improved Visual Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Although various visual localization approaches exist, such as scene coordinate regression and camera pose regression, these methods often struggle with optimization complexity or limited accuracy. To address these challenges, we explore the use of novel view synthesis techniques, particularly 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS), which enables the compact encoding of both 3D geometry and scene appearance. We propose a two-stage procedure that integrates dense and robust keypoint descriptors from the lightweight XFeat feature extractor into 3DGS, enhancing performance in both indoor and outdoor environments. The coarse pose estimates are directly obtained via 2D-3D correspondences between the 3DGS representation and query image descriptors. In the second stage, the initial pose estimate is refined by minimizing the rendering-based photometric warp loss. Benchmarking on widely used indoor and outdoor datasets demonstrates improvements over recent neural rendering-based localization methods, such as NeRFMatch and PNeRFLoc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16502v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gennady Sidorov, Malik Mohrat, Denis Gridusov, Ruslan Rakhimov, Sergey Kolyubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LS-HAR: Language Supervised Human Action Recognition with Salient Fusion, Construction Sites as a Use-Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01962v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detecting human actions is a crucial task for autonomous robots and vehicles, often requiring the integration of various data modalities for improved accuracy. In this study, we introduce a novel approach to Human Action Recognition (HAR) using language supervision named LS-HAR based on skeleton and visual cues. Our method leverages a language model to guide the feature extraction process in the skeleton encoder. Specifically, we employ learnable prompts for the language model conditioned on the skeleton modality to optimize feature representation. Furthermore, we propose a fusion mechanism that combines dual-modality features using a salient fusion module, incorporating attention and transformer mechanisms to address the modalities' high dimensionality. This fusion process prioritizes informative video frames and body joints, enhancing the recognition accuracy of human actions. Additionally, we introduce a new dataset tailored for real-world robotic applications in construction sites, featuring visual, skeleton, and depth data modalities, named VolvoConstAct. This dataset serves to facilitate the training and evaluation of machine learning models to instruct autonomous construction machines for performing necessary tasks in real-world construction sites. To evaluate our approach, we conduct experiments on our dataset as well as three widely used public datasets: NTU-RGB+D, NTU-RGB+D 120, and NW-UCLA. Results reveal that our proposed method achieves promising performance across all datasets, demonstrating its robustness and potential for various applications. The code, dataset, and demonstration of real-machine experiments are available at: https://mmahdavian.github.io/ls_har/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01962v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mahdavian, Mohammad Loni, Ted Samuelsson, Mo Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision-based Geo-Localization of Future Mars Rotorcraft in Challenging Illumination Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Planetary exploration using aerial assets has the potential for unprecedented scientific discoveries on Mars. While NASA's Mars helicopter Ingenuity proved flight in Martian atmosphere is possible, future Mars rotocrafts will require advanced navigation capabilities for long-range flights. One such critical capability is Map-based Localization (MbL) which registers an onboard image to a reference map during flight in order to mitigate cumulative drift from visual odometry. However, significant illumination differences between rotocraft observations and a reference map prove challenging for traditional MbL systems, restricting the operational window of the vehicle. In this work, we investigate a new MbL system and propose Geo-LoFTR, a geometry-aided deep learning model for image registration that is more robust under large illumination differences than prior models. The system is supported by a custom simulation framework that uses real orbital maps to produce large amounts of realistic images of the Martian terrain. Comprehensive evaluations show that our proposed system outperforms prior MbL efforts in terms of localization accuracy under significant lighting and scale variations. Furthermore, we demonstrate the validity of our approach across a simulated Martian day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09795v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Pisanti, Robert Hewitt, Roland Brockers, Georgios Georgakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Sensor Fusion Approach for Rapid Orthoimage Generation in Large-Scale UAV Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01202v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rapid generation of large-scale orthoimages from Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) has been a long-standing focus of research in the field of aerial mapping. A multi-sensor UAV system, integrating the Global Positioning System (GPS), Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU), 4D millimeter-wave radar and camera, can provide an effective solution to this problem. In this paper, we utilize multi-sensor data to overcome the limitations of conventional orthoimage generation methods in terms of temporal performance, system robustness, and geographic reference accuracy. A prior-pose-optimized feature matching method is introduced to enhance matching speed and accuracy, reducing the number of required features and providing precise references for the Structure from Motion (SfM) process. The proposed method exhibits robustness in low-texture scenes like farmlands, where feature matching is difficult. Experiments show that our approach achieves accurate feature matching orthoimage generation in a short time. The proposed drone system effectively aids in farmland detection and management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01202v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialei He, Zhihao Zhan, Zhituo Tu, Xiang Zhu, Jie Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Category-level Meta-learned NeRF Priors for Efficient Object Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01582v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 3D object mapping, category-level priors enable efficient object reconstruction and canonical pose estimation, requiring only a single prior per semantic category (e.g., chair, book, laptop). Recently, DeepSDF has predominantly been used as a category-level shape prior, but it struggles to reconstruct sharp geometry and is computationally expensive. In contrast, NeRFs capture fine details but have yet to be effectively integrated with category-level priors in a real-time multi-object mapping framework. To bridge this gap, we introduce PRENOM, a Prior-based Efficient Neural Object Mapper that integrates category-level priors with object-level NeRFs to enhance reconstruction efficiency while enabling canonical object pose estimation. PRENOM gets to know objects on a first-name basis by meta-learning on synthetic reconstruction tasks generated from open-source shape datasets. To account for object category variations, it employs a multi-objective genetic algorithm to optimize the NeRF architecture for each category, balancing reconstruction quality and training time. Additionally, prior-based probabilistic ray sampling directs sampling toward expected object regions, accelerating convergence and improving reconstruction quality under constrained resources. Experimental results on a low-end GPU highlight the ability of PRENOM to achieve high-quality reconstructions while maintaining computational feasibility. Specifically, comparisons with prior-free NeRF-based approaches on a synthetic dataset show a 21% lower Chamfer distance, demonstrating better reconstruction quality. Furthermore, evaluations against other approaches using shape priors on a noisy real-world dataset indicate a 13% improvement averaged across all reconstruction metrics, and comparable pose and size estimation accuracy, while being trained for 5x less time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01582v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saad Ejaz, Hriday Bavle, Laura Ribeiro, Holger Voos, Jose Luis Sanchez-Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
