<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-Temporal Graph Diffusion Policy with Kinematic Modeling for Bimanual Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the significant success of imitation learning in robotic manipulation, its application to bimanual tasks remains highly challenging. Existing approaches mainly learn a policy to predict a distant next-best end-effector pose (NBP) and then compute the corresponding joint rotation angles for motion using inverse kinematics. However, they suffer from two important issues: (1) rarely considering the physical robotic structure, which may cause self-collisions or interferences, and (2) overlooking the kinematics constraint, which may result in the predicted poses not conforming to the actual limitations of the robot joints. In this paper, we propose Kinematics enhanced Spatial-TemporAl gRaph Diffuser (KStar Diffuser). Specifically, (1) to incorporate the physical robot structure information into action prediction, KStar Diffuser maintains a dynamic spatial-temporal graph according to the physical bimanual joint motions at continuous timesteps. This dynamic graph serves as the robot-structure condition for denoising the actions; (2) to make the NBP learning objective consistent with kinematics, we introduce the differentiable kinematics to provide the reference for optimizing KStar Diffuser. This module regularizes the policy to predict more reliable and kinematics-aware next end-effector poses. Experimental results show that our method effectively leverages the physical structural information and generates kinematics-aware actions in both simulation and real-world</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10743v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Lv, Hao Li, Xiang Deng, Rui Shao, Yinchuan Li, Jianye Hao, Longxiang Gao, Michael Yu Wang, Liqiang Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication-Aware Iterative Map Compression for Online Path-Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of optimizing communicated information among heterogeneous, resource-aware robot teams to facilitate their navigation. In such operations, a mobile robot compresses its local map to assist another robot in reaching a target within an uncharted environment. The primary challenge lies in ensuring that the map compression step balances network load while transmitting only the most essential information for effective navigation. We propose a communication framework that sequentially selects the optimal map compression in a task-driven, communication-aware manner. It introduces a decoder capable of iterative map estimation, handling noise through Kalman filter techniques. The computational speed of our decoder allows for a larger compression template set compared to previous methods, and enables applications in more challenging environments. Specifically, our simulations demonstrate a remarkable 98% reduction in communicated information, compared to a framework that transmits the raw data, on a large Mars inclination map and an Earth map, all while maintaining similar planning costs. Furthermore, our method significantly reduces computational time compared to the state-of-the-art approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10843v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Psomiadis, Ali Reza Pedram, Dipankar Maity, Panagiotis Tsiotras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapidly Converging Time-Discounted Ergodicity on Graphs for Active Inspection of Confined Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ergodic exploration has spawned a lot of interest in mobile robotics due to its ability to design time trajectories that match desired spatial coverage statistics. However, current ergodic approaches are for continuous spaces, which require detailed sensory information at each point and can lead to fractal-like trajectories that cannot be tracked easily. This paper presents a new ergodic approach for graph-based discretization of continuous spaces. It also introduces a new time-discounted ergodicity metric, wherein early visitations of information-rich nodes are weighted more than late visitations. A Markov chain synthesized using a convex program is shown to converge more rapidly to time-discounted ergodicity than the traditional fastest mixing Markov chain. The resultant ergodic traversal method is used within a hierarchical framework for active inspection of confined spaces with the goal of detecting anomalies robustly using SLAM-driven Bayesian hypothesis testing. Both simulation and physical experiments on a ground robot show the advantages of this framework over greedy and random exploration methods for left-behind foreign object debris detection in a ballast tank.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10853v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Wong, Ryan H. Lee, Tyler M. Paine, Santosh Devasia, Ashis G. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fusion of Indirect Methods and Iterative Learning for Persistent Velocity Trajectory Optimization of a Sustainably Powered Autonomous Surface Vessel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present the methodology and results for a real-time velocity trajectory optimization for a solar-powered autonomous surface vessel (ASV), where we combine indirect optimal control techniques with iterative learning. The ASV exhibits cyclic operation due to the nature of the solar profile, but weather patterns create inevitable disturbances in this profile. The nature of the problem results in a formulation where the satisfaction of pointwise-in-time state of charge constraints does not generally guarantee persistent feasibility, and the goal is to maximize information gathered over a very long (ultimately persistent) time duration. To address these challenges, we first use barrier functions to tighten pointwise-in-time state of charge constraints by the minimal amount necessary to achieve persistent feasibility. We then use indirect methods to derive a simple switching control law, where the optimal velocity is shown to be an undetermined constant value during each constraint-inactive time segment. To identify this optimal constant velocity (which can vary from one segment to the next), we employ an iterative learning approach. The result is a simple closed-form control law that does not require a solar forecast. We present simulation-based validation results, based on a model of the SeaTrac SP-48 ASV and solar data from the North Carolina coast. These simulation results show that the proposed methodology, which amounts to a closed-form controller and simple iterative learning update law, performs nearly as well as a model predictive control approach that requires an accurate future solar forecast and significantly greater computational capability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10884v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kavin M. Govindarajan, Devansh R Agrawal, Dimitra Panagou, Chris Vermillion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transferring Kinesthetic Demonstrations across Diverse Objects for Manipulation Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a demonstration of a complex manipulation task such as pouring liquid from one container to another, we seek to generate a motion plan for a new task instance involving objects with different geometries. This is non-trivial since we need to simultaneously ensure that the implicit motion constraints are satisfied (glass held upright while moving), the motion is collision-free, and that the task is successful (e.g. liquid is poured into the target container). We solve this problem by identifying positions of critical locations and associating a reference frame (called motion transfer frames) on the manipulated object and the target, selected based on their geometries and the task at hand. By tracking and transferring the path of the motion transfer frames, we generate motion plans for arbitrary task instances with objects of different geometries and poses. We show results from simulation as well as robot experiments on physical objects to evaluate the effectiveness of our solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyendu Das, Aditya Patankar, Nilanjan Chakraborty, C. R. Ramakrishnan, I. V. Ramakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Soft Robot Control via Adiabatic Spectral Submanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanical complexity of soft robots creates significant challenges for their model-based control. Specifically, linear data-driven models have struggled to control soft robots on complex, spatially extended paths that explore regions with significant nonlinear behavior. To account for these nonlinearities, we develop here a model-predictive control strategy based on the recent theory of adiabatic spectral submanifolds (aSSMs). This theory is applicable because the internal vibrations of heavily overdamped robots decay at a speed that is much faster than the desired speed of the robot along its intended path. In that case, low-dimensional attracting invariant manifolds (aSSMs) emanate from the path and carry the dominant dynamics of the robot. Aided by this recent theory, we devise an aSSM-based model-predictive control scheme purely from data. We demonstrate the effectiveness of this data-driven model on various dynamic trajectory tracking tasks on a high-fidelity and high-dimensional finite-element model of a soft trunk robot. Notably, we find that four- or five-dimensional aSSM-reduced models outperform the tracking performance of other data-driven modeling methods by a factor up to 10 across all closed-loop control tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10919v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roshan S. Kaundinya, John Irvin Alora, Jonas G. Matt, Luis A. Pabon, Marco Pavone, George Haller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Development of the MeCO Open-Source Autonomous Underwater Vehicle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present MeCO, the Medium Cost Open-source autonomous underwater vehicle (AUV), a versatile autonomous vehicle designed to support research and development in underwater human-robot interaction (UHRI) and marine robotics in general. An inexpensive platform to build compared to similarly-capable AUVs, the MeCO design and software are released under open-source licenses, making it a cost effective, extensible, and open platform. It is equipped with UHRI-focused systems, such as front and side facing displays, light-based communication devices, a transducer for acoustic interaction, and stereo vision, in addition to typical AUV sensing and actuation components. Additionally, MeCO is capable of real-time deep learning inference using the latest edge computing devices, while maintaining low-latency, closed-loop control through high-performance microcontrollers. MeCO is designed from the ground up for modularity in internal electronics, external payloads, and software architecture, exploiting open-source robotics and containerarization tools. We demonstrate the diverse capabilities of MeCO through simulated, closed-water, and open-water experiments. All resources necessary to build and run MeCO, including software and hardware design, have been made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10928v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Widhalm, Cory Ohnsted, Corey Knutson, Demetrious Kutzke, Sakshi Singh, Rishi Mukherjee, Grant Schwidder, Ying-Kun Wu, Junaed Sattar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe Continual Domain Adaptation after Sim2Real Transfer of Reinforcement Learning Policies in Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Domain randomization has emerged as a fundamental technique in reinforcement learning (RL) to facilitate the transfer of policies from simulation to real-world robotic applications. Many existing domain randomization approaches have been proposed to improve robustness and sim2real transfer. These approaches rely on wide randomization ranges to compensate for the unknown actual system parameters, leading to robust but inefficient real-world policies. In addition, the policies pretrained in the domain-randomized simulation are fixed after deployment due to the inherent instability of the optimization processes based on RL and the necessity of sampling exploitative but potentially unsafe actions on the real system. This limits the adaptability of the deployed policy to the inevitably changing system parameters or environment dynamics over time. We leverage safe RL and continual learning under domain-randomized simulation to address these limitations and enable safe deployment-time policy adaptation in real-world robot control. The experiments show that our method enables the policy to adapt and fit to the current domain distribution and environment dynamics of the real system while minimizing safety risks and avoiding issues like catastrophic forgetting of the general policy found in randomized simulation during the pretraining phase. Videos and supplementary material are available at https://safe-cda.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10949v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josip Josifovski, Shangding Gu, Mohammadhossein Malmir, Haoliang Huang, Sayantan Auddy, Nicol\'as Navarro-Guerrero, Costas Spanos, Alois Knoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Imitation Learning Policy Better than Mine? Policy Comparison with Near-Optimal Stopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Imitation learning has enabled robots to perform complex, long-horizon tasks in challenging dexterous manipulation settings. As new methods are developed, they must be rigorously evaluated and compared against corresponding baselines through repeated evaluation trials. However, policy comparison is fundamentally constrained by a small feasible sample size (e.g., 10 or 50) due to significant human effort and limited inference throughput of policies. This paper proposes a novel statistical framework for rigorously comparing two policies in the small sample size regime. Prior work in statistical policy comparison relies on batch testing, which requires a fixed, pre-determined number of trials and lacks flexibility in adapting the sample size to the observed evaluation data. Furthermore, extending the test with additional trials risks inducing inadvertent p-hacking, undermining statistical assurances. In contrast, our proposed statistical test is sequential, allowing researchers to decide whether or not to run more trials based on intermediate results. This adaptively tailors the number of trials to the difficulty of the underlying comparison, saving significant time and effort without sacrificing probabilistic correctness. Extensive numerical simulation and real-world robot manipulation experiments show that our test achieves near-optimal stopping, letting researchers stop evaluation and make a decision in a near-minimal number of trials. Specifically, it reduces the number of evaluation trials by up to 40% as compared to state-of-the-art baselines, while preserving the probabilistic correctness and statistical power of the comparison. Moreover, our method is strongest in the most challenging comparison instances (requiring the most evaluation trials); in a multi-task comparison scenario, we save the evaluator more than 200 simulation rollouts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10966v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Snyder, Asher James Hancock, Apurva Badithela, Emma Dixon, Patrick Miller, Rares Andrei Ambrus, Anirudha Majumdar, Masha Itkina, Haruki Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image-Goal Navigation Using Refined Feature Guidance and Scene Graph Enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel image-goal navigation approach, named RFSG. Our focus lies in leveraging the fine-grained connections between goals, observations, and the environment within limited image data, all the while keeping the navigation architecture simple and lightweight. To this end, we propose the spatial-channel attention mechanism, enabling the network to learn the importance of multi-dimensional features to fuse the goal and observation features. In addition, a selfdistillation mechanism is incorporated to further enhance the feature representation capabilities. Given that the navigation task needs surrounding environmental information for more efficient navigation, we propose an image scene graph to establish feature associations at both the image and object levels, effectively encoding the surrounding scene information. Crossscene performance validation was conducted on the Gibson and HM3D datasets, and the proposed method achieved stateof-the-art results among mainstream methods, with a speed of up to 53.5 frames per second on an RTX3080. This contributes to the realization of end-to-end image-goal navigation in realworld scenarios. The implementation and model of our method have been released at: https://github.com/nubot-nudt/RFSG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10986v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhicheng Feng, Xieyuanli Chen, Chenghao Shi, Lun Luo, Zhichao Chen, Yun-Hui Liu, Huimin Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Design of Continuum Robots with Reachability Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While multi-joint continuum robots are highly dexterous and flexible, designing an optimal robot can be challenging due to its kinematics involving curvatures. Hence, the current work presents a computational method developed to find optimal designs of continuum robots given reachability constraints. First, we leverage both forward and inverse kinematic computations to perform reachability analysis in an efficient yet accurate manner. While implementing inverse kinematics, we also integrate torque minimization at joints such that robot configurations with the minimum actuator torque required to reach a given workspace could be found. Lastly, we apply an estimation of distribution algorithm (EDA) to find optimal robot dimensions while considering reachability, where the objective function could be the total length of the robot or the actuator torque required to operate the robot. Through three application problems, we show that the EDA is superior to a genetic algorithm (GA) in finding better solutions within a given number of iterations, as the objective values of the best solutions found by the EDA are 4-15\% lower than those found by the GA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2021.3066978</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hyunmin Cheong, Mehran Ebrahimi, Timothy Duggan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Abstraction to Reality: DARPA's Vision for Robust Sim-to-Real Autonomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The DARPA Transfer from Imprecise and Abstract Models to Autonomous Technologies (TIAMAT) program aims to address rapid and robust transfer of autonomy technologies across dynamic and complex environments, goals, and platforms. Existing methods for simulation-to-reality (sim-to-real) transfer often rely on high-fidelity simulations and struggle with broad adaptation, particularly in time-sensitive scenarios. Although many approaches have shown incredible performance at specific tasks, most techniques fall short when posed with unforeseen, complex, and dynamic real-world scenarios due to the inherent limitations of simulation. In contrast to current research that aims to bridge the gap between simulation environments and the real world through increasingly sophisticated simulations and a combination of methods typically assuming a small sim-to-real gap -- such as domain randomization, domain adaptation, imitation learning, meta-learning, policy distillation, and dynamic optimization -- TIAMAT takes a different approach by instead emphasizing transfer and adaptation of the autonomy stack directly to real-world environments by utilizing a breadth of low(er)-fidelity simulations to create broadly effective sim-to-real transfers. By abstractly learning from multiple simulation environments in reference to their shared semantics, TIAMAT's approaches aim to achieve abstract-to-real transfer for effective and rapid real-world adaptation. Furthermore, this program endeavors to improve the overall autonomy pipeline by addressing the inherent challenges in translating simulated behaviors into effective real-world performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11007v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erfaun Noorani, Zachary Serlin, Ben Price, Alvaro Velasquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robotic Sim-to-Real Transfer for Long-Horizon Pick-and-Place Tasks in the Robotic Sim2Real Competition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a fully autonomous robotic system that performs sim-to-real transfer in complex long-horizon tasks involving navigation, recognition, grasping, and stacking in an environment with multiple obstacles.
  The key feature of the system is the ability to overcome typical sensing and actuation discrepancies during sim-to-real transfer and to achieve consistent performance without any algorithmic modifications. To accomplish this, a lightweight noise-resistant visual perception system and a nonlinearity-robust servo system are adopted.
  We conduct a series of tests in both simulated and real-world environments. The visual perception system achieves the speed of 11 ms per frame due to its lightweight nature, and the servo system achieves sub-centimeter accuracy with the proposed controller. Both exhibit high consistency during sim-to-real transfer. Benefiting from these, our robotic system took first place in the mineral searching task of the Robotic Sim2Real Challenge hosted at ICRA 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11012v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Yang, Hongyu Cao, Lixuan Zhao, Chenrui Zhang, Yaran Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Robust Localization for Humanoid Soccer Robot via Iterative Landmark Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate robot localization is essential for effective operation. Monte Carlo Localization (MCL) is commonly used with known maps but is computationally expensive due to landmark matching for each particle. Humanoid robots face additional challenges, including sensor noise from locomotion vibrations and a limited field of view (FOV) due to camera placement. This paper proposes a fast and robust localization method via iterative landmark matching (ILM) for humanoid robots. The iterative matching process improves the accuracy of the landmark association so that it does not need MCL to match landmarks to particles. Pose estimation with the outlier removal process enhances its robustness to measurement noise and faulty detections. Furthermore, an additional filter can be utilized to fuse inertial data from the inertial measurement unit (IMU) and pose data from localization. We compared ILM with Iterative Closest Point (ICP), which shows that ILM method is more robust towards the error in the initial guess and easier to get a correct matching. We also compared ILM with the Augmented Monte Carlo Localization (aMCL), which shows that ILM method is much faster than aMCL and even more accurate. The proposed method's effectiveness is thoroughly evaluated through experiments and validated on the humanoid robot ARTEMIS during RoboCup 2024 adult-sized soccer competition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11020v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruochen Hou, Mingzhang Zhu, Hyunwoo Nam, Gabriel I. Fernandez, Dennis W. Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Adaptivity of Two-Fingered Object Reorientation Using Tactile-based Online Optimization of Deconstructed Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Object reorientation is a critical task for robotic grippers, especially when manipulating objects within constrained environments. The task poses significant challenges for motion planning due to the high-dimensional output actions with the complex input information, including unknown object properties and nonlinear contact forces. Traditional approaches simplify the problem by reducing degrees of freedom, limiting contact forms, or acquiring environment/object information in advance, which significantly compromises adaptability. To address these challenges, we deconstruct the complex output actions into three fundamental types based on tactile sensing: task-oriented actions, constraint-oriented actions, and coordinating actions. These actions are then optimized online using gradient optimization to enhance adaptability. Key contributions include simplifying contact state perception, decomposing complex gripper actions, and enabling online action optimization for handling unknown objects or environmental constraints. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed method is effective across a range of everyday objects, regardless of environmental contact. Additionally, the method exhibits robust performance even in the presence of unknown contacts and nonlinear external disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11041v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyin Huang, Tiemin Li, Yao Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Multi-robot Source Seeking in Unknown Environments with Unknown Number of Sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel distributed source seeking framework, DIAS, designed for multi-robot systems in scenarios where the number of sources is unknown and potentially exceeds the number of robots. Traditional robotic source seeking methods typically focused on directing each robot to a specific strong source and may fall short in comprehensively identifying all potential sources. DIAS addresses this gap by introducing a hybrid controller that identifies the presence of sources and then alternates between exploration for data gathering and exploitation for guiding robots to identified sources. It further enhances search efficiency by dividing the environment into Voronoi cells and approximating source density functions based on Gaussian process regression. Additionally, DIAS can be integrated with existing source seeking algorithms. We compare DIAS with existing algorithms, including DoSS and GMES in simulated gas leakage scenarios where the number of sources outnumbers or is equal to the number of robots. The numerical results show that DIAS outperforms the baseline methods in both the efficiency of source identification by the robots and the accuracy of the estimated environmental density function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11048v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingpeng Chen, Siva Kailas, Srujan Deolasee, Wenhao Luo, Katia Sycara, Woojun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fish Mouth Inspired Origami Gripper for Robust Multi-Type Underwater Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robotic grasping and manipulation in underwater environments present unique challenges for robotic hands traditionally used on land. These challenges stem from dynamic water conditions, a wide range of object properties from soft to stiff, irregular object shapes, and varying surface frictions. One common approach involves developing finger-based hands with embedded compliance using underactuation and soft actuators. This study introduces an effective alternative solution that does not rely on finger-based hand designs. We present a fish mouth inspired origami gripper that utilizes a single degree of freedom to perform a variety of robust grasping tasks underwater. The innovative structure transforms a simple uniaxial pulling motion into a grasping action based on the Yoshimura crease pattern folding. The origami gripper offers distinct advantages, including scalable and optimizable design, grasping compliance, and robustness, with four grasping types: pinch, power grasp, simultaneous grasping of multiple objects, and scooping from the seabed. In this work, we detail the design, modeling, fabrication, and validation of a specialized underwater gripper capable of handling various marine creatures, including jellyfish, crabs, and abalone. By leveraging an origami and bio-inspired approach, the presented gripper demonstrates promising potential for robotic grasping and manipulation in underwater environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11049v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honghao Guo, Junda Huang, Ian Zhang, Boyuan Liang, Xin Ma, Yunhui Liu, Jianshu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Regrasping Efficiency Using Prior Grasping Perceptions with Soft Fingertips</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grasping the same object in different postures is often necessary, especially when handling tools or stacked items. Due to unknown object properties and changes in grasping posture, the required grasping force is uncertain and variable. Traditional methods rely on real-time feedback to control the grasping force cautiously, aiming to prevent slipping or damage. However, they overlook reusable information from the initial grasp, treating subsequent regrasping attempts as if they were the first, which significantly reduces efficiency. To improve this, we propose a method that utilizes perception from prior grasping attempts to predict the required grasping force, even with changes in position. We also introduce a calculation method that accounts for fingertip softness and object asymmetry. Theoretical analyses demonstrate the feasibility of predicting grasping forces across various postures after a single grasp. Experimental verifications attest to the accuracy and adaptability of our prediction method. Furthermore, results show that incorporating the predicted grasping force into feedback-based approaches significantly enhances grasping efficiency across a range of everyday objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11057v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyin Huang, Ruomin Sui, Lunwei Zhang, Yenhang Zhou, Tiemin Li, Yao Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Directional Locomotion for Quadrupedal Low-Cost Robotic Systems via Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we present Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) training of directional locomotion for low-cost quadrupedal robots in the real world. In particular, we exploit randomization of heading that the robot must follow to foster exploration of action-state transitions most useful for learning both forward locomotion as well as course adjustments. Changing the heading in episode resets to current yaw plus a random value drawn from a normal distribution yields policies able to follow complex trajectories involving frequent turns in both directions as well as long straight-line stretches. By repeatedly changing the heading, this method keeps the robot moving within the training platform and thus reduces human involvement and need for manual resets during the training. Real world experiments on a custom-built, low-cost quadruped demonstrate the efficacy of our method with the robot successfully navigating all validation tests. When trained with other approaches, the robot only succeeds in forward locomotion test and fails when turning is required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11059v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter B\"ohm, Archie C. Chapman, Pauline Pounds</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High-Speed Time-Optimal Trajectory Generation Strategy via a Two-layer Planning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motion planning and trajectory generation are crucial technologies in various domains including the control of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAV), manipulators, and rockets. However, optimization-based real-time motion planning becomes increasingly challenging due to the problem's probable non-convexity and the inherent limitations of Non-Linear Programming algorithms. Highly nonlinear dynamics, obstacle avoidance constraints, and non-convex inputs can exacerbate these difficulties. To address these hurdles, this paper proposes a two-layer optimization algorithm for 2D vehicles by dynamically reformulating small time horizon convex programming subproblems, aiming to provide real-time guarantees for trajectory optimization. Our approach involves breaking down the original problem into small horizon-based planning cycles with fixed final times, referred to as planning cycles. Each planning cycle is then solved within a series of restricted convex sets identified by our customized search algorithms incrementally. The key benefits of our proposed algorithm include fast computation speeds and lower task time. We demonstrate these advantages through mathematical proofs under some moderate preconditions and experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11072v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haotian Tan, Yuan-Hua Ni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoMa-Kitchen: A 100K+ Benchmark for Affordance-Grounded Last-Mile Navigation in Mobile Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In mobile manipulation, navigation and manipulation are often treated as separate problems, resulting in a significant gap between merely approaching an object and engaging with it effectively. Many navigation approaches primarily define success by proximity to the target, often overlooking the necessity for optimal positioning that facilitates subsequent manipulation. To address this, we introduce MoMa-Kitchen, a benchmark dataset comprising over 100k samples that provide training data for models to learn optimal final navigation positions for seamless transition to manipulation. Our dataset includes affordance-grounded floor labels collected from diverse kitchen environments, in which robotic mobile manipulators of different models attempt to grasp target objects amidst clutter. Using a fully automated pipeline, we simulate diverse real-world scenarios and generate affordance labels for optimal manipulation positions. Visual data are collected from RGB-D inputs captured by a first-person view camera mounted on the robotic arm, ensuring consistency in viewpoint during data collection. We also develop a lightweight baseline model, NavAff, for navigation affordance grounding that demonstrates promising performance on the MoMa-Kitchen benchmark. Our approach enables models to learn affordance-based final positioning that accommodates different arm types and platform heights, thereby paving the way for more robust and generalizable integration of navigation and manipulation in embodied AI. Project page: \href{https://momakitchen.github.io/}{https://momakitchen.github.io/}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pingrui Zhang, Xianqiang Gao, Yuhan Wu, Kehui Liu, Dong Wang, Zhigang Wang, Bin Zhao, Yan Ding, Xuelong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GP-enhanced Autonomous Drifting Framework using ADMM-based iLQR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous drifting is a complex challenge due to the highly nonlinear dynamics and the need for precise real-time control, especially in uncertain environments. To address these limitations, this paper presents a hierarchical control framework for autonomous vehicles drifting along general paths, primarily focusing on addressing model inaccuracies and mitigating computational challenges in real-time control. The framework integrates Gaussian Process (GP) regression with an Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM)-based iterative Linear Quadratic Regulator (iLQR). GP regression effectively compensates for model residuals, improving accuracy in dynamic conditions. ADMM-based iLQR not only combines the rapid trajectory optimization of iLQR but also utilizes ADMM's strength in decomposing the problem into simpler sub-problems. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed framework, with significant improvements in both drift trajectory tracking and computational efficiency. Our approach resulted in a 38$\%$ reduction in RMSE lateral error and achieved an average computation time that is 75$\%$ lower than that of the Interior Point OPTimizer (IPOPT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11083v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangyang Xie, Cheng Hu, Nicolas Baumann, Edoardo Ghignone, Michele Magno, Lei Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EmbodiedVSR: Dynamic Scene Graph-Guided Chain-of-Thought Reasoning for Visual Spatial Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have made groundbreaking progress in embodied intelligence, they still face significant challenges in spatial reasoning for complex long-horizon tasks. To address this gap, we propose EmbodiedVSR (Embodied Visual Spatial Reasoning), a novel framework that integrates dynamic scene graph-guided Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning to enhance spatial understanding for embodied agents. By explicitly constructing structured knowledge representations through dynamic scene graphs, our method enables zero-shot spatial reasoning without task-specific fine-tuning. This approach not only disentangles intricate spatial relationships but also aligns reasoning steps with actionable environmental dynamics. To rigorously evaluate performance, we introduce the eSpatial-Benchmark, a comprehensive dataset including real-world embodied scenarios with fine-grained spatial annotations and adaptive task difficulty levels. Experiments demonstrate that our framework significantly outperforms existing MLLM-based methods in accuracy and reasoning coherence, particularly in long-horizon tasks requiring iterative environment interaction. The results reveal the untapped potential of MLLMs for embodied intelligence when equipped with structured, explainable reasoning mechanisms, paving the way for more reliable deployment in real-world spatial applications. The codes and datasets will be released soon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11089v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhang, Qiang Zhang, Xiaozhu Ju, Zhaoyang Liu, Jilei Mao, Jingkai Sun, Jintao Wu, Shixiong Gao, Shihan Cai, Zhiyuan Qin, Linkai Liang, Jiaxu Wang, Yiqun Duan, Jiahang Cao, Renjing Xu, Jian Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow-Aware Navigation of Magnetic Micro-Robots in Complex Fluids via PINN-Based Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While magnetic micro-robots have demonstrated significant potential across various applications, including drug delivery and microsurgery, the open issue of precise navigation and control in complex fluid environments is crucial for in vivo implementation. This paper introduces a novel flow-aware navigation and control strategy for magnetic micro-robots that explicitly accounts for the impact of fluid flow on their movement. First, the proposed method employs a Physics-Informed U-Net (PI-UNet) to refine the numerically predicted fluid velocity using local observations. Then, the predicted velocity is incorporated in a flow-aware A* path planning algorithm, ensuring efficient navigation while mitigating flow-induced disturbances. Finally, a control scheme is developed to compensate for the predicted fluid velocity, thereby optimizing the micro-robot's performance. A series of simulation studies and real-world experiments are conducted to validate the efficacy of the proposed approach. This method enhances both planning accuracy and control precision, expanding the potential applications of magnetic micro-robots in fluid-affected environments typical of many medical scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11124v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongyi Jia, Shu Miao, Jiayu Wu, Ming Yang, Chengzhi Hu, Xiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Semantic Graphs for Efficient and Robust LiDAR SLAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and robust simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM) is crucial for autonomous mobile systems, typically achieved by leveraging the geometric features of the environment. Incorporating semantics provides a richer scene representation that not only enhances localization accuracy in SLAM but also enables advanced cognitive functionalities for downstream navigation and planning tasks. Existing point-wise semantic LiDAR SLAM methods often suffer from poor efficiency and generalization, making them less robust in diverse real-world scenarios. In this paper, we propose a semantic graph-enhanced SLAM framework, named SG-SLAM, which effectively leverages the geometric, semantic, and topological characteristics inherent in environmental structures. The semantic graph serves as a fundamental component that facilitates critical functionalities of SLAM, including robust relocalization during odometry failures, accurate loop closing, and semantic graph map construction. Our method employs a dual-threaded architecture, with one thread dedicated to online odometry and relocalization, while the other handles loop closure, pose graph optimization, and map update. This design enables our method to operate in real time and generate globally consistent semantic graph maps and point cloud maps. We extensively evaluate our method across the KITTI, MulRAN, and Apollo datasets, and the results demonstrate its superiority compared to state-of-the-art methods. Our method has been released at https://github.com/nubot-nudt/SG-SLAM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11145v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neng Wang, Huimin Lu, Zhiqiang Zheng, Hesheng Wang, Yun-Hui Liu, Xieyuanli Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Benchmarking Study of Vision-based Robotic Grasping Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a benchmarking study of vision-based robotic grasping algorithms with distinct approaches, and provide a comparative analysis. In particular, we compare two machine-learning-based and two analytical algorithms using an existing benchmarking protocol from the literature and determine the algorithm's strengths and weaknesses under different experimental conditions. These conditions include variations in lighting, background textures, cameras with different noise levels, and grippers. We also run analogous experiments in simulations and with real robots and present the discrepancies. Some experiments are also run in two different laboratories using same protocols to further analyze the repeatability of our results. We believe that this study, comprising 5040 experiments, provides important insights into the role and challenges of systematic experimentation in robotic manipulation, and guides the development of new algorithms by considering the factors that could impact the performance. The experiment recordings and our benchmarking software are publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11163v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bharath K Rameshbabu, Sumukh S Balakrishna, Brian Flynn, Vinarak Kapoor, Adam Norton, Holly Yanco, Berk Calli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hand Over or Place On The Table? A Study On Robotic Object Delivery When The Recipient Is Occupied</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the subjective experiences of users in two robotic object delivery methods: direct handover and table placement, when users are occupied with another task. A user study involving 15 participants engaged in a typing game revealed that table placement significantly enhances user experience compared to direct handovers, particularly in terms of satisfaction, perceived safety and intuitiveness. Additionally, handovers negatively impacted typing performance, while all participants expressed a clear preference for table placement as the delivery method. These findings highlight the advantages of table placement in scenarios requiring minimal user disruption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11177v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thieu Long Phan, Akansel Cosgun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAIPAT -Dataset on Human Gaze and Actions for Intent Prediction in Assembly Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The primary objective of the dataset is to provide a better understanding of the coupling between human actions and gaze in a shared working environment with a cobot, with the aim of signifcantly enhancing the effciency and safety of humancobot interactions. More broadly, by linking gaze patterns with physical actions, the dataset offers valuable insights into cognitive processes and attention dynamics in the context of assembly tasks. The proposed dataset contains gaze and action data from approximately 80 participants, recorded during simulated industrial assembly tasks. The tasks were simulated using controlled scenarios in which participants manipulated educational building blocks. Gaze data was collected using two different eye-tracking setups -head-mounted and remote-while participants worked in two positions: sitting and standing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction, Mar 2025, Melbourne (AUS), Australia</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maxence Grand (Marvin), Damien Pellier (Marvin), Francis Jambon (MeTAH, M-PSI, LIG)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodic exploration of dynamic distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research addresses the challenge of performing search missions in dynamic environments, particularly for drifting targets whose movement is dictated by a flow field. This is accomplished through a dynamical system that integrates two partial differential equations: one governing the dynamics and uncertainty of the probability distribution, and the other regulating the potential field for ergodic multi-agent search. The target probability field evolves in response to the target dynamics imposed by the environment and accomplished sensing efforts, while being explored by multiple robot agents guided by the potential field gradient. The proposed methodology was tested on two simulated search scenarios, one of which features a synthetically generated domain and showcases better performance when compared to the baseline method with static target probability over a range of agent to flow field velocity ratios. The second search scenario represents a realistic sea search and rescue mission where the search start is delayed, the search is performed in multiple robot flight missions, and the procedure for target drift uncertainty compensation is demonstrated. Furthermore, the proposed method provides an accurate survey completion metric, based on the known detection/sensing parameters, that correlates with the actual number of targets found independently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11235v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luka Lan\v{c}a, Karlo Jakac, Sylvain Calinon, Stefan Ivi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prof. Robot: Differentiable Robot Rendering Without Static and Self-Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differentiable rendering has gained significant attention in the field of robotics, with differentiable robot rendering emerging as an effective paradigm for learning robotic actions from image-space supervision. However, the lack of physical world perception in this approach may lead to potential collisions during action optimization. In this work, we introduce a novel improvement on previous efforts by incorporating physical awareness of collisions through the learning of a neural robotic collision classifier. This enables the optimization of actions that avoid collisions with static, non-interactable environments as well as the robot itself. To facilitate effective gradient optimization with the classifier, we identify the underlying issue and propose leveraging Eikonal regularization to ensure consistent gradients for optimization. Our solution can be seamlessly integrated into existing differentiable robot rendering frameworks, utilizing gradients for optimization and providing a foundation for future applications of differentiable rendering in robotics with improved reliability of interactions with the physical world. Both qualitative and quantitative experiments demonstrate the necessity and effectiveness of our method compared to previous solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11269v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quanyuan Ruan, Jiabao Lei, Wenhao Yuan, Yanglin Zhang, Dekun Lu, Guiliang Liu, Kui Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Hand Palm Motion Gesture Recognition by Eliminating Reference Frame Bias via Frame-Invariant Similarity Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability of robots to recognize human gestures facilitates a natural and accessible human-robot collaboration. However, most work in gesture recognition remains rooted in reference frame-dependent representations. This poses a challenge when reference frames vary due to different work cell layouts, imprecise frame calibrations, or other environmental changes. This paper investigated the use of invariant trajectory descriptors for robust hand palm motion gesture recognition under reference frame changes. First, a novel dataset of recorded Hand Palm Motion (HPM) gestures is introduced. The motion gestures in this dataset were specifically designed to be distinguishable without dependence on specific reference frames or directional cues. Afterwards, multiple invariant trajectory descriptor approaches were benchmarked to assess how their performances generalize to this novel HPM dataset. After this offline benchmarking, the best scoring approach is validated for online recognition by developing a real-time Proof of Concept (PoC). In this PoC, hand palm motion gestures were used to control the real-time movement of a manipulator arm. The PoC demonstrated a high recognition reliability in real-time operation, achieving an $F_1$-score of 92.3%. This work demonstrates the effectiveness of the invariant descriptor approach as a standalone solution. Moreover, we believe that the invariant descriptor approach can also be utilized within other state-of-the-art pattern recognition and learning systems to improve their robustness against reference frame variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11352v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arno Verduyn, Maxim Vochten, Joris De Schutter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BEVDiffLoc: End-to-End LiDAR Global Localization in BEV View based on Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Localization is one of the core parts of modern robotics. Classic localization methods typically follow the retrieve-then-register paradigm, achieving remarkable success. Recently, the emergence of end-to-end localization approaches has offered distinct advantages, including a streamlined system architecture and the elimination of the need to store extensive map data. Although these methods have demonstrated promising results, current end-to-end localization approaches still face limitations in robustness and accuracy. Bird's-Eye-View (BEV) image is one of the most widely adopted data representations in autonomous driving. It significantly reduces data complexity while preserving spatial structure and scale consistency, making it an ideal representation for localization tasks. However, research on BEV-based end-to-end localization remains notably insufficient. To fill this gap, we propose BEVDiffLoc, a novel framework that formulates LiDAR localization as a conditional generation of poses. Leveraging the properties of BEV, we first introduce a specific data augmentation method to significantly enhance the diversity of input data. Then, the Maximum Feature Aggregation Module and Vision Transformer are employed to learn robust features while maintaining robustness against significant rotational view variations. Finally, we incorporate a diffusion model that iteratively refines the learned features to recover the absolute pose. Extensive experiments on the Oxford Radar RobotCar and NCLT datasets demonstrate that BEVDiffLoc outperforms the baseline methods. Our code is available at https://github.com/nubot-nudt/BEVDiffLoc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11372v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyue Wang, Chenghao Shi, Neng Wang, Qinghua Yu, Xieyuanli Chen, Huimin Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AQUA-SLAM: Tightly-Coupled Underwater Acoustic-Visual-Inertial SLAM with Sensor Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Underwater environments pose significant challenges for visual Simultaneous Localization and Mapping (SLAM) systems due to limited visibility, inadequate illumination, and sporadic loss of structural features in images. Addressing these challenges, this paper introduces a novel, tightly-coupled Acoustic-Visual-Inertial SLAM approach, termed AQUA-SLAM, to fuse a Doppler Velocity Log (DVL), a stereo camera, and an Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) within a graph optimization framework. Moreover, we propose an efficient sensor calibration technique, encompassing multi-sensor extrinsic calibration (among the DVL, camera and IMU) and DVL transducer misalignment calibration, with a fast linear approximation procedure for real-time online execution. The proposed methods are extensively evaluated in a tank environment with ground truth, and validated for offshore applications in the North Sea. The results demonstrate that our method surpasses current state-of-the-art underwater and visual-inertial SLAM systems in terms of localization accuracy and robustness. The proposed system will be made open-source for the community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11420v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shida Xu, Kaicheng Zhang, Sen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Torque Control of Exoskeletons under Spasticity Conditions via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spasticity is a common movement disorder symptom in individuals with cerebral palsy, hereditary spastic paraplegia, spinal cord injury and stroke, being one of the most disabling features in the progression of these diseases. Despite the potential benefit of using wearable robots to treat spasticity, their use is not currently recommended to subjects with a level of spasticity above ${1^+}$ on the Modified Ashworth Scale. The varying dynamics of this velocity-dependent tonic stretch reflex make it difficult to deploy safe personalized controllers. Here, we describe a novel adaptive torque controller via deep reinforcement learning (RL) for a knee exoskeleton under joint spasticity conditions, which accounts for task performance and interaction forces reduction. To train the RL agent, we developed a digital twin, including a musculoskeletal-exoskeleton system with joint misalignment and a differentiable spastic reflexes model for the muscles activation. Results for a simulated knee extension movement showed that the agent learns to control the exoskeleton for individuals with different levels of spasticity. The proposed controller was able to reduce maximum torques applied to the human joint under spastic conditions by an average of 10.6\% and decreases the root mean square until the settling time by 8.9\% compared to a conventional compliant controller.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11433v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Chavarr\'ias, David Rodriguez-Cianca, Pablo Lanillos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MRS-CWC: A Weakly Constrained Multi-Robot System with Controllable Constraint Stiffness for Mobility and Navigation in Unknown 3D Rough Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11461v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Navigating unknown three-dimensional (3D) rugged environments is challenging for multi-robot systems. Traditional discrete systems struggle with rough terrain due to limited individual mobility, while modular systems--where rigid, controllable constraints link robot units--improve traversal but suffer from high control complexity and reduced flexibility. To address these limitations, we propose the Multi-Robot System with Controllable Weak Constraints (MRS-CWC), where robot units are connected by constraints with dynamically adjustable stiffness. This adaptive mechanism softens or stiffens in real-time during environmental interactions, ensuring a balance between flexibility and mobility. We formulate the system's dynamics and control model and evaluate MRS-CWC against six baseline methods and an ablation variant in a benchmark dataset with 100 different simulation terrains. Results show that MRS-CWC achieves the highest navigation completion rate and ranks second in success rate, efficiency, and energy cost in the highly rugged terrain group, outperforming all baseline methods without relying on environmental modeling, path planning, or complex control. Even where MRS-CWC ranks second, its performance is only slightly behind a more complex ablation variant with environmental modeling and path planning. Finally, we develop a physical prototype and validate its feasibility in a constructed rugged environment. For videos, simulation benchmarks, and code, please visit https://wyd0817.github.io/project-mrs-cwc/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11461v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runze Xiao, Yongdong Wang, Yusuke Tsunoda, Koichi Osuka, Hajime Asama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Obstacle Avoidance with Bounded Rationality Adversarial Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) has proven largely effective in obtaining stable locomotion gaits for legged robots. However, designing control algorithms which can robustly navigate unseen environments with obstacles remains an ongoing problem within quadruped locomotion. To tackle this, it is convenient to solve navigation tasks by means of a hierarchical approach with a low-level locomotion policy and a high-level navigation policy. Crucially, the high-level policy needs to be robust to dynamic obstacles along the path of the agent. In this work, we propose a novel way to endow navigation policies with robustness by a training process that models obstacles as adversarial agents, following the adversarial RL paradigm. Importantly, to improve the reliability of the training process, we bound the rationality of the adversarial agent resorting to quantal response equilibria, and place a curriculum over its rationality. We called this method Hierarchical policies via Quantal response Adversarial Reinforcement Learning (Hi-QARL). We demonstrate the robustness of our method by benchmarking it in unseen randomized mazes with multiple obstacles. To prove its applicability in real scenarios, our method is applied on a Unitree GO1 robot in simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11467v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose-Luis Holgado-Alvarez, Aryaman Reddi, Carlo D'Eramo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exo-muscle: A semi-rigid assistive device for the knee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11474v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce the principle, design and mechatronics of Exo-Muscle, a novel assistive device for the knee joint. Different from the existing systems based on rigid exoskeleton structures or soft-tendon driven approaches, the proposed device leverages a new semi-rigid principle that explores the benefits of both rigid and soft systems. The use of a novel semi-rigid chain mechanism around the knee joint eliminates the presence of misalignment between the device and the knee joint center of rotation, while at the same time, it forms a well-defined route for the tendon. This results in more deterministic load compensation functionality compared to the fully soft systems. The proposed device can provide up to 38Nm assistive torque to the knee joint. In the experiment section, the device was successfully validated through a series of experiments demonstrating the capacity of the device to provide the target assistive functionality in the knee joint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11474v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2021.3100609</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yifang Zhang (Humanoids and Human Centered Mechatronics), Arash Ajoudani (Human-Robot Interfaces and Physical Interaction), Nikos G Tsagarakis (Humanoids and Human Centered Mechatronics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-agent coordination for on-demand data gathering with periodic information upload</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we develop a method for planning and coordinating a multi-agent team deployment to periodically gather information on demand. A static operation center (OC) periodically requests information from changing goal locations. The objective is to gather data in the goals and to deliver it to the OC, balancing the refreshing time and the total number of information packages. The system automatically splits the team in two roles: workers to gather data, or collectors to retransmit the data to the OC. The proposed three step method: 1) finds out the best area partition for the workers; 2) obtains the best balance between workers and collectors, and with whom the workers must to communicate, a collector or the OC; 3) computes the best tour for the workers to visit the goals and deliver them to the OC or to a collector in movement. The method is tested in simulations in different scenarios, providing the best area partition algorithm and the best balance between collectors and workers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11504v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-030-24209-1_13</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yaroslav Marchukov, Luis Montano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-robot coordination for connectivity recovery after unpredictable environment changes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper we develop a distributed method to reconnect a multi-robot team after connectivity failures, caused by unpredictable environment changes, i.e. appearance of new obstacles. After the changes, the team is divided into different groups of robots. The groups have a limited communication range and only a partial information in their field of view about the current scenario. Their objective is to form a chain from a static base station to a goal location. In the proposed distributed replanning approach, the robots predict new plans for the other groups from the new observed information by each robot in the changed scenario, to restore the connectivity with a base station and reach the initial joint objective. If a solution exists, the method achieves the reconnection of all the groups in a unique chain. The proposed method is compared with other two cases: 1) when all the agents have full information of the environment, and 2) when some robots must move to reach other waiting robots for reconnection. Numerical simulations are provided to evaluate the proposed approach in the presence of unpredictable scenario changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11520v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaroslav Marchukov, Luis Montano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vectorable Thrust Control for Multimodal Locomotion of Quadruped Robot SPIDAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, I present vectorable thrust control for different locomotion modes by a novel quadruped robot, SPIDAR, equipped with vectoring rotor in each link. First, the robot's unique mechanical design, the dynamics model, and the basic control framework for terrestrial/aerial locomotion are briefly introduced. Second, a vectorable thrust control method derived from the basic control framework for aerial locomotion is presented. A key feature of this extended flight control is its ability to avoid interrotor aerodynamics interference under specific joint configuration. Third, another extended thrust control method and a fundamental gait strategy is proposed for special terrestrial locomotion called crawling that requires all legs to be lifted at the same time. Finally, the experimental results of the flight with a complex joint motion and the repeatable crawling motion are explained, which demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed thrust control methods for different locomotion modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11551v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moju Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reparametrization of 3D CSC Dubins Paths Enabling 2D Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the Dubins path planning problem for vehicles in 3D space. In particular, we consider the problem of computing CSC paths -- paths that consist of a circular arc (C) followed by a straight segment (S) followed by a circular arc (C). These paths are useful for vehicles such as fixed-wing aircraft and underwater submersibles that are subject to lower bounds on turn radius. We present a new parameterization that reduces the 3D CSC planning problem to a search over 2 variables, thus lowering search complexity, while also providing gradients that assist that search. We use these equations with a numerical solver to explore numbers and types of solutions computed for a variety of planar and 3D scenarios. Our method successfully computes CSC paths for the large majority of test cases, indicating that it could be useful for future generation of robust, efficient curvature-constrained trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11560v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling Xu, Yuliy Baryshnikov, Cynthia Sung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adversarial Data Collection: Human-Collaborative Perturbations for Efficient and Robust Robotic Imitation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of data efficiency, where quality outweighs quantity, has emerged as a cornerstone in robotic manipulation, especially given the high costs associated with real-world data collection. We propose that maximizing the informational density of individual demonstrations can dramatically reduce reliance on large-scale datasets while improving task performance. To this end, we introduce Adversarial Data Collection, a Human-in-the-Loop (HiL) framework that redefines robotic data acquisition through real-time, bidirectional human-environment interactions. Unlike conventional pipelines that passively record static demonstrations, ADC adopts a collaborative perturbation paradigm: during a single episode, an adversarial operator dynamically alters object states, environmental conditions, and linguistic commands, while the tele-operator adaptively adjusts actions to overcome these evolving challenges. This process compresses diverse failure-recovery behaviors, compositional task variations, and environmental perturbations into minimal demonstrations. Our experiments demonstrate that ADC-trained models achieve superior compositional generalization to unseen task instructions, enhanced robustness to perceptual perturbations, and emergent error recovery capabilities. Strikingly, models trained with merely 20% of the demonstration volume collected through ADC significantly outperform traditional approaches using full datasets. These advances bridge the gap between data-centric learning paradigms and practical robotic deployment, demonstrating that strategic data acquisition, not merely post-hoc processing, is critical for scalable, real-world robot learning. Additionally, we are curating a large-scale ADC-Robotics dataset comprising real-world manipulation tasks with adversarial perturbations. This benchmark will be open-sourced to facilitate advancements in robotic imitation learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11646v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Huang, Yue Liao, Siyuan Feng, Shu Jiang, Si Liu, Hongsheng Li, Maoqing Yao, Guanghui Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Centaur: Robust End-to-End Autonomous Driving with Test-Time Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How can we rely on an end-to-end autonomous vehicle's complex decision-making system during deployment? One common solution is to have a ``fallback layer'' that checks the planned trajectory for rule violations and replaces it with a pre-defined safe action if necessary. Another approach involves adjusting the planner's decisions to minimize a pre-defined ``cost function'' using additional system predictions such as road layouts and detected obstacles. However, these pre-programmed rules or cost functions cannot learn and improve with new training data, often resulting in overly conservative behaviors. In this work, we propose Centaur (Cluster Entropy for Test-time trAining using Uncertainty) which updates a planner's behavior via test-time training, without relying on hand-engineered rules or cost functions. Instead, we measure and minimize the uncertainty in the planner's decisions. For this, we develop a novel uncertainty measure, called Cluster Entropy, which is simple, interpretable, and compatible with state-of-the-art planning algorithms. Using data collected at prior test-time time-steps, we perform an update to the model's parameters using a gradient that minimizes the Cluster Entropy. With only this sole gradient update prior to inference, Centaur exhibits significant improvements, ranking first on the navtest leaderboard with notable gains in safety-critical metrics such as time to collision. To provide detailed insights on a per-scenario basis, we also introduce navsafe, a challenging new benchmark, which highlights previously undiscovered failure modes of driving models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11650v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chonghao Sima, Kashyap Chitta, Zhiding Yu, Shiyi Lan, Ping Luo, Andreas Geiger, Hongyang Li, Jose M. Alvarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Control Barriers from Offline Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning-based methods for constructing control barrier functions (CBFs) are gaining popularity for ensuring safe robot control. A major limitation of existing methods is their reliance on extensive sampling over the state space or online system interaction in simulation. In this work we propose a novel framework for learning neural CBFs through a fixed, sparsely-labeled dataset collected prior to training. Our approach introduces new annotation techniques based on out-of-distribution analysis, enabling efficient knowledge propagation from the limited labeled data to the unlabeled data. We also eliminate the dependency on a high-performance expert controller, and allow multiple sub-optimal policies or even manual control during data collection. We evaluate the proposed method on real-world platforms. With limited amount of offline data, it achieves state-of-the-art performance for dynamic obstacle avoidance, demonstrating statistically safer and less conservative maneuvers compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10641v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongzhan Yu, Seth Farrell, Ryo Yoshimitsu, Zhizhen Qin, Henrik I. Christensen, Sicun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the best way for UAV visual localization under Low-altitude Multi-view Observation Condition: a Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Absolute Visual Localization (AVL) enables Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV) to determine its position in GNSS-denied environments by establishing geometric relationships between UAV images and geo-tagged reference maps. While many previous works have achieved AVL with image retrieval and matching techniques, research in low-altitude multi-view scenarios still remains limited. Low-altitude Multi-view condition presents greater challenges due to extreme viewpoint changes. To explore the best UAV AVL approach in such condition, we proposed this benchmark. Firstly, a large-scale Low-altitude Multi-view dataset called AnyVisLoc was constructed. This dataset includes 18,000 images captured at multiple scenes and altitudes, along with 2.5D reference maps containing aerial photogrammetry maps and historical satellite maps. Secondly, a unified framework was proposed to integrate the state-of-the-art AVL approaches and comprehensively test their performance. The best combined method was chosen as the baseline and the key factors that influencing localization accuracy are thoroughly analyzed based on it. This baseline achieved a 74.1% localization accuracy within 5m under Low-altitude, Multi-view conditions. In addition, a novel retrieval metric called PDM@K was introduced to better align with the characteristics of the UAV AVL task. Overall, this benchmark revealed the challenges of Low-altitude, Multi-view UAV AVL and provided valuable guidance for future research. The dataset and codes are available at https://github.com/UAV-AVL/Benchmark</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10692v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yibin Ye, Xichao Teng, Shuo Chen, Zhang Li, Leqi Liu, Qifeng Yu, Tao Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Individual Counting for Moving Drones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Video Individual Counting (VIC) has received increasing attentions recently due to its importance in intelligent video surveillance. Existing works are limited in two aspects, i.e., dataset and method. Previous crowd counting datasets are captured with fixed or rarely moving cameras with relatively sparse individuals, restricting evaluation for a highly varying view and time in crowded scenes. While VIC methods have been proposed based on localization-then-association or localization-then-classification, they may not perform well due to difficulty in accurate localization of crowded and small targets under challenging scenarios. To address these issues, we collect a MovingDroneCrowd Dataset and propose a density map based VIC method. Different from existing datasets, our dataset consists of videos captured by fast-moving drones in crowded scenes under diverse illuminations, shooting heights and angles. Other than localizing individuals, we propose a Depth-wise Cross-Frame Attention (DCFA) module, which directly estimate inflow and outflow density maps through learning shared density maps between consecutive frames. The inflow density maps across frames are summed up to obtain the number of unique pedestrians in a video. Experiments on our datasets and publicly available ones show the superiority of our method over the state of the arts for VIC in highly dynamic and complex crowded scenes. Our dataset and codes will be released publicly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10701v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaowu Fan, Jia Wan, Tao Han, Antoni B. Chan, Andy J. Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciFi-Benchmark: How Would AI-Powered Robots Behave in Science Fiction Literature?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10706v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given the recent rate of progress in artificial intelligence (AI) and robotics, a tantalizing question is emerging: would robots controlled by emerging AI systems be strongly aligned with human values? In this work, we propose a scalable way to probe this question by generating a benchmark spanning the key moments in 824 major pieces of science fiction literature (movies, tv, novels and scientific books) where an agent (AI or robot) made critical decisions (good or bad). We use a LLM's recollection of each key moment to generate questions in similar situations, the decisions made by the agent, and alternative decisions it could have made (good or bad). We then measure an approximation of how well models align with human values on a set of human-voted answers. We also generate rules that can be automatically improved via amendment process in order to generate the first Sci-Fi inspired constitutions for promoting ethical behavior in AIs and robots in the real world. Our first finding is that modern LLMs paired with constitutions turn out to be well-aligned with human values (95.8%), contrary to unsettling decisions typically made in SciFi (only 21.2% alignment). Secondly, we find that generated constitutions substantially increase alignment compared to the base model (79.4% to 95.8%), and show resilience to an adversarial prompt setting (23.3% to 92.3%). Additionally, we find that those constitutions are among the top performers on the ASIMOV Benchmark which is derived from real-world images and hospital injury reports. Sci-Fi-inspired constitutions are thus highly aligned and applicable in real-world situations. We release SciFi-Benchmark: a large-scale dataset to advance robot ethics and safety research. It comprises 9,056 questions and 53,384 answers, in addition to a smaller human-labeled evaluation set. Data is available at https://scifi-benchmark.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10706v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Sermanet, Anirudha Majumdar, Vikas Sindhwani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Extended Object Tracking based on Extruded B-Spline Side View Profiles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Object tracking is an essential task for autonomous systems. With the advancement of 3D sensors, these systems can better perceive their surroundings using effective 3D Extended Object Tracking (EOT) methods. Based on the observation that common road users are symmetrical on the right and left sides in the traveling direction, we focus on the side view profile of the object. In order to leverage of the development in 2D EOT and balance the number of parameters of a shape model in the tracking algorithms, we propose a method for 3D extended object tracking (EOT) by describing the side view profile of the object with B-spline curves and forming an extrusion to obtain a 3D extent. The use of B-spline curves exploits their flexible representation power by allowing the control points to move freely. The algorithm is developed into an Extended Kalman Filter (EKF). For a through evaluation of this method, we use simulated traffic scenario of different vehicle models and realworld open dataset containing both radar and lidar data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10730v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longfei Han, Klaus Kefferp\"utz, J\"urgen Beyerer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unifying 2D and 3D Vision-Language Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Progress in 3D vision-language learning has been hindered by the scarcity of large-scale 3D datasets. We introduce UniVLG, a unified architecture for 2D and 3D vision-language understanding that bridges the gap between existing 2D-centric models and the rich 3D sensory data available in embodied systems. Our approach initializes most model weights from pre-trained 2D models and trains on both 2D and 3D vision-language data. We propose a novel language-conditioned mask decoder shared across 2D and 3D modalities to ground objects effectively in both RGB and RGB-D images, outperforming box-based approaches. To further reduce the domain gap between 2D and 3D, we incorporate 2D-to-3D lifting strategies, enabling UniVLG to utilize 2D data to enhance 3D performance. With these innovations, our model achieves state-of-the-art performance across multiple 3D vision-language grounding tasks, demonstrating the potential of transferring advances from 2D vision-language learning to the data-constrained 3D domain. Furthermore, co-training on both 2D and 3D data enhances performance across modalities without sacrificing 2D capabilities. By removing the reliance on 3D mesh reconstruction and ground-truth object proposals, UniVLG sets a new standard for realistic, embodied-aligned evaluation. Code and additional visualizations are available at $\href{https://univlg.github.io}{univlg.github.io}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10745v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayush Jain, Alexander Swerdlow, Yuzhou Wang, Sergio Arnaud, Ada Martin, Alexander Sax, Franziska Meier, Katerina Fragkiadaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph-Grounded LLMs: Leveraging Graphical Function Calling to Minimize LLM Hallucinations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10941v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The adoption of Large Language Models (LLMs) is rapidly expanding across various tasks that involve inherent graphical structures. Graphs are integral to a wide range of applications, including motion planning for autonomous vehicles, social networks, scene understanding, and knowledge graphs. Many problems, even those not initially perceived as graph-based, can be effectively addressed through graph theory. However, when applied to these tasks, LLMs often encounter challenges, such as hallucinations and mathematical inaccuracies. To overcome these limitations, we propose Graph-Grounded LLMs, a system that improves LLM performance on graph-related tasks by integrating a graph library through function calls. By grounding LLMs in this manner, we demonstrate significant reductions in hallucinations and improved mathematical accuracy in solving graph-based problems, as evidenced by the performance on the NLGraph benchmark. Finally, we showcase a disaster rescue application where the Graph-Grounded LLM acts as a decision-support system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10941v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piyush Gupta, Sangjae Bae, David Isele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-cost Real-world Implementation of the Swing-up Pendulum for Deep Reinforcement Learning Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11065v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep reinforcement learning (DRL) has had success in virtual and simulated domains, but due to key differences between simulated and real-world environments, DRL-trained policies have had limited success in real-world applications. To assist researchers to bridge the \textit{sim-to-real gap}, in this paper, we describe a low-cost physical inverted pendulum apparatus and software environment for exploring sim-to-real DRL methods. In particular, the design of our apparatus enables detailed examination of the delays that arise in physical systems when sensing, communicating, learning, inferring and actuating. Moreover, we wish to improve access to educational systems, so our apparatus uses readily available materials and parts to reduce cost and logistical barriers. Our design shows how commercial, off-the-shelf electronics and electromechanical and sensor systems, combined with common metal extrusions, dowel and 3D printed couplings provide a pathway for affordable physical DRL apparatus. The physical apparatus is complemented with a simulated environment implemented using a high-fidelity physics engine and OpenAI Gym interface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11065v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter B\"ohm, Pauline Pounds, Archie C. Chapman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Six-DoF Stewart Platform Motion Simulator Control using Switchable Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Due to excellent mechanism characteristics of high rigidity, maneuverability and strength-to-weight ratio, 6 Degree-of-Freedom (DoF) Stewart structure is widely adopted to construct flight simulator platforms for replicating motion feelings during training pilots. Unlike conventional serial link manipulator based mechanisms, Upset Prevention and Recovery Training (UPRT) in complex flight status is often accompanied by large speed and violent rate of change in angular velocity of the simulator. However, Classical Washout Filter (CWF) based Motion Cueing Algorithm (MCA) shows limitations in providing rapid response to drive motors to satisfy high accuracy performance requirements. This paper aims at exploiting Model Predictive Control (MPC) based MCA which is proved to be efficient in Hexapod-based motion simulators through controlling over limited linear workspace. With respect to uncertainties and control solution errors from the extraction of Terminal Constraints (COTC), this paper proposes a Switchable Model Predictive Control (S-MPC) based MCA under model adaptive architecture to mitigate the solution uncertainties and inaccuracies. It is verified that high accurate tracking is achievable using the MPC-based MCA with COTC within the simulator operating envelope. The proposed method provides optimal tracking solutions by switching to MPC based MCA without COTC outside the operating envelope. By demonstrating the UPRT with horizontal stall conditions following Average Absolute Scale(AAS) evaluation criteria, the proposed S-MPC based MCA outperforms MPC based MCA and SWF based MCA by 42.34% and 65.30%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11300v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangwei Zhao, Zhengjia Xu, Dongsu Wu, Yingrui Cao, Jinpeng Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for a Capability-driven Evaluation of Scenario Understanding for Multimodal Large Language Models in Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11400v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) hold the potential to enhance autonomous driving by combining domain-independent world knowledge with context-specific language guidance. Their integration into autonomous driving systems shows promising results in isolated proof-of-concept applications, while their performance is evaluated on selective singular aspects of perception, reasoning, or planning. To leverage their full potential a systematic framework for evaluating MLLMs in the context of autonomous driving is required. This paper proposes a holistic framework for a capability-driven evaluation of MLLMs in autonomous driving. The framework structures scenario understanding along the four core capability dimensions semantic, spatial, temporal, and physical. They are derived from the general requirements of autonomous driving systems, human driver cognition, and language-based reasoning. It further organises the domain into context layers, processing modalities, and downstream tasks such as language-based interaction and decision-making. To illustrate the framework's applicability, two exemplary traffic scenarios are analysed, grounding the proposed dimensions in realistic driving situations. The framework provides a foundation for the structured evaluation of MLLMs' potential for scenario understanding in autonomous driving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11400v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tin Stribor Sohn, Philipp Reis, Maximilian Dillitzer, Johannes Bach, Jason J. Corso, Eric Sax</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LuSeg: Efficient Negative and Positive Obstacles Segmentation via Contrast-Driven Multi-Modal Feature Fusion on the Lunar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11409v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As lunar exploration missions grow increasingly complex, ensuring safe and autonomous rover-based surface exploration has become one of the key challenges in lunar exploration tasks. In this work, we have developed a lunar surface simulation system called the Lunar Exploration Simulator System (LESS) and the LunarSeg dataset, which provides RGB-D data for lunar obstacle segmentation that includes both positive and negative obstacles. Additionally, we propose a novel two-stage segmentation network called LuSeg. Through contrastive learning, it enforces semantic consistency between the RGB encoder from Stage I and the depth encoder from Stage II. Experimental results on our proposed LunarSeg dataset and additional public real-world NPO road obstacle dataset demonstrate that LuSeg achieves state-of-the-art segmentation performance for both positive and negative obstacles while maintaining a high inference speed of approximately 57\,Hz. We have released the implementation of our LESS system, LunarSeg dataset, and the code of LuSeg at:https://github.com/nubot-nudt/LuSeg.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11409v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaifeng Jiao, Zhiwen Zeng, Zhuoqun Su, Xieyuanli Chen, Zongtan Zhou, Huimin Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TASTE-Rob: Advancing Video Generation of Task-Oriented Hand-Object Interaction for Generalizable Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11423v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address key limitations in existing datasets and models for task-oriented hand-object interaction video generation, a critical approach of generating video demonstrations for robotic imitation learning. Current datasets, such as Ego4D, often suffer from inconsistent view perspectives and misaligned interactions, leading to reduced video quality and limiting their applicability for precise imitation learning tasks. Towards this end, we introduce TASTE-Rob -- a pioneering large-scale dataset of 100,856 ego-centric hand-object interaction videos. Each video is meticulously aligned with language instructions and recorded from a consistent camera viewpoint to ensure interaction clarity. By fine-tuning a Video Diffusion Model (VDM) on TASTE-Rob, we achieve realistic object interactions, though we observed occasional inconsistencies in hand grasping postures. To enhance realism, we introduce a three-stage pose-refinement pipeline that improves hand posture accuracy in generated videos. Our curated dataset, coupled with the specialized pose-refinement framework, provides notable performance gains in generating high-quality, task-oriented hand-object interaction videos, resulting in achieving superior generalizable robotic manipulation. The TASTE-Rob dataset will be made publicly available upon publication to foster further advancements in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11423v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongxiang Zhao, Xingchen Liu, Mutian Xu, Yiming Hao, Weikai Chen, Xiaoguang Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unicorn: A Universal and Collaborative Reinforcement Learning Approach Towards Generalizable Network-Wide Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Adaptive traffic signal control (ATSC) is crucial in reducing congestion, maximizing throughput, and improving mobility in rapidly growing urban areas. Recent advancements in parameter-sharing multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) have greatly enhanced the scalable and adaptive optimization of complex, dynamic flows in large-scale homogeneous networks. However, the inherent heterogeneity of real-world traffic networks, with their varied intersection topologies and interaction dynamics, poses substantial challenges to achieving scalable and effective ATSC across different traffic scenarios. To address these challenges, we present Unicorn, a universal and collaborative MARL framework designed for efficient and adaptable network-wide ATSC. Specifically, we first propose a unified approach to map the states and actions of intersections with varying topologies into a common structure based on traffic movements. Next, we design a Universal Traffic Representation (UTR) module with a decoder-only network for general feature extraction, enhancing the model's adaptability to diverse traffic scenarios. Additionally, we incorporate an Intersection Specifics Representation (ISR) module, designed to identify key latent vectors that represent the unique intersection's topology and traffic dynamics through variational inference techniques. To further refine these latent representations, we employ a contrastive learning approach in a self-supervised manner, which enables better differentiation of intersection-specific features. Moreover, we integrate the state-action dependencies of neighboring agents into policy optimization, which effectively captures dynamic agent interactions and facilitates efficient regional collaboration. Our results show that Unicorn outperforms other methods across various evaluation metrics, highlighting its potential in complex, dynamic traffic networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11488v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifeng Zhang, Yilin Liu, Ping Gong, Peizhuo Li, Mingfeng Fan, Guillaume Sartoretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangled Object-Centric Image Representation for Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11565v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning robotic manipulation skills from vision is a promising approach for developing robotics applications that can generalize broadly to real-world scenarios. As such, many approaches to enable this vision have been explored with fruitful results. Particularly, object-centric representation methods have been shown to provide better inductive biases for skill learning, leading to improved performance and generalization. Nonetheless, we show that object-centric methods can struggle to learn simple manipulation skills in multi-object environments. Thus, we propose DOCIR, an object-centric framework that introduces a disentangled representation for objects of interest, obstacles, and robot embodiment. We show that this approach leads to state-of-the-art performance for learning pick and place skills from visual inputs in multi-object environments and generalizes at test time to changing objects of interest and distractors in the scene. Furthermore, we show its efficacy both in simulation and zero-shot transfer to the real world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11565v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Emukpere, Romain Deffayet, Bingbing Wu, Romain Br\'egier, Michael Niemaz, Jean-Luc Meunier, Denys Proux, Jean-Michel Renders, Seungsu Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoPAL: Corrective Planning of Robot Actions with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07263v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the pursuit of fully autonomous robotic systems capable of taking over tasks traditionally performed by humans, the complexity of open-world environments poses a considerable challenge. Addressing this imperative, this study contributes to the field of Large Language Models (LLMs) applied to task and motion planning for robots. We propose a system architecture that orchestrates a seamless interplay between multiple cognitive levels, encompassing reasoning, planning, and motion generation. At its core lies a novel replanning strategy that handles physically grounded, logical, and semantic errors in the generated plans. We demonstrate the efficacy of the proposed feedback architecture, particularly its impact on executability, correctness, and time complexity via empirical evaluation in the context of a simulation and two intricate real-world scenarios: blocks world, barman and pizza preparation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07263v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank Joublin, Antonello Ceravola, Pavel Smirnov, Felix Ocker, Joerg Deigmoeller, Anna Belardinelli, Chao Wang, Stephan Hasler, Daniel Tanneberg, Michael Gienger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Semi-Lagrangian Approach for Time and Energy Path Planning Optimization in Static Flow Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16859v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficient path planning for autonomous mobile robots is a critical problem across numerous domains, where optimizing both time and energy consumption is paramount. This paper introduces a novel methodology that considers the dynamic influence of an environmental flow field and considers geometric constraints, including obstacles and forbidden zones, enriching the complexity of the planning problem. We formulate it as a multi-objective optimal control problem, propose a novel transformation called Harmonic Transformation, and apply a semi-Lagrangian scheme to solve it. The set of Pareto efficient solutions is obtained considering two distinct approaches: a deterministic method and an evolutionary-based one, both of which are designed to make use of the proposed Harmonic Transformation. Through an extensive analysis of these approaches, we demonstrate their efficacy in finding optimized paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16859v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jfranklin.2025.107612</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>V\'ictor C. da S. Campos, Armando A. Neto, Douglas G. Macharet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkinGrip: An Adaptive Soft Robotic Manipulator with Capacitive Sensing for Whole-Limb Bed Bathing Assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02772v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robotics presents a promising opportunity for enhancing bathing assistance, potentially to alleviate labor shortages and reduce care costs, while offering consistent and gentle care for individuals with physical disabilities. However, ensuring flexible and efficient cleaning of the human body poses challenges as it involves direct physical contact between the human and the robot, and necessitates simple, safe, and effective control. In this paper, we introduce a soft, expandable robotic manipulator with embedded capacitive proximity sensing arrays, designed for safe and efficient bathing assistance. We conduct a thorough evaluation of our soft manipulator, comparing it with a baseline rigid end effector in a human study involving 12 participants across $96$ bathing trails. Our soft manipulator achieves an an average cleaning effectiveness of 88.8% on arms and 81.4% on legs, far exceeding the performance of the baseline. Participant feedback further validates the manipulator's ability to maintain safety, comfort, and thorough cleaning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02772v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fukang Liu, Kavya Puthuveetil, Akhil Padmanabha, Karan Khokar, Zeynep Temel, Zackory Erickson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Context Learning for Socially Compliant Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11495v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robot social navigation needs to adapt to different human factors and environmental contexts. However, since these factors and contexts are difficult to predict and cannot be exhaustively enumerated, traditional learning-based methods have difficulty in ensuring the social attributes of robots in long-term and cross-environment deployments. This letter introduces an online context learning method that aims to empower robots to adapt to new social environments online. The proposed method adopts a two-layer structure. The bottom layer is built using a deep reinforcement learning-based method to ensure the output of basic robot navigation commands. The upper layer is implemented using an online robot learning-based method to socialize the control commands suggested by the bottom layer. Experiments using a community-wide simulator show that our method outperforms the state-of-the-art ones. Experimental results in the most challenging scenarios show that our method improves the performance of the state-of-the-art by 8%. The source code of the proposed method, the data used, and the tools for the per-training step are publicly available at https://github.com/Nedzhaken/SOCSARL-OL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11495v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iaroslav Okunevich, Alexandre Lombard, Tomas Krajnik, Yassine Ruichek, Zhi Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Global Localization on Neural Radiance Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12202v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF) presented a novel way to represent scenes, allowing for high-quality 3D reconstruction from 2D images. Following its remarkable achievements, global localization within NeRF maps is an essential task for enabling a wide range of applications. Recently, Loc-NeRF demonstrated a localization approach that combines traditional Monte Carlo Localization with NeRF, showing promising results for using NeRF as an environment map. However, despite its advancements, Loc-NeRF encounters the challenge of a time-intensive ray rendering process, which can be a significant limitation in practical applications. To address this issue, we introduce Fast Loc-NeRF, which leverages a coarse-to-fine approach to enable more efficient and accurate NeRF map-based global localization. Specifically, Fast Loc-NeRF matches rendered pixels and observed images on a multi-resolution from low to high resolution. As a result, it speeds up the costly particle update process while maintaining precise localization results. Additionally, to reject the abnormal particles, we propose particle rejection weighting, which estimates the uncertainty of particles by exploiting NeRF's characteristics and considers them in the particle weighting process. Our Fast Loc-NeRF sets new state-of-the-art localization performances on several benchmarks, convincing its accuracy and efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12202v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mangyu Kong, Seongwon Lee, Jaewon Lee, Euntai Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual-MPPI: Online Policy Customization for Continuous Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00898v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Policies developed through Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Imitation Learning (IL) have shown great potential in continuous control tasks, but real-world applications often require adapting trained policies to unforeseen requirements. While fine-tuning can address such needs, it typically requires additional data and access to the original training metrics and parameters. In contrast, an online planning algorithm, if capable of meeting the additional requirements, can eliminate the necessity for extensive training phases and customize the policy without knowledge of the original training scheme or task. In this work, we propose a generic online planning algorithm for customizing continuous-control policies at the execution time, which we call Residual-MPPI. It can customize a given prior policy on new performance metrics in few-shot and even zero-shot online settings, given access to the prior action distribution alone. Through our experiments, we demonstrate that the proposed Residual-MPPI algorithm can accomplish the few-shot/zero-shot online policy customization task effectively, including customizing the champion-level racing agent, Gran Turismo Sophy (GT Sophy) 1.0, in the challenging car racing scenario, Gran Turismo Sport (GTS) environment. Code for MuJoCo experiments is included in the supplementary and will be open-sourced upon acceptance. Demo videos and code are available on our website: https://sites.google.com/view/residual-mppi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00898v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengcheng Wang, Chenran Li, Catherine Weaver, Kenta Kawamoto, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Chen Tang, Wei Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baloo: A Large-Scale Hybrid Soft Robotic Torso for Whole-Arm Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08420v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Soft robotic actuators can simplify the design of controllers when operating in contact-rich environments. Importantly, their passive compliance fundamentally alters contact mechanics by smoothing impacts and distributing forces over large areas. By integrating soft actuators, we can perform high-impact, dynamic, and contact-rich tasks that are challenging or impossible for traditional rigid robots. In order to explore the benefits of passive structural compliance and learn to utilize it effectively, we present a prototype robotic torso named Baloo. Baloo's hybrid soft-rigid design incorporates both adaptability from soft components and strength from rigid components with two meter-long, pneumatic robot arms mounted on a rigid torso. The hybrid design is capable of lifting end effector payloads of up to 19 kg, far exceeding many hybrid robot designs. Such payloads are competitive with similar-sized rigid robots, but with a much higher strength-to-weight ratio. Through 30 physical whole-body grasping experiments, we also demonstrate how a simple control strategy can generalize for effective lifting across six challenging objects with diverse shapes, sizes, and weights. A 100% success rate across all objects--achieved with the simple control strategy--underscores the potential of our hybrid soft-rigid robot design for contact-rich, whole-body tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08420v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Curtis C. Johnson, Andrew Clawson, Marc D. Killpack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization-based Task and Motion Planning under Signal Temporal Logic Specifications using Logic Network Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19168v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes an optimization-based task and motion planning framework, named ``Logic Network Flow", to integrate signal temporal logic (STL) specifications into efficient mixed-binary linear programmings. In this framework, temporal predicates are encoded as polyhedron constraints on each edge of the network flow, instead of as constraints between the nodes as in the traditional Logic Tree formulation. Synthesized with Dynamic Network Flows, Logic Network Flows render a tighter convex relaxation compared to Logic Trees derived from these STL specifications. Our formulation is evaluated on several multi-robot motion planning case studies. Empirical results demonstrate that our formulation outperforms Logic Tree formulation in terms of computation time for several planning problems. As the problem size scales up, our method still discovers better lower and upper bounds by exploring fewer number of nodes during the branch-and-bound process, although this comes at the cost of increased computational load for each node when exploring branches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19168v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Lin, Jiming Ren, Samuel Coogan, Ye Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Duke Humanoid: Design and Control For Energy Efficient Bipedal Locomotion Using Passive Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19795v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the Duke Humanoid, an open-source 10-degrees-of-freedom humanoid, as an extensible platform for locomotion research. The design mimics human physiology, with symmetrical body alignment in the frontal plane to maintain static balance with straight knees. We develop a reinforcement learning policy that can be deployed zero-shot on the hardware for velocity-tracking walking tasks. Additionally, to enhance energy efficiency in locomotion, we propose an end-to-end reinforcement learning algorithm that encourages the robot to leverage passive dynamics. Our experimental results show that our passive policy reduces the cost of transport by up to $50\%$ in simulation and $31\%$ in real-world tests. Our website is http://generalroboticslab.com/DukeHumanoidv1/ .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19795v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boxi Xia, Bokuan Li, Jacob Lee, Michael Scutari, Boyuan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathcal{D(R,O)}$ Grasp: A Unified Representation of Robot and Object Interaction for Cross-Embodiment Dexterous Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01702v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dexterous grasping is a fundamental yet challenging skill in robotic manipulation, requiring precise interaction between robotic hands and objects. In this paper, we present $\mathcal{D(R,O)}$ Grasp, a novel framework that models the interaction between the robotic hand in its grasping pose and the object, enabling broad generalization across various robot hands and object geometries. Our model takes the robot hand's description and object point cloud as inputs and efficiently predicts kinematically valid and stable grasps, demonstrating strong adaptability to diverse robot embodiments and object geometries. Extensive experiments conducted in both simulated and real-world environments validate the effectiveness of our approach, with significant improvements in success rate, grasp diversity, and inference speed across multiple robotic hands. Our method achieves an average success rate of 87.53% in simulation in less than one second, tested across three different dexterous robotic hands. In real-world experiments using the LeapHand, the method also demonstrates an average success rate of 89%. $\mathcal{D(R,O)}$ Grasp provides a robust solution for dexterous grasping in complex and varied environments. The code, appendix, and videos are available on our project website at https://nus-lins-lab.github.io/drograspweb/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01702v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Wei, Zhixuan Xu, Jingxiang Guo, Yiwen Hou, Chongkai Gao, Zhehao Cai, Jiayu Luo, Lin Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dita: Scaling Diffusion Transformer for Generalist Vision-Language-Action Policy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15959v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While recent vision-language-action models trained on diverse robot datasets exhibit promising generalization capabilities with limited in-domain data, their reliance on compact action heads to predict discretized or continuous actions constrains adaptability to heterogeneous action spaces. We present Dita, a scalable framework that leverages Transformer architectures to directly denoise continuous action sequences through a unified multimodal diffusion process. Departing from prior methods that condition denoising on fused embeddings via shallow networks, Dita employs in-context conditioning -- enabling fine-grained alignment between denoised actions and raw visual tokens from historical observations. This design explicitly models action deltas and environmental nuances. By scaling the diffusion action denoiser alongside the Transformer's scalability, Dita effectively integrates cross-embodiment datasets across diverse camera perspectives, observation scenes, tasks, and action spaces. Such synergy enhances robustness against various variances and facilitates the successful execution of long-horizon tasks. Evaluations across extensive benchmarks demonstrate state-of-the-art or comparative performance in simulation. Notably, Dita achieves robust real-world adaptation to environmental variances and complex long-horizon tasks through 10-shot finetuning, using only third-person camera inputs. The architecture establishes a versatile, lightweight and open-source baseline for generalist robot policy learning. Project Page: https://robodita.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15959v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Hou, Tianyi Zhang, Yuwen Xiong, Haonan Duan, Hengjun Pu, Ronglei Tong, Chengyang Zhao, Xizhou Zhu, Yu Qiao, Jifeng Dai, Yuntao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SERN: Simulation-Enhanced Realistic Navigation for Multi-Agent Robotic Systems in Contested Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The increasing deployment of autonomous systems in complex environments necessitates efficient communication and task completion among multiple agents. This paper presents SERN (Simulation-Enhanced Realistic Navigation), a novel framework integrating virtual and physical environments for real-time collaborative decision-making in multi-robot systems. SERN addresses key challenges in asset deployment and coordination through our bi-directional SERN ROS Bridge communication framework. Our approach advances the SOTA through: accurate real-world representation in virtual environments using Unity high-fidelity simulator; synchronization of physical and virtual robot movements; efficient ROS data distribution between remote locations; and integration of SOTA semantic segmentation for enhanced environmental perception. Additionally, we introduce a Multi-Metric Cost Function (MMCF) that dynamically balances latency, reliability, computational overhead, and bandwidth consumption to optimize system performance in contested environments. We further provide theoretical justification for synchronization accuracy by proving that the positional error between physical and virtual robots remains bounded under varying network conditions. Our evaluations show a 15% to 24% improvement in latency and up to a 15% increase in processing efficiency compared to traditional ROS setups. Real-world and virtual simulation experiments with multiple robots (Clearpath Jackal and Husky) demonstrate synchronization accuracy, achieving less than $5\text{ cm}$ positional error and under $2^\circ$ rotational error. These results highlight SERN's potential to enhance situational awareness and multi-agent coordination in diverse, contested environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16686v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jumman Hossain, Emon Dey, Snehalraj Chugh, Masud Ahmed, MS Anwar, Abu-Zaher Faridee, Jason Hoppes, Theron Trout, Anjon Basak, Rafidh Chowdhury, Rishabh Mistry, Hyun Kim, Jade Freeman, Niranjan Suri, Adrienne Raglin, Carl Busart, Timothy Gregory, Anuradha Ravi, Nirmalya Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UGotMe: An Embodied System for Affective Human-Robot Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Equipping humanoid robots with the capability to understand emotional states of human interactants and express emotions appropriately according to situations is essential for affective human-robot interaction. However, enabling current vision-aware multimodal emotion recognition models for affective human-robot interaction in the real-world raises embodiment challenges: addressing the environmental noise issue and meeting real-time requirements. First, in multiparty conversation scenarios, the noises inherited in the visual observation of the robot, which may come from either 1) distracting objects in the scene or 2) inactive speakers appearing in the field of view of the robot, hinder the models from extracting emotional cues from vision inputs. Secondly, realtime response, a desired feature for an interactive system, is also challenging to achieve. To tackle both challenges, we introduce an affective human-robot interaction system called UGotMe designed specifically for multiparty conversations. Two denoising strategies are proposed and incorporated into the system to solve the first issue. Specifically, to filter out distracting objects in the scene, we propose extracting face images of the speakers from the raw images and introduce a customized active face extraction strategy to rule out inactive speakers. As for the second issue, we employ efficient data transmission from the robot to the local server to improve realtime response capability. We deploy UGotMe on a human robot named Ameca to validate its real-time inference capabilities in practical scenarios. Videos demonstrating real-world deployment are available at https://pi3-141592653.github.io/UGotMe/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18373v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peizhen Li, Longbing Cao, Xiao-Ming Wu, Xiaohan Yu, Runze Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MR-COGraphs: Communication-efficient Multi-Robot Open-vocabulary Mapping System via 3D Scene Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18381v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Collaborative perception in unknown environments is crucial for multi-robot systems. With the emergence of foundation models, robots can now not only perceive geometric information but also achieve open-vocabulary scene understanding. However, existing map representations that support open-vocabulary queries often involve large data volumes, which becomes a bottleneck for multi-robot transmission in communication-limited environments. To address this challenge, we develop a method to construct a graph-structured 3D representation called COGraph, where nodes represent objects with semantic features and edges capture their spatial adjacency relationships. Before transmission, a data-driven feature encoder is applied to compress the feature dimensions of the COGraph. Upon receiving COGraphs from other robots, the semantic features of each node are recovered using a decoder. We also propose a feature-based approach for place recognition and translation estimation, enabling the merging of local COGraphs into a unified global map. We validate our framework on two realistic datasets and the real-world environment. The results demonstrate that, compared to existing baselines for open-vocabulary map construction, our framework reduces the data volume by over 80\% while maintaining mapping and query performance without compromise. For more details, please visit our website at https://github.com/efc-robot/MR-COGraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18381v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiuyi Gu, Zhaocheng Ye, Jincheng Yu, Jiahao Tang, Tinghao Yi, Yuhan Dong, Jian Wang, Jinqiang Cui, Xinlei Chen, Yu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete GCBF Proximal Policy Optimization for Multi-agent Safe Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03640v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Control policies that can achieve high task performance and satisfy safety constraints are desirable for any system, including multi-agent systems (MAS). One promising technique for ensuring the safety of MAS is distributed control barrier functions (CBF). However, it is difficult to design distributed CBF-based policies for MAS that can tackle unknown discrete-time dynamics, partial observability, changing neighborhoods, and input constraints, especially when a distributed high-performance nominal policy that can achieve the task is unavailable. To tackle these challenges, we propose DGPPO, a new framework that simultaneously learns both a discrete graph CBF which handles neighborhood changes and input constraints, and a distributed high-performance safe policy for MAS with unknown discrete-time dynamics. We empirically validate our claims on a suite of multi-agent tasks spanning three different simulation engines. The results suggest that, compared with existing methods, our DGPPO framework obtains policies that achieve high task performance (matching baselines that ignore the safety constraints), and high safety rates (matching the most conservative baselines), with a constant set of hyperparameters across all environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03640v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songyuan Zhang, Oswin So, Mitchell Black, Chuchu Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Nash Equilibrium Solutions in Dynamic Games With Shared Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19569v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In dynamic games with shared constraints, Generalized Nash Equilibria (GNE) are often computed using the normalized solution concept, which assumes identical Lagrange multipliers for shared constraints across all players. While widely used, this approach excludes other potentially valuable GNE. This paper presents a novel method based on the Mixed Complementarity Problem (MCP) formulation to compute non-normalized GNE, expanding the solution space. We also propose a systematic approach for selecting the optimal GNE based on predefined criteria, enhancing practical flexibility. Numerical examples illustrate the methods effectiveness, offering an alternative to traditional normalized solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19569v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Pustilnik, Francesco Borrelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survival of the fastest -- algorithm-guided evolution of light-powered underwater microrobots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00204v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Depending on multiple parameters, soft robots can exhibit different modes of locomotion that are difficult to model numerically. As a result, improving their performance is complex, especially in small-scale systems characterized by low Reynolds numbers, when multiple aero- and hydrodynamical processes influence their movement. In this work, we optimize light-powered millimetre-scale underwater swimmer locomotion by applying experimental results - measured swimming speed - as the fitness function in two evolutionary algorithms: particle swarm optimization and genetic algorithm. As these soft, light-powered robots with different characteristics (phenotypes) can be fabricated quickly, they provide a great platform for optimisation experiments, using many competing robots to improve swimming speed over consecutive generations. Interestingly, just like in natural evolution, unexpected gene combinations led to surprisingly good results, including eight-fold increase in speed or the discovery of a self-oscillating underwater locomotion mode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00204v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miko{\l}aj Rog\'o\.z, Zofia Dziekan, Piotr Wasylczyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEVA: A high-mobility logistic vehicle with legged suspension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The autonomous transportation of materials over challenging terrain is a challenge with major economic implications and remains unsolved. This paper introduces LEVA, a high-payload, high-mobility robot designed for autonomous logistics across varied terrains, including those typical in agriculture, construction, and search and rescue operations. LEVA uniquely integrates an advanced legged suspension system using parallel kinematics. It is capable of traversing stairs using a rl controller, has steerable wheels, and includes a specialized box pickup mechanism that enables autonomous payload loading as well as precise and reliable cargo transportation of up to 85 kg across uneven surfaces, steps and inclines while maintaining a cot of as low as 0.15. Through extensive experimental validation, LEVA demonstrates its off-road capabilities and reliability regarding payload loading and transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10028v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Arnold, Lukas Hildebrandt, Kaspar Janssen, Efe Ongan, Pascal B\"urge, \'Ad\'am Gyula G\'abriel, James Kennedy, Rishi Lolla, Quanisha Oppliger, Micha Schaaf, Joseph Church, Michael Fritsche, Victor Klemm, Turcan Tuna, Giorgio Valsecchi, Cedric Weibel, Marco Hutter, Michael W\"utrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Guidance as a Mid-level Representation for Navigation with Augmented Reality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.02731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.02731v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the context of autonomous navigation, effectively conveying abstract navigational cues to agents in dynamic environments presents significant challenges, particularly when navigation information is derived from diverse modalities such as both vision and high-level language descriptions. To address this issue, we introduce a novel technique termed `Virtual Guidance,' which is designed to visually represent non-visual instructional signals. These visual cues are overlaid onto the agent's camera view and served as comprehensible navigational guidance signals. To validate the concept of virtual guidance, we propose a sim-to-real framework that enables the transfer of the trained policy from simulated environments to real world, ensuring the adaptability of virtual guidance in practical scenarios. We evaluate and compare the proposed method against a non-visual guidance baseline through detailed experiments in simulation. The experimental results demonstrate that the proposed virtual guidance approach outperforms the baseline methods across multiple scenarios and offers clear evidence of its effectiveness in autonomous navigation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.02731v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsuan-Kung Yang, Tsung-Chih Chiang, Jou-Min Liu, Ting-Ru Liu, Chun-Wei Huang, Tsu-Ching Hsiao, Chun-Yi Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LIX: Implicitly Infusing Spatial Geometric Prior Knowledge into Visual Semantic Segmentation for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08215v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Despite the impressive performance achieved by data-fusion networks with duplex encoders for visual semantic segmentation, they become ineffective when spatial geometric data are not available. Implicitly infusing the spatial geometric prior knowledge acquired by a data-fusion teacher network into a single-modal student network is a practical, albeit less explored research avenue. This article delves into this topic and resorts to knowledge distillation approaches to address this problem. We introduce the Learning to Infuse ''X'' (LIX) framework, with novel contributions in both logit distillation and feature distillation aspects. We present a mathematical proof that underscores the limitation of using a single, fixed weight in decoupled knowledge distillation and introduce a logit-wise dynamic weight controller as a solution to this issue. Furthermore, we develop an adaptively-recalibrated feature distillation algorithm, including two novel techniques: feature recalibration via kernel regression and in-depth feature consistency quantification via centered kernel alignment. Extensive experiments conducted with intermediate-fusion and late-fusion networks across various public datasets provide both quantitative and qualitative evaluations, demonstrating the superior performance of our LIX framework when compared to other state-of-the-art approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08215v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sicen Guo, Ziwei Long, Zhiyuan Wu, Qijun Chen, Ioannis Pitas, Rui Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmark Evaluations, Applications, and Challenges of Large Vision Language Models: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02189v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multimodal Vision Language Models (VLMs) have emerged as a transformative technology at the intersection of computer vision and natural language processing, enabling machines to perceive and reason about the world through both visual and textual modalities. For example, models such as CLIP, Claude, and GPT-4V demonstrate strong reasoning and understanding abilities on visual and textual data and beat classical single modality vision models on zero-shot classification. Despite their rapid advancements in research and growing popularity in applications, a comprehensive survey of existing studies on VLMs is notably lacking, particularly for researchers aiming to leverage VLMs in their specific domains. To this end, we provide a systematic overview of VLMs in the following aspects: model information of the major VLMs developed over the past five years (2019-2024); the main architectures and training methods of these VLMs; summary and categorization of the popular benchmarks and evaluation metrics of VLMs; the applications of VLMs including embodied agents, robotics, and video generation; the challenges and issues faced by current VLMs such as hallucination, fairness, and safety. Detailed collections including papers and model repository links are listed in https://github.com/zli12321/Awesome-VLM-Papers-And-Models.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02189v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongxia Li, Xiyang Wu, Hongyang Du, Huy Nghiem, Guangyao Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System 0/1/2/3: Quad-process theory for multi-timescale embodied collective cognitive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06138v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the System 0/1/2/3 framework as an extension of dual-process theory, employing a quad-process model of cognition. Expanding upon System 1 (fast, intuitive thinking) and System 2 (slow, deliberative thinking), we incorporate System 0, which represents pre-cognitive embodied processes, and System 3, which encompasses collective intelligence and symbol emergence. We contextualize this model within Bergson's philosophy by adopting multi-scale time theory to unify the diverse temporal dynamics of cognition. System 0 emphasizes morphological computation and passive dynamics, illustrating how physical embodiment enables adaptive behavior without explicit neural processing. Systems 1 and 2 are explained from a constructive perspective, incorporating neurodynamical and AI viewpoints. In System 3, we introduce collective predictive coding to explain how societal-level adaptation and symbol emergence operate over extended timescales. This comprehensive framework ranges from rapid embodied reactions to slow-evolving collective intelligence, offering a unified perspective on cognition across multiple timescales, levels of abstraction, and forms of human intelligence. The System 0/1/2/3 model provides a novel theoretical foundation for understanding the interplay between adaptive and cognitive processes, thereby opening new avenues for research in cognitive science, AI, robotics, and collective intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06138v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahiro Taniguchi, Yasushi Hirai, Masahiro Suzuki, Shingo Murata, Takato Horii, Kazutoshi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
