<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 01:43:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-shot Sim2Real Transfer for Magnet-Based Tactile Sensor on Insertion Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tactile sensing is an important sensing modality for robot manipulation. Among different types of tactile sensors, magnet-based sensors, like u-skin, balance well between high durability and tactile density. However, the large sim-to-real gap of tactile sensors prevents robots from acquiring useful tactile-based manipulation skills from simulation data, a recipe that has been successful for achieving complex and sophisticated control policies. Prior work has implemented binarization techniques to bridge the sim-to-real gap for dexterous in-hand manipulation. However, binarization inherently loses much information that is useful in many other tasks, e.g., insertion. In our work, we propose GCS, a novel sim-to-real technique to learn contact-rich skills with dense, distributed, 3-axis tactile readings. We evaluate our approach on blind insertion tasks and show zero-shot sim-to-real transfer of RL policies with raw tactile reading as input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02915v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beining Han, Abhishek Joshi, Jia Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MORE: Mobile Manipulation Rearrangement Through Grounded Language Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous long-horizon mobile manipulation encompasses a multitude of challenges, including scene dynamics, unexplored areas, and error recovery. Recent works have leveraged foundation models for scene-level robotic reasoning and planning. However, the performance of these methods degrades when dealing with a large number of objects and large-scale environments. To address these limitations, we propose MORE, a novel approach for enhancing the capabilities of language models to solve zero-shot mobile manipulation planning for rearrangement tasks. MORE leverages scene graphs to represent environments, incorporates instance differentiation, and introduces an active filtering scheme that extracts task-relevant subgraphs of object and region instances. These steps yield a bounded planning problem, effectively mitigating hallucinations and improving reliability. Additionally, we introduce several enhancements that enable planning across both indoor and outdoor environments. We evaluate MORE on 81 diverse rearrangement tasks from the BEHAVIOR-1K benchmark, where it becomes the first approach to successfully solve a significant share of the benchmark, outperforming recent foundation model-based approaches. Furthermore, we demonstrate the capabilities of our approach in several complex real-world tasks, mimicking everyday activities. We make the code publicly available at https://more-model.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03035v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mohammadi, Daniel Honerkamp, Martin B\"uchner, Matteo Cassinelli, Tim Welschehold, Fabien Despinoy, Igor Gilitschenski, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Modal-Space Formulation for Momentum Observer Contact Estimation and Effects of Uncertainty for Continuum Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contact detection for continuum and soft robots has been limited in past works to statics or kinematics-based methods with assumed circular bending curvature or known bending profiles. In this paper, we adapt the generalized momentum observer contact estimation method to continuum robots. This is made possible by leveraging recent results for real-time shape sensing of continuum robots along with a modal-space representation of the robot dynamics. In addition to presenting an approach for estimating the generalized forces due to contact via a momentum observer, we present a constrained optimization method to identify the wrench imparted on the robot during contact. We also present an approach for investigating the effects of unmodeled deviations in the robot's dynamic state on the contact detection method and we validate our algorithm by simulations and experiments. We also compare the performance of the momentum observer to the joint force deviation method, a direct estimation approach using the robot's full dynamic model. We also demonstrate a basic extension of the method to multisegment continuum robots. Results presented in this work extend dynamic contact detection to the domain of continuum and soft robots and can be used to improve the safety of large-scale continuum robots for human-robot collaboration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03044v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1177/02783649251342823</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Garrison L. H. Johnston, Neel Shihora, Nabil Simaan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sim2Real Transfer for Vision-Based Grasp Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The verification of successful grasps is a crucial aspect of robot manipulation, particularly when handling deformable objects. Traditional methods relying on force and tactile sensors often struggle with deformable and non-rigid objects. In this work, we present a vision-based approach for grasp verification to determine whether the robotic gripper has successfully grasped an object. Our method employs a two-stage architecture; first YOLO-based object detection model to detect and locate the robot's gripper and then a ResNet-based classifier determines the presence of an object. To address the limitations of real-world data capture, we introduce HSR-GraspSynth, a synthetic dataset designed to simulate diverse grasping scenarios. Furthermore, we explore the use of Visual Question Answering capabilities as a zero-shot baseline to which we compare our model. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach achieves high accuracy in real-world environments, with potential for integration into grasping pipelines. Code and datasets are publicly available at https://github.com/pauamargant/HSR-GraspSynth .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03046v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pau Amargant, Peter H\"onig, Markus Vincze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Adaptive Planner for Dynamic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents Latent Adaptive Planner (LAP), a novel approach for dynamic nonprehensile manipulation tasks that formulates planning as latent space inference, effectively learned from human demonstration videos. Our method addresses key challenges in visuomotor policy learning through a principled variational replanning framework that maintains temporal consistency while efficiently adapting to environmental changes. LAP employs Bayesian updating in latent space to incrementally refine plans as new observations become available, striking an optimal balance between computational efficiency and real-time adaptability. We bridge the embodiment gap between humans and robots through model-based proportional mapping that regenerates accurate kinematic-dynamic joint states and object positions from human demonstrations. Experimental evaluations across multiple complex manipulation benchmarks demonstrate that LAP achieves state-of-the-art performance, outperforming existing approaches in success rate, trajectory smoothness, and energy efficiency, particularly in dynamic adaptation scenarios. Our approach enables robots to perform complex interactions with human-like adaptability while providing an expandable framework applicable to diverse robotic platforms using the same human demonstration videos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03077v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghun Noh, Deqian Kong, Minglu Zhao, Andrew Lizarraga, Jianwen Xie, Ying Nian Wu, Dennis Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication and Characterization of Additively Manufactured Stretchable Strain Sensors Towards the Shape Sensing of Continuum Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter describes the manufacturing and experimental characterization of novel stretchable strain sensors for continuum robots. The overarching goal of this research is to provide a new solution for the shape sensing of these devices. The sensors are fabricated via direct ink writing, an extrusion-based additive manufacturing technique. Electrically conductive material (i.e., the \textit{ink}) is printed into traces whose electrical resistance varies in response to mechanical deformation. The principle of operation of stretchable strain sensors is analogous to that of conventional strain gauges, but with a significantly larger operational window thanks to their ability to withstand larger strain. Among the different conductive materials considered for this study, we opted to fabricate the sensors with a high-viscosity eutectic Gallium-Indium ink, which in initial testing exhibited high linearity ($R^2 \approx$ 0.99), gauge factor $\approx$ 1, and negligible drift. Benefits of the proposed sensors include (i) ease of fabrication, as they can be conveniently printed in a matter of minutes; (ii) ease of installation, as they can simply be glued to the outside body of a robot; (iii) ease of miniaturization, which enables integration into millimiter-sized continuum robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03087v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. Moyer, Wenpeng Wang, Logan S. Karschner, Loris Fichera, Pratap M. Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HCOA*: Hierarchical Class-ordered A* for Navigation in Semantic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of robot navigation in mixed geometric and semantic 3D environments. Given a hierarchical representation of the environment, the objective is to navigate from a start position to a goal while minimizing the computational cost. We introduce Hierarchical Class-ordered A* (HCOA*), an algorithm that leverages the environmental hierarchy for efficient path-planning in semantic graphs, significantly reducing computational effort. We use a total order over the semantic classes and prove theoretical performance guarantees for the algorithm. We propose two approaches for higher-layer node classification based on the node semantics of the lowest layer: a Graph Neural Network-based method and a Majority-Class method. We evaluate our approach through simulations on a 3D Scene Graph (3DSG), comparing it to the state-of-the-art and assessing its performance against our classification approaches. Results show that HCOA* can find the optimal path while reducing the number of expanded nodes by 25% and achieving a 16% reduction in computational time on the uHumans2 3DSG dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03128v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Psomiadis, Panagiotis Tsiotras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learn to Swim: Data-Driven LSTM Hydrodynamic Model for Quadruped Robot Gait Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a Long Short-Term Memory network-based Fluid Experiment Data-Driven model (FED-LSTM) for predicting unsteady, nonlinear hydrodynamic forces on the underwater quadruped robot we constructed. Trained on experimental data from leg force and body drag tests conducted in both a recirculating water tank and a towing tank, FED-LSTM outperforms traditional Empirical Formulas (EF) commonly used for flow prediction over flat surfaces. The model demonstrates superior accuracy and adaptability in capturing complex fluid dynamics, particularly in straight-line and turning-gait optimizations via the NSGA-II algorithm. FED-LSTM reduces deflection errors during straight-line swimming and improves turn times without increasing the turning radius. Hardware experiments further validate the model's precision and stability over EF. This approach provides a robust framework for enhancing the swimming performance of legged robots, laying the groundwork for future advances in underwater robotic locomotion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03146v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Han, Pengming Guo, Hao Chen, Weikun Li, Jingbo Ren, Naijun Liu, Ning Yang, Dixia Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Evaluation of Initial States and Exploration-Exploitation Strategies in PID Auto-Tuning: A Framework-Driven Approach Applied on Mobile Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03159v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PID controllers are widely used in control systems because of their simplicity and effectiveness. Although advanced optimization techniques such as Bayesian Optimization and Differential Evolution have been applied to address the challenges of automatic tuning of PID controllers, the influence of initial system states on convergence and the balance between exploration and exploitation remains underexplored. Moreover, experimenting the influence directly on real cyber-physical systems such as mobile robots is crucial for deriving realistic insights. In the present paper, a novel framework is introduced to evaluate the impact of systematically varying these factors on the PID auto-tuning processes that utilize Bayesian Optimization and Differential Evolution. Testing was conducted on two distinct PID-controlled robotic platforms, an omnidirectional robot and a differential drive mobile robot, to assess the effects on convergence rate, settling time, rise time, and overshoot percentage. As a result, the experimental outcomes yield evidence on the effects of the systematic variations, thereby providing an empirical basis for future research studies in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03159v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zaid Ghazal, Ali Al-Bustami, Khouloud Gaaloul, Jaerock Kwon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Data Curation Using GPS &amp; NLP to Generate Instruction-Action Pairs for Autonomous Vehicle Vision-Language Navigation Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Instruction-Action (IA) data pairs are valuable for training robotic systems, especially autonomous vehicles (AVs), but having humans manually annotate this data is costly and time-inefficient. This paper explores the potential of using mobile application Global Positioning System (GPS) references and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to automatically generate large volumes of IA commands and responses without having a human generate or retroactively tag the data. In our pilot data collection, by driving to various destinations and collecting voice instructions from GPS applications, we demonstrate a means to collect and categorize the diverse sets of instructions, further accompanied by video data to form complete vision-language-action triads. We provide details on our completely automated data collection prototype system, ADVLAT-Engine. We characterize collected GPS voice instructions into eight different classifications, highlighting the breadth of commands and referentialities available for curation from freely available mobile applications. Through research and exploration into the automation of IA data pairs using GPS references, the potential to increase the speed and volume at which high-quality IA datasets are created, while minimizing cost, can pave the way for robust vision-language-action (VLA) models to serve tasks in vision-language navigation (VLN) and human-interactive autonomous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03174v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Roque, Erika Maquiling, Jose Giovanni Tapia Lopez, Ross Greer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GraspVLA: a Grasping Foundation Model Pre-trained on Billion-scale Synthetic Action Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Embodied foundation models are gaining increasing attention for their zero-shot generalization, scalability, and adaptability to new tasks through few-shot post-training. However, existing models rely heavily on real-world data, which is costly and labor-intensive to collect. Synthetic data offers a cost-effective alternative, yet its potential remains largely underexplored. To bridge this gap, we explore the feasibility of training Vision-Language-Action models entirely with large-scale synthetic action data. We curate SynGrasp-1B, a billion-frame robotic grasping dataset generated in simulation with photorealistic rendering and extensive domain randomization. Building on this, we present GraspVLA, a VLA model pretrained on large-scale synthetic action data as a foundational model for grasping tasks. GraspVLA integrates autoregressive perception tasks and flow-matching-based action generation into a unified Chain-of-Thought process, enabling joint training on synthetic action data and Internet semantics data. This design helps mitigate sim-to-real gaps and facilitates the transfer of learned actions to a broader range of Internet-covered objects, achieving open-vocabulary generalization in grasping. Extensive evaluations across real-world and simulation benchmarks demonstrate GraspVLA's advanced zero-shot generalizability and few-shot adaptability to specific human preferences. We will release SynGrasp-1B dataset and pre-trained weights to benefit the community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03233v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengliang Deng, Mi Yan, Songlin Wei, Haixin Ma, Yuxin Yang, Jiayi Chen, Zhiqi Zhang, Taoyu Yang, Xuheng Zhang, Heming Cui, Zhizheng Zhang, He Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RobotxR1: Enabling Embodied Robotic Intelligence on Large Language Models through Closed-Loop Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Future robotic systems operating in real-world environments will require on-board embodied intelligence without continuous cloud connection, balancing capabilities with constraints on computational power and memory. This work presents an extension of the R1-zero approach, which enables the usage of low parameter-count Large Language Models (LLMs) in the robotic domain. The R1-Zero approach was originally developed to enable mathematical reasoning in LLMs using static datasets. We extend it to the robotics domain through integration in a closed-loop Reinforcement Learning (RL) framework. This extension enhances reasoning in Embodied Artificial Intelligence (Embodied AI) settings without relying solely on distillation of large models through Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT). We show that small-scale LLMs can achieve effective reasoning performance by learning through closed-loop interaction with their environment, which enables tasks that previously required significantly larger models. In an autonomous driving setting, a performance gain of 20.2%-points over the SFT-based baseline is observed with a Qwen2.5-1.5B model. Using the proposed training procedure, Qwen2.5-3B achieves a 63.3% control adaptability score, surpassing the 58.5% obtained by the much larger, cloud-bound GPT-4o. These results highlight that practical, on-board deployment of small LLMs is not only feasible but can outperform larger models if trained through environmental feedback, underscoring the importance of an interactive learning framework for robotic Embodied AI, one grounded in practical experience rather than static supervision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03238v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liam Boyle, Nicolas Baumann, Paviththiren Sivasothilingam, Michele Magno, Luca Benini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Robots to Autonomously Search Dynamic Cluttered Post-Disaster Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robots will bring search and rescue (SaR) in disaster response to another level, in case they can autonomously take over dangerous SaR tasks from humans. A main challenge for autonomous SaR robots is to safely navigate in cluttered environments with uncertainties, while avoiding static and moving obstacles. We propose an integrated control framework for SaR robots in dynamic, uncertain environments, including a computationally efficient heuristic motion planning system that provides a nominal (assuming there are no uncertainties) collision-free trajectory for SaR robots and a robust motion tracking system that steers the robot to track this reference trajectory, taking into account the impact of uncertainties. The control architecture guarantees a balanced trade-off among various SaR objectives, while handling the hard constraints, including safety. The results of various computer-based simulations, presented in this paper, showed significant out-performance (of up to 42.3%) of the proposed integrated control architecture compared to two commonly used state-of-the-art methods (Rapidly-exploring Random Tree and Artificial Potential Function) in reaching targets (e.g., trapped victims in SaR) safely, collision-free, and in the shortest possible time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03283v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karlo Rado, Mirko Baglioni, Anahita Jamshidnejad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Discrete-Time Gaussian Process Mixtures for Robot Policy Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Mixture of Discrete-time Gaussian Processes (MiDiGap), a novel approach for flexible policy representation and imitation learning in robot manipulation. MiDiGap enables learning from as few as five demonstrations using only camera observations and generalizes across a wide range of challenging tasks. It excels at long-horizon behaviors such as making coffee, highly constrained motions such as opening doors, dynamic actions such as scooping with a spatula, and multimodal tasks such as hanging a mug. MiDiGap learns these tasks on a CPU in less than a minute and scales linearly to large datasets. We also develop a rich suite of tools for inference-time steering using evidence such as collision signals and robot kinematic constraints. This steering enables novel generalization capabilities, including obstacle avoidance and cross-embodiment policy transfer. MiDiGap achieves state-of-the-art performance on diverse few-shot manipulation benchmarks. On constrained RLBench tasks, it improves policy success by 76 percentage points and reduces trajectory cost by 67%. On multimodal tasks, it improves policy success by 48 percentage points and increases sample efficiency by a factor of 20. In cross-embodiment transfer, it more than doubles policy success. We make the code publicly available at https://midigap.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03296v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Ole von Hartz, Adrian R\"ofer, Joschka Boedecker, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Miniature multihole airflow sensor for lightweight aircraft over wide speed and angular range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An aircraft's airspeed, angle of attack, and angle of side slip are crucial to its safety, especially when flying close to the stall regime. Various solutions exist, including pitot tubes, angular vanes, and multihole pressure probes. However, current sensors are either too heavy (&gt;30 g) or require large airspeeds (&gt;20 m/s), making them unsuitable for small uncrewed aerial vehicles. We propose a novel multihole pressure probe, integrating sensing electronics in a single-component structure, resulting in a mechanically robust and lightweight sensor (9 g), which we released to the public domain. Since there is no consensus on two critical design parameters, tip shape (conical vs spherical) and hole spacing (distance between holes), we provide a study on measurement accuracy and noise generation using wind tunnel experiments. The sensor is calibrated using a multivariate polynomial regression model over an airspeed range of 3-27 m/s and an angle of attack/sideslip range of +-35{\deg}, achieving a mean absolute error of 0.44 m/s and 0.16{\deg}. Finally, we validated the sensor in outdoor flights near the stall regime. Our probe enabled accurate estimations of airspeed, angle of attack and sideslip during different acrobatic manoeuvres. Due to its size and weight, this sensor will enable safe flight for lightweight, uncrewed aerial vehicles flying at low speeds close to the stall regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03331v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Stuber, Simon Jeger, Raphael Zufferey, Dario Floreano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RIFT: Closed-Loop RL Fine-Tuning for Realistic and Controllable Traffic Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving both realism and controllability in interactive closed-loop traffic simulation remains a key challenge in autonomous driving. Data-driven simulation methods reproduce realistic trajectories but suffer from covariate shift in closed-loop deployment, compounded by simplified dynamics models that further reduce reliability. Conversely, physics-based simulation methods enhance reliable and controllable closed-loop interactions but often lack expert demonstrations, compromising realism. To address these challenges, we introduce a dual-stage AV-centered simulation framework that conducts open-loop imitation learning pre-training in a data-driven simulator to capture trajectory-level realism and multimodality, followed by closed-loop reinforcement learning fine-tuning in a physics-based simulator to enhance controllability and mitigate covariate shift. In the fine-tuning stage, we propose RIFT, a simple yet effective closed-loop RL fine-tuning strategy that preserves the trajectory-level multimodality through a GRPO-style group-relative advantage formulation, while enhancing controllability and training stability by replacing KL regularization with the dual-clip mechanism. Extensive experiments demonstrate that RIFT significantly improves the realism and controllability of generated traffic scenarios, providing a robust platform for evaluating autonomous vehicle performance in diverse and interactive scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03344v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keyu Chen, Wenchao Sun, Hao Cheng, Sifa Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Reinforcement Learning Control using Conservative Soft Actor-Critic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) has shown great potential in complex control tasks, particularly when combined with deep neural networks within the Actor-Critic (AC) framework. However, in practical applications, balancing exploration, learning stability, and sample efficiency remains a significant challenge. Traditional methods such as Soft Actor-Critic (SAC) and Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) address these issues by incorporating entropy or relative entropy regularization, but often face problems of instability and low sample efficiency. In this paper, we propose the Conservative Soft Actor-Critic (CSAC) algorithm, which seamlessly integrates entropy and relative entropy regularization within the AC framework. CSAC improves exploration through entropy regularization while avoiding overly aggressive policy updates with the use of relative entropy regularization. Evaluations on benchmark tasks and real-world robotic simulations demonstrate that CSAC offers significant improvements in stability and efficiency over existing methods. These findings suggest that CSAC provides strong robustness and application potential in control tasks under dynamic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03356v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyi Yuan, Zhiwei Shang, Wenjun Huang, Yunduan Cui, Di Chen, Meixin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Close-Fitting Dressing Assistance Based on State Estimation of Feet and Garments with Semantic-based Visual Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the population continues to age, a shortage of caregivers is expected in the future. Dressing assistance, in particular, is crucial for opportunities for social participation. Especially dressing close-fitting garments, such as socks, remains challenging due to the need for fine force adjustments to handle the friction or snagging against the skin, while considering the shape and position of the garment. This study introduces a method uses multi-modal information including not only robot's camera images, joint angles, joint torques, but also tactile forces for proper force interaction that can adapt to individual differences in humans. Furthermore, by introducing semantic information based on object concepts, rather than relying solely on RGB data, it can be generalized to unseen feet and background. In addition, incorporating depth data helps infer relative spatial relationship between the sock and the foot. To validate its capability for semantic object conceptualization and to ensure safety, training data were collected using a mannequin, and subsequent experiments were conducted with human subjects. In experiments, the robot successfully adapted to previously unseen human feet and was able to put socks on 10 participants, achieving a higher success rate than Action Chunking with Transformer and Diffusion Policy. These results demonstrate that the proposed model can estimate the state of both the garment and the foot, enabling precise dressing assistance for close-fitting garments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03400v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuma Tsukakoshi, Tamon Miyake, Tetsuya Ogata, Yushi Wang, Takumi Akaishi, Shigeki Sugano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AquaticVision: Benchmarking Visual SLAM in Underwater Environment with Events and Frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many underwater applications, such as offshore asset inspections, rely on visual inspection and detailed 3D reconstruction. Recent advancements in underwater visual SLAM systems for aquatic environments have garnered significant attention in marine robotics research. However, existing underwater visual SLAM datasets often lack groundtruth trajectory data, making it difficult to objectively compare the performance of different SLAM algorithms based solely on qualitative results or COLMAP reconstruction. In this paper, we present a novel underwater dataset that includes ground truth trajectory data obtained using a motion capture system. Additionally, for the first time, we release visual data that includes both events and frames for benchmarking underwater visual positioning. By providing event camera data, we aim to facilitate the development of more robust and advanced underwater visual SLAM algorithms. The use of event cameras can help mitigate challenges posed by extremely low light or hazy underwater conditions. The webpage of our dataset is https://sites.google.com/view/aquaticvision-lias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03448v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Peng, Yuze Hong, Ziyang Hong, Apple Pui-Yi Chui, Junfeng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LogisticsVLN: Vision-Language Navigation For Low-Altitude Terminal Delivery Based on Agentic UAVs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growing demand for intelligent logistics, particularly fine-grained terminal delivery, underscores the need for autonomous UAV (Unmanned Aerial Vehicle)-based delivery systems. However, most existing last-mile delivery studies rely on ground robots, while current UAV-based Vision-Language Navigation (VLN) tasks primarily focus on coarse-grained, long-range goals, making them unsuitable for precise terminal delivery. To bridge this gap, we propose LogisticsVLN, a scalable aerial delivery system built on multimodal large language models (MLLMs) for autonomous terminal delivery. LogisticsVLN integrates lightweight Large Language Models (LLMs) and Visual-Language Models (VLMs) in a modular pipeline for request understanding, floor localization, object detection, and action-decision making. To support research and evaluation in this new setting, we construct the Vision-Language Delivery (VLD) dataset within the CARLA simulator. Experimental results on the VLD dataset showcase the feasibility of the LogisticsVLN system. In addition, we conduct subtask-level evaluations of each module of our system, offering valuable insights for improving the robustness and real-world deployment of foundation model-based vision-language delivery systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03460v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyuan Zhang, Yonglin Tian, Fei Lin, Yue Liu, Jing Ma, Korn\'elia S\'ara Szatm\'ary, Fei-Yue Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task Reconstruction and Extrapolation for $\pi_0$ using Text Latent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-language-action models (VLAs) often achieve high performance on demonstrated tasks but struggle significantly when required to extrapolate, combining skills learned from different tasks in novel ways. For instance, VLAs might successfully put the cream cheese in the bowl and put the bowl on top of the cabinet, yet still fail to put the cream cheese on top of the cabinet. In this work, we demonstrate that behaviors from distinct tasks can be effectively recombined by manipulating the VLA's internal representations at inference time. Concretely, we identify the text latent by averaging the text tokens' hidden states across all demonstrated trajectories for a specific base task. For executing an extrapolated task, we can temporally interpolate the text latent of the two base tasks and add it back to the text hidden states, so sub-behaviors from the two tasks will be activated sequentially. We evaluate this approach using the newly created libero-ood benchmark, featuring 20 tasks extrapolated from standard LIBERO suites. The results on libero-ood show that all SOTA VLAs achieve &lt; 15% success rate, while $\pi0$ with text latent interpolation reaches an 83% success rate. Further qualitative analysis reveals a tendency for VLAs to exhibit spatial overfitting, mapping object names to demonstrated locations rather than achieving genuine object and goal understanding. Additionally, we find that decoding the text latent yields human-unreadable prompts that can nevertheless instruct the VLA to achieve a 70% success rate on standard LIBERO suites, enabling private instruction or backdoor attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03500v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quanyi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Action Generation based on Action Field for Robotic Garment Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Garment manipulation using robotic systems is a challenging task due to the diverse shapes and deformable nature of fabric. In this paper, we propose a novel method for robotic garment manipulation that significantly improves the accuracy while reducing computational time compared to previous approaches. Our method features an action generator that directly interprets scene images and generates pixel-wise end-effector action vectors using a neural network. The network also predicts a manipulation score map that ranks potential actions, allowing the system to select the most effective action. Extensive simulation experiments demonstrate that our method achieves higher unfolding and alignment performances and faster computation time than previous approaches. Real-world experiments show that the proposed method generalizes well to different garment types and successfully flattens garments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03537v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hu Cheng, Fuyuki Tokuda, Kazuhiro Kosuge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal-LiDAR Fusion for Robust Tunnel Localization in GNSS-Denied and Low-Visibility Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite significant progress in autonomous navigation, a critical gap remains in ensuring reliable localization in hazardous environments such as tunnels, urban disaster zones, and underground structures. Tunnels present a uniquely difficult scenario: they are not only prone to GNSS signal loss, but also provide little features for visual localization due to their repetitive walls and poor lighting. These conditions degrade conventional vision-based and LiDAR-based systems, which rely on distinguishable environmental features. To address this, we propose a novel sensor fusion framework that integrates a thermal camera with a LiDAR to enable robust localization in tunnels and other perceptually degraded environments. The thermal camera provides resilience in low-light or smoke conditions, while the LiDAR delivers precise depth perception and structural awareness. By combining these sensors, our framework ensures continuous and accurate localization across diverse and dynamic environments. We use an Extended Kalman Filter (EKF) to fuse multi-sensor inputs, and leverages visual odometry and SLAM (Simultaneous Localization and Mapping) techniques to process the sensor data, enabling robust motion estimation and mapping even in GNSS-denied environments. This fusion of sensor modalities not only enhances system resilience but also provides a scalable solution for cyber-physical systems in connected and autonomous vehicles (CAVs). To validate the framework, we conduct tests in a tunnel environment, simulating sensor degradation and visibility challenges. The results demonstrate that our method sustains accurate localization where standard approaches deteriorate due to the tunnels featureless geometry. The frameworks versatility makes it a promising solution for autonomous vehicles, inspection robots, and other cyber-physical systems operating in constrained, perceptually poor environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03565v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Schichler, Karin Festl, Selim Solmaz, Daniel Watzenig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-reasoning Using Attention Maps and Its Applications in Cloud Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03587v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metareasoning, a branch of AI, focuses on reasoning about reasons. It has the potential to enhance robots' decision-making processes in unexpected situations. However, the concept has largely been confined to theoretical discussions and case-by-case investigations, lacking general and practical solutions when the Value of Computation (VoC) is undefined, which is common in unexpected situations. In this work, we propose a revised meta-reasoning framework that significantly improves the scalability of the original approach in unexpected situations. This is achieved by incorporating semantic attention maps and unsupervised 'attention' updates into the metareasoning processes. To accommodate environmental dynamics, 'lines of thought' are used to bridge context-specific objects with abstracted attentions, while meta-information is monitored and controlled at the meta-level for effective reasoning. The practicality of the proposed approach is demonstrated through cloud robots deployed in real-world scenarios, showing improved performance and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03587v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Lendinez, Renxi Qiu, Lanfranco Zanzi, Dayou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboOS: A Hierarchical Embodied Framework for Cross-Embodiment and Multi-Agent Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dawn of embodied intelligence has ushered in an unprecedented imperative for resilient, cognition-enabled multi-agent collaboration across next-generation ecosystems, revolutionizing paradigms in autonomous manufacturing, adaptive service robotics, and cyber-physical production architectures. However, current robotic systems face significant limitations, such as limited cross-embodiment adaptability, inefficient task scheduling, and insufficient dynamic error correction. While End-to-end VLA models demonstrate inadequate long-horizon planning and task generalization, hierarchical VLA models suffer from a lack of cross-embodiment and multi-agent coordination capabilities. To address these challenges, we introduce RoboOS, the first open-source embodied system built on a Brain-Cerebellum hierarchical architecture, enabling a paradigm shift from single-agent to multi-agent intelligence. Specifically, RoboOS consists of three key components: (1) Embodied Brain Model (RoboBrain), a MLLM designed for global perception and high-level decision-making; (2) Cerebellum Skill Library, a modular, plug-and-play toolkit that facilitates seamless execution of multiple skills; and (3) Real-Time Shared Memory, a spatiotemporal synchronization mechanism for coordinating multi-agent states. By integrating hierarchical information flow, RoboOS bridges Embodied Brain and Cerebellum Skill Library, facilitating robust planning, scheduling, and error correction for long-horizon tasks, while ensuring efficient multi-agent collaboration through Real-Time Shared Memory. Furthermore, we enhance edge-cloud communication and cloud-based distributed inference to facilitate high-frequency interactions and enable scalable deployment. Extensive real-world experiments across various scenarios, demonstrate RoboOS's versatility in supporting heterogeneous embodiments. Project website: https://github.com/FlagOpen/RoboOS</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03673v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huajie Tan, Xiaoshuai Hao, Minglan Lin, Pengwei Wang, Yaoxu Lyu, Mingyu Cao, Zhongyuan Wang, Shanghang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstrating ViSafe: Vision-enabled Safety for High-speed Detect and Avoid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assured safe-separation is essential for achieving seamless high-density operation of airborne vehicles in a shared airspace. To equip resource-constrained aerial systems with this safety-critical capability, we present ViSafe, a high-speed vision-only airborne collision avoidance system. ViSafe offers a full-stack solution to the Detect and Avoid (DAA) problem by tightly integrating a learning-based edge-AI framework with a custom multi-camera hardware prototype designed under SWaP-C constraints. By leveraging perceptual input-focused control barrier functions (CBF) to design, encode, and enforce safety thresholds, ViSafe can provide provably safe runtime guarantees for self-separation in high-speed aerial operations. We evaluate ViSafe's performance through an extensive test campaign involving both simulated digital twins and real-world flight scenarios. By independently varying agent types, closure rates, interaction geometries, and environmental conditions (e.g., weather and lighting), we demonstrate that ViSafe consistently ensures self-separation across diverse scenarios. In first-of-its-kind real-world high-speed collision avoidance tests with closure rates reaching 144 km/h, ViSafe sets a new benchmark for vision-only autonomous collision avoidance, establishing a new standard for safety in high-speed aerial navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03694v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parv Kapoor, Ian Higgins, Nikhil Keetha, Jay Patrikar, Brady Moon, Zelin Ye, Yao He, Ivan Cisneros, Yaoyu Hu, Changliu Liu, Eunsuk Kang, Sebastian Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frenet Corridor Planner: An Optimal Local Path Planning Framework for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the requirements for effectiveness and efficiency, path-speed decomposition-based trajectory planning methods have widely been adopted for autonomous driving applications. While a global route can be pre-computed offline, real-time generation of adaptive local paths remains crucial. Therefore, we present the Frenet Corridor Planner (FCP), an optimization-based local path planning strategy for autonomous driving that ensures smooth and safe navigation around obstacles. Modeling the vehicles as safety-augmented bounding boxes and pedestrians as convex hulls in the Frenet space, our approach defines a drivable corridor by determining the appropriate deviation side for static obstacles. Thereafter, a modified space-domain bicycle kinematics model enables path optimization for smoothness, boundary clearance, and dynamic obstacle risk minimization. The optimized path is then passed to a speed planner to generate the final trajectory. We validate FCP through extensive simulations and real-world hardware experiments, demonstrating its efficiency and effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03695v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faizan M. Tariq, Zheng-Hang Yeh, Avinash Singh, David Isele, Sangjae Bae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Supervised Learning for Robotic Leaf Manipulation: A Hybrid Geometric-Neural Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Automating leaf manipulation in agricultural settings faces significant challenges, including the variability of plant morphologies and deformable leaves. We propose a novel hybrid geometric-neural approach for autonomous leaf grasping that combines traditional computer vision with neural networks through self-supervised learning. Our method integrates YOLOv8 for instance segmentation and RAFT-Stereo for 3D depth estimation to build rich leaf representations, which feed into both a geometric feature scoring pipeline and a neural refinement module (GraspPointCNN). The key innovation is our confidence-weighted fusion mechanism that dynamically balances the contribution of each approach based on prediction certainty. Our self-supervised framework uses the geometric pipeline as an expert teacher to automatically generate training data. Experiments demonstrate that our approach achieves an 88.0% success rate in controlled environments and 84.7% in real greenhouse conditions, significantly outperforming both purely geometric (75.3%) and neural (60.2%) methods. This work establishes a new paradigm for agricultural robotics where domain expertise is seamlessly integrated with machine learning capabilities, providing a foundation for fully automated crop monitoring systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03702v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srecharan Selvam, Abhishesh Silwal, George Kanter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Optimization and Program Search using Language Models for Task and Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intelligent interaction with the real world requires robotic agents to jointly reason over high-level plans and low-level controls. Task and motion planning (TAMP) addresses this by combining symbolic planning and continuous trajectory generation. Recently, foundation model approaches to TAMP have presented impressive results, including fast planning times and the execution of natural language instructions. Yet, the optimal interface between high-level planning and low-level motion generation remains an open question: prior approaches are limited by either too much abstraction (e.g., chaining simplified skill primitives) or a lack thereof (e.g., direct joint angle prediction). Our method introduces a novel technique employing a form of meta-optimization to address these issues by: (i) using program search over trajectory optimization problems as an interface between a foundation model and robot control, and (ii) leveraging a zero-order method to optimize numerical parameters in the foundation model output. Results on challenging object manipulation and drawing tasks confirm that our proposed method improves over prior TAMP approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03725v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Shcherba, Eckart Cobo-Briesewitz, Cornelius V. Braun, Marc Toussaint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyRoki: A Modular Toolkit for Robot Kinematic Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robot motion can have many goals. Depending on the task, we might optimize for pose error, speed, collision, or similarity to a human demonstration. Motivated by this, we present PyRoki: a modular, extensible, and cross-platform toolkit for solving kinematic optimization problems. PyRoki couples an interface for specifying kinematic variables and costs with an efficient nonlinear least squares optimizer. Unlike existing tools, it is also cross-platform: optimization runs natively on CPU, GPU, and TPU. In this paper, we present (i) the design and implementation of PyRoki, (ii) motion retargeting and planning case studies that highlight the advantages of PyRoki's modularity, and (iii) optimization benchmarking, where PyRoki can be 1.4-1.7x faster and converges to lower errors than cuRobo, an existing GPU-accelerated inverse kinematics library.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03728v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chung Min Kim, Brent Yi, Hongsuk Choi, Yi Ma, Ken Goldberg, Angjoo Kanazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Imitation Enables Contextual Humanoid Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03729v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How can we teach humanoids to climb staircases and sit on chairs using the surrounding environment context? Arguably, the simplest way is to just show them-casually capture a human motion video and feed it to humanoids. We introduce VIDEOMIMIC, a real-to-sim-to-real pipeline that mines everyday videos, jointly reconstructs the humans and the environment, and produces whole-body control policies for humanoid robots that perform the corresponding skills. We demonstrate the results of our pipeline on real humanoid robots, showing robust, repeatable contextual control such as staircase ascents and descents, sitting and standing from chairs and benches, as well as other dynamic whole-body skills-all from a single policy, conditioned on the environment and global root commands. VIDEOMIMIC offers a scalable path towards teaching humanoids to operate in diverse real-world environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03729v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Allshire, Hongsuk Choi, Junyi Zhang, David McAllister, Anthony Zhang, Chung Min Kim, Trevor Darrell, Pieter Abbeel, Jitendra Malik, Angjoo Kanazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMO: Adaptive Motion Optimization for Hyper-Dexterous Humanoid Whole-Body Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Humanoid robots derive much of their dexterity from hyper-dexterous whole-body movements, enabling tasks that require a large operational workspace: such as picking objects off the ground. However, achieving these capabilities on real humanoids remains challenging due to their high degrees of freedom (DoF) and nonlinear dynamics. We propose Adaptive Motion Optimization (AMO), a framework that integrates sim-to-real reinforcement learning (RL) with trajectory optimization for real-time, adaptive whole-body control. To mitigate distribution bias in motion imitation RL, we construct a hybrid AMO dataset and train a network capable of robust, on-demand adaptation to potentially O.O.D. commands. We validate AMO in simulation and on a 29-DoF Unitree G1 humanoid robot, demonstrating superior stability and an expanded workspace compared to strong baselines. Finally, we show that AMO's consistent performance supports autonomous task execution via imitation learning, underscoring the system's versatility and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03738v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialong Li, Xuxin Cheng, Tianshu Huang, Shiqi Yang, Ri-Zhao Qiu, Xiaolong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of Coordination Strategies for Underground Automated Vehicle Fleets in Mixed Traffic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02842v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the efficiency and safety outcomes of implementing different adaptive coordination models for automated vehicle (AV) fleets, managed by a centralized coordinator that dynamically responds to human-controlled vehicle behavior. The simulated scenarios replicate an underground mining environment characterized by narrow tunnels with limited connectivity. To address the unique challenges of such settings, we propose a novel metric - Path Overlap Density (POD) - to predict efficiency and potentially the safety performance of AV fleets. The study also explores the impact of map features on AV fleets performance. The results demonstrate that both AV fleet coordination strategies and underground tunnel network characteristics significantly influence overall system performance. While map features are critical for optimizing efficiency, adaptive coordination strategies are essential for ensuring safe operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02842v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olga Mironenko, Hadi Banaee, Amy Loutfi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Task-aware Fault Detection, Identification For On-Orbit Multi-Spacecraft Collaborative Inspection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03088v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a global-to-local task-aware fault detection and identification algorithm to detect failures in a multi-spacecraft system performing a collaborative inspection (referred to as global) task. The inspection task is encoded as a cost functional $\costH$ that informs global (task allocation and assignment) and local (agent-level) decision-making. The metric $\costH$ is a function of the inspection sensor model, and the agent full-pose. We use the cost functional $\costH$ to design a metric that compares the expected and actual performance to detect the faulty agent using a threshold. We use higher-order cost gradients $\costH$ to derive a new metric to identify the type of fault, including task-specific sensor fault, an agent-level actuator, and sensor faults. Furthermore, we propose an approach to design adaptive thresholds for each fault mentioned above to incorporate the time dependence of the inspection task. We demonstrate the efficacy of the proposed method empirically, by simulating and detecting faults (such as inspection sensor faults, actuators, and sensor faults) in a low-Earth orbit collaborative spacecraft inspection task using the metrics and the threshold designed using the global task cost $\costH$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03088v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshita Gupta, Yashwanth Kumar Nakka, Changrak Choi, Amir Rahmani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RADE: Learning Risk-Adjustable Driving Environment via Multi-Agent Conditional Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03178v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generating safety-critical scenarios in high-fidelity simulations offers a promising and cost-effective approach for efficient testing of autonomous vehicles. Existing methods typically rely on manipulating a single vehicle's trajectory through sophisticated designed objectives to induce adversarial interactions, often at the cost of realism and scalability. In this work, we propose the Risk-Adjustable Driving Environment (RADE), a simulation framework that generates statistically realistic and risk-adjustable traffic scenes. Built upon a multi-agent diffusion architecture, RADE jointly models the behavior of all agents in the environment and conditions their trajectories on a surrogate risk measure. Unlike traditional adversarial methods, RADE learns risk-conditioned behaviors directly from data, preserving naturalistic multi-agent interactions with controllable risk levels. To ensure physical plausibility, we incorporate a tokenized dynamics check module that efficiently filters generated trajectories using a motion vocabulary. We validate RADE on the real-world rounD dataset, demonstrating that it preserves statistical realism across varying risk levels and naturally increases the likelihood of safety-critical events as the desired risk level grows up. Our results highlight RADE's potential as a scalable and realistic tool for AV safety evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03178v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Wang, Xintao Yan, Yao Mu, Haowei Sun, Zhong Cao, Henry X. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Predictive Fuzzy Control: A Hierarchical Multi-Agent Control Architecture for Outdoor Search-and-Rescue Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous robots deployed in unknown search-and-rescue (SaR) environments can significantly improve the efficiency of the mission by assisting in fast localisation and rescue of the trapped victims. We propose a novel integrated hierarchical control architecture, called model predictive fuzzy control (MPFC), for autonomous mission planning of multi-robot SaR systems that should efficiently map an unknown environment: We combine model predictive control (MPC) and fuzzy logic control (FLC), where the robots are locally controlled by computationally efficient FLC controllers, and the parameters of these local controllers are tuned via a centralised MPC controller, in a regular or event-triggered manner. The proposed architecture provides three main advantages: (1) The control decisions are made by the FLC controllers, thus the real-time computation time is affordable. (2) The centralised MPC controller optimises the performance criteria with a global and predictive vision of the system dynamics, and updates the parameters of the FLC controllers accordingly. (3) FLC controllers are heuristic by nature and thus do not take into account optimality in their decisions, while the tuned parameters via the MPC controller can indirectly incorporate some level of optimality in local decisions of the robots. A simulation environment for victim detection in a disaster environment was designed in MATLAB using discrete, 2-D grid-based models. While being comparable from the point of computational efficiency, the integrated MPFC architecture improves the performance of the multi-robot SaR system compared to decentralised FLC controllers. Moreover, the performance of MPFC is comparable to the performance of centralised MPC for path planning of SaR robots, whereas MPFC requires significantly less computational resources, since the number of the optimisation variables in the control problem are reduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03257v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Craig Maxwell, Mirko Baglioni, Anahita Jamshidnejad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OccCylindrical: Multi-Modal Fusion with Cylindrical Representation for 3D Semantic Occupancy Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The safe operation of autonomous vehicles (AVs) is highly dependent on their understanding of the surroundings. For this, the task of 3D semantic occupancy prediction divides the space around the sensors into voxels, and labels each voxel with both occupancy and semantic information. Recent perception models have used multisensor fusion to perform this task. However, existing multisensor fusion-based approaches focus mainly on using sensor information in the Cartesian coordinate system. This ignores the distribution of the sensor readings, leading to a loss of fine-grained details and performance degradation. In this paper, we propose OccCylindrical that merges and refines the different modality features under cylindrical coordinates. Our method preserves more fine-grained geometry detail that leads to better performance. Extensive experiments conducted on the nuScenes dataset, including challenging rainy and nighttime scenarios, confirm our approach's effectiveness and state-of-the-art performance. The code will be available at: https://github.com/DanielMing123/OccCylindrical</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03284v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenxing Ming, Julie Stephany Berrio, Mao Shan, Yaoqi Huang, Hongyu Lyu, Nguyen Hoang Khoi Tran, Tzu-Yun Tseng, Stewart Worrall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capability-Driven Skill Generation with LLMs: A RAG-Based Approach for Reusing Existing Libraries and Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03295v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern automation systems increasingly rely on modular architectures, with capabilities and skills as one solution approach. Capabilities define the functions of resources in a machine-readable form and skills provide the concrete implementations that realize those capabilities. However, the development of a skill implementation conforming to a corresponding capability remains a time-consuming and challenging task. In this paper, we present a method that treats capabilities as contracts for skill implementations and leverages large language models to generate executable code based on natural language user input. A key feature of our approach is the integration of existing software libraries and interface technologies, enabling the generation of skill implementations across different target languages. We introduce a framework that allows users to incorporate their own libraries and resource interfaces into the code generation process through a retrieval-augmented generation architecture. The proposed method is evaluated using an autonomous mobile robot controlled via Python and ROS 2, demonstrating the feasibility and flexibility of the approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03295v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Miguel Vieira da Silva, Aljosha K\"ocher, Nicolas K\"onig, Felix Gehlhoff, Alexander Fay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiftFeat: 3D Geometry-Aware Local Feature Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Robust and efficient local feature matching plays a crucial role in applications such as SLAM and visual localization for robotics. Despite great progress, it is still very challenging to extract robust and discriminative visual features in scenarios with drastic lighting changes, low texture areas, or repetitive patterns. In this paper, we propose a new lightweight network called \textit{LiftFeat}, which lifts the robustness of raw descriptor by aggregating 3D geometric feature. Specifically, we first adopt a pre-trained monocular depth estimation model to generate pseudo surface normal label, supervising the extraction of 3D geometric feature in terms of predicted surface normal. We then design a 3D geometry-aware feature lifting module to fuse surface normal feature with raw 2D descriptor feature. Integrating such 3D geometric feature enhances the discriminative ability of 2D feature description in extreme conditions. Extensive experimental results on relative pose estimation, homography estimation, and visual localization tasks, demonstrate that our LiftFeat outperforms some lightweight state-of-the-art methods. Code will be released at : https://github.com/lyp-deeplearning/LiftFeat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03422v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yepeng Liu, Wenpeng Lai, Zhou Zhao, Yuxuan Xiong, Jinchi Zhu, Jun Cheng, Yongchao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Protozoa Optimizer (APO): A novel bio-inspired metaheuristic algorithm for engineering optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03512v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study proposes a novel artificial protozoa optimizer (APO) that is inspired by protozoa in nature. The APO mimics the survival mechanisms of protozoa by simulating their foraging, dormancy, and reproductive behaviors. The APO was mathematically modeled and implemented to perform the optimization processes of metaheuristic algorithms. The performance of the APO was verified via experimental simulations and compared with 32 state-of-the-art algorithms. Wilcoxon signed-rank test was performed for pairwise comparisons of the proposed APO with the state-of-the-art algorithms, and Friedman test was used for multiple comparisons. First, the APO was tested using 12 functions of the 2022 IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computation benchmark. Considering practicality, the proposed APO was used to solve five popular engineering design problems in a continuous space with constraints. Moreover, the APO was applied to solve a multilevel image segmentation task in a discrete space with constraints. The experiments confirmed that the APO could provide highly competitive results for optimization problems. The source codes of Artificial Protozoa Optimizer are publicly available at https://seyedalimirjalili.com/projects and https://ww2.mathworks.cn/matlabcentral/fileexchange/162656-artificial-protozoa-optimizer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03512v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.knosys.2024.111737</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xiaopeng Wang, Vaclav Snasel, Seyedali Mirjalili, Jeng-Shyang Pan, Lingping Kong, Hisham A. Shehadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Panoramic Out-of-Distribution Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03539v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Panoramic imaging enables capturing 360{\deg} images with an ultra-wide Field-of-View (FoV) for dense omnidirectional perception. However, current panoramic semantic segmentation methods fail to identify outliers, and pinhole Out-of-distribution Segmentation (OoS) models perform unsatisfactorily in the panoramic domain due to background clutter and pixel distortions. To address these issues, we introduce a new task, Panoramic Out-of-distribution Segmentation (PanOoS), achieving OoS for panoramas. Furthermore, we propose the first solution, POS, which adapts to the characteristics of panoramic images through text-guided prompt distribution learning. Specifically, POS integrates a disentanglement strategy designed to materialize the cross-domain generalization capability of CLIP. The proposed Prompt-based Restoration Attention (PRA) optimizes semantic decoding by prompt guidance and self-adaptive correction, while Bilevel Prompt Distribution Learning (BPDL) refines the manifold of per-pixel mask embeddings via semantic prototype supervision. Besides, to compensate for the scarcity of PanOoS datasets, we establish two benchmarks: DenseOoS, which features diverse outliers in complex environments, and QuadOoS, captured by a quadruped robot with a panoramic annular lens system. Extensive experiments demonstrate superior performance of POS, with AuPRC improving by 34.25% and FPR95 decreasing by 21.42% on DenseOoS, outperforming state-of-the-art pinhole-OoS methods. Moreover, POS achieves leading closed-set segmentation capabilities. Code and datasets will be available at https://github.com/MengfeiD/PanOoS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03539v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengfei Duan, Kailun Yang, Yuheng Zhang, Yihong Cao, Fei Teng, Kai Luo, Jiaming Zhang, Zhiyong Li, Shutao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching Distance and Geometric Distribution Aided Learning Multiview Point Cloud Registration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multiview point cloud registration plays a crucial role in robotics, automation, and computer vision fields. This paper concentrates on pose graph construction and motion synchronization within multiview registration. Previous methods for pose graph construction often pruned fully connected graphs or constructed sparse graph using global feature aggregated from local descriptors, which may not consistently yield reliable results. To identify dependable pairs for pose graph construction, we design a network model that extracts information from the matching distance between point cloud pairs. For motion synchronization, we propose another neural network model to calculate the absolute pose in a data-driven manner, rather than optimizing inaccurate handcrafted loss functions. Our model takes into account geometric distribution information and employs a modified attention mechanism to facilitate flexible and reliable feature interaction. Experimental results on diverse indoor and outdoor datasets confirm the effectiveness and generalizability of our approach. The source code is available at https://github.com/Shi-Qi-Li/MDGD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03692v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3455783</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shiqi Li, Jihua Zhu, Yifan Xie, Naiwen Hu, Di Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Cooperative Transportation System involving Multi-Aerial Robots with Variable Attachment Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.10575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.10575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cooperative transportation by multi-aerial robots has the potential to support various payloads and improve failsafe against dropping. Furthermore, changing the attachment positions of robots according payload characteristics increases the stability of transportation. However, there are almost no transportation systems capable of scaling to the payload weight and size and changing the optimal attachment positions. To address this issue, we propose a cooperative transportation system comprising autonomously executable software and suitable hardware, covering the entire process, from pre-takeoff setting to controlled flight. The proposed system decides the formation of the attachment positions by prioritizing controllability based on the center of gravity obtained from Bayesian estimations with robot pairs. We investigated the cooperative transportation of an unknown payload larger than that of whole carrier robots through numerical simulations. Furthermore, we performed cooperative transportation of an unknown payload (with a weight of about 3.2 kg and maximum length of 1.76 m) using eight robots. The proposed system was found to be versatile with regard to handling unknown payloads with different shapes and center-of-gravity positions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.10575v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/IROS51168.2021.9636145</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Koshi Oishi, Tomohiko Jimbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Transportation using Multiple Single-Rotor Robots and Decentralized Control for Unknown Payloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.01963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cooperative transportation via multiple aerial robots has the potential to support various payloads and reduce the chances of them being dropped. Furthermore, autonomously controlled robots render the system scalable with respect to the payload. In this study, a cooperative transportation system was developed using rigidly attached single-rotor robots, and a decentralized controller was proposed to guarantee asymptotic stability of the error dynamics for unknown strictly positive real systems. A feedback controller was used to transform unstable systems into strictly positive real ones considering the shared attachment positions. First, the cooperative transportation of unknown payloads with different shapes larger than the carrier robots was investigated via numerical simulations. Second, cooperative transportation of an unknown payload (with a weight of approximately 2.7 kg and maximum length of 1.6 m) was demonstrated using eight robots, even under robot failure. Finally, the proposed system was shown to be capable of carrying an unknown payload, even if the attachment positions were not shared, that is, even if asymptotic stability was not strictly guaranteed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.01963v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA46639.2022.9811768</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2022 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Koshi Oishi, Yasushi Amano, Tomohiko Jimbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scratch Team of Single-Rotor Robots and Decentralized Cooperative Transportation with Robot Failure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00705v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Achieving cooperative transportation by aerial robot teams ensures flexibility regarding payloads and robustness against failures, which has garnered significant attention in recent years. This study proposes a flexible decentralized controller for robots and the shapes of payloads in a cooperative transport task using multiple single-rotor robots. The proposed controller is robust to mass and center of mass (COM) fluctuations and robot failures. Moreover, it possesses asymptotic stability against dynamics errors. Additionally, the controller supports heterogeneous single-rotor robots. Thus, robots with different specifications and deterioration may be effectively utilized for cooperative transportation. This performance is particularly effective for robot reuse. To achieve the aforementioned performance, the controller consists of a parallel structure comprising two controllers: a feedback controller, which renders the system strictly positive real, and a nonlinear controller, which renders the object asymptotic to the target. First, we confirm cooperative transportation using 8 and 10 robots for two shapes through numerical simulation. Subsequently, the cooperative transportation of a rectangle payload (with a weight of approximately 3 kg and maximum length of 1.6 m) is demonstrated using a robot team consisting of three types of robots, even under robot failure and fluctuation in the COM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00705v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koshi Oishi, Yasushi Amano, Jimbo Tomohiko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-NavGPT: Multi-Robot Cooperative Visual Semantic Navigation Using Vision Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07937v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Visual target navigation is a critical capability for autonomous robots operating in unknown environments, particularly in human-robot interaction scenarios. While classical and learning-based methods have shown promise, most existing approaches lack common-sense reasoning and are typically designed for single-robot settings, leading to reduced efficiency and robustness in complex environments. To address these limitations, we introduce Co-NavGPT, a novel framework that integrates a Vision Language Model (VLM) as a global planner to enable common-sense multi-robot visual target navigation. Co-NavGPT aggregates sub-maps from multiple robots with diverse viewpoints into a unified global map, encoding robot states and frontier regions. The VLM uses this information to assign frontiers across the robots, facilitating coordinated and efficient exploration. Experiments on the Habitat-Matterport 3D (HM3D) demonstrate that Co-NavGPT outperforms existing baselines in terms of success rate and navigation efficiency, without requiring task-specific training. Ablation studies further confirm the importance of semantic priors from the VLM. We also validate the framework in real-world scenarios using quadrupedal robots. Supplementary video and code are available at: https://sites.google.com/view/co-navgpt2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07937v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bangguo Yu, Qihao Yuan, Kailai Li, Hamidreza Kasaei, Ming Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rule-Based Lloyd Algorithm for Multi-Robot Motion Planning and Control with Safety and Convergence Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19511v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a distributed rule-based Lloyd algorithm (RBL) for multi-robot motion planning and control. The main limitations of the basic Loyd-based algorithm (LB) concern deadlock issues and the failure to address dynamic constraints effectively. Our contribution is twofold. First, we show how RBL is able to provide safety and convergence to the goal region without relying on communication between robots, nor synchronization between the robots. We considered different dynamic constraints with control inputs saturation. Second, we show that the Lloyd-based algorithm (without rules) can be successfully used as a safety layer for learning-based approaches, leading to non-negligible benefits. We further prove the soundness, reliability, and scalability of RBL through extensive simulations, comparisons with the state of the art, and experimental validations on small-scale car-like robots, unicycle-like robots, omnidirectional robots, and aerial robots on the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19511v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Boldrer, Alvaro Serra-Gomez, Lorenzo Lyons, Vit Kratky, Javier Alonso-Mora, Laura Ferranti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Ask or Not To Ask: Human-in-the-loop Contextual Bandits with Applications in Robot-Assisted Feeding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06908v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robot-assisted bite acquisition involves picking up food items with varying shapes, compliance, sizes, and textures. Fully autonomous strategies may not generalize efficiently across this diversity. We propose leveraging feedback from the care recipient when encountering novel food items. However, frequent queries impose a workload on the user. We formulate human-in-the-loop bite acquisition within a contextual bandit framework and introduce LinUCB-QG, a method that selectively asks for help using a predictive model of querying workload based on query types and timings. This model is trained on data collected in an online study involving 14 participants with mobility limitations, 3 occupational therapists simulating physical limitations, and 89 participants without limitations. We demonstrate that our method better balances task performance and querying workload compared to autonomous and always-querying baselines and adjusts its querying behavior to account for higher workload in users with mobility limitations. We validate this through experiments in a simulated food dataset and a user study with 19 participants, including one with severe mobility limitations. Please check out our project website at: http://emprise.cs.cornell.edu/hilbiteacquisition/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06908v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohan Banerjee, Rajat Kumar Jenamani, Sidharth Vasudev, Amal Nanavati, Katherine Dimitropoulou, Sarah Dean, Tapomayukh Bhattacharjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensor-Based Distributionally Robust Control for Safe Robot Navigation in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18251v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel method for mobile robot navigation in dynamic, unknown environments, leveraging onboard sensing and distributionally robust optimization to impose probabilistic safety constraints. Our method introduces a distributionally robust control barrier function (DR-CBF) that directly integrates noisy sensor measurements and state estimates to define safety constraints. This approach is applicable to a wide range of control-affine dynamics, generalizable to robots with complex geometries, and capable of operating at real-time control frequencies. Coupled with a control Lyapunov function (CLF) for path following, the proposed CLF-DR-CBF control synthesis method achieves safe, robust, and efficient navigation in challenging environments. We demonstrate the effectiveness and robustness of our approach for safe autonomous navigation under uncertainty in simulations and real-world experiments with differential-drive robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18251v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kehan Long, Yinzhuang Yi, Zhirui Dai, Sylvia Herbert, Jorge Cort\'es, Nikolay Atanasov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Computation of Expectation Models for Commonsense Affordance Estimation on 3D Scene Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article studies the commonsense object affordance concept for enabling close-to-human task planning and task optimization of embodied robotic agents in urban environments. The focus of the object affordance is on reasoning how to effectively identify object's inherent utility during the task execution, which in this work is enabled through the analysis of contextual relations of sparse information of 3D scene graphs. The proposed framework develops a Correlation Information (CECI) model to learn probability distributions using a Graph Convolutional Network, allowing to extract the commonsense affordance for individual members of a semantic class. The overall framework was experimentally validated in a real-world indoor environment, showcasing the ability of the method to level with human commonsense. For a video of the article, showcasing the experimental demonstration, please refer to the following link: https://youtu.be/BDCMVx2GiQE</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05392v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario A. V. Saucedo, Nikolaos Stathoulopoulos, Akash Patel, Christoforos Kanellakis, George Nikolakopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adversarial and Reactive Traffic Entities for Behavior-Realistic Driving Simulation: A Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite advancements in perception and planning for autonomous vehicles (AVs), validating their performance remains a significant challenge. The deployment of planning algorithms in real-world environments is often ineffective due to discrepancies between simulations and real traffic conditions. Evaluating AVs planning algorithms in simulation typically involves replaying driving logs from recorded real-world traffic. However, entities replayed from offline data are not reactive, lack the ability to respond to arbitrary AV behavior, and cannot behave in an adversarial manner to test certain properties of the driving policy. Therefore, simulation with realistic and potentially adversarial entities represents a critical task for AV planning software validation. In this work, we aim to review current research efforts in the field of traffic simulation, focusing on the application of advanced techniques for modeling realistic and adversarial behaviors of traffic entities. The objective of this work is to categorize existing approaches based on the proposed classes of traffic entity behavior and scenario behavior control. Moreover, we collect traffic datasets and examine existing traffic simulations with respect to their employed default traffic entities. Finally, we identify challenges and open questions that hold potential for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14196v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Ransiek, Philipp Reis, Tobias Sch\"urmann, Eric Sax</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Metric-Semantic Mapping for Persistent Orchard Monitoring: Method and Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19786v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monitoring orchards at the individual tree or fruit level throughout the growth season is crucial for plant phenotyping and horticultural resource optimization, such as chemical use and yield estimation. We present a 4D spatio-temporal metric-semantic mapping system that integrates multi-session measurements to track fruit growth over time. Our approach combines a LiDAR-RGB fusion module for 3D fruit localization with a 4D fruit association method leveraging positional, visual, and topology information for improved data association precision. Evaluated on real orchard data, our method achieves a 96.9% fruit counting accuracy for 1,790 apples across 60 trees, a mean fruit size estimation error of 1.1 cm, and a 23.7% improvement in 4D data association precision over baselines. We publicly release a multimodal dataset covering five fruit species across their growth seasons at https://4d-metric-semantic-mapping.org/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19786v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiuzhou Lei, Ankit Prabhu, Xu Liu, Fernando Cladera, Mehrad Mortazavi, Reza Ehsani, Pratik Chaudhari, Vijay Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-order regularization dealing with ill-conditioned robot localization problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a high-order regularization method to solve the ill-conditioned problems in robot localization. Numerical solutions to robot localization problems are often unstable when the problems are ill-conditioned. A typical way to solve ill-conditioned problems is regularization, and a classical regularization method is the Tikhonov regularization. It is shown that the Tikhonov regularization is a low-order case of our method. We find that the proposed method is superior to the Tikhonov regularization in approximating some ill-conditioned inverse problems, such as some basic robot localization problems. The proposed method overcomes the over-smoothing problem in the Tikhonov regularization as it uses more than one term in the approximation of the matrix inverse, and an explanation for the over-smoothing of the Tikhonov regularization is given. Moreover, one a priori criterion, which improves the numerical stability of the ill-conditioned problem, is proposed to obtain an optimal regularization matrix. As most of the regularization solutions are biased, we also provide two bias-correction techniques for the proposed high-order regularization. The simulation and experimental results using an Ultra-Wideband sensor network in a 3D environment are discussed, demonstrating the performance of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01919v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/tro.2025.3562487</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xinghua Liu, Ming Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variable-Speed Teaching-Playback as Real-World Data Augmentation for Imitation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03252v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Because imitation learning relies on human demonstrations in hard-to-simulate settings, the inclusion of force control in this method has resulted in a shortage of training data, even with a simple change in speed. Although the field of data augmentation has addressed the lack of data, conventional methods of data augmentation for robot manipulation are limited to simulation-based methods or downsampling for position control. This paper proposes a novel method of data augmentation that is applicable to force control and preserves the advantages of real-world datasets. We applied teaching-playback at variable speeds as real-world data augmentation to increase both the quantity and quality of environmental reactions at variable speeds. An experiment was conducted on bilateral control-based imitation learning using a method of imitation learning equipped with position-force control. We evaluated the effect of real-world data augmentation on two tasks, pick-and-place and wiping, at variable speeds, each from two human demonstrations at fixed speed. The results showed a maximum 55% increase in success rate from a simple change in speed of real-world reactions and improved accuracy along the duration/frequency command by gathering environmental reactions at variable speeds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03252v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/01691864.2025.2497423</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nozomu Masuya, Hiroshi Sato, Koki Yamane, Takuya Kusume, Sho Sakaino, Toshiaki Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-Based Forklift Learning System Enabling Zero-Shot Sim2Real Without Real-World Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11503v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Forklifts are used extensively in various industrial settings and are in high demand for automation. In particular, counterbalance forklifts are highly versatile and employed in diverse scenarios. However, efforts to automate these processes are lacking, primarily owing to the absence of a safe and performance-verifiable development environment. This study proposes a learning system that combines a photorealistic digital learning environment with a 1/14-scale robotic forklift environment to address this challenge. Inspired by the training-based learning approach adopted by forklift operators, we employ an end-to-end vision-based deep reinforcement learning approach. The learning is conducted in a digitalized environment created from CAD data, making it safe and eliminating the need for real-world data. In addition, we safely validate the method in a physical setting utilizing a 1/14-scale robotic forklift with a configuration similar to that of a real forklift. We achieved a 60% success rate in pallet loading tasks in real experiments using a robotic forklift. Our approach demonstrates zero-shot sim2real with a simple method that does not require heuristic additions. This learning-based approach is considered a first step towards the automation of counterbalance forklifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11503v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koshi Oishi, Teruki Kato, Hiroya Makino, Seigo Ito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Multi-Robot Semantic Navigation Through Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Score Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18292v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding how humans cooperatively utilize semantic knowledge to explore unfamiliar environments and decide on navigation directions is critical for house service multi-robot systems. Previous methods primarily focused on single-robot centralized planning strategies, which severely limited exploration efficiency. Recent research has considered decentralized planning strategies for multiple robots, assigning separate planning models to each robot, but these approaches often overlook communication costs. In this work, we propose Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Co-Navigation (MCoCoNav), a modular approach that utilizes multimodal Chain-of-Thought to plan collaborative semantic navigation for multiple robots. MCoCoNav combines visual perception with Vision Language Models (VLMs) to evaluate exploration value through probabilistic scoring, thus reducing time costs and achieving stable outputs. Additionally, a global semantic map is used as a communication bridge, minimizing communication overhead while integrating observational results. Guided by scores that reflect exploration trends, robots utilize this map to assess whether to explore new frontier points or revisit history nodes. Experiments on HM3D_v0.2 and MP3D demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. Our code is available at https://github.com/FrankZxShen/MCoCoNav.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18292v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixuan Shen, Haonan Luo, Kexun Chen, Fengmao Lv, Tianrui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow-based Domain Randomization for Learning and Sequencing Robotic Skills</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Domain randomization in reinforcement learning is an established technique for increasing the robustness of control policies trained in simulation. By randomizing environment properties during training, the learned policy can become robust to uncertainties along the randomized dimensions. While the environment distribution is typically specified by hand, in this paper we investigate automatically discovering a sampling distribution via entropy-regularized reward maximization of a normalizing-flow-based neural sampling distribution. We show that this architecture is more flexible and provides greater robustness than existing approaches that learn simpler, parameterized sampling distributions, as demonstrated in six simulated and one real-world robotics domain. Lastly, we explore how these learned sampling distributions, combined with a privileged value function, can be used for out-of-distribution detection in an uncertainty-aware multi-step manipulation planner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01800v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Curtis, Eric Li, Michael Noseworthy, Nishad Gothoskar, Sachin Chitta, Hui Li, Leslie Pack Kaelbling, Nicole Carey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward-Based Collision-Free Algorithm for Trajectory Planning of Autonomous Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06149v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel mission planning algorithm for autonomous robots that selects an optimal waypoint sequence from a predefined set to maximize total reward while satisfying obstacle avoidance, state, input, derivative, mission time, and distance constraints. The formulation extends the prize-collecting traveling salesman problem. A tailored genetic algorithm evolves candidate solutions using a fitness function, crossover, and mutation, with constraint enforcement via a penalty method. Differential flatness and clothoid curves are employed to penalize infeasible trajectories efficiently, while the Euler spiral method ensures curvature-continuous trajectories with bounded curvature, enhancing dynamic feasibility and mitigating oscillations typical of minimum-jerk and snap parameterizations. Due to the discrete variable length optimization space, crossover is performed using a dynamic time-warping-based method and extended convex combination with projection. The algorithm's performance is validated through simulations and experiments with a ground vehicle, quadrotor, and quadruped, supported by benchmarking and time-complexity analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06149v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose D. Hoyos, Tianyu Zhou, Zehui Lu, Shaoshuai Mou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DEFT: Differentiable Branched Discrete Elastic Rods for Modeling Furcated DLOs in Real-Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15037v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomous wire harness assembly requires robots to manipulate complex branched cables with high precision and reliability. A key challenge in automating this process is predicting how these flexible and branched structures behave under manipulation. Without accurate predictions, it is difficult for robots to reliably plan or execute assembly operations. While existing research has made progress in modeling single-threaded Deformable Linear Objects (DLOs), extending these approaches to Branched Deformable Linear Objects (BDLOs) presents fundamental challenges. The junction points in BDLOs create complex force interactions and strain propagation patterns that cannot be adequately captured by simply connecting multiple single-DLO models. To address these challenges, this paper presents Differentiable discrete branched Elastic rods for modeling Furcated DLOs in real-Time (DEFT), a novel framework that combines a differentiable physics-based model with a learning framework to: 1) accurately model BDLO dynamics, including dynamic propagation at junction points and grasping in the middle of a BDLO, 2) achieve efficient computation for real-time inference, and 3) enable planning to demonstrate dexterous BDLO manipulation. A comprehensive series of real-world experiments demonstrates DEFT's efficacy in terms of accuracy, computational speed, and generalizability compared to state-of-the-art alternatives. Project page:https://roahmlab.github.io/DEFT/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15037v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yizhou Chen, Xiaoyue Wu, Yeheng Zong, Yuzhen Chen, Anran Li, Bohao Zhang, Ram Vasudevan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Configuration-Space Barriers for Manipulation Planning and Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04929v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Planning and control for high-dimensional robot manipulators in cluttered, dynamic environments require both computational efficiency and robust safety guarantees. Inspired by recent advances in learning configuration-space distance functions (CDFs) as robot body representations, we propose a unified framework for motion planning and control that formulates safety constraints as CDF barriers. A CDF barrier approximates the local free configuration space, substantially reducing the number of collision-checking operations during motion planning. However, learning a CDF barrier with a neural network and relying on online sensor observations introduce uncertainties that must be considered during control synthesis. To address this, we develop a distributionally robust CDF barrier formulation for control that explicitly accounts for modeling errors and sensor noise without assuming a known underlying distribution. Simulations and hardware experiments on a 6-DoF xArm manipulator show that our neural CDF barrier formulation enables efficient planning and robust real-time safe control in cluttered and dynamic environments, relying only on onboard point-cloud observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04929v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kehan Long, Ki Myung Brian Lee, Nikola Raicevic, Niyas Attasseri, Melvin Leok, Nikolay Atanasov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Imitation Learning Policy Better than Mine? Policy Comparison with Near-Optimal Stopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10966v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Imitation learning has enabled robots to perform complex, long-horizon tasks in challenging dexterous manipulation settings. As new methods are developed, they must be rigorously evaluated and compared against corresponding baselines through repeated evaluation trials. However, policy comparison is fundamentally constrained by a small feasible sample size (e.g., 10 or 50) due to significant human effort and limited inference throughput of policies. This paper proposes a novel statistical framework for rigorously comparing two policies in the small sample size regime. Prior work in statistical policy comparison relies on batch testing, which requires a fixed, pre-determined number of trials and lacks flexibility in adapting the sample size to the observed evaluation data. Furthermore, extending the test with additional trials risks inducing inadvertent p-hacking, undermining statistical assurances. In contrast, our proposed statistical test is sequential, allowing researchers to decide whether or not to run more trials based on intermediate results. This adaptively tailors the number of trials to the difficulty of the underlying comparison, saving significant time and effort without sacrificing probabilistic correctness. Extensive numerical simulation and real-world robot manipulation experiments show that our test achieves near-optimal stopping, letting researchers stop evaluation and make a decision in a near-minimal number of trials. Specifically, it reduces the number of evaluation trials by up to 37% as compared to state-of-the-art baselines, while preserving the probabilistic correctness and statistical power of the comparison. Moreover, our method is strongest in the most challenging comparison instances (requiring the most evaluation trials); in a multi-task comparison scenario, we save the evaluator more than 200 simulation rollouts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10966v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Snyder, Asher James Hancock, Apurva Badithela, Emma Dixon, Patrick Miller, Rares Andrei Ambrus, Anirudha Majumdar, Masha Itkina, Haruki Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Uncertainty Unification: A Case Study for Preference Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19317v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Learning human preferences is essential for human-robot interaction, as it enables robots to adapt their behaviors to align with human expectations and goals. However, the inherent uncertainties in both human behavior and robotic systems make preference learning a challenging task. While probabilistic robotics algorithms offer uncertainty quantification, the integration of human preference uncertainty remains underexplored. To bridge this gap, we introduce uncertainty unification and propose a novel framework, uncertainty-unified preference learning (UUPL), which enhances Gaussian Process (GP)-based preference learning by unifying human and robot uncertainties. Specifically, UUPL includes a human preference uncertainty model that improves GP posterior mean estimation, and an uncertainty-weighted Gaussian Mixture Model (GMM) that enhances GP predictive variance accuracy. Additionally, we design a user-specific calibration process to align uncertainty representations across users, ensuring consistency and reliability in the model performance. Comprehensive experiments and user studies demonstrate that UUPL achieves state-of-the-art performance in both prediction accuracy and user rating. An ablation study further validates the effectiveness of human uncertainty model and uncertainty-weighted GMM of UUPL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19317v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Robotics: Science and Systems, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shaoting Peng, Haonan Chen, Katherine Driggs-Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A0: An Affordance-Aware Hierarchical Model for General Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12636v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robotic manipulation faces critical challenges in understanding spatial affordances--the "where" and "how" of object interactions--essential for complex manipulation tasks like wiping a board or stacking objects. Existing methods, including modular-based and end-to-end approaches, often lack robust spatial reasoning capabilities. Unlike recent point-based and flow-based affordance methods that focus on dense spatial representations or trajectory modeling, we propose A0, a hierarchical affordance-aware diffusion model that decomposes manipulation tasks into high-level spatial affordance understanding and low-level action execution. A0 leverages the Embodiment-Agnostic Affordance Representation, which captures object-centric spatial affordances by predicting contact points and post-contact trajectories. A0 is pre-trained on 1 million contact points data and fine-tuned on annotated trajectories, enabling generalization across platforms. Key components include Position Offset Attention for motion-aware feature extraction and a Spatial Information Aggregation Layer for precise coordinate mapping. The model's output is executed by the action execution module. Experiments on multiple robotic systems (Franka, Kinova, Realman, and Dobot) demonstrate A0's superior performance in complex tasks, showcasing its efficiency, flexibility, and real-world applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12636v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongtao Xu, Jian Zhang, Minghao Guo, Youpeng Wen, Haoting Yang, Min Lin, Jianzheng Huang, Zhe Li, Kaidong Zhang, Liqiong Wang, Yuxuan Kuang, Meng Cao, Feng Zheng, Xiaodan Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>J-PARSE: Jacobian-based Projection Algorithm for Resolving Singularities Effectively in Inverse Kinematic Control of Serial Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00306v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: J-PARSE is a method for smooth first-order inverse kinematic control of a serial manipulator near kinematic singularities. The commanded end-effector velocity is interpreted component-wise, according to the available mobility in each dimension of the task space. First, a substitute "Safety" Jacobian matrix is created, keeping the aspect ratio of the manipulability ellipsoid above a threshold value. The desired motion is then projected onto non-singular and singular directions, and the latter projection scaled down by a factor informed by the threshold value. A right-inverse of the non-singular Safety Jacobian is applied to the modified command. In the absence of joint limits and collisions, this ensures smooth transition into and out of low-rank poses, guaranteeing asymptotic stability for target poses within the workspace, and stability for those outside. Velocity control with J-PARSE is benchmarked against the Least-Squares and Damped Least-Squares inversions of the Jacobian, and shows high accuracy in reaching and leaving singular target poses. By expanding the available workspace of manipulators, the method finds applications in servoing, teleoperation, and learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00306v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Guptasarma, Matthew Strong, Honghao Zhen, Monroe Kennedy III</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robotic Visual Instruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, natural language has been the primary medium for human-robot interaction. However, its inherent lack of spatial precision introduces challenges for robotic task definition such as ambiguity and verbosity. Moreover, in some public settings where quiet is required, such as libraries or hospitals, verbal communication with robots is inappropriate. To address these limitations, we introduce the Robotic Visual Instruction (RoVI), a novel paradigm to guide robotic tasks through an object-centric, hand-drawn symbolic representation. RoVI effectively encodes spatial-temporal information into human-interpretable visual instructions through 2D sketches, utilizing arrows, circles, colors, and numbers to direct 3D robotic manipulation. To enable robots to understand RoVI better and generate precise actions based on RoVI, we present Visual Instruction Embodied Workflow (VIEW), a pipeline formulated for RoVI-conditioned policies. This approach leverages Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to interpret RoVI inputs, decode spatial and temporal constraints from 2D pixel space via keypoint extraction, and then transform them into executable 3D action sequences. We additionally curate a specialized dataset of 15K instances to fine-tune small VLMs for edge deployment,enabling them to effectively learn RoVI capabilities. Our approach is rigorously validated across 11 novel tasks in both real and simulated environments, demonstrating significant generalization capability. Notably, VIEW achieves an 87.5% success rate in real-world scenarios involving unseen tasks that feature multi-step actions, with disturbances, and trajectory-following requirements. Project website: https://robotic-visual-instruction.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00693v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanbang Li, Ziyang Gong, Haoyang Li, Xiaoqi Huang, Haolan Kang, Guangping Bai, Xianzheng Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReLI: A Language-Agnostic Approach to Human-Robot Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01862v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Adapting autonomous agents to industrial, domestic, and other daily tasks is currently gaining momentum. However, in the global or cross-lingual application contexts, ensuring effective interaction with the environment and executing unrestricted human task-specified instructions in diverse languages remains an unsolved problem. To address this challenge, we propose ReLI, a language-agnostic framework designed to enable autonomous agents to converse naturally, semantically reason about the environment, and to perform downstream tasks, regardless of the task instruction's linguistic origin. First, we ground large-scale pre-trained foundation models and transform them into language-to-action models that can directly provide common-sense reasoning and high-level robot control through natural, free-flow human-robot conversational interactions. Further, we perform cross-lingual grounding of the models to ensure that ReLI generalises across the global languages. To demonstrate the ReLI's robustness, we conducted extensive simulated and real-world experiments on various short- and long-horizon tasks, including zero-shot and few-shot spatial navigation, scene information retrieval, and query-oriented tasks. We benchmarked the performance on 140 languages involving over 70K multi-turn conversations. On average, ReLI achieved over 90%$\pm$0.2 accuracy in cross-lingual instruction parsing and task execution success rates. These results demonstrate the ReLI's potential to enhance natural human-robot interaction in the real world while championing linguistic diversity. Demonstrations and resources will be publicly available at https://linusnep.github.io/ReLI/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01862v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linus Nwankwo, Bjoern Ellensohn, Ozan \"Ozdenizci, Elmar Rueckert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Synergistic Framework of Nonlinear Acoustic Computing and Reinforcement Learning for Real-World Human-Robot Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel framework integrating nonlinear acoustic computing and reinforcement learning to enhance advanced human-robot interaction under complex noise and reverberation. Leveraging physically informed wave equations (e.g., Westervelt, KZK), the approach captures higher-order phenomena such as harmonic generation and shock formation. By embedding these models in a reinforcement learning-driven control loop, the system adaptively optimizes key parameters (e.g., absorption, beamforming) to mitigate multipath interference and non-stationary noise. Experimental evaluations, covering far-field localization, weak signal detection, and multilingual speech recognition, demonstrate that this hybrid strategy surpasses traditional linear methods and purely data-driven baselines, achieving superior noise suppression, minimal latency, and robust accuracy in demanding real-world scenarios. The proposed system demonstrates broad application prospects in AI hardware, robot, machine audition, artificial audition, and brain-machine interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01998v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoliang Chen (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Xin Yu (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Le Chang (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Yunhe Huang (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Jiashuai He (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Shibo Zhang (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Jin Li (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Likai Lin (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Ziyu Zeng (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Xianling Tu (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd), Shuyu Zhang (SoundAI Technology Co., Ltd)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing Trust and Resilience in Distributed Consensus for Cyberphysical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.05464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.05464v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work considers the problem of resilient consensus where stochastic values of trust between agents are available. Specifically, we derive a unified mathematical framework to characterize convergence, deviation of the consensus from the true consensus value, and expected convergence rate, when there exists additional information of trust between agents. We show that under certain conditions on the stochastic trust values and consensus protocol: 1) almost sure convergence to a common limit value is possible even when malicious agents constitute more than half of the network connectivity, 2) the deviation of the converged limit, from the case where there is no attack, i.e., the true consensus value, can be bounded with probability that approaches 1 exponentially, and 3) correct classification of malicious and legitimate agents can be attained in finite time almost surely. Further, the expected convergence rate decays exponentially as a function of the quality of the trust observations between agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.05464v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Yemini, Angelia Nedi\'c, Andrea Goldsmith, Stephanie Gil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysicsFC: Learning User-Controlled Skills for a Physics-Based Football Player Controller</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21216v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose PhysicsFC, a method for controlling physically simulated football player characters to perform a variety of football skills--such as dribbling, trapping, moving, and kicking--based on user input, while seamlessly transitioning between these skills. Our skill-specific policies, which generate latent variables for each football skill, are trained using an existing physics-based motion embedding model that serves as a foundation for reproducing football motions. Key features include a tailored reward design for the Dribble policy, a two-phase reward structure combined with projectile dynamics-based initialization for the Trap policy, and a Data-Embedded Goal-Conditioned Latent Guidance (DEGCL) method for the Move policy. Using the trained skill policies, the proposed football player finite state machine (PhysicsFC FSM) allows users to interactively control the character. To ensure smooth and agile transitions between skill policies, as defined in the FSM, we introduce the Skill Transition-Based Initialization (STI), which is applied during the training of each skill policy. We develop several interactive scenarios to showcase PhysicsFC's effectiveness, including competitive trapping and dribbling, give-and-go plays, and 11v11 football games, where multiple PhysicsFC agents produce natural and controllable physics-based football player behaviors. Quantitative evaluations further validate the performance of individual skill policies and the transitions between them, using the presented metrics and experimental designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21216v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3731425</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Minsu Kim, Eunho Jung, Yoonsang Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
