<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:34:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>EdgeNav-QE: QLoRA Quantization and Dynamic Early Exit for LAM-based Navigation on Edge Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Action Models (LAMs) have shown immense potential in autonomous navigation by bridging high-level reasoning with low-level control. However, deploying these multi-billion parameter models on edge devices remains a significant challenge due to memory constraints and latency requirements. In this paper, we propose EdgeNav-QE, a novel framework that integrates Quantized Low-Rank Adaptation (QLoRA) with a dynamic early-exit (DEE) mechanism to optimize LAMs for real-time edge navigation. By quantizing the backbone to 4-bit precision and strategically placing early-exit branches, we enable the model to terminate inference early for simple navigation tasks while retaining full depth for complex decision-making. Experimental results on the Habitat-Sim environment with Matterport3D dataset using OpenVLA-7B backbone, demonstrate that EdgeNav-QE reduces inference latency by 82.7% and memory footprint by 66.7% compared to full-precision baselines, while maintaining 81.8% navigation success rate. Furthermore, it outperforms state-of-the-art static early-exit method by 17.9% in latency, demonstrating the superiority of content-aware adaptive computation for safety-critical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15836v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyun Liu, Shanshan Huang, Jianan Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Conflicts to Collisions: A Two-Stage Collision Scenario-Testing Approach for Autonomous Driving Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous driving systems (ADS) are safety-critical and require rigorous testing before public deployment. Simulation-based scenario testing provides a safe and cost-effective alternative to extensive on-road trials, enabling efficient evaluation of ADS under diverse and high-risk conditions. However, existing approaches mainly evaluates the scenarios based on their proximity to collisions and focus on scenarios already close to collision, leaving many other hazardous situations unexplored. To bridge this, we introduce a collision-related concept of conflict as an intermediate search target and propose a two-stage scenario testing framework that first searches for conflicts and then mutates these conflict scenarios to induce actual collisions. Evaluated on Baidu Apollo, our approach reveals up to 12 distinct collision types in a single run, doubling the diversity discovered by state-of-the-art baselines while requiring fewer simulations thanks to conflict-targeted mutations. These results show that using conflicts as intermediate objectives broadens the search horizon and significantly improves the efficiency and effectiveness of ADS safety evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15837v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Chen, Fuyuan Zhang, Hua Qi, Lei Ma, Tomoyuki Tsuchiya, Michio Hayashi, Manabu Okada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TurboADMM: A Structure-Exploiting Parallel Solver for Multi-Agent Trajectory Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-agent trajectory optimization with dense interaction networks require solving large coupled QPs at control rates, yet existing solvers fail to simultaneously exploit temporal structure, agent decomposition, and iteration similarity. One usually treats multi-agent problems monolithically when using general-purpose QP solvers (OSQP, MOSEK), which encounter scalability difficulties with agent count. Structure-exploiting solvers (HPIPM) leverage temporal structure through Riccati recursion but can be vulnerable to dense coupling constraints. We introduce TurboADMM, a specialized single-machine QP solver that achieves empirically near linear complexity in agent count through systematic co-design of three complementary components: (1) ADMM decomposition creates per-agent subproblems solvable in parallel, preserving block-tridiagonal structure under dense coupling; (2) Riccati warmstart exploits temporal structure to provide high-quality primal-dual initialization for each agent's QP; (3) parametric QP hotstart \footnote{In the paper, we refer warmstart as the technique that uses the Riccati equation results as auxiliary QP initialization for a single QP solve, while hotstart as reusing the QR factorization across QP solve iterations.}in qpOASES reuses similar KKT system factorizations across ADMM iterations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15838v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Decade of Human-Robot Interaction Through Immersive Lenses: Reviewing Extended Reality as a Research Instrument in Social Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15840v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past decade, Extended Reality (XR), including Virtual, Augmented, and Mixed Reality, gained attention as a research instrument in human-robot interaction studies, but remains underexplored in empirical investigations of social robotics. To map the field, we systematically reviewed empirical studies from 2015 to 2025. Of 6,527 peer-reviewed articles, only 33 met strict inclusion criteria. We examined (1) how XR and virtual social robots are used, focusing on the software and hardware employed and the application contexts in which they are deployed, (2) data collection and analysis methods, (3) demographics of the researchers and participants, and (4) the challenges and future directions. Our findings show that social XR-HRI research is still driven by laboratory simulations, while crucial specifications - such as the hardware, software, and robots used - are often not reported. Robots typically act as passive and hardly interactive visual stimulus, while the rich biosignal (e.g., eye-tracking) and logging (e.g. motion capturing) functions of modern head-mounted displays remain largely untapped. While there are gaps in demographic reporting, the research teams and samples are predominantly tech-centric, Western, young, and male. Key limitations include hardware delays, small homogeneous samples, and short study cycles. We propose a four-phase roadmap to establish social XR-HRI as a reliable research medium, which includes (1) strengthen application contexts, (2) more robust and testable technological iterations, (3) embedding diversity in samples and research teams, and (4) the need for reporting standards, e.g., in form of a suitable taxonomy. Advancing in these directions is essential for XR to mature from a lab prototype into an ecologically valid research instrument for social robotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15840v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e Helgert, Carolin Stra{\ss}mann, Sabrina C. Eimler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReasonNavi: Human-Inspired Global Map Reasoning for Zero-Shot Embodied Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Embodied agents often struggle with efficient navigation because they rely primarily on partial egocentric observations, which restrict global foresight and lead to inefficient exploration. In contrast, humans plan using maps: we reason globally first, then act locally. We introduce ReasonNavi, a human-inspired framework that operationalizes this reason-then-act paradigm by coupling Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) with deterministic planners. ReasonNavi converts a top-down map into a discrete reasoning space by room segmentation and candidate target nodes sampling. An MLLM is then queried in a multi-stage process to identify the candidate most consistent with the instruction (object, image, or text goal), effectively leveraging the model's semantic reasoning ability while sidestepping its weakness in continuous coordinate prediction. The selected waypoint is grounded into executable trajectories using a deterministic action planner over an online-built occupancy map, while pretrained object detectors and segmenters ensure robust recognition at the goal. This yields a unified zero-shot navigation framework that requires no MLLM fine-tuning, circumvents the brittleness of RL-based policies and scales naturally with foundation model improvements. Across three navigation tasks, ReasonNavi consistently outperforms prior methods that demand extensive training or heavy scene modeling, offering a scalable, interpretable, and globally grounded solution to embodied navigation. Project page: https://reasonnavi.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15864v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhuo Ao, Anbang Wang, Yu-Wing Tai, Chi-Keung Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARVL: Multi-Stage Guidance for Robotic Manipulation via Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing dense reward functions is pivotal for efficient robotic Reinforcement Learning (RL). However, most dense rewards rely on manual engineering, which fundamentally limits the scalability and automation of reinforcement learning. While Vision-Language Models (VLMs) offer a promising path to reward design, naive VLM rewards often misalign with task progress, struggle with spatial grounding, and show limited understanding of task semantics. To address these issues, we propose MARVL-Multi-stAge guidance for Robotic manipulation via Vision-Language models. MARVL fine-tunes a VLM for spatial and semantic consistency and decomposes tasks into multi-stage subtasks with task direction projection for trajectory sensitivity. Empirically, MARVL significantly outperforms existing VLM-reward methods on the Meta-World benchmark, demonstrating superior sample efficiency and robustness on sparse-reward manipulation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15872v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunlan Zhou, Xuanlin Chen, Shaowei Zhang, Xiangkun Li, ShengHua Wan, Xiaohai Hu, Yuan Lei, Le Gan, De-chuan Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test-Time Adaptation for Tactile-Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tactile-vision-language (TVL) models are increasingly deployed in real-world robotic and multimodal perception tasks, where test-time distribution shifts are unavoidable. Existing test-time adaptation (TTA) methods provide filtering in unimodal settings but lack explicit treatment of modality-wise reliability under asynchronous cross-modal shifts, leaving them brittle when some modalities become unreliable. We study TTA for TVL models under such shifts and propose a reliability-aware framework that estimates per-modality reliability from prediction uncertainty and perturbation-based responses. This shared reliability signal is used to (i) filter unreliable test samples, (ii) adaptively fuse tactile, visual, and language features, and (iii) regularize test-time optimization with a reliability-guided objective. On the TAG-C benchmark and additional TVL scenarios, our approach consistently outperforms strong TTA baselines, achieving accuracy gains of up to 49.9\% under severe modality corruptions, underscoring the importance of explicit modality-wise reliability modeling for robust test-time adaptation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15873v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuyang Ye, Haoxian Jing, Qinting Jiang, Yixi Lin, Qiang Li, Xing Tang, Jingyan Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fly0: Decoupling Semantic Grounding from Geometric Planning for Zero-Shot Aerial Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current Visual-Language Navigation (VLN) methodologies face a trade-off between semantic understanding and control precision. While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) offer superior reasoning, deploying them as low-level controllers leads to high latency, trajectory oscillations, and poor generalization due to weak geometric grounding. To address these limitations, we propose Fly0, a framework that decouples semantic reasoning from geometric planning. The proposed method operates through a three-stage pipeline: (1) an MLLM-driven module for grounding natural language instructions into 2D pixel coordinates; (2) a geometric projection module that utilizes depth data to localize targets in 3D space; and (3) a geometric planner that generates collision-free trajectories. This mechanism enables robust navigation even when visual contact is lost. By eliminating the need for continuous inference, Fly0 reduces computational overhead and improves system stability. Extensive experiments in simulation and real-world environments demonstrate that Fly0 outperforms state-of-the-art baselines, improving the Success Rate by over 20\% and reducing Navigation Error (NE) by approximately 50\% in unstructured environments. Our code is available at https://github.com/xuzhenxing1/Fly0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15875v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenxing Xu, Brikit Lu, Weidong Bao, Zhengqiu Zhu, Junsong Zhang, Hui Yan, Wenhao Lu, Ji Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FUTURE-VLA: Forecasting Unified Trajectories Under Real-time Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General vision-language models increasingly support unified spatiotemporal reasoning over long video streams, yet deploying such capabilities on robots remains constrained by the prohibitive latency of processing long-horizon histories and generating high-dimensional future predictions. To bridge this gap, we present FUTURE-VLA, a unified architecture that reformulates long-horizon control and future forecasting as a monolithic sequence-generation task. Adopting a dual-sided efficiency paradigm, FUTURE-VLA leverages a temporally adaptive compression strategy to maximize spatiotemporal information density, enabling the ingestion of extensive multi-view histories while maintaining constant inference latency. Simultaneously, it performs latent-space autoregression to align actionable dynamics with reviewable visual look-aheads in a single forward pass. These real-time predictive capabilities further enable a prediction-guided Human-In-the-Loop mechanism via interactive execution gating, allowing operators to dynamically validate behaviors based on interpretable future previews. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that FUTURE-VLA establishes new state-of-the-art performance, attaining success rates of 99.2% on LIBERO, 75.4% on RoboTwin, and 78.0% on a real-world Piper platform, all with a $16\times$ extended spatiotemporal window while maintaining the inference latency of a single-frame baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingjing Fan, Yushan Liu, Shoujie Li, Botao Ren, Siyuan Li, Xiao-Ping Zhang, Wenbo Ding, Zhidong Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SLAM Confidence Trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The SLAM community has fallen into a "Confidence Trap" by prioritizing benchmark scores over principled uncertainty estimation. This yields systems that are geometrically accurate but probabilitistically inconsistent and brittle. We advocate for a paradigm shift where the consistent, real-time computation of uncertainty becomes a primary metric of success.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15884v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICAR65334.2025.11338690</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Sansoni, Santiago Ram\'on Tosetti Sanz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel Integrated Motion Tracking Device (IMTD) for Objective Laparoscopic Training Assessment: Development and Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel, compact four-degree-of-freedom motion-tracking device (IMTD) designed for training and evaluation in laparoscopic surgery. The device's kinematics, mechanical design, instrumentation, and prototypes are developed and presented to meet the specific requirements of laparoscopic training context, including movement around a fixed center of motion and seamless integration into standard box trainers. The system IMTD's tracking accuracy and reliability are compared to a motion capture system (MoCap), assessing its ability to capture both angular and translational motions of surgical instruments. The study then focuses on key performance parameters including precision, fluidity, speed, and overall motion efficiency. The results highlight the system's effectiveness in tracking surgical gestures, providing valuable insights into its potential as a tool for training and performance evaluation in minimally invasive surgery. Additionally, IMTD's low cost and integrated design allow for easy integration and implementation in training rooms, offering a practical and accessible solution for general use. By offering objective, real-time feedback, the system can significantly contribute to improving surgical skills and shortening the learning curve for novice students, while also providing a foundation for future development of gesture scoring algorithms and standardized training protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15885v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siwar Bouzid (COBRA), Abdelbadia Chaker (COBRA), Marc Arsicault (COBRA), Sami Bennour (COBRA, PPrime), Med Amine Laribi (COBRA, PPrime)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of an Augmented R-CUBE mechanism for Cervical Surgery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In some surgical operations targeting the spine, it is required to drill cavities in the vertebrae for the insertion of pedicle screws. A new mechanical architecture is proposed for this application. It is based on an augmented version of the full translational R-CUBE mechanism, with improved linkages to implement additional rotational motion. Using this concept, a mechanism presented with a 3T2R motion that is required for the manipulation of the surgical drill. It is mainly composed three stages: one translational, one transmitting and one rotational. Their respective kinematic and velocity models are separately derived, then combined. Based on the drilling trajectories obtained from a real patient case, the mechanism is optimized for generating the highest kinematic performances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15886v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>the 9th International Workshop on Medical and Service Robots (MESROB), Jul 2025, Poitiers, France. pp.82-91</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Terence Essomba (COBRA, PPrime), Yu-Wen Wu (COBRA, PPrime), Abdelbadia Chaker (COBRA, PPrime), Med Amine Laribi (COBRA, PPrime)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Drive in New Cities Without Human Demonstrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While autonomous vehicles have achieved reliable performance within specific operating regions, their deployment to new cities remains costly and slow. A key bottleneck is the need to collect many human demonstration trajectories when adapting driving policies to new cities that differ from those seen in training in terms of road geometry, traffic rules, and interaction patterns. In this paper, we show that self-play multi-agent reinforcement learning can adapt a driving policy to a substantially different target city using only the map and meta-information, without requiring any human demonstrations from that city. We introduce NO data Map-based self-play for Autonomous Driving (NOMAD), which enables policy adaptation in a simulator constructed based on the target-city map. Using a simple reward function, NOMAD substantially improves both task success rate and trajectory realism in target cities, demonstrating an effective and scalable alternative to data-intensive city-transfer methods. Project Page: https://nomaddrive.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15891v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilin Wang, Saeed Rahmani, Daphne Cornelisse, Bidipta Sarkar, Alexander David Goldie, Jakob Nicolaus Foerster, Shimon Whiteson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical-Geometric Degeneracy in UAV Search: A Physics-Aware Asymmetric Filtering Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15893v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Post-disaster survivor localization using Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) faces a fundamental physical challenge: the prevalence of Non-Line-of-Sight (NLOS) propagation in collapsed structures. Unlike standard Gaussian noise, signal reflection from debris introduces strictly non-negative ranging biases. Existing robust estimators, typically designed with symmetric loss functions (e.g., Huber or Tukey), implicitly rely on the assumption of error symmetry. Consequently, they experience a theoretical mismatch in this regime, leading to a phenomenon we formally identify as Statistical-Geometric Degeneracy (SGD)-a state where the estimator stagnates due to the coupling of persistent asymmetric bias and limited observation geometry. While emerging data-driven approaches offer alternatives, they often struggle with the scarcity of training data and the sim-to-real gap inherent in unstructured disaster zones. In this work, we propose a physically-grounded solution, the AsymmetricHuberEKF, which explicitly incorporates the non-negative physical prior of NLOS biases via a derived asymmetric loss function. Theoretically, we show that standard symmetric filters correspond to a degenerate case of our framework where the physical constraint is relaxed. Furthermore, we demonstrate that resolving SGD requires not just a robust filter, but specific bilateral information, which we achieve through a co-designed active sensing strategy. Validated in a 2D nadir-view scanning scenario, our approach significantly accelerates convergence compared to symmetric baselines, offering a resilient building block for search operations where data is scarce and geometry is constrained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15893v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Ren, Yudong Fang, Tao Zhang, Wenchi Cheng, Ben Lan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SceneVGGT: VGGT-based online 3D semantic SLAM for indoor scene understanding and navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15899v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present SceneVGGT, a spatio-temporal 3D scene understanding framework that combines SLAM with semantic mapping for autonomous and assistive navigation. Built on VGGT, our method scales to long video streams via a sliding-window pipeline. We align local submaps using camera-pose transformations, enabling memory- and speed-efficient mapping while preserving geometric consistency. Semantics are lifted from 2D instance masks to 3D objects using the VGGT tracking head, maintaining temporally coherent identities for change detection. As a proof of concept, object locations are projected onto an estimated floor plane for assistive navigation. The pipeline's GPU memory usage remains under 17 GB, irrespectively of the length of the input sequence and achieves competitive point-cloud performance on the ScanNet++ benchmark. Overall, SceneVGGT ensures robust semantic identification and is fast enough to support interactive assistive navigation with audio feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15899v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Gelencs\'er-Horv\'ath, Gergely Dinya, Dorka Bogl\'arka Er\H{o}s, P\'eter Hal\'asz, Islam Muhammad Muqsit, Krist\'of Karacs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Illumination Control for Robot Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robot perception under low light or high dynamic range is usually improved downstream - via more robust feature extraction, image enhancement, or closed-loop exposure control. However, all of these approaches are limited by the image captured these conditions. An alternate approach is to utilize a programmable onboard light that adds to ambient illumination and improves captured images. However, it is not straightforward to predict its impact on image formation. Illumination interacts nonlinearly with depth, surface reflectance, and scene geometry. It can both reveal structure and induce failure modes such as specular highlights and saturation. We introduce Lightning, a closed-loop illumination-control framework for visual SLAM that combines relighting, offline optimization, and imitation learning. This is performed in three stages. First, we train a Co-Located Illumination Decomposition (CLID) relighting model that decomposes a robot observation into an ambient component and a light-contribution field. CLID enables physically consistent synthesis of the same scene under alternative light intensities and thereby creates dense multi-intensity training data without requiring us to repeatedly re-run trajectories. Second, using these synthesized candidates, we formulate an offline Optimal Intensity Schedule (OIS) problem that selects illumination levels over a sequence trading off SLAM-relevant image utility against power consumption and temporal smoothness. Third, we distill this ideal solution into a real-time controller through behavior cloning, producing an Illumination Control Policy (ILC) that generalizes beyond the initial training distribution and runs online on a mobile robot to command discrete light-intensity levels. Across our evaluation, Lightning substantially improves SLAM trajectory robustness while reducing unnecessary illumination power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15900v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yash Turkar, Shekoufeh Sadeghi, Karthik Dantu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coverage Path Planning for Autonomous Sailboats in Inhomogeneous and Time-Varying Oceans: A Spatiotemporal Optimization Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous sailboats are well suited for long-duration ocean observation due to their wind-driven endurance. However, their performance is highly anisotropic and strongly influenced by inhomogeneous and time-varying wind and current fields, limiting the effectiveness of existing coverage methods such as boustrophedon sweeping. Planning under these environmental and maneuvering constraints remains underexplored. This paper presents a spatiotemporal coverage path planning framework tailored to autonomous sailboats, combining (1) topology-based morphological constraints in the spatial domain to promote compact and continuous coverage, and (2) forecast-aware look-ahead planning in the temporal domain to anticipate environmental evolution and enable foresighted decision-making. Simulations conducted under stochastic inhomogeneous and time-varying ocean environments, including scenarios with partial directional accessibility, demonstrate that the proposed method generates efficient and feasible coverage paths where traditional strategies often fail. To the best of our knowledge, this study provides the first dedicated solution to the coverage path planning problem for autonomous sailboats operating in inhomogeneous and time-varying ocean environments, establishing a foundation for future cooperative multi-sailboat coverage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang An, Zhikang Ge, Taiyu Zhang, Jean-Baptiste R. G. Souppez, Gaofei Xu, Zhengru Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Action Models are Zero-shot Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: State-of-the-art Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models excel at semantic generalization but struggle to generalize to unseen physical motions in novel environments. We introduce DreamZero, a World Action Model (WAM) built upon a pretrained video diffusion backbone. Unlike VLAs, WAMs learn physical dynamics by predicting future world states and actions, using video as a dense representation of how the world evolves. By jointly modeling video and action, DreamZero learns diverse skills effectively from heterogeneous robot data without relying on repetitive demonstrations. This results in over 2x improvement in generalization to new tasks and environments compared to state-of-the-art VLAs in real robot experiments. Crucially, through model and system optimizations, we enable a 14B autoregressive video diffusion model to perform real-time closed-loop control at 7Hz. Finally, we demonstrate two forms of cross-embodiment transfer: video-only demonstrations from other robots or humans yield a relative improvement of over 42% on unseen task performance with just 10-20 minutes of data. More surprisingly, DreamZero enables few-shot embodiment adaptation, transferring to a new embodiment with only 30 minutes of play data while retaining zero-shot generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15922v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seonghyeon Ye, Yunhao Ge, Kaiyuan Zheng, Shenyuan Gao, Sihyun Yu, George Kurian, Suneel Indupuru, You Liang Tan, Chuning Zhu, Jiannan Xiang, Ayaan Malik, Kyungmin Lee, William Liang, Nadun Ranawaka, Jiasheng Gu, Yinzhen Xu, Guanzhi Wang, Fengyuan Hu, Avnish Narayan, Johan Bjorck, Jing Wang, Gwanghyun Kim, Dantong Niu, Ruijie Zheng, Yuqi Xie, Jimmy Wu, Qi Wang, Ryan Julian, Danfei Xu, Yilun Du, Yevgen Chebotar, Scott Reed, Jan Kautz, Yuke Zhu, Linxi "Jim" Fan, Joel Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Model Predictive Control with Physics-Informed Neural Network for Satellite Attitude Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable spacecraft attitude control depends on accurate prediction of attitude dynamics, particularly when model-based strategies such as Model Predictive Control (MPC) are employed, where performance is limited by the quality of the internal system model. For spacecraft with complex dynamics, obtaining accurate physics-based models can be difficult, time-consuming, or computationally heavy. Learning-based system identification presents a compelling alternative; however, models trained exclusively on data frequently exhibit fragile stability properties and limited extrapolation capability. This work explores Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) for modeling spacecraft attitude dynamics and contrasts it with a conventional data-driven approach. A comprehensive dataset is generated using high-fidelity numerical simulations, and two learning methodologies are investigated: a purely data-driven pipeline and a physics-regularized approach that incorporates prior knowledge into the optimization process. The results indicate that embedding physical constraints during training leads to substantial improvements in predictive reliability, achieving a 68.17% decrease in mean relative error relative. When deployed within an MPC architecture, the physics-informed models yield superior closed-loop tracking performance and improved robustness to uncertainty. Furthermore, a hybrid control formulation that merges the learned nonlinear dynamics with a nominal linear model enables consistent steady-state convergence and significantly faster response, reducing settling times by 61.52%-76.42% under measurement noise and reaction wheel friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15954v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Cena, Mauro Martini, Marcello Chiaberge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The human intention. A taxonomy attempt and its applications to robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite a surge in robotics research dedicated to inferring and understanding human intent, a universally accepted definition remains elusive since existing works often equate human intention with specific task-related goals. This article seeks to address this gap by examining the multifaceted nature of intention. Drawing on insights from psychology, it attempts to consolidate a definition of intention into a comprehensible framework for a broader audience. The article classifies different types of intention based on psychological and communication studies, offering guidance to researchers shifting from pure technical enhancements to a more human-centric perspective in robotics. It then demonstrates how various robotics studies can be aligned with these intention categories. Finally, through in-depth analyses of collaborative search and object transport use cases, the article underscores the significance of considering the diverse facets of human intention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15963v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s12369-025-01304-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>J. E. Dom\'inguez-Vidal, Alberto Sanfeliu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ODYN: An All-Shifted Non-Interior-Point Method for Quadratic Programming in Robotics and AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce ODYN, a novel all-shifted primal-dual non-interior-point quadratic programming (QP) solver designed to efficiently handle challenging dense and sparse QPs. ODYN combines all-shifted nonlinear complementarity problem (NCP) functions with proximal method of multipliers to robustly address ill-conditioned and degenerate problems, without requiring linear independence of the constraints. It exhibits strong warm-start performance and is well suited to both general-purpose optimization, and robotics and AI applications, including model-based control, estimation, and kernel-based learning methods. We provide an open-source implementation and benchmark ODYN on the Maros-M\'esz\'aros test set, demonstrating state-of-the-art convergence performance in small-to-high-scale problems. The results highlight ODYN's superior warm-starting capabilities, which are critical in sequential and real-time settings common in robotics and AI. These advantages are further demonstrated by deploying ODYN as the backend of an SQP-based predictive control framework (OdynSQP), as the implicitly differentiable optimization layer for deep learning (ODYNLayer), and the optimizer of a contact-dynamics simulation (ODYNSim).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16005v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Rojas, Aristotelis Papatheodorou, Sergi Martinez, Ioannis Havoutis, Carlos Mastalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Class Uncertainty Propagation in Perception-Based Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous vehicles (AVs) are being increasingly deployed in urban environments. In order to operate safely and reliably, AVs need to account for the inherent uncertainty associated with perceiving the world through sensor data and incorporate that into their decision-making process. Uncertainty-aware planners have recently been developed to account for upstream perception and prediction uncertainty. However, such planners may be sensitive to prediction uncertainty miscalibration, the magnitude of which has not yet been characterized. Towards this end, we perform a detailed analysis on the impact that perceptual uncertainty propagation and calibration has on perception-based motion planning. We do so by comparing two novel prediction-planning pipelines with varying levels of uncertainty propagation on the recently-released nuPlan planning benchmark. We study the impact of upstream uncertainty calibration using closed-loop evaluation on the nuPlan challenge scenarios. We find that the method incorporating upstream uncertainty propagation demonstrates superior generalization to complex closed-loop scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16035v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jibran Iqbal Shah, Andrei Ivanovic, Kelly Zhu, Masha Itkina, Rowan McAllister, Igor Gilitschenski, Florian Shkurti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScenicRules: An Autonomous Driving Benchmark with Multi-Objective Specifications and Abstract Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Developing autonomous driving systems for complex traffic environments requires balancing multiple objectives, such as avoiding collisions, obeying traffic rules, and making efficient progress. In many situations, these objectives cannot be satisfied simultaneously, and explicit priority relations naturally arise. Also, driving rules require context, so it is important to formally model the environment scenarios within which such rules apply. Existing benchmarks for evaluating autonomous vehicles lack such combinations of multi-objective prioritized rules and formal environment models. In this work, we introduce ScenicRules, a benchmark for evaluating autonomous driving systems in stochastic environments under prioritized multi-objective specifications. We first formalize a diverse set of objectives to serve as quantitative evaluation metrics. Next, we design a Hierarchical Rulebook framework that encodes multiple objectives and their priority relations in an interpretable and adaptable manner. We then construct a compact yet representative collection of scenarios spanning diverse driving contexts and near-accident situations, formally modeled in the Scenic language. Experimental results show that our formalized objectives and Hierarchical Rulebooks align well with human driving judgments and that our benchmark effectively exposes agent failures with respect to the prioritized objectives. Our benchmark can be accessed at https://github.com/BerkeleyLearnVerify/ScenicRules/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16073v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Kai-Chun Chang, Ekin Beyazit, Alberto Sangiovanni-Vincentelli, Tichakorn Wongpiromsarn, Sanjit A. Seshia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Slip Control in Multifingered Grasping: Hybrid Tactile Sensing and Internal-Force Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a hybrid learning and model-based approach that adapts internal grasp forces to halt in-hand slip on a multifingered robotic gripper. A multimodal tactile stack combines piezoelectric (PzE) sensing for fast slip cues with piezoresistive (PzR) arrays for contact localization, enabling online construction of the grasp matrix. Upon slip, we update internal forces computed in the null space of the grasp via a quadratic program that preserves the object wrench while enforcing actuation limits. The pipeline yields a theoretical sensing-to-command latency of 35-40 ms, with 5 ms for PzR-based contact and geometry updates and about 4 ms for the quadratic program solve. In controlled trials, slip onset is detected at 20ms. We demonstrate closed-loop stabilization on multifingered grasps under external perturbations. Augmenting efficient analytic force control with learned tactile cues yields both robustness and rapid reactions, as confirmed in our end-to-end evaluation. Measured delays are dominated by the experimental data path rather than actual computation. The analysis outlines a clear route to sub-50 ms closed-loop stabilization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16127v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Ayral, Saifeddine Aloui, Mathieu Grossard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Measurement Method for Automatic Insertion of Forks into Inclined Pallet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In order to insert a fork into a hole of a pallet by a forklift located in front of a pallet, it is necessary to control the height position, reach position, and tilt angle of the fork to match the position and orientation of the hole of the pallet. In order to make AGF (Autonomous Guided Forklift) do this automatically, we propose an image measurement method to measure the pitch inclination of the pallet in the camera coordinate system from an image obtained by using a wide-angle camera. In addition, we propose an image measurement method to easily acquire the calibration information between the camera coordinate system and the fork coordinate system necessary to apply the measurements in the camera coordinate system to the fork control. In the experiment space, a wide-angle camera was fixed at the backrest of a reach type forklift. The wide-angle images taken by placing a pallet in front of the camera were processed. As a result of evaluating the error by comparing the image measurement value with the hand measurement value when changing the pitch inclination angle of the pallet, the relative height of the pallet and the fork, and whether the pallet is loaded or not, it was confirmed that the error was within the allowable range for safely inserting the fork.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16178v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICARCV57592.2022.10004283</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. IEEE International Conference on Control, Automation, Robotics and Vision (ICARCV), 2022, pp. 441-448</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nobuyuki Kita, Takuro Kato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Model Failure Classification and Anomaly Detection for Autonomous Inspection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16182v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous inspection robots for monitoring industrial sites can reduce costs and risks associated with human-led inspection. However, accurate readings can be challenging due to occlusions, limited viewpoints, or unexpected environmental conditions. We propose a hybrid framework that combines supervised failure classification with anomaly detection, enabling classification of inspection tasks as a success, known failure, or anomaly (i.e., out-of-distribution) case. Our approach uses a world model backbone with compressed video inputs. This policy-agnostic, distribution-free framework determines classifications based on two decision functions set by conformal prediction (CP) thresholds before a human observer does. We evaluate the framework on gauge inspection feeds collected from office and industrial sites and demonstrate real-time deployment on a Boston Dynamics Spot. Experiments show over 90% accuracy in distinguishing between successes, failures, and OOD cases, with classifications occurring earlier than a human observer. These results highlight the potential for robust, anticipatory failure detection in autonomous inspection tasks or as a feedback signal for model training to assess and improve the quality of training data. Project website: https://autoinspection-classification.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16182v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michelle Ho, Muhammad Fadhil Ginting, Isaac R. Ward, Andrzej Reinke, Mykel J. Kochenderfer, Ali-akbar Agha-Mohammadi, Shayegan Omidshafiei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIT-LMPC: Safe Information-Theoretic Learning Model Predictive Control for Iterative Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robots executing iterative tasks in complex, uncertain environments require control strategies that balance robustness, safety, and high performance. This paper introduces a safe information-theoretic learning model predictive control (SIT-LMPC) algorithm for iterative tasks. Specifically, we design an iterative control framework based on an information-theoretic model predictive control algorithm to address a constrained infinite-horizon optimal control problem for discrete-time nonlinear stochastic systems. An adaptive penalty method is developed to ensure safety while balancing optimality. Trajectories from previous iterations are utilized to learn a value function using normalizing flows, which enables richer uncertainty modeling compared to Gaussian priors. SIT-LMPC is designed for highly parallel execution on graphics processing units, allowing efficient real-time optimization. Benchmark simulations and hardware experiments demonstrate that SIT-LMPC iteratively improves system performance while robustly satisfying system constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16187v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2025.3634881</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, vol. 11, no. 1, pp. 986-993, 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zirui Zang, Ahmad Amine, Nick-Marios T. Kokolakis, Truong X. Nghiem, Ugo Rosolia, Rahul Mangharam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonplanar Model Predictive Control for Autonomous Vehicles with Recursive Sparse Gaussian Process Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a nonplanar model predictive control (MPC) framework for autonomous vehicles operating on nonplanar terrain. To approximate complex vehicle dynamics in such environments, we develop a geometry-aware modeling approach that learns a residual Gaussian Process (GP). By utilizing a recursive sparse GP, the framework enables real-time adaptation to varying terrain geometry. The effectiveness of the learned model is demonstrated in a reference-tracking task using a Model Predictive Path Integral (MPPI) controller. Validation within a custom Isaac Sim environment confirms the framework's capability to maintain high tracking accuracy on challenging 3D surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16206v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Amine, Kabir Puri, Viet-Anh Le, Rahul Mangharam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markerless Robot Detection and 6D Pose Estimation for Multi-Agent SLAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The capability of multi-robot SLAM approaches to merge localization history and maps from different observers is often challenged by the difficulty in establishing data association. Loop closure detection between perceptual inputs of different robotic agents is easily compromised in the context of perceptual aliasing, or when perspectives differ significantly. For this reason, direct mutual observation among robots is a powerful way to connect partial SLAM graphs, but often relies on the presence of calibrated arrays of fiducial markers (e.g., AprilTag arrays), which severely limits the range of observations and frequently fails under sharp lighting conditions, e.g., reflections or overexposure. In this work, we propose a novel solution to this problem leveraging recent advances in Deep-Learning-based 6D pose estimation. We feature markerless pose estimation as part of a decentralized multi-robot SLAM system and demonstrate the benefit to the relative localization accuracy among the robotic team. The solution is validated experimentally on data recorded in a test field campaign on a planetary analogous environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16308v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Rueggeberg, Maximilian Ulmer, Maximilian Durner, Wout Boerdijk, Marcus Gerhard Mueller, Rudolph Triebel, Riccardo Giubilato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Driven Prediction of the Behavior of Biohybrid Actuators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Skeletal muscle-based biohybrid actuators have proved to be a promising component in soft robotics, offering efficient movement. However, their intrinsic biological variability and nonlinearity pose significant challenges for controllability and predictability. To address these issues, this study investigates the application of supervised learning, a form of machine learning, to model and predict the behavior of biohybrid machines (BHMs), focusing on a muscle ring anchored on flexible polymer pillars. First, static prediction models (i.e., random forest and neural network regressors) are trained to estimate the maximum exerted force achieved from input variables such as muscle sample, electrical stimulation parameters, and baseline exerted force. Second, a dynamic modeling framework, based on Long Short-Term Memory networks, is developed to serve as a digital twin, replicating the time series of exerted forces observed in response to electrical stimulation. Both modeling approaches demonstrate high predictive accuracy. The best performance of the static models is characterized by R2 of 0.9425, whereas the dynamic model achieves R2 of 0.9956. The static models can enable optimization of muscle actuator performance for targeted applications and required force outcomes, while the dynamic model provides a foundation for developing robustly adaptive control strategies in future biohybrid robotic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16330v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michail-Antisthenis Tsompanas, Marco Perez Hernandez, Faisal Abdul-Fattah, Karim Elhakim, Mostafa Ibrahim, Judith Fuentes, Florencia Lezcano, Riccardo Collu, Massimo Barbaro, Stefano Lai, Samuel Sanchez, Andrew Adamatzky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-Quadruped Collaborative Transportation in Narrow Environments via Safe Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collaborative transportation, where multiple robots collaboratively transport a payload, has garnered significant attention in recent years. While ensuring safe and high-performance inter-robot collaboration is critical for effective task execution, it is difficult to pursue in narrow environments where the feasible region is extremely limited. To address this challenge, we propose a novel approach for dual-quadruped collaborative transportation via safe reinforcement learning (RL). Specifically, we model the task as a fully cooperative constrained Markov game, where collision avoidance is formulated as constraints. We introduce a cost-advantage decomposition method that enforces the sum of team constraints to remain below an upper bound, thereby guaranteeing task safety within an RL framework. Furthermore, we propose a constraint allocation method that assigns shared constraints to individual robots to maximize the overall task reward, encouraging autonomous task-assignment among robots, thereby improving collaborative task performance. Simulation and real-time experimental results demonstrate that the proposed approach achieves superior performance and a higher success rate in dual-quadruped collaborative transportation compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16353v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhezhi Lei, Zhihai Bi, Wenxin Wang, Jun Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Articulated 3D Scene Graphs for Open-World Mobile Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semantics has enabled 3D scene understanding and affordance-driven object interaction. However, robots operating in real-world environments face a critical limitation: they cannot anticipate how objects move. Long-horizon mobile manipulation requires closing the gap between semantics, geometry, and kinematics. In this work, we present MoMa-SG, a novel framework for building semantic-kinematic 3D scene graphs of articulated scenes containing a myriad of interactable objects. Given RGB-D sequences containing multiple object articulations, we temporally segment object interactions and infer object motion using occlusion-robust point tracking. We then lift point trajectories into 3D and estimate articulation models using a novel unified twist estimation formulation that robustly estimates revolute and prismatic joint parameters in a single optimization pass. Next, we associate objects with estimated articulations and detect contained objects by reasoning over parent-child relations at identified opening states. We also introduce the novel Arti4D-Semantic dataset, which uniquely combines hierarchical object semantics including parent-child relation labels with object axis annotations across 62 in-the-wild RGB-D sequences containing 600 object interactions and three distinct observation paradigms. We extensively evaluate the performance of MoMa-SG on two datasets and ablate key design choices of our approach. In addition, real-world experiments on both a quadruped and a mobile manipulator demonstrate that our semantic-kinematic scene graphs enable robust manipulation of articulated objects in everyday home environments. We provide code and data at: https://momasg.cs.uni-freiburg.de.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16356v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin B\"uchner, Adrian R\"ofer, Tim Engelbracht, Tim Welschehold, Zuria Bauer, Hermann Blum, Marc Pollefeys, Abhinav Valada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Identification under Constraints and Disturbance: A Bayesian Estimation Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16358v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a Bayesian system identification (SysID) framework for jointly estimating robot's state trajectories and physical parameters with high accuracy. It embeds physically consistent inverse dynamics, contact and loop-closure constraints, and fully featured joint friction models as hard, stage-wise equality constraints. It relies on energy-based regressors to enhance parameter observability, supports both equality and inequality priors on inertial and actuation parameters, enforces dynamically consistent disturbance projections, and augments proprioceptive measurements with energy observations to disambiguate nonlinear friction effects. To ensure scalability, we derive a parameterized equality-constrained Riccati recursion that preserves the banded structure of the problem, achieving linear complexity in the time horizon, and develop computationally efficient derivatives. Simulation studies on representative robotic systems, together with hardware experiments on a Unitree B1 equipped with a Z1 arm, demonstrate faster convergence, lower inertial and friction estimation errors, and improved contact consistency compared to forward-dynamics and decoupled identification baselines. When deployed within model predictive control frameworks, the resulting models yield measurable improvements in tracking performance during locomotion over challenging environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16358v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergi Martinez, Steve Tonneau, Carlos Mastalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Docking and Persistent Operations for a Resident Underwater Vehicle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our understanding of the oceans remains limited by sparse and infrequent observations, primarily because current methods are constrained by the high cost and logistical effort of underwater monitoring, relying either on sporadic surveys across broad areas or on long-term measurements at fixed locations. To overcome these limitations, monitoring systems must enable persistent and autonomous operations without the need for continuous surface support. Despite recent advances, resident underwater vehicles remain uncommon due to persistent challenges in autonomy, robotic resilience, and mechanical robustness, particularly under long-term deployment in harsh and remote environments. This work addresses these problems by presenting the development, deployment, and operation of a resident infrastructure using a docking station with a mini-class Remotely Operated Vehicle (ROV) at 90m depth. The ROVis equipped with enhanced onboard processing and perception, allowing it to autonomously navigate using USBL signals, dock via ArUco marker-based visual localisation fused through an Extended Kalman Filter, and carry out local inspection routines. The system demonstrated a 90% autonomous docking success rate and completed full inspection missions within four minutes, validating the integration of acoustic and visual navigation in real-world conditions. These results show that reliable, untethered operations at depth are feasible, highlighting the potential of resident ROV systems for scalable, cost-effective underwater monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16360v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonard G\"unzel, Gabriel\.e Kasparavi\v{c}i\=ut\.e, Ambj{\o}rn Grimsrud Waldum, Bj{\o}rn-Magnus Mosl{\aa}tt, Abubakar Aliyu Badawi, Celil Y{\i}lmaz, Md Shamin Yeasher Yousha, Robert Staven, Martin Ludvigsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markerless 6D Pose Estimation and Position-Based Visual Servoing for Endoscopic Continuum Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuum manipulators in flexible endoscopic surgical systems offer high dexterity for minimally invasive procedures; however, accurate pose estimation and closed-loop control remain challenging due to hysteresis, compliance, and limited distal sensing. Vision-based approaches reduce hardware complexity but are often constrained by limited geometric observability and high computational overhead, restricting real-time closed-loop applicability. This paper presents a unified framework for markerless stereo 6D pose estimation and position-based visual servoing of continuum manipulators. A photo-realistic simulation pipeline enables large-scale automatic training with pixel-accurate annotations. A stereo-aware multi-feature fusion network jointly exploits segmentation masks, keypoints, heatmaps, and bounding boxes to enhance geometric observability. To enforce geometric consistency without iterative optimization, a feed-forward rendering-based refinement module predicts residual pose corrections in a single pass. A self-supervised sim-to-real adaptation strategy further improves real-world performance using unlabeled data. Extensive real-world validation achieves a mean translation error of 0.83 mm and a mean rotation error of 2.76{\deg} across 1,000 samples. Markerless closed-loop visual servoing driven by the estimated pose attains accurate trajectory tracking with a mean translation error of 2.07 mm and a mean rotation error of 7.41{\deg}, corresponding to 85% and 59% reductions compared to open-loop control, together with high repeatability in repeated point-reaching tasks. To the best of our knowledge, this work presents the first fully markerless pose-estimation-driven position-based visual servoing framework for continuum manipulators, enabling precise closed-loop control without physical markers or embedded sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16365v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junhyun Park, Chunggil An, Myeongbo Park, Ihsan Ullah, Sihyeong Park, Minho Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Modeling and MPC for Locomotion of Tendon-Driven Soft Quadruped</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: SLOT (Soft Legged Omnidirectional Tetrapod), a tendon-driven soft quadruped robot with 3D-printed TPU legs, is presented to study physics-informed modeling and control of compliant legged locomotion using only four actuators. Each leg is modeled as a deformable continuum using discrete Cosserat rod theory, enabling the capture of large bending deformations, distributed elasticity, tendon actuation, and ground contact interactions. A modular whole-body modeling framework is introduced, in which compliant leg dynamics are represented through physically consistent reaction forces applied to a rigid torso, providing a scalable interface between continuum soft limbs and rigid-body locomotion dynamics. This formulation allows efficient whole-body simulation and real-time control without sacrificing physical fidelity. The proposed model is embedded into a convex model predictive control framework that optimizes ground reaction forces over a 0.495 s prediction horizon and maps them to tendon actuation through a physics-informed force-angle relationship. The resulting controller achieves asymptotic stability under diverse perturbations. The framework is experimentally validated on a physical prototype during crawling and walking gaits, achieving high accuracy with less than 5 mm RMSE in center of mass trajectories. These results demonstrate a generalizable approach for integrating continuum soft legs into model-based locomotion control, advancing scalable and reusable modeling and control methods for soft quadruped robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16371v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saumya Karan, Neerav Maram, Suraj Borate, Madhu Vadali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboGene: Boosting VLA Pre-training via Diversity-Driven Agentic Framework for Real-World Task Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16444v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of general-purpose robotic manipulation is hindered by the scarcity of diverse, real-world interaction data. Unlike data collection from web in vision or language, robotic data collection is an active process incurring prohibitive physical costs. Consequently, automated task curation to maximize data value remains a critical yet under-explored challenge. Existing manual methods are unscalable and biased toward common tasks, while off-the-shelf foundation models often hallucinate physically infeasible instructions. To address this, we introduce RoboGene, an agentic framework designed to automate the generation of diverse, physically plausible manipulation tasks across single-arm, dual-arm, and mobile robots. RoboGene integrates three core components: diversity-driven sampling for broad task coverage, self-reflection mechanisms to enforce physical constraints, and human-in-the-loop refinement for continuous improvement. We conduct extensive quantitative analysis and large-scale real-world experiments, collecting datasets of 18k trajectories and introducing novel metrics to assess task quality, feasibility, and diversity. Results demonstrate that RoboGene significantly outperforms state-of-the-art foundation models (e.g., GPT-4o, Gemini 2.5 Pro). Furthermore, real-world experiments show that VLA models pre-trained with RoboGene achieve higher success rates and superior generalization, underscoring the importance of high-quality task generation. Our project is available at https://robogene-boost-vla.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16444v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixue Zhang, Kun Wu, Zhi Gao, Zhen Zhao, Pei Ren, Zhiyuan Xu, Fei Liao, Xinhua Wang, Shichao Fan, Di Wu, Qiuxuan Feng, Meng Li, Zhengping Che, Chang Liu, Jian Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Motion Generation With Particle-Based Perception in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reactive motion generation in dynamic and unstructured scenarios is typically subject to essentially static perception and system dynamics. Reliably modeling dynamic obstacles and optimizing collision-free trajectories under perceptive and control uncertainty are challenging. This article focuses on revealing tight connection between reactive planning and dynamic mapping for manipulators from a model-based perspective. To enable efficient particle-based perception with expressively dynamic property, we present a tensorized particle weight update scheme that explicitly maintains obstacle velocities and covariance meanwhile. Building upon this dynamic representation, we propose an obstacle-aware MPPI-based planning formulation that jointly propagates robot-obstacle dynamics, allowing future system motion to be predicted and evaluated under uncertainty. The model predictive method is shown to significantly improve safety and reactivity with dynamic surroundings. By applying our complete framework in simulated and noisy real-world environments, we demonstrate that explicit modeling of robot-obstacle dynamics consistently enhances performance over state-of-the-art MPPI-based perception-planning baselines avoiding multiple static and dynamic obstacles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16462v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiyuan Zhao, Huijun Li, Lifeng Zhu, Zhikai Wei, Xianyi Zhu, Aiguo Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIGOR: Visual Goal-In-Context Inference for Unified Humanoid Fall Safety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable fall recovery is critical for humanoids operating in cluttered environments. Unlike quadrupeds or wheeled robots, humanoids experience high-energy impacts, complex whole-body contact, and large viewpoint changes during a fall, making recovery essential for continued operation. Existing methods fragment fall safety into separate problems such as fall avoidance, impact mitigation, and stand-up recovery, or rely on end-to-end policies trained without vision through reinforcement learning or imitation learning, often on flat terrain. At a deeper level, fall safety is treated as monolithic data complexity, coupling pose, dynamics, and terrain and requiring exhaustive coverage, limiting scalability and generalization. We present a unified fall safety approach that spans all phases of fall recovery. It builds on two insights: 1) Natural human fall and recovery poses are highly constrained and transferable from flat to complex terrain through alignment, and 2) Fast whole-body reactions require integrated perceptual-motor representations. We train a privileged teacher using sparse human demonstrations on flat terrain and simulated complex terrains, and distill it into a deployable student that relies only on egocentric depth and proprioception. The student learns how to react by matching the teacher's goal-in-context latent representation, which combines the next target pose with the local terrain, rather than separately encoding what it must perceive and how it must act. Results in simulation and on a real Unitree G1 humanoid demonstrate robust, zero-shot fall safety across diverse non-flat environments without real-world fine-tuning. The project page is available at https://vigor2026.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16511v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osher Azulay, Zhengjie Xu, Andrew Scheffer, Stella X. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized and Fully Onboard: Range-Aided Cooperative Localization and Navigation on Micro Aerial Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16594v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controlling a team of robots in a coordinated manner is challenging because centralized approaches (where all computation is performed on a central machine) scale poorly, and globally referenced external localization systems may not always be available. In this work, we consider the problem of range-aided decentralized localization and formation control. In such a setting, each robot estimates its relative pose by combining data only from onboard odometry sensors and distance measurements to other robots in the team. Additionally, each robot calculates the control inputs necessary to collaboratively navigate an environment to accomplish a specific task, for example, moving in a desired formation while monitoring an area. We present a block coordinate descent approach to localization that does not require strict coordination between the robots. We present a novel formulation for formation control as inference on factor graphs that takes into account the state estimation uncertainty and can be solved efficiently. Our approach to range-aided localization and formation-based navigation is completely decentralized, does not require specialized trajectories to maintain formation, and achieves decimeter-level positioning and formation control accuracy. We demonstrate our approach through multiple real experiments involving formation flights in diverse indoor and outdoor environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16594v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Goudar, Angela P. Schoellig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensor Query Schedule and Sensor Noise Covariances for Accuracy-constrained Trajectory Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16598v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trajectory estimation involves determining the trajectory of a mobile robot by combining prior knowledge about its dynamic model with noisy observations of its state obtained using sensors. The accuracy of such a procedure is dictated by the system model fidelity and the sensor parameters, such as the accuracy of the sensor (as represented by its noise covariance) and the rate at which it can generate observations, referred to as the sensor query schedule. Intuitively, high-rate measurements from accurate sensors lead to accurate trajectory estimation. However, cost and resource constraints limit the sensor accuracy and its measurement rate. Our work's novel contribution is the estimation of sensor schedules and sensor covariances necessary to achieve a specific estimation accuracy. Concretely, we focus on estimating: (i) the rate or schedule with which a sensor of known covariance must generate measurements to achieve specific estimation accuracy, and alternatively, (ii) the sensor covariance necessary to achieve specific estimation accuracy for a given sensor update rate. We formulate the problem of estimating these sensor parameters as semidefinite programs, which can be solved by off-the-shelf solvers. We validate our approach in simulation and real experiments by showing that the sensor schedules and the sensor covariances calculated using our proposed method achieve the desired trajectory estimation accuracy. Our method also identifies scenarios where certain estimation accuracy is unachievable with the given system and sensor characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16598v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Goudar, Angela P. Schoellig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Autonomous Robotic Kidney Ultrasound: Spatial-Efficient Volumetric Imaging via Template Guided Optimal Pivoting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Medical ultrasound (US) imaging is a frontline tool for the diagnosis of kidney diseases. However, traditional freehand imaging procedure suffers from inconsistent, operator-dependent outcomes, lack of 3D localization information, and risks of work-related musculoskeletal disorders. While robotic ultrasound (RUS) systems offer the potential for standardized, operator-independent 3D kidney data acquisition, the existing scanning methods lack the ability to determine the optimal imaging window for efficient imaging. As a result, the scan is often blindly performed with excessive probe footprint, which frequently leads to acoustic shadowing and incomplete organ coverage. Consequently, there is a critical need for a spatially efficient imaging technique that can maximize the kidney coverage through minimum probe footprint. Here, we propose an autonomous workflow to achieve efficient kidney imaging via template-guided optimal pivoting. The system first performs an explorative imaging to generate partial observations of the kidney. This data is then registered to a kidney template to estimate the organ pose. With the kidney localized, the robot executes a fixed-point pivoting sweep where the imaging plane is aligned with the kidney long axis to minimize the probe translation. The proposed method was validated in simulation and in-vivo. Simulation results indicate that a 60% exploration ratio provides optimal balance between kidney localization accuracy and scanning efficiency. In-vivo evaluation on two male subjects demonstrates a kidney localization accuracy up to 7.36 mm and 13.84 degrees. Moreover, the optimal pivoting approach shortened the probe footprint by around 75 mm when compared with the baselines. These results valid our approach of leveraging anatomical templates to align the probe optimally for volumetric sweep.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16641v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xihan Ma, Haichong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to unfold cloth: Scaling up world models to deformable object manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning to manipulate cloth is both a paradigmatic problem for robotic research and a problem of immediate relevance to a variety of applications ranging from assistive care to the service industry. The complex physics of the deformable object makes this problem of cloth manipulation nontrivial. In order to create a general manipulation strategy that addresses a variety of shapes, sizes, fold and wrinkle patterns, in addition to the usual problems of appearance variations, it becomes important to carefully consider model structure and their implications for generalisation performance. In this paper, we present an approach to in-air cloth manipulation that uses a variation of a recently proposed reinforcement learning architecture, DreamerV2. Our implementation modifies this architecture to utilise surface normals input, in addition to modiying the replay buffer and data augmentation procedures. Taken together these modifications represent an enhancement to the world model used by the robot, addressing the physical complexity of the object being manipulated by the robot. We present evaluations both in simulation and in a zero-shot deployment of the trained policies in a physical robot setup, performing in-air unfolding of a variety of different cloth types, demonstrating the generalisation benefits of our proposed architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16675v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Rome, Stephen James, Subramanian Ramamoorthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Humanoid End-Effector Control for Open-Vocabulary Visual Loco-Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Visual loco-manipulation of arbitrary objects in the wild with humanoid robots requires accurate end-effector (EE) control and a generalizable understanding of the scene via visual inputs (e.g., RGB-D images). Existing approaches are based on real-world imitation learning and exhibit limited generalization due to the difficulty in collecting large-scale training datasets. This paper presents a new paradigm, HERO, for object loco-manipulation with humanoid robots that combines the strong generalization and open-vocabulary understanding of large vision models with strong control performance from simulated training. We achieve this by designing an accurate residual-aware EE tracking policy. This EE tracking policy combines classical robotics with machine learning. It uses a) inverse kinematics to convert residual end-effector targets into reference trajectories, b) a learned neural forward model for accurate forward kinematics, c) goal adjustment, and d) replanning. Together, these innovations help us cut down the end-effector tracking error by 3.2x. We use this accurate end-effector tracker to build a modular system for loco-manipulation, where we use open-vocabulary large vision models for strong visual generalization. Our system is able to operate in diverse real-world environments, from offices to coffee shops, where the robot is able to reliably manipulate various everyday objects (e.g., mugs, apples, toys) on surfaces ranging from 43cm to 92cm in height. Systematic modular and end-to-end tests in simulation and the real world demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed design. We believe the advances in this paper can open up new ways of training humanoid robots to interact with daily objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16705v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runpei Dong, Ziyan Li, Xialin He, Saurabh Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoScale: Scaling Dexterous Manipulation with Diverse Egocentric Human Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Human behavior is among the most scalable sources of data for learning physical intelligence, yet how to effectively leverage it for dexterous manipulation remains unclear. While prior work demonstrates human to robot transfer in constrained settings, it is unclear whether large scale human data can support fine grained, high degree of freedom dexterous manipulation. We present EgoScale, a human to dexterous manipulation transfer framework built on large scale egocentric human data. We train a Vision Language Action (VLA) model on over 20,854 hours of action labeled egocentric human video, more than 20 times larger than prior efforts, and uncover a log linear scaling law between human data scale and validation loss. This validation loss strongly correlates with downstream real robot performance, establishing large scale human data as a predictable supervision source. Beyond scale, we introduce a simple two stage transfer recipe: large scale human pretraining followed by lightweight aligned human robot mid training. This enables strong long horizon dexterous manipulation and one shot task adaptation with minimal robot supervision. Our final policy improves average success rate by 54% over a no pretraining baseline using a 22 DoF dexterous robotic hand, and transfers effectively to robots with lower DoF hands, indicating that large scale human motion provides a reusable, embodiment agnostic motor prior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16710v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijie Zheng, Dantong Niu, Yuqi Xie, Jing Wang, Mengda Xu, Yunfan Jiang, Fernando Casta\~neda, Fengyuan Hu, You Liang Tan, Letian Fu, Trevor Darrell, Furong Huang, Yuke Zhu, Danfei Xu, Linxi Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Hand to Rule Them All: Canonical Representations for Unified Dexterous Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dexterous manipulation policies today largely assume fixed hand designs, severely restricting their generalization to new embodiments with varied kinematic and structural layouts. To overcome this limitation, we introduce a parameterized canonical representation that unifies a broad spectrum of dexterous hand architectures. It comprises a unified parameter space and a canonical URDF format, offering three key advantages. 1) The parameter space captures essential morphological and kinematic variations for effective conditioning in learning algorithms. 2) A structured latent manifold can be learned over our space, where interpolations between embodiments yield smooth and physically meaningful morphology transitions. 3) The canonical URDF standardizes the action space while preserving dynamic and functional properties of the original URDFs, enabling efficient and reliable cross-embodiment policy learning. We validate these advantages through extensive analysis and experiments, including grasp policy replay, VAE latent encoding, and cross-embodiment zero-shot transfer. Specifically, we train a VAE on the unified representation to obtain a compact, semantically rich latent embedding, and develop a grasping policy conditioned on the canonical representation that generalizes across dexterous hands. We demonstrate, through simulation and real-world tasks on unseen morphologies (e.g., 81.9% zero-shot success rate on 3-finger LEAP Hand), that our framework unifies both the representational and action spaces of structurally diverse hands, providing a scalable foundation for cross-hand learning toward universal dexterous manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16712v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Wei, Yunchao Yao, Mingyu Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Survey on Deep Learning-Based LiDAR Super-Resolution for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15904v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: LiDAR sensors are often considered essential for autonomous driving, but high-resolution sensors remain expensive while affordable low-resolution sensors produce sparse point clouds that miss critical details. LiDAR super-resolution addresses this challenge by using deep learning to enhance sparse point clouds, bridging the gap between different sensor types and enabling cross-sensor compatibility in real-world deployments. This paper presents the first comprehensive survey of LiDAR super-resolution methods for autonomous driving. Despite the importance of practical deployment, no systematic review has been conducted until now. We organize existing approaches into four categories: CNN-based architectures, model-based deep unrolling, implicit representation methods, and Transformer and Mamba-based approaches. We establish fundamental concepts including data representations, problem formulation, benchmark datasets and evaluation metrics. Current trends include the adoption of range image representation for efficient processing, extreme model compression and the development of resolution-flexible architectures. Recent research prioritizes real-time inference and cross-sensor generalization for practical deployment. We conclude by identifying open challenges and future research directions for advancing LiDAR super-resolution technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>June Moh Goo, Zichao Zeng, Jan Boehm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCAR: Satellite Imagery-Based Calibration for Aerial Recordings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce SCAR, a method for long-term auto-calibration refinement of aerial visual-inertial systems that exploits georeferenced satellite imagery as a persistent global reference. SCAR estimates both intrinsic and extrinsic parameters by aligning aerial images with 2D--3D correspondences derived from publicly available orthophotos and elevation models. In contrast to existing approaches that rely on dedicated calibration maneuvers or manually surveyed ground control points, our method leverages external geospatial data to detect and correct calibration degradation under field deployment conditions. We evaluate our approach on six large-scale aerial campaigns conducted over two years under diverse seasonal and environmental conditions. Across all sequences, SCAR consistently outperforms established baselines (Kalibr, COLMAP, VINS-Mono), reducing median reprojection error by a large margin, and translating these calibration gains into substantially lower visual localization rotation errors and higher pose accuracy. These results demonstrate that SCAR provides accurate, robust, and reproducible calibration over long-term aerial operations without the need for manual intervention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16349v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry H\"olzemann, Michael Schleiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-wideband Time Difference of Arrival Indoor Localization: From Sensor Placement to System Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12427v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Wireless indoor localization has attracted significant research interest due to its high accuracy, low cost, lightweight design, and low power consumption. Specifically, ultra-wideband (UWB) time difference of arrival (TDOA)-based localization has emerged as a scalable positioning solution for mobile robots, consumer electronics, and wearable devices, featuring good accuracy and reliability. While UWB TDOA-based localization systems rely on the deployment of UWB radio sensors as positioning landmarks, existing works often assume these placements are predetermined or study the sensor placement problem alone without evaluating it in practical scenarios. In this article, we bridge this gap by approaching the UWB TDOA localization from a system-level perspective, integrating sensor placement as a key component and conducting practical evaluation in real-world scenarios. Through extensive real-world experiments, we demonstrate the accuracy and robustness of our localization system, comparing its performance to the theoretical lower bounds. Using a challenging multi-room environment as a case study, we illustrate the full system construction process, from sensor placement optimization to real-world deployment. Our evaluation, comprising a cumulative total of 39 minutes of real-world experiments involving up to five agents and covering 2608 meters across four distinct scenarios, provides valuable insights and guidelines for constructing UWB TDOA localization systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12427v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenda Zhao, Abhishek Goudar, Mingliang Tang, Angela P. Schoellig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FindAnything: Open-Vocabulary and Object-Centric Mapping for Robot Exploration in Any Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08603v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Geometrically accurate and semantically expressive map representations have proven invaluable for robot deployment and task planning in unknown environments. Nevertheless, real-time, open-vocabulary semantic understanding of large-scale unknown environments still presents open challenges, mainly due to computational requirements. In this paper we present FindAnything, an open-world mapping framework that incorporates vision-language information into dense volumetric submaps. Thanks to the use of vision-language features, FindAnything combines pure geometric and open-vocabulary semantic information for a higher level of understanding. It proposes an efficient storage of open-vocabulary information through the aggregation of features at the object level. Pixelwise vision-language features are aggregated based on eSAM segments, which are in turn integrated into object-centric volumetric submaps, providing a mapping from open-vocabulary queries to 3D geometry that is scalable also in terms of memory usage. We demonstrate that FindAnything performs on par with the state-of-the-art in terms of semantic accuracy while being substantially faster and more memory-efficient, allowing its deployment in large-scale environments and on resourceconstrained devices, such as MAVs. We show that the real-time capabilities of FindAnything make it useful for downstream tasks, such as autonomous MAV exploration in a simulated Search and Rescue scenario. Project Page: https://ethz-mrl.github.io/findanything/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08603v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebasti\'an Barbas Laina, Simon Boche, Sotiris Papatheodorou, Simon Schaefer, Jaehyung Jung, Stefan Leutenegger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IMPACT: Behavioral Intention-aware Multimodal Trajectory Prediction with Adaptive Context Trimming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09103v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While most prior research has focused on improving the precision of multimodal trajectory predictions, the explicit modeling of multimodal behavioral intentions (e.g., yielding, overtaking) remains relatively underexplored. This paper proposes a unified framework that jointly predicts both behavioral intentions and trajectories to enhance prediction accuracy, interpretability, and efficiency. Specifically, we employ a shared context encoder for both intention and trajectory predictions, thereby reducing structural redundancy and information loss. Moreover, we address the lack of ground-truth behavioral intention labels in mainstream datasets (Waymo, Argoverse) by auto-labeling these datasets, thus advancing the community's efforts in this direction. We further introduce a vectorized occupancy prediction module that infers the probability of each map polyline being occupied by the target vehicle's future trajectory. By leveraging these intention and occupancy prediction priors, our method conducts dynamic, modality-dependent pruning of irrelevant agents and map polylines in the decoding stage, effectively reducing computational overhead and mitigating noise from non-critical elements. Our approach ranks first among LiDAR-free methods on the Waymo Motion Dataset and achieves first place on the Waymo Interactive Prediction Dataset. Remarkably, even without model ensembling, our single-model framework improves the soft mean average precision (softmAP) by 10 percent compared to the second-best method in the Waymo Interactive Prediction Leaderboard. Furthermore, the proposed framework has been successfully deployed on real vehicles, demonstrating its practical effectiveness in real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09103v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Sun, Xibin Yue, Jiahui Li, Tianle Shen, Chengran Yuan, Shuo Sun, Sheng Guo, Quanyun Zhou, Marcelo H Ang Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FreqPolicy: Efficient Flow-based Visuomotor Policy via Frequency Consistency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generative modeling-based visuomotor policies have been widely adopted in robotic manipulation, attributed to their ability to model multimodal action distributions. However, the high inference cost of multi-step sampling limits its applicability in real-time robotic systems. Existing approaches accelerate sampling in generative modeling-based visuomotor policies by adapting techniques originally developed to speed up image generation. However, a major distinction exists: image generation typically produces independent samples without temporal dependencies, while robotic manipulation requires generating action trajectories with continuity and temporal coherence. To this end, we propose FreqPolicy, a novel approach that first imposes frequency consistency constraints on flow-based visuomotor policies. Our work enables the action model to capture temporal structure effectively while supporting efficient, high-quality one-step action generation. Concretely, we introduce a frequency consistency constraint objective that enforces alignment of frequency-domain action features across different timesteps along the flow, thereby promoting convergence of one-step action generation toward the target distribution. In addition, we design an adaptive consistency loss to capture structural temporal variations inherent in robotic manipulation tasks. We assess FreqPolicy on 53 tasks across 3 simulation benchmarks, proving its superiority over existing one-step action generators. We further integrate FreqPolicy into the vision-language-action (VLA) model and achieve acceleration without performance degradation on 40 tasks of LIBERO. Besides, we show efficiency and effectiveness in real-world robotic scenarios with an inference frequency of 93.5 Hz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08822v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Su, Ning Liu, Dong Chen, Zhen Zhao, Kun Wu, Meng Li, Zhiyuan Xu, Zhengping Che, Jian Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Context-Aware Exoskeleton Assistance: Integrating Computer Vision Payload Estimation with a User-Centric Optimization Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Back-support exoskeletons (BSEs) mitigate musculoskeletal strain, yet their efficacy depends on precise, context-aware modulation. This paper introduces a user-centric optimization framework and a vision-based adaptive control strategy for industrial BSEs. First, we constructed a multi-metric optimization space, integrating electromyography reduction, perceived discomfort, and user preference, through baseline experiments with 12 subjects. This revealed a non-linear relationship between optimal assistance and payload. Second, we developed a predictive computer vision pipeline using a Vision Transformer (DINOv2) to estimate payloads before lifting, effectively overcoming actuation latency. Validation with 12 subjects confirmed the system's robustness, achieving over 82% estimation accuracy. Crucially, the adaptive controller reduced peak back muscle activation by up to 23% compared to static baselines while optimizing user comfort. These results validate the proposed framework, demonstrating that pre-lift environmental perception and user-centric optimization significantly enhance physical assistance and human-robot interaction in industrial settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06207v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Dal Prete, Seyram Ofori, Chan Yon Sin, Ashwin Narayan, Ding Shuo, Francesco Braghin, Marta Gandolla, Haoyong Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Robot Design with Multi-Objective Black-Box Optimization and Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17178v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Various methods for robot design optimization have been developed so far. These methods are diverse, ranging from numerical optimization to black-box optimization. While numerical optimization is fast, it is not suitable for cases involving complex structures or discrete values, leading to frequent use of black-box optimization instead. However, black-box optimization suffers from low sampling efficiency and takes considerable sampling iterations to obtain good solutions. In this study, we propose a method to enhance the efficiency of robot body design based on black-box optimization by utilizing large language models (LLMs). In parallel with the sampling process based on black-box optimization, sampling is performed using LLMs, which are provided with problem settings and extensive feedback. We demonstrate that this method enables more efficient exploration of design solutions and discuss its characteristics and limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17178v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2026.3664844</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kento Kawaharazuka, Yoshiki Obinata, Naoaki Kanazawa, Haoyu Jia, Kei Okada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Diffusion Policies for Robotic Manipulation of Timber Joinery under Fabrication Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17774v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fabrication uncertainties, such as tolerance accumulation and material imperfections, pose a significant challenge to contact-rich robotic manipulation in construction by hindering precise and robust assembly. In this paper, we investigate the performance and robustness of diffusion policy learning for contact-rich assembly at the construction scale, using a tight-fitting timber mortise and tenon joint as a case study. A two-phase experimental study is conducted: first, to evaluate baseline policy performance and applicability; second, to assess policy robustness under fabrication-induced uncertainties modeled as randomized perturbations to the mortise position. The diffusion policy is trained on teleoperated demonstrations using an industrial robotic arm conditioned on end-effector pose and force/torque feedback. The best-performing policy achieved a total average success rate of 75% under perturbations up to 10 mm, including 100% success in unperturbed cases. The results demonstrate the potential of sensory-motor diffusion policies to enable high-precision contact-rich manipulation on large-scale industrial robotic arms, reducing reliance on skilled manual intervention. This work advances robotic construction under uncertainty and provides practical insights for deploying learning-based control in real-world Architectural, Engineering, and Construction applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17774v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salma Mozaffari (Princeton University), Daniel Ruan (Princeton University), William van den Bogert (University of Michigan), Nima Fazeli (University of Michigan), Sigrid Adriaenssens (Princeton University), Arash Adel (Princeton University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkillWrapper: Generative Predicate Invention for Task-level Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18203v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generalizing from individual skill executions to solving long-horizon tasks remains a core challenge in building autonomous agents. A promising direction is learning high-level, symbolic abstractions of the low-level skills of the agents, enabling reasoning and planning independent of the low-level state space. Among possible high-level representations, object-centric skill abstraction with symbolic predicates has been proven to be efficient because of its compatibility with domain-independent planners. Recent advances in foundation models have made it possible to generate symbolic predicates that operate on raw sensory inputs, a process we call generative predicate invention, to facilitate downstream abstraction learning. However, it remains unclear which formal properties the learned representations must satisfy, and how they can be learned to guarantee these properties. In this paper, we address both questions by presenting a formal theory of generative predicate invention for skill abstraction, resulting in symbolic operators that can be used for provably sound and complete planning. Within this framework, we propose SkillWrapper, a method that leverages foundation models to actively collect robot data and learn human-interpretable, plannable representations of black-box skills, using only RGB image observations. Our extensive empirical evaluation in simulation and on real robots shows that SkillWrapper learns abstract representations that enable solving unseen, long-horizon tasks in the real world with black-box skills.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18203v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Yang, Benned Hedegaard, Ahmed Jaafar, Yichen Wei, Skye Thompson, Shreyas S. Raman, Haotian Fu, Stefanie Tellex, George Konidaris, David Paulius, Naman Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMBER: A tether-deployable gripping crawler with compliant microspines for canopy manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07680v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents an aerially deployable crawler designed for adaptive locomotion and manipulation within tree canopies. The system combines compliant microspine-based tracks, a dual-track rotary gripper, and an elastic tail, enabling secure attachment and stable traversal across branches of varying curvature and inclination. Experiments demonstrate reliable gripping up to 90$^\circ$ body roll and inclination, while effective climbing on branches inclined up to 67.5$^\circ$, achieving a maximum speed of 0.55 body lengths per second on horizontal branches. The compliant tracks allow yaw steering of up to 10$^\circ$, enhancing maneuverability on irregular surfaces. Power measurements show efficient operation with a dimensionless cost of transport over an order of magnitude lower than typical hovering power consumption in aerial robots. The crawler provides a robust, low-power platform for environmental sampling and in-canopy sensing. The aerial deployment is demonstrated at a conceptual and feasibility level, while full drone-crawler integration is left as future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07680v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. A. Wigner, L. Romanello, A. Hammad, P. H. Nguyen, T. Lan, S. F. Armanini, B. B. Kocer, M. Kovac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elements of Robot Morphology: Supporting Designers in Robot Form Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Robot morphology, the form, shape, and structure of robots, is a key design space in human-robot interaction (HRI), shaping how robots function, express themselves, and interact with people. Yet, despite its importance, little is known about how design frameworks can guide systematic form exploration. To address this gap, we introduce Elements of Robot Morphology, a framework that identifies five fundamental elements: perception, articulation, end effectors, locomotion, and structure. Derived from an analysis of existing robots, the framework supports structured exploration of diverse robot forms. To operationalize the framework, we developed Morphology Exploration Blocks (MEB), a set of tangible blocks that enable hands-on, collaborative experimentation with robot morphologies. We evaluate the framework and toolkit through a case study and design workshops, showing how they support analysis, ideation, reflection, and collaborative robot design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09203v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amy Koike, Serena Ge Guo, Xinning He, Callie Y. Kim, Dakota Sullivan, Bilge Mutlu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Verification Can Be More Effective than Scaling Policy Learning for Vision-Language-Action Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12281v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The long-standing vision of general-purpose robots hinges on their ability to understand and act upon natural language instructions. Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have made remarkable progress toward this goal, yet their generated actions can still misalign with the given instructions. In this paper, we investigate test-time verification as a means to shrink the "intention-action gap." We first characterize the test-time scaling laws for embodied instruction following and demonstrate that jointly scaling the number of rephrased instructions and generated actions greatly increases test-time sample diversity, often recovering correct actions more efficiently than scaling each dimension independently. To capitalize on these scaling laws, we present CoVer, a contrastive verifier for vision-language-action alignment, and show that our architecture scales gracefully with additional computational resources and data. We then introduce CoVer-VLA, a hierarchical test-time verification pipeline using the trained verifier. At deployment, our framework precomputes a diverse set of rephrased instructions from a Vision-Language-Model (VLM), repeatedly generates action candidates for each instruction, and then uses the verifier to select the optimal high-level prompt and low-level action chunks. Compared to scaling policy pre-training on the same data, our verification approach yields 22% gains in-distribution and 13% out-of-distribution on the SIMPLER benchmark, with a further 45% improvement in real-world experiments. On the PolaRiS benchmark, CoVer-VLA achieves 14% gains in task progress and 9% in success rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12281v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacky Kwok, Xilun Zhang, Mengdi Xu, Yuejiang Liu, Azalia Mirhoseini, Chelsea Finn, Marco Pavone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BPP: Long-Context Robot Imitation Learning by Focusing on Key History Frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many robot tasks require attending to the history of past observations. For example, finding an item in a room requires remembering which places have already been searched. However, the best-performing robot policies typically condition only on the current observation, limiting their applicability to such tasks. Naively conditioning on past observations often fails due to spurious correlations: policies latch onto incidental features of training histories that do not generalize to out-of-distribution trajectories upon deployment. We analyze why policies latch onto these spurious correlations and find that this problem stems from limited coverage over the space of possible histories during training, which grows exponentially with horizon. Existing regularization techniques provide inconsistent benefits across tasks, as they do not fundamentally address this coverage problem. Motivated by these findings, we propose Big Picture Policies (BPP), an approach that conditions on a minimal set of meaningful keyframes detected by a vision-language model. By projecting diverse rollouts onto a compact set of task-relevant events, BPP substantially reduces distribution shift between training and deployment, without sacrificing expressivity. We evaluate BPP on four challenging real-world manipulation tasks and three simulation tasks, all requiring history conditioning. BPP achieves 70% higher success rates than the best comparison on real-world evaluations. Videos are available at https://bigpicturepolicies.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15010v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Sobol Mark, Jacky Liang, Maria Attarian, Chuyuan Fu, Debidatta Dwibedi, Dhruv Shah, Aviral Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboSpatial: Teaching Spatial Understanding to 2D and 3D Vision-Language Models for Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16537v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spatial understanding is a crucial capability that enables robots to perceive their surroundings, reason about their environment, and interact with it meaningfully. In modern robotics, these capabilities are increasingly provided by vision-language models. However, these models face significant challenges in spatial reasoning tasks, as their training data are based on general-purpose image datasets that often lack sophisticated spatial understanding. For example, datasets frequently do not capture reference frame comprehension, yet effective spatial reasoning requires understanding whether to reason from ego-, world-, or object-centric perspectives. To address this issue, we introduce RoboSpatial, a large-scale dataset for spatial understanding in robotics. It consists of real indoor and tabletop scenes, captured as 3D scans and egocentric images, and annotated with rich spatial information relevant to robotics. The dataset includes 1M images, 5k 3D scans, and 3M annotated spatial relationships, and the pairing of 2D egocentric images with 3D scans makes it both 2D- and 3D- ready. Our experiments show that models trained with RoboSpatial outperform baselines on downstream tasks such as spatial affordance prediction, spatial relationship prediction, and robot manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16537v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chan Hee Song, Valts Blukis, Jonathan Tremblay, Stephen Tyree, Yu Su, Stan Birchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SurgRAW: Multi-Agent Workflow with Chain of Thought Reasoning for Robotic Surgical Video Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10265v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Robotic-assisted surgery (RAS) is central to modern surgery, driving the need for intelligent systems with accurate scene understanding. Most existing surgical AI methods rely on isolated, task-specific models, leading to fragmented pipelines with limited interpretability and no unified understanding of RAS scene. Vision-Language Models (VLMs) offer strong zero-shot reasoning, but struggle with hallucinations, domain gaps and weak task-interdependency modeling. To address the lack of unified data for RAS scene understanding, we introduce SurgCoTBench, the first reasoning-focused benchmark in RAS, covering 14256 QA pairs with frame-level annotations across five major surgical tasks. Building on SurgCoTBench, we propose SurgRAW, a clinically aligned Chain-of-Thought (CoT) driven agentic workflow for zero-shot multi-task reasoning in surgery. SurgRAW employs a hierarchical reasoning workflow where an orchestrator divides surgical scene understanding into two reasoning streams and directs specialized agents to generate task-level reasoning, while higher-level agents capture workflow interdependencies or ground output clinically. Specifically, we propose a panel discussion mechanism to ensure task-specific agents collaborate synergistically and leverage on task interdependencies. Similarly, we incorporate a retrieval-augmented generation module to enrich agents with surgical knowledge and alleviate domain gaps in general VLMs. We design task-specific CoT prompts grounded in surgical domain to ensure clinically aligned reasoning, reduce hallucinations and enhance interpretability. Extensive experiments show that SurgRAW surpasses mainstream VLMs and agentic systems and outperforms a supervised model by 14.61% accuracy. Dataset and code is available at https://github.com/jinlab-imvr/SurgRAW.git .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10265v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2026.3665443</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, 2026, pp. 1-8</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chang Han Low, Ziyue Wang, Tianyi Zhang, Zhu Zhuo, Zhitao Zeng, Evangelos B. Mazomenos, Yueming Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query-Based Adaptive Aggregation for Multi-Dataset Joint Training Toward Universal Visual Place Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03831v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Deep learning methods for Visual Place Recognition (VPR) have advanced significantly, largely driven by large-scale datasets. However, most existing approaches are trained on a single dataset, which can introduce dataset-specific inductive biases and limit model generalization. While multi-dataset joint training offers a promising solution for developing universal VPR models, divergences among training datasets can saturate the limited information capacity in feature aggregation layers, leading to suboptimal performance. To address these challenges, we propose Query-based Adaptive Aggregation (QAA), a novel feature aggregation technique that leverages learned queries as reference codebooks to effectively enhance information capacity without significant computational or parameter complexity. We show that computing the Cross-query Similarity (CS) between query-level image features and reference codebooks provides a simple yet effective way to generate robust descriptors. Our results demonstrate that QAA outperforms state-of-the-art models, achieving balanced generalization across diverse datasets while maintaining peak performance comparable to dataset-specific models. Ablation studies further explore QAA's mechanisms and scalability. Visualizations reveal that the learned queries exhibit diverse attention patterns across datasets. Project page: http://xjh19971.github.io/QAA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03831v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiuhong Xiao, Yang Zhou, Giuseppe Loianno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>View Invariant Learning for Vision-Language Navigation in Continuous Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08831v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vision-Language Navigation in Continuous Environments (VLNCE), where an agent follows instructions and moves freely to reach a destination, is a key research problem in embodied AI. However, most navigation policies are sensitive to viewpoint changes, i.e., variations in camera height and viewing angle that alter the agent's observation. In this paper, we introduce a generalized scenario, V2-VLNCE (VLNCE with Varied Viewpoints), and propose VIL (View Invariant Learning), a view-invariant post-training strategy that enhances the robustness of existing navigation policies to changes in camera viewpoint. VIL employs a contrastive learning framework to learn sparse and view-invariant features. Additionally, we introduce a teacher-student framework for the Waypoint Predictor Module, a core component of most VLNCE baselines, where a view-dependent teacher model distills knowledge into a view-invariant student model. We employ an end-to-end training paradigm to jointly optimize these components, thus eliminating the cost for individual module training. Empirical results show that our method outperforms state-of-the-art approaches on V2-VLNCE by 8-15% measured on Success Rate for two standard benchmark datasets R2R-CE and RxR-CE. Furthermore, we evaluate VIL under the standard VLNCE setting and find that, despite being trained for varied viewpoints, it often still improves performance. On the more challenging RxR-CE dataset, our method also achieved state-of-the-art performance across all metrics when compared to other map-free methods. This suggests that adding VIL does not diminish the standard viewpoint performance and can serve as a plug-and-play post-training method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08831v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Qixuan Sun, Xiaoying Xing, Huaiyuan Weng, Chul Min Yeum, Mark Crowley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverting Non-Injective Functions with Twin Neural Network Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05378v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-injective functions are not globally invertible. However, they can often be restricted to locally injective subdomains where the inversion is well-defined. In many settings a preferred solution can be selected even when multiple valid preimages exist or input and output dimensions differ. This manuscript describes a natural reformulation of the inverse learning problem for non-injective functions as a collection of locally invertible problems. More precisely, Twin Neural Network Regression is trained to predict local inverse corrections around known anchor points. By anchoring predictions to points within the same locally invertible region, the method consistently selects a valid branch of the inverse. In contrast to current probabilistic state-of-the art inversion methods, Inverse Twin Neural Network Regression is a deterministic framework for resolving multi-valued inverse mappings. I demonstrate the approach on problems that are defined by mathematical equations or by data, including multi-solution toy problems and robot arm inverse kinematics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05378v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian J. Wetzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Shot UAV Navigation in Forests via Relightable 3D Gaussian Splatting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: UAV navigation in unstructured outdoor environments using passive monocular vision is hindered by the substantial visual domain gap between simulation and reality. While 3D Gaussian Splatting enables photorealistic scene reconstruction from real-world data, existing methods inherently couple static lighting with geometry, severely limiting policy generalization to dynamic real-world illumination. In this paper, we propose a novel end-to-end reinforcement learning framework designed for effective zero-shot transfer to unstructured outdoors. Within a high-fidelity simulation grounded in real-world data, our policy is trained to map raw monocular RGB observations directly to continuous control commands. To overcome photometric limitations, we introduce Relightable 3D Gaussian Splatting, which decomposes scene components to enable explicit, physically grounded editing of environmental lighting within the neural representation. By augmenting training with diverse synthesized lighting conditions ranging from strong directional sunlight to diffuse overcast skies, we compel the policy to learn robust, illumination-invariant visual features. Extensive real-world experiments demonstrate that a lightweight quadrotor achieves robust, collision-free navigation in complex forest environments at speeds up to 10 m/s, exhibiting significant resilience to drastic lighting variations without fine-tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07101v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zinan Lv, Yeqian Qian, Chen Sang, Hao Liu, Danping Zou, Ming Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision and Language: Novel Representations and Artificial intelligence for Driving Scene Safety Assessment and Autonomous Vehicle Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07680v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vision-language models (VLMs) have recently emerged as powerful representation learning systems that align visual observations with natural language concepts, offering new opportunities for semantic reasoning in safety-critical autonomous driving. This paper investigates how vision-language representations support driving scene safety assessment and decision-making when integrated into perception, prediction, and planning pipelines. We study three complementary system-level use cases. First, we introduce a lightweight, category-agnostic hazard screening approach leveraging CLIP-based image-text similarity to produce a low-latency semantic hazard signal. This enables robust detection of diverse and out-of-distribution road hazards without explicit object detection or visual question answering. Second, we examine the integration of scene-level vision-language embeddings into a transformer-based trajectory planning framework using the Waymo Open Dataset. Our results show that naively conditioning planners on global embeddings does not improve trajectory accuracy, highlighting the importance of representation-task alignment and motivating the development of task-informed extraction methods for safety-critical planning. Third, we investigate natural language as an explicit behavioral constraint on motion planning using the doScenes dataset. In this setting, passenger-style instructions grounded in visual scene elements suppress rare but severe planning failures and improve safety-aligned behavior in ambiguous scenarios. Taken together, these findings demonstrate that vision-language representations hold significant promise for autonomous driving safety when used to express semantic risk, intent, and behavioral constraints. Realizing this potential is fundamentally an engineering problem requiring careful system design and structured grounding rather than direct feature injection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07680v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ross Greer, Maitrayee Keskar, Angel Martinez-Sanchez, Parthib Roy, Shashank Shriram, Mohan Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
