<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.RO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO</link>
    <description>cs.RO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.RO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Formal Safety Guarantees for Autonomous Vehicles using Barrier Certificates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern AI technologies enable autonomous vehicles to perceive complex scenes, predict human behavior, and make real-time driving decisions. However, these data-driven components often operate as black boxes, lacking interpretability and rigorous safety guarantees. Autonomous vehicles operate in dynamic, mixed-traffic environments where interactions with human-driven vehicles introduce uncertainty and safety challenges. This work develops a formally verified safety framework for Connected and Autonomous Vehicles (CAVs) that integrates Barrier Certificates (BCs) with interpretable traffic conflict metrics, specifically Time-to-Collision (TTC) as a spatio-temporal safety metric. Safety conditions are verified using Satisfiability Modulo Theories (SMT) solvers, and an adaptive control mechanism ensures vehicles comply with these constraints in real time. Evaluation on real-world highway datasets shows a significant reduction in unsafe interactions, with up to 40\% fewer events where TTC falls below a 3 seconds threshold, and complete elimination of conflicts in some lanes. This approach provides both interpretable and provable safety guarantees, demonstrating a practical and scalable strategy for safe autonomous driving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09740v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oumaima Barhoumi, Mohamed H Zaki, Sofi\`ene Tahar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interprofessional and Agile Development of Mobirobot: A Socially Assistive Robot for Pediatric Therapy Across Clinical and Therapeutic Settings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Introduction: Socially assistive robots hold promise for enhancing therapeutic engagement in paediatric clinical settings. However, their successful implementation requires not only technical robustness but also context-sensitive, co-designed solutions. This paper presents Mobirobot, a socially assistive robot developed to support mobilisation in children recovering from trauma, fractures, or depressive disorders through personalised exercise programmes.
  Methods: An agile, human-centred development approach guided the iterative design of Mobirobot. Multidisciplinary clinical teams and end users were involved throughout the co-development process, which focused on early integration into real-world paediatric surgical and psychiatric settings. The robot, based on the NAO platform, features a simple setup, adaptable exercise routines with interactive guidance, motivational dialogue, and a graphical user interface (GUI) for monitoring and no-code system feedback.
  Results: Deployment in hospital environments enabled the identification of key design requirements and usability constraints. Stakeholder feedback led to refinements in interaction design, movement capabilities, and technical configuration. A feasibility study is currently underway to assess acceptance, usability, and perceived therapeutic benefit, with data collection including questionnaires, behavioural observations, and staff-patient interviews.
  Discussion: Mobirobot demonstrates how multiprofessional, stakeholder-led development can yield a socially assistive system suited for dynamic inpatient settings. Early-stage findings underscore the importance of contextual integration, robustness, and minimal-intrusion design. While challenges such as sensor limitations and patient recruitment remain, the platform offers a promising foundation for further research and clinical application.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09838v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonie Dyck, Aiko Galetzka, Maximilian Noller, Anna-Lena Rinke, Jutta Bormann, Jekaterina Miller, Michelle Hochbaum, Julia Siemann, J\"ordis Alboth, Andre Berwinkel, Johanna Luz, Britta Kley-Zobel, Marcine Cyrys, Nora Fl\"ottmann, Ariane Vogeler, Mariia Melnikova, Ira-Katharina Petras, Michael Siniatchkin, Winfried Barthlen, Anna-Lisa Vollmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Human Motion Prediction Quality Shapes Social Robot Navigation Performance in Constrained Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the vision of integrating mobile robots closer to humans in warehouses, hospitals, manufacturing plants, and the home, we focus on robot navigation in dynamic and spatially constrained environments. Ensuring human safety, comfort, and efficiency in such settings requires that robots are endowed with a model of how humans move around them. Human motion prediction around robots is especially challenging due to the stochasticity of human behavior, differences in user preferences, and data scarcity. In this work, we perform a methodical investigation of the effects of human motion prediction quality on robot navigation performance, as well as human productivity and impressions. We design a scenario involving robot navigation among two human subjects in a constrained workspace and instantiate it in a user study ($N=80$) involving two different robot platforms, conducted across two sites from different world regions. Key findings include evidence that: 1) the widely adopted average displacement error is not a reliable predictor of robot navigation performance and human impressions; 2) the common assumption of human cooperation breaks down in constrained environments, with users often not reciprocating robot cooperation, and causing performance degradations; 3) more efficient robot navigation often comes at the expense of human efficiency and comfort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09856v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Stratton, Phani Teja Singamaneni, Pranav Goyal, Rachid Alami, Christoforos Mavrogiannis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SyncTwin: Fast Digital Twin Construction and Synchronization for Safe Robotic Grasping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and safe grasping under dynamic and visually occluded conditions remains a core challenge in real-world robotic manipulation. We present SyncTwin, a digital twin framework that unifies fast 3D scene reconstruction and real-to-sim synchronization for robust and safety-aware grasping in such environments. In the offline stage, we employ VGGT to rapidly reconstruct object-level 3D assets from RGB images, forming a reusable geometry library for simulation. During execution, SyncTwin continuously synchronizes the digital twin by tracking real-world object states via point cloud segmentation updates and aligning them through colored-ICP registration. The updated twin enables motion planners to compute collision-free and dynamically feasible trajectories in simulation, which are safely executed on the real robot through a closed real-to-sim-to-real loop. Experiments in dynamic and occluded scenes show that SyncTwin improves grasp accuracy and motion safety, demonstrating the effectiveness of digital-twin synchronization for real-world robotic execution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09920v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruopeng Huang, Boyu Yang, Wenlong Gui, Jeremy Morgan, Erdem Biyik, Jiachen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-the-Wild Compliant Manipulation with UMI-FT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many manipulation tasks require careful force modulation. With insufficient force the task may fail, while excessive force could cause damage. The high cost, bulky size and fragility of commercial force/torque (F/T) sensors have limited large-scale, force-aware policy learning. We introduce UMI-FT, a handheld data-collection platform that mounts compact, six-axis force/torque sensors on each finger, enabling finger-level wrench measurements alongside RGB, depth, and pose. Using the multimodal data collected from this device, we train an adaptive compliance policy that predicts position targets, grasp force, and stiffness for execution on standard compliance controllers. In evaluations on three contact-rich, force-sensitive tasks (whiteboard wiping, skewering zucchini, and lightbulb insertion), UMI-FT enables policies that reliably regulate external contact forces and internal grasp forces, outperforming baselines that lack compliance or force sensing. UMI-FT offers a scalable path to learning compliant manipulation from in-the-wild demonstrations. We open-source the hardware and software to facilitate broader adoption at:https://umi-ft.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09988v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hojung Choi, Yifan Hou, Chuer Pan, Seongheon Hong, Austin Patel, Xiaomeng Xu, Mark R. Cutkosky, Shuran Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoCoPlan: Adaptive Coordination and Communication for Multi-robot Systems in Dynamic and Unknown Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-robot systems can greatly enhance efficiency through coordination and collaboration, yet in practice, full-time communication is rarely available and interactions are constrained to close-range exchanges. Existing methods either maintain all-time connectivity, rely on fixed schedules, or adopt pairwise protocols, but none adapt effectively to dynamic spatio-temporal task distributions under limited communication, resulting in suboptimal coordination. To address this gap, we propose CoCoPlan, a unified framework that co-optimizes collaborative task planning and team-wise intermittent communication. Our approach integrates a branch-and-bound architecture that jointly encodes task assignments and communication events, an adaptive objective function that balances task efficiency against communication latency, and a communication event optimization module that strategically determines when, where and how the global connectivity should be re-established. Extensive experiments demonstrate that it outperforms state-of-the-art methods by achieving a 22.4% higher task completion rate, reducing communication overhead by 58.6%, and improving the scalability by supporting up to 100 robots in dynamic environments. Hardware experiments include the complex 2D office environment and large-scale 3D disaster-response scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xintong Zhang, Junfeng Chen, Yuxiao Zhu, Bing Luo, Meng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terrain-Adaptive Mobile 3D Printing with Hierarchical Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobile 3D printing on unstructured terrain remains challenging due to the conflict between platform mobility and deposition precision. Existing gantry-based systems achieve high accuracy but lack mobility, while mobile platforms struggle to maintain print quality on uneven ground. We present a framework that tightly integrates AI-driven disturbance prediction with multi-modal sensor fusion and hierarchical hardware control, forming a closed-loop perception-learning-actuation system. The AI module learns terrain-to-perturbation mappings from IMU, vision, and depth sensors, enabling proactive compensation rather than reactive correction. This intelligence is embedded into a three-layer control architecture: path planning, predictive chassis-manipulator coordination, and precision hardware execution. Through outdoor experiments on terrain with slopes and surface irregularities, we demonstrate sub-centimeter printing accuracy while maintaining full platform mobility. This AI-hardware integration establishes a practical foundation for autonomous construction in unstructured environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10208v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuangshan Nors Li, J. Nathan Kutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Framework for Kinematic Simulation of Rigid Foldable Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Origami-inspired structures with rigid panels now span thick, kirigami, and multi-sheet realizations, making unified kinematic analysis essential. Yet a general method that consolidates their loop constraints has been lacking. We present an automated approach that generates the Pfaffian constraint matrix for arbitrary rigid foldable structures (RFS). From a minimally extended data schema, the tool constructs the facet-hinge graph, extracts a minimum cycle basis that captures all constraints, and assembles a velocity-level constraint matrix via screw theory that encodes coupled rotation and translation loop closure. The framework computes and visualizes deploy and fold motions across diverse RFS while eliminating tedious and error-prone constraint calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10225v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongwook Kwak, Geonhee Cho, Jiook Chung, Jinkyu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proactive Local-Minima-Free Robot Navigation: Blending Motion Prediction with Safe Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work addresses the challenge of safe and efficient mobile robot navigation in complex dynamic environments with concave moving obstacles. Reactive safe controllers like Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) design obstacle avoidance strategies based only on the current states of the obstacles, risking future collisions. To alleviate this problem, we use Gaussian processes to learn barrier functions online from multimodal motion predictions of obstacles generated by neural networks trained with energy-based learning. The learned barrier functions are then fed into quadratic programs using modulated CBFs (MCBFs), a local-minimum-free version of CBFs, to achieve safe and efficient navigation. The proposed framework makes two key contributions. First, it develops a prediction-to-barrier function online learning pipeline. Second, it introduces an autonomous parameter tuning algorithm that adapts MCBFs to deforming, prediction-based barrier functions. The framework is evaluated in both simulations and real-world experiments, consistently outperforming baselines and demonstrating superior safety and efficiency in crowded dynamic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10233v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Xue, Ze Zhang, Knut {\AA}kesson, Nadia Figueroa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of tactile sensor configurations on grasp learning efficiency -- a comparative evaluation in simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tactile sensors are breaking into the field of robotics to provide direct information related to contact surfaces, including contact events, slip events and even texture identification. These events are especially important for robotic hand designs, including prosthetics, as they can greatly improve grasp stability. Most presently published robotic hand designs, however, implement them in vastly different densities and layouts on the hand surface, often reserving the majority of the available space. We used simulations to evaluate 6 different tactile sensor configurations with different densities and layouts, based on their impact on reinforcement learning. Our two-setup system allows for robust results that are not dependent on the use of a given physics simulator, robotic hand model or machine learning algorithm. Our results show setup-specific, as well as generalized effects across the 6 sensorized simulations, and we identify one configuration as consistently yielding the best performance across both setups. These results could help future research aimed at robotic hand designs, including prostheses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10268v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eszter Birtalan, Mikl\'os Koller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHORAL: Traversal-Aware Planning for Safe and Efficient Heterogeneous Multi-Robot Routing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monitoring large, unknown, and complex environments with autonomous robots poses significant navigation challenges, where deploying teams of heterogeneous robots with complementary capabilities can substantially improve both mission performance and feasibility. However, effectively modeling how different robotic platforms interact with the environment requires rich, semantic scene understanding. Despite this, existing approaches often assume homogeneous robot teams or focus on discrete task compatibility rather than continuous routing. Consequently, scene understanding is not fully integrated into routing decisions, limiting their ability to adapt to the environment and to leverage each robot's strengths. In this paper, we propose an integrated semantic-aware framework for coordinating heterogeneous robots. Starting from a reconnaissance flight, we build a metric-semantic map using open-vocabulary vision models and use it to identify regions requiring closer inspection and capability-aware paths for each platform to reach them. These are then incorporated into a heterogeneous vehicle routing formulation that jointly assigns inspection tasks and computes robot trajectories. Experiments in simulation and in a real inspection mission with three robotic platforms demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in planning safer and more efficient routes by explicitly accounting for each platform's navigation capabilities. We release our framework, CHORAL, as open source to support reproducibility and deployment of diverse robot teams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10340v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Morilla-Cabello, Eduardo Montijano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FastStair: Learning to Run Up Stairs with Humanoid Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Running up stairs is effortless for humans but remains extremely challenging for humanoid robots due to the simultaneous requirements of high agility and strict stability. Model-free reinforcement learning (RL) can generate dynamic locomotion, yet implicit stability rewards and heavy reliance on task-specific reward shaping tend to result in unsafe behaviors, especially on stairs; conversely, model-based foothold planners encode contact feasibility and stability structure, but enforcing their hard constraints often induces conservative motion that limits speed. We present FastStair, a planner-guided, multi-stage learning framework that reconciles these complementary strengths to achieve fast and stable stair ascent. FastStair integrates a parallel model-based foothold planner into the RL training loop to bias exploration toward dynamically feasible contacts and to pretrain a safety-focused base policy. To mitigate planner-induced conservatism and the discrepancy between low- and high-speed action distributions, the base policy was fine-tuned into speed-specialized experts and then integrated via Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) to enable smooth operation across the full commanded-speed range. We deploy the resulting controller on the Oli humanoid robot, achieving stable stair ascent at commanded speeds up to 1.65 m/s and traversing a 33-step spiral staircase (17 cm rise per step) in 12 s, demonstrating robust high-speed performance on long staircases. Notably, the proposed approach served as the champion solution in the Canton Tower Robot Run Up Competition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10365v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Liu, Tao Yu, Haolin Song, Hongbo Zhu, Nianzong Hu, Yuzhi Hao, Xiuyong Yao, Xizhe Zang, Hua Chen, Jie Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online identification of nonlinear time-varying systems with uncertain information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital twins (DTs), serving as the core enablers for real-time monitoring and predictive maintenance of complex cyber-physical systems, impose critical requirements on their virtual models: high predictive accuracy, strong interpretability, and online adaptive capability. However, existing techniques struggle to meet these demands simultaneously: Bayesian methods excel in uncertainty quantification but lack model interpretability, while interpretable symbolic identification methods (e.g., SINDy) are constrained by their offline, batch-processing nature, which make real-time updates challenging. To bridge this semantic and computational gap, this paper proposes a novel Bayesian Regression-based Symbolic Learning (BRSL) framework. The framework formulates online symbolic discovery as a unified probabilistic state-space model. By incorporating sparse horseshoe priors, model selection is transformed into a Bayesian inference task, enabling simultaneous system identification and uncertainty quantification. Furthermore, we derive an online recursive algorithm with a forgetting factor and establish precise recursive conditions that guarantee the well-posedness of the posterior distribution. These conditions also function as real-time monitors for data utility, enhancing algorithmic robustness. Additionally, a rigorous convergence analysis is provided, demonstrating the convergence of parameter estimates under persistent excitation conditions. Case studies validate the effectiveness of the proposed framework in achieving interpretable, probabilistic prediction and online learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10379v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He Ren, Gaowei Yan, Hang Liu, Lifeng Cao, Zhijun Zhao, Gang Dang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Organizing Dual-Buffer Adaptive Clustering Experience Replay (SODASER) for Safe Reinforcement Learning in Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06540v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel reinforcement learning framework, named Self-Organizing Dual-buffer Adaptive Clustering Experience Replay (SODACER), designed to achieve safe and scalable optimal control of nonlinear systems. The proposed SODACER mechanism consisting of a Fast-Buffer for rapid adaptation to recent experiences and a Slow-Buffer equipped with a self-organizing adaptive clustering mechanism to maintain diverse and non-redundant historical experiences. The adaptive clustering mechanism dynamically prunes redundant samples, optimizing memory efficiency while retaining critical environmental patterns. The approach integrates SODASER with Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) to guarantee safety by enforcing state and input constraints throughout the learning process. To enhance convergence and stability, the framework is combined with the Sophia optimizer, enabling adaptive second-order gradient updates. The proposed SODACER-Sophia's architecture ensures reliable, effective, and robust learning in dynamic, safety-critical environments, offering a generalizable solution for applications in robotics, healthcare, and large-scale system optimization. The proposed approach is validated on a nonlinear Human Papillomavirus (HPV) transmission model with multiple control inputs and safety constraints. Comparative evaluations against random and clustering-based experience replay methods demonstrate that SODACER achieves faster convergence, improved sample efficiency, and a superior bias-variance trade-off, while maintaining safe system trajectories, validated via the Friedman test.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06540v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roya Khalili Amirabadi, Mohsen Jalaeian Farimani, Omid Solaymani Fard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous computing platform for real-time robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: After Industry 4.0 has embraced tight integration between machinery (OT), software (IT), and the Internet, creating a web of sensors, data, and algorithms in service of efficient and reliable production, a new concept of Society 5.0 is emerging, in which infrastructure of a city will be instrumented to increase reliability, efficiency, and safety. Robotics will play a pivotal role in enabling this vision that is pioneered by the NEOM initiative - a smart city, co-inhabited by humans and robots. In this paper we explore the computing platform that will be required to enable this vision. We show how we can combine neuromorphic computing hardware, exemplified by the Loihi2 processor used in conjunction with event-based cameras, for sensing and real-time perception and interaction with a local AI compute cluster (GPUs) for high-level language processing, cognition, and task planning. We demonstrate the use of this hybrid computing architecture in an interactive task, in which a humanoid robot plays a musical instrument with a human. Central to our design is the efficient and seamless integration of disparate components, ensuring that the synergy between software and hardware maximizes overall performance and responsiveness. Our proposed system architecture underscores the potential of heterogeneous computing architectures in advancing robotic autonomy and interactive intelligence, pointing toward a future where such integrated systems become the norm in complex, real-time applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09755v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Fil, Yulia Sandamirskaya, Hector Gonzalez, Lo\"ic Azzalin, Stefan Gl\"uge, Lukas Friedenstab, Friedrich Wolf, Tim Rosmeisl, Matthias Lohrmann, Mahmoud Akl, Khaleel Khan, Leonie Wolf, Kristin Richter, Holm Puder, Mazhar Ali Bari, Xuan Choo, Noha Alharthi, Michael Hopkins, Mansoor Hanif Christian Mayr, Jens Struckmeier, Steve Furber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LCF3D: A Robust and Real-Time Late-Cascade Fusion Framework for 3D Object Detection in Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurately localizing 3D objects like pedestrians, cyclists, and other vehicles is essential in Autonomous Driving. To ensure high detection performance, Autonomous Vehicles complement RGB cameras with LiDAR sensors, but effectively combining these data sources for 3D object detection remains challenging. We propose LCF3D, a novel sensor fusion framework that combines a 2D object detector on RGB images with a 3D object detector on LiDAR point clouds. By leveraging multimodal fusion principles, we compensate for inaccuracies in the LiDAR object detection network. Our solution combines two key principles: (i) late fusion, to reduce LiDAR False Positives by matching LiDAR 3D detections with RGB 2D detections and filtering out unmatched LiDAR detections; and (ii) cascade fusion, to recover missed objects from LiDAR by generating new 3D frustum proposals corresponding to unmatched RGB detections. Experiments show that LCF3D is beneficial for domain generalization, as it turns out to be successful in handling different sensor configurations between training and testing domains. LCF3D achieves significant improvements over LiDAR-based methods, particularly for challenging categories like pedestrians and cyclists in the KITTI dataset, as well as motorcycles and bicycles in nuScenes. Code can be downloaded from: https://github.com/CarloSgaravatti/LCF3D.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09812v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.patcog.2026.113046</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Sgaravatti, Riccardo Pieroni, Matteo Corno, Sergio M. Savaresi, Luca Magri, Giacomo Boracchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OT-Drive: Out-of-Distribution Off-Road Traversable Area Segmentation via Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09952v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reliable traversable area segmentation in unstructured environments is critical for planning and decision-making in autonomous driving. However, existing data-driven approaches often suffer from degraded segmentation performance in out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios, consequently impairing downstream driving tasks. To address this issue, we propose OT-Drive, an Optimal Transport--driven multi-modal fusion framework. The proposed method formulates RGB and surface normal fusion as a distribution transport problem. Specifically, we design a novel Scene Anchor Generator (SAG) to decompose scene information into the joint distribution of weather, time-of-day, and road type, thereby constructing semantic anchors that can generalize to unseen scenarios. Subsequently, we design an innovative Optimal Transport-based multi-modal fusion module (OT Fusion) to transport RGB and surface normal features onto the manifold defined by the semantic anchors, enabling robust traversable area segmentation under OOD scenarios. Experimental results demonstrate that our method achieves 95.16% mIoU on ORFD OOD scenarios, outperforming prior methods by 6.35%, and 89.79% mIoU on cross-dataset transfer tasks, surpassing baselines by 13.99%.These results indicate that the proposed model can attain strong OOD generalization with only limited training data, substantially enhancing its practicality and efficiency for real-world deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09952v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhihua Zhao, Guoqiang Li, Chen Min, Kangping Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UEOF: A Benchmark Dataset for Underwater Event-Based Optical Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10054v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Underwater imaging is fundamentally challenging due to wavelength-dependent light attenuation, strong scattering from suspended particles, turbidity-induced blur, and non-uniform illumination. These effects impair standard cameras and make ground-truth motion nearly impossible to obtain. On the other hand, event cameras offer microsecond resolution and high dynamic range. Nonetheless, progress on investigating event cameras for underwater environments has been limited due to the lack of datasets that pair realistic underwater optics with accurate optical flow. To address this problem, we introduce the first synthetic underwater benchmark dataset for event-based optical flow derived from physically-based ray-traced RGBD sequences. Using a modern video-to-event pipeline applied to rendered underwater videos, we produce realistic event data streams with dense ground-truth flow, depth, and camera motion. Moreover, we benchmark state-of-the-art learning-based and model-based optical flow prediction methods to understand how underwater light transport affects event formation and motion estimation accuracy. Our dataset establishes a new baseline for future development and evaluation of underwater event-based perception algorithms. The source code and dataset for this project are publicly available at https://robotic-vision-lab.github.io/ueof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10054v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick Truong, Pritam P. Karmokar, William J. Beksi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAG-3DSG: Enhancing 3D Scene Graphs with Re-Shot Guided Retrieval-Augmented Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Open-vocabulary 3D Scene Graph (3DSG) generation can enhance various downstream tasks in robotics, such as manipulation and navigation, by leveraging structured semantic representations. A 3DSG is constructed from multiple images of a scene, where objects are represented as nodes and relationships as edges. However, existing works for open-vocabulary 3DSG generation suffer from both low object-level recognition accuracy and speed, mainly due to constrained viewpoints, occlusions, and redundant surface density. To address these challenges, we propose RAG-3DSG to mitigate aggregation noise through re-shot guided uncertainty estimation and support object-level Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) via reliable low-uncertainty objects. Furthermore, we propose a dynamic downsample-mapping strategy to accelerate cross-image object aggregation with adaptive granularity. Experiments on Replica dataset demonstrate that RAG-3DSG significantly improves node captioning accuracy in 3DSG generation while reducing the mapping time by two-thirds compared to the vanilla version.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10168v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Chang, Rufeng Chen, Zhaofan Zhang, Yi Chen, Sihong Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SurgGoal: Rethinking Surgical Planning Evaluation via Goal-Satisfiability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Surgical planning integrates visual perception, long-horizon reasoning, and procedural knowledge, yet it remains unclear whether current evaluation protocols reliably assess vision-language models (VLMs) in safety-critical settings. Motivated by a goal-oriented view of surgical planning, we define planning correctness via phase-goal satisfiability, where plan validity is determined by expert-defined surgical rules. Based on this definition, we introduce a multicentric meta-evaluation benchmark with valid procedural variations and invalid plans containing order and content errors. Using this benchmark, we show that sequence similarity metrics systematically misjudge planning quality, penalizing valid plans while failing to identify invalid ones. We therefore adopt a rule-based goal-satisfiability metric as a high-precision meta-evaluation reference to assess Video-LLMs under progressively constrained settings, revealing failures due to perception errors and under-constrained reasoning. Structural knowledge consistently improves performance, whereas semantic guidance alone is unreliable and benefits larger models only when combined with structural constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10455v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruochen Li, Kun Yuan, Yufei Xia, Yue Zhou, Qingyu Lu, Weihang Li, Youxiang Zhu, Nassir Navab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>See Less, Drive Better: Generalizable End-to-End Autonomous Driving via Foundation Models Stochastic Patch Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10707v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in end-to-end autonomous driving show that policies trained on patch-aligned features extracted from foundation models generalize better to Out-of-Distribution (OOD). We hypothesize that due to the self-attention mechanism, each patch feature implicitly embeds/contains information from all other patches, represented in a different way and intensity, making these descriptors highly redundant. We quantify redundancy in such (BLIP2) features via PCA and cross-patch similarity: $90$% of variance is captured by $17/64$ principal components, and strong inter-token correlations are pervasive. Training on such overlapping information leads the policy to overfit spurious correlations, hurting OOD robustness. We present Stochastic-Patch-Selection (SPS), a simple yet effective approach for learning policies that are more robust, generalizable, and efficient. For every frame, SPS randomly masks a fraction of patch descriptors, not feeding them to the policy model, while preserving the spatial layout of the remaining patches. Thus, the policy is provided with different stochastic but complete views of the (same) scene: every random subset of patches acts like a different, yet still sensible, coherent projection of the world. The policy thus bases its decisions on features that are invariant to which specific tokens survive. Extensive experiments confirm that across all OOD scenarios, our method outperforms the state of the art (SOTA), achieving a $6.2$% average improvement and up to $20.4$% in closed-loop simulations, while being $2.4\times$ faster. We conduct ablations over masking rates and patch-feature reorganization, training and evaluating 9 systems, with 8 of them surpassing prior SOTA. Finally, we show that the same learned policy transfers to a physical, real-world car without any tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10707v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Mallak, Erfan Aasi, Shiva Sreeram, Tsun-Hsuan Wang, Daniela Rus, Alaa Maalouf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Quadrotor Control From Visual Features Using Differentiable Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15979v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The sample inefficiency of reinforcement learning (RL) remains a significant challenge in robotics. RL requires large-scale simulation and can still cause long training times, slowing research and innovation. This issue is particularly pronounced in vision-based control tasks where reliable state estimates are not accessible. Differentiable simulation offers an alternative by enabling gradient back-propagation through the dynamics model, providing low-variance analytical policy gradients and, hence, higher sample efficiency. However, its usage for real-world robotic tasks has yet been limited. This work demonstrates the great potential of differentiable simulation for learning quadrotor control. We show that training in differentiable simulation significantly outperforms model-free RL in terms of both sample efficiency and training time, allowing a policy to learn to recover a quadrotor in seconds when providing vehicle states and in minutes when relying solely on visual features. The key to our success is two-fold. First, the use of a simple surrogate model for gradient computation greatly accelerates training without sacrificing control performance. Second, combining state representation learning with policy learning enhances convergence speed in tasks where only visual features are observable. These findings highlight the potential of differentiable simulation for real-world robotics and offer a compelling alternative to conventional RL approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15979v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA55743.2025.11128641</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Heeg, Yunlong Song, Davide Scaramuzza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Querying for Reward Learning from Human Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Learning from human feedback is a popular approach to train robots to adapt to user preferences and improve safety. Existing approaches typically consider a single querying (interaction) format when seeking human feedback and do not leverage multiple modes of user interaction with a robot. We examine how to learn a penalty function associated with unsafe behaviors using multiple forms of human feedback, by optimizing both the query state and feedback format. Our proposed adaptive feedback selection is an iterative, two-phase approach which first selects critical states for querying, and then uses information gain to select a feedback format for querying across the sampled critical states. The feedback format selection also accounts for the cost and probability of receiving feedback in a certain format. Our experiments in simulation demonstrate the sample efficiency of our approach in learning to avoid undesirable behaviors. The results of our user study with a physical robot highlight the practicality and effectiveness of adaptive feedback selection in seeking informative, user-aligned feedback that accelerate learning. Experiment videos, code and appendices are found on our website: https://tinyurl.com/AFS-learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07990v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yashwanthi Anand, Nnamdi Nwagwu, Kevin Sabbe, Naomi T. Fitter, Sandhya Saisubramanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularity-Free Guiding Vector Field over B\'ezier's Curves Applied to Rovers Path Planning and Path Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a guidance algorithm for solving the problem of following parametric paths, as well as a curvature-varying speed setpoint for land-based car-type wheeled mobile robots (WMRs). The guidance algorithm relies on Singularity-Free Guiding Vector Fields SF-GVF. This novel GVF approach expands the desired robot path and the Guiding vector field to a higher dimensional space, in which an angular control function can be found to ensure global asymptotic convergence to the desired parametric path while avoiding field singularities. In SF-GVF, paths should follow a parametric definition. This feature makes using Bezier's curves attractive to define the robot's desired patch. The curvature-varying speed setpoint, combined with the guidance algorithm, eases the convergence to the path when physical restrictions exist, such as minimal turning radius or maximal lateral acceleration. We provide theoretical results, simulations, and outdoor experiments using a WMR platform assembled with off-the-shelf components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13033v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/rob.22541</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Field Robotics, 2025. 42:2720-27-39</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alfredo Gonz\'alez-Calvin, L\'ia Garc\'ia-P\'erez, Juan Jim\'enez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling-Based Constrained Motion Planning with Products of Experts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17462v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to enhance the performance of sampling-based Model Predictive Control (MPC) in constrained optimization by leveraging products of experts. Our methodology divides the main problem into two components: one focused on optimality and the other on feasibility. By combining the solutions from each component, represented as distributions, we apply products of experts to implement a project-then-sample strategy. In this strategy, the optimality distribution is projected into the feasible area, allowing for more efficient sampling. This approach contrasts with the traditional sample-then-project and naive sample-then-reject method, leading to more diverse exploration and reducing the accumulation of samples on the boundaries. We demonstrate an effective implementation of this principle using a tensor train-based distribution model, which is characterized by its non-parametric nature, ease of combination with other distributions at the task level, and straightforward sampling technique. We adapt existing tensor train models to suit this purpose and validate the efficacy of our approach through experiments in various tasks, including obstacle avoidance, non-prehensile manipulation, and tasks involving staying in a restricted volume. Our experimental results demonstrate that the proposed method consistently outperforms known baselines, providing strong empirical support for its effectiveness. Sample codes for this project are available at https://github.com/idiap/smpc_poe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17462v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1177/02783649251404955</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Amirreza Razmjoo, Teng Xue, Suhan Shetty, Sylvain Calinon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Taxonomy for Evaluating Generalist Robot Manipulation Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01238v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine learning for robot manipulation promises to unlock generalization to novel tasks and environments. But how should we measure the progress of these policies towards generalization? Evaluating and quantifying generalization is the Wild West of modern robotics, with each work proposing and measuring different types of generalization in their own, often difficult to reproduce settings. In this work, our goal is (1) to outline the forms of generalization we believe are important for robot manipulation in a comprehensive and fine-grained manner, and (2) to provide reproducible guidelines for measuring these notions of generalization. We first propose STAR-Gen, a taxonomy of generalization for robot manipulation structured around visual, semantic, and behavioral generalization. Next, we instantiate STAR-Gen with two case studies on real-world benchmarking: one based on open-source models and the Bridge V2 dataset, and another based on the bimanual ALOHA 2 platform that covers more dexterous and longer horizon tasks. Our case studies reveal many interesting insights: for example, we observe that open-source vision-language-action models often struggle with semantic generalization, despite pre-training on internet-scale language datasets. We provide videos and other supplementary material at our website stargen-taxonomy.github.io.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01238v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jensen Gao, Suneel Belkhale, Sudeep Dasari, Ashwin Balakrishna, Dhruv Shah, Dorsa Sadigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoinFT: A Coin-Sized, Capacitive 6-Axis Force Torque Sensor for Robotic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19225v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce CoinFT, a capacitive 6-axis force/torque (F/T) sensor that is compact, light, low-cost, and robust with an average root-mean-squared error of 0.16N for force and 1.08mNm for moment when the input ranges from 0~14N and 0~5N in normal and shear directions, respectively. CoinFT is a stack of two rigid PCBs with comb-shaped electrodes connected by an array of silicone rubber pillars. The microcontroller interrogates the electrodes in different subsets in order to enhance sensitivity for measuring 6-axis F/T. The combination of features of CoinFT enables various contact-rich robot interactions across different embodiment domains including drones, robot end-effectors, and wearable haptic devices. We demonstrate the utility of CoinFT through two representative applications: a multi-axial contact-probing experiment in which a CoinFT mounted beneath a hemispherical fingertip measures 6-axes of force and torque representative of manipulation scenarios, and an attitude-based force-control task on a drone. The design, fabrication, and firmware of CoinFT are open-sourced at https://coin-ft.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19225v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hojung Choi, Jun En Low, Tae Myung Huh, Seongheon Hong, Gabriela A. Uribe, Kenneth A. W. Hoffmann, Julia Di, Tony G. Chen, Andrew A. Stanley, Mark R. Cutkosky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robot-R1: Reinforcement Learning for Enhanced Embodied Reasoning in Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) have recently shown great promise in advancing robotics by combining embodied reasoning with robot control. A common approach involves training on embodied reasoning tasks related to robot control using Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT). However, SFT datasets are often heuristically constructed and not explicitly optimized for improving robot control. Furthermore, SFT often leads to issues such as catastrophic forgetting and reduced generalization performance. To address these limitations, we introduce Robot-R1, a novel framework that leverages reinforcement learning to enhance embodied reasoning specifically for robot control. Robot-R1 learns to predict the next keypoint state required for task completion, conditioned on the current scene image and environment metadata derived from expert demonstrations. Inspired by the DeepSeek-R1 learning approach, Robot-R1 samples reasoning-based responses and reinforces those that lead to more accurate predictions. To rigorously evaluate Robot-R1, we also introduce a new benchmark that demands the diverse embodied reasoning capabilities for the task. Our experiments show that models trained with Robot-R1 outperform SFT methods on embodied reasoning tasks. Despite having only 7B parameters, Robot-R1 even surpasses GPT-4o on reasoning tasks related to low-level action control, such as spatial and movement reasoning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00070v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongyoung Kim, Sumin Park, Huiwon Jang, Jinwoo Shin, Jaehyung Kim, Younggyo Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Model-Predictive Control of a Soft Continuum Robot Using a Physics-Informed Neural Network Based on Cosserat Rod Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamic control of soft continuum robots (SCRs) holds great potential for expanding their applications, but remains a challenging problem due to the high computational demands of accurate dynamic models. While data-driven approaches like Koopman-operator-based methods have been proposed, they typically lack adaptability and cannot reconstruct the full robot shape, limiting their applicability. This work introduces a real-time-capable nonlinear model-predictive control (MPC) framework for SCRs based on a domain-decoupled physics-informed neural network (DD-PINN) with adaptable bending stiffness. The DD-PINN serves as a surrogate for the dynamic Cosserat rod model with a speed-up factor of 44000. It is also used within an unscented Kalman filter for estimating the model states and bending compliance from end-effector position measurements. We implement a nonlinear evolutionary MPC running at 70 Hz on the GPU. In simulation, it demonstrates accurate tracking of dynamic trajectories and setpoint control with end-effector position errors below 3 mm (2.3% of the actuator's length). In real-world experiments, the controller achieves similar accuracy and accelerations up to 3.55 m/s2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12681v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johann Licher, Max Bartholdt, Henrik Krauss, Tim-Lukas Habich, Thomas Seel, Moritz Schappler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UrbanNav: Learning Language-Guided Urban Navigation from Web-Scale Human Trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09607v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Navigating complex urban environments using natural language instructions poses significant challenges for embodied agents, including noisy language instructions, ambiguous spatial references, diverse landmarks, and dynamic street scenes. Current visual navigation methods are typically limited to simulated or off-street environments, and often rely on precise goal formats, such as specific coordinates or images. This limits their effectiveness for autonomous agents like last-mile delivery robots navigating unfamiliar cities. To address these limitations, we introduce UrbanNav, a scalable framework that trains embodied agents to follow free-form language instructions in diverse urban settings. Leveraging web-scale city walking videos, we develop an scalable annotation pipeline that aligns human navigation trajectories with language instructions grounded in real-world landmarks. UrbanNav encompasses over 1,500 hours of navigation data and 3 million instruction-trajectory-landmark triplets, capturing a wide range of urban scenarios. Our model learns robust navigation policies to tackle complex urban scenarios, demonstrating superior spatial reasoning, robustness to noisy instructions, and generalization to unseen urban settings. Experimental results show that UrbanNav significantly outperforms existing methods, highlighting the potential of large-scale web video data to enable language-guided, real-world urban navigation for embodied agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09607v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanghong Mei, Yirong Yang, Longteng Guo, Qunbo Wang, Ming-Ming Yu, Xingjian He, Wenjun Wu, Jing Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Euclidean Distance Field Properties for Fast and Safe 3D planning with a modified Lazy Theta*</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24024v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the FS-Planner, a fast graph-search planner based on a modified Lazy Theta* algorithm that exploits the analytical properties of Euclidean Distance Fields (EDFs). We introduce a new cost function that integrates an EDF-based term proven to satisfy the triangle inequality, enabling efficient parent selection and reducing computation time while generating safe paths with smaller heading variations. We also derive an analytic approximation of the EDF integral along a segment and analyze the influence of the line-of-sight limit on the approximation error, motivating the use of a bounded visibility range. Furthermore, we propose a gradient-based neighbour-selection mechanism that decreases the number of explored nodes and improves computational performance without degrading safety or path quality. The FS-Planner produces safe paths with small heading changes without requiring the use of post-processing methods. Extensive experiments and comparisons in challenging 3D indoor simulation environments, complemented by tests in real-world outdoor environments, are used to evaluate and validate the FS-Planner. The results show consistent improvements in computation time, exploration efficiency, safety, and smoothness in a geometric sense compared with baseline heuristic planners, while maintaining sub-optimality within acceptable bounds. Finally, the proposed EDF-based cost formulation is orthogonal to the underlying search method and can be incorporated into other planning paradigms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24024v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.robot.2025.105317</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in Robotics and Autonomous Systems (RAS), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. Cobano, L. Merino, F. Caballero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrap Off-policy with World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00423v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Online planning has proven effective in reinforcement learning (RL) for improving sample efficiency and final performance. However, using planning for environment interaction inevitably introduces a divergence between the collected data and the policy's actual behaviors, degrading both model learning and policy improvement. To address this, we propose BOOM (Bootstrap Off-policy with WOrld Model), a framework that tightly integrates planning and off-policy learning through a bootstrap loop: the policy initializes the planner, and the planner refines actions to bootstrap the policy through behavior alignment. This loop is supported by a jointly learned world model, which enables the planner to simulate future trajectories and provides value targets to facilitate policy improvement. The core of BOOM is a likelihood-free alignment loss that bootstraps the policy using the planner's non-parametric action distribution, combined with a soft value-weighted mechanism that prioritizes high-return behaviors and mitigates variability in the planner's action quality within the replay buffer. Experiments on the high-dimensional DeepMind Control Suite and Humanoid-Bench show that BOOM achieves state-of-the-art results in both training stability and final performance. The code is accessible at https://github.com/molumitu/BOOM_MBRL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00423v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guojian Zhan, Likun Wang, Xiangteng Zhang, Jiaxin Gao, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Shengbo Eben Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RGS-SLAM: Robust Gaussian Splatting SLAM with One-Shot Dense Initialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00705v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce RGS-SLAM, a robust Gaussian-splatting SLAM framework that replaces the residual-driven densification stage of GS-SLAM with a training-free correspondence-to-Gaussian initialization. Instead of progressively adding Gaussians as residuals reveal missing geometry, RGS-SLAM performs a one-shot triangulation of dense multi-view correspondences derived from DINOv3 descriptors refined through a confidence-aware inlier classifier, generating a well-distributed and structure-aware Gaussian seed prior to optimization. This initialization stabilizes early mapping and accelerates convergence by roughly 20\%, yielding higher rendering fidelity in texture-rich and cluttered scenes while remaining fully compatible with existing GS-SLAM pipelines. Evaluated on the TUM RGB-D and Replica datasets, RGS-SLAM achieves competitive or superior localization and reconstruction accuracy compared with state-of-the-art Gaussian and point-based SLAM systems, sustaining real-time mapping performance at up to 925 FPS. Additional details and resources are available at this URL: https://breeze1124.github.io/rgs-slam-project-page/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00705v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Tse Cheng, Yen-Jen Chiou, Yuan-Fu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Monocular Depth Refinement via Neural Radiance Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03869v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Monocular depth estimation has applications in many fields, such as autonomous navigation and extended reality, making it an essential computer vision task. However, current methods often produce smooth depth maps that lack the fine geometric detail needed for accurate scene understanding. We propose MDENeRF, an iterative framework that refines monocular depth estimates using depth information from Neural Radiance Fields (NeRFs). MDENeRF consists of three components: (1) an initial monocular estimate for global structure, (2) a NeRF trained on perturbed viewpoints, with per-pixel uncertainty, and (3) Bayesian fusion of the noisy monocular and NeRF depths. We derive NeRF uncertainty from the volume rendering process to iteratively inject high-frequency fine details. Meanwhile, our monocular prior maintains global structure. We demonstrate improvements on key metrics and experiments using indoor scenes from the SUN RGB-D dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03869v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun Muthukkumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DAVOS: An Autonomous Vehicle Operating System in the Vehicle Computing Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05072v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vehicle computing represents a fundamental shift in how autonomous vehicles are designed and deployed, transforming them from isolated transportation systems into mobile computing platforms that support both safety-critical, real-time driving and data-centric services. In this setting, vehicles simultaneously support real-time driving pipelines and a growing set of data-driven applications, placing increased responsibility on the vehicle operating system to coordinate computation, data movement, storage, and access. These demands highlight recurring system considerations related to predictable execution, data and execution protection, efficient handling of high-rate sensor data, and long-term system evolvability, commonly summarized as Safety, Security, Efficiency, and Extensibility (SSEE). Existing vehicle operating systems and runtimes address these concerns in isolation, resulting in fragmented software stacks that limit coordination between autonomy workloads and vehicle data services. This paper presents DAVOS, the Delaware Autonomous Vehicle Operating System, a unified vehicle operating system architecture designed for the vehicle computing context. DAVOS provides a cohesive operating system foundation that supports both real-time autonomy and extensible vehicle computing within a single system framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05072v2</guid>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Wang, Yuankai He, Boyang Tian, Lichen Xian, Weisong Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safety Not Found (404): Hidden Risks of LLM-Based Robotics Decision Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One mistake by an AI system in a safety-critical setting can cost lives. As Large Language Models (LLMs) become integral to robotics decision-making, the physical dimension of risk grows; a single wrong instruction can directly endanger human safety. This paper addresses the urgent need to systematically evaluate LLM performance in scenarios where even minor errors are catastrophic. Through a qualitative evaluation of a fire evacuation scenario, we identified critical failure cases in LLM-based decision-making. Based on these, we designed seven tasks for quantitative assessment, categorized into: Complete Information, Incomplete Information, and Safety-Oriented Spatial Reasoning (SOSR). Complete information tasks utilize ASCII maps to minimize interpretation ambiguity and isolate spatial reasoning from visual processing. Incomplete information tasks require models to infer missing context, testing for spatial continuity versus hallucinations. SOSR tasks use natural language to evaluate safe decision-making in life-threatening contexts. We benchmark various LLMs and Vision-Language Models (VLMs) across these tasks. Beyond aggregate performance, we analyze the implications of a 1% failure rate, highlighting how "rare" errors escalate into catastrophic outcomes. Results reveal serious vulnerabilities: several models achieved a 0% success rate in ASCII navigation, while in a simulated fire drill, models instructed robots to move toward hazardous areas instead of emergency exits. Our findings lead to a sobering conclusion: current LLMs are not ready for direct deployment in safety-critical systems. A 99% accuracy rate is dangerously misleading in robotics, as it implies one out of every hundred executions could result in catastrophic harm. We demonstrate that even state-of-the-art models cannot guarantee safety, and absolute reliance on them creates unacceptable risks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05529v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jua Han, Jaeyoon Seo, Jungbin Min, Jean Oh, Jihie Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
