<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.hist-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph</link>
    <description>physics.hist-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 04:01:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mikhail Lomonosov: Oration on the Birth of Metals by Earth's Tremor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This English translation of seminal work of Russian polymath Mikhail Lomonosov. It is derived from its Russian and Latin originals (1757) and continues the series of English translations of Lomonosov nine most important scientific works, which were included by Lomonosov himself in the convolute Lomonosow Opera Academica sent for distribution among Academies in Europe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17724v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Lomonosov, Vladimir Shiltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mikhail Lomonosov: Oration on Benefits of Chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mikhail Lomonosov (1711-1765) was a Russian polymath and one of the giants of the European Enlightenment. This English translation of his seminal work Oration on Benefits of Chemistry continues the series of translations of nine most important scientific works, which were included by Lomonosov himself in the convolute Lomonosow Opera Academica and sent for distribution among scientific Academies in Europe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18018v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Lomonosov, Vladimir Shiltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mikhail Lomonosov: Oration on the Origin of Light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mikhail Lomonosov (1711-1765) was the eminent Russian polymath and a towering figure of the European Enlightenment. This English translation of Mikhail Lomonosov seminal work "Oration on the Origin of Light " draws from its original Russian and Latin sources. It is part of a series of English translations of nine most significant scientific treatises, all of which Lomonosov himself compiled in the volume titled Lomonosow Opera Academica, intended for dissemination among European Academies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18250v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Lomonosov, Vladimir Shiltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stagnant Lakatosian Research Programmes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an extension of the classical dichotomous categorization of research programmes into progress and degeneration according to Lakatos in the form of a neutral third category: the stagnant research programme. First, a critical examination of the primary literature with its often criticized definitional gaps justifies such a category. Through a generic derivation of criteria for stagnant programmes, a clear demarcation from progressive and degenerative ones is achieved. An empirical cross-check is subsequently employed for support: Both a series of examples from fundamental physics and a general analysis of today's research landscape also suggest on an empirical level the need to go beyond the traditional Lakatosian conception. Attributing stagnation is entirely in line with Lakatos' original intentions, which aimed not to hastily discard promising research but to exercise patience until the lifting of certain external constraints potentially enables progress once again.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18307v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Branahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dressing vs. Fixing: On How to Extract and Interpret Gauge-Invariant Content</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is solid consensus among physicists and philosophers that, in gauge field theory, for a quantity to be physically meaningful or real, it must be gauge-invariant. Yet, every ``elementary" field in the Standard Model of particle physics is actually gauge-variant. This has led a number of researchers to insist that new manifestly gauge-invariant approaches must be established. Indeed, in the foundational literature, dissatisfaction with standard methods for reducing gauge symmetries has been expressed: Spontaneous symmetry breaking is deemed conceptually dubious, while gauge fixing suffers the same limitations and is subject to the same criticisms as coordinate choices in General Relativity.
  An alternative gauge-invariant proposal was recently introduced in the literature, the so-called ``dressing field method" (DFM). It is a mathematically subtle tool, and unfortunately prone to be confused with simple gauge transformations, hence with standard gauge~fixings. As a matter of fact, in the physics literature the two are often conflated, and in the philosophy community some doubts have been raised about whether there is any substantial difference between them. Clarifying this issue is of special significance for anyone interested in both the foundational issues of gauge theories and their invariant formulation. It is thus our objective to establish as precisely as possible the technical and conceptual distinctions between the DFM and gauge fixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18582v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Berghofer, Jordan Fran\c{c}ois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mikhail Lomonosov: Discourse on Greater Accuracy of Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mikhail Lomonosov (1711-1765) is the eminent Russian polymath and a towering figure of the European Enlightenment. This English translation of his seminal work Discourse on Greater Accuracy of Navigation concludes the series of English translations of nine most significant scientific treatises, all of which Lomonosov himself compiled in the volume titled Lomonosow Opera Academica, intended for dissemination among European Academies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18885v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikahil Lomonosov, Vladimir Shiltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elements of Ion Linear Accelerators + Calm in the Resonances -- and Other Tales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.04249v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The main part of this book, Elements of Linear Accelerators, outlines in Part 1 a framework for non-relativistic linear accelerator focusing and accelerating channel design, simulation, optimization and analysis where space charge is an important factor. Part 1 is the most important part of the book; grasping the framework is essential to fully understand and appreciate the elements within it, and the myriad application details of the following Parts. The treatment concentrates on all linacs, large or small, intended for high-intensity, very low beam loss, factory-type application. The Radio-Frequency-Quadrupole (RFQ) is especially developed as a representative and the most complicated linac form (from dc to bunched and accelerated beam), extending to practical design of long, high energy linacs, including space charge resonances and beam halo formation, and some challenges for future work. Also a practical method is presented for designing Alternating-Phase- Focused (APF) linacs with long sequences and high energy gain. Full open-source software is available. The following part, Calm in the Resonances and Other Tales, contains eyewitness accounts of nearly 60 years of participation in accelerator technology.
  (September 2023) The LINACS codes are released at no cost and, as always, with fully open-source coding. (p.2 &amp; Ch 19.10)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.04249v3</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Jameson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Travel Paradoxes and Entangled Timelines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.07635v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For time travel to be consistent with the known laws of physics, the resulting paradoxes must be resolved. It has been suggested that parallel timelines (a.k.a. multiple histories) may provide a resolution. However, so far, a concrete mechanism by which parallel timelines can be created has never been satisfactorily formulated. In this paper we propose such a mechanism within the framework of unmodified quantum mechanics, also known as the Everett or "many-worlds" interpretation. The timelines in our model are emergent, like the "worlds" of the Everett interpretation; they are created by quantum entanglement between the time machine and the environment. Therefore, we call them "entangled timelines" or E-CTCs. As the entanglement gradually spreads out to additional systems, the timelines spread out as well, providing a local and well-defined alternative to the naive "branching timelines" picture often presented in the literature. The E-CTC model is similar to Deutsch's familiar D-CTC model, but differs from it mainly by making the entanglement explicit, which allows us to create a clearer practical definition of the resulting parallel timelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.07635v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barak Shoshany, Zipora Stober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic bra-ket interpretation of quantum mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03151v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The stochastic nature of quantum mechanics is more naturally reflected in a bilinear two-process representation of density matrices rather than in squared wave functions. This proposition comes with a remarkable change of the entanglement mechanism: entanglement effects do not originate from superpositions of wave functions, but result from the bilinear structure of density matrices. Quantum interference appears as a multiplicative phenomenon rather than an additive superposition mechanism. We propose two general requirements such that the bilinear representation of density matrices is given in terms of two uniquely defined, identically distributed, Markovian stochastic jump processes. These general ideas are illustrated for the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen and double-slit experiments. The expression of the stochastic nature of quantum mechanics in terms of random variables rather than their probability distributions facilitates an ontological viewpoint and leads us to a bra-ket interpretation of quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03151v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Christian \"Ottinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
