<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.hist-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph</link>
    <description>physics.hist-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 20:56:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics without Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our fundamental theories, i.e., the quantum theory and general relativity, are invariant under time reversal. Only when we treat system from the point of view of thermodynamics, i.e., averaging between many subsystem components, an arrow of time emerges. The relation between thermodynamic and the quantum theory has been fertile, deeply explored and still a source of new investigations. The relation between the quantum theory and gravity, while it has not yet brought an established theory of quantum gravity, has certainly sparkled in depth analysis and tentative new theories. On the other hand, the connection between gravity and thermodynamics is less investigated and more puzzling. I review a selection of results in covariant thermodynamics, such as the construction of a covariant notion of thermal equilibrium by considering tripartite systems. I discuss how such construction requires a relational take on thermodynamics, similarly of what happens in the quantum theory and in gravity</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19098v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Vidotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freedom in the many-worlds interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.07596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.07596v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I analyze the possibility of free-will in the many-worlds interpretation (MWI), arguing for their compatibility. I use as a starting point Nicolas Gisin's "The Multiverse Pandemic" (preprint arXiv:2210.05377, after Gisin, N., "L'\'epid\'emie du multivers", in "Le Plus Grand des Hasards", Belin, Paris, 2010), in which he makes an interesting case that MWI is contradicted by our hard to deny free-will. The counts he raised are:
  (1) MWI is deterministic, forcing choices on us,
  (2) in MWI all our possible choices happen, and
  (3) MWI limits creativity, because everything is entangled with everything else.
  I argue that each of these features of MWI is in fact compatible with more freedom than it may seem. In particular, MWI allows compatibilist free-will, but also free-will very much like the libertarian free-will defined by Chisholm. I argue that the position that alternative choices exist as possibilities does not make sense from a physical point of view, but MWI offers a physical ground for alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.07596v2</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ovidiu Cristinel Stoica</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
