<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.hist-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph</link>
    <description>physics.hist-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Spirit of Chien-Shiung Wu: From Quantum Entanglement to Parity Nonconservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1950, Chien-Shiung Wu and her student published a coincidence experiment on entangled photon pairs that were created in electron-positron annihilation. This experiment precisely verified the prediction of quantum electrodynamics. Additionally, it was also the first instance of a precisely controlled quantum entangled state of spatially separated particles, although Wu did not know about this at the time. In 1956, Wu initiated and led the so-called Wu experiment, which discovered parity nonconservation, becoming one of the greatest experiments of the 20th century. As Chen Ning Yang said, Wu's experiments were well known for their precision and accuracy. Experimental precision and accuracy manifested Wu's scientific spirit, which we investigate here in some detail. This paper is the translated transcript of the speech the author made at the International Symposium Commemorating the 110th Anniversary of the Birth of Chien-Shiung Wu, on May 31, 2022. The above abstract is the translation of the original abstract of the speech.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16978v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Gauge Symmetry Breaking in the Abelian Higgs Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper aims to resolve the incompatibility between two extant gauge-invariant accounts of the Abelian Higgs mechanism: the first account uses global gauge symmetry breaking, and the second eliminates spontaneous symmetry breaking entirely. We resolve this incompatibility by using the constrained Hamiltonian formalism in symplectic geometry. First we argue that, unlike their local counterparts, global gauge symmetries are physical. The symmetries that are spontaneously broken by the Higgs mechanism are then the global ones. Second, we explain how the dressing field method singles out the Coulomb gauge as a preferred gauge for a gauge-invariant account of the Abelian Higgs mechanism. Based on the existence of this group of global gauge symmetries that are physical, we resolve the incompatibility between the two accounts by arguing that the correct way to carry out the second method is to eliminate only the redundant gauge symmetries, i.e. those local gauge symmetries which are not global. We extend our analysis to quantum field theory, where we show that the Abelian Higgs mechanism can be understood as spontaneous global $U(1)$ symmetry breaking in the $C^*$-algebraic sense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17483v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvester Borsboom, Sebastian De Haro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification is Pointless: Quantum Coordinates, Localisation of Events, and the Quantum Hole Argument</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10267v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The study of quantum reference frames (QRFs) is motivated by the idea of taking into account the quantum properties of the reference frames used, explicitly or implicitly, in our description of physical systems. Like classical reference frames, QRFs can be used to define physical quantities relationally. Unlike their classical analogue, they relativise the notions of superposition and entanglement. Here, we explain this feature by examining how configurations or locations are identified across different branches in superposition. We show that, in the presence of symmetries, whether a system is in "the same" or "different" configurations across the branches depends on the choice of QRF. Hence, sameness and difference -- and thus superposition and entanglement -- lose their absolute meaning. We apply these ideas to the context of semi-classical spacetimes in superposition and use coincidences of four scalar fields to construct a comparison map between spacetime points in the different branches. This reveals that the localisation of an event is frame-dependent. We discuss the implications for indefinite causal order and the locality of interaction and conclude with a generalisation of Einstein's hole argument to the quantum context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10267v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktoria Kabel, Anne-Catherine de la Hamette, Luca Apadula, Carlo Cepollaro, Henrique Gomes, Jeremy Butterfield, \v{C}aslav Brukner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
