<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.hist-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph</link>
    <description>physics.hist-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.hist-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Two Shades of Quark Color: Parallel Canons across the Cold War Divide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The introduction of the color quantum number is conventionally narrated as a linear progression from the quark-model statistics paradox to quantum chromodynamics (QCD). This paper challenges that teleology by arguing that "color" emerged as two conceptually distinct constructs during the Cold War. The first, originating with Han and Nambu and culminating in QCD, conceived of color as a local gauge charge, the source of a fundamental force mediated by gluons. The second, developed at the Joint Institute for Nuclear Research (JINR) in Dubna, treated color as a hidden, three-valued label--a statistical and structural property within a composite, S-matrix-inflected hadron model. We trace these parallel narratives, linking the Dubna approach to a holist epistemology that prioritizes observable amplitudes and global constraints, and the QCD approach to a reductionist program grounded in micro-dynamics. A case study of Fermilab's E-36 experimental chain (1970--78) shows how an observables-first design-tuned to S-matrix and Regge constraints on forward elastic scattering--performed robustly within its natural domain but was ultimately discontinued amid declining theoretical interest and involvement. The subsequent hegemony of QCD retroactively projected its gauge-theoretic conception of color onto history, erasing this epistemic diversity. We conclude that the marginalization of Dubna's structural color was not merely a political outcome of the Cold War but a result of deep ontological and philosophical divergences, advocating for a domain-sensitive pluralism in the historiography of particle physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23909v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitaly Pronskikh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Randomness, Exchangeability, and the Principal Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a framework uniting algorithmic randomness with exchangeable credences to address foundational questions in philosophy of probability and philosophy of science. To demonstrate its power, we show how one might use the framework to derive the Principal Principle -- the norm that rational credence should match known objective chance -- without circularity. The derivation brings together de Finetti's exchangeability, Martin-L\"of randomness, Lewis's and Skyrms's chance-credence norms, and statistical constraining laws (arXiv:2303.01411). Laws that constrain histories to algorithmically random sequences naturally pair with exchangeable credences encoding inductive symmetries. Using the de Finetti representation theorem, we show that this pairing directly entails the Principal Principle of this framework. We extend the proof to partial exchangeability and provide finite-history bounds that vanish in the infinite limit. The Principal Principle thus emerges as a mathematical consequence of the alignment between nomological constraints and inductive learning. This reveals how algorithmic randomness and exchangeability can illuminate foundational questions about chance, frequency, and rational belief.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24054v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey A. Barrett, Eddy Keming Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology and Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scientific cosmology has now reached its period of maturity with the establishment of a standard model, which is the theory of an expanding universe. The question of whether this expansion resolves itself, in the past, into a singularity identifiable with an absolute beginning, or whether the universe in which we are is only one of the multiple possible universes existing either in space or in time, is still under debate. Moreover, the assimilation of the beginning of the universe to a "creation" has often been contested by theology, which, since Thomas Aquinas, if not since the Fathers of the Church, tends to carefully distinguish the two. In the following article, after briefly summarizing some points in the recent history of scientific cosmology, we will attempt to present in broad outline the standard model that scientists have arrived at. Then, we will undertake to study some of the problems it raises as well as the alternative theories that can be opposed to it. Finally, we will discuss the problematic links that scientific cosmology continues to maintain with philosophy and theology, notably the thorny question of creation from nothing ({\it creatio ex nihilo}).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24296v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Parrochia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversity legitimizes science: Holding basic research in the physical sciences accountable to the public</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The American scientific community is reeling from funding cuts and policy directives that will debilitate scientific research and education. The underlying hostilities fueling these attacks have intensified in recent years as the COVID-19 pandemic increased suspicion of scientific experts and the institutional embrace of diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) policies in 2020 prompted a backlash along longstanding political fault lines. Under the banner of anti-elitism, opponents of science and DEI have formed a coalition that sees attacks on higher education as a strategic means to achieve their political ends. While some of their arguments contain legitimate criticisms, academics must resist these attacks that seek to dismantle higher education altogether. Instead, we should engage the public in our research process, build a scientific practice representative of and accountable to the communities we serve, and interrogate the aims of our work by critically studying the history of science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23616v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kay T. Xia, Thayer L. Anderson, Phelan Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
