<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN</link>
    <description>q-bio.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 02:16:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable AI Methods for Multi-Omics Analysis: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advancements in high-throughput technologies have led to a shift from traditional hypothesis-driven methodologies to data-driven approaches. Multi-omics refers to the integrative analysis of data derived from multiple 'omes', such as genomics, proteomics, transcriptomics, metabolomics, and microbiomics. This approach enables a comprehensive understanding of biological systems by capturing different layers of biological information. Deep learning methods are increasingly utilized to integrate multi-omics data, offering insights into molecular interactions and enhancing research into complex diseases. However, these models, with their numerous interconnected layers and nonlinear relationships, often function as black boxes, lacking transparency in decision-making processes. To overcome this challenge, explainable artificial intelligence (xAI) methods are crucial for creating transparent models that allow clinicians to interpret and work with complex data more effectively. This review explores how xAI can improve the interpretability of deep learning models in multi-omics research, highlighting its potential to provide clinicians with clear insights, thereby facilitating the effective application of such models in clinical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11910v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Hussein, Mukesh Prasad, Ali Braytee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A SARS-CoV-2 Interaction Dataset and VHH Sequence Corpus for Antibody Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18749v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Antibodies are crucial proteins produced by the immune system to eliminate harmful foreign substances and have become pivotal therapeutic agents for treating human diseases. To accelerate the discovery of antibody therapeutics, there is growing interest in constructing language models using antibody sequences. However, the applicability of pre-trained language models for antibody discovery has not been thoroughly evaluated due to the scarcity of labeled datasets. To overcome these limitations, we introduce AVIDa-SARS-CoV-2, a dataset featuring the antigen-variable domain of heavy chain of heavy chain antibody (VHH) interactions obtained from two alpacas immunized with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) spike proteins. AVIDa-SARS-CoV-2 includes binary labels indicating the binding or non-binding of diverse VHH sequences to 12 SARS-CoV-2 mutants, such as the Delta and Omicron variants. Furthermore, we release VHHCorpus-2M, a pre-training dataset for antibody language models, containing over two million VHH sequences. We report benchmark results for predicting SARS-CoV-2-VHH binding using VHHBERT pre-trained on VHHCorpus-2M and existing general protein and antibody-specific pre-trained language models. These results confirm that AVIDa-SARS-CoV-2 provides valuable benchmarks for evaluating the representation capabilities of antibody language models for binding prediction, thereby facilitating the development of AI-driven antibody discovery. The datasets are available at https://datasets.cognanous.com.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18749v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirofumi Tsuruta, Hiroyuki Yamazaki, Ryota Maeda, Ryotaro Tamura, Akihiro Imura</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
