<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN</link>
    <description>q-bio.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 04:00:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pairwise Rearrangement is Fixed-Parameter Tractable in the Single Cut-and-Join Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01942v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Genome rearrangement is a common model for molecular evolution. In this paper, we consider the Pairwise Rearrangement problem, which takes as input two genomes and asks for the number of minimum-length sequences of permissible operations transforming the first genome into the second. In the Single Cut-and-Join model (Bergeron, Medvedev, &amp; Stoye, J. Comput. Biol. 2010), Pairwise Rearrangement is $\#\textsf{P}$-complete (Bailey, et. al., COCOON 2023), which implies that exact sampling is intractable. In order to cope with this intractability, we investigate the parameterized complexity of this problem. We exhibit a fixed-parameter tractable algorithm with respect to the number of components in the adjacency graph that are not cycles of length $2$ or paths of length $1$. As a consequence, we obtain that Pairwise Rearrangement in the Single Cut-and-Join model is fixed-parameter tractable by distance. Our results suggest that the number of nontrivial components in the adjacency graph serves as the key obstacle for efficient sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01942v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lora Bailey, Heather Smith Blake, Garner Cochran, Nathan Fox, Michael Levet, Reem Mahmoud, Inne Singgih, Grace Stadnyk, Alexander Wiedemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
