<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN</link>
    <description>q-bio.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 01:55:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Genetic Influences on Brain Aging: Analyzing Sex Differences in the UK Biobank using Structural MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Brain aging trajectories differ between males and females, yet the genetic factors underlying these differences remain underexplored. Using structural MRI and genotyping data from 40,940 UK Biobank participants (aged 45-83), we computed Brain Age Gap Estimates (BrainAGE) for total brain, hippocampal, and ventricular volumes. We conducted sex-stratified genome-wide association studies (GWAS) and Post-GWAS analyses to identify genetic variants associated with accelerated brain aging. Distinct gene sets emerged by sex: in females, neurotransmitter transport and mitochondrial stress response genes were implicated; in males, immune and inflammation-related genes dominated. Shared genes, including GMNC and OSTN, were consistently linked to brain volumes across sexes, suggesting core roles in neurostructural maintenance. Tissue expression analyses revealed sex-specific enrichment in pathways tied to neurodegeneration. These findings highlight the importance of sex-stratified approaches in aging research and suggest genetic targets for personalized interventions against age-related cognitive decline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20344v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine, ISMRM Annual Meeting, May 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Karen Ardila, Aashka Mohite, Abdoljalil Addeh, Amanda V. Tyndall, Cindy K. Barha, Quan Long, M. Ethan MacDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ctrl-DNA: Controllable Cell-Type-Specific Regulatory DNA Design via Constrained RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Designing regulatory DNA sequences that achieve precise cell-type-specific gene expression is crucial for advancements in synthetic biology, gene therapy and precision medicine. Although transformer-based language models (LMs) can effectively capture patterns in regulatory DNA, their generative approaches often struggle to produce novel sequences with reliable cell-specific activity. Here, we introduce Ctrl-DNA, a novel constrained reinforcement learning (RL) framework tailored for designing regulatory DNA sequences with controllable cell-type specificity. By formulating regulatory sequence design as a biologically informed constrained optimization problem, we apply RL to autoregressive genomic LMs, enabling the models to iteratively refine sequences that maximize regulatory activity in targeted cell types while constraining off-target effects. Our evaluation on human promoters and enhancers demonstrates that Ctrl-DNA consistently outperforms existing generative and RL-based approaches, generating high-fitness regulatory sequences and achieving state-of-the-art cell-type specificity. Moreover, Ctrl-DNA-generated sequences capture key cell-type-specific transcription factor binding sites (TFBS), short DNA motifs recognized by regulatory proteins that control gene expression, demonstrating the biological plausibility of the generated sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20578v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Chen, Shihao Ma, Runsheng Lin, Jiecong Lin, Bo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HAD: Hybrid Architecture Distillation Outperforms Teacher in Genomic Sequence Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the great success of Masked Language Modeling (MLM) in the natural language domain, the paradigm of self-supervised pre-training and fine-tuning has also achieved remarkable progress in the field of DNA sequence modeling. However, previous methods often relied on massive pre-training data or large-scale base models with huge parameters, imposing a significant computational burden. To address this, many works attempted to use more compact models to achieve similar outcomes but still fell short by a considerable margin. In this work, we propose a Hybrid Architecture Distillation (HAD) approach, leveraging both distillation and reconstruction tasks for more efficient and effective pre-training. Specifically, we employ the NTv2-500M as the teacher model and devise a grouping masking strategy to align the feature embeddings of visible tokens while concurrently reconstructing the invisible tokens during MLM pre-training. To validate the effectiveness of our proposed method, we conducted comprehensive experiments on the Nucleotide Transformer Benchmark and Genomic Benchmark. Compared to models with similar parameters, our model achieved excellent performance. More surprisingly, it even surpassed the distillation ceiling-teacher model on some sub-tasks, which is more than 500 $\times$ larger. Lastly, we utilize t-SNE for more intuitive visualization, which shows that our model can gain a sophisticated understanding of the intrinsic representation pattern in genomic sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20836v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hexiong Yang, Mingrui Chen, Huaibo Huang, Junxian Duan, Jie Cao, Zhen Zhou, Ran He</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
