<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN</link>
    <description>q-bio.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 05:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Risk Gene Discovery Across the Allele Frequency Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of genetic risk factors has transformed human genetics, yet the pace of new gene identification has slowed despite the exponential expansion of sequencing and biobank resources. Current approaches are optimized for the extremes of the allele frequency spectrum: rare, high-penetrance variants identified through burden testing, and common, low-effect variants mapped by genome-wide association studies. Between these extremes lies variants of intermediate frequency and effect size where statistical power is limited, pathogenicity is often misclassified, and gene discovery lags behind empirical evidence of heritable contribution. This 'missing middle' represents a critical blind spot across disease areas, from neurodevelopmental and psychiatric disorders to cancer and aging. In this review, we organize strategies for risk gene identification by variant frequency class, highlighting methodological strengths and constraints at each scale. We draw on lessons across fields to illustrate how innovations in variant annotation, joint modeling, phenotype refinement, and network-based inference can extend discovery into the intermediate range. By framing the frequency spectrum as a unifying axis, we provide a conceptual map of current capabilities, their limitations, and emerging directions toward more comprehensive risk gene discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04637v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madison Caballero, Behrang Mahjani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PETRA: Pretrained Evolutionary Transformer for SARS-CoV-2 Mutation Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03976v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since its emergence, SARS-CoV-2 has demonstrated a rapid and unpredictable evolutionary trajectory, characterized by the continual emergence of immune-evasive variants. This poses persistent challenges to public health and vaccine development.
  While large-scale generative pre-trained transformers (GPTs) have revolutionized the modeling of sequential data, their direct applications to noisy viral genomic sequences are limited. In this paper, we introduce PETRA(Pretrained Evolutionary TRAnsformer), a novel transformer approach based on evolutionary trajectories derived from phylogenetic trees rather than raw RNA sequences. This method effectively mitigates sequencing noise and captures the hierarchical structure of viral evolution.
  With a weighted training framework to address substantial geographical and temporal imbalances in global sequence data, PETRA excels in predicting future SARS-CoV-2 mutations, achieving a weighted recall@1 of 9.45% for nucleotide mutations and 17.10\% for spike amino-acid mutations, compared to 0.49% and 6.64% respectively for the best baseline. PETRA also demonstrates its ability to aid in the real-time mutation prediction of major clades like 24F(XEC) and 25A(LP.8.1). The code is open sourced on https://github.com/xz-keg/PETra</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03976v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LA-MARRVEL: A Knowledge-Grounded and Language-Aware LLM Reranker for AI-MARRVEL in Rare Disease Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02263v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diagnosing rare diseases requires linking gene findings with often unstructured reference text. Current pipelines collect many candidate genes, but clinicians still spend a lot of time filtering false positives and combining evidence from papers and databases. A key challenge is language: phenotype descriptions and inheritance patterns are written in prose, not fully captured by tables. Large language models (LLMs) can read such text, but clinical use needs grounding in citable knowledge and stable, repeatable behavior. We explore a knowledge-grounded and language-aware reranking layer on top of a high-recall first-stage pipeline. The goal is to improve precision and explainability, not to replace standard bioinformatics steps. We use expert-built context and a consensus method to reduce LLM variability, producing shorter, better-justified gene lists for expert review. LA-MARRVEL achieves the highest accuracy, outperforming other methods -- including traditional bioinformatics diagnostic tools (AI-MARRVEL, Exomiser, LIRICAL) and naive large language models (e.g., Anthropic Claude) -- with an average Recall@5 of 94.10%, a +3.65 percentage-point improvement over AI-MARRVEL. The LLM-generated reasoning provides clear prose on phenotype matching and inheritance patterns, making clinical review faster and easier. LA-MARRVEL has three parts: expert-engineered context that enriches phenotype and disease information; a ranked voting algorithm that combines multiple LLM runs to choose a consensus ranked gene list; and the AI-MARRVEL pipeline that provides first-stage ranks and gene annotations, already known as a state-of-the-art method in Rare Disease Diagnosis on BG, DDD, and UDN cohorts. The online AI-MARRVEL includes LA-MARRVEL as an LLM feature at https://ai.marrvel.org . We evaluate LA-MARRVEL on three datasets from independent cohorts of real-world diagnosed patients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02263v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaeyeon Lee, Hyun-Hwan Jeong, Zhandong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>scMEDAL for the interpretable analysis of single-cell transcriptomics data with batch effect visualization using a deep mixed effects autoencoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06635v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Single-cell RNA sequencing enables high-resolution analysis of cellular heterogeneity, yet disentangling biological signal from batch effects remains a major challenge. Existing batch-correction algorithms suppress or discard batch-related variation rather than modeling it. We propose scMEDAL, single-cell Mixed Effects Deep Autoencoder Learning, a framework that separately models batch-invariant and batch-specific effects using two complementary subnetworks. The principal innovation, scMEDAL-RE, is a random-effects Bayesian autoencoder that learns batch-specific representations while preserving biologically meaningful information confounded with batch effects signal often lost under standard correction. Complementing it, the fixed-effects subnetwork, scMEDAL-FE, trained via adversarial learning provides a default batch-correction component. Evaluations across diverse conditions (autism, leukemia, cardiovascular), cell types, and technical and biological effects show that scMEDAL-RE produces interpretable, batch-specific embeddings that complement both scMEDAL-FE and established correction methods (scVI, Scanorama, Harmony, SAUCIE), yielding more accurate prediction of disease status, donor group, and tissue. scMEDAL also provides generative visualizations, including counterfactual reconstructions of a cell's expression as if acquired in another batch. The framework allows substitution of the fixed-effects component with other correction methods, while retaining scMEDAL-RE's enhanced predictive power and visualization. Overall, scMEDAL is a versatile, interpretable framework that complements existing correction, providing enhanced insight into cellular heterogeneity and data acquisition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06635v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aixa X. Andrade, Son Nguyen, Austin Marckx, Albert Montillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
