<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN</link>
    <description>q-bio.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:01:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>pHapCompass: Probabilistic Assembly and Uncertainty Quantification of Polyploid Haplotype Phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computing haplotypes from sequencing data, i.e. haplotype assembly, is an important component of foundational molecular and population genetics problems, including interpreting the effects of genetic variation on complex traits and reconstructing genealogical relationships. Assembling the haplotypes of polyploid genomes remains a significant challenge due to the exponential search space of haplotype phasings and read assignment ambiguity; the latter challenge is particularly difficult for polyploid haplotype assemblers since the information contained within the observed sequence reads is often insufficient for unambiguous haplotype assignment in polyploid genomes. We present pHapCompass, probabilistic haplotype assembly algorithms for diploid and polyploid genomes that explicitly model and propagate read assignment ambiguity to compute a distribution over polyploid haplotype phasings. We develop graph theoretic algorithms to enable statistical inference and uncertainty quantification despite an exponential space of possible phasings. Since prior work evaluates polyploid haplotype assembly on synthetic genomes that do not reflect the realistic genomic complexity of polyploidy organisms, we develop a computational workflow for simulating genomes and DNA-seq for auto- and allopolyploids. Additionally, we generalize the vector error rate and minimum error correction evaluation criteria for partially phased haplotypes. Benchmarking of pHapCompass and several existing polyploid haplotype assemblers shows that pHapCompass yields competitive performance across varying genomic complexities and polyploid structures while retaining an accurate quantification of phase uncertainty. The source code for pHapCompass, simulation scripts, and datasets are freely available at https://github.com/bayesomicslab/pHapCompass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04393v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marjan Hosseini (School of Computing, University of Connecticut), Ella Veiner (School of Computing, University of Connecticut), Thomas Bergendahl (School of Computing, University of Connecticut), Tala Yasenpoor (School of Computing, University of Connecticut), Zane Smith (Department of Entomology and Plant Pathology, University of Tennessee), Margaret Staton (Department of Entomology and Plant Pathology, University of Tennessee), Derek Aguiar (School of Computing, University of Connecticut, Institute for Systems Genomics, University of Connecticut)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
