<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 03:51:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The relevance of higher-order ties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Higher-order networks effectively represent complex systems with group interactions. Existing methods usually overlook the relative contribution of group interactions (hyperlinks) of different sizes to the overall network structure. Yet, this has many important applications, especially when the network has meaningful node labels. In this work, we propose a comprehensive methodology to precisely measure the contribution of different orders to the overall network structure. First, we propose the order contribution measure, which quantifies the contribution of hyperlinks of different orders to the link weights (local scale), number of triangles (mesoscale) and size of the largest connected component (global scale) of the pairwise weighted network. Second, we propose the measure of order relevance, which gives insights in how hyperlinks of different orders contribute to the considered network property. Most interestingly, it enables an assessment of whether this contribution is synergistic or redundant with respect to that of hyperlinks of other orders. Third, to account for labels, we propose a metric of label group balance to assess how hyperlinks of different orders connect label-induced groups of nodes. We applied these metrics to a large-scale board interlock network and scientific collaboration network, in which node labels correspond to geographical location of the nodes. Experiments including a comparison with randomized null models reveal how from the global level perspective, we observe synergistic contributions of orders in the board interlock network, whereas in the collaboration network there is more redundancy. The findings shed new light on social scientific debates on the role of busy directors in global business networks and the connective effects of large author teams in scientific collaboration networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04584v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Ceria, Frank W. Takes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutation mitigates finite-size effects in spatial evolutionary games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Agent-based simulations are essential for studying cooperation on spatial networks. However, finite-size effects -- random fluctuations due to limited network sizes -- can cause certain strategies to unexpectedly dominate or disappear, leading to unreliable outcomes. While enlarging network sizes or carefully preparing initial states can reduce these effects, both approaches require significant computational resources. In this study, we demonstrate that incorporating mutation into simulations on limited networks offers an effective and resource-efficient alternative. Using spatial optional public goods games and a more intricate tolerance-based variant, we find that rare mutations preserve inherently stable equilibria. When equilibria are affected by finite-size effects, introducing moderate mutation rates prevent finite-size-induced strategy dominance or extinction, producing results consistent with large-network simulations. Our findings position mutation as a practical tool for improving the reliability of agent-based models and emphasize the importance of mutation sensitivity analysis in managing finite-size effects across spatial networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04654v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Shen, Zhixue He, Lei Shi, Jun Tanimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feature-Based Network Construction: From Sampling to What-if Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Networks are characterized by structural features, such as degree distribution, triangular closures, and assortativity. This paper addresses the problem of reconstructing instances of continuously (and non-negatively) weighted networks from given feature values. We introduce the gradient-based Feature-Based Network Construction (FBNC) framework. FBNC allows for sampling networks that satisfy prespecified features exactly (hard constraint sampling). Initializing the FBNC gradient descent with a random graph, FBNC can be used as an alternative to exponential random graphs in sampling graphs conditional on given feature values. We establish an implicit regularization approach to the original feature-fitting loss minimization problem so that FBNC achieves a parsimonious change in the underlying graph, where the term "implicit" stems from using appropriate norms in the very construction of the FBNC gradient descent. In constructing the implicit regularization, we distinguish between the case where weights of a link can be chosen from a bounded range, and, the more demanding case, where the weight matrix of the graph constitutes a Markov chain. We show that FBNC expands to "what-if analysis" of networks, that is, for a given initial network and a set of features satisfied by this network, FBNC finds the network closest to the initial network with some of the feature values adjusted or new features added. Numerical experiments in social network management and financial network regulation demonstrate the value of FBNC for graph (re)construction and what-if analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05124v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Franssen, Joost Berkhout, Bernd Heidergott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual approach to proving electoral fraud via statistics and forensics (Dvojnoe dokazatel'stvo falsifikazij na vyborah statistikoj i kriminalistikoj)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04535v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electoral fraud often manifests itself as statistical anomalies in election results, yet its extent can rarely be reliably confirmed by other evidence. Here we report complete results of municipal elections in Vlasikha town near Moscow, where we observe both statistical irregularities in the vote-counting transcripts and forensic evidence of tampering with ballots during their overnight storage. We evaluate two types of statistical signatures in the vote sequence that can prove batches of fraudulent ballots have been injected. We find that pairs of factory-made security bags with identical serial numbers are used in this fraud scheme. At 8 out of our 9 polling stations, the statistical and forensic evidence agrees (identifying 7 as fraudulent and 1 as honest), while at the remaining station the statistical evidence detects the fraud while the forensic one is insufficient. We also illustrate that the use of tamper-indicating seals at elections is inherently unreliable. -- --
  Tezis po-russki est' v russkoj versii stat'i (normal'noj kirillicej, ne translitom)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04535v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Podlazov, Vadim Makarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac-Equation Signal Processing: Physics Boosts Topological Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological signals are variables or features associated with both nodes and edges of a network. Recently, in the context of Topological Machine Learning, great attention has been devoted to signal processing of such topological signals. Most of the previous topological signal processing algorithms treat node and edge signals separately and work under the hypothesis that the true signal is smooth and/or well approximated by a harmonic eigenvector of the Hodge-Laplacian, which may be violated in practice. Here we propose Dirac-equation signal processing, a framework for efficiently reconstructing true signals on nodes and edges, also if they are not smooth or harmonic, by processing them jointly. The proposed physics-inspired algorithm is based on the spectral properties of the topological Dirac operator. It leverages the mathematical structure of the topological Dirac equation to boost the performance of the signal processing algorithm. We discuss how the relativistic dispersion relation obeyed by the topological Dirac equation can be used to assess the quality of the signal reconstruction. Finally, we demonstrate the improved performance of the algorithm with respect to previous algorithms. Specifically, we show that Dirac-equation signal processing can also be used efficiently if the true signal is a non-trivial linear combination of more than one eigenstate of the Dirac equation, as it generally occurs for real signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05132v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runyue Wang, Yu Tian, Pietro Li\`o, Ginestra Bianconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Sets the Agenda on Social Media? Ideology and Polarization in Online Debates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05176v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The abundance of information on social media has reshaped public discussions, shifting attention to the mechanisms that drive online discourse. This study analyzes large-scale Twitter (now X) data from three global debates -- Climate Change, COVID-19, and the Russo-Ukrainian War -- to investigate the structural dynamics of engagement. Our findings reveal that discussions are not primarily shaped by specific categories of actors, such as media or activists, but by shared ideological alignment. Users consistently form polarized communities, where their ideological stance in one debate predicts their positions in others. This polarization transcends individual topics, reflecting a broader pattern of ideological divides. Furthermore, the influence of individual actors within these communities appears secondary to the reinforcing effects of selective exposure and shared narratives. Overall, our results underscore that ideological alignment, rather than actor prominence, plays a central role in structuring online discourse and shaping the spread of information in polarized environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05176v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edoardo Loru, Alessandro Galeazzi, Anita Bonetti, Emanuele Sangiorgio, Niccol\`o Di Marco, Matteo Cinelli, Andrea Baronchelli, Walter Quattrociocchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-feeding Creates Tipping Points in Microbiome Diversity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05212v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A key unresolved question in microbial ecology is how the extraordinary diversity of microbiomes emerges from the behaviour of individual populations. This process is driven by the cross-feeding networks that structure these communities, but are hard to untangle due to their inherent complexity. We address this problem using the tools of network science to develop a model of microbial community structure. We discover tipping points at which diversity abruptly declines due to the catastrophic collapse of cross-feeding networks. Our results are a rare example of an ecological tipping point in diversity and provide insight into the fundamental processes shaping microbiota and their robustness. We illustrate this by showing how the unculturability of microbial diversity emerges as an inherent property of their microbial cross-feeding networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05212v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Clegg, Thilo gross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal spatial inflation of human mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06889v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the interplay between egocentric preference and urban structure in shaping human mobility has profound implications for improving epidemic intervention, social equity, and urban resilience. However, numerous existing studies either solely identify the egocentric preferences -- the anchoring effects from home -- or the impact of hierarchical urban structures. Here, we propose a network-based approach to present human mobility in both spatial and topological aspects within the urban system, using cell phone trajectory data from millions of users across three countries. By segmenting mobility trajectories into modules and examining their overlap with urban scales, we have observed the inflation law that the geospatial extent of these modules increases sub-linearly with their distance from home. Moreover, the egocentric preference for higher urban levels leads to this increase. This universal finding indicates that home-based preferences distort the hierarchical scales of human mobility in the urban environment, regardless of demographics or geography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06889v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Zhong, Lei Dong, Qi Wang, Chaoming Song, Jianxi Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural results for the Tree Builder Random Walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18734v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the Tree Builder Random Walk: a randomly growing tree, built by a walker as she is walking around the tree. Namely, at each time $n$, she adds a leaf to her current vertex with probability $p_n \asymp n^{-\gamma}$, $\gamma\in (2/3,1]$, then moves to a uniform random neighbor on the possibly modified tree. We show that the tree process at its growth times, after a random finite number of steps, can be coupled to be identical to the Barab\'asi-Albert preferential attachment tree model.
  Thus, our TBRW-model is a local dynamics giving rise to the BA-model. The coupling also implies that many properties known for the BA-model, such as diameter and degree distribution, can be directly transferred to our TBRW-model, extending previous results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18734v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janos Engl\"ander, Giulio Iacobelli, G\'abor Pete, Rodrigo Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
