<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 04:01:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the role of network structure in learning to coordinate with bounded rationality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many socioeconomic phenomena, such as technology adoption, collaborative problem-solving, and content engagement, involve a collection of agents coordinating to take a common action, aligning their decisions to maximize their individual goals. We consider a model for networked interactions where agents learn to coordinate their binary actions under a strict bound on their rationality. We first prove that our model is a potential game and that the optimal action profile is always to achieve perfect alignment at one of the two possible actions, regardless of the network structure. Using a stochastic learning algorithm known as Log Linear Learning, where agents have the same finite rationality parameter, we show that the probability of agents successfully agreeing on the correct decision is monotonically increasing in the number of network links. Therefore, more connectivity improves the accuracy of collective decision-making, as predicted by the phenomenon known as Wisdom of Crowds. Finally, we show that for a fixed number of links, a regular network maximizes the probability of success. We conclude that when using a network of irrational agents, promoting more homogeneous connectivity improves the accuracy of collective decision-making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15683v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Zhang, Marcos M. Vasconcelos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric inference of higher order interaction patterns in networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a method for obtaining parsimonious decompositions of networks into higher order interactions which can take the form of arbitrary motifs.The method is based on a class of analytically solvable generative models, where vertices are connected via explicit copies of motifs, which in combination with non-parametric priors allow us to infer higher order interactions from dyadic graph data without any prior knowledge on the types or frequencies of such interactions. Crucially, we also consider 'degree--corrected' models that correctly reflect the degree distribution of the network and consequently prove to be a better fit for many real world--networks compared to non-degree corrected models. We test the presented approach on simulated data for which we recover the set of underlying higher order interactions to a high degree of accuracy. For empirical networks the method identifies concise sets of atomic subgraphs from within thousands of candidates that cover a large fraction of edges and include higher order interactions of known structural and functional significance. The method not only produces an explicit higher order representation of the network but also a fit of the network to analytically tractable models opening new avenues for the systematic study of higher order network structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15635v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatol E. Wegner, Sofia C. Olhede</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initialisation and Topology Effects in Decentralised Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15855v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fully decentralised federated learning enables collaborative training of individual machine learning models on distributed devices on a network while keeping the training data localised. This approach enhances data privacy and eliminates both the single point of failure and the necessity for central coordination. Our research highlights that the effectiveness of decentralised federated learning is significantly influenced by the network topology of connected devices. A simplified numerical model for studying the early behaviour of these systems leads us to an improved artificial neural network initialisation strategy, which leverages the distribution of eigenvector centralities of the nodes of the underlying network, leading to a radically improved training efficiency. Additionally, our study explores the scaling behaviour and choice of environmental parameters under our proposed initialisation strategy. This work paves the way for more efficient and scalable artificial neural network training in a distributed and uncoordinated environment, offering a deeper understanding of the intertwining roles of network structure and learning dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15855v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arash Badie-Modiri, Chiara Boldrini, Lorenzo Valerio, J\'anos Kert\'esz, M\'arton Karsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Demand Prediction in Open Systems by Cartogram-aided Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Predicting temporal patterns across various domains poses significant challenges due to their nuanced and often nonlinear trajectories. To address this challenge, prediction frameworks have been continuously refined, employing data-driven statistical methods, mathematical models, and machine learning. Recently, as one of the challenging systems, shared transport systems such as public bicycles have gained prominence due to urban constraints and environmental concerns. Predicting rental and return patterns at bicycle stations remains a formidable task due to the system's openness and imbalanced usage patterns across stations. In this study, we propose a deep learning framework to predict rental and return patterns by leveraging cartogram approaches. The cartogram approach facilitates the prediction of demand for newly installed stations with no training data as well as long-period prediction, which has not been achieved before. We apply this method to public bicycle rental-and-return data in Seoul, South Korea, employing a spatial-temporal convolutional graph attention network. Our improved architecture incorporates batch attention and modified node feature updates for better prediction accuracy across different time scales. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our framework in predicting temporal patterns and its potential applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16049v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangjoon Park, Yongsung Kwon, Hyungjoon Soh, Mi Jin Lee, Seung-Woo Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Road layout in the KPZ class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a road layout and traffic model, based on last passage percolation (LPP). An easy naive argument shows that coalescence of traffic trajectories is essential to be considered when observing traffic networks around us. This is a fundamental feature in first passage percolation (FPP) models where nearby geodesics naturally coalesce in search of the easiest passage through the landscape. Road designers seek the same in pursuing cost savings, hence FPP geodesics are straightforward candidates to model road layouts. Unfortunately no detailed knowledge is rigorously available on FPP geodesics. To address this, we use exponential LPP instead to build a stochastic model of road traffic and prove certain characteristics thereof. Cars start from every point of the lattice and follow half-infinite geodesics in random directions. Exponential LPP is known to be in the KPZ universality class and it is widely expected that FPP shares very similar properties, hence our findings should equally apply to FPP-based modelling. We address several traffic-related quantities of this model and compare our theorems to real life road networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16268v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M\'arton Bal\'azs, Sudeshna Bhattacharjee, Karambir Das, David Harper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Droughts in Germany -- Why global climate change amplifies hydrological extremes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16551v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The warmer temperatures of global climate change strengthen the water cycle, evaporation and precipitation increase. But the extremes of heavy rain, floods, dry periods and droughts will also increase. How does this fit together? Simple physical considerations show which factors mainly regulate the strength of the water cycle in the Earth system, and how this determines water availability on land. This can be used to interpret the observed changes in the water balance in Germany and explain the increasing dryness in Germany.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16551v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/piuz.202401697</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physik in unserer Zeit, 2024, (in German)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Axel Kleidon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilevel Modeling as a Methodology for the Simulation of Human Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multilevel modeling is increasingly relevant in the context of modelling and simulation since it leads to several potential benefits, such as software reuse and integration, the split of semantically separated levels into sub-models, the possibility to employ different levels of detail, and the potential for parallel execution. The coupling that inevitably exists between the sub-models, however, implies the need for maintaining consistency between the various components, more so when different simulation paradigms are employed (e.g., sequential vs parallel, discrete vs continuous). In this paper we argue that multilevel modelling is well suited for the simulation of human mobility, since it naturally leads to the decomposition of the model into two layers, the "micro" and "macro" layer, where individual entities (micro) and long-range interactions (macro) are described. In this paper we investigate the challenges of multilevel modeling, and describe some preliminary results using prototype implementations of multilayer simulators in the context of epidemic diffusion and vehicle pollution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16745v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/DS-RT55542.2022.9932080</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>proc. 2022 IEEE/ACM 26th International Symposium on Distributed Simulation and Real-Time Applications (DS-RT'22), Al\`es, France, September 26-28, 2022, pp. 49-56</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Serena, Moreno Marzolla, Gabriele D'Angelo, Stefano Ferretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Affective Polarization: From Consensus to Partisan Divides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Politically divided societies are also often divided emotionally: people like and trust those with similar political views (in-group favoritism) while disliking and distrusting those with different views (out-group animosity). This phenomenon, called affective polarization, influences individual decisions, including seemingly apolitical choices such as whether to wear a mask or what car to buy. We present a dynamical model of decision-making in an affectively polarized society, identifying three potential global outcomes separated by a sharp boundary in the parameter space: consensus, partisan polarization, and non-partisan polarization. Analysis reveals that larger out-group animosity compared to in-group favoritism, i.e. more hate than love, is sufficient for polarization, while larger in-group favoritism compared to out-group animosity, i.e., more love than hate, is necessary for consensus. We also show that, counter-intuitively, increasing cross-party connections facilitates polarization, and that by emphasizing partisan differences, mass media creates self-fulfilling prophecies that lead to polarization. Affective polarization also creates tipping points in the opinion landscape where one group suddenly reverses their trends. Our findings aid in understanding and addressing the cascading effects of affective polarization, offering insights for strategies to mitigate polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16940v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Buddhika Nettasinghe, Allon G. Percus, Kristina Lerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of mobile phone sensing data to estimate residence and mobility times in urban patches during the COVID-19 epidemic: The case of the 2020 outbreak in Hermosillo, Mexico</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.09963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.09963v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is often necessary to introduce the main characteristics of population mobility dynamics to model critical social phenomena such as the economy, violence, transmission of information, or infectious diseases. In this work, we focus on modeling and inferring urban population mobility using the geospatial data of its inhabitants. The objective is to estimate mobility and times inhabitants spend in the areas of interest, such as zip codes and census geographical areas. The proposed method uses the Brownian bridge model for animal movement in ecology. We illustrate its possible applications using mobile phone GPS data in 2020 from the city of Hermosillo, Sonora, in Mexico. We incorporate the estimated residence-mobility matrix into a multi-patch compartmental SEIR model to assess the effect of mobility changes due to governmental interventions</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.09963v2</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Leticia Ram\'irez-Ram\'irez, Jos\'e A. Montoya, Jes\'us F. Espinoza, Chahak Mehta, Albert Orwa Akuno, Tan Bui-Thanh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-agent reinforcement learning using echo-state network and its application to pedestrian dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11834v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, simulations of pedestrians using the multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) have been studied. This study considered the roads on a grid-world environment, and implemented pedestrians as MARL agents using an echo-state network and the least squares policy iteration method. Under this environment, the ability of these agents to learn to move forward by avoiding other agents was investigated. Specifically, we considered two types of tasks: the choice between a narrow direct route and a broad detour, and the bidirectional pedestrian flow in a corridor. The simulations results indicated that the learning was successful when the density of the agents was not that high.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11834v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisato Komatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
