<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 05:02:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemiology of the Living Dead: A social Force Model of a Zombie Outbreak</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We adapt the social force model of crowd dynamics to capture the evacuation during a zombie outbreak from an academic building. Individuals navigate the building, opening doors, and evacuate to the nearest exit. Zombies chase the uninfected individuals, and once caught there is a probability of a susceptible individual being infected or killed, or for the zombie to be killed by the person being attacked. We find that the speed of the zombies plays a crucial role in the dynamics of the evacuation, the rate of infection, and the number of casualties during the outbreak. The model leads to insights that may be relevant to other, less fictitious, emergency situations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05444v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sydney Balkovitz, Alyssa Croco, Jake Garda, Maggie Hatch, Franklyn Paul, Lauren Vu, Tristan West, Gavin Buxton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive geolocation data reveal evacuation behaviour during the 2024 Noto Peninsula earthquake and tsunami</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On 1 January 2024, devastating tsunamis caused by the Noto Peninsula earthquake hit coastal areas within several minutes, but only two tsunami casualties were officially reported. Despite its importance, the cause of this unexpectedly low human loss was unclear because of the limited access to the peninsula and the presence of many visitors during the holiday, which made conducting conventional surveys infeasible. Here, we reveal evacuation behaviour during the 2024 Noto Peninsula tsunami using massive geolocation data collected from a smartphone app. By analysing these massive data, which include over 1.5 million records collected on this day, we find that the evacuation was extremely fast, occurring within 2--6 minutes after the origin time. Further analyses suggest that these fast departures were driven mainly by strong ground shaking; the fact that the tsunami occurred during the family-oriented New Year holiday was also a key factor. Additionally, the long-term analysis of the data reveals that people started returning to the coastal area 20--100 minutes after the origin time, which was long before the downgrading and cancellation of the tsunami warnings. These results highlight the utility of the innovative data-driven approach to evacuation surveys, which addresses the limitations of conventional evacuation surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05795v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fumiyasu Makinoshima, Saki Yotsui, Shosuke Sato, Fumihiko Imamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network analysis of the Danish bicycle infrastructure: Bikeability across urban-rural divides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Research on cycling conditions focuses on cities, because cycling is commonly considered an urban phenomenon. People outside of cities should, however, also have access to the benefits of active mobility. To bridge the gap between urban and rural cycling research, we analyze the bicycle network of Denmark, covering around 43,000 km2 and nearly 6 mio. inhabitants. We divide the network into four levels of traffic stress and quantify the spatial patterns of bikeability based on network density, fragmentation, and reach. We find that the country has a high share of low-stress infrastructure, but with a very uneven distribution. The widespread fragmentation of low-stress infrastructure results in low mobility for cyclists who do not tolerate high traffic stress. Finally, we partition the network into bikeability clusters and conclude that both high and low bikeability are strongly spatially clustered. Our research confirms that in Denmark, bikeability tends to be high in urban areas. The latent potential for cycling in rural areas is mostly unmet, although some rural areas benefit from previous infrastructure investments. To mitigate the lack of low-stress cycling infrastructure outside of urban centers, we suggest prioritizing investments in urban-rural cycling connections and encourage further research in improving rural cycling conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06083v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ane Rahbek Vier{\o}, Michael Szell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Phase Transitions in Non-equilibrium Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamical phase transitions (DPTs) characterize critical changes in system behavior occurring at finite times, providing a lens to study nonequilibrium phenomena beyond conventional equilibrium physics. While extensively studied in quantum systems, DPTs have remained largely unexplored in classical settings. Recent experiments on complex systems, from social networks to financial markets, have revealed abrupt dynamical changes analogous to quantum DPTs, motivating the search for a theoretical understanding. Here, we present a minimal model for nonequilibrium networks, demonstrating that nonlinear interactions among network edges naturally give rise to DPTs. Specifically, we show that network degree diverges at a finite critical time, following a universal hyperbolic scaling, consistent with empirical observations. Our analytical results predict that key network properties, including degree distributions and clustering coefficients, exhibit critical scaling as criticality approaches. These findings establish a theoretical foundation for understanding emergent nonequilibrium criticality across diverse complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06704v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiazhen Liu, Nathaniel M. Aden, Debasish Sarker, Chaoming Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hallmarks of Deception in Asset-Exchange Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06761v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the transient and steady-state dynamics of the Bennati-Dregulescu-Yakovenko money game in the presence of probabilistic cheaters, who can misrepresent their financial status by claiming to have no money. We derive the steady-state wealth distribution per player analytically and show how the presence of hidden cheaters can be inferred from the relative variance of wealth per player. In scenarios with a finite number of cheaters amidst an infinite pool of honest players, we identify a critical probability of cheating at which the total wealth owned by the cheaters experiences a second-order discontinuity. Below this point, the probability to lose money is larger than the probability to gain; conversely, above this point, the direction is reversed. Additionally, we establish a threshold probability at which cheaters collectively possess more than half of the total wealth in the game. Lastly, we provide bounds on the rate at which both cheaters and honest players can gain or lose wealth, contributing to a deeper understanding of deception in asset exchange models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06761v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian Blom, Dmitrii E. Makarov, Alja\v{z} Godec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global transformer overheating from geomagnetic storms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Geomagnetic storms occurring due to sustained, high-speed solar winds are known to induce currents in power distribution networks. These geomagnetically induced currents (GICs) can cause high voltage transformers (HVT) to overheat, thus resulting in a catastrophic electricity loss event (CELE). Since significant portions of infrastructures around the world rely heavily on access to electric power, it is essential to estimate the risks associated with GICs on a global scale. We assemble multiple methodologies across various scientific disciplines to develop a framework assessing the probability of a severe geomagnetic storm causing a long-term, widespread power outage. Our model incorporates thermal models of HVT tie bar hot spots, historical geoelectric field estimates, and a global conductivity model to estimate the risk of long-term power outage for regions between -70 degrees and 80 degrees geomagnetic latitude due to transformer overheating failure. Assuming a uniform 33% HVT spare capacity, our analysis indicates that a 1 in 10,000 year storm would result in approximately 1% of the population in Europe and North America experiencing a long-term (months to years) electricity loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18070v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Morgan Rivers, {\L}ukasz G. Gajewski, David Denkenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragility of Chess positions: measure, universality and tipping points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02333v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel metric to quantify the fragility of chess positions using the interaction graph of pieces. This fragility score $F$ captures the tension within a position and serves as a strong indicator of tipping points in a game. In well-known games, maximum fragility often aligns with decisive moments marked by brilliant moves. Analyzing a large dataset of games, we find that fragility typically peaks around move $15$, with pawns ($\approx 60\%$) and knights ($\approx 20\%$) frequently involved in high-tension positions. Comparing the Stockfish evaluation with the fragility score, we observe that the maximum fragility ply often serves as a critical turning point, where the moves made afterward can determine the outcome of the game. Remarkably, average fragility curves show a universal pattern across a wide range of players, games, and openings, with a subtle deviation observed in games played by the engine Stockfish. Our analysis reveals a gradual buildup of fragility starting around $8$ moves before the peak, followed by a prolonged fragile state lasting up to $15$ moves. This suggests a gradual intensification of positional tension leading to decisive moments in the game. These insights offer a valuable tool for both players and engines to assess critical moments in chess.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02333v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Barthelemy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Media Informatics for Sustainable Cities and Societies: An Overview of the Applications, associated Challenges, and Potential Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the modern world, our cities and societies face several technological and societal challenges, such as rapid urbanization, global warming &amp; climate change, the digital divide, and social inequalities, increasing the need for more sustainable cities and societies. Addressing these challenges requires a multifaceted approach involving all the stakeholders, sustainable planning, efficient resource management, innovative solutions, and modern technologies. Like other modern technologies, social media informatics also plays its part in developing more sustainable and resilient cities and societies. Despite its limitations, social media informatics has proven very effective in various sustainable cities and society applications. In this paper, we review and analyze the role of social media informatics in sustainable cities and society by providing a detailed overview of its applications, associated challenges, and potential solutions. This work is expected to provide a baseline for future research in the domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03600v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jebran Khan, Kashif Ahmad, Senthil Kumar Jagatheesaperumal, Nasir Ahmad, Kyung-Ah Sohn</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
