<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 04:01:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multigraph reconstruction via nonlinear random walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last few years, network science has proved to be useful in modeling a variety of complex systems, composed of a large number of interconnected units. The intricate pattern of interactions often allows the system to achieve complex tasks, such as synchronization or collective motions. In this regard, the interplay between network structure and dynamics has long been recognized as a cornerstone of network science. Among dynamical processes, random walks are undoubtedly among the most studied stochastic processes. While traditionally, the random walkers are assumed to be independent, this assumption breaks down if nodes are endowed with a finite carrying capacity, a feature shared by many real-life systems. Recently, a class of nonlinear diffusion processes accounting for the finite carrying capacities of the nodes was introduced. The stationary nodes densities were shown to be nonlinearly correlated with the nodes degrees, allowing to uncover the network structure by performing a few measurements of the stationary density at the level of a single arbitrary node and by solving an inverse problem. In this work, we extend this class of nonlinear diffusion processes to the case of multigraphs, in which links between nodes carry distinct attributes. Assuming the knowledge of the pattern of interactions associated with one type of links, we show how the degree distribution of the whole multigraph can be reconstructed. The effectiveness of the reconstruction algorithm is demonstrated through simulations on various multigraph topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18555v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois de Kemmeter, Timoteo Carletti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equity Implications of Net-Zero Emissions: A Multi-Model Analysis of Energy Expenditures Across Income Classes Under Economy-Wide Deep Decarbonization Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With companies, states, and countries targeting net-zero emissions around midcentury, there are questions about how these targets alter household welfare and finances, including distributional effects across income groups. This paper examines the distributional dimensions of technology transitions and net-zero policies with a focus on welfare impacts across household incomes. The analysis uses a model intercomparison with a range of energy-economy models using harmonized policy scenarios reaching economy-wide, net-zero CO2 emissions across the United States in 2050. We employ a novel linking approach that connects output from detailed energy system models with survey microdata on energy expenditures across income classes to provide distributional analysis of net-zero policies. Although there are differences in model structure and input assumptions, we find broad agreement in qualitative trends in policy incidence and energy burdens across income groups. Models generally agree that direct energy expenditures for many households will likely decline over time with reference and net-zero policies. However, there is variation in the extent of changes relative to current levels, energy burdens relative to reference levels, and electricity expenditures. Policy design, primarily how climate policy revenues are used, has first-order impacts on distributional outcomes. Net-zero policy costs, in both absolute and relative terms, are unevenly distributed across households, and relative increases in energy expenditures are higher for lowest-income households. However, we also find that recycled revenues from climate policies have countervailing effects when rebated on a per-capita basis, offsetting higher energy burdens and potentially even leading to net progressive outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18748v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.egycc.2023.100118</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024, Energy and Climate Change, 5: 100118</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>John Bistlinea, Chikara Onda, Morgan Browning, Johannes Emmerling, Gokul Iyer, Megan Mahajan, Jim McFarland, Haewon McJeon, Robbie Orvis, Francisco Ralston Fonseca, Christopher Roney, Noah Sandoval, Luis Sarmiento, John Weyant, Jared Woollacott, Mei Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resilience of mobility network to dynamic population response across COVID-19 interventions: evidences from Chile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The COVID19 pandemic highlighted the importance of non-traditional data sources, such as mobile phone data, to inform effective public health interventions and monitor adherence to such measures. Previous studies showed how socioeconomic characteristics shaped population response during restrictions and how repeated interventions eroded adherence over time. Less is known about how different population strata changed their response to repeated interventions and how this impacted the resulting mobility network. We study population response during the first and second infection waves of the COVID-19 pandemic in Chile and Spain. Via spatial lag and regression models, we investigate the adherence to mobility interventions at the municipality level in Chile, highlighting the significant role of wealth, labor structure, COVID-19 incidence, and network metrics characterizing business-as-usual municipality connectivity in shaping mobility changes during the two waves. We assess network structural similarities in the two periods by defining mobility hotspots and traveling probabilities in the two countries. As a proof of concept, we simulate and compare outcomes of an epidemic diffusion occurring in the two waves. Our analysis reveals the resilience of the mobility network across waves. We test the robustness of our findings recovering similar results for Spain. Finally, epidemic modeling suggests that historical mobility data from past waves can be leveraged to inform future disease spatial invasion models in repeated interventions. This study highlights the value of historical mobile phone data for building pandemic preparedness and lessens the need for real-time data streams for risk assessment and outbreak response. Our work provides valuable insights into the complex interplay of factors driving mobility across repeated interventions, aiding in developing targeted mitigation strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19141v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Casaburi, Lorenzo Dall'Amico, Nicol\`o Gozzi, Kyriaki Kalimeri, Anna Sapienza, Rossano Schifanella, T. Di Matteo, Leo Ferres, Mattia Mazzoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A statistical analysis of drug seizures and opioid overdose deaths in Ohio from 2014 to 2018</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper examines the association between police drug seizures and drug overdose deaths in Ohio from 2014 to 2018. We use linear regression, ARIMA models, and categorical data analysis to quantify the effect of drug seizure composition and weight on drug overdose deaths, to quantify the lag between drug seizures and overdose deaths, and to compare the weight distributions of drug seizures conducted by different types of law enforcement (national, local, and drug task forces). We find that drug seizure composition and weight have strong predictive value for drug overdose deaths (F = 27.14, p &lt; 0.0001, R^2 = .7799). A time series analysis demonstrates no statistically significant lag between drug seizures and overdose deaths or weight. Histograms and Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests demonstrate stark differences between seizure weight distributions of different types of law enforcement (p &lt; 0.0001 for each pairwise comparison). We include a discussion of what our conclusions mean for law enforcement and harm reduction efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19199v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.47611/jsr.v10i1.786</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Student Research, Volume 10, Issue 1, 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lin Ma, Lam Tran, David White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the Potential of Renewable Energy Through Curtailment Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A significant fraction (5-15%) of renewable energy generated goes into waste in the grids around the world today due to oversupply issues and transmission constraints. Being able to predict when and where renewable curtailment occurs would improve renewable utilization. The core of this work is to enable the machine learning community to help decarbonize electricity grids by unlocking the potential of renewable energy through curtailment prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18526v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bilge Acun, Brent Morgan, Henry Richardson, Nat Steinsultz, Carole-Jean Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Detection of Critical Urban Events using Mobile Phone Network Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19125v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Network Signalling Data (NSD) have the potential to provide continuous spatio-temporal information about the presence, mobility, and usage patterns of cell phone services by individuals. Such information is invaluable for monitoring large urban areas and supporting the implementation of decision-making services. When analyzed in real time, NSD can enable the early detection of critical urban events, including fires, large accidents, stampedes, terrorist attacks, and sports and leisure gatherings, especially if these events significantly impact mobile phone network activity in the affected areas. This paper presents empirical evidence that advanced NSD can detect anomalies in mobile traffic service consumption, attributable to critical urban events, with fine spatial and temporal resolutions. We introduce two methodologies for real-time anomaly detection from multivariate time series extracted from large-scale NSD, utilizing a range of algorithms adapted from the state-of-the-art in unsupervised machine learning techniques for anomaly detection. Our research includes a comprehensive quantitative evaluation of these algorithms on a large-scale dataset of NSD service consumption for the Paris region. The evaluation uses an original dataset of documented critical or unusual urban events. This dataset has been built as a ground truth basis for assessing the algorithms performance. The obtained results demonstrate that our framework can detect unusual events almost instantaneously and locate the affected areas with high precision, largely outperforming random classifiers. This efficiency and effectiveness underline the potential of NSD-based anomaly detection in significantly enhancing emergency response strategies and urban planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19125v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Lemaire, Angelo Furno, Stefania Rubrichi, Alexis Bondu, Zbigniew Smoreda, Cezary Ziemlicki, Nour-Eddin El Faouzi, Eric Gaume</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling public opinion control by a charismatic leader</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the average long-time behavior of the binary opinions of a social group with peer-to-peer interactions under the influence of an external bias and a persuadable leader, a strongly-biased agent with a dynamic opinion with the intention of spreading it across the system. We use a generalized, fully-connected Ising model, with each spin representing the binary opinion of an agent at a given time and a single, super spin representing the opinion of the leader. External fields and interaction constants model the opinion bias and peer-to-peer interactions, respectively, while the temperature $T$ models an idealized social climate, representing an authoritarian regime if $T$ is low or a liberal one if $T$ is high. We derive a mean-field solution for the average magnetization $m$, the "social mood", and investigate how $m$ and the super spin magnetization vary as a function of $T$. We find that, depending on the initial conditions, due to the presence of metastable states, the sign of the average magnetization depends on the temperature. Finally, we verify that this effect is also present even if we consider only nearest-neighbor interactions within the social group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19242v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago S. A. N. Sim\~oes, Antonio Coniglio, Hans J. Herrmann, Lucilla de Arcangelis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cascades towards noise-induced transitions on networks revealed using information flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.14016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.14016v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Abrupt, system-wide transitions can be endogenously generated by seemingly stable networks of interacting dynamical units, such as mode switching in neuronal networks or public opinion changes in social systems. However, it remains poorly understood how such `noise-induced transitions' emerge from the interplay of network structure and dynamics on the network. Here, we report on two key roles that nodes can play in the progression towards noise-induced tipping points. The models used are dynamical networks where the nodes are governed by the Boltzmann-Gibbs distribution, but the concept is easily generalized. First, so-called `initiator nodes' absorb and then transmit short-lived fluctuations to neighboring nodes, making them temporarily more dynamic. These neighbor nodes can then in turn transmit fluctuations to their neighbors, and so on, leading to a domino-effect where the more stable a node is (i.e., high average free energy barrier), the more neighbors are needed that have become temporarily dynamic. Interestingly, towards the tipping point we identify so-called `stabilizer nodes' whose state information becomes part of the long-term memory of the system, after which the domino-effect is reversed and settles the node in their new stable attractor. We validate these roles by targeted interventions that make tipping points more (or less) likely to begin or lead to systemic change. This opens up possibilities for understanding and controlling endogenously generated metastable behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.14016v4</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Casper van Elteren, Rick Quax, Peter Sloot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics-based Feature Augmentation of Graph Neural Networks for Variant Emergence Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: During the COVID-19 pandemic, a major driver of new surges has been the emergence of new variants. When a new variant emerges in one or more countries, other nations monitor its spread in preparation for its potential arrival. The impact of the new variant and the timings of epidemic peaks in a country highly depend on when the variant arrives. The current methods for predicting the spread of new variants rely on statistical modeling, however, these methods work only when the new variant has already arrived in the region of interest and has a significant prevalence. Can we predict when a variant existing elsewhere will arrive in a given region? To address this question, we propose a variant-dynamics-informed Graph Neural Network (GNN) approach. First, we derive the dynamics of variant prevalence across pairs of regions (countries) that apply to a large class of epidemic models. The dynamics motivate the introduction of certain features in the GNN. We demonstrate that our proposed dynamics-informed GNN outperforms all the baselines, including the currently pervasive framework of Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs). To advance research in this area, we introduce a benchmarking tool to assess a user-defined model's prediction performance across 87 countries and 36 variants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03390v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Majd Al Aawar, Srikar Mutnuri, Mansooreh Montazerin, Ajitesh Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implicit degree bias in the link prediction task</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14985v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Link prediction -- a task of distinguishing actual hidden edges from random unconnected node pairs -- is one of the quintessential tasks in graph machine learning. Despite being widely accepted as a universal benchmark and a downstream task for representation learning, the validity of the link prediction benchmark itself has been rarely questioned. Here, we show that the common edge sampling procedure in the link prediction task has an implicit bias toward high-degree nodes and produces a highly skewed evaluation that favors methods overly dependent on node degree, to the extent that a ``null'' link prediction method based solely on node degree can yield nearly optimal performance. We propose a degree-corrected link prediction task that offers a more reasonable assessment that aligns better with the performance in the recommendation task. Finally, we demonstrate that the degree-corrected benchmark can more effectively train graph machine-learning models by reducing overfitting to node degrees and facilitating the learning of relevant structures in graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14985v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachith Aiyappa, Xin Wang, Munjung Kim, Ozgur Can Seckin, Jisung Yoon, Yong-Yeol Ahn, Sadamori Kojaku</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
