<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 01:31:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Structural evolution of international crop trade networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Food security is a critical issue closely linked to human being. With the increasing demand for food, international trade has become the main access to supplementing domestic food shortages, which not only alleviates local food shocks, but also exposes economies to global food crises. In this paper, we construct four temporal international crop trade networks (iCTNs) based on trade values of maize, rice, soybean and wheat, and describe the structural evolution of different iCTNs from{ {1993}} to 2018. We find that the size of all the four iCTNs expanded from{ {1993}} to 2018 with more participants and larger trade values. Our results show that the iCTNs not only become tighter according to the increasing in network density and clustering coefficient, but also get more similar. We also find that the iCTNs are not always disassortative, unlike the world cereal trade networks and other international commodity trade networks. The degree assortative coefficients depend on degree directions and crop types. The analysis about assortativity also indicates that economies with high out-degrees tend to connect with economies with low in-degrees and low out-degrees. Additionally, we compare the structure of the four iCTNs to enhance our understanding of the international food trade system. Although the overall evolutionary patterns of different iCTNs are similar, some crops exhibit idiosyncratic trade patterns. It highlights the need to consider different crop networks' idiosyncratic features while making food policies. Our findings about the dynamics of the iCTNs play an important role in understanding vulnerabilities in the global food system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02986v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin-Ting Zhang, Wei-Xing Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Could a gravity inversion exist within the Hollow Earth of Legendary's Monsterverse?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: One of the most popular movie franchises of late is Legendary's Monsterverse as is evidenced by the gross earnings of the series recently surpassing the two and a half billion dollar mark with the release of $\it{Godzilla X Kong}$. As is typical with many movies of this genre, in order to enjoy them one must suspend their disbelief when it comes to the laws of physics. While there are a plethora of examples of violations of basic principles (the square-cube law being the prime example) the idea of a "gravity inversion" occurring inside of the "Hollow Earth" is among the most debated as well as the most relevant to the storylines of the recent movies. The intent of this paper is to show that, while typical scientific arguments refuting the possibility of such an inversion are definitely completely correct, a slight modification of the conditions assumed to exist inside the planet in these arguments may allow for the inversion to actually occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02867v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Steven Millward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring interconnectedness of infectious diseases in funded and unfunded research: a temporal network analysis on bibliometric data 1995-2022</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite substantial investments in infectious disease research over the past decades, the field continues to struggle with inadequate long-term investment strategies and resource disparities, which highlights the critical need for a better understanding of funding and research landscapes to support evidence-based policymaking. Our study presents a novel perspective on the interconnectedness of evolving infectious disease knowledge. Through identifying publications based on funded and unfunded research, the analysis of temporal network of infectious disease associations reveals (i) growing compartmentalisation of funded research, i.e., it focuses on the groups of infectious diseases with readily established connections, and (ii) the growth in global integration in unfunded research, i.e., it tends to be more widely exploratory and links distant diseases. Moreover, we find that in both funded and unfunded research prominent diseases like HIV, malaria and tuberculosis have strong bridging effects facilitating global integration, while diphtheria, tetanus, and pertussis are characterised with strong local connectivity between themselves. We also find that although coronavirus has seen a surge in publications since COVID-19, its systemic impact on the interconnectedness of infectious disease knowledge remains relatively low. Our work highlights the importance of considering the interconnectedness of infectious diseases in health policy making and has potential to contribute to more efficient health resource allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03140v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anbang Du, Michael Head, Markus Brede</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical Modeling of Local Balance in Signed Networks and Its Applications to Global International Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.03774v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Alliances and conflicts in social, political and economic relations can be represented by positive and negative edges in signed networks. A cycle is said to be positive if the product of its edge signs is positive, otherwise it is negative. Then, a signed network is balanced if and only if all its cycles are positive. An index characterizing how much a signed network deviates from being balanced is known as a global balance index. Here we give a step forward in the characterization of signed networks by defining a local balance index, which characterizes how much a given vertex of a signed network contributes to its global balance. We analyze the mathematical foundations and unique structural properties of this index. Then, we apply this index to the study of the evolution of international relations in the globe for the period 1816-2014. In this way we detect and categorize major historic events based on balance fluctuations, helping our understanding towards new mixed approaches to history based on network theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.03774v5</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Diaz-Diaz, Paolo Bartesaghi, Ernesto Estrada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal rich club phenomenon and its formation mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.12192v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The temporal rich club (TRC) phenomenon is widespread in real systems, forming a tight and continuous collection of the prominent nodes that control the system. However, there is still a lack of sufficient understanding of the mechanisms of TRC formation. Here we use the international N-nutrient trade network as an example of an in-depth identification, analysis, and modeling of its TRC phenomenon. The system exhibits a statistically significant TRC phenomenon, with eight economies forming the cornerstone club. Our analysis reveals that node degree is the most influential factor in TRC formation compared to other variables. The mathematical evolution models we constructed propose that the TRC in the N-nutrient trade network arises from the coexistence of degree-homophily and path-dependence mechanisms. By comprehending these mechanisms, we introduce a novel perspective on TRC formation. Although our analysis is limited to the international trade system, the methodology can be extended to analyze the mechanisms underlying TRC emergence in other systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.12192v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.109.014126</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 109 (1), 014126 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mu-Yao Li (ECUST), Ying-Ting Zhang (ECUST), Wei-Xing Zhou (ECUST)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using mathematics to study how people influence each other's opinions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01915v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: People sometimes change their opinions when they discuss things with other people. Researchers can use mathematics to study opinion changes in simplifications of real-life situations. These simplified settings, which are examples of mathematical models, help researchers explore how people influence each other through their social interactions. In today's digital world, these models can help us learn how to promote the spread of accurate information and reduce the spread of inaccurate information. In this article, we discuss a simple mathematical model of opinion changes that arise from social interactions. We briefly describe what such opinion models can tell us and how researchers try to make them more realistic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01915v4</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace J. Li, Jiajie Luo, Kaiyan Peng, Mason A. Porter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visibility graph analysis of the grains and oilseeds indices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.05760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.05760v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Grains and Oilseeds Index (GOI) and its sub-indices of wheat, maize, soyabeans, rice, and barley are daily price indexes reflect the price changes of the global spot markets of staple agro-food crops. In this paper, we carry out a visibility graph (VG) analysis of the GOI and its five sub-indices. Our findings reveal that the degree distributions of the VGs, except for rice, exhibit exponentially truncated power-law tails, while the rice VG conforms to a power-law tail. The average clustering coefficients of the six VGs are quite large ($&gt;0.5$) and exhibit a nice power-law relation with respect to the average degrees of the VGs. For each VG, the clustering coefficients of nodes are inversely proportional to their degrees for large degrees and are correlated to their degrees as a power law for small degrees. All the six VGs exhibit small-world characteristics. The degree-degree correlation coefficients shows that the VGs for maize and soyabeans indices exhibit weak assortative mixing patterns, while the other four VGs are weakly disassortative. The average nearest neighbor degree functions have similar patterns, and each function shows a more complex mixing pattern which decreases for small degrees, increases for mediate degrees, and decreases again for large degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.05760v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physa.2024.130004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica A 650, 130004 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Ran Liu (ECUST), Ming-Xia Li (ECUST), Wei-Xing Zhou (ECUST)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network analysis of graduate program support structures through experiences of various demographic groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.04637v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physics graduate studies are substantial efforts on the part of individual students, departments, and institutions of higher education. Understanding the factors that lead to student success and attrition is crucial for improving these programs. One factor that has recently started to be investigated is the broadly defined students' experiences related to support structures. The Aspects of Student Experience Scale (ASES), a Likert-style survey, was developed by researchers to do just that. In this study, we leverage the network approach for Likert-style surveys (NALS) methodology to provide a unique interpretation of responses to the ASES instrument for well-defined demographic groups. We confirm the validity of our findings by studying the stability of the NALS themes and investigating how they are expressed within demographic-based networks. We find that for all four themes in the original ASES study, certain thematic trends capturing students' experiences vary across the demographic-based networks in meaningful ways. We also reveal that for some demographic groups, there is an interesting interplay between, and mixing of, the original themes. Finally, our study showcases how NALS can be applied to other Likert-style datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.04637v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Phys. Educ. Res. 20, 020106 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Robert P. Dalka, Justyna P. Zwolak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing Individual and Collective Behaviours to Predict Out-of-Routine Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02740v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Predicting human displacements is crucial for addressing various societal challenges, including urban design, traffic congestion, epidemic management, and migration dynamics. While predictive models like deep learning and Markov models offer insights into individual mobility, they often struggle with out-of-routine behaviours. Our study introduces an approach that dynamically integrates individual and collective mobility behaviours, leveraging collective intelligence to enhance prediction accuracy. Evaluating the model on millions of privacy-preserving trajectories across three US cities, we demonstrate its superior performance in predicting out-of-routine mobility, surpassing even advanced deep learning methods. Spatial analysis highlights the model's effectiveness near urban areas with a high density of points of interest, where collective behaviours strongly influence mobility. During disruptive events like the COVID-19 pandemic, our model retains predictive capabilities, unlike individual-based models. By bridging the gap between individual and collective behaviours, our approach offers transparent and accurate predictions, crucial for addressing contemporary mobility challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02740v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Bontorin, Simone Centellegher, Riccardo Gallotti, Luca Pappalardo, Bruno Lepri, Massimiliano Luca</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
