<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 01:56:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ranking matters: Does the new format select the best teams for the knockout phase in the UEFA Champions League?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starting in the 2024/25 season, the Union of European Football Associations (UEFA) has fundamentally changed the format of its club competitions: the group stage has been replaced by a league phase played by 36 teams in an incomplete round robin format. This makes ranking the teams based on their results challenging because teams play against different sets of opponents, whose strengths vary. In this research note, we apply several well-known ranking methods for incomplete round robin tournaments to the 2024/25 UEFA Champions League league phase. Our results show that it is doubtful whether the currently used point-based system provides the best ranking of the teams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13569v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'aszl\'o Csat\'o, Karel Devriesere, Dries Goossens, Andr\'as Gyimesi, Roel Lambers, Frits Spieksma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemic Dynamics in Homes and Destinations under Recurrent Mobility Patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The structure of heterogeneous networks and human mobility patterns profoundly influence the spreading of endemic diseases. In small-scale communities, individuals engage in social interactions within confined environments, such as homes and workplaces, where daily routines facilitate virus transmission through predictable mobility pathways. Here, we introduce a metapopulation model grounded in a Microscopic Markov Chain Approach to simulate susceptible--infected--susceptible dynamics within structured populations. There are two primary types of nodes, homes and destinations, where individuals interact and transmit infections through recurrent mobility patterns. We derive analytical expressions for the epidemic threshold and validate our theoretical findings through comparative simulations on Watts--Strogatz and Barab\'asi--Albert networks. The experimental results reveal a nonlinear relationship between mobility probability and the epidemic threshold, indicating that further increases can inhibit disease transmission beyond a certain critical mobility level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14016v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusheng Li, Yichao Yao, Minyu Feng, Tina P. Benko, Matja\v{z} Perc, Jernej Zavr\v{s}nik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Knowledge Networks: Rethinking Technological Value Distribution in mRNA Vaccine Innovations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines the roles of public and private sector actors in the development of mRNA vaccines, a breakthrough innovation in modern medicine. Using a dataset of 151 core patent families and 2,416 antecedent (cited) patents, we analyze the structure and dynamics of the mRNA vaccine knowledge network through network theory. Our findings highlight the central role of biotechnology firms, such as Moderna and BioNTech, alongside the crucial contributions of universities and public research organizations (PROs) in providing foundational knowledge.We develop a novel credit allocation framework, showing that universities, PROs, government and research centers account for at least 27% of the external technological knowledge base behind mRNA vaccine breakthroughs - representing a minimum threshold of their overall contribution. Our study offers new insights into pharmaceutical and biotechnology innovation dynamics, emphasizing how Moderna and BioNTech's mRNA technologies have benefited from academic institutions, with notable differences in their institutional knowledge sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14072v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rossana Mastrandrea, Fabio Montobbio, Gabriele Pellegrino, Massimo Riccaboni, Valerio Sterzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>States of Disarray: Cleaning Data for Gerrymandering Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The mathematics of redistricting is an area of study that has exploded in recent years. In particular, many different research groups and expert witnesses in court cases have used outlier analysis to argue that a proposed map is a gerrymander. This outlier analysis relies on having an ensemble of potential redistricting maps against which the proposed map is compared. Arguably the most widely-accepted method of creating such an ensemble is to use a Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) process. This process requires that various pieces of data be gathered, cleaned, and coalesced into a single file that can be used as the seed of the MCMC process.
  In this article, we describe how we have begun this cleaning process for each state, and made the resulting data available for the public at https://github.com/eveomett-states . At the time of submission, we have data for 22 states available for researchers, students, and the general public to easily access and analyze. We will continue the data cleaning process for each state, and we hope that the availability of these datasets will both further research in this area, and increase the public's interest in and understanding of modern techniques to detect gerrymandering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13521v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ananya Agarwal, Fnu Alusi, Arbie Hsu, Arif Syraj, Ellen Veomett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aging in coevolving voter models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03597v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aging, understood as the tendency to remain in a given state the longer the persistence time in that state, plays a crucial role in the dynamics of complex systems. In this paper, we explore the influence of aging on coevolution models, that is, models in which the dynamics of the states of the nodes in a complex network is coupled to the dynamics of the structure of the network. In particular we consider the coevolving voter model, and we introduce two versions of this model that include aging effects: the Link Aging Model (LAM) and the Node Aging Model (NAM). In the LAM, aging is associated with the persistence time of a link in the evolving network, while in the NAM, aging is associated with the persistence time of a node in a given state. We show that aging significantly affects the absorbing phase transition of the coevolution voter model, shifting the transition point in opposite directions for the LAM and NAM. We also show that the generic absorbing phase transition can disappear due to aging effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03597v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byungjoon Min, Maxi San Miguel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holding Periods: Measuring the Inverse of Money Velocity from Transaction Records</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.01512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.01512v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper defines the average holding period of money and proposes a methodology for fully disaggregated measurement. Our measure is shown to be the inverse of the transfer velocity of money under stationary conditions, which is implicitly assumed in conventional aggregate measurement. Our methodology does not require stationarity. We leverage a recent computational technique to extract empirical holding periods from micro-level transaction data as recorded by real-world payment systems. This enables novel empirical analyses of money velocity under non-stationarity conditions. We illustrate several such analyses on Sarafu, a small digital community currency in Kenya, where transaction data is available from 25 January 2020 to 15 June 2021. Our measure implies faster circulation than does the aggregate transfer velocity; we can say that 58% of Sarafu was effectively static. We also disaggregate by geography to study the heterogeneous impact of economic disruptions related to the COVID-19 pandemic on Sarafu. Finally, we consider an ad-hoc currency management operation that took place in October 2020. Measuring the average holding period of money makes it possible to track money velocity during ongoing monetary interventions and on other important occasions when conditions are not stationary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.01512v3</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina E. S. Mattsson, Allison Luedtke, Frank W. Takes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information and motor constraints shape melodic diversity across cultures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12635v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The number of possible melodies is unfathomably large, yet despite this virtually unlimited potential for melodic variation, melodies from different societies can be surprisingly similar. The motor constraint hypothesis accounts for certain similarities, such as scalar motion and contour shape, but not for other major common features, such as repetition, song length, and scale size. Here we investigate the role of information constraints arising from limitations on human memory in shaping these hallmarks of melodies. We measure determinants of information rate in 62 corpora of Folk melodies spanning several continents, finding multiple trade-offs that all act to constrain the information rate across societies. By contrast, 39 corpora of Art music from Europe (including Turkey) show longer, more complex melodies, and increased complexity over time, suggesting different cultural-evolutionary selection pressures in Art and Folk music, possibly due to the use of written versus oral transmission. Our parameter-free model predicts the empirical scale degree distribution using information constraints on scalar motion, melody length, and, most importantly, information rate. This provides strong evidence that information constraints during cultural transmission of music limit the number of notes in a scale, and proposes that preference for intermediate melodic complexity is a fundamental constraint on the cultural evolution of melody.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12635v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John M McBride, Nahie Kim, Yuri Nishikawa, Mekhmed Saadakeev, Marcus T Pearce, Tsvi Tlusty</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
