<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 04:03:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Most Western African migrants remain local and travel short distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Migration patterns are complex and context-dependent, with the distances migrants travel varying greatly depending on socio-economic and demographic factors. While global migration studies often focus on Western countries, there is a crucial gap in our understanding of migration dynamics within the African continent, particularly in West Africa. Using data from over 60,000 individuals from eight West African countries, this study examines the determinants of migration distance in the region. Our analysis reveals a bimodal distribution of migration distances: while most migrants travel locally within a hundred km, a smaller yet significant portion undertakes long-distance journeys, often exceeding 3,000 km. Socio-economic factors such as employment status, marital status and level of education play a decisive role in determining migration distances. Unemployed migrants, for instance, travel substantially farther (1,467 km on average) than their employed counterparts (295 km). Furthermore, we find that conflict-induced migration is particularly variable, with migrants fleeing violence often undertaking longer and riskier journeys. Our findings highlight the importance of considering both local and long-distance migration in policy decisions and support systems, as well as the need for a comprehensive understanding of migration in non-Western contexts. This study contributes to the broader discourse on human mobility by providing new insights into migration patterns in Western Africa, which in turn has implications for global migration research and policy development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10314v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irene Tafani, Ola Ali, Rafael Prieto-Curiel, Massimo Riccaboni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CosForce: A Force-Based General Pedestrian Model with Anticipation and Reaction Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10746v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a general force-based pedestrian model named CosForce, in which cosine functions are employed to describe asymmetric interactions. These functions implicitly capture the mechanisms of anticipation and reaction. By focusing on binary interactions, the CosForce model provides new insights into pedestrian modeling while achieving property of linear time complexity. Two specific scenarios in crowd dynamics were analyzed: self-organization (entropy decrease) and crowd collapse (entropy increase). The average normalized speed and order parameter were introduced to quantitatively describe the processes of crowd dynamics. Quantitative evaluations demonstrate that phase separation in crowds is effectively reproduced by the model, including lane formation, stripe formation, and cross-channel formation. Next, in the simulation of mass gathering, within a density-accumulating scenario, processes of critical transition in high-density crowds are clearly revealed through time series observations of the order parameter. These findings provide valuable insights into crowd dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10746v4</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinghui Wang, Wei Lv, Shuchao Cao, Chenglin Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Un)biased data and spin glasses reveal clustering for Turing phase transitions within human-transformer interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02879v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies a Large Language Model's ability to exhibit intelligence equivalent to that of a human by analyzing temperature-induced phase transitions, abrupt changes in the macroscopic behavior of a system, in the Turing test. We utilize three approaches: statistical analysis and bias quantification of a human evaluation survey, information retrieval from real human-written versus AI-generated text data using cosine similarity as a comparison metric, and mathematical spin glass model and simulation. We collect text data in the case study of Flitzing, a tradition of emailing poem-like romantic invitations at Dartmouth College because of its richness in information. Across the three approaches, we obtain consistency in phase transition and clustering results, which also align with literature on the mathematics of transformers and metastability. Our work inspires utilizing spin glass theory for the mathematical foundations of artificial intelligence, especially under environmental stochasticity from human interactions, with justification from real data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02879v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson George, Zachariah Yusaf, Stephanie Zoltick, Linh Huynh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synergistic Motifs in Gaussian Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-order interdependencies are central features of complex systems, yet a mechanistic explanation for their emergence remains elusive. Currently, it is unknown under what conditions high-order interdependencies, quantified by the information-theoretic construct of synergy, arise in systems governed by pairwise interactions. We solve this problem by providing precise sufficient and necessary conditions for when synergy prevails over low-order interdependencies, namely, we prove that antibalanced (highly frustrated) correlational structures in Gaussian systems are sufficient for synergy-dominance and that antibalanced interaction motifs in Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes are necessary for synergy-dominance. We validate the applicability of these analytical insights in Ising, oscillatory, and empirical networks from multiple domains. Our results demonstrate that pairwise interactions can give rise to synergistic information in the absence of explicit high-order mechanisms, and highlight structural balance theory as an instrumental conceptual framework to study high-order interdependencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24686v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Caprioglio, Pedro A. M. Mediano, Luc Berthouze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Compartment Model of Epidemic Spreading in Complex Networks with Mortality and Resetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06039v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an epidemic compartment model, which includes mortality caused by the disease, but excludes demographic birth and death processes. Individuals are represented by random walkers, which are in one of the following states (compartments) S (susceptible to infection), E (exposed: infected but not infectious corresponding to the latency period), I (infected and infectious), R (recovered, immune), D (dead). The disease is transmitted with a certain probability at contacts of I to S walkers. The compartmental sojourn times are independent random variables drawn from specific (here Gamma-) distributions. We implement this model into random walk simulations. Each walker performs an independent simple Markovian random walk on a graph, where we consider a Watts-Strogatz (WS) network. Only I walkers may die. For zero mortality, we prove the existence of an endemic equilibrium for basic reproduction number ${\cal R}_0 &gt; 1$ and for which the disease free (globally healthy) state is unstable. We explore the effects of long-range-journeys (stochastic resetting) and mortality. Our model allows for various interpretations, such as certain chemical reactions, the propagation of wildfires, and in population dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06039v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas M. Michelitsch, Bernard Collet, Michael Bestehorn, Alejandro P. Riascos, Andrzej F. Nowakowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
