<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 05:00:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AirCalypse: Can Twitter Help in Urban Air Quality Measurement and Who are the Influential Users?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this digital age, Online Social Media's ubiquity has led it to it's role as a "Sensor". Starting from disaster response to political predictions, online social media like Twitter, have been instrumental and are actively researched areas. In this work, we have focused on something quite insidious in the current context, i.e., air pollution in developing regions. Starting as an empirical study on using Twitter as a "Sensor" to measure air quality, the focal point of this work is to identify the users who have been actively tweeting in the air pollution events in Delhi, the capital of India. From these users, we try to identify the influential ones, who play a significant role in creating the initial awareness and hence act as "Sensors". We have utilized a tailored "TRank" algorithm for finding out the influential users by considering \textit{Retweet, Favorite, and Follower influence} of the users. After ranking the users based on their social influence, we further study the behavior, i.e., perception of pollution from those users' posts with respect to the actual air pollution levels using the physical sensors. The tracking of influential users in air quality monitoring assists in developing a crowd sensed air quality measurement framework, which can augment the physical air quality sensors for raising awareness against air pollution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19421v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3366424.3382120</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Prithviraj Pramanik, Tamal Mondal, Subrata Nandi, Mousumi Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Will the Technological Singularity Come Soon? Modeling the Dynamics of Artificial Intelligence Development via Multi-Logistic Growth Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We are currently in an era of escalating technological complexity and profound societal transformations, where artificial intelligence (AI) technologies exemplified by large language models (LLMs) have reignited discussions on the 'Technological Singularity'. 'Technological Singularity' is a philosophical concept referring to an irreversible and profound transformation that occurs when AI capabilities surpass those of humans comprehensively. However, quantitative modeling and analysis of the historical evolution and future trends of AI technologies remain scarce, failing to substantiate the singularity hypothesis adequately. This paper hypothesizes that the development of AI technologies could be characterized by the superposition of multiple logistic growth processes. To explore this hypothesis, we propose a multi-logistic growth process model and validate it using two real-world datasets: AI Historical Statistics and Arxiv AI Papers. Our analysis of the AI Historical Statistics dataset assesses the effectiveness of the multi-logistic model and evaluates the current and future trends in AI technology development. Additionally, cross-validation experiments on the Arxiv AI Paper, GPU Transistor and Internet User dataset enhance the robustness of our conclusions derived from the AI Historical Statistics dataset. The experimental results reveal that around 2024 marks the fastest point of the current AI wave, and the deep learning-based AI technologies are projected to decline around 2035-2040 if no fundamental technological innovation emerges. Consequently, the technological singularity appears unlikely to arrive in the foreseeable future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19425v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangyin Jin, Xiaohan Ni, Kun Wei, Jie Zhao, Haoming Zhang, Leiming Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Exploration into Chinese Characters: from Simplification to Deeper Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to Chinese characters through the lens of physics, network analysis, and natural systems. Computational analysis of over 6,000 characters identified 422 elemental characters as fundamental building blocks. Using a physics-inspired "Zi-Matrix" model, we analyzed character structure across eleven spatial positions, revealing systematic patterns in component relationships and semantic extension. Our research demonstrates that Chinese characters exhibit properties of natural systems: emergent complexity, self-organization, and adaptive resilience. The Fibonacci sequence provides an organizing framework for understanding character evolution, from simple pictographs to sophisticated abstractions. Case studies of character families and semantic networks show how meaning radiates from concrete to abstract domains while maintaining coherent principles. By viewing Chinese characters as a living system, this research transcends mere simplification to reveal how human cognition organizes and transmits knowledge. While the elemental character set reduces memorization burden, it also illuminates profound connections between language, thought, and natural patterns. Chinese characters emerge not just as tools for communication, but as windows into human understanding. This perspective, combined with AI-assisted learning approaches, promises to transform language education from knowledge mastery to meaning discovery, bridging traditional wisdom with modern computational methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19428v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen G. Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A systematic literature review on the application of analytical approaches and mathematical programming in public bus transit network design and operations planning: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Among all public transit modes, bus transit systems stand out as the most prevalent and popular. This prominence has spurred a significant body of research addressing various aspects of bus systems. In the literature, analytical approaches and mathematical programming are predominantly used to explore the Public Bus Transit Network Design Problem and Operations Planning (PBTNDP&amp;OP). Part I of our study presented statistical analyses of literature applying these methodologies to PBTNDP&amp;OP, along with a comprehensive review of analytical papers, highlighting the strengths and weaknesses of each approach. In Part II, we delve into the applications of mathematical programming within PBTNDP&amp;OP, building upon the 15 major sub-categories identified in Part I. We have critically analyzed the identified papers within these sub-categories from various perspectives, including the problems investigated, modeling methods employed, decision variables, network structures, and key findings. This critical review highlights selected papers in each category. Finally, acknowledging existing research gaps, we propose potential extensions for future research. Despite the extensive array of publications, numerous topics still warrant further exploration. Notably, sustainable PBTNDP&amp;OP and challenges associated with integrating emerging technologies are poised to dominate future research agendas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19430v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Mahmoudi, Saeid Saidi, S. Chan Wirasinghe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Actions for the American Astronomical Society: CSWA's Perspective on Steps for a more Inclusive Astronomy -- I. Background and Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a series of two papers, we provide a comprehensive agenda of actions the American Astronomical Society (AAS) can take to create a more diverse and inclusive professional system for astronomers, with a focus on women astronomers. This first paper of the series outlines the background and methods, while the recommendations are treated in the second companion paper (Paper II). We take the stance that since the 2020 Decadal Survey (Astro2020) was delivered in 2021, with its first-ever set of recommendations on the State of the Profession, now is the time for the AAS to take decisive action to transform astronomy into a diverse and inclusive profession. In the spring of 2019, the CSWA surveyed the astronomical community to assess the popularity and feasibility of actions that the AAS can take to reduce harassment and advance career development for women in astronomy. Here we present the quantitative results of that survey and a synopsis of the free response sections, which are publicly accessible. By combining the results of our survey, peer-reviewed academic literature, and findings from many of the white papers submitted to Astro2020, the CSWA has developed 26 specific actions that the AAS can take to help end harassment in astronomy, to advance career development for astronomers who are women and who are other members of historically marginalized groups, and intersections of these populations, and to improve the climate and culture of AAS and AAS-sponsored meetings. This paper presents the data we used to make these recommendations, and the recommendations themselves will be presented in Paper II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19432v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/25c2cfeb.cdff43a1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bulletin of the AAS, 57(1)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Wexler, Patricia Knezek, Gregory Rudnick, Nicolle Zellner, Kathleen Eckert, JoEllen McBride, Maria Patterson, Christina Richey, the Committee on the Status of Women in Astronomy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Actions for the American Astronomical Society: CSWA's Perspective on Steps for a more Inclusive Astronomy -- II. Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper, the second in a series of two, provides a set of recommendations that the American Astronomical Society (AAS) can take to create a more diverse and inclusive professional society for astronomers, with a focus on women astronomers. As noted in Paper I, now is the time for the AAS to take decisive action to transform astronomy into a diverse and inclusive profession. By combining the results of our 2019 survey, which is described in Paper I, peer-reviewed academic literature, and findings from many of the white papers submitted to Astro2020, the CSWA has developed 26 specific actions the AAS can take to help end harassment and bullying in astronomy; advance career development for astronomers who are women, members of other underrepresented groups, and intersections of these populations; and improve the climate and culture of AAS meetings. Actions to reduce rates of harassment and bullying include improvements to the AAS's anti-harassment policies and procedures and the development of astronomy-specific anti-harassment training resources. Actions to advance career development include creating a compensation database, improving how jobs are posted in the AAS Job Register, and supporting/enhancing a distance mentorship program. Finally, we call on the AAS to continue improving the accessibility of AAS meetings and to continue to support meeting sessions whose focus is to discuss issues of equity, diversity, and inclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19433v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/25c2cfeb.144eafda</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bulletin of the AAS, 57(1)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Wexler, Patricia Knezek, Gregory Rudnick, Nicolle Zellner, Kathleen Eckert, JoEllen McBride, Maria Patterson, Christina Richey, the Committee on the Status of Women in Astronomy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Study of the Provincial Road Networks of Canada as Complex Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19434v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we report on a study of the road networks of the provinces of Canada as complex networks. A number of statistical features have been analyzed and compared with two random models. In addition, we have also studied the resilience of these road networks under random failures and targeted attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19434v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srivatsan Vasudevan, Asish Mukhopadhyay, Sudarshan Sundararajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arrival flow profile estimation and predication for urban arterials using license plate recognition data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Arrival flow profiles enable precise assessment of urban arterial dynamics, aiding signal control optimization. License Plate Recognition (LPR) data, with its comprehensive coverage and event-based detection, is promising for reconstructing arrival flow profiles. This paper introduces an arrival flow profile estimation and prediction method for urban arterials using LPR data. Unlike conventional methods that assume traffic homogeneity and overlook detailed traffic wave features and signal timing impacts, our approach employs a time partition algorithm and platoon dispersion model to calculate arrival flow, considering traffic variations and driving behaviors using only boundary data. Shockwave theory quantifies the piecewise function between arrival flow and profile. We derive the relationship between arrival flow profiles and traffic dissipation at downstream intersections, enabling recursive calculations for all intersections. This approach allows prediction of arrival flow profiles under any signal timing schemes. Validation through simulation and empirical cases demonstrates promising performance and robustness under various conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19435v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Wu (the Hong Kong Polytechnic University), Jiarong Yao (Nanyang Technological University), Peize Kang (Tongji University), Chaopeng Tan (Delft University of Technology), Yang Cai (Shanghai Urban Construction Design and Research Institute), Junjie Zhou (Beijing Kuaishou Technology Co., Ltd), Edward Chung (the Hong Kong Polytechnic University), Keshuang Tang (Tongji University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling individual and collective temporal patterns in the tanker shipping network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The global shipping network, which moves over 80% of the world's goods, is not only a vital backbone of the global economy but also one of the most polluting industries. Studying how this network operates is crucial for improving its efficiency and sustainability. While the transport of solid goods like packaged products and raw materials has been extensively researched, far less is known about the competitive trade of crude oil and petroleum, despite these commodities accounting for nearly 30% of the market. Using 4 years of high-resolution data on oil tanker movements, we employ sequential motif mining and dynamic mode decomposition to uncover global spatio-temporal patterns in the movement of individual ships. Across all ship classes, we demonstrate that maximizing the proportion of time ships spend carrying cargo -- a metric of efficiency -- is achieved through strategic diversification of routes and the effective use of intra-regional ports for trips without cargo. Moreover, we uncover a globally stable travel structure in the fleet, with pronounced seasonal variations linked to annual and semi-annual regional climate patterns and economic cycles. Our findings highlight the importance of integrating high-resolution data with innovative analysis methods not only to improve our understanding of the underlying dynamics of shipping patterns, but to design and evaluate strategies aimed at reducing their environmental impact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19957v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Teo, Naomi Arnold, Andrew Hone, Michael Coulon, Martin Ireland, Mauricio Santillana, Istv\'an Zolt\'an Kiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond costs: Mapping Norwegian youth preferences for a more inclusive energy transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Environmental movements and climate strikes have made it apparent that youth feel excluded from the ongoing energy transformation process, highlighting the crucial need for their engagement to achieve a socially accepted transition. This interdisciplinary study focuses on the Norwegian electricity system and involves conducting educational workshops with high school students aged 15 to 16 to ascertain their perspectives towards a net-zero energy system. The workshops were structured into three segments, starting with the dissemination of common knowledge about energy and climate, followed by interactive activities designed to explore and develop an understanding of various aspects of energy transition. Three rounds of questionnaires, administered at distinct time intervals, assessed changes in students' attitudes and socio-techno-economic preferences. Our findings show that 33\% of pupils favored exclusively offshore wind as a main energy source, while 35\% opted to combine it with solar energy, indicating that over 68\% viewed offshore wind as favorable. Although 32\% supported some form of land-based wind turbines, there was strong disagreement about wind parks in agricultural, forested, and residential areas. Preferences also exhibited considerable regional variation; solar installations were favored in southern and southeastern Norway, while wind farms were suggested for central and northern regions. Pupils emphasized energy independence, showed reluctance towards demand response, prioritized reducing emissions and preserving biodiversity over minimizing electricity costs. Despite cost-minimization being core to most energy system models, youth deemed it the least important factor, highlighting a disconnect between modeling priorities and their perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19974v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Shahzad Javed, Karin Fossheim, Paola Velasco-Herrej\'on, Nikolai Elias Koop, Matylda N. Guzik, Charles Dana Samuelson, Beate Seibt, Marianne Zeyringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Block-corrected Modularity for Community Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unknown node attributes in complex networks may introduce community structures that are important to distinguish from those driven by known attributes. We propose a block-corrected modularity that discounts given block structures present in the network to reveal communities masked by them. We show analytically how the proposed modularity finds the community structure driven by an unknown attribute in a simple network model. Further, we observe that the block-corrected modularity finds the underlying community structure on a number of simple synthetic network models while methods using different null models fail. We develop an efficient spectral method as well as two Louvain-inspired fine-tuning algorithms to maximize the proposed modularity and demonstrate their performance on several synthetic network models. Finally, we assess our methodology on various real-world citation networks built using the OpenAlex data by correcting for the temporal citation patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20083v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hasti Narimanzadeh, Takayuki Hiraoka, Mikko Kivel\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On measure problems in allometric analysis of cities -- How to correctly understand the law of allometric growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The law of allometric growth originated from biology has been widely used in urban research for a long time. Some conditional research conclusions based on biological phenomena have been erroneously transmitted in the field of urban geography, leading to some misunderstandings. One of the misunderstandings is that allometric analysis must be based on average measure. The aim of this paper is at explaining how to correctly understand the law of urban allometric growth by means of the methods of literature analysis and mathematical analysis. The results show the average measures cannot be applied to all types of allometric relationships, and the allometric relationships based on average measures cannot be derived from a general principle. Whether it is an empirical model or a theoretical model of allometric growth, its generation and derivation are independent of the average measures. Conclusions can be reached that the essence of allometric growth lies in that the ratio of two related general relative growth rates is a constant, and this constant represents the allometric scaling exponent and fractal dimension ratio. The average measures are helpful to estimate the allometric scaling exponent value which accords with certain theoretical expectations more effectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17251v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanguang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control of an Impulsive VS-EIAR Epidemic Model with Application to COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00864v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate a VS-EIAR epidemiological model that incorporates vaccinated individuals $\{V_i : i = 1, \ldots, n\}$, where $n \in \mathbb{N}^{*}$. The dynamics of the VS-EIAR model are governed by a system of ordinary differential equations describing the evolution of vaccinated, susceptible, exposed, infected, asymptomatic, and deceased population groups. Our primary objective is to minimize the number of susceptible, exposed, infected, and asymptomatic individuals by administering vaccination doses to susceptible individuals and providing treatment to the infected population. To achieve this, we employ optimal control theory to regulate the epidemic dynamics within an optimal terminal time $\tau^{*}$. Using Pontryagin's Maximum Principle (PMP), we establish the existence of an optimal control pair $(v^{*}(t), u^{*}(t))$. Additionally, we extend the model to an impulsive VS-EIAR framework, with particular emphasis on the impact of immigration and population movement. Finally, we present numerical simulations to validate the theoretical results and demonstrate their practical applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00864v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mamadou Abdoul Diop, Mohammed Elghandouri, Khalil Ezzinbi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repeated and incontrovertible collective action failure leads to protester disengagement and radicalisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Protest is ubiquitous in the 21st Century and the people who participate in such movements do so because they seek to bring about social change. However, social change takes time and involves repeated interactions between individual protesters, social movements and the authorities to whom they appeal for change. These complexities of time and scale have frustrated efforts to isolate the conditions that foster an enduring movement, on the one hand, and the adoption of more radical (unconventional, unacceptable) tactics on the other. Here, we present a novel, theoretically informed and empirically evidenced, agent-based model of collective action that provides a unified framework to address these dual challenges. We model ~10,000 iterations within a simulated society and show that where an authority is responsive, and protesters can (cognitively and/or socially) contest the failure of their movement, a moderate conventional movement prevails. Conversely, where an authority repeatedly and incontrovertibly fails the movement, the population disengages but becomes radicalised (latent radicalism). This latter finding, whereby the whole population is disengaged but prepared to use radical methods to bring about social change, likely reflects the febrile pre-cursor state to sudden, revolutionary change. Results highlight the potential for simulations to reveal emergent, as-yet under-theorized, phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12795v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma F. Thomas, Mengbin Ye, Simon D. Angus, Tony J. Mathew, Winnifred Louis, Liam Walsh, Silas Ellery, Morgana Lizzio-Wilson, Craig McGarty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy and type-token ratio in gigaword corpora</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10227v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There are different ways of measuring diversity in complex systems. In particular, in language, lexical diversity is characterized in terms of the type-token ratio and the word entropy. We here investigate both diversity metrics in six massive linguistic datasets in English, Spanish, and Turkish, consisting of books, news articles, and tweets. These gigaword corpora correspond to languages with distinct morphological features and differ in registers and genres, thus constituting a varied testbed for a quantitative approach to lexical diversity. We unveil an empirical functional relation between entropy and type-token ratio of texts of a given corpus and language, which is a consequence of the statistical laws observed in natural language. Further, in the limit of large text lengths we find an analytical expression for this relation relying on both Zipf and Heaps laws that agrees with our empirical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10227v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Rosillo-Rodes, Maxi San Miguel, David Sanchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2064 global population crisis scenario predicted by the most general dynamic model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19063v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There is currently no consensus on how the global population will evolve in the next decades and in the next century. The reason for this uncertainty is the absence of reliable population dynamic models. In this paper, we remedy to this situation by reporting on a population dynamic model, a single nonlinear differential equation adapted from the physics of disordered systems, which is able to mathematically describe all the various regimes encountered in the global population recorded as a function of time, over the past 12000 years until now. Regimes of simple exponential growth (Malthus), logistic (Verhulst) plateaus as well as stretched-exponential and compressed-exponential growth regimes are all reliably described by this mathematical equation in its various limits. Besides showing that this is, indeed, the most general population dynamic model, we use it to explore its solutions projected into the future. In particular, two different scenarios are predicted. In one of them, which assumes that the future evolution would continue along a similar pattern as the past decades (hence without any major global ecological crisis affecting the resource exploitation), a von Foerster-type doomsday scenario with a sudden rise of the global population to unsustainable levels could appear as early as 2078. In the opposite scenario, if a global ecological crisis were to set in today, affecting the ability to exploit resources, given the current estimates of the Earth's carrying capacity, the global population is forecasted to reduce by half by 2064. Furthermore, the proposed dynamic model provides with a new aggregated parameter (K, in the model) that can be monitored and controlled so as to avoid the doomsday scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19063v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Zaccone, Kostya Trachenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
