<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.soc-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph</link>
    <description>physics.soc-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.soc-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 16:23:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling financial transactions via random walks on temporal networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.20713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.20713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We model financial transactions as random walks on activity-driven temporal networks. By enforcing fund conservation, our framework analytically derives heavy-tailed distributions for the stationary balances and transaction sizes. Crucially, the latter is driven by variance in the spending propensity of individuals. Calibrated with empirical data from a closed, digital currency community, the model also reproduces observed correlations between inflows and outflows. Our findings provide a path for understanding emergent properties of the circulation of money.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.20713v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina E. Mattsson, Claudio Cellerini, Jaume Ojer, Michele Starnini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between ideology and language in the Catalan independence context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.20821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.20821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Political polarization generates strong effects on society, driving controversial debates and influencing the institutions. Territorial disputes are one of the most important polarized scenarios and have been consistently related to the use of language. In this work, we analyzed the opinion and language distributions through Twitter data of a particular territorial dispute around the independence of Catalonia. We infer a continuous opinion distribution by applying a model based on retweet interactions, previously detecting elite users with fixed and antagonist opinions. The resulting distribution presents a mainly bimodal behavior with an intermediate third pole that shows a less polarized society with the presence of not only antagonist opinions. We find that the more active, engaged and influential users hold more extreme positions. Also we prove that there is a clear relationship between political positions and the use of language, showing that against independence users speak mainly Spanish while pro-independence users speak Catalan and Spanish almost indistinctly. However, the third pole, closer in political opinion to the pro-independence pole, behaves similarly to the against-independence one concerning the use of language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.20821v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-019-53404-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci Rep 9, 17148 (2019)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julia Atienza-Barthelemy, Samuel Martin-Gutierrez, Juan C. Losada, Rosa M. Benito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrent patterns of user behavior in different electoral campaigns: A Twitter analysis of the Spanish general elections of 2015 and 2016</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.20837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.20837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have retrieved and analyzed several millions of Twitter messages corresponding to the Spanish General elections held on the 20th of December 2015 and repeated on the 26th of June 2016. The availability of data from two electoral campaigns that are very close in time allows us to compare collective behaviors of two analogous social systems with a similar context. By computing and analyzing the time series of daily activity, we have found a significant linear correlation between both elections. Additionally, we have revealed that the daily number of tweets, retweets and mentions follow a power law with respect to the number of unique users that take part in the conversation. Furthermore, we have verified that the topologies of the networks of mentions and retweets do not change from one election to the other, indicating that their underlying dynamics are robust in the face of a change in social context. Hence, in the light of our results, there are several recurrent collective behavioral patterns that exhibit similar and consistent properties in different electoral campaigns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.20837v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1155/2018/2413481</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Complexity, 2018, 2413481</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Martin-Gutierrez, Juan C. Losada, Rosa M. Benito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of individual actions on the collective response of social systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.20897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.20897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a social system individual actions have the potential to trigger spontaneous collective reactions. The way and extent to which the activity (number of actions$-A$) of an individual causes or is connected to the response (number of reactions$-R$) of the system is still an open question. We measure the relationship between activity and response with the distribution of efficiency, a metric defined as $\eta=R/A$. Generalizing previous results, we show that the efficiency distribution presents a universal structure in three systems of different nature: Twitter, Wikipedia and the scientific citations network. To understand this phenomenon, we develop a theoretical framework composed of three minimal statistical models that contemplate different levels of dependence between $A$ and $R$. The models not only are able to reproduce the empirical activity-response data but also can serve as baselines or null models for more elaborated and domain-specific approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.20897v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-020-69005-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci Rep 10, 12126 (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Martin-Gutierrez, Juan C. Losada, Rosa M. Benito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empathy Modeling in Active Inference Agents for Perspective-Taking and Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.20936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.20936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial agents capable of understanding and aligning with others' intentions are essential for safe and socially robust artificial intelligence. We introduce a computational framework for empathy in active inference agents, grounded in explicit perspective-taking via self-other model transformation.
  We instantiate this framework in a multi-agent Iterated Prisoner's Dilemma and show that empathic perspective-taking induces robust cooperation without explicit communication or reward shaping. Cooperation emerges only when empathy is reciprocated, while asymmetric empathy leads to systematic exploitation. Beyond equilibrium outcomes, empathic agents exhibit synchronized behavior, rapid recovery from stochastic defections, and joint intentional dynamics resembling apology-forgiveness cycles. Near empathy symmetry, interactions display long transients and elevated variance, consistent with critical dynamics near regime boundaries.
  We further examine a learning-enabled variant in which agents infer opponent type via Bayesian updating. While opponent models converge rapidly, long-run cooperation remains primarily determined by the empathy parameter, indicating that cooperation is driven by empathic structure rather than learned reciprocity. Empathy functions as a structural prior over social interaction, shaping coordination stability, robustness, and temporal dynamics. The proposed framework highlights active inference as a principled foundation for socially aligned artificial agents that coordinate through internal simulation rather than behavioral mimicry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.20936v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albarracin Mahault, Mikeda Anna, Jimenez Rodriguez Alejandro, Namjoshi Sanjeev, Sakthivadivel Dalton, Pae Hongju, Shah Harshil, Wilson Philip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the non-uniformity of the 2026 FIFA World Cup draw</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The group stage of a sports tournament is often made more appealing by introducing additional constraints in the group draw that promote an attractive and balanced group composition. For example, the number of intra-regional group matches is minimised in several World Cups. However, under such constraints, the traditional draw procedure may become non-uniform, meaning that the feasible allocations of the teams into groups are not equally likely to occur. Our paper quantifies this non-uniformity of the 2026 FIFA World Cup draw for the official draw procedure, as well as for 47 reasonable alternatives implied by all permutations of the four pots and two group labelling policies. We show why simulating with a recursive backtracking algorithm is intractable, and propose a workable implementation using integer programming. The official draw mechanism is found to be optimal based on four measures of non-uniformity. Nonetheless, non-uniformity can be more than halved if the organiser aims to treat the best teams drawn from the first pot equally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21029v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'aszl\'o Csat\'o, Martin Becker, Karel Devriesere, Dries Goossens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Verification of (Mis)Information in Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.01830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.01830v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the diffusion of a true and a false message (misinformation) when agents are biased and able to verify messages. As a recipient of a false message who verifies it becomes informed of the truth, a higher prevalence of misinformation can increase the prevalence of the truth. We uncover conditions such that this happens and discuss policy implications. Specifically, a planner aiming to maximize the prevalence of the truth should allow misinformation to circulate if: non-verified messages may be ignored, transmission of information is relatively low, and the planner's budget to induce verification is neither too low nor too high. Homophily increases the spread of misinformation, but also facilitates diffusion of truth, and leads to similar results on the effect of verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.01830v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Paolo Merlino, Nicole Tabasso</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
