<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Grid Evolution for Doubly Fractional Channel Estimation in OTFS Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In orthogonal time-frequency space communications, the performances of existing on-grid and off-grid channel estimation (CE) schemes are determined by the delay-Doppler (DD) grid density. In practice, multiple real-life DD channel responses might be co-located within a same DD grid interval, leading to performance degradation. A finer grid interval is needed to distinguish these responses, but this could result in a significantly higher CE complexity when traditional methods are used.To address this issue, a grid evolution method for doubly fractional CE is proposed by evolving the initially uniform coarse DD grid into a non-uniform dense grid. Simulation results show that our proposed method leads to improved computational efficiency, and achieves a good trade-off between CE performance and complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17584v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangjun Li, Pingzhi Fan, Qianli Wang, Zilong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital and Hybrid Precoding Designs in Massive MIMO with Low-Resolution ADCs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-resolution analog-to-digital converters (ADCs) have emerged as an efficient solution for massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems to reap high data rates with reasonable power consumption and hardware complexity. In this paper, we study precoding designs for digital, fully connected (FC) hybrid, and partially connected (PC) hybrid beamforming architectures in massive MIMO systems with low-resolution ADCs at the receiver. We aim to maximize the spectral efficiency (SE) subject to a transmit power budget and hardware constraints on the analog components. The resulting problems are nonconvex and the quantization distortion introduces additional challenges. To address them, we first derive a tight lower bound for the SE, based on which we optimize the precoders for the three beamforming architectures under the majorization-minorization framework. Numerical results validate the superiority of the proposed precoding designs over their state-of-the-art counterparts in systems with low-resolution ADCs, particularly those with 1-bit resolution. The results show that the PC hybrid precoding design can achieve an SE close to those of the digital and FC hybrid precoding designs in 1-bit systems, highlighting the potential of the PC hybrid beamforming architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17638v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyuan Ma, Nhan Thanh Nguyen, Italo Atzeni, A. Lee Swindlehurst, Markku Juntti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-Based Machine Learning for Max-Min Fairness Beamforming Design in JCAS Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Joint communications and sensing (JCAS) is expected to be a crucial technology for future wireless systems. This paper investigates beamforming design for a multi-user multi-target JCAS system to ensure fairness and balance between communications and sensing performance. We jointly optimize the transmit and receive beamformers to maximize the weighted sum of the minimum communications rate and sensing mutual information. The formulated problem is highly challenging due to its non-smooth and non-convex nature. To overcome the challenges, we reformulate the problem into an equivalent but more tractable form. We first solve this problem by alternating optimization (AO) and then propose a machine learning algorithm based on the AO approach. Numerical results show that our algorithm scales effectively with the number of the communications users and provides better performance with shorter run time compared to conventional optimization approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17644v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyuan Ma, Tianyu Fang, Nir Shlezinger, A. L. Swindlehurst, Markku Juntti, Nhan Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fronthaul-Constrained Distributed Radar Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a network of distributed radar sensors that collaboratively perform sensing tasks by transmitting their quantized radar signals over capacity-constrained fronthaul links to a central unit for joint processing. We consider per-antenna and per-radar vector quantization and fronthaul links with dedicated resources as well as shared resources based on time-division multiple access. For this setting, we formulate a joint optimization problem for fronthaul compression and time allocation that minimizes the Cramer Rao bound of the aggregated radar signals at the central unit. Since the problem does not admit a standard form that can be solved by existing commercial numerical solvers, we propose refomulations that enable us to develop an efficient suboptimal algorithm based on semidefinite programming and alternating convex optimization. Moreover, we analyze the convergence and complexity of the proposed algorithm. Simulation results confirm that a significant performance gain can be achieved by distributed sensing, particularly in practical scenarios where one radar may not have a sufficient view of all the scene. Furthermore, the simulation results suggest that joint fronthaul compression and time allocation are crucial for efficient exploitation of the limited fronthaul capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17753v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Eckrich, Abdelhak M. Zoubir, Vahid Jamali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Impact of HAPS-RIS on UAV-based Networks: A Novel Architectural Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a network architecture where two types of aerial infrastructures together with a ground station provide connectivity to a remote area. A high altitude platform station (HAPS) is equipped with reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS), so-called HAPS-RIS, to be exploited to assist the unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV)-based wireless networks. A key challenge in such networks is the restricted number of UAVs, which limits full coverage and leaves some users unsupported. To tackle this issue, we propose a hierarchical bilevel optimization framework including a leader and a follower problem. The users served by HAPS-RIS are in a zone called HAPS-RIS zone and the users served by the UAVs are in another zone called UAV zone. In the leader problem, the goal is to establish the zone boundary that maximizes the number of users covered by HAPS-RIS while ensuring that users in this zone meet their rate requirements. This is achieved through an algorithm that integrates RIS clustering, subcarrier allocation, and zone determination. The follower problem focuses on minimizing the number of UAVs required, ensuring that the rate requirements of the users in the UAV zone are met. This is addressed using an algorithm that employs k-means clustering and subcarrier allocation. Our study reveals that increasing the number of RIS elements significantly decreases the number of required UAVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17817v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arman Azizi, Mustafa Kishk, Arman Farhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhantomLiDAR: Cross-modality Signal Injection Attacks against LiDAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) is a pivotal sensor for autonomous driving, offering precise 3D spatial information. Previous signal attacks against LiDAR systems mainly exploit laser signals. In this paper, we investigate the possibility of cross-modality signal injection attacks, i.e., injecting intentional electromagnetic interference (IEMI) to manipulate LiDAR output. Our insight is that the internal modules of a LiDAR, i.e., the laser receiving circuit, the monitoring sensors, and the beam-steering modules, even with strict electromagnetic compatibility (EMC) testing, can still couple with the IEMI attack signals and result in the malfunction of LiDAR systems. Based on the above attack surfaces, we propose the PhantomLiDAR attack, which manipulates LiDAR output in terms of Points Interference, Points Injection, Points Removal, and even LiDAR Power-Off. We evaluate and demonstrate the effectiveness of PhantomLiDAR with both simulated and real-world experiments on five COTS LiDAR systems. We also conduct feasibility experiments in real-world moving scenarios. We provide potential defense measures that can be implemented at both the sensor level and the vehicle system level to mitigate the risks associated with IEMI attacks. Video demonstrations can be viewed at https://sites.google.com/view/phantomlidar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17907v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.14722/ndss.2025.23997</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zizhi Jin, Qinhong Jiang, Xuancun Lu, Chen Yan, Xiaoyu Ji, Wenyuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LDA-MIG Detectors for Maritime Targets in Nonhomogeneous Sea Clutter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper deals with the problem of detecting maritime targets embedded in nonhomogeneous sea clutter, where limited number of secondary data is available due to the heterogeneity of sea clutter. A class of linear discriminant analysis (LDA)-based matrix information geometry (MIG) detectors is proposed in the supervised scenario. As customary, Hermitian positive-definite (HPD) matrices are used to model the observational sample data, and the clutter covariance matrix of received dataset is estimated as geometric mean of the secondary HPD matrices. Given a set of training HPD matrices with class labels, that are elements of a higher-dimensional HPD matrix manifold, the LDA manifold projection learns a mapping from the higher-dimensional HPD matrix manifold to a lower-dimensional one subject to maximum discrimination. In the current study, the LDA manifold projection, with the cost function maximizing between-class distance while minimizing within-class distance, is formulated as an optimization problem in the Stiefel manifold. Four robust LDA-MIG detectors corresponding to different geometric measures are proposed. Numerical results based on both simulated radar clutter with interferences and real IPIX radar data show the advantage of the proposed LDA-MIG detectors against their counterparts without using LDA as well as the state-of-art maritime target detection methods in nonhomogeneous sea clutter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17911v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TGRS.2023.3250990</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing 61, 5101815, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoqiang Hua, Linyu Peng, Weijian Liu, Yongqiang Cheng, Hongqiang Wang, Huafei Sun, Zhenghua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Roles can Spatial Modulation and Space Shift Keying Play in LEO Satellite-Assisted Communication?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, the rapid evolution of satellite communications play a pivotal role in addressing the ever-increasing demand for global connectivity, among which the Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellites attract a great amount of attention due to their low latency and high data throughput capabilities. Based on this, we explore spatial modulation (SM) and space shift keying (SSK) designs as pivotal techniques to enhance spectral efficiency (SE) and bit-error rate (BER) performance in the LEO satellite-assisted multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems. The various performance analysis of these designs are presented in this paper, revealing insightful findings and conclusions through analytical methods and Monte Carlo simulations with perfect and imperfect channel state information (CSI) estimation. The results provide a comprehensive analysis of the merits and trade-offs associated with the investigated schemes, particularly in terms of BER, computational complexity, and SE. This analysis underscores the potential of both schemes as viable candidates for future 6G LEO satellite-assisted wireless communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17553v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaorong Zhang, Qingying Wu, Yuyan Liu, Benjamin K. Ng, Chan-Tong Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oversampled Low Ambiguity Zone Sequences for Channel Estimation over Doubly Selective Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17707v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pilot sequence design over doubly selective channels (DSC) is challenging due to the variations in both the time- and frequency-domains. Against this background, the contribution of this paper is twofold: Firstly, we investigate the optimal sequence design criteria for efficient channel estimation in orthogonal frequency division multiplexing systems under DSC. Secondly, to design pilot sequences that can satisfy the derived criteria, we propose a new metric called oversampled ambiguity function (O-AF), which considers both fractional and integer Doppler frequency shifts. Optimizing the sidelobes of O-AF through a modified iterative twisted approximation (ITROX) algorithm, we develop a new class of pilot sequences called ``oversampled low ambiguity zone (O-LAZ) sequences". Through numerical experiments, we evaluate the efficiency of the proposed O-LAZ sequences over the traditional low ambiguity zone (LAZ) sequences, Zadoff-Chu (ZC) sequences and m-sequences, by comparing their channel estimation performances over DSC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17707v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Gu, Zhengchun Zhou, Pingzhi Fan, Avik Ranjan Adhikary, Zilong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confounder-adjusted Covariances of System Outputs and Applications to Structural Health Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Automated damage detection is an integral component of each structural health monitoring (SHM) system. Typically, measurements from various sensors are collected and reduced to damage-sensitive features, and diagnostic values are generated by statistically evaluating the features. Since changes in data do not only result from damage, it is necessary to determine the confounding factors (environmental or operational variables) and to remove their effects from the measurements or features. Many existing methods for correcting confounding effects are based on different types of mean regression. This neglects potential changes in higher-order statistical moments, but in particular, the output covariances are essential for generating reliable diagnostics for damage detection. This article presents an approach to explicitly quantify the changes in the covariance, using conditional covariance matrices based on a non-parametric, kernel-based estimator. The method is applied to the Munich Test Bridge and the KW51 Railway Bridge in Leuven, covering both raw sensor measurements (acceleration, strain, inclination) and extracted damage-sensitive features (natural frequencies). The results show that covariances between different vibration or inclination sensors can significantly change due to temperature changes, and the same is true for natural frequencies. To highlight the advantages, it is explained how conditional covariances can be combined with standard approaches for damage detection, such as the Mahalanobis distance and principal component analysis. As a result, more reliable diagnostic values can be generated with fewer false alarms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17735v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lizzie Neumann, Philipp Wittenberg, Alexander Mendler, Jan Gertheiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobility in Age-Based Gossip Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18094v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a gossiping network where a source forwards updates to a set of $n$ gossiping nodes that are placed in an arbitrary graph structure and gossip with their neighbors. In this paper, we analyze how mobility of nodes affects the freshness of nodes in the gossiping network. To model mobility, we let nodes randomly exchange positions with other nodes in the network. The position of the node determines how the node interacts with the rest of the network. In order to quantify information freshness, we use the version age of information metric. We use the stochastic hybrid system (SHS) framework to derive recursive equations to find the version age for a set of positions in the network in terms of the version ages of sets of positions that are one larger or of the same size. We use these recursive equations to find an upper bound for the average version age of a node in two example networks. We show that mobility can decrease the version age of nodes in a disconnected network from linear scaling in $n$ to at most square root scaling and even to constant scaling in some cases. We perform numerical simulations to analyze how mobility affects the version age of different positions in the network and also show that the upper bounds obtained for the example networks are tight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18094v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arunabh Srivastava, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switch-based Hybrid Beamforming Transceiver Design for Wideband Communications with Beam Squint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.06890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.06890v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hybrid beamforming (HBF) transceiver architectures based on frequency-independent phase shifters (PS-HBF) are sensitive to the phases and physical directions with limited capability to compensate for the detrimental effects of the beam squint. Motivated by the fact that switches are phase-independent and more power/cost efficient than PSs, we consider the switch-based HBF (SW-HBF) for wideband large-scale multiple-input multiple-output systems in this paper. We first derive a closed-form expression of the beam squint ratio and compare the expected array gains of both SW-HBF and PS-HBF architectures. The results show that SW-HBF is more robust to the beam squint effect. We then focus on the SW-HBF designs to maximize the spectral efficiency (SE) in both single-user and multiuser systems, which are both non-convex mixed-integer problems. For the former, by combining the tabu search (TS) method and projected gradient ascend (PGA), we propose an efficient heuristic PGA-TS algorithm to design analog beamformers while the digital ones admit closed-form solutions. For the latter, we develop a two-step algorithm based on fractional programming and the PGA-TS method. Simulations show that the proposed SW-HBF schemes are efficient and can outperform PS-based HBF architectures in terms of both SE and energy efficiency in terahertz communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.06890v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyuan Ma, Nhan Thanh Nguyen, Markku Juntti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rate-Splitting Multiple Access for Overloaded Multi-group Multicast: A First Experimental Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15217v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multi-group multicast (MGM) is an increasingly important form of multi-user wireless communications with several potential applications, such as video streaming, federated learning, safety-critical vehicular communications, etc. Rate-Splitting Multiple Access (RSMA) is a powerful interference management technique that can, in principle, achieve higher data rates and greater fairness for all types of multi-user wireless communications, including MGM. This paper presents the first-ever experimental evaluation of RSMA-based MGM, as well as the first-ever three-way comparison of RSMA-based, Space Divison Multiple Access (SDMA)-based and Non-Orthogonal Multiple Access (NOMA)-based MGM. Using a measurement setup involving a two-antenna transmitter and two groups of two single-antenna users per group, we consider the problem of realizing throughput (max-min) fairness across groups for each of three multiple access schemes, over nine experimental cases in a line-of-sight environment capturing varying levels of pathloss difference and channel correlation across the groups. Over these cases, we observe that RSMA-based MGM achieves fairness at a higher throughput for each group than SDMA- and NOMA-based MGM. These findings validate RSMA-based MGM's promised gains from the theoretical literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15217v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinze Lyu, Sundar Aditya, Bruno Clerckx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces for 6G Mobile Networks: An Industry R&amp;D Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19868v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS) technology is a potential solution to enhance network capacity and coverage without significant investment into additional infrastructure in 6G networks. This work highlights the interest of the mobile communication industry on RIS, and discusses the development of liquid crystal-based RIS for improved energy efficiency and coverage in the millimeter-wave band. Furthermore, the paper discusses perspectives and insights from an industry R&amp;D point of view, addressing relevant use cases, technical requirements, implementation challenges, and practical considerations for RIS deployment optimization in the context of 6G networks. A hardware design of a RIS with liquid crystal at 28 GHz is presented. A propagation model for RIS as a new part in the system architecture is discussed with the approaches of semi-empirical models, geometric models and its combination by the application of artificial intelligence / machine learning. Finally, a channel model for deployment optimization and dimensioning is presented with the findings that rather large RIS is in favor for coverage improvement as well as a greater attenuation at higher frequencies combined with a smaller RIS size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19868v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maik Sode (Ericsson Antenna Technology Germany GmbH, Rosenheim, Germany), Michael Ponschab (Ericsson Antenna Technology Germany GmbH, Rosenheim, Germany), Lucas N. Ribeiro (Ericsson Antenna Technology Germany GmbH, Rosenheim, Germany), Sven Haesloop (Fraunhofer Heinrich-Hertz-Institut, Berlin, Germany), Ehsan Tohidi (Fraunhofer Heinrich-Hertz-Institut, Berlin, Germany, Technische Universit\"at Berlin, Berlin, Germany), Michael Peter (Fraunhofer Heinrich-Hertz-Institut, Berlin, Germany), S{\l}awomir Sta\'nczak (Fraunhofer Heinrich-Hertz-Institut, Berlin, Germany, Technische Universit\"at Berlin, Berlin, Germany), Bilal H. Mohamed (Technische Universit\"at Berlin, Berlin, Germany), Wilhelm Keusgen (Technische Universit\"at Berlin, Berlin, Germany), Heinz Mellein (Rohde \&amp; Schwarz GmbH \&amp; Co. KG, Munich, Germany), Eslam Yassin (brown-iposs GmbH, Bonn, Germany), Bernd Schroeder (brown-iposs GmbH, Bonn, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uplink Wave-Domain Combiner for Stacked Intelligent Metasurfaces Accounting for Hardware Limitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21012v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Refractive metasurfaces (RMTSs) offer a promising solution to improve energy efficiency of wireless systems. To address the limitations of single-layer RMTS, stacked intelligent metasurfaces (SIMs), which form the desired precoder and combiner in the wave domain, have been proposed. However, previous analyses overlooked hardware non-idealities that significantly affect SIM performance. In this paper, we study the achievable sum-rate of SIM antennas in an uplink scenario, accounting for hardware constraints. We propose a system model that includes noise and hardware effects, formulate a non-convex sum-rate optimization problem, and solve it using gradient ascent and interior point methods. We compare SIMs and digital phased arrays (DPAs) under Rayleigh fading and 3GPP channels with two conditions: equal number of RF chains and equal physical aperture size. Our results show SIMs outperform DPAs under equal number of RF chains but underperform DPAs with equal aperture size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21012v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Rezvani, Raviraj Adve, Akram bin Sediq, Amr El-Keyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Transmitter and Receiver Design for Movable Antenna Enhanced Multicast Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11881v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Movable antenna (MA) is an emerging technology that utilizes localized antenna movement to achieve better channel conditions for enhancing communication performance. In this paper, we study the MA-enhanced multicast transmission from a base station equipped with multiple MAs to multiple groups of single-MA users. Our goal is to maximize the minimum weighted signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) among all the users by jointly optimizing the position of each transmit/receive MA and the transmit beamforming. To tackle this challenging problem, we first consider the single-group scenario and propose an efficient algorithm based on the techniques of alternating optimization and successive convex approximation. Particularly, when optimizing transmit or receive MA positions, we construct a concave lower bound for the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of each user using only the second-order Taylor expansion, which simplifies the problem-solving process compared to the existing two-step approximation method. The proposed design is then extended to the general multi-group scenario. Simulation results show that the proposed algorithm converges faster than the existing two-step approximation method, achieving a 3.4% enhancement in max-min SNR. Moreover, it can improve the max-min SNR/SINR by up to 22.5%, 181.7%, and 343.9% compared to benchmarks employing only receive MAs, only transmit MAs, and both transmit and receive FPAs, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11881v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TWC.2024.3463390</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ying Gao, Qingqing Wu, Wen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Modelling and Cancellation of External Passive Intermodulation in FDD MIMO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21135v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the physical approach to model external (air-induced) passive intermodulation (PIM) is presented in a frequency-division duplexing (FDD) multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) system with an arbitrary number of transceiver chains. The external PIM is a special case of intermodulation distortion (IMD), mainly generated by metallic objects possessing nonlinear properties ("rusty bolt" effect). Typically, such sources are located in the near-field or transition region of the antenna array. PIM products may fall into the receiver band of the FDD system, negatively affecting the uplink signal. In contrast to other works, this one directly simulates the physical external PIM. The system includes models of a point-source external PIM, a finite-length dipole antenna, a MIMO antenna array, and a baseband multicarrier 5G NR OFDM signal. The Channel coefficients method for multi-PIM-source compensation is replicated to verify the proposed external PIM modelling approach. Simulation results of artificially generated PIM cancellation show similar performance as real-life experiments. Therefore, the proposed approach allows testing PIM compensation algorithms on large systems with many antennas and arbitrary array structures. This eliminates the need for experiments with real hardware at the development stage of the PIM cancellation algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21135v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislav Krikunov, Viacheslav Zemlyakov, Andrey Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralised Variational Inference Frameworks for Multi-object Tracking on Sensor Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13689v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper tackles the challenge of multi-sensor multi-object tracking by proposing various decentralised Variational Inference (VI) schemes that match the tracking performance of centralised sensor fusion with only local message exchanges among neighboring sensors. We first establish a centralised VI sensor fusion scheme as a benchmark and analyse the limitations of its decentralised counterpart, which requires sensors to await consensus at each VI iteration. Therefore, we propose a decentralised gradient-based VI framework that optimises the Locally Maximised Evidence Lower Bound (LM-ELBO) instead of the standard ELBO, which reduces the parameter search space and enables faster convergence, making it particularly beneficial for decentralised tracking.This proposed framework is inherently self-evolving, improving with advancements in decentralised optimisation techniques for convergence guarantees and efficiency. Further, we enhance the convergence speed of proposed decentralised schemes using natural gradients and gradient tracking strategies. Results verify that our decentralised VI schemes are empirically equivalent to centralised fusion in tracking performance. Notably, the decentralised natural gradient VI method is the most communication-efficient, with communication costs comparable to suboptimal decentralised strategies while delivering notably higher tracking accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13689v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Li, Runze Gan, Simon Godsill</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
