<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 01:37:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Post-resonance reflections break the loss-vs-phase-resolution trade-off in microwave electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precise phase control of microwaves and millimeter waves is critical for today's wireless communication and signal processing electronics. For decades, achieving even modest phase-shifting resolution has demanded a complex mix of transistor switches and passive electromagnetic structures. These true-phase delay, true-time-delay or quasi-true-time-delay circuits operate near resonances that heavily attenuate and distort signals, limiting transmission bandwidth. Despite numerous attempts, passive phase shifters have remained lossy and incompatible with high-channel-capacity beamforming, irrespective of the semiconductor fabrication process. In this article, we introduce a mechanism whereby waveguide reflectors based on coupled resonances can be reprogrammed to evade loss. Central to their operation is that loss from internal resonances is confined to low frequencies, while at high frequencies, their reflectivity is maximized and broadband phase variations, induced by those resonances, still persist. Since performance in the low-loss post-resonance spectrum is largely agnostic to the number of switches, ultra-fine digital tuning is possible. This breaks the historical tradeoff between loss and precision to achieve resolution surpassing state-of-the-art integrated circuits by over three orders (bits) of magnitude. The device does not distort the transmitted signal and consumes no power. Moreover, the chip occupies a sub-wavelength footprint in a Complementary Metal Oxide Semiconductor platform. This makes it an optimal candidate for seamless integration in on-chip multi-gigabit data links, radio astronomy transceivers and control hardware for millimeter-wave qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16016v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bala Govind, Andreia Cathelin, Alyssa Apsel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Limits for Signals of Opportunity-Based Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the potential of non-terrestrial and terrestrial signals of opportunity (SOOP) for navigation applications. Non-terrestrial SOOP analysis employs modified Cram\`er-Rao lower bound (MCRLB) to establish a relationship between SOOP characteristics and the accuracy of ranging information. This approach evaluates hybrid navigation module performance without direct signal simulation. The MCRLB is computed for ranging accuracy, considering factors like propagation delay, frequency offset, phase offset, and angle-of-arrival (AOA), across diverse non-terrestrial SOOP candidates. Additionally, Geometric Dilution of Precision (GDOP) and low earth orbit (LEO) SOOP availability are assessed. Validation involves comparing MCRLB predictions with actual ranging measurements obtained in a realistic simulated scenario. Furthermore, a qualitative evaluation examines terrestrial SOOP, considering signal availability, accuracy attainability, and infrastructure demands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16426v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Zanirato, Francesco Ardizzon, Laura Crosara, Alessio Curzio, Luca Canzian, Stefano Tomasin, Nicola Laurenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Beam Symbol-Level Secure Communication for Hybrid Near- and Far-Field Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a multi-beam secure communication scheme for mixed near-field and far-field (hNF) scenarios, primarily designed to address the challenges faced by sixth-generation (6G) networks in simultaneously managing near-field and far-field communications. This method significantly reduces the signal quality at eavesdroppers(Eves) while ensuring high-quality reception for legitimate users, effectively enhancing communication security. At the transmitter, this study employs multi-beam symbol-level directional modulation to ensure secure and reliable transmission in a mixed eavesdropping environment. Given the uncertainty about eavesdropper information, the transmission beamforming vectors are specially designed to meet specific symbol-level constraints, thereby ensuring effective reception for legitimate users. Experimental and simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in improving secrecy performance, reducing transmission power, and enhancing energy efficiency, offering a practical solution to the security challenges faced by future wireless networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16438v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wensheng Deng, Bin Qiu, Wenchi Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of 3GPP and Ray-Tracing Based Channel Model for 5G Industrial Network Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Appropriate channel models tailored to the specific needs of industrial environments are crucial for the 5G private industrial network design and guiding deployment strategies. This paper scrutinizes the applicability of 3GPP's channel model for industrial scenarios. The challenges in accurately modeling industrial channels are addressed, and a refinement strategy is proposed employing a ray-tracing (RT) based channel model calibrated with continuous-wave received power measurements collected in a manufacturing facility in Sweden. The calibration helps the RT model achieve a root mean square error (RMSE) and standard deviation of less than 7 dB. The 3GPP and the calibrated RT model are statistically compared with the measurements, and the coverage maps of both models are also analyzed. The calibrated RT model is used to simulate the network deployment in the factory to satisfy the reference signal received power (RSRP) requirement. The deployment performance is compared with the prediction from the 3GPP model in terms of the RSRP coverage map and coverage rate. Evaluation of deployment performance provides crucial insights into the efficacy of various channel modeling techniques for optimizing 5G industrial network planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16528v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurjot Singh Bhatia, Yoann Corre, Linus Thrybom, M. Di Renzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Active and Passive Beamforming Design for IRS-aided MIMO ISAC Based on Sensing Mutual Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the intelligent reflecting surface (IRS)/reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS)-aided integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system based on sensing mutual information (MI). Specifically, the base station (BS) perceives the sensing target via the reflected sensing signal by the IRS, while communicating with the users simultaneously. Our aim is to maximize the sensing MI, subject to the quality of service (QoS) constraints for all communication users, the transmit power constraint at the BS, and the unit-modulus constraint on the IRS's passive reflection. We solve this problem under two cases: one simplified case assuming a line-of-sight (LoS) channel between the BS and IRS and no clutter interference to sensing, and the other generalized case considering the Rician fading channel of the BS-IRS link and the presence of clutter interference to sensing. For the first case, we show that the dedicated sensing beamformer cannot enhance the sensing MI if the BS-user direct links are blocked, and develop a low-complexity iterative algorithm to jointly optimize the BS and IRS active/passive beamformers. In contrast, for the second case, we propose an alternative iterative algorithm, which can also be applied to the first case, to solve the beamforming design problem under the general setup. Numerical results are provided to validate the performance of the proposed algorithms, as compared to various benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16543v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Li, Gui Zhou, Tantao Gong, Nan Liu, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer Disease Classification through ASR-based Transcriptions: Exploring the Impact of Punctuation and Pauses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Alzheimer's Disease (AD) is the world's leading neurodegenerative disease, which often results in communication difficulties. Analysing speech can serve as a diagnostic tool for identifying the condition. The recent ADReSS challenge provided a dataset for AD classification and highlighted the utility of manual transcriptions. In this study, we used the new state-of-the-art Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) model Whisper to obtain the transcriptions, which also include automatic punctuation. The classification models achieved test accuracy scores of 0.854 and 0.833 combining the pretrained FastText word embeddings and recurrent neural networks on manual and ASR transcripts respectively. Additionally, we explored the influence of including pause information and punctuation in the transcriptions. We found that punctuation only yielded minor improvements in some cases, whereas pause encoding aided AD classification for both manual and ASR transcriptions across all approaches investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03443v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21437/Interspeech.2023-1734</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. INTERSPEECH 2023, pp. 2403-2407, Dublin, Ireland, 20-24, August 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luc\'ia G\'omez-Zaragoz\'a, Simone Wills, Cristian Tejedor-Garcia, Javier Mar\'in-Morales, Mariano Alca\~niz, Helmer Strik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Assessment of Oral Reading Accuracy for Reading Diagnostics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03444v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Automatic assessment of reading fluency using automatic speech recognition (ASR) holds great potential for early detection of reading difficulties and subsequent timely intervention. Precise assessment tools are required, especially for languages other than English. In this study, we evaluate six state-of-the-art ASR-based systems for automatically assessing Dutch oral reading accuracy using Kaldi and Whisper. Results show our most successful system reached substantial agreement with human evaluations (MCC = .63). The same system reached the highest correlation between forced decoding confidence scores and word correctness (r = .45). This system's language model (LM) consisted of manual orthographic transcriptions and reading prompts of the test data, which shows that including reading errors in the LM improves assessment performance. We discuss the implications for developing automatic assessment systems and identify possible avenues of future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03444v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21437/Interspeech.2023-1681</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. INTERSPEECH 2023, pp. 5232-5236, Dublin, Ireland, 20-24, August 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bo Molenaar, Cristian Tejedor-Garcia, Helmer Strik, Catia Cucchiarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An ASR-Based Tutor for Learning to Read: How to Optimize Feedback to First Graders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.04190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.04190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interest in employing automatic speech recognition (ASR) in applications for reading practice has been growing in recent years. In a previous study, we presented an ASR-based Dutch reading tutor application that was developed to provide instantaneous feedback to first-graders learning to read. We saw that ASR has potential at this stage of the reading process, as the results suggested that pupils made progress in reading accuracy and fluency by using the software. In the current study, we used children's speech from an existing corpus (JASMIN) to develop two new ASR systems, and compared the results to those of the previous study. We analyze correct/incorrect classification of the ASR systems using human transcripts at word level, by means of evaluation measures such as Cohen's Kappa, Matthews Correlation Coefficient (MCC), precision, recall and F-measures. We observe improvements for the newly developed ASR systems regarding the agreement with human-based judgment and correct rejection (CR). The accuracy of the ASR systems varies for different reading tasks and word types. Our results suggest that, in the current configuration, it is difficult to classify isolated words. We discuss these results, possible ways to improve our systems and avenues for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.04190v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-030-87802-3_6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In: Karpov A., Potapova R. (eds) Speech and Computer. SPECOM 2021. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 12997. Springer, Cham</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu Bai, Cristian Tejedor-Garcia, Ferdy Hubers, Catia Cucchiarini, Helmer Strik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Speech Recognition of Non-Native Child Speech for Language Learning Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16710v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Voicebots have provided a new avenue for supporting the development of language skills, particularly within the context of second language learning. Voicebots, though, have largely been geared towards native adult speakers. We sought to assess the performance of two state-of-the-art ASR systems, Wav2Vec2.0 and Whisper AI, with a view to developing a voicebot that can support children acquiring a foreign language. We evaluated their performance on read and extemporaneous speech of native and non-native Dutch children. We also investigated the utility of using ASR technology to provide insight into the children's pronunciation and fluency. The results show that recent, pre-trained ASR transformer-based models achieve acceptable performance from which detailed feedback on phoneme pronunciation quality can be extracted, despite the challenging nature of child and non-native speech.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16710v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4230/OASIcs.SLATE.2023.7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>12th Symposium on Languages, Applications and Technologies (SLATE 2023) (p. 7:1-7:8)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Simone Wills, Yu Bai, Cristian Tejedor-Garcia, Catia Cucchiarini, Helmer Strik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading Miscue Detection in Primary School through Automatic Speech Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07060v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Automatic reading diagnosis systems can benefit both teachers for more efficient scoring of reading exercises and students for accessing reading exercises with feedback more easily. However, there are limited studies on Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) for child speech in languages other than English, and limited research on ASR-based reading diagnosis systems. This study investigates how efficiently state-of-the-art (SOTA) pretrained ASR models recognize Dutch native children speech and manage to detect reading miscues. We found that Hubert Large finetuned on Dutch speech achieves SOTA phoneme-level child speech recognition (PER at 23.1\%), while Whisper (Faster Whisper Large-v2) achieves SOTA word-level performance (WER at 9.8\%). Our findings suggest that Wav2Vec2 Large and Whisper are the two best ASR models for reading miscue detection. Specifically, Wav2Vec2 Large shows the highest recall at 0.83, whereas Whisper exhibits the highest precision at 0.52 and an F1 score of 0.52.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07060v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingyun Gao, Cristian Tejedor-Garcia, Helmer Strik, Catia Cucchiarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An RF-Domain Leakage Cancellation Scheme for FMCW Radars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15969v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel solution to address the leakage from the transmitter (TX) to the receiver (RX) in frequency-modulated continuous-wave (FMCW) radars. The proposed scheme replicates the leakage using an in-phase and quadrature mixer (IQ-mixer) and performs leakage cancellation in the radio-frequency (RF) domain. This approach utilizes a Wilkinson power combiner after the RX antenna to subtract the replicated leakage signal from the received signal, ensuring that only the true target signal reaches the low-noise amplifier (LNA). This scheme enhances the dynamic range and the receiver's ability to discern proximate targets from previously indistinguishable low beat-frequency clutter. In addition, the proposed technique incorporates a second IQ-mixer based complex modulator in the transmitter to tune the leakage beat frequency. This allows for accurate estimation of the leakage amplitude and phase without additional hardware. Simulation results show more than 20 dB of leakage cancellation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15969v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yikuan Chen, Ali Niknejad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transformer-based Capacity Prediction for Lithium-ion Batteries with Data Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lithium-ion batteries are pivotal to technological advancements in transportation, electronics, and clean energy storage. The optimal operation and safety of these batteries require proper and reliable estimation of battery capacities to monitor the state of health. Current methods for estimating the capacities fail to adequately account for long-term temporal dependencies of key variables (e.g., voltage, current, and temperature) associated with battery aging and degradation. In this study, we explore the usage of transformer networks to enhance the estimation of battery capacity. We develop a transformer-based battery capacity prediction model that accounts for both long-term and short-term patterns in battery data. Further, to tackle the data scarcity issue, data augmentation is used to increase the data size, which helps to improve the performance of the model. Our proposed method is validated with benchmark datasets. Simulation results show the effectiveness of data augmentation and the transformer network in improving the accuracy and robustness of battery capacity prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16036v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gift Modekwe, Saif Al-Wahaibi, Qiugang Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Signal Processing for Extremely Large-Scale Antenna Array Systems: State-of-the-Art and Future Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16121v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extremely large-scale antenna arrays (ELAA) play a critical role in enabling the functionalities of next generation wireless communication systems. However, as the number of antennas increases, ELAA systems face significant bottlenecks, such as excessive interconnection costs and high computational complexity. Efficient distributed signal processing (SP) algorithms show great promise in overcoming these challenges. In this paper, we provide a comprehensive overview of distributed SP algorithms for ELAA systems, tailored to address these bottlenecks. We start by presenting three representative forms of ELAA systems: single-base station ELAA systems, coordinated distributed antenna systems, and ELAA systems integrated with emerging technologies. For each form, we review the associated distributed SP algorithms in the literature. Additionally, we outline several important future research directions that are essential for improving the performance and practicality of ELAA systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16121v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanqing Xu, Erik G. Larsson, Eduard A. Jorswieck, Xiao Li, Shi Jin, Tsung-Hui Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DOLOS: Tricking the Wi-Fi APs with Incorrect User Locations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16138v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wi-Fi-based indoor localization has been extensively studied for context-aware services. As a result, the accurate Wi-Fi-based indoor localization introduces a great location privacy threat. However, the existing solutions for location privacy protection are hard to implement on current devices. They require extra hardware deployment in the environment or hardware modifications at the transmitter or receiver side. To this end, we propose DOLOS, a system that can protect the location privacy of the Wi-Fi user with a novel signal obfuscation approach. DOLOSis a software-only solution that can be deployed on existing protocol-compliant Wi-Fi user devices. We provide this obfuscation by invalidating a simple assumption made by most localization systems -- "direct path signal arrives earlier than all the reflections to distinguish this direct path prior to estimating the location". However, DOLOS creates a novel software fix that allows the user to transmit the signal wherein this direct path arrives later, creating ambiguity in the location estimates. Our experimental results demonstrate DOLOS can degrade the localization accuracy of state-of-art systems by 6x for a single AP and 2.5x for multiple AP scenarios, thereby protecting the Wi-Fi user's location privacy without compromising the Wi-Fi communication performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16138v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Arun, Vaibhav Anand, Wei Sun, Roshan Ayyalasomayajula, Dinesh Bharadia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIC-based Random Multiple Access Protocol: Fixed or Adaptive Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficient data collection from a multitude of Internet of Things (IoT) devices is crucial for various applications, yet existing solutions often struggle with minimizing access delay and Age of Information (AoI), especially when managing multiple simultaneous transmissions and access strategies. This challenge becomes increasingly critical as IoT deployments continue to expand, demanding robust mechanisms for handling diverse traffic scenarios. In this study, we propose a novel approach leveraging Successive Interference Cancellation (SIC) based on adaptive and fixed parameter schemes to address these limitations. By analyzing both throughput and AoI along with access delay, we demonstrate the effectiveness of our adaptive approach compared to the fixed approach, particularly in scenarios featuring heavy and light traffic. Our findings highlight the pivotal role of adaptive approaches in optimizing data collection processes in IoT ecosystems, with a particular focus on minimizing access delay, AoI, and spectral efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16378v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. B. Abdul Razzaque, A. Baiocchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Analysis of Fronthaul Compression in Massive MIMO Receiver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Future generations of cellular systems presume to use an extremely high number of antennas to enable mm waves. Increasing the number of antennas requires a growth in connections between a remote radio head (RRH) and a baseband unit (BBU). Therefore, the traffic load between RRH and BBU has to grow, and the compression of interconnection between them becomes a serious problem. In this paper, we propose a compression scheme to reduce the bitrate of the fronthaul interface that connects BBU and RRU. Then we justify compression block size and mantissa length to guarantee the required error vector magnitude (EVM). The knowledge of propagation channel sparsity and the condition number of the channel matrix helps to achieve higher compression ratios without performance loss. Simulation results with a realistic propagation channel are provided to confirm theoretical derivations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16478v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Bychkov, Andrey Dergachev, Alexander Osinsky, Dmitry Lakontsev, Andrey Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Resource-Power Allocation and UE Rank Selection in Multi-User MIMO Systems with Linear Transceivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16483v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Next-generation wireless networks aim to deliver data speeds much faster than 5G. This requires base stations with lots of antennas and a large operating bandwidth. These advanced base stations are expected to serve several multi-antenna user-equipment (UEs) simultaneously on the same time-frequency resources on both the uplink and the downlink. The UE data rates are affected by the following three main factors: UE rank, which refers to the number of data layers used by each UE, UE frequency allocation, which refers to the assignment of slices of the overall frequency band to use for each UE in an orthogonal frequency-division multiplexing (OFDM) system, and UE power allocation/control, which refers to the power allocated by the base station for data transmission to each UE on the downlink or the power used by the UE to send data on the uplink. Since multiple UEs are to be simultaneously served, the type of precoder used for downlink transmission and the type of receiver used for uplink reception predominantly influence these three aforementioned factors and the resulting overall UE throughput. This paper addresses the problem of jointly selecting these three parameters specifically when zero-forcing (ZF) precoders are used for downlink transmission and linear minimum mean square error (LMMSE) receivers are employed for uplink reception.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16483v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Pavan Srinath, Alix Jeannerot, Alvaro Valcarce Rial</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DC is all you need: describing ReLU from a signal processing standpoint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-linear activation functions are crucial in Convolutional Neural Networks. However, until now they have not been well described in the frequency domain. In this work, we study the spectral behavior of ReLU, a popular activation function. We use the ReLU's Taylor expansion to derive its frequency domain behavior. We demonstrate that ReLU introduces higher frequency oscillations in the signal and a constant DC component. Furthermore, we investigate the importance of this DC component, where we demonstrate that it helps the model extract meaningful features related to the input frequency content. We accompany our theoretical derivations with experiments and real-world examples. First, we numerically validate our frequency response model. Then we observe ReLU's spectral behavior on two example models and a real-world one. Finally, we experimentally investigate the role of the DC component introduced by ReLU in the CNN's representations. Our results indicate that the DC helps to converge to a weight configuration that is close to the initial random weights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christodoulos Kechris, Jonathan Dan, Jose Miranda, David Atienza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Particle and Ensemble Kalman Filters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16623v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In cognitive systems, recent emphasis has been placed on studying cognitive processes of the subject whose behavior was the primary focus of the system's cognitive response. This approach, known as inverse cognition, arises in counter-adversarial applications and has motivated the development of inverse Bayesian filters. In this context, a cognitive adversary, such as a radar, uses a forward Bayesian filter to track its target of interest. An inverse filter is then employed to infer adversary's estimate of target's or defender's state. Previous studies have addressed this inverse filtering problem by introducing methods like inverse Kalman filter (I-KF), inverse extended KF (I-EKF), and inverse unscented KF (I-UKF). However, these inverse filters assume additive Gaussian noises and/or rely on local approximations of non-linear dynamics at the state estimates, limiting their practical application. Contrarily, this paper adopts a global filtering approach and develops an inverse particle filter (I-PF). The particle filter framework employs Monte Carlo (MC) methods to approximate arbitrary posterior distributions. Moreover, under mild system-level conditions, the proposed I-PF demonstrates convergence to the optimal inverse filter. Additionally, we explore MC techniques to approximate Gaussian posteriors and introduce inverse Gaussian PF (I-GPF) and inverse ensemble KF (I-EnKF). Our I-GPF and I-EnKF can efficiently handle non-Gaussian noises with suitable modifications. Additionally, we propose the differentiable I-PF, differentiable I-EnKF, and reproducing kernel Hilbert space-based EnKF (RKHS-EnKF) methods to address scenarios where system information is unknown to defender. Using recursive Cram\'er-Rao lower bound and non-credibility index (NCI), our numerical experiments for different applications demonstrate the estimation performance and time complexity of the proposed filters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16623v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himali Singh, Arpan Chattopadhyay, Kumar Vijay Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Multicarrier Multiantenna Systems for LoS Channel Charting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Channel charting (CC) consists in learning a mapping between the space of raw channel observations, made available from pilot-based channel estimation in multicarrier multiantenna system, and a low-dimensional space where close points correspond to channels of user equipments (UEs) close spatially. Among the different methods of learning this mapping, some rely on a distance measure between channel vectors. Such a distance should reliably reflect the local spatial neighborhoods of the UEs. The recently proposed phase-insensitive (PI) distance exhibits good properties in this regards, but suffers from ambiguities due to both its periodic and oscillatory aspects, making users far away from each other appear closer in some cases. In this paper, a thorough theoretical analysis of the said distance and its limitations is provided, giving insights on how they can be mitigated. Guidelines for designing systems capable of learning quality charts are consequently derived. Experimental validation is then conducted on synthetic and realistic data in different scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03762v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taha Yassine (IRT b-com, Hypermedia), Luc Le Magoarou (INSA Rennes, IETR), Matthieu Crussi\`ere (IETR), Stephane Paquelet (IRT b-com)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Spatial Block-Correlation Model for Fluid Antenna Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04513v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Powered by position-flexible antennas, the emerging fluid antenna system (FAS) technology is postulated as a key enabler for massive connectivity in 6G networks. The free movement of antenna elements enables the opportunistic minimization of interference, allowing several users to share the same radio channel without the need of precoding. However, the true potential of FAS is still unknown due to the extremely high spatial correlation of the wireless channel between very close-by antenna positions. To unveil the multiplexing capabilities of FAS, proper (simple yet accurate) modeling of the spatial correlation is prominently needed. Realistic classical models such as Jakes's are prohibitively complex, rendering intractable analyses, while state-of-the-art approximations often are too simplistic and poorly accurate. Aiming to fill this gap, we here propose a general framework to approximate spatial correlation by block-diagonal matrices, motivated by the well-known block fading assumption and by statistical results on large correlation matrices. The proposed block-correlation model makes the performance analysis possible, and tightly approximates the results obtained with realistic models (Jakes's and Clarke's). Our framework is leveraged to analyze fluid antenna multiple access (FAMA) systems, evaluating their performance for both one- and two-dimensional fluid antennas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04513v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Ramirez-Espinosa, David Morales-Jimenez, Kai-Kit Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small-Noise Sensitivity Analysis of Locating Pulses in the Presence of Adversarial Perturbation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03294v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A fundamental small-noise sensitivity analysis of spike localization in the presence of adversarial perturbations and an arbitrary point spread function (PSF) is presented. The analysis leverages the local Lipschitz property of the inverse map from measurement noise to parameter estimate. In the small noise regime, the local Lipschitz constant converges to the spectral norm of the noiseless Jacobian of the inverse map. An interpretable upper bound in terms of the minimum separation of spikes, norms, and flatness of the PSF and its derivative, as well as the distribution of spike amplitudes is provided. Numerical experiments highlighting the relevance of the theoretical bound as a proxy to the local Lipschitz constant and its dependence on the key attributes of the problem are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03294v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meghna Kalra, Maxime Ferreira Da Costa, Kiryung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Bounds for Near-Field Multi-Antenna Range Estimation of Extended Targets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06949v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, performance bounds for the multi-antenna near-field range estimation of extended targets are provided. First, analytic expressions of the ambiguity functions are obtained, emphasising the cooperation between the waveform delay and the near-field phase shift information. The impact of estimating the range of an extended target with a point target model is analysed, showing that a model mismatch leads to severe performance degradation in the near-field region. Secondly, Cramer-Rao bounds are derived. Expressions emphasising the parameters' impact are obtained, the parameters being the carrier frequency, and the central frequency and root-mean-square bandwidth of the waveform. The near-field range information is shown to depend on the root-mean-square value of the propagation delay derivatives, this value scaling with the fourth power of the ratio between the antenna array dimension and the target range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06949v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Thiran, Fran\c{c}ois De Saint Moulin, Claude Oestges, Luc Vandendorpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRANK: a singular value based noise filtering of multiple response datasets for experimental dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07578v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High quality measurements are paramount to a successful application of experimental techniques in structural dynamics. The presence of noise and disturbances can significantly distort the information stored in the data and, if not adequately treated, may result in erroneous findings and misleading predictions. A common technique to filter out noise relies on decomposing the dataset into singular components sorted by their degree of significance. Discarding low-value contributions helps to clean the data and remove spuriousness. This paper presents PRANK, a novel singular value-based reconstruction approach for multiple response vibration datasets. PRANK integrates the effect of Principal Response Functions and Hankel filtering actions, resulting in an improved data reconstruction for both system poles and zeros. The proposed formulation is tested on both analytical and numerical examples, showcasing its robustness, efficiency and versatility. PRANK operates with both time- and frequency-based data. Applied to noisy full-field camera measurements, the filter delivered excellent performance, indicating its potential for various identification tasks and applications in vibration analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07578v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Trainotti, Steven W. B. Klaassen, Tomaz Bregar, Daniel J. Rixen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Explainable AI for EEG-based Reduced Montage Neonatal Seizure Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16908v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The neonatal period is the most vulnerable time for the development of seizures. Seizures in the immature brain lead to detrimental consequences, therefore require early diagnosis. The gold-standard for neonatal seizure detection currently relies on continuous video-EEG monitoring; which involves recording multi-channel electroencephalogram (EEG) alongside real-time video monitoring within a neonatal intensive care unit (NICU). However, video-EEG monitoring technology requires clinical expertise and is often limited to technologically advanced and resourceful settings. Cost-effective new techniques could help the medical fraternity make an accurate diagnosis and advocate treatment without delay. In this work, a novel explainable deep learning model to automate the neonatal seizure detection process with a reduced EEG montage is proposed, which employs convolutional nets, graph attention layers, and fully connected layers. Beyond its ability to detect seizures in real-time with a reduced montage, this model offers the unique advantage of real-time interpretability. By evaluating the performance on the Zenodo dataset with 10-fold cross-validation, the presented model achieves an absolute improvement of 8.31% and 42.86% in area under curve (AUC) and recall, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16908v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dinuka Sandun Udayantha, Kavindu Weerasinghe, Nima Wickramasinghe, Akila Abeyratne, Kithmin Wickremasinghe, Jithangi Wanigasinghe, Anjula De Silva, Chamira U. S. Edussooriya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Channel Shaping Using Beyond Diagonal Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface: Analysis, Optimization, and Enhanced Flexibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the capability of a passive Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (RIS) to redistribute the singular values of point-to-point Multiple-Input Multiple-Output (MIMO) channels for achieving power and rate gains. We depart from the conventional Diagonal (D)-RIS with diagonal phase shift matrix and adopt a Beyond Diagonal (BD) architecture that offers greater wave manipulation flexibility through element-wise connections. Specifically, we first provide shaping insights by characterizing the channel singular value regions attainable by D-RIS and BD-RIS via a novel geodesic optimization. Analytical singular value bounds are then derived to explore their shaping limits in typical deployment scenarios. As a side product, we tackle BD-RIS-aided MIMO rate maximization problem by a local-optimal Alternating Optimization (AO) and a shaping-inspired low-complexity approach. Results show that compared to D-RIS, BD-RIS significantly improves the dynamic range of all channel singular values, the trade-off in manipulating them, and thus the channel power and achievable rate. Those observations become more pronounced when the number of RIS elements and MIMO dimensions increase. Of particular interest, BD-RIS is shown to activate multi-stream transmission at lower transmit power than D-RIS, hence achieving the asymptotic Degrees of Freedom (DoF) at low Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) thanks to its higher flexibility of shaping the distribution of channel singular values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15196v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Zhao, Hongyu Li, Massimo Franceschetti, Bruno Clerckx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guaranteed Private Communication with Secret Block Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12949v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel private communication framework is proposed where privacy is induced by transmitting over a channel instances of linear inverse problems that are identifiable to the legitimate receiver but unidentifiable to an eavesdropper. The gap in identifiability is created in the framework by leveraging secret knowledge between the transmitter and the legitimate receiver. Specifically, the case where the legitimate receiver harnesses a secret block structure to decode a transmitted block-sparse message from underdetermined linear measurements in conditions where classical compressed sensing would provably fail is examined. The applicability of the proposed scheme to practical multiple-access wireless communication systems is discussed. The protocol's privacy is studied under a single transmission, and under multiple transmissions without refreshing the secret block structure. It is shown that, under a specific scaling of the channel dimensions and transmission parameters, the eavesdropper can attempt to overhear the block structure from the fourth-order moments of the channel output. Computation of a statistical lower bound suggests that the proposed fourth-order moment secret block estimation strategy is near optimal. The performance of a spectral clustering algorithm is studied to that end, defining scaling laws on the lifespan of the secret key before the communication is compromised. Finally, numerical experiments corroborating the theoretical findings are conducted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12949v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Ferreira Da Costa, Jianxiu Li, Urbashi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next Generation Advanced Transceiver Technologies for 6G and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16458v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To accommodate new applications such as extended reality, fully autonomous vehicular networks and the metaverse, next generation wireless networks are going to be subject to much more stringent performance requirements than the fifth-generation (5G) in terms of data rates, reliability, latency, and connectivity. It is thus necessary to develop next generation advanced transceiver (NGAT) technologies for efficient signal transmission and reception. In this tutorial, we explore the evolution of NGAT from three different perspectives. Specifically, we first provide an overview of new-field NGAT technology, which shifts from conventional far-field channel models to new near-field channel models. Then, three new-form NGAT technologies and their design challenges are presented, including reconfigurable intelligent surfaces, flexible antennas, and holographic multi-input multi-output (MIMO) systems. Subsequently, we discuss recent advances in semantic-aware NGAT technologies, which can utilize new metrics for advanced transceiver designs. Finally, we point out other promising transceiver technologies for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16458v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changsheng You, Yunlong Cai, Yuanwei Liu, Marco Di Renzo, Tolga M. Duman, Aylin Yener, A. Lee Swindlehurst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Movable Antenna Empowered Downlink NOMA Systems: Power Allocation and Antenna Position Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18692v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates a novel communication paradigm employing movable antennas (MAs) within a multiple-input single-output (MISO) non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA) downlink framework, where users are equipped with MAs. Initially, leveraging the far-field response, we delineate the channel characteristics concerning both the power allocation coefficient and positions of MAs. Subsequently, we endeavor to maximize the channel capacity by jointly optimizing power allocation and antenna positions. To tackle the resultant non-convex problem, we propose an alternating optimization (AO) scheme underpinned by successive convex approximation (SCA) to converge towards a stationary point. Through numerical simulations, our findings substantiate the superiority of the MA-assisted NOMA system over both orthogonal multiple access (OMA) and conventional NOMA configurations in terms of average sum rate and outage probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18692v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufeng Zhou, Wen Chen, Qingqing Wu, Xusheng Zhu, Nan Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
