<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 04:02:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neuromorphic Split Computing with Wake-Up Radios: Architecture and Design via Digital Twinning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neuromorphic computing leverages the sparsity of temporal data to reduce processing energy by activating a small subset of neurons and synapses at each time step. When deployed for split computing in edge-based systems, remote neuromorphic processing units (NPUs) can reduce the communication power budget by communicating asynchronously using sparse impulse radio (IR) waveforms. This way, the input signal sparsity translates directly into energy savings both in terms of computation and communication. However, with IR transmission, the main contributor to the overall energy consumption remains the power required to maintain the main radio on. This work proposes a novel architecture that integrates a wake-up radio mechanism within a split computing system consisting of remote, wirelessly connected, NPUs. A key challenge in the design of a wake-up radio-based neuromorphic split computing system is the selection of thresholds for sensing, wake-up signal detection, and decision making. To address this problem, as a second contribution, this work proposes a novel methodology that leverages the use of a digital twin (DT), i.e., a simulator, of the physical system, coupled with a sequential statistical testing approach known as Learn Then Test (LTT) to provide theoretical reliability guarantees. The proposed DT-LTT methodology is broadly applicable to other design problems, and is showcased here for neuromorphic communications. Experimental results validate the design and the analysis, confirming the theoretical reliability guarantees and illustrating trade-offs among reliability, energy consumption, and informativeness of the decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01815v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiechen Chen, Sangwoo Park, Petar Popovski, H. Vincent Poor, Osvaldo Simeone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Reflecting Surfaces assisted Laser-based Optical Wireless Communication Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing demand for wireless networks of higher capacity requires key-enabling technologies. Optical wireless communication (OWC) arises as a complementary technology to radio frequency (RF) systems that can support high aggregate data rates. However, OWC systems face some challenges including beam-blockage. Intelligent reflecting surfaces (IRSs) can offer alternative pathways for the optical signal, ensuring continuous connectivity. In this work, we investigate the potential of using IRS in an indoor OWC network. In particular, we define a system model of indoor OWC that employs IRS in conjunction with angle diversity transmitters (ADT) using vertical-cavity surface-emitting laser (VCSEL) arrays. The VCSEL beam is narrow, directed, and easy to block, however, it can deliver high data rates under eye safety regulations. Simulation results show that the deployment of IRS can significantly improve the achievable data rates of Laser-based OWC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01850v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahrar N. Hamad, Walter Zibusiso Ncube, Ahmad Adnan Qidan, Taisir E. H. El-Gorashi, Jaafar M. H. Elmirghani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Satellite Federated Edge Learning: Architecture Design and Convergence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The proliferation of low-earth-orbit (LEO) satellite networks leads to the generation of vast volumes of remote sensing data which is traditionally transferred to the ground server for centralized processing, raising privacy and bandwidth concerns. Federated edge learning (FEEL), as a distributed machine learning approach, has the potential to address these challenges by sharing only model parameters instead of raw data. Although promising, the dynamics of LEO networks, characterized by the high mobility of satellites and short ground-to-satellite link (GSL) duration, pose unique challenges for FEEL. Notably, frequent model transmission between the satellites and ground incurs prolonged waiting time and large transmission latency. This paper introduces a novel FEEL algorithm, named FEDMEGA, tailored to LEO mega-constellation networks. By integrating inter-satellite links (ISL) for intra-orbit model aggregation, the proposed algorithm significantly reduces the usage of low data rate and intermittent GSL. Our proposed method includes a ring all-reduce based intra-orbit aggregation mechanism, coupled with a network flow-based transmission scheme for global model aggregation, which enhances transmission efficiency. Theoretical convergence analysis is provided to characterize the algorithm performance. Extensive simulations show that our FEDMEGA algorithm outperforms existing satellite FEEL algorithms, exhibiting an approximate 30% improvement in convergence rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01875v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanming Shi, Li Zeng, Jingyang Zhu, Yong Zhou, Chunxiao Jiang, Khaled B. Letaief</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Processing in Hybrid Photonic Electrical Reservoir Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01479v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Physical Reservoir Computing (PRC) is a recently developed variant of Neuromorphic Computing, where a pertinent physical system effectively projects information encoded in the input signal into a higher-dimensional space. While various physical hardware has demonstrated promising results for Reservoir Computing (RC), systems allowing tunability of their dynamical regimes have not received much attention regarding how to optimize relevant system parameters. In this work we employ hybrid photonic-electronic (HPE) system offering both parallelism inherent to light propagation, and electronic memory and programmable feedback allowing to induce nonlinear dynamics and tunable encoding of the photonic signal to realize HPE-RC. Specifically, we experimentally and theoretically analyze performance of integrated silicon photonic on-chip Mach-Zehnder interferometer and ring resonators with heaters acting as programmable phase modulators, controlled by detector and the feedback unit capable of realizing complex temporal dynamics of the photonic signal. Furthermore, we present an algorithm capable of predicting optimal parameters for RC by analyzing the corresponding Lyapunov exponent of the output signal and mutual information of reservoir nodes. By implementing the derived optimal parameters, we demonstrate that the corresponding resulting error of RC can be lowered by several orders of magnitude compared to a reservoir operating with randomly chosen set of parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01479v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prabhav Gaur, Chengkuan Gao, Karl Johnson, Shimon Rubin, Yeshaiahu Fainman, Tzu-Chien Hsueh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Heterogeneity in Federated Load Forecasting with Personalization Layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The advent of smart meters has enabled pervasive collection of energy consumption data for training short-term load forecasting models. In response to privacy concerns, federated learning (FL) has been proposed as a privacy-preserving approach for training, but the quality of trained models degrades as client data becomes heterogeneous. In this paper we propose the use of personalization layers for load forecasting in a general framework called PL-FL. We show that PL-FL outperforms FL and purely local training, while requiring lower communication bandwidth than FL. This is done through extensive simulations on three different datasets from the NREL ComStock repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01517v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shourya Bose, Yu Zhang, Kibaek Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI WALKUP: A Computer-Vision Approach to Quantifying MDS-UPDRS in Parkinson's Disease</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01654v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Parkinson's Disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder. The existing assessment method for PD is usually the Movement Disorder Society - Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS) to assess the severity of various types of motor symptoms and disease progression. However, manual assessment suffers from high subjectivity, lack of consistency, and high cost and low efficiency of manual communication. We want to use a computer vision based solution to capture human pose images based on a camera, reconstruct and perform motion analysis using algorithms, and extract the features of the amount of motion through feature engineering. The proposed approach can be deployed on different smartphones, and the video recording and artificial intelligence analysis can be done quickly and easily through our APP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01654v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Xiang, Zihan Zhang, Jing Ma, Yao Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Meta Distribution of the SIR in Joint Communication and Sensing Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel mathematical framework for assessing the performance of joint communication and sensing (JCAS) in wireless networks, employing stochastic geometry as an analytical tool. We focus on deriving the meta distribution of the signal-to-interference ratio (SIR) for JCAS networks. This approach enables a fine-grained quantification of individual user or radar performance intrinsic to these networks. Our work involves the modeling of JCAS networks and the derivation of mathematical expressions for the JCAS SIR meta distribution. Through simulations, we validate both our theoretical analysis and illustrate how the JCAS SIR meta distribution varies with the network deployment density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01672v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Ma, Chenyuan Feng, Giovanni Geraci, Howard H. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning-Based Joint Beamforming and Antenna Movement Design for Movable Antenna Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01784v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a multi-receiver communication system enabled by movable antennas (MAs). Specifically, the transmit beamforming and the double-side antenna movement at the transceiver are jointly designed to maximize the sum-rate of all receivers under imperfect channel state information (CSI). Since the formulated problem is non-convex with highly coupled variables, conventional optimization methods cannot solve it efficiently. To address these challenges, an effective learning-based algorithm is proposed, namely heterogeneous multi-agent deep deterministic policy gradient (MADDPG), which incorporates two agents to learn policies for beamforming and movement of MAs, respectively. Based on the offline learning under numerous imperfect CSI, the proposed heterogeneous MADDPG can output the solutions for transmit beamforming and antenna movement in real time. Simulation results validate the effectiveness of the proposed algorithm, and the MA can significantly improve the sum-rate performance of multiple receivers compared to other benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01784v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caihao Weng, Yuanbin Chen, Lipeng Zhu, Ying Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiparametric quantification and visualization of liver fat using ultrasound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02143v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Objectives- Several ultrasound measures have shown promise for assessment of steatosis compared to traditional B-scan, however clinicians may be required to integrate information across the parameters. Here, we propose an integrated multiparametric approach, enabling simple clinical assessment of key information from combined ultrasound parameters. Methods- We have measured 13 parameters related to ultrasound and shear wave elastography. These were measured in 30 human subjects under a study of liver fat. The 13 individual measures are assessed for their predictive value using independent magnetic resonance imaging-derived proton density fat fraction (MRI-PDFF) measurements as a reference standard. In addition, a comprehensive and fine-grain analysis is made of all possible combinations of sub-sets of these parameters to determine if any subset can be efficiently combined to predict fat fraction. Results- We found that as few as four key parameters related to ultrasound propagation are sufficient to generate a linear multiparametric parameter with a correlation against MRI-PDFF values of greater than 0.93. This optimal combination was found to have a classification area under the curve (AUC) approaching 1.0 when applying a threshold for separating steatosis grade zero from higher classes. Furthermore, a strategy is developed for applying local estimates of fat content as a color overlay to produce a visual impression of the extent and distribution of fat within the liver. Conclusion- In principle, this approach can be applied to most clinical ultrasound systems to provide the clinician and patient with a rapid and inexpensive estimate of liver fat content.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02143v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihye Baek, Ahmed El Kaffas, Aya Kamaya, Kenneth Hoyt, Kevin J. Parker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learned Kernels for Sparse, Interpretable, and Efficient Medical Time Series Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05385v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Background: Rapid, reliable, and accurate interpretation of medical signals is crucial for high-stakes clinical decision-making. The advent of deep learning allowed for an explosion of new models that offered unprecedented performance in medical time series processing but at a cost: deep learning models are often compute-intensive and lack interpretability.
  Methods: We propose Sparse Mixture of Learned Kernels (SMoLK), an interpretable architecture for medical time series processing. The method learns a set of lightweight flexible kernels to construct a single-layer neural network, providing not only interpretability, but also efficiency and robustness. We introduce novel parameter reduction techniques to further reduce the size of our network. We demonstrate the power of our architecture on two important tasks: photoplethysmography (PPG) artifact detection and atrial fibrillation detection from single-lead electrocardiograms (ECGs). Our approach has performance similar to the state-of-the-art deep neural networks with several orders of magnitude fewer parameters, allowing for deep neural network level performance with extremely low-power wearable devices.
  Results: Our interpretable method achieves greater than 99% of the performance of the state-of-the-art methods on the PPG artifact detection task, and even outperforms the state-of-the-art on a challenging out-of-distribution test set, while using dramatically fewer parameters (2% of the parameters of Segade, and about half of the parameters of Tiny-PPG). On single lead atrial fibrillation detection, our method matches the performance of a 1D-residual convolutional network, at less than 1% the parameter count, while exhibiting considerably better performance in the low-data regime, even when compared to a parameter-matched control deep network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05385v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sully F. Chen, Zhicheng Guo, Cheng Ding, Xiao Hu, Cynthia Rudin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Precoding and Combining for mmWave Full-Duplex Joint Radar and Communication Systems under Self-Interference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14942v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the context of integrated sensing and communication (ISAC), a full-duplex (FD) transceiver can operate as a monostatic radar while maintaining communication capabilities. This paper investigates the design of precoders and combiners for a joint radar and communication (JRC) system at mmWave frequencies. The primary goal of the design is to guarantee certain performance in terms of some sensing and communication metrics while minimizing the self-interference (SI) caused by FD operation and taking into account the hardware limitations coming from a hybrid MIMO architecture. Specifically, we introduce a generalized eigenvalue-based precoder design that considers the downlink user rate, the radar gain, and the SI suppression. Since the hybrid analog/digital architecture degrades the SI mitigation capability of the precoder, we further enhance SI suppression with the analog combiner. Our numerical results demonstrate that the proposed architecture achieves the required radar gain and SI mitigation while incurring a small loss in downlink spectral efficiency. Additionally, the numerical experiments also show that the use of orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) radar with the proposed beamforming architecture results in highly accurate range and velocity estimates for the detected targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14942v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Murat Bayraktar, Nuria Gonz\'alez-Prelcic, Hao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolution Limit of Single-Photon LiDAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17719v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Single-photon Light Detection and Ranging (LiDAR) systems are often equipped with an array of detectors for improved spatial resolution and sensing speed. However, given a fixed amount of flux produced by the laser transmitter across the scene, the per-pixel Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) will decrease when more pixels are packed in a unit space. This presents a fundamental trade-off between the spatial resolution of the sensor array and the SNR received at each pixel. Theoretical characterization of this fundamental limit is explored. By deriving the photon arrival statistics and introducing a series of new approximation techniques, the Mean Squared Error (MSE) of the maximum-likelihood estimator of the time delay is derived. The theoretical predictions align well with simulations and real data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17719v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanley H. Chan, Hashan K. Weerasooriya, Weijian Zhang, Pamela Abshire, Istvan Gyongy, Robert K. Henderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning The Likelihood Test With One-Class Classifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.12494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.12494v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given an observation randomly generated from two alternative probability density functions (pdfs) P0 and P1, we consider the problem of deciding which pdf generated the observation. To design the decision technique we assume that we either know P0 or have a set of samples generated from it; the P1 pdf is instead completely unknown. Such a scenario arises, for example, in security contexts, where the attacker's behavior is completely unknown to the legitimate users. When the P0 pdf is known, we resort to the likelihood test (LT), while when a set of samples with its distribution is available, we resort to one-class classification (OCC). We focus on the problem of learning OCC models that operate as the LT. We show this occurs for the multilayer perceptron neural network (NN) and the one-class least-squares support vector machine (OCLSSVM) models properly trained as two-class classifiers using an artificial dataset for the negative class, obtained by generating samples uniformly distributed over the domain of the positive class dataset. The artificial dataset is used only for training, while the OCC is used on negative-class samples generated from a different pdf. We also derive a modified stochastic gradient descent (SGD) algorithm that provides OCC operating as LT without the need for the artificial dataset. Furthermore, we show that the OCLSSVM with suitable kernels operates as the LT at convergence. Lastly, we prove that the widely used autoencoder (AE) classifier generally does not provide the LT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.12494v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Ardizzon, Stefano Tomasin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive Analysis of Maximum Power Association Policy for Cellular Networks Using Distance and Angular Coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.09939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.09939v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel stochastic geometry framework is proposed in this paper to study the downlink coverage performance in a millimeter wave (mmWave) cellular network by jointly considering the polar coordinates of the Base Stations (BSs) with respect to the typical user located at the origin. Specifically, both the Euclidean and the angular distances of the BSs in a maximum power-based association policy for the UE are considered to account for realistic beam management considerations, which have been largely ignored in the literature, especially in the cell association phase. For completeness, two other association schemes are considered and exact-form expressions for the coverage probability are derived. Subsequently, the key role of angular distances is highlighted by defining the dominant interferer using angular distance-based criteria instead of Euclidean distance-based, and conducting a dominant interferer-based coverage probability analysis. Among others, the numerical results revealed that considering angular distance-based criteria for determining both the serving and the dominant interfering BS, can approximate the coverage performance more accurately as compared to utilizing Euclidean distance-based criteria. To the best of the authors$'$ knowledge, this is the first work that rigorously explores the role of angular distances in the association policy and analysis of cellular networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.09939v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harris K. Armeniakos, Athanasios G. Kanatas, Harpreet S. Dhillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
