<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 04:03:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>TypeII-CsiNet: CSI Feedback with TypeII Codebook</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The latest TypeII codebook selects partial strongest angular-delay ports for the feedback of downlink channel state information (CSI), whereas its performance is limited due to the deficiency of utilizing the correlations among the port coefficients. To tackle this issue, we propose a tailored autoencoder named TypeII-CsiNet to effectively integrate the TypeII codebook with deep learning, wherein three novel designs are developed for sufficiently boosting the sum rate performance. Firstly, a dedicated pre-processing module is designed to sort the selected ports for reserving the correlations of their corresponding coefficients. Secondly, a position-filling layer is developed in the decoder to fill the feedback coefficients into their ports in the recovered CSI matrix, so that the corresponding angular-delay-domain structure is adequately leveraged to enhance the reconstruction accuracy. Thirdly, a two-stage loss function is proposed to improve the sum rate performance while avoiding the trapping in local optimums during model training. Simulation results verify that our proposed TypeII-CsiNet outperforms the TypeII codebook and existing deep learning benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12569v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiliang Sang, Ke Ma, Yang Ming, Jin Lian, Zhaocheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Digital-Analog Semantic Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital and analog semantic communications (SemCom) face inherent limitations such as data security concerns in analog SemCom, as well as leveling-off and cliff-edge effects in digital SemCom. In order to overcome these challenges, we propose a novel SemCom framework and a corresponding system called HDA-DeepSC, which leverages a hybrid digital-analog approach for multimedia transmission. This is achieved through the introduction of digital-analog allocation and fusion modules. To strike a balance between data rate and distortion, we design new loss functions that take into account long-distance dependencies in the semantic distortion constraint, essential information recovery in the channel distortion constraint, and optimal bit stream generation in the rate constraint. Additionally, we propose denoising diffusion-based signal detection techniques, which involve carefully designed variance schedules and sampling algorithms to refine transmitted signals. Through extensive numerical experiments, we will demonstrate that HDA-DeepSC exhibits robustness to channel variations and is capable of supporting various communication scenarios. Our proposed framework outperforms existing benchmarks in terms of peak signal-to-noise ratio and multi-scale structural similarity, showcasing its superiority in semantic communication quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12580v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiqiang Xie, Zhijin Qin, Zhu Han, Khaled B. Letaief</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Improved Robust Total Logistic Distance Metric algorithm for Generalized Gaussian Noise and Noisy Input</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although the known maximum total generalized correntropy (MTGC) and generalized maximum blakezisserman total correntropy (GMBZTC) algorithms can maintain good performance under the errors-in-variables (EIV) model disrupted by generalized Gaussian noise, their requirement for manual ad-justment of parameters is excessive, greatly increasing the practical difficulty of use. To solve this problem, the total arctangent based on logical distance metric (TACLDM) algo-rithm is proposed by utilizing the advantage of few parameters in logical distance metric (LDM) theory and the convergence behavior is improved by the arctangent function. Compared with other competing algorithms, the TACLDM algorithm not only has fewer parameters, but also has better robustness to generalized Gaussian noise and significantly reduces the steady-state error. Furthermore, the analysis of the algorithm in the generalized Gaussian noise environment is analyzed in detail in this paper. Finally, computer simulations demonstrate the outstanding performance of the TACLDM algorithm and the rigorous theoretical deduction in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12589v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiquan Zhao, Yi Peng, Zian Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive mm-Wave FMCW Radar Dataset for Vital Sign Monitoring: Embracing Extreme Physiological Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advancements in non-invasive health monitoring technologies underscore the potential of mm-Wave Frequency-Modulated Continuous Wave (FMCW) radar in real-time vital sign detection. This paper introduces a novel dataset, the first of its kind, derived from mm-Wave FMCW radar, meticulously capturing heart rate and respiratory rate under various conditions. Comprising data from ten participants, including scenarios with elevated heart rates and participants with diverse physiological profiles such as asthma and meditation practitioners, this dataset is validated against the Polar H10 sensor, ensuring its reliability for scientific research. This dataset can offer a significant resource for developing and testing algorithms aimed at non-invasive health monitoring, promising to facilitate advancements in remote health monitoring technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12659v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Sadeghi, Karina Skurule, Alessandro Chiumento, Paul Havinga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying 5G NR Downlink Synchronization for Tactical Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: 5G NR is touted to be an attractive candidate for tactical networks owing to its versatility, scalability, and low cost. However, tactical networks need to be stealthy, where an adversary is not able to detect or intercept the tactical communication. In this paper, we investigate the stealthiness of 5G NR by looking at the probability with which an adversary that monitors the downlink synchronization signals can detect the presence of the network. We simulate a single-cell single-eavesdropper scenario and evaluate the probability with which the eavesdropper can detect the synchronization signal block when using either a correlator or an energy detector. We show that this probability is close to $ 100 $% suggesting that 5G out-of-the-box is not suitable for a tactical network. We then propose methods that lower this value without affecting the performance of a legitimate tactical UE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12704v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karthik Upadhya, Akshay Jain, Mikko A. Uusitalo, Harish Viswanathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Coded-Apertures for Depth-Resolved Diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coded apertures, traditionally employed in x-ray astronomy for imaging celestial objects, are now being adapted for micro-scale applications, particularly in studying microscopic specimens with synchrotron light diffraction. In this paper, we focus on micro-coded aperture imaging and its capacity to accomplish depth-resolved micro-diffraction analysis within crystalline specimens. We study aperture specifications and scanning parameters by assessing characteristics like size, thickness, and patterns. Numerical experiments assist in assessing their impact on reconstruction quality. Empirical data from a Laue diffraction microscope at a synchrotron undulator beamline supports our findings. Overall, our results offer key insights for optimizing aperture design in advancing micro-scale diffraction imaging at synchrotrons. This study contributes insights to this expanding field and suggests significant advancements, especially when coupled with the enhanced flux anticipated from the global upgrades of synchrotron sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12813v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do\u{g}a G\"ursoy, Dina Sheyfer, Michael Wojcik, Wenjun Liu, Jonathan Tischler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Experimental Study of C-Band Channel Model in Integrated LEO Satellite and Terrestrial Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies the channel model for the integrated satellite-terrestrial networks operating at C-band under deployment in dense urban and rural areas. Particularly, the interference channel from the low-earth-orbit (LEO) satellite to the dense urban area is analyzed carefully under the impact of the environment's characteristics, i.e., the building density, building height, and the elevation angle. Subsequently, the experimental results show the strong relationships between these characteristics and the channel gain loss. Especially, the functions of channel gain loss are obtained by utilizing the model-fitting approach that can be used as the basis for studying future works of integration of satellite and terrestrial networks (ISTNs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12839v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hung Nguyen-Kha, Vu Nguyen Ha, Eva Lagunas, Symeon Chatzinotas, Joel Grotz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Column Bound for Orthogonal Matrix Factorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12858v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article explores the intersection of the Coupon Collector's Problem and the Orthogonal Matrix Factorization (OMF) problem. Specifically, we derive bounds on the minimum number of columns $p$ (in $\mathbf{X}$) required for the OMF problem to be tractable, using insights from the Coupon Collector's Problem. Specifically, we establish a theorem outlining the relationship between the sparsity of the matrix $\mathbf{X}$ and the number of columns $p$ required to recover the matrices $\mathbf{V}$ and $\mathbf{X}$ in the OMF problem. We show that the minimum number of columns $p$ required is given by $p = \Omega \left(\max \left\{ \frac{n}{1 - (1 - \theta)^n}, \frac{1}{\theta} \log n \right\} \right)$, where $\theta$ is the i.i.d Bernoulli parameter from which the sparsity model of the matrix $\mathbf{X}$ is derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12858v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirudh Dash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic analysis of sum-rate under SIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12937v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Limitation of the cost of coordination and contention among a large number of nodes calls for grant-free approaches, exploiting physical layer techniques to solve collisions. Successive Interference Cancellation (SIC) is becoming a key building block of multiple access channel receiver, in an effort to support massive Internet of Things (IoT). In this paper, we explore the large-scale performance of SIC in a theoretical framework. A general model of a SIC receiver is stated for a shared channel with $n$ transmitters. The asymptotic sum-rate performance is characterized as $n \rightarrow \infty$, for a suitably scaled target Signal to Noise Interference Ratio (SNIR). The probability distribution of the number of correctly decoded packets is shown to tend to a deterministic distribution asymptotically for large values of $n$. The asymptotic analysis is carried out for any probability distribution of the wireless channel gain, assuming that the average received power level is same for all nodes, through power control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12937v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Baiocchi, Asmad Razzaque</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the Autism spectrum heterogeneity: Insights from ABIDE I Database using data/model-driven permutation testing approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12225v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autism Spectrum Condition (ASC) is a neurodevelopmental condition characterized by impairments in communication, social interaction and restricted or repetitive behaviors. Extensive research has been conducted to identify distinctions between individuals with ASC and neurotypical individuals. However, limited attention has been given to comprehensively evaluating how variations in image acquisition protocols across different centers influence these observed differences. This analysis focuses on structural magnetic resonance imaging (sMRI) data from the Autism Brain Imaging Data Exchange I (ABIDE I) database, evaluating subjects' condition and individual centers to identify disparities between ASC and control groups. Statistical analysis, employing permutation tests, utilizes two distinct statistical mapping methods: Statistical Agnostic Mapping (SAM) and Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM). Results reveal the absence of statistically significant differences in any brain region, attributed to factors such as limited sample sizes within certain centers, noise effects and the problem of multicentrism in a heterogeneous condition such as autism. This study indicates limitations in using the ABIDE I database to detect structural differences in the brain between neurotypical individuals and those diagnosed with ASC. Furthermore, results from the SAM mapping method show greater consistency with existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12225v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. J. Alcaide, I. A. Illan, J. Ramirez, J. M. Gorriz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power Measurement Based Channel Estimation for IRS-Enhanced Wireless Coverage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study an IRS-assisted coverage enhancement problem for a given region, aiming to optimize the passive reflection of the IRS for improving the average communication performance in the region by accounting for both deterministic and random channels in the environment. To this end, we first derive the closed-form expression of the average received signal power in terms of the deterministic base station (BS)-IRS-user cascaded channels over all user locations, and propose an IRS-aided coverage enhancement framework to facilitate the estimation of such deterministic channels for IRS passive reflection design. Specifically, to avoid the exorbitant overhead of estimating the cascaded channels at all possible user locations, a location selection method is first proposed to select only a set of typical user locations for channel estimation by exploiting the channel spatial correlation in the region. To estimate the deterministic cascaded channels at the selected user locations, conventional IRS channel estimation methods require additional pilot signals, which not only results in high system training overhead but also may not be compatible with the existing communication protocols. To overcome this issue, we further propose a single-layer neural network (NN)-enabled IRS channel estimation method in this paper, based on only the average received signal power measurements at each selected location corresponding to different IRS random training reflections, which can be offline implemented in current wireless systems. Numerical results demonstrate that our proposed scheme can significantly improve the coverage performance of the target region and outperform the existing power-measurement-based IRS reflection designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12432v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He Sun, Lipeng Zhu, Weidong Mei, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Integrating Wireless Technology into Active Noise Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Active Noise Control (ANC) is a widely adopted technology for reducing environmental noise across various scenarios. This paper focuses on enhancing noise reduction performance, particularly through the refinement of signal quality fed into ANC systems. We discuss the main wireless technique integrated into the ANC system, equipped with some innovative algorithms, in diverse environments. Instead of using microphone arrays, which increase the computation complexity of the ANC system, to isolate multiple noise sources to improve noise reduction performance, the application of the wireless technique avoids extra computation demand. Wireless transmissions of reference, error, and control signals are also applied to improve the convergence performance of the ANC system. Furthermore, this paper lists some wireless ANC applications, such as earbuds, headphones, windows, and headrests, underscoring their adaptability and efficiency in various settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12496v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyi Shen, Dongyuan Shi, Zhengding Luo, Junwei Ji, Woon-Seng Gan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EchoPT: A Pretrained Transformer Architecture that Predicts 2D In-Air Sonar Images for Mobile Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The predictive brain hypothesis suggests that perception can be interpreted as the process of minimizing the error between predicted perception tokens generated by an internal world model and actual sensory input tokens. When implementing working examples of this hypothesis in the context of in-air sonar, significant difficulties arise due to the sparse nature of the reflection model that governs ultrasonic sensing. Despite these challenges, creating consistent world models using sonar data is crucial for implementing predictive processing of ultrasound data in robotics. In an effort to enable robust robot behavior using ultrasound as the sole exteroceptive sensor modality, this paper introduces EchoPT, a pretrained transformer architecture designed to predict 2D sonar images from previous sensory data and robot ego-motion information. We detail the transformer architecture that drives EchoPT and compare the performance of our model to several state-of-the-art techniques. In addition to presenting and evaluating our EchoPT model, we demonstrate the effectiveness of this predictive perception approach in two robotic tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12573v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Steckel, Wouter Jansen, Nico Huebel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Information Hub-Empowered 6G NTN: Latency-Oriented Resource Orchestration and Configuration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quick response to disasters is crucial for saving lives and reducing loss. This requires low-latency uploading of situation information to the remote command center. Since terrestrial infrastructures are often damaged in disaster areas, non-terrestrial networks (NTNs) are preferable to provide network coverage, and mobile edge computing (MEC) could be integrated to improve the latency performance. Nevertheless, the communications and computing in MEC-enabled NTNs are strongly coupled, which complicates the system design. In this paper, an edge information hub (EIH) that incorporates communication, computing and storage capabilities is proposed to synergize communication and computing and enable systematic design. We first address the joint data scheduling and resource orchestration problem to minimize the latency for uploading sensing data. The problem is solved using an optimal resource orchestration algorithm. On that basis, we propose the principles for resource configuration of the EIH considering payload constraints on size, weight and energy supply. Simulation results demonstrate the superiority of our proposed scheme in reducing the overall upload latency, thus enabling quick emergency rescue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12652v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueshan Lin, Wei Feng, Yunfei Chen, Ning Ge, Zhiyong Feng, Yue Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blind Separation of Vibration Sources using Deep Learning and Deconvolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vibrations of rotating machinery primarily originate from two sources, both of which are distorted by the machine's transfer function on their way to the sensor: the dominant gear-related vibrations and a low-energy signal linked to bearing faults. The proposed method facilitates the blind separation of vibration sources, eliminating the need for any information about the monitored equipment or external measurements. This method estimates both sources in two stages: initially, the gear signal is isolated using a dilated CNN, followed by the estimation of the bearing fault signal using the squared log envelope of the residual. The effect of the transfer function is removed from both sources using a novel whitening-based deconvolution method (WBD). Both simulation and experimental results demonstrate the method's ability to detect bearing failures early when no additional information is available. This study considers both local and distributed bearing faults, assuming that the vibrations are recorded under stable operating conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12774v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Makienko, Michael Grebshtein, Eli Gildish</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark-Field X-Ray Microscopy with Structured Illumination for Three-Dimensional Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12799v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a structured illumination technique for dark-field x-ray microscopy optimized for three-dimensional imaging of ordered materials at sub-micrometer length scales. Our method utilizes a coded aperture to spatially modulate the incident x-ray beam on the sample, enabling the reconstruction of the sample's 3D structure from images captured at various aperture positions. Unlike common volumetric imaging techniques such as tomography, our approach casts a scanning x-ray silhouette of a coded aperture for depth resolution along the axis of diffraction, eliminating any need for sample rotation or rastering, leading to a highly stable imaging modality. This modification provides robustness against geometric uncertainties during data acquisition, particularly for achieving sub-micrometer resolutions where geometric uncertainties typically limit resolution. We introduce the image reconstruction model and validate our results with experimental data on an isolated twin domain within a bulk single crystal of an iron pnictide obtained using a dark-field x-ray microscope. This timely advancement aligns with the enhanced brightness upgrade of the world's synchrotron radiation facilities, opening unprecedented opportunities in imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12799v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do\u{g}a G\"ursoy, Kaan Alp Yay, Elliot Kisiel, Michael Wojcik, Dina Sheyfer, Matthew Highland, Ian Randal Fisher, Stephan Hruszkewycz, Zahir Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wav-KAN: Wavelet Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12832v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper , we introduce Wav-KAN, an innovative neural network architecture that leverages the Wavelet Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (Wav-KAN) framework to enhance interpretability and performance. Traditional multilayer perceptrons (MLPs) and even recent advancements like Spl-KAN face challenges related to interpretability, training speed, robustness, computational efficiency, and performance. Wav-KAN addresses these limitations by incorporating wavelet functions into the Kolmogorov-Arnold network structure, enabling the network to capture both high-frequency and low-frequency components of the input data efficiently. Wavelet-based approximations employ orthogonal or semi-orthogonal basis and also maintains a balance between accurately representing the underlying data structure and avoiding overfitting to the noise. Analogous to how water conforms to the shape of its container, Wav-KAN adapts to the data structure, resulting in enhanced accuracy, faster training speeds, and increased robustness compared to Spl-KAN and MLPs. Our results highlight the potential of Wav-KAN as a powerful tool for developing interpretable and high-performance neural networks, with applications spanning various fields. This work sets the stage for further exploration and implementation of Wav-KAN in frameworks such as PyTorch, TensorFlow, and also it makes wavelet in KAN in wide-spread usage like nowadays activation functions like ReLU, sigmoid in universal approximation theory (UAT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12832v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zavareh Bozorgasl, Hao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Neural Networks over the Air for Decentralized Tasks in Wireless Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.08447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.08447v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graph neural networks (GNNs) model representations from networked data and allow for decentralized inference through localized communications. Existing GNN architectures often assume ideal communications and ignore potential channel effects, such as fading and noise, leading to performance degradation in real-world implementation. Considering a GNN implemented over nodes connected through wireless links, this paper conducts a stability analysis to study the impact of channel impairments on the performance of GNNs, and proposes graph neural networks over the air (AirGNNs), a novel GNN architecture that incorporates the communication model. AirGNNs modify graph convolutional operations that shift graph signals over random communication graphs to take into account channel fading and noise when aggregating features from neighbors, thus, improving architecture robustness to channel impairments during testing. We develop a channel-inversion signal transmission strategy for AirGNNs when channel state information (CSI) is available, and propose a stochastic gradient descent based method to train AirGNNs when CSI is unknown. The convergence analysis shows that the training procedure approaches a stationary solution of an associated stochastic optimization problem and the variance analysis characterizes the statistical behavior of the trained model. Experiments on decentralized source localization and multi-robot flocking corroborate theoretical findings and show superior performance of AirGNNs over wireless communication channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.08447v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhan Gao, Deniz Gunduz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Visibility Region Detection and Channel Estimation for XL-MIMO Systems via Alternating MAP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a joint visibility region (VR) detection and channel estimation problem in extremely large-scale multiple-input-multiple-output (XL-MIMO) systems, where near-field propagation and spatial non-stationary effects exist. In this case, each scatterer can only see a subset of antennas, i.e., it has a certain VR over the antennas. Because of the spatial correlation among adjacent sub-arrays, VR of scatterers exhibits a two-dimensional (2D) clustered sparsity. We design a 2D Markov prior model to capture such a structured sparsity. Based on this, a novel alternating maximum a posteriori (MAP) framework is developed for high-accuracy VR detection and channel estimation. The alternating MAP framework consists of three basic modules: a channel estimation module, a VR detection module, and a grid update module. Specifically, the first module is a low-complexity inverse-free variational Bayesian inference (IF-VBI) algorithm that avoids the matrix inverse via minimizing a relaxed Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence. The second module is a structured expectation propagation (EP) algorithm which has the ability to deal with complicated prior information. And the third module refines polar-domain grid parameters via gradient ascent. Simulations demonstrate the superiority of the proposed algorithm in both VR detection and channel estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04027v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenkang Xu, An Liu, Min-jian Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces for Satellite-Terrestrial Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11909v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a three-dimensional (3D) satellite-terrestrial communication network assisted with reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs). Using stochastic geometry models, we present an original framework to derive tractable yet accurate closed-form expressions for coverage probability and ergodic capacity in the presence of fading. A homogeneous Poisson point process models the satellites on a sphere, while RISs are randomly deployed in a 3D cylindrical region. We consider nonidentical channels that correspond to different RISs and follow the {\kappa}-{\mu} fading distribution. We verify the high accuracy of the adopted approach through Monte Carlo simulations and demonstrate the significant improvement in system performance due to using RISs. Furthermore, we comprehensively study the effect of the different system parameters on its performance using the derived analytical expressions, which enable system engineers to predict and optimize the expected downlink coverage and capacity performance analytically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11909v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Islam M. Tanash, Risto Wichman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auto-Linear Phenomenon in Subsurface Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13314v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Subsurface imaging involves solving full waveform inversion (FWI) to predict geophysical properties from measurements. This problem can be reframed as an image-to-image translation, with the usual approach being to train an encoder-decoder network using paired data from two domains: geophysical property and measurement. A recent seminal work (InvLINT) demonstrates there is only a linear mapping between the latent spaces of the two domains, and the decoder requires paired data for training.
  This paper extends this direction by demonstrating that only linear mapping necessitates paired data, while both the encoder and decoder can be learned from their respective domains through self-supervised learning. This unveils an intriguing phenomenon (named Auto-Linear) where the self-learned features of two separate domains are automatically linearly correlated. Compared with existing methods, our Auto-Linear has four advantages: (a) solving both forward and inverse modeling simultaneously, (b) applicable to different subsurface imaging tasks and achieving markedly better results than previous methods, (c)enhanced performance, especially in scenarios with limited paired data and in the presence of noisy data, and (d) strong generalization ability of the trained encoder and decoder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13314v3</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinan Feng, Yinpeng Chen, Peng Jin, Shihang Feng, Zicheng Liu, Youzuo Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal preprocessing of WiFi CSI for sensing applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12126v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to its ubiquitous and contact-free nature, the use of WiFi infrastructure for performing sensing tasks has tremendous potential. However, the channel state information (CSI) measured by a WiFi receiver suffers from errors in both its gain and phase, which can significantly hinder sensing tasks. By analyzing these errors from different WiFi receivers, a mathematical model for these gain and phase errors is developed in this work. Based on these models, several theoretically justified preprocessing algorithms for correcting such errors at a receiver and, thus, obtaining clean CSI are presented. Simulation results show that at typical system parameters, the developed algorithms for cleaning CSI can reduce noise by $40$% and $200$%, respectively, compared to baseline methods for gain correction and phase correction, without significantly impacting computational cost. The superiority of the proposed methods is also validated in a real-world test bed for respiration rate monitoring (an example sensing task), where they improve the estimation signal-to-noise ratio by $20$% compared to baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12126v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TWC.2024.3376332</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vishnu V. Ratnam (Charlie), Hao Chen (Charlie), Hao Hsuan Chang (Charlie), Abhishek Sehgal (Charlie),  Jianzhong (Charlie),  Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Polynomial Graph Filters: A Novel Adaptive Krylov Subspace Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07954v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Graph Neural Networks (GNNs), known as spectral graph filters, find a wide range of applications in web networks. To bypass eigendecomposition, polynomial graph filters are proposed to approximate graph filters by leveraging various polynomial bases for filter training. However, no existing studies have explored the diverse polynomial graph filters from a unified perspective for optimization.
  In this paper, we first unify polynomial graph filters, as well as the optimal filters of identical degrees into the Krylov subspace of the same order, thus providing equivalent expressive power theoretically. Next, we investigate the asymptotic convergence property of polynomials from the unified Krylov subspace perspective, revealing their limited adaptability in graphs with varying heterophily degrees. Inspired by those facts, we design a novel adaptive Krylov subspace approach to optimize polynomial bases with provable controllability over the graph spectrum so as to adapt various heterophily graphs. Subsequently, we propose AdaptKry, an optimized polynomial graph filter utilizing bases from the adaptive Krylov subspaces. Meanwhile, in light of the diverse spectral properties of complex graphs, we extend AdaptKry by leveraging multiple adaptive Krylov bases without incurring extra training costs. As a consequence, extended AdaptKry is able to capture the intricate characteristics of graphs and provide insights into their inherent complexity. We conduct extensive experiments across a series of real-world datasets. The experimental results demonstrate the superior filtering capability of AdaptKry, as well as the optimized efficacy of the adaptive Krylov basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07954v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keke Huang, Wencai Cao, Hoang Ta, Xiaokui Xiao, Pietro Li\`o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safeguarding Next Generation Multiple Access Using Physical Layer Security Techniques: A Tutorial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16477v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Driven by the ever-increasing requirements of ultra-high spectral efficiency, ultra-low latency, and massive connectivity, the forefront of wireless research calls for the design of advanced next generation multiple access schemes to facilitate provisioning of these stringent demands. This inspires the embrace of non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA) in future wireless communication networks. Nevertheless, the support of massive access via NOMA leads to additional security threats, due to the open nature of the air interface, the broadcast characteristic of radio propagation as well as intertwined relationship among paired NOMA users. To address this specific challenge, the superimposed transmission of NOMA can be explored as new opportunities for security aware design, for example, multiuser interference inherent in NOMA can be constructively engineered to benefit communication secrecy and privacy. The purpose of this tutorial is to provide a comprehensive overview on the state-of-the-art physical layer security techniques that guarantee wireless security and privacy for NOMA networks, along with the opportunities, technical challenges, and future research trends.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16477v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Lv, Dongyang Xu, Rose Qingyang Hu, Yinghui Ye, Long Yang, Xianfu Lei, Xianbin Wang, Dong In Kim, Arumugam Nallanathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
