<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AI-Enhanced Wi-Fi Sensing Through Single Transceiver Pair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The advancement of next-generation Wi-Fi technology heavily relies on sensing capabilities, which play a pivotal role in enabling sophisticated applications. In response to the growing demand for large-scale deployments, contemporary Wi-Fi sensing systems strive to achieve high-precision perception while maintaining minimal bandwidth consumption and antenna count requirements. Remarkably, various AI-driven perception technologies have demonstrated the ability to surpass the traditional resolution limitations imposed by radar theory. However, the theoretical underpinnings of this phenomenon have not been thoroughly investigated in existing research. In this study, we found that under hardware-constrained conditions, the performance gains brought by AI to Wi-Fi sensing systems primarily originate from two aspects: prior information and temporal correlation. Prior information enables the AI to generate plausible details based on vague input, while temporal correlation helps reduce the upper bound of sensing error. We developed an AI-based Wi-Fi sensing system using a single transceiver pair and designed experiments focusing on human pose estimation and indoor localization to validate the theoretical claims. The results confirm the performance gains contributed by temporal correlation and prior information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02845v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Liu, Chiya Zhang, Yifeng Yuan, Chunlong He, Weizheng Zhang, Gaojie Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Attention Network for Epileptic Seizure Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02846v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we present a deep learning framework that learns complex spatio-temporal correlation structures of EEG signals through a Spatio-Temporal Attention Network (STAN) for accurate predictions of onset of seizures for Epilepsy patients. Unlike existing methods, which rely on feature engineering and/or assume fixed preictal durations, our approach simultaneously models spatio-temporal correlations through STAN and employs an adversarial discriminator to distinguish preictal from interictal attention patterns, enabling patient-specific learning. Evaluation on CHB-MIT and MSSM datasets demonstrates 96.6\% sensitivity with 0.011/h false detection rate on CHB-MIT, and 94.2% sensitivity with 0.063/h FDR on MSSM, significantly outperforming state-of-the-art methods. The framework reliably detects preictal states at least 15 minutes before an onset, with patient-specific windows extending to 45 minutes, providing sufficient intervention time for clinical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02846v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zan Li, Kyongmin Yeo, Wesley Gifford, Lara Marcuse, Madeline Fields, B\"ulent Yener</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EEGReXferNet: A Lightweight Gen-AI Framework for EEG Subspace Reconstruction via Cross-Subject Transfer Learning and Channel-Aware Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electroencephalography (EEG) is a widely used non-invasive technique for monitoring brain activity, but low signal-to-noise ratios (SNR) due to various artifacts often compromise its utility. Conventional artifact removal methods require manual intervention or risk suppressing critical neural features during filtering/reconstruction. Recent advances in generative models, including Variational Autoencoders (VAEs) and Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), have shown promise for EEG reconstruction; however, these approaches often lack integrated temporal-spectral-spatial sensitivity and are computationally intensive, limiting their suitability for real-time applications like brain-computer interfaces (BCIs). To overcome these challenges, we introduce EEGReXferNet, a lightweight Gen-AI framework for EEG subspace reconstruction via cross-subject transfer learning - developed using Keras TensorFlow (v2.15.1). EEGReXferNet employs a modular architecture that leverages volume conduction across neighboring channels, band-specific convolution encoding, and dynamic latent feature extraction through sliding windows. By integrating reference-based scaling, the framework ensures continuity across successive windows and generalizes effectively across subjects. This design improves spatial-temporal-spectral resolution (mean PSD correlation &gt;= 0.95; mean spectrogram RV-Coefficient &gt;= 0.85), reduces total weights by ~45% to mitigate overfitting, and maintains computational efficiency for robust, real-time EEG preprocessing in neurophysiological and BCI applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02848v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shantanu Sarkar, Piotr Nabrzyski, Saurabh Prasad, Jose Luis Contreras-Vidal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking ResNet for Short-Term Hypoglycemia Classification with DiaData</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Individualized therapy is driven forward by medical data analysis, which provides insight into the patient's context. In particular, for Type 1 Diabetes (T1D), which is an autoimmune disease, relationships between demographics, sensor data, and context can be analyzed. However, outliers, noisy data, and small data volumes cannot provide a reliable analysis. Hence, the research domain requires large volumes of high-quality data. Moreover, missing values can lead to information loss. To address this limitation, this study improves the data quality of DiaData, an integration of 15 separate datasets containing glucose values from 2510 subjects with T1D. Notably, we make the following contributions: 1) Outliers are identified with the interquartile range (IQR) approach and treated by replacing them with missing values. 2) Small gaps ($\le$ 25 min) are imputed with linear interpolation and larger gaps ($\ge$ 30 and $&lt;$ 120 min) with Stineman interpolation. Based on a visual comparison, Stineman interpolation provides more realistic glucose estimates than linear interpolation for larger gaps. 3) After data cleaning, the correlation between glucose and heart rate is analyzed, yielding a moderate relation between 15 and 60 minutes before hypoglycemia ($\le$ 70 mg/dL). 4) Finally, a benchmark for hypoglycemia classification is provided with a state-of-the-art ResNet model. The model is trained with the Maindatabase and Subdatabase II of DiaData to classify hypoglycemia onset up to 2 hours in advance. Training with more data improves performance by 7% while using quality-refined data yields a 2-3% gain compared to raw data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02849v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JBHI.2025.3620603</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Beyza Cinar, Maria Maleshkova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECGXtract: Deep Learning-based ECG Feature Extraction for Automated CVD Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents ECGXtract, a deep learning-based approach for interpretable ECG feature extraction, addressing the limitations of traditional signal processing and black-box machine learning methods. In particular, we develop convolutional neural network models capable of extracting both temporal and morphological features with strong correlations to a clinically validated ground truth. Initially, each model is trained to extract a single feature, ensuring precise and interpretable outputs. A series of experiments is then carried out to evaluate the proposed method across multiple setups, including global versus lead-specific features, different sampling frequencies, and comparisons with other approaches such as ECGdeli. Our findings show that ECGXtract achieves robust performance across most features with a mean correlation score of 0.80 with the ground truth for global features, with lead II consistently providing the best results. For lead-specific features, ECGXtract achieves a mean correlation score of 0.822. Moreover, ECGXtract achieves superior results to the state-of-the-art open source ECGdeli as it got a higher correlation score with the ground truth in 90% of the features. Furthermore, we explore the feasibility of extracting multiple features simultaneously utilizing a single model. Semantic grouping is proved to be effective for global features, while large-scale grouping and lead-specific multi-output models show notable performance drops. These results highlight the potential of structured grouping strategies to balance the computational efficiency vs. model accuracy, paving the way for more scalable and clinically interpretable ECG feature extraction systems in limited resource settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02850v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youssif Abuzied, Hassan AbdEltawab, Abdelrhman Gaber, Tamer ElBatt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaching Low-Cost Cardiac Intelligence with Semi-Supervised Knowledge Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deploying advanced cardiac artificial intelligence for daily cardiac monitoring is hindered by its reliance on extensive medical data and high computational resources. Low-cost cardiac intelligence (LCCI) offers a promising alternative by using wearable device data, such as 1-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), but it suffers from a significant diagnostic performance gap compared to high-cost cardiac intelligence (HCCI). To bridge this gap, we propose LiteHeart, a semi-supervised knowledge distillation framework. LiteHeart introduces a region-aware distillation module to mimic how cardiologists focus on diagnostically relevant ECG regions and a cross-layer mutual information module to align the decision processes of LCCI and HCCI systems. Using a semi-supervised training strategy, LiteHeart further improves model robustness under limited supervision. Evaluated on five datasets covering over 38 cardiovascular diseases, LiteHeart substantially reduces the performance gap between LCCI and HCCI, outperforming existing methods by 4.27% to 7.10% in macro F1 score. These results demonstrate that LiteHeart significantly enhances the diagnostic capabilities of low-cost cardiac intelligence systems, paving the way for scalable, affordable, and accurate daily cardiac healthcare using wearable technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02851v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rushuang Zhou, Yuan-Ting Zhang, M. Jamal Deen, Yining Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Interactive Hybrid Ocean: Spectrum-Consistent Wave Particle-FFT Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fast Fourier Transform-based (FFT) spectral oceans are widely adopted for their efficiency and large-scale realism, but they assume global stationarity and spatial homogeneity, making it difficult to represent non-uniform seas and near-field interactions (e.g., ships and floaters). In contrast, wave particles capture local wakes and ripples, yet are costly to maintain at scale and hard to match global spectral statistics.We present a real-time interactive hybrid ocean: a global FFT background coupled with local wave-particle (WP) patch regions around interactive objects, jointly driven under a unified set of spectral parameters and dispersion. At patch boundaries, particles are injected according to the same directional spectrum as the FFT, aligning the local frequency-direction distribution with the background and matching energy density, without disturbing the far field.Our approach introduces two main innovations: (1) Hybrid ocean representation. We couple a global FFT background with local WP patches under a unified spectrum, achieving large-scale spectral consistency while supporting localized wakes and ripples.(2) Frequency-bucketed implementation. We design a particle sampling and GPU-parallel synthesis scheme based on frequency buckets, which preserves spectral energy consistency and sustains real-time interactive performance.Together, these innovations enable a unified framework that delivers both large-scale spectral realism and fine-grained interactivity in real time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02852v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengze Xue, Yu Ren, Jiacheng Hong, Run Ni, Shuangjiu Xiao, Deli Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consciousness-ECG Transformer for Conscious State Estimation System with Real-Time Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conscious state estimation is important in various medical settings, including sleep staging and anesthesia management, to ensure patient safety and optimize health outcomes. Traditional methods predominantly utilize electroencephalography (EEG), which faces challenges such as high sensitivity to noise and the requirement for controlled environments. In this study, we propose the consciousness-ECG transformer that leverages electrocardiography (ECG) signals for non-invasive and reliable conscious state estimation. Our approach employs a transformer with decoupled query attention to effectively capture heart rate variability features that distinguish between conscious and unconscious states. We implemented the conscious state estimation system with real-time monitoring and validated our system on datasets involving sleep staging and anesthesia level monitoring during surgeries. Experimental results demonstrate that our model outperforms baseline models, achieving accuracies of 0.877 on sleep staging and 0.880 on anesthesia level monitoring. Moreover, our model achieves the highest area under curve values of 0.786 and 0.895 on sleep staging and anesthesia level monitoring, respectively. The proposed system offers a practical and robust alternative to EEG-based methods, particularly suited for dynamic clinical environments. Our results highlight the potential of ECG-based consciousness monitoring to enhance patient safety and advance our understanding of conscious states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02853v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.eswa.2025.130091</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Expert Systems with Applications 299 (2026) 130091</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Young-Seok Kweon, Gi-Hwan Shin, Ji-Yong Kim, Bokyeong Ryu, Seong-Whan Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NEF-NET+: Adapting Electrocardio panorama in the wild</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional multi-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) systems capture cardiac signals from a fixed set of anatomical viewpoints defined by lead placement. However, certain cardiac conditions (e.g., Brugada syndrome) require additional, non-standard viewpoints to reveal diagnostically critical patterns that may be absent in standard leads. To systematically overcome this limitation, Nef-Net was recently introduced to reconstruct a continuous electrocardiac field, enabling virtual observation of ECG signals from arbitrary views (termed Electrocardio Panorama). Despite its promise, Nef-Net operates under idealized assumptions and faces in-the-wild challenges, such as long-duration ECG modeling, robustness to device-specific signal artifacts, and suboptimal lead placement calibration. This paper presents NEF-NET+, an enhanced framework for realistic panoramic ECG synthesis that supports arbitrary-length signal synthesis from any desired view, generalizes across ECG devices, and com- pensates for operator-induced deviations in electrode placement. These capabilities are enabled by a newly designed model architecture that performs direct view transformation, incorporating a workflow comprising offline pretraining, device calibration tuning steps as well as an on-the-fly calibration step for patient-specific adaptation. To rigorously evaluate panoramic ECG synthesis, we construct a new Electrocardio Panorama benchmark, called Panobench, comprising 5367 recordings with 48-view per subject, capturing the full spatial variability of cardiac electrical activity. Experimental results show that NEF-NET+ delivers substantial improvements over Nef-Net, yielding an increase of around 6 dB in PSNR in real-world setting. The code and Panobench will be released in a subsequent publication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02880v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zehui Zhan, Yaojun Hu, Jiajing Zhan, Wanchen Lian, Wanqing Wu, Jintai Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Internal Calibration for Temperature-Robust mmWave FMCW Radars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel internal calibration framework for Millimeter- Wave (mmWave) Frequency-Modulated Continuous-Wave (FMCW) radars to ensure robust performance under internal temperature variations, tailored for deployment in dense wireless networks. Our approach mitigates the impact of temperature-induced drifts in radar hardware, enhancing reliability. We propose a temperature compensation model that leverages internal sensor data and signal processing techniques to maintain measurement accuracy. Experimental results demonstrate improved robustness across a range of internal temperature conditions, with minimal computational overhead, ensuring scalability in dense network environments. The framework also incorporates ethical design principles, avoiding reliance on sensitive external data. The proposed scheme reduces the Pearson correlation between the amplitude of the Intermediate Frequency (IF) signal and internal temperature drift up to 84%, significantly mitigating the temperature drift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02884v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dariush Salami, Nima Bahmani, H\"useyin Yi\u{g}itler, Stephan Sigg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Narrow to Wide: Autoencoding Transformers for Ultrasound Bandwidth Recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional pulse-echo ultrasound suffers when low-cost probes deliver only narrow fractional bandwidths, elongating pulses and erasing high-frequency detail. We address this limitation by learning a data-driven mapping from band-limited to broadband spectrogram of radio-frequency (RF) lines. To this end, a variation of Tiny Vision Transform (ViT) auto-encoder is trained on simulation data using a curriculum-weighted loss. On heterogeneous speckle-cyst phantoms, the network reduces image-domain MSE by 90 percent, boosts PSNR by 6.7 dB, and raises SSIM to 0.965 compared with the narrow-band input. It also sharpens point-target rows in a completely unseen resolution phantom, demonstrating strong out-of-distribution generalisation without sacrificing frame rate or phase information. These results indicate that a purely software upgrade can endow installed narrow-band probes with broadband-like performance, potentially widening access to high-resolution ultrasound in resource-constrained settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02938v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepideh KhakzadGharamaleki, Hassan Rivaz, Brandon Helfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consensus Tracking of an Underwater Vehicle Using Weighted Harmonic Mean Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses an underwater target tracking problem in which a large number of sonobuoy sensors are deployed on a surveillance region. The region is divided into several sub-regions, where a single tracker, capable of generating track is installed. Each sonobuoy can measure the direction of arrival of acoustic signals (known as bearing angles) and communicate the measurements with the local tracker. Further, each local tracker can communicate with all other trackers, where each of them can exchange their estimate and finally a consensus is reached. We propose a weighted harmonic mean density (HMD) based tracking to reach a consensus and provide a solution for the fusion of Gaussian densities. In this approach, optimal weights are assigned by minimizing the Kullback-Leibler divergence measure. Performance of the proposed method is measured using root mean square error, percentage of track divergence, and normalized estimation error squared. Simulation results demonstrate that the optimized HMD-based fusion outperforms existing fusion methods during a distributed tracking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03130v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ved Prakash Dubey, Shovan Bhaumik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and Algorithm for Multi IRS Collaborative Localization via Hybrid Time Angle Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel multiple intelligent reflecting surfaces (IRSs) collaborative hybrid localization system, which involves deploying multiple IRSs near the target area and achieving target localization through joint time delay and angle estimation. Specifically, echo signals from all reflective elements are received by each sensor and jointly processed to estimate the time delay and angle parameters. Based on the above model, we derive the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM) for cascaded delay, Angle of Arrival (AOA), and Angle of Departure (AOD) estimation in semi passive passive models, along with the corresponding Cramer Rao Bound (CRB). To achieve precise estimation close to the CRB, we design efficient algorithms for angle and location estimation. For angle estimation, reflective signals are categorized into three cases based on their rank, with different signal preprocessing. By constructing an atomic norm set and minimizing the atomic norm, the joint angle estimation problem is transformed into a convex optimization problem, and low-complexity estimation of multiple AOA and AOD pairs is achieved using the Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM). For location estimation, we propose a three-stage localization algorithm that combines weighted least squares, total least squares, and quadratic correction to handle errors in the coefficient matrix and observation vector, thus improving accuracy. Numerical simulations validate the superiority of the proposed system, demonstrating that the system's collaboration, hybrid localization, and distributed deployment provide substantial benefits, as well as the accuracy of the proposed estimation algorithms, particularly in low signal to noise ratio (SNR) condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03133v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziheng Zhang, Wen Chen, Qingqing Wu, Haoran Qin, Zhendong Li, Qiong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal-Wireless: A Large-Scale Dataset for Sensing and Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents Multimodal-Wireless, an open-source multimodal sensing dataset designed for wireless communication research. The dataset is generated through an integrated and customizable data pipeline built upon the CARLA simulator and Sionna framework. It contains approximately 160,000 frames collected across four virtual towns, sixteen communication scenarios, and three weather conditions, encompassing multiple sensing modalities--communication channel, light detection and ranging, RGB and depth cameras, inertial measurement unit, and radar. This paper provides a comprehensive overview of the dataset, outlining its key features, overall framework, and technical implementation details. In addition, it explores potential research applications concerning communication and collaborative perception, exemplified by beam prediction using a multimodal large language model. The dataset is open in https://le-liang.github.io/mmw/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03220v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianhao Mao, Le Liang, Jie Yang, Hao Ye, Shi Jin, Geoffrey Ye Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Sensing and Communication with UAV Swarms via Decentralized Consensus ADMM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: UAV swarms can form virtual antenna arrays to exploit additional spatial degrees of freedom and enhance integrated sensing and communication (ISAC). The optimization of UAV positions is challenging due to the distributed nature of swarms and the lack of a global view at individual UAVs.
  This paper presents a new decentralized optimization framework that allows UAVs to decide their locations in parallel and reach consensus on a globally optimal swarm geometry for ISAC.
  Specifically, we derive the achievable uplink rate and Cram\'er-Rao Bound (CRB) as tractable metrics for communication and sensing, respectively.
  The UAV positions are optimized to balance maximizing the communication rate and minimizing the CRB.
  To solve this non-convex problem with coupled variables, we develop a decentralized consensus alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) algorithm, which enables the UAVs to iteratively align their local updates and reach consensus.
  The algorithm decomposes the global objective into local projection updates, proxy-assisted consensus coordination, and lightweight dual updates, ensuring scalability and consistency throughout the swarm.
  Simulations demonstrate that the proposed consensus ADMM algorithm converges rapidly with strong scalability, and that the UAV swarm significantly outperforms fixed-array baselines in both communication and sensing performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03283v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Zhai, Wei Ni, Xin Wang, Dusit Niyato, Ekram Hossain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Federated Learning with Distributed Aggregation Weight Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decentralized federated learning (DFL) is an emerging paradigm to enable edge devices collaboratively training a learning model using a device-to-device (D2D) communication manner without the coordination of a parameter server (PS). Aggregation weights, also known as mixing weights, are crucial in DFL process, and impact the learning efficiency and accuracy. Conventional design relies on a so-called central entity to collect all local information and conduct system optimization to obtain appropriate weights. In this paper, we develop a distributed aggregation weight optimization algorithm to align with the decentralized nature of DFL. We analyze convergence by quantitatively capturing the impact of the aggregation weights over decentralized communication networks. Based on the analysis, we then formulate a learning performance optimization problem by designing the aggregation weights to minimize the derived convergence bound. The optimization problem is further transformed as an eigenvalue optimization problem and solved by our proposed subgradient-based algorithm in a distributed fashion. In our algorithm, edge devices only need local information to obtain the optimal aggregation weights through local (D2D) communications, just like the learning itself. Therefore, the optimization, communication, and learning process can be all conducted in a distributed fashion, which leads to a genuinely distributed DFL system. Numerical results demonstrate the superiority of the proposed algorithm in practical DFL deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03284v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Zhai, Xiaojun Yuan, Xin Wang, Geoffrey Ye Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-Driven Terahertz Air-Ground Communications under Dynamic Atmospheric Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ever-increasing demand for ultra-high data rates in space-air-ground integrated networks (SAGINs) has rendered terahertz THz communications a promising technology owing to its exceptionally broad and continuous spectrum resources. Nevertheless, in air-ground (AG) scenarios, the high mobility of aircraft induces intense and rapidly fluctuating turbulence, leading to additional propagation loss that is often overlooked in existing studies. To bridge this gap, this paper presents an AI-empowered THz AG communication framework that explicitly models turbulence-induced attenuation through fluid dynamics and integrates it into an adaptive optimization paradigm for communication performance enhancement. Specifically, a fluid-dynamics-informed attenuation model is established to characterize aircraft-generated turbulence and quantify its impact on THz signal propagation. Building upon this model, a joint power-attitude optimization problem is formulated to adaptively allocate transmit power and adjust aircraft attitude for maximizing link capacity. The optimization problem is efficiently solved using a diffusion-based algorithm that learns the nonlinear relationship between flight configuration and turbulence-induced attenuation. Comprehensive numerical evaluations demonstrate that the turbulence-induced attenuation ranges from 18 to 28 dB under attacking angles between -10 degree and 10 degree at 0.7 Mach, verifying the pronounced impact of aircraft-induced turbulence on THz propagation. Furthermore, the proposed framework attains an average capacity of 11.241 bps/Hz, substantially outperforming existing strategies by 22.8% and 66.5%, and approaching approximately 98% of the theoretical capacity limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03290v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhao Yi, Weijun Gao, Chong Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral-Convergent Decentralized Machine Learning: Theory and Application in Space Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decentralized machine learning (DML) supports collaborative training in large-scale networks with no central server. It is sensitive to the quality and reliability of inter-device communications that result in time-varying and stochastic topologies. This paper studies the impact of unreliable communication on the convergence of DML and establishes a direct connection between the spectral properties of the mixing process and the global performance. We provide rigorous convergence guarantees under random topologies and derive bounds that characterize the impact of the expected mixing matrix's spectral properties on learning. We formulate a spectral optimization problem that minimizes the spectral radius of the expected second-order mixing matrix to enhance the convergence rate under probabilistic link failures. To solve this non-smooth spectral problem in a fully decentralized manner, we design an efficient subgradient-based algorithm that integrates Chebyshev-accelerated eigenvector estimation with local update and aggregation weight adjustment, while ensuring symmetry and stochasticity constraints without central coordination. Experiments on a realistic low Earth orbit (LEO) satellite constellation with time-varying inter-satellite link models and real-world remote sensing data demonstrate the feasibility and effectiveness of the proposed method. The method significantly improves classification accuracy and convergence efficiency compared to existing baselines, validating its applicability in satellite and other decentralized systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03291v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Zhai, Shuyan Hu, Wei Ni, Xiaojun Yuan, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UAV SAR Imaging with 5G NR OFDM Signals in NLOS Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integration of sensing and communication (ISAC) has significant potential for future wireless systems, enabling efficient spectrum utilization and novel application scenarios. In this paper, we propose a cooperative ISAC framework for synthetic aperture radar (SAR) imaging by leveraging orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) communication signals. We address the challenge of severe imaging degradation in non-line-of-sight (NLOS) environments under the QUAsi Deterministic RadIo channel GenerAtor (QuaDRiGa). To detect weak signals and eliminate false points, we develop a two-stage compressed sensing-space alternating generalized expectation maximization (CS-SAGE) scheme for high-precision scatterer localization. In stage I, orthogonal matching pursuit (OMP) is employed for coarse estimation to identify the approximate locations of dominant scatterers. Then, the SAGE algorithm in stage II performs fine estimation to accurately extract scatterer parameters. Simulation results validate the effectiveness of the proposed cooperative ISAC framework, and provide valuable insights for practical system design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03292v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiuyuan Yang, Cunhua Pan, Ruidong Li, Zhenkun Zhang, Hong Ren, Changhong Wang, Jiangzhou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-RAN Advanced: From a Network Cooperation Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03302v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Future mobile networks in the sixth generation (6G) are poised for a paradigm shift from conventional communication services toward comprehensive information services, driving the evolution of radio access network (RAN) architectures toward enhanced cooperation, intelligence, and service orientation. Building upon the concept of centralized, collaborative, cloud, and clean RAN (C-RAN), this article proposes a novel cooperative, intelligent, and service-based RAN (CIS-RAN) architecture. Focusing on cooperation, CIS-RAN extends the traditional cooperative communication paradigm by further integrating cooperative sensing and cooperative artificial intelligence (AI). To improve both performance and effectiveness across diverse application scenarios, CIS-RAN enhances network cooperation throughout the entire process of acquisition, transmission, and processing, thereby enabling efficient information acquisition, diverse cooperative interactions, and intelligent fusion decision-making. Key technologies are discussed, with network cooperative multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) examined as a case study, demonstrating superior performance over traditional architectures, as demonstrated by numerical results. Future research directions are outlined, emphasizing the continued exploration and advancement of the CIS-RAN architecture, particularly in enhancing network cooperation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03302v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyun Wang, Yutong Zhang, Sen Wang, Sun Qi, Hanning Wang, Qixing Wang, Jing Jin, Jiwei He, Nan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Analysis of Wireless-Powered Pinching Antenna Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pinching antenna system (PAS) serves as a groundbreaking paradigm that enhances wireless communications by flexibly adjusting the position of pinching antenna (PA) and establishing a strong line-of-sight (LoS) link, thereby reducing the free-space path loss. This paper introduces the concept of wireless-powered PAS, and investigates the reliability of wireless-powered PAS to explore the advantages of PA in improving the performance of wireless-powered communication (WPC) system. In addition, we derive the closed-form expressions of outage probability and ergodic rate for the practical lossy waveguide case and ideal lossless waveguide case, respectively, and analyze the optimal deployment of waveguides and user to provide valuable insights for guiding their deployments. The results show that an increase in the absorption coefficient and in the dimensions of the user area leads to higher in-waveguide and free-space propagation losses, respectively, which in turn increase the outage probability and reduce the ergodic rate of the wireless-powered PAS. However, the performance of wireless-powered PAS is severely affected by the absorption coefficient and the waveguide length, e.g., under conditions of high absorption coefficient and long waveguide, the outage probability of wireless-powered PAS is even worse than that of traditional WPC system. While the ergodic rate of wireless-powered PAS is better than that of traditional WPC system under conditions of high absorption coefficient and long waveguide. Interestingly, the wireless-powered PAS has the optimal time allocation factor and optimal distance between power station (PS) and access point (AP) to minimize the outage probability or maximize the ergodic rate. Moreover, the system performance of PS and AP separated at the optimal distance between PS and AP is superior to that of PS and AP integrated into a hybrid access point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03401v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunrui Cao, Jingyu Chen, Panagiotis D. Diamantoulakis, Lei Zhou, Xingwang Li, Yuanwei Liu, George K. Karagiannidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Modified Pulse and Design Framework to Halve the Complexity of OFDM Spectral Shaping Techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03465v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) is a widespread modulation but suffers from high out-of-band emissions (OOBE). Spectral shaping strategies such as precoding, active interference cancellation (AIC) and time-domain methods are effective at reducing the OOBE but entail optimization procedures and real-time implementation costs which might be considerable. This letter proposes a modification of the conventional OFDM waveform aimed at reducing the cost associated to many of the state-of-theart spectral shaping techniques and sets a framework for future works that want to benefit from the same reduction. This approach may reduce both the number of coefficients involved in the optimization and the number of products of its implementation by up to 50%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03465v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LCOMM.2024.3432155</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Communications Letters, vol. 28, no. 9, pp. 2146-2150, Sept. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Javier Gim\'enez, Jos\'e A. Cort\'es, Francisco Javier Ca\~nete, Eduardo Martos-Naya, Luis D\'iez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Multi-Reference-Point Modeling Framework for Monostatic Background Channel: Toward 3GPP ISAC Standardization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integrated Sensing and Communication (ISAC) has been identified as a key 6G application by ITU and 3GPP. A realistic, standard-compatible channel model is essential for ISAC system design. To characterize the impact of Sensing Targets (STs), 3GPP defines ISAC channel as a combination of target and background channels, comprising multipath components related to STs and those originating solely from the environment, respectively. Although the background channel does not carry direct ST information, its accurate modeling is critical for evaluating sensing performance, especially in complex environments. Existing communication standards characterize propagation between separated transmitter (Tx) and receiver (Rx). However, modeling background channels in the ISAC monostatic mode, where the Tx and Rx are co-located, remains a pressing challenge. In this paper, we firstly conduct ISAC monostatic background channel measurements for an indoor scenario at 28 GHz. Realistic channel parameters are extracted, revealing pronounced single-hop propagation and discrete multipath distribution. Inspired by these properties, a novel stochastic model is proposed to characterizing the ISAC monostatic background channel as the superposition of sub-channels between the monostatic Tx&amp;Rx and multiple communication Rx-like Reference Points (RPs). This model is compatible with standardizations, and a 3GPP-extended implementation framework is introduced. Finally, a genetic algorithm-based method is proposed to extract the optimal number and placement of multi-RPs. The optimization approach and modeling framework are validated by comparing measured and simulated channel parameters. Results demonstrate that the proposed model effectively captures monostatic background channel characteristics, addresses a critical gap in ISAC channel modeling, and supports 6G standardization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03487v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yameng Liu, Jianhua Zhang, Yuxiang Zhang, Zhiqiang Yuan, Chuangxin Jiang, Junchen Liu, Wei Hong, Yingyang Li, Yan Li, Guangyi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Cooperative User Tracking for Distributed Integrated Sensing and Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) becomes an integral part of 6G networks, distributed ISAC (DISAC) is expected to enhance both sensing and communication performance through its decentralized architecture. This paper presents a complete framework to address the challenge of cooperative user tracking in DISAC systems. By incorporating a global probability hypothesis density (PHD) filter and a field-of-view-aware access point (AP) management strategy, the framework enables accurate user tracking using radio signals while optimizing AP scheduling. In addition, a real-world distributed MIMO channel measurement campaign is performed to evaluate the effectiveness of the framework. The results demonstrate that a centimeter-level root mean-square trajectory error can be achieved. Furthermore, the results show that it is not necessary to keep APs active at all times to maintain high tracking accuracy, indicating the need for robust and efficient AP management. These findings provide valuable insight into practical deployments and further development of cooperative user tracking techniques in DISAC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03612v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingjie Xu, Xuesong Cai, Michiel Sandra, Sara Willhammar, Fredrik Tufvesson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PrivyWave: Privacy-Aware Wireless Sensing of Heartbeat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02993v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wireless sensing technologies can now detect heartbeats using radio frequency and acoustic signals, raising significant privacy concerns. Existing privacy solutions either protect from all sensing systems indiscriminately preventing any utility or operate post-data collection, failing to enable selective access where authorized devices can monitor while unauthorized ones cannot. We present a key-based physical obfuscation system, PrivyWave, that addresses this challenge by generating controlled decoy heartbeat signals at cryptographically-determined frequencies. Unauthorized sensors receive a mixture of real and decoy signals that are indistinguishable without the secret key, while authorized sensors use the key to filter out decoys and recover accurate measurements. Our evaluation with 13 participants demonstrates effective protection across both sensing modalities: for mmWave radar, unauthorized sensors show 21.3 BPM mean absolute error while authorized sensors maintain a much smaller 5.8 BPM; for acoustic sensing, unauthorized error increases to 42.0 BPM while authorized sensors achieve 9.7 BPM. The system operates across multiple sensing modalities without per-modality customization and provides cryptographic obfuscation guarantees. Performance benchmarks show robust protection across different distances (30-150 cm), orientations (120{\deg} field of view), and diverse indoor environments, establishing physical-layer obfuscation as a viable approach for selective privacy in pervasive health monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02993v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixuan Gao, Tanvir Ahmed, Zekun Chang, Thijs Roumen, Rajalakshmi Nandakumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Articulatory Coordination as a Biomarker for Schizophrenia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Advances in artificial intelligence (AI) and deep learning have improved diagnostic capabilities in healthcare, yet limited interpretability continues to hinder clinical adoption. Schizophrenia, a complex disorder with diverse symptoms including disorganized speech and social withdrawal, demands tools that capture symptom severity and provide clinically meaningful insights beyond binary diagnosis. Here, we present an interpretable framework that leverages articulatory speech features through eigenspectra difference plots and a weighted sum with exponential decay (WSED) to quantify vocal tract coordination. Eigenspectra plots effectively distinguished complex from simpler coordination patterns, and WSED scores reliably separated these groups, with ambiguity confined to a narrow range near zero. Importantly, WSED scores correlated not only with overall BPRS severity but also with the balance between positive and negative symptoms, reflecting more complex coordination in subjects with pronounced positive symptoms and the opposite trend for stronger negative symptoms. This approach offers a transparent, severity-sensitive biomarker for schizophrenia, advancing the potential for clinically interpretable speech-based assessment tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03084v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gowtham Premananth, Carol Espy-Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speech-Based Prioritization for Schizophrenia Intervention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03086v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Millions of people suffer from mental health conditions, yet many remain undiagnosed or receive delayed care due to limited clinical resources and labor-intensive assessment methods. While most machine-assisted approaches focus on diagnostic classification, estimating symptom severity is essential for prioritizing care, particularly in resource-constrained settings. Speech-based AI provides a scalable alternative by enabling automated, continuous, and remote monitoring, reducing reliance on subjective self-reports and time-consuming evaluations. In this paper, we introduce a speech-based model for pairwise comparison of schizophrenia symptom severity, leveraging articulatory and acoustic features. These comparisons are used to generate severity rankings via the Bradley-Terry model. Our approach outperforms previous regression-based models on ranking-based metrics, offering a more effective solution for clinical triage and prioritization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03086v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gowtham Premananth, Philip Resnik, Sonia Bansal, Deanna L. Kelly, Carol Espy-Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Computational Approach to Analyzing Disrupted Language in Schizophrenia: Integrating Surprisal and Coherence Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03089v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Language disruptions are one of the well-known effects of schizophrenia symptoms. They are often manifested as disorganized speech and impaired discourse coherence. These abnormalities in spontaneous language production reflect underlying cognitive disturbances and have the potential to serve as objective markers for symptom severity and diagnosis of schizophrenia. This study focuses on how these language disruptions can be characterized in terms of two computational linguistic measures: surprisal and semantic coherence. By computing surprisal and semantic coherence of language using computational models, this study investigates how they differ between subjects with schizophrenia and healthy controls. Furthermore, this study provides further insight into how language disruptions in terms of these linguistic measures change with varying degrees of schizophrenia symptom severity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03089v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gowtham Premananth, Carol Espy-Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Noise Control Method Using Time Domain Neural Networks for Path Decoupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In decentralized active noise control (ANC) systems, crosstalk between multichannel secondary sources and error microphones significantly degrades control accuracy. Moreover, prefiltering reference signals in filtered-x (Fx) type algorithms may further introduce modeling errors. A theoretical analysis of the Fx-based decentralized control algorithm was performed, which reveals how prefiltering and crosstalk affect the control performance. Then, a hybrid method combining fixed-value neural networks and adaptive strategies was proposed for efficient decentralized ANC. The adaptive filter models the primary path of its own channel online using the least mean square (LMS) algorithm while the neural network (named DecNet) is used for secondary paths inverting and decoupling. The hybrid DecNet-LMS algorithm was implemented in the time domain to guarantee causality and avoid latency. Simulation results with measured acoustic paths show that the proposed method outperforms the existing ANC algorithms using either traditional adaptive filters or neural network-based fixed-coefficient methods under different acoustic conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03162v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijing Chu, Qinxuan Xiang, Sipei Zhao, Ming Wu, Y. Zhao, Guangzheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAPEX: Fractional Amplitude-Phase Expressor for Robust Cross-Subject Seizure Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03263v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise, generalizable subject-agnostic seizure prediction (SASP) remains a fundamental challenge due to the intrinsic complexity and significant spectral variability of electrophysiological signals across individuals and recording modalities. We propose FAPEX, a novel architecture that introduces a learnable fractional neural frame operator (FrNFO) for adaptive time-frequency decomposition. Unlike conventional models that exhibit spectral bias toward low frequencies, our FrNFO employs fractional-order convolutions to capture both high and low-frequency dynamics, achieving approximately 10% improvement in F1-score and sensitivity over state-of-the-art baselines. The FrNFO enables the extraction of instantaneous phase and amplitude representations that are particularly informative for preictal biomarker discovery and enhance out-of-distribution generalization. FAPEX further integrates structural state-space modeling and channelwise attention, allowing it to handle heterogeneous electrode montages. Evaluated across 12 benchmarks spanning species (human, rat, dog, macaque) and modalities (Scalp-EEG, SEEG, ECoG, LFP), FAPEX consistently outperforms 23 supervised and 10 self-supervised baselines under nested cross-validation, with gains of up to 15% in sensitivity on complex cross-domain scenarios. It further demonstrates superior performance in several external validation cohorts. To our knowledge, these establish FAPEX as the first epilepsy model to show consistent superiority in SASP, offering a promising solution for discovering epileptic biomarker evidence supporting the existence of a distinct and identifiable preictal state and clinical translation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03263v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruizhe Zheng, Lingyan Mao, Dingding Han, Tian Luo, Yi Wang, Jing Ding, Yuguo Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lightwave Power Transfer-Enabled Underwater Optical ISAC Systems under Ship Attitude Variation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03366v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a lightwave power transfer-enabled underwater optical integrated sensing and communication (O-ISAC) system, where an access point (AP) mounted on a seasurface ship transmits lightwave signals to two nodes, namely ($i$) a seabed sensor that harvests energy and transmits uplink information to the AP, and ($ii$) a sensing target whose position is estimated by the AP using an array of pinhole cameras. To capture practical deployment conditions, the ship attitude variation is modeled through its roll, pitch, and yaw angles, each following a Gaussian distribution under low-to-moderate sea states. Closed-form approximations are derived for the mean squared error (MSE) of target localization and the achievable uplink data rate. Analytical and simulation results demonstrate excellent agreement, validating the proposed models and derived expressions, while revealing the fundamental communication-sensing tradeoff in the O-ISAC system. The results further provide valuable design insights, including the optimal camera placement on the ship to minimize localization error, achieving a minimum MSE of $10^{-2}$ $\text{m}^2$ with multiple cameras under roll, pitch, and yaw angle variation of $10^{\circ}$, and the optimal harvest-use ratio of $0.55$ for the considered setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03366v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kapila W. S. Palitharathna, Constantinos Psomas, Ioannis Krikidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Beamforming with Doppler-Aware Sparse Attention for High Mobility Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03632v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Beamforming has significance for enhancing spectral efficiency and mitigating interference in multi-antenna wireless systems, facilitating spatial multiplexing and diversity in dense and high mobility scenarios. Traditional beamforming techniques such as zero-forcing beamforming (ZFBF) and minimum mean square error (MMSE) beamforming experience performance deterioration under adverse channel conditions. Deep learning-based beamforming offers an alternative with nonlinear mappings from channel state information (CSI) to beamforming weights by improving robustness against dynamic channel environments. Transformer-based models are particularly effective due to their ability to model long-range dependencies across time and frequency. However, their quadratic attention complexity limits scalability in large OFDM grids. Recent studies address this issue through sparse attention mechanisms that reduce complexity while maintaining expressiveness, yet often employ patterns that disregard channel dynamics, as they are not specifically designed for wireless communication scenarios. In this work, we propose a Doppler-aware Sparse Neural Network Beamforming (Doppler-aware Sparse NNBF) model that incorporates a channel-adaptive sparse attention mechanism in a multi-user single-input multiple-output (MU-SIMO) setting. The proposed sparsity structure is configurable along 2D time-frequency axes based on channel dynamics and is theoretically proven to ensure full connectivity within p hops, where p is the number of attention heads. Simulation results under urban macro (UMa) channel conditions show that Doppler-aware Sparse NNBF significantly outperforms both a fixed-pattern baseline, referred to as Standard Sparse NNBF, and conventional beamforming techniques ZFBF and MMSE beamforming in high mobility scenarios, while maintaining structured sparsity with a controlled number of attended keys per query.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03632v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cemil Vahapoglu, Timothy J. O'Shea, Wan Liu, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Sampling for Scalable and Expressive Graph Neural Networks on Homophilic Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16593v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) excel in many graph machine learning tasks but face challenges when scaling to large networks. GNN transferability allows training on smaller graphs and applying the model to larger ones, but existing methods often rely on random subsampling, leading to disconnected subgraphs and reduced model expressivity. We propose a novel graph sampling algorithm that leverages feature homophily to preserve graph structure. By minimizing the trace of the data correlation matrix, our method better preserves the graph Laplacian trace -- a proxy for the graph connectivity -- than random sampling, while achieving lower complexity than spectral methods. Experiments on citation networks show improved performance in preserving Laplacian trace and GNN transferability compared to random sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16593v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haolin Li, Haoyu Wang, Luana Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Positioning, Beamforming, and Power Allocation in Full-Duplex MIMO with Position-Reconfigurable Antenna Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09845v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a multi-user (MU) full-duplex (FD) multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) communication system, in which the base station transceiver is equipped with transmit and receive position reconfigurable antennas (PRAs) to mitigate both MU-interference (MUI) and self-interference (SI) while enhancing the desired signal quality. We first formulate a joint design of beamforming, transmit power allocation, and antenna placement to maximize the weighted sum-rate of the considered PRA-based MU-FD-MIMO system under the constraints on reconfigurable region size, minimum antenna spacing, and transmit power. To address this highly non-convex problem, we then propose an alternating optimization (AO) framework that decomposes the original problem into subproblems and solves them iteratively. In particular, fractional programming techniques are used to separate the optimization variables from the logarithmic and ratio terms, while the block successive upper bound minimization method handles the non-convexity of PRA placement. Simulation results confirm a significant performance gain when integrating PRAs into the MU-FD-MIMO system and demonstrate the advantage of the proposed optimization framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09845v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengjie Zhao, Yuanzhe Gong, Tho Le-Ngoc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Analysis of Multipath Characteristics in Indoor Distributed Massive MIMO Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12258v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Distributed multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO), also known as cell-free massive MIMO, has emerged as a promising technology for sixth-generation (6G) wireless networks. This letter introduces an indoor channel measurement campaign designed to explore the behavior of multipath components (MPCs) in distributed MIMO channels. Fully coherent channels were measured between eight distributed uniform planar arrays (128 elements in total) and a 12-meter user equipment route. A method is introduced to determine the order (single- or multi-bounce) of MPC interaction by leveraging map information and MPC parameters. In addition, a Kalman filter-based framework is used for identifying the MPC interaction mechanisms (reflection or scattering/diffraction/mixed). Finally, a comprehensive MPC-level characterization is performed based on the measured channels, including the significance of single-bounce MPCs, common single-bounce MPCs, spherical wavefront features, birth-and-death processes of the MPCs, and spatial distribution of reflections. The findings serve as a valuable reference for understanding the propagation behavior of MPCs, which is necessary for future modeling of indoor distributed MIMO channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12258v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LAWP.2025.3598631</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Antennas and Wireless Propagation Letters, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yingjie Xu, Xuesong Cai, Sara Willhammar, Fredrik Tufvesson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aerial Active STAR-RIS-assisted Satellite-Terrestrial Covert Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An integration of satellites and terrestrial networks is crucial for enhancing performance of next generation communication systems. However, the networks are hindered by the long-distance path loss and security risks in dense urban environments. In this work, we propose a satellite-terrestrial covert communication system assisted by the aerial active simultaneous transmitting and reflecting reconfigurable intelligent surface (AASTAR-RIS) to improve the channel capacity while ensuring the transmission covertness. Specifically, we first derive the minimal detection error probability (DEP) under the worst condition that the Warden has perfect channel state information (CSI). Then, we formulate an AASTAR-RIS-assisted satellite-terrestrial covert communication optimization problem (ASCCOP) to maximize the sum of the fair channel capacity for all ground users while meeting the strict covert constraint, by jointly optimizing the trajectory and active beamforming of the AASTAR-RIS. Due to the challenges posed by the complex and high-dimensional state-action spaces as well as the need for efficient exploration in dynamic environments, we propose a generative deterministic policy gradient (GDPG) algorithm, which is a generative deep reinforcement learning (DRL) method to solve the ASCCOP. Concretely, the generative diffusion model (GDM) is utilized as the policy representation of the algorithm to enhance the exploration process by generating diverse and high-quality samples through a series of denoising steps. Moreover, we incorporate an action gradient mechanism to accomplish the policy improvement of the algorithm, which refines the better state-action pairs through the gradient ascent. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed approach significantly outperforms important benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16146v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuang Zhang, Geng Sun, Jiahui Li, Jiacheng Wang, Ruichen Zhang, Dusit Niyato, Shiwen Mao, Tony Q. S. Quek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Robust Stationary Crowd Counting with Commodity WiFi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14309v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel method for estimating the size of seated crowds with commodity WiFi signals, by leveraging natural body fidgeting behaviors as a passive sensing cue. Departing from prior binary fidget representations, our approach leverages the bandwidth of the received signal as a finer-grained and robust indicator of crowd counts. More specifically, we propose a mathematical model that relates the probability density function (PDF) of the signal bandwidth to the crowd size, using a principled derivation based on the PDF of an individual's fidget-induced bandwidth. To characterize the individual fidgeting PDF, we use publicly available online videos, each of a seated individual, from which we extract body motion profiles using vision techniques, followed by a speed-to-bandwidth conversion inspired by Carson's Rule from analog FM radio design. Finally, to enhance robustness in real-world deployments where unrelated motions may occur nearby, we further introduce an anomaly detection module that filters out non-fidget movements. We validate our system through 42 experiments across two indoor environments with crowd sizes up to and including 13 people, achieving a mean absolute error of 1.04 and a normalized mean square error of 0.15, with an average convergence time of 51 seconds, significantly reducing the convergence time as compared to the state of the art. Additional simulation results demonstrate scalability to larger crowd sizes. Overall, our results show that our pipeline enables fast, robust, and highly accurate counting of seated crowds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14309v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mert Torun, Alireza Parsay, Yasamin Mostofi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RIS-Assisted 3D Spherical Splatting for Object Composition Visualization using Detection Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02573v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The pursuit of immersive and structurally aware multimedia experiences has intensified interest in sensing modalities that reconstruct objects beyond the limits of visible light. Conventional optical pipelines degrade under occlusion or low illumination, motivating the use of radio-frequency (RF) sensing, whose electromagnetic waves penetrate materials and encode both geometric and compositional information. Yet, uncontrolled multipath propagation restricts reconstruction accuracy. Recent advances in Programmable Wireless Environments (PWEs) mitigate this limitation by enabling software-defined manipulation of propagation through Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces (RISs), thereby providing controllable illumination diversity. Building on this capability, this work introduces a PWE-driven RF framework for three-dimensional object reconstruction using material-aware spherical primitives. The proposed approach combines RIS-enabled field synthesis with a Detection Transformer (DETR) that infers spatial and material parameters directly from extracted RF features. Simulation results confirm the framework's ability to approximate object geometries and classify material composition with an overall accuracy of 79.35%, marking an initial step toward programmable and physically grounded RF-based 3D object composition visualization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02573v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasios T. Sotiropoulos, Stavros Tsimpoukis, Dimitrios Tyrovolas, Sotiris Ioannidis, Panagiotis D. Diamantoulakis, George K. Karagiannidis, Christos K. Liaskos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Spectrum Linking: Identification of Governing PDE via Koopman-Chebyshev Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23078v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A numerical framework is proposed for identifying partial differential equations (PDEs) governing dynamical systems directly from their observation data using Chebyshev polynomial approximation. In contrast to data-driven approaches such as dynamic mode decomposition (DMD), which approximate the Koopman operator without a clear connection to differential operators, the proposed method constructs finite-dimensional Koopman matrices by projecting the dynamics onto a Chebyshev basis, thereby capturing both differential and nonlinear terms. This establishes a numerical link between the Koopman and differential operators. Numerical experiments on benchmark dynamical systems confirm the accuracy and efficiency of the approach, underscoring its potential for interpretable operator learning. The framework also lays a foundation for future integration with symbolic regression, enabling the construction of explicit mathematical models directly from data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23078v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phonepaserth Sisaykeo, Shogo Muramatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
