<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Actor DDPG for Airborne STAR-RIS Assisted Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study departs from the prevailing assumption of independent Transmission and Reflection Coefficients (TRC) in Airborne Simultaneous Transmit and Reflect Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (STAR-RIS) research. Instead, we explore a novel multi-user downlink communication system that leverages a UAV-mounted STAR-RIS (Aerial-STAR) incorporating a coupled TRC phase shift model. Our key contributions include the joint optimization of UAV trajectory, active beamforming vectors at the base station, and passive RIS TRCs to enhance communication efficiency, while considering UAV energy constraints. We design the TRC as a combination of discrete and continuous actions, and propose a novel Dual Actor Deep Deterministic Policy Gradient (DA-DDPG) algorithm. The algorithm relies on two separate actor networks for high-dimensional hybrid action space. We also propose a novel harmonic mean index (HFI)-based reward function to ensure communication fairness amongst users. For comprehensive analysis, we study the impact of RIS size on UAV aerodynamics showing that it increases drag and energy demand. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed DA-DDPG algorithm outperforms conventional DDPG and DQN-based solutions by 24% and 97%, respectively, in accumulated reward. Three-dimensional UAV trajectory optimization achieves 28% higher communication efficiency compared to two-dimensional and altitude optimization. The HFI based reward function provides 41% lower QoS denial rates as compared to other benchmarks. The mobile Aerial-STAR system shows superior performance over fixed deployed counterparts, with the coupled phase STAR-RIS outperforming dual Transmit/Reflect RIS and conventional RIS setups. These findings highlight the potential of Aerial-STAR systems and the effectiveness of our proposed DA-DDPG approach in optimizing their performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13328v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danish Rizvi, David Boyle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environment Reconstruction in Multi-Bounce Channels with Array Partial Blockage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extremely-large antenna arrays (ELAA) are important in applications requiring high angular resolution. However, a prominent issue is the spatial non-stationary (SNS) channels due to partial blockage to the ELAA. In this paper, we address the scatterer localization and subsequent environment reconstruction considering partially blocked SNS channels. Specifically, the SNS effects are parametrically modeled through spatial-varying amplitudes with sparsity. Based on the established signal model, the graph-based dictionary-aided multi-bounce space-alternating generalized expectation-maximization (GM-SAGE) algorithm is applied to estimate the channel parameters and the channel sparsity is empirically detected along with amplitude estimation. To validate the proposed approach, we generate multi-bounce paths through ray tracing (RT) simulations, where the SNS channels caused by partial blockage could be configured flexibly. The simulation results demonstrate the robustness of the proposed approach in dealing with the SNS channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13559v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Liu, Linlong Wu, Xuesong Cai, M. R. Bhavani Shankar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Single-Snapshot Harmonic Recovery with 2D Sparse Arrays using BCCB Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce an efficient implementation of sparse recovery methods for the problem of harmonic estimation with 2D sparse arrays using a single snapshot. By imposing a uniformity constraint on the harmonic grids of the subdictionaries used in the sparse recovery problem, in addition to a mild constraint on the array topology that consists in having the elements lie on a grid specified in half-wavelength units, we show that the Gram matrices that appear in these sparse recovery methods exhibit a block-circulant with circulant blocks (BCCB) structure. The BCCB structure is then exploited to reduce the computational complexity of the matrix-vector products that appear in these methods through the use of 2D fast Fourier transforms (FFT) from O((L1L2)^2) down to O(L1L2 log(L1L2)) operations per iterations, where L1, L2 are the lengths of the subdictionaries used for estimating the harmonics in the first and second dimension, respectively. We experimentally verify the proposed implementation using the iterative shrinkage thresholding algorithm (ISTA), the fast iterative shrinkage-thresholding algorithm (FISTA), and the alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) where we observe improvements</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13592v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youval Klioui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GNSS Jamming and Spoofing Monitoring Using Low-Cost COTS Receivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS) is increasingly vulnerable to radio frequency interference (RFI), including jamming and spoofing, which threaten the integrity of navigation and timing services. This paper presents a methodology for detecting and classifying RFI events using low-cost commercial off-the-shelf (COTS) GNSS receivers. By combining carrier-to-noise ratio (C/N0) measurements with a calibrated received power metric, a two-dimensional detection space is constructed to identify and distinguish nominal, jammed, spoofed, and blocked signal conditions. The method is validated through both controlled jamming tests in Norway and real-world deployments in Poland, and the Southeast Mediterranean which have experienced such conditions. Results demonstrate that COTS-based detection, when properly calibrated, offers a viable and effective approach for GNSS RFI monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13600v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Argyris Kriezis, Yu-Hsuan Chen, Dennis Akos, Sherman Lo, Todd Walter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Validation of the Latent Optimally Partitioned-$\ell_2/\ell_1$ Penalty with Application to Angular Power Spectrum Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates that, in both theory and practice, the latent optimally partitioned (LOP)-$\ell_2/\ell_1$ penalty is effective for exploiting block-sparsity without the knowledge of the concrete block structure. More precisely, we first present a novel theoretical result showing that the optimized block partition in the LOP-$\ell_2/\ell_1$ penalty satisfy a condition required for accurate recovery of block-sparse signals. Motivated by this result, we present a new application of the LOP-$\ell_2/\ell_1$ penalty to estimation of angular power spectrum, which is block-sparse with unknown block partition, in MIMO communication systems. Numerical simulations show that the proposed use of block-sparsity with the LOP-$\ell_2/\ell_1$ penalty significantly improves the estimation accuracy of the angular power spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13745v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Kuroda, Renato Luis Garrido Cavalcante, Masahiro Yukawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Quantization-Aware Neural Receivers: Beyond Post-Training Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As wireless communication systems advance toward Sixth Generation (6G) Radio Access Networks (RAN), Deep Learning (DL)-based neural receivers are emerging as transformative solutions for Physical Layer (PHY) processing, delivering superior Block Error Rate (BLER) performance compared to traditional model-based approaches. Practical deployment on resource-constrained hardware, however, requires efficient quantization to reduce latency, energy, and memory without sacrificing reliability. We extend Post-Training Quantization (PTQ) baselines with Quantization-Aware Training (QAT), which incorporates low-precision simulation during training for robustness at ultra-low bitwidths. Our study applies QAT/PTQ to a neural receiver architecture and evaluates across 3GPP Clustered Delay Line (CDL)-B/D channels in LoS and NLoS environments at user velocities up to 40 m/s. Results show that 4-bit and 8-bit QAT models achieve BLERs similar to that of FP32 models at 10% target BLER. QAT models are also shown to outperform PTQ models by up to 3 dB, and yield 8x compression. These results demonstrate that QAT is a key enabler of low-complexity and latency-constrained inference at the PHY layer, facilitating real-time processing in 6G edge devices</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13786v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>SaiKrishna Saketh Yellapragada, Esa Ollila, Mario Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domino: Dominant Path-based Compensation for Hardware Impairments in Modern WiFi Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: WiFi sensing faces a critical reliability challenge due to hardware-induced RF distortions, especially with modern, market-dominant WiFi cards supporting 802.11ac/ax protocols. These cards employ sensitive automatic gain control and separate RF chains, introducing complex and dynamic distortions that render existing compensation methods ineffective. In this paper, we introduce Domino, a new framework that transforms channel state information (CSI) into channel impulse response (CIR) and leverages it for precise distortion compensation. Domino is built on the key insight that hardware-induced distortions impact all signal paths uniformly, allowing the dominant static path to serve as a reliable reference for effective compensation through delay-domain processing. Real-world respiration monitoring experiments show that Domino achieves at least 2x higher mean accuracy over existing methods, maintaining robust performance with a median error below 0.24 bpm, even using a single antenna in both direct line-of-sight and obstructed scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13807v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiqi Kong, He Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow Matching-Based Active Learning for Radio Map Construction with Low-Altitude UAVs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The employment of unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) in the lowaltitude economy necessitates precise and real-time radio maps for reliable communication and safe navigation. However, constructing such maps is hindered by the infeasibility of exhaustive measurements due to UAVs' limited flight endurance. To address this, we propose a novel active learning framework for low-altitude radio map construction based on limited measurements. First, a Plug-and-Play (PnP)-refined flow matching algorithm is introduced, which leverages flow matching as a powerful generative prior within a PnP scheme to reconstruct high-fidelity radio maps. Second, the generative nature of flow matching is exploited to quantify uncertainty by generating an ensemble of radio maps and computing the location-wise variance. The resulting uncertainty map guides a multi-objective candidate selection and then a trajectory is planned via utility-aware path search (UAPS), directing the UAV to the most informative locations while taking travel costs into account. Simulation results demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms the baselines, achieving more than a 70% reduction in normalized mean squared error (NMSE).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13822v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Sun, Shicong Liu, Xianghao Yu, Ying Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FFT-Free PAPR Reduction Methods for OFDM Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose two low-complexity peak to average power ratio(PAPR) reduction algorithms for orthogonal frequency division multiplexing(OFDM) signals. The main content is as follows: First, a non-convex optimization model is established by minimizing the signal distortion power. Then, a customized alternating direction method of multipliers(ADMM) algorithm is proposed to solve the problem, named time domain ADMM(T-ADMM) along with an improved version called T-ADMM with constrain update(TCU-ADMM). In the algorithms, all subproblems can be solved analytically, and each iteration has linear computational complexity. These algorithms circumvents the challenges posed by repeated fast Fourier transform(FFT) and inverse FFT(IFFT) operations in traditional PAPR reduction algorithms. Additionally, we prove that the T-ADMM algorithm is theoretically guaranteed convergent if proper parameter is chosen. Finally, simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13851v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Su, Jiangtao Wang, Yongchao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface-Assisted Multiuser Tracking and Signal Detection in ISAC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the multiuser tracking and signal detection problem in integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) systems with the assistance of reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs). Due to the diverse and high user mobility, the tracking and signal detection performance can be significantly deteriorated without choreographed user state (position and velocity) updating principle. To tackle this challenge, we manage to establish a comprehensive probabilistic signal model to characterize the interdependencies among user states, transmit signals, and received signals during the tracking procedure. Based on the Bayesian problem formulation, we further propose a novel hybrid variational message passing algorithm for the online estimation of user states, which can iteratively update the posterior probabilities of user states during each tracking frame with computational efficiency. Numerical results are provided to demonstrate that the proposed algorithm can significantly improve both of the tracking and signal detection performance over the representative Bayesian estimation counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13940v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weifeng Zhu, Junyuan Gao, Shuowen Zhang, Liang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive and robust smartphone-based step detection in multiple sclerosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Background: Many attempts to validate gait pipelines that process sensor data to detect gait events have focused on the detection of initial contacts only in supervised settings using a single sensor. Objective: To evaluate the performance of a gait pipeline in detecting initial/final contacts using a step detection algorithm adaptive to different test settings, smartphone wear locations, and gait impairment levels. Methods: In GaitLab (ISRCTN15993728), healthy controls (HC) and people with multiple sclerosis (PwMS; Expanded Disability Status Scale 0.0-6.5) performed supervised Two-Minute Walk Test [2MWT] (structured in-lab overground and treadmill 2MWT) during two on-site visits carrying six smartphones and unsupervised walking activities (structured and unstructured real-world walking) daily for 10-14 days using a single smartphone. Reference gait data were collected with a motion capture system or Gait Up sensors. The pipeline's performance in detecting initial/final contacts was evaluated through F1 scores and absolute temporal error with respect to reference measurement systems. Results: We studied 35 HC and 93 PwMS. Initial/final contacts were accurately detected across all smartphone wear locations. Median F1 scores for initial/final contacts on in-lab 2MWT were &gt;=98.2%/96.5% in HC and &gt;=98.5%/97.7% in PwMS. F1 scores remained high on structured (HC: 100% [0.3%]/100% [0.2%]; PwMS: 99.5% [1.9%]/99.4% [2.5%]) and unstructured real-world walking (HC: 97.8% [2.6%]/97.8% [2.8%]; PwMS: 94.4% [6.2%]/94.0% [6.5%]). Median temporal errors were &lt;=0.08 s. Neither age, sex, disease severity, walking aid use, nor setting (outdoor/indoor) impacted pipeline performance (all p&gt;0.05). Conclusion: This gait pipeline accurately and consistently detects initial and final contacts in PwMS across different smartphone locations and environments, highlighting its potential for real-world gait assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13961v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenza Angelini, Dimitar Stanev, Marta P{\l}onka, Rafa{\l} Klimas, Natan Napi\'orkowski, Gabriela Gonz\'alez Chan, Lisa Bunn, Paul S Glazier, Richard Hosking, Jenny Freeman, Jeremy Hobart, Jonathan Marsden, Licinio Craveiro, Mike D Rinderknecht, Mattia Zanon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a streaming signal in which each sample is linked to a latent class. We assume that multiple classifiers are available, each providing class probabilities with varying degrees of accuracy. These classifiers are employed following a straightforward and fixed policy. In this setting, we consider the problem of fusing the output of the classifiers while incorporating the temporal aspect to improve classification accuracy. We propose a state-space model and develop a filter tailored for realtime execution. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed filter in an activity classification application based on inertial measurement unit (IMU) data from a wearable device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13975v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilker Bayram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Coherent Beamforming at 60 GHz Enabled by Optically-Established Coherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We implement and experimentally demonstrate a 60 GHz distributed system leveraging an optical time synchronization system that provides precise time and frequency alignment between independent elements of the distributed mesh. Utilizing such accurate coherence, we perform receive beamforming with interference rejection and transmit nulling. In these configurations, the system achieves a coherent gain over an incoherent network of N nodes, significantly improving the relevant signal power ratios. Our system demonstrates extended array phase coherence times, enabling advanced techniques. Results from over-the-air experiments demonstrate a 14.3 dB signal-to-interference-plus-noise improvement in interference-laden scenarios with a contributing 13.5 dB null towards interference in receive beamforming. In transmit nulling, a signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) gain of 7.9 dB is measured towards an intended receiver while maintaining an SNR reduction of 8.9 dB at another receiver. These findings represent the use of distributed coherence in the V band without the use of GPS timing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13984v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drake Silbernagel, Yu Rong, Isabella Lenz, Prithvi Hemanth, Carl Morgenstern, Owen Ma, Nolan Matthews, Nader Zaki, Kyle W. Martin, John D. Elgin, Jacob Holtom, Daniel W. Bliss, Kimberly Frey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Deep Learning with RIS Grouping for Accurate Cascaded Channel Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (RIS) panels are envisioned as a key technology for sixth-generation (6G) wireless networks, providing a cost-effective means to enhance coverage and spectral efficiency. A critical challenge is the estimation of the cascaded base station (BS)-RIS-user channel, since the passive nature of RIS elements prevents direct channel acquisition, incurring prohibitive pilot overhead, computational complexity, and energy consumption. To address this, we propose a deep learning (DL)-based channel estimation framework that reduces pilot overhead by grouping RIS elements and reconstructing the cascaded channel from partial pilot observations. Furthermore, conventional DL models trained under single-user settings suffer from poor generalization across new user locations and propagation scenarios. We develop a distributed machine learning (DML) strategy in which the BS and users collaboratively train a shared neural network using diverse channel datasets collected across the network, thereby achieving robust generalization. Building on this foundation, we design a hierarchical DML neural architecture that first classifies propagation conditions and then employs scenario-specific feature extraction to further improve estimation accuracy. Simulation results confirm that the proposed framework substantially reduces pilot overhead and complexity while outperforming conventional methods and single-user models in channel estimation accuracy. These results demonstrate the practicality and effectiveness of the proposed approach for 6G RIS-assisted systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14062v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saifur Rahman, Syed Luqman Shah, Salman Khan, Jalal Khan, Muhammad Irfan, Maaz Shafi, Said Muhammad, Fazal Muhammad, Mohammad Shahed Akond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel Phase-Noise-Tolerant Variational-Autoencoder-Based Equalization Suitable for Space-Division-Multiplexed Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate the effectiveness of a novel phase-noise-tolerant, variational-autoencoder-based equalization scheme for space-division-multiplexed (SDM) transmission in an experiment over 150km of randomly-coupled multi-core fibers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14072v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Lauinger, Lennart Schmitz, Patrick Matalla, Andrej Rode, Sebastian Randel, Laurent Schmalen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware-Efficient Cognitive Radar: Multi-Target Detection with RL-Driven Transmissive RIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cognitive radar has emerged as a key paradigm for next-generation sensing, enabling adaptive, intelligent operation in dynamic and complex environments. Yet, conventional cognitive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) radars offer strong detection performance but suffer from high hardware complexity and power demands. To overcome these limitations, we develop a reinforcement learning (RL)-based framework that leverages a transmissive reconfigurable intelligent surface (TRIS) for adaptive beamforming. A state-action-reward-state-action (SARSA) agent tunes TRIS phase shifts to improve multi-target detection in low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) conditions while operating with far fewer radio frequency (RF) chains. Simulations confirm that the proposed TRIS-RL radar matches or, for large number of elements, even surpasses MIMO performance with reduced cost and energy requirements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14160v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Umra, Aya Mostafa Ahmed, Stefan Roth, Aydin Sezgin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quickest Change Detection with Cost-Constrained Experiment Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the classical quickest change detection problem, an observer performs only one experiment to monitor a stochastic process. This paper considers the case where, at each observation time, the decision-maker needs to choose between multiple experiments with different information qualities and costs. The goal is to minimize the worst-case average detection delay subject to false alarm and cost constraints. An algorithm called the 2E-CUSUM Algorithm has been developed to achieve this goal for the two-experiment case. Extensions to multiple-experiment designs are also studied, and 2E-CUSUM is extended accordingly. Data efficiency, where the observer has the choice not to perform an experiment, is explored as well. The proposed algorithms are analyzed and shown to be asymptotically optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14186v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Vincent N. Lubenia, Taposh Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Inference Framework for Closed-Loop Sensing, Communication, and Control in UAV Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) is a core technology for 6G, and its application to closed-loop sensing, communication, and control (SCC) enables various services. Existing SCC solutions often treat sensing and control separately, leading to suboptimal performance and resource usage. In this work, we introduce the active inference framework (AIF) into SCC-enabled unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) systems for joint state estimation, control, and sensing resource allocation. By formulating a unified generative model, the problem reduces to minimizing variational free energy for inference and expected free energy for action planning. Simulation results show that both control cost and sensing cost are reduced relative to baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14201v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangjin Pan, Liping Bai, Zhuojun Tian, Hui Chen, Mehdi Bennis, Henk Wymeersch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goal-Oriented Joint Source-Channel Coding: Distortion-Classification-Power Trade-off</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Joint source-channel coding is a compelling paradigm when low-latency and low-complexity communication is required. This work proposes a theoretical framework that integrates classification and anomaly detection within the conventional signal reconstruction objective. Assuming a Gaussian scalar source and constraining the encoder to piecewise linear mappings, we derive tractable design rules and explicitly characterize the trade-offs between distortion, classification error, and transmission power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14217v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andriy Enttsel, Weichen Wang, Mauro Mangia, Riccardo Rovatti, Deniz G\"und\"uz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uplink-Downlink Duality for Beamforming in Integrated Sensing and Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13661v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper considers the beamforming and power optimization problem for a class of integrated sensing and communications (ISAC) problems that utilize the communication signals simultaneously for sensing. We formulate the problem of minimizing the Bayesian Cram\'er-Rao bound (BCRB) on the mean-squared error of estimating a vector of parameters, while satisfying downlink signal-to-interference-and-noise-ratio constraints for a set of communication users at the same time. The proposed optimization framework comprises two key new ingredients. First, we show that the BCRB minimization problem corresponds to maximizing beamforming power along certain sensing directions of interest. Second, the classical uplink-downlink duality for multiple-input multiple-output communications can be extended to the ISAC setting, but unlike the classical communication problem, the dual uplink problem for ISAC may entail negative noise power and needs to include an extra condition on the uplink beamformers. This new duality theory opens doors for an efficient iterative algorithm for optimizing power and beamformers for ISAC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13661v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kareem M. Attiah, Wei Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Analysis of Nonlinear One-Bit Precoding in Massive MIMO Systems via Approximate Message Passing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13955v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems employing one-bit digital-to-analog converters offer a hardware-efficient solution for wireless communications. However, the one-bit constraint poses significant challenges for precoding design, as it transforms the problem into a discrete and nonconvex optimization task. In this paper, we investigate a widely adopted ``convex-relaxation-then-quantization" approach for nonlinear symbol-level one-bit precoding. Specifically, we first solve a convex relaxation of the discrete minimum mean square error precoding problem, and then quantize the solution to satisfy the one-bit constraint. To analyze the high-dimensional asymptotic performance of this scheme, we develop a novel analytical framework based on approximate message passing (AMP). This framework enables us to derive a closed-form expression for the symbol error probability (SEP) at the receiver side in the large-system limit, which provides a quantitative characterization of how model and system parameters affect the SEP performance. Our empirical results suggest that the $\ell_\infty^2$ regularizer, when paired with an optimally chosen regularization parameter, achieves optimal SEP performance within a broad class of convex regularization functions. As a first step towards a theoretical justification, we prove the optimality of the $\ell_\infty^2$ regularizer within the mixed $\ell_\infty^2$-$\ell_2^2$ regularization functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13955v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheyu Wu, Junjie Ma, Ya-Feng Liu, Bruno Clerckx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personalization on a Budget: Minimally-Labeled Continual Learning for Resource-Efficient Seizure Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13974v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Objective: Epilepsy, a prevalent neurological disease, demands careful diagnosis and continuous care. Seizure detection remains challenging, as current clinical practice relies on expert analysis of electroencephalography, which is a time-consuming process and requires specialized knowledge. Addressing this challenge, this paper explores automated epileptic seizure detection using deep learning, focusing on personalized continual learning models that adapt to each patient's unique electroencephalography signal features, which evolve over time. Methods: In this context, our approach addresses the challenge of integrating new data into existing models without catastrophic forgetting, a common issue in static deep learning models. We propose EpiSMART, a continual learning framework for seizure detection that uses a size-constrained replay buffer and an informed sample selection strategy to incrementally adapt to patient-specific electroencephalography signals. By selectively retaining high-entropy and seizure-predicted samples, our method preserves critical past information while maintaining high performance with minimal memory and computational requirements. Results: Validation on the CHB-MIT dataset, shows that EpiSMART achieves a 21% improvement in the F1 score over a trained baseline without updates in all other patients. On average, EpiSMART requires only 6.46 minutes of labeled data and 6.28 updates per day, making it suitable for real-time deployment in wearable systems. Conclusion:EpiSMART enables robust and personalized seizure detection under realistic and resource-constrained conditions by effectively integrating new data into existing models without degrading past knowledge. Significance: This framework advances automated seizure detection by providing a continual learning approach that supports patient-specific adaptation and practical deployment in wearable healthcare systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13974v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirhossein Shahbazinia, Jonathan Dan, Jose A. Miranda, Giovanni Ansaloni, David Atienza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning-Driven Peptide Classification in Biological Nanopores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A device capable of performing real time classification of proteins in a clinical setting would allow for inexpensive and rapid disease diagnosis. One such candidate for this technology are nanopore devices. These devices work by measuring a current signal that arises when a protein or peptide enters a nanometer-length-scale pore. Should this current be uniquely related to the structure of the peptide and its interactions with the pore, the signals can be used to perform identification. While such a method would allow for real time identification of peptides and proteins in a clinical setting, to date, the complexities of these signals limit their accuracy. In this work, we tackle the issue of classification by converting the current signals into scaleogram images via wavelet transforms, capturing amplitude, frequency, and time information in a modality well-suited to machine learning algorithms. When tested on 42 peptides, our method achieved a classification accuracy of ~$81\,\%$, setting a new state-of-the-art in the field and taking a step toward practical peptide/protein diagnostics at the point of care. In addition, we demonstrate model transfer techniques that will be critical when deploying these models into real hardware, paving the way to a new method for real-time disease diagnosis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14029v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Tovey, Julian Ho{\ss}bach, Sandro Kuppel, Tobias Ensslen, Jan C. Behrends, Christian Holm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnyAccomp: Generalizable Accompaniment Generation via Quantized Melodic Bottleneck</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14052v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Singing Accompaniment Generation (SAG) is the process of generating instrumental music for a given clean vocal input. However, existing SAG techniques use source-separated vocals as input and overfit to separation artifacts. This creates a critical train-test mismatch, leading to failure on clean, real-world vocal inputs. We introduce AnyAccomp, a framework that resolves this by decoupling accompaniment generation from source-dependent artifacts. AnyAccomp first employs a quantized melodic bottleneck, using a chromagram and a VQ-VAE to extract a discrete and timbre-invariant representation of the core melody. A subsequent flow-matching model then generates the accompaniment conditioned on these robust codes. Experiments show AnyAccomp achieves competitive performance on separated-vocal benchmarks while significantly outperforming baselines on generalization test sets of clean studio vocals and, notably, solo instrumental tracks. This demonstrates a qualitative leap in generalization, enabling robust accompaniment for instruments - a task where existing models completely fail - and paving the way for more versatile music co-creation tools. Demo audio and code: https://anyaccomp.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14052v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junan Zhang, Yunjia Zhang, Xueyao Zhang, Zhizheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual mode multispectral imaging system for food and agricultural product quality estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03110v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multispectral imaging coupled with Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning and Signal Processing techniques work as a feasible alternative for laboratory testing, especially in food quality control. Most of the recent related research has been focused on reflectance multispectral imaging but a system with both reflectance, transmittance capabilities would be ideal for a wide array of specimen types including solid and liquid samples. In this paper, a device which includes a dedicated reflectance mode and a dedicated transmittance mode is proposed. Dual mode operation where fast switching between two modes is facilitated. An innovative merged mode is introduced in which both reflectance and transmittance information of a specimen are combined to form a higher dimensional dataset with more features. Spatial and temporal variations of measurements are analyzed to ensure the quality of measurements. The concept is validated using a standard color palette and specific case studies are done for standard food samples such as turmeric powder and coconut oil proving the validity of proposed contributions. The classification accuracy of standard color palette testing was over 90% and the accuracy of coconut oil adulteration was over 95%. while the merged mode was able to provide the best accuracy of 99% for the turmeric adulteration. A linear functional mapping was done for coconut oil adulteration with an R2 value of 0.9558.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03110v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darsha Udayanga, Ashan Serasinghe, Supun Dassanayake, Roshan Godaliyadda, H. M. V. R. Herath, M. P. B. Ekanayake, H. L. P. Malshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bit Efficient Toeplitz Covariance Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses the challenge of Toeplitz covariance matrix estimation from partial entries of random quantized samples. To balance trade-offs among the number of samples, the number of entries observed per sample, and the data resolution, we propose a ruler-based quantized Toeplitz covariance estimator. We derive non-asymptotic error bounds and analyze the convergence rates of the proposed estimator. Our results show that the estimator is near-optimal and imply that reducing data resolution within a certain range has a limited impact on the estimation accuracy. Numerical experiments are provided that validate our theoretical findings and show effectiveness of the proposed estimator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12678v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongwei Xu, Zai Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Spatial Modulation Aided Affine Frequency Division Multiplexing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10865v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generalized spatial modulation-aided affine frequency division multiplexing (GSM-AFDM) is conceived for reliable multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) communications over doubly selective channels. \textcolor{black}{We commence by proposing several low-complexity detectors for large-scale GSM-AFDM systems to meet the diverse requirements of heterogeneous receiver designs in terms of detection complexity and reliability.} Specifically, we introduce the linear minimum mean square error (LMMSE) equalizer-based maximum likelihood detector (LMMSE-MLD). By exploiting the GSM properties, we then derive the LMMSE-based transmit-antenna activation pattern (TAP) check-based log-likelihood ratio detector (LMMSE-TC-LLRD). In addition, we propose a pair of new detectors, namely the greedy residual check detector (GRCD) and the reduced space check detector (RSCD). We also derive a bit error rate (BER) upper-bound by considering the MLD. \textcolor{black}{Our analytical results are also available for multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO)-AFDM, since MIMO-AFDM can be regarded as a special case of the proposed GSM-AFDM.} Our simulation results demonstrate that 1) the BER upper bound derived is tight for moderate to high signal-to-noise ratios (SNRs), \textcolor{black}{2) the proposed GSM-AFDM achieves lower BER than its conventional orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM), orthogonal time frequency space (OTFS) and AFDM counterparts. Specifically, at a BER of $10^{-4}$ and a velocity of $540$ km/h, the proposed GSM-AFDM is capable of attaining about $6$ dB SNR gain compared to GSM-OFDM,} and 3) the conceived detectors strike a compelling trade-off between the BER and complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10865v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeping Sui, Zilong Liu, Leila Musavian, Lie-Liang Yang, Lajos Hanzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotatable Antenna Aided Mixed Near-Field and Far-Field Communications in the Upper Mid-Band: Interference Analysis and Joint Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04865v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose to leverage rotatable antennas (RAs) for improving the communication performance in mixed near-field and far-field communication systems by exploiting a new spatial degree-of-freedom (DoF) offered by antenna rotation to mitigate complex near-field interference and mixed-field interference. Specifically, we investigate a modular RA-enabled mixed-field downlink communication system, where a base station (BS) consisting of multiple RA subarrays communicates with multiple near-field users in the presence of several legacy far-field users. We formulate an optimization problem to maximize the sum-rate of the near-field users by jointly optimizing the power allocation and rotation angles of all subarrays at the BS. To gain useful insights into the effect of RAs on mixed-field communications, we first analyze a special case where all subarrays share the same rotation angle and obtain closed-form expressions for the rotation-aware normalized near-field interference and the rotation-aware normalized mixed-field interference using the Fresnel integrals. We then analytically reveal that array rotation effectively suppresses both interference types, thereby significantly enhancing mixed-field communication performance. For the general case involving subarray-wise rotation, we propose an efficient double-layer algorithm to obtain a high-quality solution, where the inner layer optimizes power allocation using the successive convex approximation (SCA) technique, while the outer layer determines the rotation angles of all subarrays via particle swarm optimization (PSO). Finally, numerical results highlight the significant performance gains achieved by RAs over conventional fixed-antenna systems and demonstrate the effectiveness of our developed joint design compared to benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04865v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunpu Zhang, Changsheng You, Hing Cheung So, Dusit Niyato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Sampling of Multiple Correlated Stochastic Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09225v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multiple stochastic signals possess inherent statistical correlations, yet conventional sampling methods that process each channel independently result in data redundancy. To leverage this correlation for efficient sampling, we model correlated channels as a linear combination of a smaller set of uncorrelated, wide-sense stationary latent sources. We establish a theoretical lower bound on the total sampling density for zero mean-square error reconstruction, proving it equals the ratio of the joint spectral bandwidth of latent sources to the number of correlated signal channels. We then develop a constructive multi-band sampling scheme that attains this bound. The proposed method operates via spectral partitioning of the latent sources, followed by spatio-temporal sampling and interpolation. Experiments on synthetic and real datasets confirm that our scheme achieves near-lossless reconstruction precisely at the theoretical sampling density, validating its efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09225v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Jin, Hang Sheng, Hui Feng, Bo Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMC Limit Level Guidelines for In-System Interference with GPS Receivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12770v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Because GPS signals are weak, electronic systems and components that are placed near GPS receivers can easily cause disruptive electromagnetic interference through their unintended radiated emissions. In this paper, EMC limit level guidelines are presented for electronics that are intended to be placed near to GPS receivers, as often happens in automotive and other applications. One of the challenges of defining limit-levels for systems intended to be integrated with GPS receivers is that the impact of noise at the input of the receiver may vary substantially depending on the form of the noise due to the correlator function implemented by GPS receiver. The quality of the correlated signal is typically represented using the carrier-to-noise ratio ($C / N_0$). A theoretical model predicting the degredation of the carrier-to-noise ratio with radio frequency interference is presented in this paper and is validated with realistic noise sources. The model is then used to develop guidelines to assess the impact of unintended emissions from electronic devices on nearby GPS receivers based on the frequency, bandwidth, and magnitude of the noise. These guidelines provide a more nuanced method of evaluating emissions than simple limit lines that are used by many emissions standards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12770v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgi Tsintsadze, Haran Manoharan, Aaron Harmon, Daniel Commerou, Connor Buneta, Brian Booth, Daryl Beetner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jammer Mitigation in Absorptive RIS-Assisted Uplink NOMA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16786v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA) is a promising technology for next-generation wireless communication systems due to its enhanced spectral efficiency. In this paper, we consider an uplink NOMA system operating together with a high-dimensional absorptive reconfigurable intelligent surface (A-RIS). We aim to minimize the total power transmitted by the users in order to meet signal-to-interference-plus-noise constraints at the base station in the presence of a jammer. We propose an iterative algorithm to solve the high-dimensional non-convex optimization problem using linear programming to find the transmit powers and a fractional programming algorithm based on the Dinkelbach algorithm with a sequential convex relaxation procedure to optimize the reflection coefficients. We show that our algorithm converges on large optimization problems, with a jammer comprising as many as $64$ antennas, and an A-RIS with $128$ elements. Our numerical results show that, compared with a standard RIS that reflects all impinging energy, the A-RIS can dramatically reduce the users' required transmit power and successfully mitigate interference from the jammer. The absorption capability of the A-RIS is in particular useful in cases when the number of jammer antennas is of the same order as the number of A-RIS elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16786v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azadeh Tabeshnezhad, Yuqing Zhu, Artem Vilenskiy, Van Ly Nguyen, A. Lee Swindlehurst, Tommy Svensson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Benchmark of Federated Learning with Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks for Medical Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19639v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Federated Learning (FL) enables model training across decentralized devices without sharing raw data, thereby preserving privacy in sensitive domains like healthcare. In this paper, we evaluate Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KAN) architectures against traditional MLP across six state-of-the-art FL algorithms on a blood cell classification dataset. Notably, our experiments demonstrate that KAN can effectively replace MLP in federated environments, achieving superior performance with simpler architectures. Furthermore, we analyze the impact of key hyperparameters-grid size and network architecture-on KAN performance under varying degrees of Non-IID data distribution. In addition, our ablation studies reveal that optimizing KAN width while maintaining minimal depth yields the best performance in federated settings. As a result, these findings establish KAN as a promising alternative for privacy-preserving medical imaging applications in distributed healthcare. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first comprehensive benchmark of KAN in FL settings for medical imaging task.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19639v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngjoon Lee, Jinu Gong, Joonhyuk Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Generalizability of Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks via Error-Correcting Output Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05798v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KAN) offer universal function approximation using univariate spline compositions without nonlinear activations. In this work, we integrate Error-Correcting Output Codes (ECOC) into the KAN framework to transform multi-class classification into multiple binary tasks, improving robustness via Hamming distance decoding. Our proposed KAN with ECOC framework outperforms vanilla KAN on a challenging blood cell classification dataset, achieving higher accuracy across diverse hyperparameter settings. Ablation studies further confirm that ECOC consistently enhances performance across FastKAN and FasterKAN variants. These results demonstrate that ECOC integration significantly boosts KAN generalizability in critical healthcare AI applications. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work of ECOC with KAN for enhancing multi-class medical image classification performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05798v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngjoon Lee, Jinu Gong, Joonhyuk Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoVariance Filters and Neural Networks over Hilbert Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13178v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: CoVariance Neural Networks (VNNs) perform graph convolutions on the empirical covariance matrix of signals defined over finite-dimensional Hilbert spaces, motivated by robustness and transferability properties. Yet, little is known about how these arguments extend to infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces. In this work, we take a first step by introducing a novel convolutional learning framework for signals defined over infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces, centered on the (empirical) covariance operator. We constructively define Hilbert coVariance Filters (HVFs) and design Hilbert coVariance Networks (HVNs) as stacks of HVF filterbanks with nonlinear activations. We propose a principled discretization procedure, and we prove that empirical HVFs can recover the Functional PCA (FPCA) of the filtered signals. We then describe the versatility of our framework with examples ranging from multivariate real-valued functions to reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces. Finally, we validate HVNs on both synthetic and real-world time-series classification tasks, showing robust performance compared to MLP and FPCA-based classifiers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13178v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Battiloro, Andrea Cavallo, Elvin Isufi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
