<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficient Wireless Communications by Harnessing Huygens' Metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ambitions for the next generation of wireless communication include high data rates, low latency, ubiquitous access, ensuring sustainability (in terms of consumption of energy and natural resources), all while maintaining a reasonable level of implementation complexity. Achieving these goals necessitates reforms in cellular networks, specifically in the physical layer and antenna design. The deployment of transmissive metasurfaces at basestations (BSs) presents an appealing solution, enabling beamforming in the radiated wave domain, minimizing the need for energy-hungry RF chains. Among various metasurface-based antenna designs, we propose using Huygens' metasurface-based antennas (HMAs) at BSs. Huygens' metasurfaces offer an attractive solution for antennas because, by utilizing Huygens' equivalence principle, they allow independent control over both the amplitude and phase of the transmitted electromagnetic wave. In this paper, we investigate the fundamental limits of HMAs in wireless networks by integrating electromagnetic theory and information theory within a unified analytical framework. Specifically, we model the unique electromagnetic characteristics of HMAs and incorporate them into an information-theoretic optimization framework to determine their maximum achievable sum rate. By formulating an optimization problem that captures the impact of HMA's hardware constraints and electromagnetic properties, we quantify the channel capacity of HMA-assisted systems. We then compare the performance of HMAs against phased arrays and other metasurface-based antennas in both rich scattering and realistic 3GPP channels, highlighting their potential in improving spectral and energy efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21128v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Rezvani, Raviraj Adve, Akram bin Sediq, Amr El-Keyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised Label-free Artefact Cleaning for Real-time Medical Pulsatile Time Series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artefacts compromise clinical decision-making in the use of medical time series. Pulsatile waveforms offer probabilities for accurate artefact detection, yet most approaches rely on supervised manners and overlook patient-level distribution shifts. To address these issues, we introduce a generalised label-free framework, GenClean, for real-time artefact cleaning and leverage an in-house dataset of 180,000 ten-second arterial blood pressure (ABP) samples for training. We first investigate patient-level generalisation, demonstrating robust performances under both intra- and inter-patient distribution shifts. We further validate its effectiveness through challenging cross-disease cohort experiments on the MIMIC-III database. Additionally, we extend our method to photoplethysmography (PPG), highlighting its applicability to diverse medical pulsatile signals. Finally, its integration into ICM+, a clinical research monitoring software, confirms the real-time feasibility of our framework, emphasising its practical utility in continuous physiological monitoring. This work provides a foundational step toward precision medicine in improving the reliability of high-resolution medical time series analysis</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21209v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuhang Chen, Ihsane Olakorede, Stefan Yu B\"ogli, Wenhao Xu, Erta Beqiri, Xuemeng Li, Chenyu Tang, Zeyu Gao, Shuo Gao, Ari Ercole, Peter Smielewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveform Design Based on Mutual Information Upper Bound For Joint Detection and Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Adaptive radar waveform design grounded in information-theoretic principles is critical for advancing cognitive radar performance in complex environments. This paper investigates the optimization of phase-coded waveforms under constant modulus constraints to jointly enhance target detection and parameter estimation. We introduce a unified design framework based on maximizing a Mutual Information Upper Bound (MIUB), which inherently reconciles the trade-off between detection sensitivity and estimation precision without relying on ad hoc weighting schemes. To model realistic, potentially non-Gaussian statistics of target returns and clutter, we adopt Gaussian Mixture Distributions (GMDs), enabling analytically tractable approximations of the MIUB's constituent Kullback-Leibler divergence and mutual information terms. To address the resulting non-convex problem, we propose the Phase-Coded Dream Optimization Algorithm (PC-DOA), a tailored metaheuristic that leverages hybrid initialization and adaptive exploration-exploitation mechanisms specifically designed for phase-variable optimization. Numerical simulations demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed method in achieving modestly better detection-estimation trade-off.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21322v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruofeng Yu, Caiguang Zhang, Chenyang Luo, Mengdi Bai, Shangqu Yan, Wei Yang, Yaowen Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Stage Composite Outlier Identification of Wind Power Data: Integrating Physical Rules with Regression Learning and Mathematical Morphology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existing studies on identifying outliers in wind speed-power datasets are often challenged by the complicated and irregular distributions of outliers, especially those being densely stacked yet staying close to normal data. This could degrade their identification reliability and robustness in practice. To address this defect, this paper develops a three-stage composite outlier identification method by systematically integrating three complementary techniques, i.e., physical rule-based preprocessing, regression learning-enabled detection, and mathematical morphology-based refinement. Firstly, the raw wind speed-power data are preprocessed via a set of simple yet efficient physical rules to filter out some outliers obviously going against the physical operating laws of practical wind turbines. Secondly, a robust wind speed-power regression learning model is built upon the random sample consensus algorithm. This model is able to reliably detect most outliers with the help of an adaptive threshold automatically set by the interquartile range method. Thirdly, by representing the wind speed-power data distribution with a two-dimensional image, mathematical morphology operations are applied to perform refined outlier identification from a data distribution perspective. This technique can identify outliers that are not effectively detected in the first two stages, including those densely stacked ones near normal data points. By integrating the above three techniques, the whole method is capable of identifying various types of outliers in a reliable and adaptive manner. Numerical test results with wind power datasets acquired from distinct wind turbines in practice and from simulation environments extensively demonstrate the superiority of the proposed method as well as its potential in enhancing wind power prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21354v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Limengqian Zheng, Lipeng Zhu, Weijia Wen, Jiayong Li, Cong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic Modelling of Extended Targets in a Distributed Antenna System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional radar and integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) systems often approximate targets as point sources, a simplification that fails to capture the essential scattering characteristics for many applications. This paper presents a novel electromagnetic (EM)-based framework to accurately model the near-field (NF) scattering response of extended targets, which is then applied to three canonical shapes : a flat rectangular plate, a sphere and a cylinder. Mathematical expressions for the received signal are provided in each case. Based on this model, the influence of bandwidth, carrier frequency and target distance on localisation accuracy is analysed, showing how higher bandwidths and carrier frequencies improve resolution. Additionally, the impact of target curvature on localisation performance is studied. Results indicate that detection performance is slightly enhanced when considering curved objects. A comparative analysis between the extended and point target models shows significant similarities when targets are small and curved. However, as the target size increases or becomes flatter, the point target model introduces estimation errors owing to model mismatch. The impact of this model mismatch as a function of system parameters is analysed, and the operational zones where the point abstraction remains valid and where it breaks down are identified. These findings provide theoretical support for experimental results based on point-target models in previous studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21388v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Sambon, Fran\c{c}ois De Saint Moulin, Guillaume Thiran, Claude Oestges, Luc Vandendorpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Intelligent Edge Sensing for ISCC Network: Joint Multi-Tier DNN Partitioning and Beamforming Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The combination of Integrated Sensing and Communication (ISAC) and Mobile Edge Computing (MEC) enables devices to simultaneously sense the environment and offload data to the base stations (BS) for intelligent processing, thereby reducing local computational burdens. However, transmitting raw sensing data from ISAC devices to the BS often incurs substantial fronthaul overhead and latency. This paper investigates a three-tier collaborative inference framework enabled by Integrated Sensing, Communication, and Computing (ISCC), where cloud servers, MEC servers, and ISAC devices cooperatively execute different segments of a pre-trained deep neural network (DNN) for intelligent sensing. By offloading intermediate DNN features, the proposed framework can significantly reduce fronthaul transmission load. Furthermore, multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) technology is employed to enhance both sensing quality and offloading efficiency. To minimize the overall sensing task inference latency across all ISAC devices, we jointly optimize the DNN partitioning strategy, ISAC beamforming, and computational resource allocation at the MEC servers and devices, subject to sensing beampattern constraints. We also propose an efficient two-layer optimization algorithm. In the inner layer, we derive closed-form solutions for computational resource allocation using the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker conditions. Moreover, we design the ISAC beamforming vectors via an iterative method based on the majorization-minimization and weighted minimum mean square error techniques. In the outer layer, we develop a cross-entropy based probabilistic learning algorithm to determine an optimal DNN partitioning strategy. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed framework substantially outperforms existing two-tier schemes in inference latency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21409v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Liu, Zesong Fei, Xinyi Wang, Xiaoyang Li, Weijie Yuan, Yuanhao Li, Cheng Hu, Dusit Niyato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Intercept OFDM Waveform Design with Secure Coding for Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellite networks are integral to next-generation communication systems, providing global coverage, low latency, and minimal signal loss. However, their unique characteristics, such as constrained onboard resources, Line-of-Sight (LoS) propagation, and vulnerability to eavesdropping over wide coverage areas, present significant challenges to physical layer security. To address these challenges, this paper focuses on the design of anti-intercept waveforms for satellite-ground links within Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM) systems, aiming to enhance security against eavesdropping threats. We formulate a secrecy rate maximization problem that aims to balance secrecy performance and communication reliability under eavesdropping constraints and sub-carrier power limitations. To solve this non-convex optimization problem, we propose a bisection search-activated neural network (BSA-Net) that integrates unsupervised learning for secure coding optimization and bisection search for dynamic power allocation. The proposed method is structured in two stages: the first optimizes secure coding under power constraints, while the second allocates power across sub-carriers under eavesdropping constraints. Extensive simulation results demonstrate the efficacy of our approach, showcasing significant improvements in secrecy rate performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21446v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhisheng Yin, Yonghong Liu, Dongbo Li, Nan Cheng, Linlin Liang, Changle Li, Jie Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Features for Grassmannian Kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21533v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Grassmannian manifold G(k, n) serves as a fundamental tool in signal processing, computer vision, and machine learning, where problems often involve classifying, clustering, or comparing subspaces. In this work, we propose a sketching-based approach to approximate Grassmannian kernels using random projections. We introduce three variations of kernel approximation, including two that rely on binarised sketches, offering substantial memory gains. We establish theoretical properties of our method in the special case of G(1, n) and extend it to general G(k, n). Experimental validation demonstrates that our sketched kernels closely match the performance of standard Grassmannian kernels while avoiding the need to compute or store the full kernel matrix. Our approach enables scalable Grassmannian-based methods for large-scale applications in machine learning and pattern recognition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21533v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'emi Delogne, Laurent Jacques</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Agnostic Semantic Communications Relying on Information Bottleneck and Federated Meta-Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As a paradigm shift towards pervasive intelligence, semantic communication (SemCom) has shown great potentials to improve communication efficiency and provide user-centric services by delivering task-oriented semantic meanings. However, the exponential growth in connected devices, data volumes, and communication demands presents significant challenges for practical SemCom design, particularly in resource-constrained wireless networks. In this work, we first propose a task-agnostic SemCom (TASC) framework that can handle diverse tasks with multiple modalities. Aiming to explore the interplay between communications and intelligent tasks from the information-theoretical perspective, we leverage information bottleneck (IB) theory and propose a distributed multimodal IB (DMIB) principle to learn minimal and sufficient unimodal and multimodal information effectively by discarding redundancy while preserving task-related information. To further reduce the communication overhead, we develop an adaptive semantic feature transmission method under dynamic channel conditions. Then, TASC is trained based on federated meta-learning (FML) for rapid adaptation and generalization in wireless networks. To gain deep insights, we rigorously conduct theoretical analysis and devise resource management to accelerate convergence while minimizing the training latency and energy consumption. Moreover, we develop a joint user selection and resource allocation algorithm to address the non-convex problem with theoretical guarantees. Extensive simulation results validate the effectiveness and superiority of the proposed TASC compared to baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21723v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Wei, Wen Wang, Wanli Ni, Wenjun Xu, Yongming Huang, Dusit Niyato, Ping Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smart Environmental Monitoring of Marine Pollution using Edge AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Oil spill incidents pose severe threats to marine ecosystems and coastal environments, necessitating rapid detection and monitoring capabilities to mitigate environmental damage. In this paper, we demonstrate how artificial intelligence, despite the inherent high computational and memory requirements, can be efficiently integrated into marine pollution monitoring systems. More precisely, we propose a drone-based smart monitoring system leveraging a compressed deep learning U-Net architecture for oil spill detection and thickness estimation. Compared to the standard U-Net architecture, the number of convolution blocks and channels per block are modified. The new model is then trained on synthetic radar data to accurately predict thick oil slick thickness up to 10 mm. Results show that our optimized Tiny U-Net achieves superior performance with an Intersection over Union (IoU) metric of approximately 79%, while simultaneously reducing the model size by a factor of $\sim$269x compared to the state-of-the-art. This significant model compression enables efficient edge computing deployment on field-programmable gate array (FPGA) hardware integrated directly into the drone platform. Hardware implementation demonstrates near real-time thickness estimation capabilities with a run-time power consumption of approximately 2.2 watts. Our findings highlight the increasing potential of smart monitoring technologies and efficient edge computing for operational characterization in marine environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21759v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Moursi, Norbert Wehn, Bilal Hammoud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility assessment of optical communications between ground and satellite on Mars through the simulation of atmospheric effects on signal quality leading to a proposal for a new communications network architecture during extreme weather</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21148v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mars is the next milestone in human exploration. However, there are still several challenges that must be assessed to ensure appropriate conditions in a future settlement. Communications services will be essential for this task, providing not only a link between Earth and Mars but also supporting Martian weather forecasting and any potential rescue missions. These applications require a robust, high data rate communications network that allows for rapid response, remote sensing and public engagement. This research aims to study the feasibility of ground-to-satellite (and vice versa) optical communications during extreme Martian weather conditions, focusing on the link between a ground station on the surface of Mars and a satellite orbiting the planet. Long-lasting and expansive Martian dust storms, particularly common in the southern hemisphere, pose a considerable challenge when considering the feasibility of optical communications with Mars due to their significant impact in terms of signal attenuation and scattering. The methodology of this study is based on a computer simulation of the system featuring the characterisation of the Martian atmosphere and optical link to measure the attenuation and undesired effects suffered by the data signal when applying different environmental configuration parameters. The flexibility of the approach allows for the prediction of communications link quality in extreme cases such as global dust storms. The simulation is based on atmospheric data from the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter's Mars Climate Sounder instrument and considers the recently launched Laser Communication Relay Demonstration (LCRD). The extreme conditions during dust storms in the southern polar-hood region lead to the proposal of a new communications network architecture to ensure connectivity during these events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21148v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary C. Rowland, Eva Fernandez Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green Satellite Networks Using Segment Routing and Software-Defined Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21181v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive evaluation of network performance in software defined networking (SDN)-based low Earth orbit (LEO) satellite networks, focusing on the Telesat Lightspeed constellation. We propose a green traffic engineering (TE) approach leveraging segment routing IPv6 (SRv6) to enhance energy efficiency. Through simulations, we analyze the impact of SRv6, multi-protocol label switching (MPLS), IPv4, and IPv6 with open shortest path first (OSPF) on key network performance metrics, including peak and average CPU usage, memory consumption, packet delivery rate (PDR), and packet overhead under varying traffic loads. Results show that the proposed green TE approach using SRv6 achieves notable energy efficiency, maintaining lower CPU usage and high PDR compared to traditional protocols. While SRv6 and MPLS introduce slightly higher memory usage and overhead due to their advanced configurations, these trade-offs remain manageable. Our findings highlight SRv6 with green TE as a promising solution for optimizing energy efficiency in LEO satellite networks, contributing to the development of more sustainable and efficient satellite communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21181v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintao Liang, Pablo G. Madoery, Chung-Horng Lung, Halim Yanikomeroglu, Gunes Karabulut Kurt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redundancy Analysis and Mitigation for Machine Learning-Based Process Monitoring of Additive Manufacturing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The deployment of machine learning (ML)-based process monitoring systems has significantly advanced additive manufacturing (AM) by enabling real-time defect detection, quality assessment, and process optimization. However, redundancy is a critical yet often overlooked challenge in the deployment and operation of ML-based AM process monitoring systems. Excessive redundancy leads to increased equipment costs, compromised model performance, and high computational requirements, posing barriers to industrial adoption. However, existing research lacks a unified definition of redundancy and a systematic framework for its evaluation and mitigation. This paper defines redundancy in ML-based AM process monitoring and categorizes it into sample-level, feature-level, and model-level redundancy. A comprehensive multi-level redundancy mitigation (MLRM) framework is proposed, incorporating advanced methods such as data registration, downscaling, cross-modality knowledge transfer, and model pruning to systematically reduce redundancy while improving model performance. The framework is validated through an ML-based in-situ defect detection case study for directed energy deposition (DED), demonstrating a 91% reduction in latency, a 47% decrease in error rate, and a 99.4% reduction in storage requirements. Additionally, the proposed approach lowers sensor costs and energy consumption, enabling a lightweight, cost-effective, and scalable monitoring system. By defining redundancy and introducing a structured mitigation framework, this study establishes redundancy analysis and mitigation as a key enabler of efficient ML-based process monitoring in production environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21317v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiarui Xie, Yaoyao Fiona Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Inversion Theorem for Buffered Linear Toeplitz (BLT) Matrices and Applications to Streaming Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21413v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Buffered Linear Toeplitz (BLT) matrices are a family of parameterized lower-triangular matrices that play an important role in streaming differential privacy with correlated noise. Our main result is a BLT inversion theorem: the inverse of a BLT matrix is itself a BLT matrix with different parameters. We also present an efficient and differentiable $O(d^3)$ algorithm to compute the parameters of the inverse BLT matrix, where $d$ is the degree of the original BLT (typically $d &lt; 10$). Our characterization enables direct optimization of BLT parameters for privacy mechanisms through automatic differentiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21413v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Brendan McMahan, Krishna Pillutla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sionna RT: Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21719v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sionna is an open-source, GPU-accelerated library that, as of version 0.14, incorporates a ray tracer for simulating radio wave propagation. A unique feature of Sionna RT is differentiability, enabling the calculation of gradients for the channel impulse responses (CIRs), radio maps, and other related metrics with respect to system and environmental parameters, such as material properties, antenna patterns, and array geometries. The release of Sionna 1.0 provides a complete overhaul of the ray tracer, significantly improving its speed, memory efficiency, and extensibility. This document details the algorithms employed by Sionna RT to simulate radio wave propagation efficiently, while also addressing their current limitations. Given that the computation of CIRs and radio maps requires distinct algorithms, these are detailed in separate sections. For CIRs, Sionna RT integrates shooting and bouncing of rays (SBR) with the image method and uses a hashing-based mechanism to efficiently eliminate duplicate paths. Radio maps are computed using a purely SBR-based approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21719v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fay\c{c}al A\"it Aoudia, Jakob Hoydis, Merlin Nimier-David, Sebastian Cammerer, Alexander Keller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing Biased Backpressure Routing and Scheduling to Wireless Multi-hop Networks with Advanced Air-interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Backpressure (BP) routing and scheduling is a well-established resource allocation method for wireless multi-hop networks, known for its fully distributed operations and proven maximum queue stability. Recent advances in shortest path-biased BP routing (SP-BP) mitigate shortcomings such as slow startup and random walk, but exclusive link-level commodity selection still suffers from the last-packet problem and bandwidth underutilization. Moreover, classic BP routing implicitly assumes single-input-single-output (SISO) transceivers, which can lead to the same packets being scheduled on multiple outgoing links for multiple-input-multiple-output (MIMO) transceivers, causing detouring and looping in MIMO networks. In this paper, we revisit the foundational Lyapunov drift theory underlying BP routing and demonstrate that exclusive commodity selection is unnecessary, and instead propose a Max-Utility link-sharing method. Additionally, we generalize MaxWeight scheduling to MIMO networks by introducing attributed capacity hypergraphs (ACH), an extension of traditional conflict graphs for SISO networks, and by incorporating backlog reassignment into scheduling iterations to prevent redundant packet routing. Numerical evaluations show that our approach substantially mitigates the last-packet problem in state-of-the-art (SOTA) SP-BP under lightweight traffic, and slightly expands the network capacity region for heavier traffic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21721v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongyuan Zhao, Yujun Ming, Ananthram Swami, Kevin Chan, Fikadu Dagefu, Santiago Segarra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obstructive Sleep Apnea Characterization: A Multimodal Cross-Recurrence-Based Approach for Investigating Atrial Fibrillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is believed to contribute significantly to atrial fibrillation (AF) development in certain patients. Recent studies indicate a rising risk of AF with increasing OSA severity. However, the commonly used apnea-hypopnea index in clinical practice may not adequately account for the potential cardiovascular risks associated with OSA. (1) Objective: to propose and explore a novel method for assessing OSA severity considering potential connection to cardiac arrhythmias. (2) Method: the approach utilizes cross-recurrence features to characterize OSA and AF by considering the relationships among oxygen desaturation, pulse arrival time, and heart-beat intervals. Multinomial logistic regression models were trained to predict four levels of OSA severity and four groups related to heart rhythm issues. The rank biserial correlation coefficient, rrb, was used to estimate effect size for statistical analysis. The investigation was conducted using the MESA database, which includes polysomnography data from 2055 subjects. (3) Results: a derived cross-recurrence-based index showed a significant association with a higher OSA severity (p &lt; 0.01) and the presence of AF (p &lt; 0.01). Additionally, the proposed index had a significantly larger effect, rrb, than the conventional apnea-hypopnea index in differentiating increasingly severe heart rhythm issue groups: 0.14 &gt; 0.06, 0.33 &gt; 0.10, and 0.41 &gt; 0.07. (4) Significance: the proposed method holds relevance as a supplementary diagnostic tool for assessing the authentic state of sleep apnea in clinical practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21743v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JBHI.2024.3428845</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mantas Rinkevi\v{c}ius, Jes\'us L\'azaro, Eduardo Gil, Pablo Laguna, Peter H. Charlton, Raquel Bail\'on, Vaidotas Marozas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Road-Aware Line-of-Sight Probability Model for Urban Air Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15009v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As urban air mobility (UAM) emerges as a transformative solution to urban transportation, the demand for robust communication frameworks capable of supporting high-density aerial traffic becomes increasingly critical. An essential area of communications improvement is reliably characterizing and minimizing interference on UAM aircraft from other aircraft and ground vehicles. To achieve this, accurate line-of-sight (LOS) models must be used. In this work, we highlight the limitations of a LOS probability model extensively used in the literature in accurately predicting interference caused by ground vehicles. Then, we introduce a modified probability of LOS model that improves interference prediction by incorporating the urban topography and the dynamic positioning of ground vehicles on streets. Our model's parameters are derived from extensive simulations and validated through real-world urban settings to ensure reliability and applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15009v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdullah Abu Zaid, Baha Eddine Youcef Belmekki, Mohamed-Slim Alouini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Sampling Frequency Offset Estimation and Compensation Based on the Farrow Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a sampling frequency offset (SFO) estimation method based on the Farrow structure, which is typically utilized for the SFO compensation and thereby enables a reduction of the implementation complexity of the SFO estimation. The proposed method is implemented in the time domain and works for arbitrary bandlimited signals, thus with no additional constraints on the waveform structure. Moreover, it can operate on only the real or imaginary part of a complex signal, which further reduces the estimation complexity. Furthermore, the proposed method can simultaneously estimate the SFO and additional sampling time offset (STO) and it is insensitive to other synchronization errors, like carrier frequency offset. Both the derivations of the proposed method and its implementation are presented, and through simulation examples, it is demonstrated that it can accurately estimate both SFO and STO for different types of bandlimited signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07577v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deijany Rodriguez Linares, Oksana Moryakova, H{\aa}kan Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotatable Antenna-Enabled Secure Wireless Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10473v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rotatable antenna (RA) is a promising technology that exploits new spatial degree-of-freedom (DoF) to improve wireless communication and sensing performance. In this letter, we investigate an RA-enabled secure communication system where confidential information is transmitted from an RA-based access point (AP) to a single-antenna legitimate user in the presence of multiple eavesdroppers. We aim to maximize the secrecy rate by jointly optimizing the transmit beamforming and the deflection angles of all RAs at the AP. Accordingly, we propose an efficient alternating optimization (AO) algorithm to obtain a high-quality suboptimal solution in an iterative manner, where the generalized Rayleigh quotient-based beamforming is applied and the RAs' deflection angles are optimized by the successive convex approximation (SCA) technique. Our simulation results show that the proposed RA-enabled secure communication system achieves a significantly higher secrecy rate as compared to various benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10473v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Dai, Beixiong Zheng, Qingjie Wu, Changsheng You, Robert Schober, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markovian Continuity of the MMSE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14659v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Minimum mean square error (MMSE) estimation is widely used in signal processing and related fields. While it is known to be non-continuous with respect to all standard notions of stochastic convergence, it remains robust in practical applications. In this work, we review the known counterexamples to the continuity of the MMSE. We observe that, in these counterexamples, the discontinuity arises from an element in the converging measurement sequence providing more information about the estimand than the limit of the measurement sequence. We argue that this behavior is uncharacteristic of real-world applications and introduce a new stochastic convergence notion, termed Markovian convergence, to address this issue. We prove that the MMSE is, in fact, continuous under this new notion. We supplement this result with semi-continuity and continuity guarantees of the MMSE in other settings and prove the continuity of the MMSE under linear estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14659v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elad Domanovitz, Anatoly Khina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDWPF: A Dataset for Spatial Dynamic Wind Power Forecasting Challenge at KDD Cup 2022</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.04360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.04360v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The variability of wind power supply can present substantial challenges to incorporating wind power into a grid system. Thus, Wind Power Forecasting (WPF) has been widely recognized as one of the most critical issues in wind power integration and operation. There has been an explosion of studies on wind power forecasting problems in the past decades. Nevertheless, how to well handle the WPF problem is still challenging, since high prediction accuracy is always demanded to ensure grid stability and security of supply. We present a unique Spatial Dynamic Wind Power Forecasting dataset: SDWPF, which includes the spatial distribution of wind turbines, as well as the dynamic context factors. Whereas, most of the existing datasets have only a small number of wind turbines without knowing the locations and context information of wind turbines at a fine-grained time scale. By contrast, SDWPF provides the wind power data of 134 wind turbines from a wind farm over half a year with their relative positions and internal statuses. We use this dataset to launch the Baidu KDD Cup 2022 to examine the limit of current WPF solutions. The dataset is released at https://aistudio.baidu.com/aistudio/competition/detail/152/0/datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.04360v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41597-024-03427-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Zhou, J., Lu, X., Xiao, Y. et al. SDWPF: A Dataset for Spatial Dynamic Wind Power Forecasting over a Large Turbine Array. Sci Data 11, 649 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingbo Zhou, Xinjiang Lu, Yixiong Xiao, Jiantao Su, Junfu Lyu, Yanjun Ma, Dejing Dou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benefits of Mutual Coupling in Dynamic Metasurface Antennas for Optimizing Wireless Communications -- Theory and Experimental Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dynamic metasurface antennas (DMAs) are a promising embodiment of next-generation reconfigurable antenna technology to realize base stations and access points with reduced cost and power consumption. A DMA is a thin structure patterned on its front with reconfigurable radiating metamaterial elements (meta-atoms) that are excited by waveguides or cavities. Mutual coupling between the meta-atoms can result in a strongly non-linear dependence of the DMA's radiation pattern on the configuration of its meta-atoms. However, besides the obvious algorithmic challenges of working with physics-compliant DMA models, it remains unclear how mutual coupling in DMAs influences the ability to achieve a desired wireless functionality. In this paper, we provide theoretical, numerical and experimental evidence that strong mutual coupling in DMAs increases the radiation pattern sensitivity to the DMA configuration and thereby boosts the available control over the radiation pattern, improving the ability to tailor the radiation pattern to the requirements of a desired wireless functionality. Counterintuitively, we hence encourage next-generation DMA implementations to enhance (rather than suppress) mutual coupling, in combination with suitable physics-compliant modeling and optimization. We expect the unveiled mechanism by which mutual coupling boosts the radiation pattern control to also apply to other reconfigurable antenna systems based on tunable lumped elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15565v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Prod'homme, Jean Tapie, Luc Le Magoarou, Philipp del Hougne</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
