<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 05:00:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Resilience to IRS-Assisted Secure Wireless Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intelligent reflecting surfaces (IRSs) are envisioned as a transformative method for enhancing the physical layer security of future communication networks. However, current IRS-assisted secure wireless system designs incur high time cost for the joint optimization of beamforming vectors and IRS phase shifts and are susceptible to unforeseen disruption. Therefore, introducing resilience in IRS-assisted secure systems is essential. In this paper, we first quantify the resilience performance as the combination of the absorption and adaptation performance. In particular, the absorption performance measures the system's robustness when facing failure while the adaptation performance reflects the system's ability to recover from failure. Then, we propose a two-timescale transmission protocol aiming to enhance system resilience while limiting maximum information leakage to eavesdroppers. Specifically, in the initialization phase, the base station (BS) beamforming vectors and IRS phase shifts are optimized iteratively using an alternating optimization (AO) approach to improve the absorption performance of the system, i.e., the worst-case achievable rate, given a predefined maximum tolerable leakage rate, by accounting for the impact of long-term channel variations. When the system detects an outage, a fast system recovery mechanism is activated to restore operation by adjusting only the BS beamforming vectors, which enhances the adaptation performance of the system. Our numerical results reveal that the proposed algorithm significantly improves system resilience, including system robustness and recovery performance. Moreover, the proposed design guarantees outage-free transmission over a long time interval for moderate-size IRSs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12551v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Wu, Mehmet Emin Arslan, Niels Neumann, Wolfgang Gerstacker, Robert Schober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware-in-the-Loop Evaluation of Goodness of Fit (GoF) Testing for Dynamic Spectrum Sharing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In contrast to parametric spectrum sensing, non-parametric spectrum sensing can effectively detect the primary user's presence or absence without prior information about the primary user. Particularly, non-parametric spectrum sensing can be useful in dynamic spectrum sharing. The secondary user must detect incumbents and peer secondary users in dynamic spectrum sharing. The secondary user can use the licensed spectrum if the primary user is not detected using its band. The primary user detection problem is the goodness-of-fit testing problem. In this work, we performed a hardware-in-the-loop evaluation of goodness-of-fit tests such as Cramer-von-Mises (CM), Anderson-Darling (AD) and Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) tests. We used a wideband radio transceiver RFSoC 4x2 from AMD and an F8 radio channel emulator to perform GoF tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12693v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mir Lodro, Simon Armour, Mark A. Beach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware Distortion Modeling for Panel Selection in Large Intelligent Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hardware distortion in large intelligent surfaces (LISs) may limit their performance when scaling up such systems. It is of great importance to model the non-ideal effects in their transceivers to study the hardware distortions that can affect their performance. Therefore, we have focused on modeling and studying the effects of nonlinear RX-chains in LISs. We first derive expressions for SNDR of a LIS with a memory-less polynomial-based model at its RX-chains. Then we propose a simplified double-parameter exponential model for the distortion power and show that compared to the polynomial based model, the exponential model can improve the analytical tractability for SNDR optimization problems. In particular, we consider a panel selection optimization problems in a panel-based LIS scenario and show that the proposed model enables us to derive two closed-form sub-optimal solutions for panel selection, and can be a favorable alternative to high-order polynomial models in terms of computation complexity, especially for theoretical works on hardware distortion in MIMO and LIS systems. Numerical results show that the sub-optimal closed-form solutions have a near-optimal performance in terms of SNDR compared to the global optimum found by high-complexity heuristic search methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12861v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashkan Sheikhi, Juan Vidal Alegr\'ia, Ove Edfors</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM4WM: Adapting LLM for Wireless Multi-Tasking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The wireless channel is fundamental to communication, encompassing numerous tasks collectively referred to as channel-associated tasks. These tasks can leverage joint learning based on channel characteristics to share representations and enhance system design. To capitalize on this advantage, LLM4WM is proposed--a large language model (LLM) multi-task fine-tuning framework specifically tailored for channel-associated tasks. This framework utilizes a Mixture of Experts with Low-Rank Adaptation (MoE-LoRA) approach for multi-task fine-tuning, enabling the transfer of the pre-trained LLM's general knowledge to these tasks. Given the unique characteristics of wireless channel data, preprocessing modules, adapter modules, and multi-task output layers are designed to align the channel data with the LLM's semantic feature space. Experiments on a channel-associated multi-task dataset demonstrate that LLM4WM outperforms existing methodologies in both full-sample and few-shot evaluations, owing to its robust multi-task joint modeling and transfer learning capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12983v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanyu Liu, Shijian Gao, Boxun Liu, Xiang Cheng, Liuqing Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Model-Based Semantic Communication System for Image Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The remarkable success of Large Language Models (LLMs) in understanding and generating various data types, such as images and text, has demonstrated their ability to process and extract semantic information across diverse domains. This transformative capability lays the foundation for semantic communications, enabling highly efficient and intelligent communication systems. In this work, we present a novel OFDM-based semantic communication framework for image transmission. We propose an innovative semantic encoder design that leverages the ability of LLMs to extract the meaning of transmitted data rather than focusing on its raw representation. On the receiver side, we design an LLM-based semantic decoder capable of comprehending context and generating the most appropriate representation to fit the given context. We evaluate our proposed system under different scenarios, including Urban Macro-cell environments with varying speed ranges. The evaluation metrics demonstrate that our proposed system reduces the data size 4250 times, while achieving a higher data rate compared to conventional communication methods. This approach offers a robust and scalable solution to unlock the full potential of 6G connectivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12988v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soheyb Ribouh, Osama Saleem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz Integrated Sensing Communications and Powering for 6G Wireless Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The terahertz (THz) band has attracted significant interest for future wireless networks. In this paper, a THz integrated sensing communications and powering (THz-ISCAP) system, where sensing is leveraged to enhance communications and powering, is studied. For a given total amount of time, we aim to determine an optimal time allocation for sensing to improve the efficiency of communications and powering, along with an optimal power splitting ratio to balance these two functionalities. This is achieved by maximizing between communications and powering either the achievable rate or harvested energy while ensuring a minimum requirement on the other. Numerical results indicate that the optimal system performance can be achieved by jointly optimizing the sensing time allocation and the power splitting ratio. Additionally, the results reveal the effects of various factors, such as THz frequencies and antenna aperture sizes, on the system performance. This study provides some interesting results to offer a new perspective for the research on THz-ISCAP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13006v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua Yan, Yunfei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Egoistic MDS-based Rigid Body Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12417v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a novel anchorless rigid body localization (RBL) suitable for application in autonomous driving (AD), in so far as the algorithm enables a rigid body to egoistically detect the location (relative translation) and orientation (relative rotation) of another body, without knowledge of the shape of the latter, based only on a set of measurements of the distances between sensors of one vehicle to the other. A key point of the proposed method is that the translation vector between the two-bodies is modeled using the double-centering operator from multidimensional scaling (MDS) theory, enabling the method to be used between rigid bodies regardless of their shapes, in contrast to conventional approaches which require both bodies to have the same shape. Simulation results illustrate the good performance of the proposed technique in terms of root mean square error (RMSE) of the estimates in different setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12417v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niclas F\"uhrling, Giuseppe Abreu, David Gonz\'alez G., Osvaldo Gonsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy Polarization-Based Data Compression Without Frozen Set Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12584v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical source polar codes require the construction of frozen sets for given sources. While this scheme offers excellent theoretical performance, it faces challenges in practical data compression systems, including sensitivity to the accuracy and computational complexity of the construction algorithm. In this letter, we explore the feasibility of construction-free polar compression schemes. By optimally selecting output symbols based on the decoder's behavior, the proposed scheme not only enhances flexibility but also achieves significant improvements in compression rates. Several enhancements are introduced to facilitate the practical implementation of the proposed scheme. Numerical results demonstrate the superior performance compared to existing polar compression approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12584v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zichang Ren, Yuping Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current Opinions on Memristor-Accelerated Machine Learning Hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12644v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The unprecedented advancement of artificial intelligence has placed immense demands on computing hardware, but traditional silicon-based semiconductor technologies are approaching their physical and economic limit, prompting the exploration of novel computing paradigms. Memristor offers a promising solution, enabling in-memory analog computation and massive parallelism, which leads to low latency and power consumption. This manuscript reviews the current status of memristor-based machine learning accelerators, highlighting the milestones achieved in developing prototype chips, that not only accelerate neural networks inference but also tackle other machine learning tasks. More importantly, it discusses our opinion on current key challenges that remain in this field, such as device variation, the need for efficient peripheral circuitry, and systematic co-design and optimization. We also share our perspective on potential future directions, some of which address existing challenges while others explore untouched territories. By addressing these challenges through interdisciplinary efforts spanning device engineering, circuit design, and systems architecture, memristor-based accelerators could significantly advance the capabilities of AI hardware, particularly for edge applications where power efficiency is paramount.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12644v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingrui Jiang, Yichun Xu, Zefan Li, Can Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoundSpring: Loss-Resilient Audio Transceiver with Dual-Functional Masked Language Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose "SoundSpring", a cutting-edge error-resilient audio transceiver that marries the robustness benefits of joint source-channel coding (JSCC) while also being compatible with current digital communication systems. Unlike recent deep JSCC transceivers, which learn to directly map audio signals to analog channel-input symbols via neural networks, our SoundSpring adopts the layered architecture that delineates audio compression from digital coded transmission, but it sufficiently exploits the impressive in-context predictive capabilities of large language (foundation) models. Integrated with the casual-order mask learning strategy, our single model operates on the latent feature domain and serve dual-functionalities: as efficient audio compressors at the transmitter and as effective mechanisms for packet loss concealment at the receiver. By jointly optimizing towards both audio compression efficiency and transmission error resiliency, we show that mask-learned language models are indeed powerful contextual predictors, and our dual-functional compression and concealment framework offers fresh perspectives on the application of foundation language models in audio communication. Through extensive experimental evaluations, we establish that SoundSpring apparently outperforms contemporary audio transmission systems in terms of signal fidelity metrics and perceptual quality scores. These new findings not only advocate for the practical deployment of SoundSpring in learning-based audio communication systems but also inspire the development of future audio semantic transceivers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12696v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JSAC.2025.3531406</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shengshi Yao, Jincheng Dai, Xiaoqi Qin, Sixian Wang, Siye Wang, Kai Niu, Ping Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Complexity Channel Estimation for RIS-Assisted Multi-User Wireless Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) are eminently suitable for improving the reliability of wireless communications by jointly designing the active beamforming at the base station (BS) and the passive beamforming at the RIS. Therefore, the accuracy of channel estimation is crucial for RIS-aided systems. The challenge is that only the cascaded two-hop channel spanning from the user equipments (UEs) to the RIS and spanning from the RIS to the BS can be estimated, due to the lack of active radio frequency (RF) chains at RIS elements, which leads to high pilot overhead. In this paper, we propose a low-overhead linear minimum mean square error (LMMSE) channel estimation method by exploiting the spatial correlation of channel links, which strikes a trade-off between the pilot overhead and the channel estimation accuracy. Moreover, we calculate the theoretical normalized mean square error (MSE) for our channel estimation method. Finally, we verify numerically that the proposed LMMSE estimator has lower MSE than the state-of-the-art (SoA) grouping based estimators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12773v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingchao Li, Mohammed El-Hajjar, Ibrahim Hemadeh, Arman Shojaeifard, Lajos Hanzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Black Metal Tribometer: high-resolution measurement of normal load-indentation curves and partial slip hysteresis cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new instrument has been designed for measuring frictional hysteresis cycles and normal load-indentation curves. The primary purpose of the BMT is the validation of more predictive modeling approaches for damping in friction joints. An important original feature of the BMT is its ability to measure both normal and tangential contact behavior without having to separate the samples. Special attention was paid to alignment and smooth motion in order to permit testing nominally flat-on-flat contacts in the microslip regime. Examples are shown for finely resolved, undistorted hysteresis cycles with relative tangential displacement amplitudes in the sub-micrometer range at about 50 MPa nominal normal pressure, which is maintained well over the tangential load cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12838v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Fochler, Stefan Schwarz, Lukas Kohlmann, Malte Krack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication-Efficient Distributed Kalman Filtering using ADMM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13003v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of optimal linear filtering in a network of local estimators, commonly referred to as distributed Kalman filtering (DKF). The DKF problem is formulated within a distributed optimization framework, where coupling constraints require the exchange of local state and covariance updates between neighboring nodes to achieve consensus. To address these constraints, the problem is transformed into an unconstrained optimization form using the augmented Lagrangian method. The distributed alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) is then applied to derive update steps that achieve the desired performance while exchanging only the primal variables. Notably, the proposed method enhances communication efficiency by eliminating the need for dual variable exchange. We show that the design parameters depend on the maximum eigenvalue of the network's Laplacian matrix, yielding a significantly tighter bound compared to existing results. A rigorous convergence analysis is provided, proving that the state estimates converge to the true state and that the covariance matrices across all local estimators converge to a globally optimal solution. Numerical results are presented to validate the efficacy of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13003v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Iqbal, Kundan Kumar, Simo S\"arkk\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which Sensor to Observe? Timely Tracking of a Joint Markov Source with Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the problem of remote estimation of a discrete-time joint Markov process using multiple sensors. Each sensor observes a different component of the joint Markov process, and in each time slot, the monitor obtains a partial state value by sending a pull request to one of the sensors. The monitor chooses the sequence of sensors to observe with the goal of minimizing the mean of age of incorrect information (MAoII) by using the partial state observations obtained, which have different freshness levels. For instance, a monitor may be interested in tracking the location of an object by obtaining observations from two sensors, which observe the $x$ and $y$ coordinates of the object separately, in different time slots. The monitor, then, needs to decide which coordinate to observe in the next time slot given the history. In addition to this partial observability of the state of Markov process, there is an erasure channel with a fixed one-slot delay between each sensor and the monitor. First, we obtain a sufficient statistic, namely the \emph{belief}, representing the joint distribution of the age of incorrect information (AoII) and the current state of the observed process by using the history of all pull requests and observations. Then, we formulate the problem with a continuous state-space Markov decision problem (MDP), namely belief MDP. To solve the problem, we propose two model predictive control (MPC) methods, namely MPC without terminal costs (MPC-WTC) and reinforcement learning MPC (RL-MPC), that have different advantages in implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismail Cosandal, Sennur Ulukus, Nail Akar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Graph Signal Processing Perspective of Network Multiple Hypothesis Testing with False Discovery Rate Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03142v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a multiple hypothesis testing problem in a sensor network over the joint spatio-temporal domain. The sensor network is modeled as a graph, with each vertex representing a sensor and a signal over time associated with each vertex. We assume a hypothesis test and an associated $p$-value for every sample point in the joint spatio-temporal domain. Our goal is to determine which points have true alternative. By parameterizing the unknown $p$-value distribution under the alternative and the prior probabilities of hypotheses being null with a bandlimited generalized graph signal, we can obtain consistent estimates for them. Consequently, we also obtain an estimate of the local false discovery rates (lfdr). We prove that by using a step-up procedure on the estimated lfdr, we can achieve asymptotic false discovery rate control at a pre-determined level. Numerical experiments validate the effectiveness of our approach compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03142v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingchao Jian, Martin G\"olz, Feng Ji, Wee Peng Tay, Abdelhak M. Zoubir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Hybrid Beamforming Designs for ELAA Near-Field Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03560v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Extremely large-scale antenna array (ELAA) is a key candidate technology for the sixth generation (6G) mobile networks. Nevertheless, using substantial numbers of antennas to transmit high-frequency signals in ELAA systems significantly exacerbates the near-field effect. Unfortunately, traditional hybrid beamforming schemes are highly vulnerable to ELAA near-field communications. To effectively mitigate severe near-field effect, we propose a novel dynamic hybrid beamforming architecture for ELAA systems, in which each antenna is either adaptively connected to one radio frequency (RF) chain for signal transmission or deactivated for power saving. For the case that instantaneous channel state information (CSI) is available during each channel coherence time, a real-time dynamic hybrid beamforming design is developed to maximize the achievable sum rate under the constraints of the constant modulus of phase-shifters (PSs), non-overlapping dynamic connection network and total transmit power. When instantaneous CSI cannot be easily obtained in real-time, we propose a two-timescale dynamic hybrid beamforming design, which optimizes analog beamformer in long-timescale and digital beamformer in short-timescale, with the goal of maximizing ergodic sum-rate under the same constraints. Simulation results demonstrate the advantages of the proposed dynamic hybrid beamforming architecture and the effectiveness of the developed algorithms for ELAA near-field communications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03560v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengzhen Liu, Ming Li, Rang Liu, Qian Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchronization for Multiuser Uplink OTFS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10740v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose time and frequency synchronization techniques for the uplink of multiuser orthogonal time frequency space (MU-OTFS) in high-mobility scenarios. We introduce a spectrally efficient and practical pilot pattern where each user utilizes a pilot with a cyclic prefix (PCP) within a shared pilot region on the delay-Doppler plane. At the receiver, a bank of filters is deployed to separate the users' signals and accurately estimate their timing offsets (TOs) and carrier frequency offsets (CFOs). Our technique employs a threshold-based approach that provides precise TO estimates. Our proposed CFO estimation technique reduces the multi-dimensional maximum likelihood (ML) search problem into multiple one-dimensional search problems. Furthermore, we apply the Chebyshev polynomials of the first kind basis expansion model (CPF-BEM) to effectively handle the time-variations of the channel in obtaining the CFO estimates for all the users. Finally, we numerically investigate the error performance of our proposed synchronization technique in high mobility scenarios for the MU-OTFS uplink. Our simulation results confirm the efficacy of the proposed technique in estimating the TOs and CFOs which also leads to an improved channel estimation performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10740v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Bayat, Sanoopkumar P. S., Arman Farhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capacity Maximization for MIMO Channels Assisted by Beyond-Diagonal RIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) can improve the capacity of wireless communication links by passively beamforming the impinging signals in desired directions. This feature has been demonstrated both analytically and experimentally for conventional RISs, consisting of independently reflecting elements. To further enhance reconfigurability, a new architecture called beyond-diagonal RIS (BD-RIS) has been proposed. It allows for controllable signal flows between RIS elements, resulting in a non-diagonal reflection matrix, unlike the conventional RIS architecture. Previous studies on BD-RIS-assisted communications have predominantly considered single-antenna transmitters/receivers. One recent work provides an iterative capacity-improving algorithm for multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) setups but without providing geometrical insights.
  In this paper, we derive the first closed-form capacity-maximizing BD-RIS reflection matrix for a MIMO channel. We describe how this solution pairs together propagation paths, how it behaves when the signal-to-noise ratio is high, and what capacity is achievable with ideal semi-unitary channel matrices. The analytical results are corroborated numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18298v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emil Bj\"ornson, \"Ozlem Tu\u{g}fe Demir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SE(3)-Based Trajectory Optimization and Target Tracking in UAV-Enabled ISAC Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11687v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to enhance sensing capabilities in UAV-enabled MIMO-OFDM ISAC systems by leveraging UAV mobility as a mono-static radar. By integrating uniform planar arrays (UPAs) and modeling the UAV dynamics in $SE(3)$, we address key challenges such as 3D space sensing and trajectory design. We propose a target tracking scheme using extended Kalman filtering (EKF) in $SE(3)$, along with trajectory optimization based on the conditional Posterior Cramer-Rao bound (CPCRB). Numerical results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed trajectory design in enhancing performance of target tracking and physical parameter estimation in UAV-enabled MIMO-OFDM ISAC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11687v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongxiao Xu, Xinyang Li, Vlad C. Andrei, Moritz Wiese, Ullrich J. Moenich, Holger Boche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Structural Shifts in Multivariate Hawkes Processes with Fr\'echet Statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06769v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a new approach for change point detection in multivariate Hawkes processes using Fr\'echet statistic of a network. The method splits the point process into overlapping windows, estimates kernel matrices in each window, and reconstructs the signed Laplacians by treating the kernel matrices as the adjacency matrices of the causal network. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our method through experiments on both simulated and cryptocurrency datasets. Our results show that our method is capable of accurately detecting and characterizing changes in the causal structure of multivariate Hawkes processes, and may have potential applications in fields such as finance and neuroscience. The proposed method is an extension of previous work on Fr\'echet statistics in point process settings and represents an important contribution to the field of change point detection in multivariate point processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06769v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Luo, Vikram Krishnamurthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Optimal MMSE Channel Estimation for One-Bit Quantized MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05536v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper focuses on the minimum mean squared error (MMSE) channel estimator for multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems with one-bit quantization at the receiver side. Despite its optimality and significance in estimation theory, the MMSE channel estimator has not been fully investigated in this context due to its general non-linearity and computational complexity. Instead, the typically suboptimal Bussgang linear MMSE (BLMMSE) estimator has been widely adopted. In this work, we develop a new framework to compute the MMSE channel estimator that hinges on computation of the orthant probability of the multivariate normal distribution. Based on this framework, we determine a necessary and sufficient condition for the BLMMSE channel estimator to be optimal and equivalent to the MMSE estimator. Under the assumption of specific channel correlation or pilot symbols, we further utilize the framework to derive analytical expressions for the MMSE channel estimator that are particularly convenient for computation when certain system dimensions become large, thereby enabling a comparison between the BLMMSE and MMSE channel estimators in these cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05536v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minhua Ding, Italo Atzeni, Antti T\"olli, A. Lee Swindlehurst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficient Transmission Parameters Selection Method Using Reinforcement Learning in Distributed LoRa Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11270v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the increase in demand for Internet of Things (IoT) applications, the number of IoT devices has drastically grown, making spectrum resources seriously insufficient. Transmission collisions and retransmissions increase power consumption. Therefore, even in long-range (LoRa) networks, selecting appropriate transmission parameters, such as channel and transmission power, is essential to improve energy efficiency. However, due to the limited computational ability and memory, traditional transmission parameter selection methods for LoRa networks are challenging to implement on LoRa devices. To solve this problem, a distributed reinforcement learning-based channel and transmission power selection method is proposed, which can be implemented on the LoRa devices to improve energy efficiency in this paper. Specifically, the channel and transmission power selection problem in LoRa networks is first mapped to the multi-armed-bandit (MAB) problem. Then, an MAB-based method is introduced to solve the formulated transmission parameter selection problem based on the acknowledgment (ACK) packet and the power consumption for data transmission of the LoRa device. The performance of the proposed method is evaluated by the constructed actual LoRa network. Experimental results show that the proposed method performs better than fixed assignment, adaptive data rate low-complexity (ADR-Lite), and $\epsilon$-greedy-based methods in terms of both transmission success rate and energy efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11270v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotai Airiyoshi, Mikio Hasegawa, Tomoaki Ohtsuki, Aohan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenEarthMap-SAR: A Benchmark Synthetic Aperture Radar Dataset for Global High-Resolution Land Cover Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10891v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: High-resolution land cover mapping plays a crucial role in addressing a wide range of global challenges, including urban planning, environmental monitoring, disaster response, and sustainable development. However, creating accurate, large-scale land cover datasets remains a significant challenge due to the inherent complexities of geospatial data, such as diverse terrain, varying sensor modalities, and atmospheric conditions. Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) imagery, with its ability to penetrate clouds and capture data in all-weather, day-and-night conditions, offers unique advantages for land cover mapping. Despite these strengths, the lack of benchmark datasets tailored for SAR imagery has limited the development of robust models specifically designed for this data modality. To bridge this gap and facilitate advancements in SAR-based geospatial analysis, we introduce OpenEarthMap-SAR, a benchmark SAR dataset, for global high-resolution land cover mapping. OpenEarthMap-SAR consists of 1.5 million segments of 5033 aerial and satellite images with the size of 1024$\times$1024 pixels, covering 35 regions from Japan, France, and the USA, with partially manually annotated and fully pseudo 8-class land cover labels at a ground sampling distance of 0.15--0.5 m. We evaluated the performance of state-of-the-art methods for semantic segmentation and present challenging problem settings suitable for further technical development. The dataset also serves the official dataset for IEEE GRSS Data Fusion Contest Track I. The dataset has been made publicly available at https://zenodo.org/records/14622048.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10891v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junshi Xia, Hongruixuan Chen, Clifford Broni-Bediako, Yimin Wei, Jian Song, Naoto Yokoya</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
