<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Markov Model Decoding for LDPC Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper proposes an iterative Hidden Markov Model (HMM) for decoding a Low Density Parity Check (LDPC) code. It is demonstrated that a first-order HMM provides a natural framework for the decoder. The HMM is time-homogeneous with a fixed transition matrix and is based on a random walk through the encoded frame bits. Each hidden state contains a pair of two encoded bits, and parity checks are naturally incorporated into the observation model. The paper shows that by implementing a forward-backward smoothing estimator for the hidden states, decoding is efficient and requires only a small number of iterations in most cases. The results show that the LDPC decoding threshold is significantly improved compared to belief propagation (BP) on a Tanner graph. Numerical results are presented showing that LDPC codes under the proposed decoder yield a frame error rate (FER) and decoding threshold comparable to that of a Polar code where Successive Cancellation List (SCL) - Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) decoding is deployed. This is shown to be achieved even if the frame length is short (on the order of $512$ bits or less) and a regular LDPC code is used. 1</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21872v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan C Olivier, Etienne Barnard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRB minimization for PASS Assisted ISAC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A multiple waveguide PASS assisted integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system is proposed, where the base station (BS) is equipped with transmitting pinching antennas (PAs) and receiving uniform linear array (ULA) antennas. The PASS-transmitting-ULA-receiving (PTUR) BS transmits the communication and sensing signals through the stretched PAs on waveguides and collects the echo sensing signals with the mounted ULA. Based on this configuration, a target sensing Cramer Rao Bound (CRB) minimization problem is formulated under communication quality-of-service (QoS) constraints, power budget constraints, and PA deployment constraints. An alternating optimization (AO) method is employed to address the formulated non-convex optimization problem. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed PASS assisted ISAC framework achieves superior performance over benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22181v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haochen Li, Ruikang Zhong, Jiayi Lei, Pan Zhiwen, Yuanwei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Deep Neural Network Codebook Approach for Near-Field Nulling Control Beam Focusing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a deep neural network (DNN) codebook approach for multi-user interference (MUI) mitigation in extremely large multiple-input multiple-output (XL-MIMO) systems operating in the near-field region. Unlike existing DNN-based nulling control beamforming (NCBF) methods that face scalability and complexity challenges, the proposed framework partitions the Fresnel region using correlation-based sampling and assigns a lightweight fully connected DNN model to each subsection. Each model is trained on beamforming weights generated using the linearly constrained minimum variance (LCMV) method, enabling accurate prediction of nulling control beam-focusing weights that simultaneously optimize the desired signal strength and suppress potential interference for both collinear and non-collinear user configurations. Simulation results show that the trained models achieve average phase and magnitude prediction errors of 0.085 radians and 0.52 dB, respectively, across 75 sample subsections. Full-wave simulations in Ansys HFSS further demonstrate that the proposed DNN codebook achieves interference suppression better than 31.64 dB, with a performance gap within 2 dB of the LCMV method, thereby validating its effectiveness in mitigating MUI while reducing computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22204v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadhossein Karimi, Yuanzhe Gong, Tho Le-Ngoc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacked Intelligent Metasurface-Enhanced Wideband Multiuser MIMO OFDM-IM Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Leveraging the multilayer realization of programmable metasurfaces, stacked intelligent metasurfaces (SIM) enable fine-grained wave-domain control. However, their wideband deployment is impeded by two structural factors: (i) a single, quasi-static SIM phase tensor must adapt to all subcarriers, and (ii) multiuser scheduling changes the subcarrier activation pattern frame by frame, requiring rapid reconfiguration. To address both challenges, we develop a SIM-enhanced wideband multiuser transceiver built on orthogonal frequency-division multiplexing with index modulation (OFDM-IM). The sparse activation of OFDM-IM confines high-fidelity equalization to the active tones, effectively widening the usable bandwidth. To make the design reliability-aware, we directly target the worst-link bit-error rate (BER) and adopt a max-min per-tone signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) as a principled surrogate, turning the reliability optimization tractable. For frame-rate inference and interpretability, we propose an unfolded projected-gradient-descent network (UPGD-Net) that double-unrolls across the SIM's layers and algorithmic iterations: each cell computes the analytic gradient from the cascaded precoder with a learnable per-iteration step size. Simulations on wideband multiuser downlinks show fast, monotone convergence, an evident layer-depth sweet spot, and consistent gains in worst-link BER and sum rate. By combining structural sparsity with a BER-driven, deep-unfolded optimization backbone, the proposed framework directly addresses the key wideband deficiencies of SIM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22327v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheao Li, Jiancheng An, Chau Yuen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Specific multi-emitter identification via multi-label learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Specific emitter identification leverages hardware-induced impairments to uniquely determine a specific transmitter. However, existing approaches fail to address scenarios where signals from multiple emitters overlap. In this paper, we propose a specific multi-emitter identification (SMEI) method via multi-label learning to determine multiple transmitters. Specifically, the multi-emitter fingerprint extractor is designed to mitigate the mutual interference among overlapping signals. Then, the multi-emitter decision maker is proposed to assign the all emitter identification using the previous extracted fingerprint. Experimental results demonstrate that, compared with baseline approach, the proposed SMEI scheme achieves comparable identification accuracy under various overlapping conditions, while operating at significantly lower complexity. The significance of this paper is to identify multiple emitters from overlapped signal with a low complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22396v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Chen, Boxiang He, Shilian Wang, Jing Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation of the Range Ambiguity Function in Near-field Sensing Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the range ambiguity function of near-field systems where bandwidth and near-field beamfocusing jointly determine the resolution. First, the general matched filter ambiguity function is derived and the near-field array factors of different antenna array geometries are introduced. Next, the near-field ambiguity function is approximated as a product of the range-dependent near-field array factor and the ambiguity function due to the utilized bandwidth and waveform. An approximation criterion based on the aperture-bandwidth product is formulated, and its accuracy is examined. Finally, the improvements to the ambiguity function offered by the near-field beamfocusing, as compared to the far-field case, are presented. The performance gains are evaluated in terms of resolution improvement offered by beamfocusing, peak-to-sidelobe and integrated-sidelobe level improvement. The gains offered by the near-field regime are shown to be range-dependent and substantial only in close proximity to the array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22423v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcin Wachowiak, Andr\'e Bourdoux, Sofie Pollin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Pruning Criteria for Fast SBL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sparse Bayesian learning (SBL) associates to each weight in the underlying linear model a hyperparameter by assuming that each weight is Gaussian distributed with zero mean and precision (inverse variance) equal to its associated hyperparameter. The method estimates the hyperparameters by marginalizing out the weights and performing (marginalized) maximum likelihood (ML) estimation. SBL returns many hyperparameter estimates to diverge to infinity, effectively setting the estimates of the corresponding weights to zero (i.e., pruning the corresponding weights from the model) and thereby yielding a sparse estimate of the weight vector.
  In this letter, we analyze the marginal likelihood as function of a single hyperparameter while keeping the others fixed, when the Gaussian assumptions on the noise samples and the weight distribution that underlies the derivation of SBL are weakened. We derive sufficient conditions that lead, on the one hand, to finite hyperparameter estimates and, on the other, to infinite ones. Finally, we show that in the Gaussian case, the two conditions are complementary and coincide with the pruning condition of fast SBL (F-SBL), thereby providing additional insights into this algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21572v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakob M\"oderl, Erik Leitinger, Bernard Henri Fleury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transabdominal Fetal Oximetry via Diffuse Optics: Principled Analysis and Demonstration in Pregnant Ovine Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diffuse optics has the potential to offer a substantial advancement in fetal health monitoring via enabling continuous measurement of fetal blood oxygen saturation (fSpO$_2$). Aiming to enhance the sensing accuracy and to elucidate the foundational limits of Transabdominal Fetal Oximetry (TFO) via diffuse optics, we introduce a theoretical derivation, and a comprehensive pipeline for fSpO$_2$ estimation from non-invasively sensed diffuse light intensity values, which are leveraged to analyze datasets obtained through both simulations and in-vivo experiments in gold standard large animal model of pregnancy. We propose the Exponential Pulsation Ratio (EPR) as a key feature, and develop machine-learning models to fuse the information collected across multiple detectors. Our proposed method demonstrates a Mean Absolute Error (MAE) of 4.81% and 6.85% with a Pearson's r correlation of 0.81 (p&lt;0.001) and 0.71 (p&lt;0.001) for estimation of fSpO$_2$ in simulated dataset and in-vivo dataset, respectively. Across both datasets, our method outperforms the existing approaches, enhancing the accuracy of the fSpO$_2$ estimation and demonstrates its viability as a supplemental technology for intrapartum fetal monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21594v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weitai Qian, Rishad Raiyan Joarder, Randall Fowler, Begum Kasap, Mahya Saffarpour, Kourosh Vali, Tailai Lihe, Aijun Wang, Diana Farmer, Soheil Ghiasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World's First Authenticated Satellite Pseudorange from Orbit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cryptographic Ranging Authentication is here! We present initial results on the Pulsar authenticated ranging service broadcast from space with Pulsar-0 utilizing a recording taken at Xona headquarters in Burlingame, CA. No assumptions pertaining to the ownership or leakage of encryption keys are required. This work discusses the Pulsar watermark design and security analysis. We derive the Pulsar watermark's probabilities of missed detection and false alarm, and we discuss the required receiver processing needed to utilize the Pulsar watermark. We present validation results of the Pulsar watermark utilizing the transmissions from orbit. Lastly, we provide results that demonstrate the spoofing detection efficacy with a spoofing scenario that incorporates the authentic transmissions from orbit. Because we make no assumption about the leakage of symmetric encryption keys, this work provides mathematical justification of the watermark's security, and our July 2025 transmissions from orbit, we claim the world's first authenticated satellite pseudorange from orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21601v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Anderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snapshot Synthetic Aperture Imaging with Boiling Speckle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21682v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light-based synthetic aperture (SA) imaging methods, such as Fourier Ptychography, have brought breakthrough high-resolution wide-field-of-view imaging capabilities to microscopy. While these technologies promise similar improvements in long-range imaging applications, macroscale light-based SA imaging is significantly more challenging. In this work, we first demonstrate that speckle noise is particularly problematic for light-based SA systems. Specifically, we prove that it is fundamentally impossible to perform SA imaging of fully diffuse scenes if one captures sequential measurements that suffer from per-measurement-independent speckle. We then develop a snapshot SA imaging method and aperture-phase-synchronization strategy that can overcome this limitation and enable SA imaging. Remarkably, we further demonstrate, in simulation, that speckle can be exploited to recover missing spatial frequency information in SA imaging systems with distributed, non-overlapping apertures. That is, one can use speckle to improve the resolution of an SA imaging system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21682v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janith B. Senanayaka, Christopher A. Metzler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Parallel Ultra-Low Power Silent Speech Interface based on a Wearable, Fully-dry EMG Neckband</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a wearable, fully-dry, and ultra-low power EMG system for silent speech recognition, integrated into a textile neckband to enable comfortable, non-intrusive use. The system features 14 fully-differential EMG channels and is based on the BioGAP-Ultra platform for ultra-low power (22 mW) biosignal acquisition and wireless transmission. We evaluate its performance on eight speech commands under both vocalized and silent articulation, achieving average classification accuracies of 87$\pm$3% and 68$\pm$3% respectively, with a 5-fold CV approach. To mimic everyday-life conditions, we introduce session-to-session variability by repositioning the neckband between sessions, achieving leave-one-session-out accuracies of 64$\pm$18% and 54$\pm$7% for the vocalized and silent experiments, respectively. These results highlight the robustness of the proposed approach and the promise of energy-efficient silent-speech decoding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21964v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fiona Meier, Giusy Spacone, Sebastian Frey, Luca Benini, Andrea Cossettini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multicollinearity-Aware Parameter-Free Strategy for Hyperspectral Band Selection: A Dependence Measures-Based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21973v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hyperspectral bands offer rich spectral and spatial information; however, their high dimensionality poses challenges for efficient processing. Band selection (BS) methods aim to extract a smaller subset of bands to reduce spectral redundancy. Existing approaches, such as ranking-based, clustering-based, and iterative methods, often suffer from issues like sensitivity to initialization, parameter tuning, and high computational cost. This work introduces a BS strategy integrating three dependence measures: Average Band Correlation (ABC) and Mutual Information (MI), and Variance Inflation Factor (VIF). ABC quantifies linear correlations between spectral bands, while MI measures uncertainty reduction relative to ground truth labels. To address multicollinearity and reduce the search space, the approach first applies a VIF-based pre-selection of spectral bands. Subsequently, a clustering algorithm is used to identify the optimal subset of bands based on the ABC and MI values. Unlike previous methods, this approach is completely parameter-free for hyperspectral band selection, eliminating the need for optimal parameter estimation. The proposed method is evaluated on four standard benchmark datasets: WHU-Hi-LongKou, Pavia University, Salinas, and Oil Spill datasets, and is compared to existing state-of-the-art approaches. There is significant overlap between the bands identified by our proposed method and those selected by other methods, indicating that our approach effectively captures the most relevant spectral features. Further, support vector machine (SVM) classification validates that VIF-driven pruning enhances classification by minimizing multicollinearity. Ablation studies confirm that combining ABC with MI yields robust, discriminative band subsets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21973v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyabha Deb, Ujjwal Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel Regression of Multi-Way Data via Tensor Trains with Hadamard Overparametrization: The Dynamic Graph Flow Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A regression-based framework for interpretable multi-way data imputation, termed Kernel Regression via Tensor Trains with Hadamard overparametrization (KReTTaH), is introduced. KReTTaH adopts a nonparametric formulation by casting imputation as regression via reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces. Parameter efficiency is achieved through tensors of fixed tensor-train (TT) rank, which reside on low-dimensional Riemannian manifolds, and is further enhanced via Hadamard overparametrization, which promotes sparsity within the TT parameter space. Learning is accomplished by solving a smooth inverse problem posed on the Riemannian manifold of fixed TT-rank tensors. As a representative application, the estimation of dynamic graph flows is considered. In this setting, KReTTaH exhibits flexibility by seamlessly incorporating graph-based (topological) priors via its inverse problem formulation. Numerical tests on real-world graph datasets demonstrate that KReTTaH consistently outperforms state-of-the-art alternatives-including a nonparametric tensor- and a neural-network-based methods-for imputing missing, time-varying edge flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22197v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duc Thien Nguyen, Konstantinos Slavakis, Eleftherios Kofidis, Dimitris Pados</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a more realistic evaluation of machine learning models for bearing fault diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reliable detection of bearing faults is essential for maintaining the safety and operational efficiency of rotating machinery. While recent advances in machine learning (ML), particularly deep learning, have shown strong performance in controlled settings, many studies fail to generalize to real-world applications due to methodological flaws, most notably data leakage. This paper investigates the issue of data leakage in vibration-based bearing fault diagnosis and its impact on model evaluation. We demonstrate that common dataset partitioning strategies, such as segment-wise and condition-wise splits, introduce spurious correlations that inflate performance metrics. To address this, we propose a rigorous, leakage-free evaluation methodology centered on bearing-wise data partitioning, ensuring no overlap between the physical components used for training and testing. Additionally, we reformulate the classification task as a multi-label problem, enabling the detection of co-occurring fault types and the use of prevalence-independent metrics such as Macro AUROC. Beyond preventing leakage, we also examine the effect of dataset diversity on generalization, showing that the number of unique training bearings is a decisive factor for achieving robust performance. We evaluate our methodology on three widely adopted datasets: CWRU, Paderborn University (PU), and University of Ottawa (UORED-VAFCLS). This study highlights the importance of leakage-aware evaluation protocols and provides practical guidelines for dataset partitioning, model selection, and validation, fostering the development of more trustworthy ML systems for industrial fault diagnosis applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22267v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Paulo Vieira, Victor Afonso Bauler, Rodrigo Kobashikawa Rosa, Danilo Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Associative Memory via Online Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An associative memory (AM) enables cue-response recall, and associative memorization has recently been noted to underlie the operation of modern neural architectures such as Transformers. This work addresses a distributed setting where agents maintain a local AM to recall their own associations as well as selective information from others. Specifically, we introduce a distributed online gradient descent method that optimizes local AMs at different agents through communication over routing trees. Our theoretical analysis establishes sublinear regret guarantees, and experiments demonstrate that the proposed protocol consistently outperforms existing online optimization baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22321v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Wang, Matteo Zecchin, Osvaldo Simeone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio-PPG: photoplethysmogram digital twin synthesis using deep neural representation of 6G/WiFi ISAC signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22326v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Digital twins for 1D bio-signals enable real-time monitoring of physiological processes of a person, which enables early disease diagnosis and personalized treatment. This work introduces a novel non-contact method for digital twin (DT) photoplethysmogram (PPG) signal synthesis under the umbrella of 6G/WiFi integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) systems. We employ a software-defined radio (SDR) operating at 5.23 GHz that illuminates the chest of a nearby person with a wideband 6G/WiFi signal and collects the reflected signals. This allows us to acquire Radio-PPG dataset that consists of 300 minutes worth of near synchronous 64-channel radio data, PPG data, along with the labels (three body vitals) of 30 healthy subjects. With this, we test two artificial intelligence (AI) models for DT-PPG signal synthesis: i) discrete cosine transform followed by a multi-layer perceptron, ii) two U-NET models (Approximation network, Refinement network) in cascade, along with a custom loss function. Experimental results indicate that U-NET model achieves an impressive relative mean absolute error of 0.194 with a small ISAC sensing overhead of 15.62%, for DT-PPG synthesis. Furthermore, we performed quality assessment of the synthetic DT-PPG by computing the accuracy of DT-PPG-based vitals estimation and feature extraction, which turned out to be at par with that of reference PPG-based vitals estimation and feature extraction. This work highlights the potential of generative AI and 6G/WiFi ISAC technologies and serves as a foundational step towards the development of non-contact screening tools for covid-19, cardiovascular diseases and well-being assessment of people with special needs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22326v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Israel Jesus Santos Filho, Muhammad Mahboob Ur Rahman, Taous-Meriem Laleg-Kirati, Tareq Al-Naffouri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UAV-Enabled Fluid Antenna Systems for Multi-Target Wireless Sensing over LAWCNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22497v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fluid antenna system (FAS) is emerging as a key technology for enhancing spatial flexibility and sensing accuracy in future wireless systems. This paper investigates an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV)-enabled FAS for multi-target wireless sensing in low-altitude wireless consumer networks (LAWCNs) for achieving the low-altitude economy (LAE) missions. We formulate an optimization problem aimed at minimizing the average Cram\'er-Rao bound (CRB) for multiple target estimations. To tackle this non-convex problem, an efficient alternating optimization (AO) algorithm is proposed, which jointly optimizes the UAV trajectory, the antenna position of the transmit fluid antennas (FAs) and the receive FAs, and the transmit beamforming at the UAV. Simulation results demonstrate significant performance improvements in estimation accuracy and sensing reliability compared to conventional schemes, e.g., the fixed position antenna scheme. The proposed system achieves enhanced sensing performance through adaptive trajectory design and beamforming, alongside effective interference suppression via the flexible FAS antenna repositioning, underscoring its practical potential for precision sensing in the UAV-enabled LAWCNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22497v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuhui Zhang, Wenchao Liu, Chunjie Wang, Jinke Ren, Huijun Xing, Shuqiang Wang, Yanyan Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECHO: Toward Contextual Seq2Seq Paradigms in Large EEG Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electroencephalography (EEG), with its broad range of applications, necessitates models that can generalize effectively across various tasks and datasets. Large EEG Models (LEMs) address this by pretraining encoder-centric architectures on large-scale unlabeled data to extract universal representations. While effective, these models lack decoders of comparable capacity, limiting the full utilization of the learned features. To address this issue, we introduce ECHO, a novel decoder-centric LEM paradigm that reformulates EEG modeling as sequence-to-sequence learning. ECHO captures layered relationships among signals, labels, and tasks within sequence space, while incorporating discrete support samples to construct contextual cues. This design equips ECHO with in-context learning, enabling dynamic adaptation to heterogeneous tasks without parameter updates. Extensive experiments across multiple datasets demonstrate that, even with basic model components, ECHO consistently outperforms state-of-the-art single-task LEMs in multi-task settings, showing superior generalization and adaptability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu Liu, Yuqiu Deng, Tianyu Liu, Jinan Zhou, Xinliang Zhou, Ziyu Jia, Yi Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Subarray Segmentation: A New Paradigm of Spatial Non-Stationary Near-Field Channel Estimation for XL-MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04211v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To address the complexities of spatial non-stationary (SnS) effects and spherical wave propagation in near-field channel estimation (CE) for extremely large-scale multiple-input multiple-output (XL-MIMO) systems, this paper proposes an SnS-aware CE framework based on adaptive subarray partitioning. We first investigate spherical wave propagation and various SnS characteristics and construct an SnS near-field channel model for XL-MIMO systems. Due to the limitations of uniform array partitioning in capturing SnS, we analyze the adverse effects of the non-ideal array segmentation (over- and under-segmentation) on CE accuracy. To counter these issues, we develop a dynamic hybrid beamforming-assisted power-based subarray segmentation paradigm (DHBF-PSSP), which integrates power measurements with a dynamic hybrid beamforming structure to enable joint subarray partitioning and decoupling. A power-adaptive subarray segmentation (PASS) algorithm leverages the statistical properties of power profiles, while subarray decoupling is achieved via a subarray segmentation-based sampling method (SS-SM) under radio frequency (RF) chain constraints. For subarray CE, we propose a subarray segmentation-based assorted block sparse Bayesian learning algorithm under the multiple measurement vectors framework (SS-ABSBL-MMV). This algorithm exploits angular-domain block sparsity under a discrete Fourier transform (DFT) codebook and inter-subcarrier structured sparsity. Simulation results confirm that the proposed framework outperforms existing methods in CE performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04211v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhang Yang, Puguang An, Peng Yang, Xianbin Cao, Dapeng Oliver Wu, Tony Q. S. Quek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hybrid Approach for Extending Automotive Radar Operation to NLOS Urban Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05413v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Automotive radar is a key component of sensing suites in autonomous driving (AD) and advanced driver-assist systems (ADAS). However, limited line-of-sight (LOS) significantly reduces radar efficiency in dense urban environments. Therefore, automotive radars need to extend their capabilities beyond LOS by localizing occluding and reflective surfaces and non-line-of-sight (NLOS) targets. This work addresses the NLOS target localization challenge by revisiting the NLOS radar signal propagation model and introducing a hybrid localization approach. The proposed approach first detects and localizes reflective surfaces, then identifies the LOS/NLOS propagation conditions, and finally localizes the target without prior scene knowledge, without using Doppler information, and without any auxiliary sensors. The proposed hybrid approach addresses the computational complexity challenge by integrating a physical radar electromagnetic wave propagation model with a deep neural network (DNN) to estimate occluding surface parameters. The efficiency of the proposed approach to localize the NLOS targets and to identify the NLOS/LOS propagation conditions is evaluated via simulations in a broad range of realistic automotive scenarios. Extending automotive radar sensing beyond LOS is expected to enhance the safety and reliability of autonomous and ADAS-equipped vehicles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05413v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAES.2025.3596572</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Trans. Aerosp. Electron. Syst., Early Access (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aviran Gal, Igal Bilik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attention-Enhanced Learning for Sensing-Assisted Long-Term Beam Tracking in mmWave Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Beam training and prediction in millimeter-wave communications are highly challenging due to fast time-varying channels and sensitivity to blockages and mobility. In this context, infrastructure-mounted cameras can capture rich environmental information that can facilitate beam tracking design. In this work, we develop an efficient attention-enhanced machine learning model for long-term beam tracking built upon convolutional neural networks and gated recurrent units to predict both current and future beams from past observed images. The integrated temporal attention mechanism substantially improves its predictive performance. Numerical results demonstrate that the proposed design achieves Top-5 beam prediction accuracies exceeding 90% across both current and six future time slots, significantly reducing overhead arising from sensing and processing for beam training. It further attains 97% of state-of-the-art performance with only 3% of the computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11725v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyuan Ma, Nhan Thanh Nguyen, Nir Shlezinger, Yonina C. Eldar, Markku Juntti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotatable Antenna Enabled Spectrum Sharing: Joint Antenna Orientation and Beamforming Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19912v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conventional antenna arrays rely primarily on digital beamforming for spatial control. While adding more elements can narrow beamwidth and suppress interference, such scaling incurs prohibitive hardware and power costs. Rotatable antennas (RAs), which allow mechanical or electronic adjustment of element orientations, introduce a new degree of freedom to exploit spatial flexibility without enlarging the array. By dynamically optimizing orientations, RAs can substantially improve desired link alignment and interference suppression. This paper investigates RA-enabled multiple-input single-output (MISO) interference channels under co-channel spectrum sharing and formulates a weighted sum-rate maximization problem that jointly optimizes transmit beamforming and antenna orientations. To tackle this nonconvex problem, we develop an alternating optimization (AO) framework that integrates weighted minimum mean-square error (WMMSE)-based beamforming with Frank-Wolfe-based orientation updates. To reduce complexity, we further study orientation optimization under maximum-ratio transmission (MRT) and zero-forcing (ZF) beamforming schemes. For finite-resolution actuators, we construct spherical Fibonacci codebooks and design a cross-entropy method (CEM)-based algorithm for discrete orientation selection. Simulations show that integrating RAs with conventional beamforming markedly increases weighted sum-rate, with gains rising with element directivity. Under discrete orientation control, the proposed CEM algorithm consistently outperforms the nearest-projection baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19912v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingxiang Peng, Qingqing Wu, Ziyuan Zheng, Wen Chen, Yanze Zhu, Ying Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Study of Low-Latency Video Streaming in an ORAN Setup with Generative AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12751v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Current Adaptive Bit Rate (ABR) methods react to network congestion after it occurs, causing application layer buffering and latency spikes in live video streaming. We introduce a proactive semantic control channel that enables coordination between Open Radio Access Network (ORAN) xApp, Mobile Edge computing (MEC), and User Equipment (UE) components for seamless live video streaming between mobile devices. When the transmitting UE experiences poor Uplink (UL) conditions, the MEC proactively instructs downscaling based on low-level RAN metrics, including channel SNR updated every millisecond, preventing buffering before it occurs. A Generative AI (GAI) module at the MEC reconstructs high-quality frames from downscaled video before forwarding to the receiving UE via the typically more robust Downlink (DL). Experimental validation on a live ORAN testbed with 50 video streams shows that our approach reduces latency tail behavior while achieving up to 4 dB improvement in PSNR and 15 points in VMAF compared to reactive ABR methods. The proactive control eliminates latency spikes exceeding 600 ms, demonstrating effective cross-layer coordination for latency-critical live video streaming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12751v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Casparsen, Van-Phuc Bui, Shashi Raj Pandey, Jimmy Jessen Nielsen, Petar Popovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Analysis of Fluid Antenna Multiple Access Assisted Wireless Powered Communication Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13405v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates a novel fluid antenna multiple access (FAMA)-assisted wireless powered communication network (WPCN), in which a hybrid access point (HAP) equipped with multiple fixed position antennas (FPAs) provides integrated data and energy transfer (IDET) services towards low-power devices that are equipped with a single fluid antenna (FA), while the low-power devices use harvested energy to power their own uplink transmission. Using the block correlation channel model, both the downlink and uplink wireless data transfer (WDT) outage probabilities are analyzed under specific port selection strategies, including downlink signal-to-interference ratio-based port selection (DSPS) strategy, downlink energy harvesting power-based port selection (DEPS) strategy, uplink signal-to-noise ratio-based port selection (USPS) strategy, and uplink channel-based port selection (UCPS) strategy. A step function approximation (SFA) approach is also relied upon to derive closed-form expressions for the outage probabilities, while the lower bounds for uplink WDT outage probabilities are also formulated. Numerical results demonstrate the validity of our theoretical analysis, which also provide useful guidelines for the system design through the analytical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13405v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Lin, Yizhe Zhao, Halvin Yang, Jie Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tokenizing Single-Channel EEG with Time-Frequency Motif Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Foundation models are reshaping EEG analysis, yet an important problem of EEG tokenization remains a challenge. This paper presents TFM-Tokenizer, a novel tokenization framework that learns a vocabulary of time-frequency motifs from single-channel EEG signals and encodes them into discrete tokens. We propose a dual-path architecture with time-frequency masking to capture robust motif representations, and it is model-agnostic, supporting both lightweight transformers and existing foundation models for downstream tasks. Our study demonstrates three key benefits: Accuracy: Experiments on four diverse EEG benchmarks demonstrate consistent performance gains across both single- and multi-dataset pretraining settings, achieving up to 17% improvement in Cohen's Kappa over strong baselines. Generalization: Moreover, as a plug-and-play component, it consistently boosts the performance of diverse foundation models, including BIOT and LaBraM. Scalability: By operating at the single-channel level rather than relying on the strict 10-20 EEG system, our method has the potential to be device-agnostic. Experiments on ear-EEG sleep staging, which differs from the pretraining data in signal format, channel configuration, recording device, and task, show that our tokenizer outperforms baselines by 14%. A comprehensive token analysis reveals strong class-discriminative, frequency-aware, and consistent structure, enabling improved representation quality and interpretability. Code is available at https://github.com/Jathurshan0330/TFM-Tokenizer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16060v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jathurshan Pradeepkumar, Xihao Piao, Zheng Chen, Jimeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOCO Codes Can Correct as Well: Error-Correction Constrained Coding for DNA Data Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01262v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As a medium for cold data storage, DNA stands out as it promises significant gains in storage capacity and lifetime. However, it comes with its own data processing challenges to overcome. Constrained codes over the DNA alphabet $\{A,T,G,C\}$ have been used to design DNA sequences that are free of long homopolymers to increase stability, yet effective error detection and error correction are required to achieve reliability in data retrieval. Recently, we introduced lexicographically-ordered constrained (LOCO) codes, namely DNA LOCO (D-LOCO) codes, with error detection. In this paper, we equip our D-LOCO codes with error correction for substitution errors via syndrome-like decoding, designated as residue decoding. We only use D-LOCO codewords of indices divisible by a suitable redundancy metric $R(m) &gt; 0$, where $m$ is the code length, for error correction. We provide the community with a construction of constrained codes forbidding runs of length higher than fixed $\ell \in \{1,2,3\}$ and $GC$-content in $\big [0.5-\frac{1}{2K},0.5+\frac{1}{2K}\big ]$ that correct $K$ segmented substitution errors, one per codeword. We call the proposed codes error-correction (EC) D-LOCO codes. We also give a list-decoding procedure with near-quadratic time-complexity in $m$ to correct double-substitution errors within EC D-LOCO codewords, which has $&gt; 98.20\%$ average success rate. The redundancy metric is projected to require $2\log_2(m)+O(1)$-bit allocation for a length-$m$ codeword. Hence, our EC D-LOCO codes are projected to be capacity-approaching with respect to the error-free constrained system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01262v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Canberk \.Irima\u{g}z{\i}, Ahmed Hareedy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repetitive TMS-based Identification of Methamphetamine-Dependent Individuals Using EEG Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11312v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The impact of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) on methamphetamine (METH) users' craving levels is often assessed using questionnaires. This study explores the feasibility of using neural signals to obtain more objective results. EEG signals recorded from 20 METH-addicted participants Before and After rTMS (MBT and MAT) and from 20 healthy participants (HC) are analyzed. In each EEG paradigm, participants are shown 15 METH-related and 15 neutral pictures randomly, and the relative band power (RBP) of each EEG sub-band frequency is derived. The average RBP across all 31 channels, as well as individual brain regions, is analyzed. Statistically, MAT's alpha, beta, and gamma RBPs are more like those of HC compared to MBT, as indicated by the power topographies. Utilizing a random forest (RF), the gamma RBP is identified as the optimal frequency band for distinguishing between MBT and HC with a 90% accuracy. The performance of classifying MAT versus HC is lower than that of MBT versus HC, suggesting that the efficacy of rTMS can be validated using RF with gamma RBP. Furthermore, the gamma RBP recorded by the TP10 and CP2 channels dominates the classification task of MBT versus HC when receiving METH-related image cues. The gamma RBP during exposure to METH-related cues can serve as a biomarker for distinguishing between MBT and HC and for evaluating the effectiveness of rTMS. Therefore, real-time monitoring of gamma RBP variations holds promise as a parameter for implementing a customized closed-loop neuromodulation system for treating METH addiction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11312v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JSEN.2025.3612041</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ziyi Zeng, Yun-Hsuan Chen, Xurong Gao, Wenyao Zheng, Hemmings Wu, Zhoule Zhu, Jie Yang, Chengkai Wang, Lihua Zhong, Weiwei Cheng, Mohamad Sawan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DualNILM: Energy Injection Identification Enabled Disaggregation with Deep Multi-Task Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14600v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-Intrusive Load Monitoring (NILM) offers a cost-effective method to obtain fine-grained appliance-level energy consumption in smart homes and building applications. However, the increasing adoption of behind-the-meter (BTM) energy sources such as solar panels and battery storage poses new challenges for conventional NILM methods that rely solely on at-the-meter data. The energy injected from the BTM sources can obscure the power signatures of individual appliances, leading to a significant decrease in NILM performance. To address this challenge, we present DualNILM, a deep multi-task learning framework designed for the dual tasks of appliance state recognition and injected energy identification. Using a Transformer-based architecture that integrates sequence-to-point and sequence-to-sequence strategies, DualNILM effectively captures multiscale temporal dependencies in the aggregate power consumption patterns, allowing for accurate appliance state recognition and energy injection identification. Extensive evaluation on self-collected and synthesized datasets demonstrates that DualNILM maintains an excellent performance for dual tasks in NILM, much outperforming conventional methods. Our work underscores the framework's potential for robust energy disaggregation in modern energy systems with renewable penetration. Synthetic photovoltaic augmented datasets with realistic injection simulation methodology will be open-sourced after review.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14600v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xudong Wang, Guoming Tang, Junyu Xue, Srinivasan Keshav, Tongxin Li, Chris Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling to Multimodal and Multichannel Heart Sound Classification: Fine-Tuning Wav2Vec 2.0 with Synthetic and Augmented Biosignals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11606v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cardiovascular diseases (CVDs) are the leading cause of death worldwide, accounting for approximately 17.9 million deaths each year. Early detection is critical, creating a demand for accurate and inexpensive pre-screening methods. Deep learning has recently been applied to classify abnormal heart sounds indicative of CVDs using synchronised phonocardiogram (PCG) and electrocardiogram (ECG) signals, as well as multichannel PCG (mPCG). However, state-of-the-art architectures remain underutilised due to the limited availability of synchronised and multichannel datasets. Augmented datasets and pre-trained models provide a pathway to overcome these limitations, enabling transformer-based architectures to be trained effectively. This work combines traditional signal processing with denoising diffusion models, WaveGrad and DiffWave, to create an augmented dataset to fine-tune a Wav2Vec 2.0-based classifier on multimodal and multichannel heart sound datasets. The approach achieves state-of-the-art performance. On the Computing in Cardiology (CinC) 2016 dataset of single channel PCG, accuracy, unweighted average recall (UAR), sensitivity, specificity and Matthew's correlation coefficient (MCC) reach 92.48%, 93.05%, 93.63%, 92.48%, 94.93% and 0.8283, respectively. Using the synchronised PCG and ECG signals of the training-a dataset from CinC, 93.14%, 92.21%, 94.35%, 90.10%, 95.12% and 0.8380 are achieved for accuracy, UAR, sensitivity, specificity and MCC, respectively. Using a wearable vest dataset consisting of mPCG data, the model achieves 77.13% accuracy, 74.25% UAR, 86.47% sensitivity, 62.04% specificity, and 0.5082 MCC. These results demonstrate the effectiveness of transformer-based models for CVD detection when supported by augmented datasets, highlighting their potential to advance multimodal and multichannel heart sound classification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11606v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milan Marocchi, Matthew Fynn, Kayapanda Mandana, Yue Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-Augmented Contrastive Learning: A Noise-Robust Encoder for Biosignal Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20048v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Learning robust representations for biosignals is often hampered by the challenge of designing effective data augmentations.Traditional methods can fail to capture the complex variations inherent in physiological data. Within this context, we propose a novel hybrid framework, Diffusion-Augmented Contrastive Learning (DACL), that fuses concepts from diffusion models and supervised contrastive learning. The DACL framework operates on a latent space created by a lightweight Variational Autoencoder (VAE) trained on our novel Scattering Transformer (ST) features [12]. It utilizes the diffusion forward process as a principled data augmentation technique to generate multiple noisy views of these latent embeddings. A U-Net style encoder is then trained with a supervised contrastive objective to learn a representation that balances class discrimination with robustness to noise across various diffusion time steps. We evaluated this proof-of-concept method on the PhysioNet 2017 ECG dataset, achieving a competitive AUROC of 0.7815. This work establishes a new paradigm for representation learning by using the diffusion process itself to drive the contrastive objective, creating noise-invariant embeddings that demonstrate a strong foundation for class separability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20048v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rami Zewail</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
