<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>COMET: Co-Optimization of a CNN Model using Efficient-Hardware OBC Techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) are highly effective for computer vision and pattern recognition tasks; however, their computational intensity and reliance on hardware such as FPGAs pose challenges for deployment on low-power edge devices. In this work, we present COMET, a framework of CNN designs that employ efficient hardware offset-binary coding (OBC) techniques to enable co-optimization of performance and resource utilization. The approach formulates CNN inference with OBC representations of inputs (Scheme A) and weights (Scheme B) separately, enabling exploitation of bit-width asymmetry. The shift-accumulate operation is modified by incorporating the offset term with the pre-scaled bias. Leveraging inherent symmetries in Schemes A and B, we introduce four novel look-up table (LUT) techniques -- parallel, shared, split, and hybrid -- and analyze them to identify the most efficient options. Building on this foundation, we develop an OBC-based general matrix multiplication core using the im2col transformation, enabling efficient acceleration of a fixed-point modified LeNet-5 model. FPGA evaluations demonstrate that the proposed co-optimization approach significantly reduces resource utilization compared to state-of-the-art LeNet-5 based CNN designs, with minimal impact on accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03516v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyang Chen, Mohd Tasleem Khan, George Goussetis, Mathini Sellathurai, Yuan Ding, Jo\~ao F. C. Mota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variable Block-Correlation Modeling and Optimization for Secrecy Analysis in Fluid Antenna Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fluid antenna systems (FAS) are emerging as a transformative enabler for sixth-generation (6G) wireless communications, providing unprecedented spatial diversity through dynamic reconfiguration of antenna ports. However, the inherent spatial correlation among ports poses significant challenges for accurate analysis. Conventional models such as Jakes are analytically intractable, while oversimplified constant-correlation models fail to capture the true behavior. In this work, we address these challenges by applying the variable block-correlation model (VBCM) -- originally proposed by Ram\'{i}rez-Espinosa \textit{et al.} in 2024 -- to FAS security analysis, and by developing comprehensive optimization methods to enhance analytical accuracy. We derive new closed-form expressions for average secrecy capacity (ASC) and secrecy outage probability (SOP), demonstrating that the VBCM framework achieves simulation-aligned accuracy, with relative errors consistently below $5\%$ (compared to $10$--$15\%$ for constant-correlation models). To maximize ASC, we further design two algorithms: a grid search (GS) method and a gradient descent (GD) method. Numerical results reveal that the VBCM-based approach not only provides reliable insights into FAS security performance, but also yields substantial gains -- ASC improvements exceeding $120\%$ in high-threat scenarios and $18$--$19\%$ performance enhancements for compact antenna configurations. These findings underscore the practical value of integrating VBCM into FAS security analysis and optimization, establishing it as a powerful tool for advancing 6G communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03594v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuo Wu, Kwai-Man Luk, Jie Tang, Kai-Kit Wong, Jianchao Zheng, Baiyang Liu, David Morales-Jimenez, Maged Elkashlan, Kin-Fai Tong, Chan-Byoung Chae, Fumiyuki Adachi, George K. Karagiannidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-Grid Equivalence of Continuous-Time Doubly Selective Channels: A Revisit of Bello's Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Significant studies on communications over doubly selective channels have utilized on-grid DD channel models, which are previously investigated in Bello's seminar paper in 1963. The DD grid is typically specified by the bandwidth and time duration of the transmission frames. However, the physical channels are determined by the propagation environments and they are typically off-grid. Hence, there is often a gap between an actual physical channel and the on-grid model. This paper revisits the on-grid modeling of practical physical channels. We study the associated on-grid DD-domain representations for continuous-time, doubly selective channels with off-grid delay and Doppler shifts, accounting for practical time/frequency-domain windowing at the transceivers. The universal models obtained are applicable under the mild assumption that the windows have finite supports, and they extend Bello's classical results to account for more general windows. We also discuss the features and implications of the equivalent on-grid models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03626v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pinching Antenna Systems (PASS) for Cell-Free Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A pinching antenna system (PASS) assisted cell-free communication system is proposed. A sum rate maximization problem under the BS power budget constraint and PA deployment constraint is formulated. To tackle the proposed non-convex optimization problem, an alternating optimization (AO) algorithm is developed. In particular, the digital beamforming sub-problem is solved using the weighted minimum mean square error (WMMSE) method, whereas the pinching beamforming sub-problem is handled via a penalty based approach combined with element-wise optimization. Simulation results demonstrate that: 1) the PASS assisted cell-free systems achieve superior performance over benchmark schemes; 2) increasing the number of PAs per waveguides can improve the advantage of PASS assisted cell-free systems; and 3) the cell-free architecture mitigates the average user rate degradation as the number of users increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03628v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haochen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Secure ISAC Beamforming: How Many Dedicated Sensing Beams Are Required?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, sensing-assisted secure communication in a multi-user multi-eavesdropper integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system is investigated. Confidential communication signals and dedicated sensing signals are jointly transmitted by a base station (BS) to simultaneously serve users and sense aerial eavesdroppers (AEs). A sum rate maximization problem is formulated under AEs' Signal-to-Interference-plus-Noise Ratio (SINR) and sensing Signal-to-Clutter-plus-Noise Ratio (SCNR) constraints. A fractional-programming-based alternating optimization algorithm is developed to solve this problem for fully digital arrays, where successive convex approximation (SCA) and semidefinite relaxation (SDR) are leveraged to handle non-convex constraints. Furthermore, the minimum number of dedicated sensing beams is analyzed via a worst-case rank bound, upon which the proposed beamforming design is further extended to the hybrid analog-digital (HAD) array architecture, where the unit-modulus constraint is addressed by manifold optimization. Simulation results demonstrate that only a small number of sensing beams are sufficient for both sensing and jamming AEs, and the proposed designs consistently outperform strong baselines while also revealing the communication-sensing trade-off.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03749v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fanghao Xia, Zesong Fei, Xinyi Wang, Nanchi Su, Zhaolin Wang, Yuanwei Liu, Jie Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Benchmark Study of Deep Learning Methods for Multi-Label Pediatric Electrocardiogram-Based Cardiovascular Disease Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is a major pediatric health burden, and early screening is of critical importance. Electrocardiography (ECG), as a noninvasive and accessible tool, is well suited for this purpose. This paper presents the first benchmark study of deep learning for multi-label pediatric CVD classification on the recently released ZZU-pECG dataset, comprising 3716 recordings with 19 CVD categories. We systematically evaluate four representative paradigms--ResNet-1D, BiLSTM, Transformer, and Mamba 2--under both 9-lead and 12-lead configurations. All models achieved strong results, with Hamming Loss as low as 0.0069 and F1-scores above 85% in most settings. ResNet-1D reached a macro-F1 of 94.67% on the 12-lead subset, while BiLSTM and Transformer also showed competitive performance. Per-class analysis indicated challenges for rare conditions such as hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in the 9-lead subset, reflecting the effect of limited positive samples. This benchmark establishes reusable baselines and highlights complementary strengths across paradigms. It further points to the need for larger-scale, multi-center validation, age-stratified analysis, and broader disease coverage to support real-world pediatric ECG applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03780v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqiao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Multiband Sensing in FR3: Frequency Anisotropy Characterization and Non-Contiguous Bands Aggregation Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03787v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frequency Range 3 (FR3) in the 7-24 GHz band will be the new spectrum for 6G wireless networks. The bandwidth availability and diversity of FR3 offer unprecedented opportunities for coherent multiband Integrated Sensing and Communications (ISAC), which aggregates the carrier phase information from multiple frequency bands to increase the sensing resolution to the cm-level. However, the frequency anisotropy of sensing targets over GHz-wide bands and the non-contiguity of the 6G spectrum, pose critical challenges to the application of existing multiband ISAC techniques. We present the first study on coherent multiband sensing in FR3. We experimentally characterize the frequency anisotropy of targets and propose new phase coherence metrics for multiband processing. Then, we analyze the impact of non-contiguous FR3 bands considered by 3GPP, and design a new algorithm to mitigate the resulting sensing artifacts, outperforming existing techniques. Our results represent a first step toward fully developing multiband ISAC for FR3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03787v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Pegoraro, Gianmaria Ventura, Dario Tagliaferri, Marco Mezzavilla, Andrea Bedin, Michele Rossi, Joerg Widmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Source PAC Coding for Low-latency Secret Key Generation in Short Blocklength Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Source polar coding is a potential solution for short blocklength-based low-latency key generation with limited sources, which is a critical aspect of six generation (6G) Internet of things. However, existing source coding schemes still suffer from significant degradation in key generation rate and reconciliation reliability in short blocklength regime. To address this issue, we introduce a multilevel source polarization-adjusted convolutional (PAC) coding framework. Furthermore, we propose a novel code construction algorithm that jointly leverages polarization effects and the maximum likelihood (ML) decoding error coefficient. Simulations demonstrate that the multilevel source PAC scheme with the proposed code construction achieves superior key generation rate under key disagreement constraints compared to conventional and multilevel source polar coding methods even in short blocklength regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03818v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lulu Song, Di Zhang, Tingting Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Frequency Resonating Based Magnetic Induction Underground Emergency Communications with Diverse Mediums</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic induction (MI) communication is an effective underground emergency communication technique after disasters such as landslides, mine collapses, and earthquakes, due to its advantages in mediums such as soil, concrete, and metals. However, the propagation mediums in practical MI based underground emergency communications are usually diverse and composed randomly due to the impact of disasters, which poses a challenge for MI communication in practical applications. In this paper, we formulate a statistical fading channel model, which reflects the random composition of diverse mediums and is shown to follow a lognormal distribution. To mitigate the impact of diverse medium fading, Multi-frequency Resonating Compensation (MuReC) based coils are used to achieve multiband transmission. Then, we analyze the performance of MuReC based multi-band MI communication with diverse medium fading and derive the expressions of signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) probability density functions, ergodic capacities, average bit error rates (BERs), and outage probabilities for both multiplexing and diversity cases. Numerical results show that MuReC based multiband transmission schemes can effectively reduce the impact of diverse medium fading and enhance the performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03848v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyu Wang, Zhichao Li, Wenchi Cheng, Wei Zhang, Hailin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Exact Sum PDF and CDF of {\alpha}-{\mu} Variates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sum of random variables (RVs) appears extensively in wireless communications, at large, both conventional and advanced, and has been subject of longstanding research. The statistical characterization of the referred sum is crucial to determine the performance of such communications systems. Although efforts have been undertaken to unveil these sum statistics, e.g., probability density function (PDF) and cumulative distribution function (CDF), no general efficient nor manageable solutions capable of evaluating the exact sum PDF and CDF are available to date. The only formulations are given in terms of either the multi-fold Brennan's integral or the multivariate Fox H-function. Unfortunately, these methods are only feasible up to a certain number of RVs, meaning that when the number of RVs in the sum increases, the computation of the sum PDF and CDF is subject to stability problems, convergence issues, or inaccurate results. In this paper, we derive new, simple, exact formulations for the PDF and CDF of the sum of L independent and identically distributed {\alpha}-{\mu} RVs. Unlike the available solutions, the computational complexity of our analytical expressions is independent of the number of summands. Capitalizing on our unprecedented findings, we analyze, in exact and asymptotic manners, the performance of L-branch pre-detection equal-gain combining and maximal-ratio combining receivers over {\alpha}-{\mu} fading environments. The coding and diversity gains of the system for both receivers are analyzed and quantified. Moreover, numerical simulations show that the computation time reduces drastically when using our expressions, which are arguably the most efficient and manageable formulations derived so far.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03850v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Dar\'io Almeida Garc\'ia, Francisco Raimundo Albuquerque Parente, Michel Daoud Yacoub, Jose C\^andido Silveira Santos Filho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Beamforming for Magnetic Induction Based Underground Emergency Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic induction (MI) communication is an effective underground emergency communication technique after disasters such as landslides, mine collapses, and earthquakes, due to its advantages in mediums such as soil, concrete, and metals. Based on channel state information (CSI), magnetic beamforming can significantly improve the performance of MI communication. However, in post-disaster underground communication, channel estimation may suffer from errors due to factors such as complex environmental interferences. Taking channel estimation error into account, we formulate a beamforming optimization problem for multi-user MI underground emergency communications, which aims to minimize the power consumption under the constraints of sum rate and signal to interference plus noise ratio (SINR) of each user. Based on the worst-case optimization criterion and the S-procedure, the non-convex optimization problem is transformed into convex and solved. Numerical results show that the proposed robust beamforming scheme can effectively enhance communication reliability and effective throughput in the presence of channel estimation errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03852v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyu Wang, Tianrui Hou, Wenchi Cheng, Hailin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Noise Robustness of Affine Frequency Division Multiplexing: Analysis and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the robustness of affine frequency division multiplexing (AFDM) and orthogonal time frequency space (OTFS) modulation schemes against non-white Gaussian noise, which can model various sources of additive disturbances to the received signal. The proposed approach demonstrates that the performance of these waveforms depends on the ability of the demodulation matrix to whiten the noise-a property that is, in turn, related to the sparsity of the matrix. AFDM is shown to outperform OTFS and orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM), as its demodulation matrix is generally less sparse than those of the other waveforms. Based on this analysis, several application examples and use cases are presented, such as the use of AFDM and OTFS in narrowband signals or in coexistence with OFDM signals. Finally, simulation results confirm that AFDM achieves better performance than OTFS and OFDM in the presence of non-white noise, with gains exceeding 1 dB in most application scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03901v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Savaux, Steve Sawadogo, Hyeon Seok Rou, Giuseppe Thadeu Freitas de Abreu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-form Solutions for Velocity and Acceleration of a Moving Vehicle Using Range, Range Rate, and Derivative of Range Rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04037v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter presents a novel method for estimating the position, velocity, and acceleration of a moving target using range-based measurements. Although most existing studies focus on position and velocity estimation, the framework of this letter is extended to include acceleration. To achieve this, we propose using the derivative of the range rate, in addition to the range and range rate measurements. The proposed method estimates the position at first using Time-of-Arrival (TOA)-based techniques; then, develops a reformulated least squares (LS) and weighted least squares (WLS) approaches for velocity estimation; and finally, employs the derivative of the range rate to estimate the acceleration using previous position and velocity estimates. On the other hand, closed-form LS and WLS solutions are derived for both velocity and acceleration. The simulation results show that the proposed approach provides improved performance in estimating moving target kinematics compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04037v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Salman, Hadi Zayyani, Hasan Abu Hilal, Mostafa Rashdan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLEAR: A Closed-Form Minimal-Sensor TDOA/FDOA Estimator for Moving-Source IoT Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents CLEAR -- a closed-form localization estimator with a reduced sensor network. The proposed method is a computationally efficient, two-stage estimator that fuses time-difference-of-arrival (TDOA) and frequency-difference-of-arrival (FDOA) measurements with a minimal number of sensors. CLEAR localizes a moving source in N-dimensional space using only N+1 sensors, achieving the theoretical minimum sensor count. The first stage introduces auxiliary range and range-rate parameters to construct a set of pseudo-linear equations, solved via weighted least squares. An algebraic elimination using Sylvester's resultant then reduces the problem to a quartic equation, yielding closed-form estimates for the nuisance variables. A second, lightweight linear refinement stage is applied to mitigate residual bias. Under mild Gaussian noise assumptions, the estimator's position and velocity estimates are statistically efficient, closely approaching the Cramer-Rao lower bound (CRLB). Extensive Monte Carlo simulations in 2-D and 3-D scenarios demonstrate CRLB-level accuracy and consistent performance gains over representative two-stage and iterative baselines, confirming the method's high suitability for power-constrained, distributed Internet of Things (IoT) applications such as UAV tracking and smart transportation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04160v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Kazzazi, Mohammad Morsali, Rouhollah Amiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Phase-Coherent Multistatic Imaging in Downlink D-MIMO Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04240v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the challenge of integrating multistatic coherent imaging functionalities in the downlink (DL) of a phase-coherent distributed multiple input multiple output (D-MIMO) communication network. During DL, the D-MIMO access points (APs) jointly precode the transmitted signals to maximize the spectral efficiency (SE) at the users (UEs) locations. However, imaging requires that \textit{(i)} a fraction of the APs work as receivers for sensing and \textit{(ii)} the transmitting APs emit AP-specific and orthogonal signals to illuminate the area to be imaged and allow multistatic operation. In these settings, our contribution is twofold. We propose a novel distributed integrated sensing and communication (D-ISAC) system that superposes a purposely designed AP-specific signal for imaging to the legacy UE-specific communication one, with a tunable trade-off factor. We detail both the imaging waveform design according to the \textit{extended orthogonality condition} and the space-frequency precoder design. Then, we propose an optimized selection strategy for the receiving APs, in order to maximize imaging performance under half-duplex constraints. Extensive numerical results prove the feasibility and benefits of our proposal, materializing the potential of joint multistatic imaging and communications in practical D-MIMO deployments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04240v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Tagliaferri, Silvia Mura, Musa Furkan Keskin, Sauradeep Dey, Henk Wymeersch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz Channel Measurement and Modeling for Short-Range Indoor Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate channel modeling is essential for realizing the potential of terahertz (THz) communications in 6G indoor networks, where existing models struggle with severe frequency selectivity and multipath effects. We propose a physically grounded Rician fading channel model that jointly incorporates deterministic line-of-sight (LOS) and stochastic non-line-of-sight (NLOS) components, enhanced by frequency-dependent attenuation characterized by optimized exponents alpha and beta. Unlike conventional approaches, our model integrates a two-ray reflection framework to capture standing wave phenomena and employs wideband spectral averaging to mitigate frequency selectivity over bandwidths up to 15 GHz. Empirical measurements at a 208 GHz carrier, spanning 0.1-0.9 m, demonstrate that our model achieves root mean square errors (RMSE) as low as 2.54 dB, outperforming free-space path loss (FSPL) by up to 14.2% and reducing RMSE by 73.3% as bandwidth increases. These findings underscore the importance of bandwidth in suppressing oscillatory artifacts and improving modeling accuracy. Our approach provides a robust foundation for THz system design, supporting reliable indoor wireless personal area networks (WPANs), device-to-device (D2D) communications, and precise localization in future 6G applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04258v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziang Zhao, Weixi Liang, Kai Hu, Qun Zhang, Xiongbin Yu, Qiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Domain Generalization in Wireless Networks with Scarce Multi-Modal Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 6G wireless networks, multi-modal ML models can be leveraged to enable situation-aware network decisions in dynamic environments. However, trained ML models often fail to generalize under domain shifts when training and test data distributions are different because they often focus on modality-specific spurious features. In practical wireless systems, domain shifts occur frequently due to dynamic channel statistics, moving obstacles, or hardware configuration. Thus, there is a need for learning frameworks that can achieve robust generalization under scarce multi-modal data in wireless networks. In this paper, a novel and data-efficient two-phase learning framework is proposed to improve generalization performance in unseen and unfamiliar wireless environments with minimal amount of multi-modal data. In the first stage, a physics-based loss function is employed to enable each BS to learn the physics underlying its wireless environment captured by multi-modal data. The data-efficiency of the physics-based loss function is analytically investigated. In the second stage, collaborative domain adaptation is proposed to leverage the wireless environment knowledge of multiple BSs to guide under-performing BSs under domain shift. Specifically, domain-similarity-aware model aggregation is proposed to utilize the knowledge of BSs that experienced similar domains. To validate the proposed framework, a new dataset generation framework is developed by integrating CARLA and MATLAB-based mmWave channel modeling to predict mmWave RSS. Simulation results show that the proposed physics-based training requires only 13% of data samples to achieve the same performance as a state-of-the-art baseline that does not use physics-based training. Moreover, the proposed collaborative domain adaptation needs only 25% of data samples and 20% of FLOPs to achieve the convergence compared to baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04359v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minsu Kim, Walid Saad, Dour Calin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Rank-Based Approximate Computation with Memristors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Memristor crossbars enable vector-matrix multiplication (VMM), and are promising for low-power applications. However, it can be difficult to write the memristor conductance values exactly. To improve the accuracy of VMM, we propose a scheme based on low-rank matrix approximation. Specifically, singular value decomposition (SVD) is first applied to obtain a low-rank approximation of the target matrix, which is then factored into a pair of smaller matrices. Subsequently, a two-step serial VMM is executed, where the stochastic write errors are mitigated through step-wise averaging. To evaluate the performance of the proposed scheme, we derive a general expression for the resulting computation error and provide an asymptotic analysis under a prescribed singular-value profile, which reveals how the error scales with matrix size and rank. Both analytical and numerical results confirm the superiority of the proposed scheme compared with the benchmark scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04402v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binyu Lu, Matthias Frey, Stark Draper, Jingge Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of nearby Metals on Electro-Quasistatic Human Body Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent decades Human Body Communication has emerged as a promising alternative to traditional radio wave communication, utilizing the body's conductive properties for low-power connectivity among wearables. This method harnesses the human body as an energy-efficient channel for data transmission within the electro-quasistatic frequency range, enabling advancements in human-machine interaction. While prior work has noted the role of parasitic return paths in such capacitively coupled systems, the influence of surrounding metallic objects on these paths, which are critical for EQS wireless signaling, has not been fully explored. This paper fills that gap with a structured study of how various conducting objects, from non-grounded (floating) metals and grounded metals to enclosed metallic environments such as elevators and cars, affect the body-communication channel. We present a theoretical framework supported by finite element method simulations and experiments with wearable devices. Results show that metallic objects within 20 cm of devices can reduce transmission loss by about 10 dB. When a device ground connects to a grounded metallic object, channel gain can increase by at least 20 dB. Contact area during touch-based interactions with grounded metals produces contact-impedance dependent high-pass channel characteristics. Proximity to metallic objects introduces variability within a critical distance, with grounded metals producing a larger overall effect than floating metals. These findings improve understanding of body-centric communication links and inform design for healthcare, consumer electronics, defense, and industrial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04409v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samyadip Sarkar, Arunashish Datta, David Yang, Mayukh Nath, Shovan Maity, Shreyas Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of ISAC in 6G Networks: Enabling Next-Generation Wireless Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The commencement of the sixth-generation (6G) wireless networks represents a fundamental shift in the integration of communication and sensing technologies to support next-generation applications. Integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) is a key concept in this evolution, enabling end-to-end support for both communication and sensing within a unified framework. It enhances spectrum efficiency, reduces latency, and supports diverse use cases, including smart cities, autonomous systems, and perceptive environments. This tutorial provides a comprehensive overview of ISAC's role in 6G networks, beginning with its evolution since 5G and the technical drivers behind its adoption. Core principles and system variations of ISAC are introduced, followed by an in-depth discussion of the enabling technologies that facilitate its practical deployment. The paper further analyzes current research directions to highlight key challenges, open issues, and emerging trends. Design insights and recommendations are also presented to support future development and implementation. This work ultimately try to address three central questions: Why is ISAC essential for 6G? What innovations does it bring? How will it shape the future of wireless communication?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04413v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Umar Farooq Qaisar, Weijie Yuan, Onur G\"unl\"u, Taneli Riihonen, Yuanhao Cui, Lin Zhang, Nuria Gonzalez-Prelcic, Marco Di Renzo, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Probing and Scheduling for Cache-Aided Hybrid Satellite-Terrestrial Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Caching is crucial in hybrid satellite-terrestrial networks to reduce latency, optimize throughput, and improve data availability by storing frequently accessed content closer to users, especially in bandwidth-limited satellite systems, requiring strategic Medium Access Control (MAC) layer. This paper addresses throughput optimization in satellite-terrestrial integrated networks through opportunistic cooperative caching. We propose a joint probing and scheduling strategy to enhance content retrieval efficiency. The strategy leverages the LEO satellite to probe satellite-to-ground links and cache states of multiple cooperative terrestrial stations, enabling dynamic user scheduling for content delivery. Using an optimal stopping theoretic approach with two levels of incomplete information, we make real-time decisions on satellite-terrestrial hybrid links and caching probing. Our threshold-based strategy optimizes probing and scheduling, significantly improving average system throughput by exploiting cooperative caching, satellite-terrestrial link transmission, and time diversity from dynamic user requests. Simulation results validate the effectiveness and practicality of the proposed strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04492v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Zhang, Yizhu Wang, Saman Atapattu, Sumei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Analysis for Multi-User Holographic MIMO Downlink with Matched Filter Precoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04530v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Holographic MIMO (HMIMO) has emerged as a promising solution for future wireless systems by enabling ultra-dense, spatially continuous antenna deployments. While prior studies have primarily focused on electromagnetic (EM) modeling or simulation-based performance analysis, a rigorous communication-theoretic framework remains largely unexplored. This paper presents the first analytical performance study of a multi-user HMIMO downlink system with matched filter (MF) precoding - a low-complexity baseline scheme. By incorporating multipath propagation, mutual coupling, and element excitation, we derive a novel closed-form expression for the MF signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) using an equivalent random variable model. Leveraging bivariate gamma distributions, we then develop tractable throughput approximations under full, partial, and no channel state information (CSI) scenarios. Additionally, we formulate a max-min beamforming problem to benchmark optimal user fairness performance. Numerical results validate the accuracy of the proposed framework and reveal that MF precoding achieves competitive performance with strong robustness to low SINR and CSI uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04530v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gayathri Shekar, Saman Atapattu, Prathapasinghe Dharmawansa, Kandeepan Sithamparanathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coordinated Beamforming for Networked Integrated Communication and Multi-TMT Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Networked integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) has gained significant attention as a promising technology for enabling next-generation wireless systems. To further enhance networked ISAC, delegating the reception of sensing signals to dedicated target monitoring terminals (TMTs) instead of base stations (BSs) offers significant advantages in terms of sensing capability and deployment flexibility. Despite its potential, the coordinated beamforming design for networked integrated communication and time-of-arrival (ToA)-based multi-TMT localization remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we present a comprehensive study to fill this gap. Specifically, we first establish signal models for both communication and localization, and, for the first time, derive a closed-form Cram\'er-Rao lower bound (CRLB) to characterize the localization performance. Subsequently, we exploit this CRLB to formulate two optimization problems, focusing on sensing-centric and communication-centric criteria, respectively. For the sensing-centric problem, we develop a globally optimal algorithm based on semidefinite relaxation (SDR) when each BS is equipped with more antennas than the total number of communication users. While for the communication-centric problem, we design a globally optimal algorithm for the single-BS case using bisection search. For the general case of both problems, we propose a unified successive convex approximation (SCA)-based algorithm, which is suboptimal yet efficient, and further extend it from single-target scenarios to more practical multi-target scenarios. Finally, simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed algorithms, reveal the intrinsic performance trade-offs between communication and localization, and further show that deploying more TMTs is always preferable to deploying more BSs in networked ISAC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04600v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meidong Xia, Zhenyao He, Wei Xu, Yongming Huang, Derrick Wing Kwan Ng, Naofal Al-Dhahir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensionally-Efficient Transmission and Storage of Unitary Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unitary matrices are the basis of a large number of signal processing applications. In many of these applications, finding ways to efficiently store, and even transmit these matrices, can significantly reduce memory and throughput requirements. In this work, we study the problem of efficient transmission and storage of unitary matrices. Specifically, we explicitly derive a dimensionally-efficient parametrization (DEP) for unitary matrices that allows identifying them with sequences of real numbers, where the dimension coincides with the dimension of the unitary group where they lie. We also characterize its inverse map that allows retrieving the original unitary matrices from their DEP. The proposed approach effectively allows halving the dimension with respect to naively considering all the entries of each unitary matrix, thus reducing the resources required to store and transmit these matrices. Furthermore, we show that the sequence of real numbers associated to the proposed DEP is bounded, and we delimit the interval where these numbers are contained, facilitating the implementation of quantization approaches with limited distortion. On the other hand, we outline ways to further reduce the dimension of the DEP when considering more restrictive constraints for matrices that show up in certain applications. The numerical results showcase the potential of the proposed approach in general settings, as well as in three specific applications of current interest for wireless communications research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04734v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Vidal Alegr\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilayer Non-Terrestrial Networks with Spectrum Access aided by Beyond-Diagonal RIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we study a multi-user NTN in which a satellite serves as the primary network and a high-altitude platform station (HAPS) operates as the secondary network, acting as a cognitive radio. To reduce the cost, complexity, and power consumption of conventional antenna arrays, we equip the HAPS with a transmissive BD-RIS antenna front end. We then formulate a joint optimization problem for the BD-RIS phase response and the HAPS transmit power allocation under strict per-user interference temperature constraints. To tackle the resulting highly nonconvex problem, we propose an alternating-optimization framework: the power-allocation subproblem admits a closed-form, water-filling-type solution derived from the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions, while the BD-RIS configuration is refined via Riemannian manifold optimization. Simulation results show significant gains in data rate and interference suppression over diagonal RIS-assisted benchmarks, establishing BD-RIS as a promising enabler for future multilayer NTNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04744v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wali Ullah Khan, Chandan Kumar Sheemar, Eva Lagunas, Xingwang Li, Symeon Chatzinotas, Petar Popovski, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interference Alignment for Multi-cluster Over-the-Air Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the main challenges facing Internet of Things (IoT) networks is managing interference caused by the large number of devices communicating simultaneously, particularly in multi-cluster networks where multiple devices simultaneously transmit to their respective receiver. Over-the-Air Computation (AirComp) has emerged as a promising solution for efficient real-time data aggregation, yet its performance suffers in dense, interference-limited environments. To address this, we propose a novel Interference Alignment (IA) scheme tailored for up-link AirComp systems. Unlike previous approaches, the proposed method scales to an arbitrary number $\sf K$ of clusters and enables each cluster to exploit half of the available channels, instead of only $\tfrac{1}{\sf K}$ as in time-sharing. In addition, we develop schemes tailored to scenarios where users are shared between adjacent clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04745v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Semp\'er\'e, Yue Bi, Yue Wu, Pengwenlong Gu, Selma Boumerdassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The IEEE Signal Processing Society's Leading Role in Developing Standards for Computational Imaging and Sensing: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In every imaging or sensing application, the physical hardware creates constraints that must be overcome or they limit system performance. Techniques that leverage additional degrees of freedom can effectively extend performance beyond the inherent physical capabilities of the hardware. An example includes synchronizing distributed sensors so as to synthesize a larger aperture for remote sensing applications. An additional example is integrating the communication and sensing functions in a wireless system through the clever design of waveforms and optimized resource management. As these technologies mature beyond the conceptual and prototype phase they will ultimately transition to the commercial market. Here, standards play a critical role in ensuring success. Standards ensure interoperability between systems manufactured by different vendors and define industry best practices for vendors and customers alike. The Signal Processing Society of the Institute for Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) plays a leading role in developing high-quality standards for computational sensing technologies through the working groups of the Synthetic Aperture Standards Committee (SASC). In this column we highlight the standards activities of the P3383 Performance Metrics for Integrated Sensing and Communication (ISAC) Systems Working Group and the P3343 Spatio-Temporal Synchronization of a Synthetic Aperture of Distributed Sensors Working Group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04913v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Bathelt, Benjamin Deutschmann, Hyeon Seok Rou, Kuranage Roche Rayan Ranasinghe, Giuseppe Thadeu Freitas de Abreu, Peter Vouras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady-State Spread Bounds for Graph Diffusion via Laplacian Regularisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study how far a diffusion process on a graph can drift from a designed starting pattern when that pattern is produced using Laplacian regularisation. Under standard stability conditions for undirected, entrywise nonnegative graphs, we give a closed-form, instance-specific upper bound on the steady-state spread, measured as the relative change between the final and initial profiles. The bound separates two effects: (i) an irreducible term determined by the graph's maximum node degree, and (ii) a design-controlled term that shrinks as the regularisation strength increases (following an inverse square-root law). This leads to a simple design rule: given any target limit on spread, one can choose a sufficient regularisation strength in closed form. Although one motivating application is array beamforming, where the initial pattern is the squared magnitude of the beamformer weights, the result applies to any scenario that first enforces Laplacian smoothness and then evolves by linear diffusion on a graph. Overall, the guarantee is non-asymptotic, easy to compute, and certifies how much steady-state deviation can occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04924v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ardavan Rahimian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Five Years of Faculty Career at the University of Delaware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short article, I would like to briefly summarize my research in the first 5 years in my university academia life in USA. I think that my research results obtained in these 5 years are the best in my career, at least which I like the most by myself. I wish that my experience in my junior academia career could be of some help to young researchers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05000v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Gen Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of a Virtual Imaging Framework for Investigating a Deep Learning-Based Reconstruction Method for 3D Quantitative Photoacoustic Computed Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03431v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantitative photoacoustic computed tomography (qPACT) is a promising imaging modality for estimating physiological parameters such as blood oxygen saturation. However, developing robust qPACT reconstruction methods remains challenging due to computational demands, modeling difficulties, and experimental uncertainties. Learning-based methods have been proposed to address these issues but remain largely unvalidated. Virtual imaging (VI) studies are essential for validating such methods early in development, before proceeding to less-controlled phantom or in vivo studies. Effective VI studies must employ ensembles of stochastically generated numerical phantoms that accurately reflect relevant anatomy and physiology. Yet, most prior VI studies for qPACT relied on overly simplified phantoms. In this work, a realistic VI testbed is employed for the first time to assess a representative 3D learning-based qPACT reconstruction method for breast imaging. The method is evaluated across subject variability and physical factors such as measurement noise and acoustic aberrations, offering insights into its strengths and limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03431v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Refik Mert Cam, Seonyeong Park, Umberto Villa, Mark A. Anastasio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MECKD: Deep Learning-Based Fall Detection in Multilayer Mobile Edge Computing With Knowledge Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rising aging population has increased the importance of fall detection (FD) systems as an assistive technology, where deep learning techniques are widely applied to enhance accuracy. FD systems typically use edge devices (EDs) worn by individuals to collect real-time data, which are transmitted to a cloud center (CC) or processed locally. However, this architecture faces challenges such as a limited ED model size and data transmission latency to the CC. Mobile edge computing (MEC), which allows computations at MEC servers deployed between EDs and CC, has been explored to address these challenges. We propose a multilayer MEC (MLMEC) framework to balance accuracy and latency. The MLMEC splits the architecture into stations, each with a neural network model. If front-end equipment cannot detect falls reliably, data are transmitted to a station with more robust back-end computing. The knowledge distillation (KD) approach was employed to improve front-end detection accuracy by allowing high-power back-end stations to provide additional learning experiences, enhancing precision while reducing latency and processing loads. Simulation results demonstrate that the KD approach improved accuracy by 11.65% on the SisFall dataset and 2.78% on the FallAllD dataset. The MLMEC with KD also reduced the data latency rate by 54.15% on the FallAllD dataset and 46.67% on the SisFall dataset compared to the MLMEC without KD. In summary, the MLMEC FD system exhibits improved accuracy and reduced latency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03601v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JSEN.2024.3456577</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Sensors Journal, vol. 24, no. 24, pp. 42195-42209, Dec., 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Lung Mao, Chun-Chi Wang, Po-Heng Chou, Kai-Chun Liu, Yu Tsao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lightweight and Generalizable Acoustic Scene Representations via Contrastive Fine-Tuning and Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03728v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Acoustic scene classification (ASC) models on edge devices typically operate under fixed class assumptions, lacking the transferability needed for real-world applications that require adaptation to new or refined acoustic categories. We propose ContrastASC, which learns generalizable acoustic scene representations by structuring the embedding space to preserve semantic relationships between scenes, enabling adaptation to unseen categories without retraining. Our approach combines supervised contrastive fine-tuning of pre-trained models with contrastive representation distillation to transfer this structured knowledge to compact student models. Our evaluation shows that ContrastASC demonstrates improved few-shot adaptation to unseen categories while maintaining strong closed-set performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03728v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuang Yuan, Yang Gao, Xilin Li, Xinhao Mei, Syavosh Zadissa, Tarun Pruthi, Saeed Bagheri Sereshki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency vs. Efficacy: Assessing the Compression Ratio-Dice Score Relationship through a Simple Benchmarking Framework for Cerebrovascular 3D Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03769v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing size and complexity of medical imaging datasets, particularly in 3D formats, present significant barriers to collaborative research and transferability. This study investigates whether the ZFP compression technique can mitigate these challenges without compromising the performance of automated cerebrovascular segmentation, a critical first step in intracranial aneurysm detection. We apply ZFP in both its error tolerance and fixed-rate modes to a large scale, and one of the most recent, datasets in the literature, 3D medical dataset containing ground-truth vascular segmentations. The segmentation quality on the compressed volumes is rigorously compared to the uncompressed baseline (Dice approximately equals 0.8774). Our findings reveal that ZFP can achieve substantial data reduction--up to a 22.89:1 ratio in error tolerance mode--while maintaining a high degree of fidelity, with the mean Dice coefficient remaining high at 0.87656. These results demonstrate that ZFP is a viable and powerful tool for enabling more efficient and accessible research on large-scale medical datasets, fostering broader collaboration across the community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03769v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shimaa Elbana, Ahmad Kamal, Shahd Ahmed Ali, Ahmad Al-Kabbany</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Trustworthy Industrial Fault Diagnosis Architecture Integrating Probabilistic Models and Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03815v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There are limitations of traditional methods and deep learning methods in terms of interpretability, generalization, and quantification of uncertainty in industrial fault diagnosis, and there are core problems of insufficient credibility in industrial fault diagnosis. The architecture performs preliminary analysis through a Bayesian network-based diagnostic engine and features an LLM-driven cognitive quorum module with multimodal input capabilities. The module conducts expert-level arbitration of initial diagnoses by analyzing structured features and diagnostic charts, prioritizing final decisions after conflicts are identified. To ensure the reliability of the system output, the architecture integrates a confidence calibration module based on temperature calibration and a risk assessment module, which objectively quantifies the reliability of the system using metrics such as expected calibration error (ECE). Experimental results on a dataset containing multiple fault types showed that the proposed framework improved diagnostic accuracy by more than 28 percentage points compared to the baseline model, while the calibrated ECE was reduced by more than 75%. Case studies have confirmed that HCAA effectively corrects misjudgments caused by complex feature patterns or knowledge gaps in traditional models, providing novel and practical engineering solutions for building high-trust, explainable AI diagnostic systems for industrial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03815v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pilot Contamination Attacks Detection with Machine Learning for Multi-User Massive MIMO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive multiple-input multiple-output (MMIMO) is essential to modern wireless communication systems, like 5G and 6G, but it is vulnerable to active eavesdropping attacks. One type of such attack is the pilot contamination attack (PCA), where a malicious user copies pilot signals from an authentic user during uplink, intentionally interfering with the base station's (BS) channel estimation accuracy. In this work, we propose to use a Decision Tree (DT) algorithm for PCA detection at the BS in a multi-user system. We present a methodology to generate training data for the DT classifier and select the best DT according to their depth. Then, we simulate different scenarios that could be encountered in practice and compare the DT to a classical technique based on likelihood ratio testing (LRT) submitted to the same scenarios. The results revealed that a DT with only one level of depth is sufficient to outperform the LRT. The DT shows a good performance regarding the probability of detection in noisy scenarios and when the malicious user transmits with low power, in which case the LRT fails to detect the PCA. We also show that the reason for the good performance of the DT is its ability to compute a threshold that separates PCA data from non-PCA data better than the LRT's threshold. Moreover, the DT does not necessitate prior knowledge of noise power or assumptions regarding the signal power of malicious users, prerequisites typically essential for LRT and other hypothesis testing methodologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03831v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11235-024-01163-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Telecommun Syst 86, 797-809 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Ivo da Cruz, Dimitri Silva, Tito Spadini, Ricardo Suyama, Murilo Bellezoni Loiola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Enhancement in Over-the-Air Federated Learning via Adaptive Receive Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03860v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Federated Learning (FL) with over-the-air aggregation, the quality of the signal received at the server critically depends on the receive scaling factors. While a larger scaling factor can reduce the effective noise power and improve training performance, it also compromises the privacy of devices by reducing uncertainty. In this work, we aim to adaptively design the receive scaling factors across training rounds to balance the trade-off between training convergence and privacy in an FL system under dynamic channel conditions. We formulate a stochastic optimization problem that minimizes the overall R\'enyi differential privacy (RDP) leakage over the entire training process, subject to a long-term constraint that ensures convergence of the global loss function. Our problem depends on unknown future information, and we observe that standard Lyapunov optimization is not applicable. Thus, we develop a new online algorithm, termed AdaScale, based on a sequence of novel per-round problems that can be solved efficiently. We further derive upper bounds on the dynamic regret and constraint violation of AdaSacle, establishing that it achieves diminishing dynamic regret in terms of time-averaged RDP leakage while ensuring convergence of FL training to a stationary point. Numerical experiments on canonical classification tasks show that our approach effectively reduces RDP and DP leakages compared with state-of-the-art benchmarks without compromising learning performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03860v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faeze Moradi Kalarde, Ben Liang, Min Dong, Yahia A. Eldemerdash Ahmed, Ho Ting Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pitch-Conditioned Instrument Sound Synthesis From an Interactive Timbre Latent Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to neural instrument sound synthesis using a two-stage semi-supervised learning framework capable of generating pitch-accurate, high-quality music samples from an expressive timbre latent space. Existing approaches that achieve sufficient quality for music production often rely on high-dimensional latent representations that are difficult to navigate and provide unintuitive user experiences. We address this limitation through a two-stage training paradigm: first, we train a pitch-timbre disentangled 2D representation of audio samples using a Variational Autoencoder; second, we use this representation as conditioning input for a Transformer-based generative model. The learned 2D latent space serves as an intuitive interface for navigating and exploring the sound landscape. We demonstrate that the proposed method effectively learns a disentangled timbre space, enabling expressive and controllable audio generation with reliable pitch conditioning. Experimental results show the model's ability to capture subtle variations in timbre while maintaining a high degree of pitch accuracy. The usability of our method is demonstrated in an interactive web application, highlighting its potential as a step towards future music production environments that are both intuitive and creatively empowering: https://pgesam.faresschulz.com</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04339v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Limberg, Fares Schulz, Zhe Zhang, Stefan Weinzierl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environment-Aware Indoor LoRaWAN Path Loss: Parametric Regression Comparisons, Shadow Fading, and Calibrated Fade Margins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Indoor LoRaWAN propagation is shaped by structural and time-varying context factors, which challenge log-distance models and the assumption of log-normal shadowing. We present an environment-aware, statistically disciplined path loss framework evaluated using leakage-safe cross-validation on a 12-month campaign in an eighth-floor office measuring 240 m^2. A log-distance multi-wall mean is augmented with environmental covariates (relative humidity, temperature, carbon dioxide, particulate matter, and barometric pressure), as well as the signal-to-noise ratio. We compare multiple linear regression with regularized variants, Bayesian linear regression, and a selective second-order polynomial applied to continuous drivers. Predictor relevance is established using heteroscedasticity-robust Type II and III analysis of variance and nested partial F tests. Shadow fading is profiled with kernel density estimation and non-parametric families, including Normal, Skew-Normal, Student's t, and Gaussian mixtures. The polynomial mean reduces cross-validated RMSE from 8.07 to 7.09 dB and raises R^2 from 0.81 to 0.86. Out-of-fold residuals are non-Gaussian; a 3-component mixture captures a sharp core with a light, broad tail. We convert accuracy into reliability by prescribing the fade margin as the upper-tail quantile of cross-validated residuals, quantifying uncertainty via a moving-block bootstrap, and validating on a held-out set. At 99% packet delivery ratio, the environment-aware polynomial requires 25.7 dB versus 27.7 to 27.9 dB for linear baselines. This result presents a deployment-ready, interpretable workflow with calibrated reliability control for indoor Internet of Things planning, aligned with 6G targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04346v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nahshon Mokua Obiri, Kristof Van Laerhoven</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting-Based Biomedical Time-series Data Synthesis for Open Data and Robust AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The limited data availability due to strict privacy regulations and significant resource demands severely constrains biomedical time-series AI development, which creates a critical gap between data requirements and accessibility. Synthetic data generation presents a promising solution by producing artificial datasets that maintain the statistical properties of real biomedical time-series data without compromising patient confidentiality. We propose a framework for synthetic biomedical time-series data generation based on advanced forecasting models that accurately replicates complex electrophysiological signals such as EEG and EMG with high fidelity. These synthetic datasets preserve essential temporal and spectral properties of real data, which enables robust analysis while effectively addressing data scarcity and privacy challenges. Our evaluations across multiple subjects demonstrate that the generated synthetic data can serve as an effective substitute for real data and also significantly boost AI model performance. The approach maintains critical biomedical features while provides high scalability for various applications and integrates seamlessly into open-source repositories, substantially expanding resources for AI-driven biomedical research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04622v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngjoon Lee, Seongmin Cho, Yehhyun Jo, Jinu Gong, Hyunjoo Jenny Lee, Joonhyuk Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Federated Self-Supervised Learning for Automatic Modulation Classification under Non-IID and Class-Imbalanced Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Training automatic modulation classification (AMC) models on centrally aggregated data raises privacy concerns, incurs communication overhead, and often fails to confer robustness to channel shifts. Federated learning (FL) avoids central aggregation by training on distributed clients but remains sensitive to class imbalance, non-IID client distributions, and limited labeled samples. We propose FedSSL-AMC, which trains a causal, time-dilated CNN with triplet-loss self-supervision on unlabeled I/Q sequences across clients, followed by per-client SVMs on small labeled sets. We establish convergence of the federated representation learning procedure and a separability guarantee for the downstream classifier under feature noise. Experiments on synthetic and over-the-air datasets show consistent gains over supervised FL baselines under heterogeneous SNR, carrier-frequency offsets, and non-IID label partitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04927v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Usman Akram, Yiyue Chen, Haris Vikalo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Distributed Optimization With Feasible Set Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05068v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of decentralized constrained optimization with multiple agents $E_1,\ldots,E_N$ who jointly wish to learn the optimal solution set while keeping their feasible sets $\mathcal{P}_1,\ldots,\mathcal{P}_N$ private from each other. We assume that the objective function $f$ is known to all agents and each feasible set is a collection of points from a universal alphabet $\mathcal{P}_{alph}$. A designated agent (leader) starts the communication with the remaining (non-leader) agents, and is the first to retrieve the solution set. The leader searches for the solution by sending queries to and receiving answers from the non-leaders, such that the information on the individual feasible sets revealed to the leader should be no more than nominal, i.e., what is revealed from learning the solution set alone. We develop achievable schemes for obtaining the solution set at nominal information leakage, and characterize their communication costs under two communication setups between agents. In this work, we focus on two kinds of network setups: i) ring, where each agent communicates with two adjacent agents, and ii) star, where only the leader communicates with the remaining agents. We show that, if the leader first learns the joint feasible set through an existing private set intersection (PSI) protocol and then deduces the solution set, the information leaked to the leader is greater than nominal. Moreover, we draw connection of our schemes to threshold PSI (ThPSI), which is a PSI-variant where the intersection is revealed only when its cardinality is larger than a threshold value. Finally, for various realizations of $f$ mapped uniformly at random to a fixed range of values, our schemes are more communication-efficient with a high probability compared to retrieving the entire feasible set through PSI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05068v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Meel, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Majorization-Minimization based Hybrid Localization Method for High Precision Localization in Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.03881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.03881v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the hybrid source localization problem using the four radio measurements - time of arrival (TOA), time difference of arrival (TDOA), received signal strength (RSS), and angle of arrival (AOA). First, after invoking tractable approximations in the RSS and AOA models, the maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) problem for the hybrid TOA-TDOA-RSS-AOA data model is derived. Then a weighted least-squares problem is formulated from the MLE, which is solved using the principle of the majorization-minimization (MM), resulting in an iterative algorithm with guaranteed convergence. The key feature of the proposed method is that it provides a unified framework where localization using any possible merger out of these four measurements can be implemented as per the requirement/application. Extensive numerical simulations are conducted to study the performance of the proposed method. The obtained results indicate that the hybrid localization model improves the localization accuracy compared to the heterogeneous measurements under different network scenarios, which also includes the presence of non-line of sight (NLOS) errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.03881v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuntal Panwar, Prabhu Babu, R. Jyothi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson multi-Bernoulli mixture filter for trajectory measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08421v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a Poisson multi-Bernoulli mixture (PMBM) filter for multi-target filtering based on sensor measurements that are sets of trajectories in the last two-time step window. The proposed filter, the trajectory measurement PMBM (TM-PMBM) filter, propagates a PMBM density on the set of target states. In prediction, the filter obtains the PMBM density on the set of trajectories over the last two time steps. This density is then updated with the set of trajectory measurements. After the update step, the PMBM posterior on the set of two-step trajectories is marginalised to obtain a PMBM density on the set of target states. The filter provides a closed-form solution for multi-target filtering based on sets of trajectory measurements, estimating the set of target states at the end of each time window. Additionally, the paper proposes computationally lighter alternatives to the TM-PMBM filter by deriving a Poisson multi-Bernoulli (PMB) density through Kullback-Leibler divergence minimisation in an augmented space with auxiliary variables. The performance of the proposed filters are evaluated in a simulation study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08421v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Fontana, \'Angel F. Garc\'ia-Fern\'andez, Simon Maskell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving 70 Gb/s Over A VCSEL-Based Optical Wireless Link Using A Multi-Mode Fiber-Coupled Receiver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we demonstrate a laser-based optical wireless communication (OWC) system employing a 940 nm single-mode (SM) vertical cavity surface emitting laser (VCSEL) and a multi-mode (MM) fiber-coupled receiver, achieving a record data rate beyond 70 Gb/s, while the optical transmit power is below 5 mW. The use of a high speed fiber-optic photoreceiver avoids limiting the communication bandwidth by the receiver, enabling ultra-high capacity and energy-efficient light fidelity (LiFi) links to unlock new applications. This work experimentally validates the feasibility of ultra-high speed indoor OWC systems using a single low-power and low-cost VCSEL for next-generation LiFi connectivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18864v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Kazemi, Isaac N. O. Osahon, Nikolay Ledentsov Jr., Ilya Titkov, Nikolay Ledentsov, Harald Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implicit Neural Representation of Beamforming for Continuous Aperture Array (CAPA) System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03609v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, a learning-based approach for optimizing downlink beamforming in continuous aperture array (CAPA) systems is proposed, where a MIMO scenario that both the base station (BS) and the user are equipped with CAPA is considered. As the beamforming in the CAPA system is a function that maps a coordinate on the aperture to the beamforming weight at the coordinate, a DNN called BeaINR is proposed to parameterize this function, which is called implicit neural representation (INR). We further find that the optimal beamforming function lies in the subspace of channel function, i.e., it can be expressed as a weighted integral of channel function. Based on this finding, we propose another DNN called CoefINR to learn the weighting coefficient with INR, which has lower complexity than learning the beamforming function with BeaINR. Simulation results show that the proposed INR-based methods outperform numerical baselines in both spectral efficiency (SE) and inference time, with CoefINR offering additional training efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03609v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiyong Chen, Jia Guo, Shengqian Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensing Accuracy Optimization for Multi-UAV SAR Interferometry with Data Offloading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11284v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The integration of unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) with radar imaging sensors has revolutionized the monitoring of dynamic and local Earth surface processes by enabling high-resolution and cost-effective remote sensing. This paper investigates the optimization of the sensing accuracy of a UAV swarm deployed to perform multi-baseline interferometric synthetic aperture radar (InSAR) sensing. In conventional single-baseline InSAR systems, only one synthetic aperture radar (SAR) antenna pair acquires two SAR images from two distinct angles to generate a digital elevation model (DEM) of the target area. However, multi-baseline InSAR extends this concept by aggregating multiple acquisitions from different angles, thus, significantly enhancing the vertical accuracy of the DEM. The heavy computations required for this process are performed on the ground and, therefore, the radar data is transmitted in real time to a ground station (GS) via a frequency-division multiple access (FDMA) air-to-ground backhaul link. This work focuses on improving the sensing precision by minimizing the height error of the averaged DEM while simultaneously ensuring sensing and communication quality-of-service (QoS). To this end, the UAV formation, velocity, and communication power allocation are jointly optimized using evolutionary algorithms (EAs). Our approach is benchmarked against established optimization methods, including genetic algorithms (GAs), simulated annealing (SA), and deep reinforcement learning (DRL) techniques. Numerical results show that the proposed solution outperforms these baseline schemes and achieves sub-decimeter vertical accuracy in several scenarios. These findings underline the potential of coordinated UAV swarms for delivering high-precision and real-time Earth observations through radar interferometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11284v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed-Amine Lahmeri, Pouya Fakharizadeh, V\'ictor Mustieles-P\'erez, Martin Vossiek, Gerhard Krieger, Robert Schober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KAN-HAR: A Human activity recognition based on Kolmogorov-Arnold Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11186v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human Activity Recognition (HAR) plays a critical role in numerous applications, including healthcare monitoring, fitness tracking, and smart environments. Traditional deep learning (DL) approaches, while effective, often require extensive parameter tuning and may lack interpretability. In this work, we investigate the use of a single three-axis accelerometer and the Kolmogorov--Arnold Network (KAN) for HAR tasks, leveraging its ability to model complex nonlinear relationships with improved interpretability and parameter efficiency. The MotionSense dataset, containing smartphone-based motion sensor signals across various physical activities, is employed to evaluate the proposed approach. Our methodology involves preprocessing and normalization of accelerometer and gyroscope data, followed by KAN-based feature learning and classification. Experimental results demonstrate that the KAN achieves competitive or superior classification performance compared to conventional deep neural networks, while maintaining a significantly reduced parameter count. This highlights the potential of KAN architectures as an efficient and interpretable alternative for real-world HAR systems. The open-source implementation of the proposed framework is available at the Project's GitHub Repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11186v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Alikhani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Deterministic and Stochastic Approaches in Electromagnetic Information Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16601v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the relationship between the Number of Degrees of Freedom ($N_{\rm DoF}$) of the field in deterministic and stochastic source models within Electromagnetic Information Theory (EIT). Our findings demonstrate a fundamental connection between these two approaches. Specifically, we show that a deterministic model and a stochastic model with a spatially incoherent and homogeneous source yield not only the same $N_{\rm DoF}$ but also identical eigenvalues and basis functions for field representation. This key equivalence not only explains the effectiveness of deterministic approaches in EIT but also corroborates the use of classical electromagnetic methods within this new discipline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16601v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Donald Migliore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RTR: A Transformer-Based Lossless Crossover with Perfect Phase Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08272v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a transformer-based lossless crossover method, termed Resonant Transformer Router (RTR), which achieves frequency separation while ensuring perfect phase alignment between low-frequency (LF) and high-frequency (HF) channels at the crossover frequency. The core property of RTR is that its frequency responses satisfy a linear complementary relation HLF(f)+HHF(f)=1. so that the original signal can be perfectly reconstructed by linear summation of the two channels. Theoretical derivation and circuit simulations demonstrate that RTR provides superior energy efficiency, phase consistency, and robustness against component tolerances. Compared with conventional LC crossovers and digital FIR/IIR filters, RTR offers a low-loss, low-latency hardware-assisted filtering solution suitable for high-fidelity audio and communication front-ends.
  The core theory behind this paper's work, lossless crossover, is based on a Chinese patent [CN116318117A] developed from the previous research of one of the authors, Jiankuan Li. We provide a comprehensive experimental validation of this theory and propose a new extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08272v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangying Li, Jiankuan Li, Yong Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacked Intelligent Metasurface for End-to-End OFDM System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stacked intelligent metasurface (SIM) and dual-polarized SIM (DPSIM) enabled wave-domain signal processing have emerged as promising research directions for offloading baseband digital processing tasks and efficiently simplifying transceiver design. However, existing architectures are limited to employing SIM (DPSIM) for a single communication function, such as precoding or combining. To further enhance the overall performance of SIM (DPSIM)-assisted systems and achieve end-to-end (E2E) joint optimization from the transmitted bitstream to the received bitstream, we propose an SIM (DPSIM)-assisted E2E orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) system, in which traditional communication tasks such as channel coding, modulation, precoding, combining, demodulation, and channel decoding are performed synchronously within the electromagnetic (EM) forward propagation. Furthermore, inspired by the idea of abstracting real metasurfaces as hidden layers of a neural network, we propose the EM neural network (EMNN) to enable the control of the E2E OFDM communication system. In addition, transfer learning is introduced into the model training, and a training and deployment framework for the EMNN is designed. Simulation results demonstrate that both SIM-assisted E2E OFDM systems and DPSIM-assisted E2E OFDM systems can achieve robust bitstream transmission under complex channel conditions. Our study highlights the application potential of EMNN and SIM (DPSIM)-assisted E2E OFDM systems in the design of next-generation transceivers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11551v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yida Zhang, Qiuyan Liu, Hongtao Luo, Yuqi Xia, Qiang Wang, Fuchang Li, Xiaofeng Tao, Yuanwei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional WMMSE Algorithm for Continuous Aperture Array Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17101v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, a functional weighted minimum mean-squared error (WMMSE) algorithm is proposed for downlink beamforming in multiuser continuous aperture array (CAPA) systems where both the base station (BS) and users employ CAPAs. The beamforming optimization problem in such systems is inherently functional. To address this challenge, we first employ an orthonormal basis expansion to transform the functional problem into a discrete formulation that shares the same structure as the conventional discrete multi-user multiple-input multiple-output (MU-MIMO) problem. By deriving the first-order optimality conditions of the discrete formulation and mapping them back to the functional domain, we obtain the update equations of the proposed functional WMMSE algorithm. Simulation results show that the proposed method outperforms baselines in both spectral efficiency (SE) and computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17101v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiyong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NGGAN: Noise Generation GAN Based on the Practical Measurement Dataset for Narrowband Powerline Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To effectively process impulse noise for narrowband powerline communications (NB-PLCs) transceivers, capturing comprehensive statistics of nonperiodic asynchronous impulsive noise (APIN) is a critical task. However, existing mathematical noise generative models only capture part of the characteristics of noise. In this study, we propose a novel generative adversarial network (GAN) called noise generation GAN (NGGAN) that learns the complicated characteristics of practically measured noise samples for data synthesis. To closely match the statistics of complicated noise over the NB-PLC systems, we measured the NB-PLC noise via the analog coupling and bandpass filtering circuits of a commercial NB-PLC modem to build a realistic dataset. To train NGGAN, we adhere to the following principles: 1) we design the length of input signals that the NGGAN model can fit to facilitate cyclostationary noise generation; 2) the Wasserstein distance is used as a loss function to enhance the similarity between the generated noise and training data; and 3) to measure the similarity performances of GAN-based models based on the mathematical and practically measured datasets, we conduct both quantitative and qualitative analyses. The training datasets include: 1) a piecewise spectral cyclostationary Gaussian model (PSCGM); 2) a frequency-shift (FRESH) filter; and 3) practical measurements from NB-PLC systems. Simulation results demonstrate that the generated noise samples from the proposed NGGAN are highly close to the real noise samples. The principal component analysis (PCA) scatter plots and Fr\'echet inception distance (FID) analysis have shown that NGGAN outperforms other GAN-based models by generating noise samples with superior fidelity and higher diversity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01850v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIM.2024.3523361</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation and Measurement, vol. 24, pp. 1-15, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Ren Chien, Po-Heng Chou, You-Jie Peng, Chun-Yuan Huang, Hen-Wai Tsao, Yu Tsao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust MRI Reconstruction by Smoothed Unrolling (SMUG)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07784v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As the popularity of deep learning (DL) in the field of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) continues to rise, recent research has indicated that DL-based MRI reconstruction models might be excessively sensitive to minor input disturbances, including worst-case additive perturbations. This sensitivity often leads to unstable, aliased images. This raises the question of how to devise DL techniques for MRI reconstruction that can be robust to train-test variations. To address this problem, we propose a novel image reconstruction framework, termed Smoothed Unrolling (SMUG), which advances a deep unrolling-based MRI reconstruction model using a randomized smoothing (RS)-based robust learning approach. RS, which improves the tolerance of a model against input noises, has been widely used in the design of adversarial defense approaches for image classification tasks. Yet, we find that the conventional design that applies RS to the entire DL-based MRI model is ineffective. In this paper, we show that SMUG and its variants address the above issue by customizing the RS process based on the unrolling architecture of a DL-based MRI reconstruction model. Compared to the vanilla RS approach, we show that SMUG improves the robustness of MRI reconstruction with respect to a diverse set of instability sources, including worst-case and random noise perturbations to input measurements, varying measurement sampling rates, and different numbers of unrolling steps. Furthermore, we theoretically analyze the robustness of our method in the presence of perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07784v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Liang, Van Hoang Minh Nguyen, Jinghan Jia, Ismail Alkhouri, Sijia Liu, Saiprasad Ravishankar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wall-Street: Smart Surface-Enabled 5G mmWave for Roadside Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06754v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: 5G mmWave roadside networks promise high bandwidth but face significant challenges in maintaining reliable connections for users moving at high speed. Frequent handovers, complex beam alignment, and signal blockage from car bodies lead to service interruptions and degraded performance. We present Wall-Street, a vehicle-mounted smart surface that enhances 5G mmWave connectivity for in-vehicle users. Wall-Street improves mobility management by (1) steering outdoor mmWave signals into the vehicle for shared coverage, enabling a single, collective handover decision for all users; (2) enabling neighbor-cell search without interrupting data transfer, allowing for seamless handovers; and (3) connecting users to a new cell before disconnecting from the old cell for reliable handovers. We have implemented and integrated Wall-Street in the COSMOS testbed and evaluated its real-time performance with multiple gNBs and users inside a surface-mounted vehicle, driving on a nearby road. In multi-UE scenarios, Wall-Street improves TCP throughput by up to 78% and reduces RTT by up to 34% over the standard 5G Standalone handover protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06754v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Woo Cho, Prasanthi Maddala, Ivan Seskar, Kyle Jamieson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual VNA 2.0: Ambiguity-Free Scattering Matrix Estimation by Terminating Not-Directly-Accessible Ports with Tunable and Coupled Loads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10977v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We recently introduced the "Virtual VNA" concept which estimates the $N \times N$ scattering matrix characterizing an arbitrarily complex linear reciprocal system with $N$ monomodal lumped ports by inputting and outputting waves only via $N_\mathrm{A}&lt;N$ ports while terminating the $N_\mathrm{S}=N-N_\mathrm{A}$ remaining ports with known tunable individual loads. However, vexing ambiguities about the signs of the off-diagonal scattering coefficients involving the $N_\mathrm{S}$ not-directly-accessible (NDA) ports remained. If only phase-insensitive measurements were used, an additional blockwise phase ambiguity ensued. Here, inspired by the emergence of "beyond-diagonal reconfigurable intelligent surfaces" in wireless communications, we lift all ambiguities with at most $N_\mathrm{S}$ additional measurements involving a known multi-port load network. We experimentally validate our approach based on an 8-port chaotic cavity, using a simple coaxial cable as two-port load network. Endowed with the multi-port load network, the "Virtual VNA 2.0" is now able to estimate the entire scattering matrix without any ambiguity, even without ever measuring phase information explicitly. Potential applications include the challenging characterization of large and/or embedded antenna arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10977v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAP.2025.3553371</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation, vol. 73, no. 7, pp. 4903-4908, July 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Philipp del Hougne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EEG-based AI-BCI Wheelchair Advancement: A Brain-Computer Interfacing Wheelchair System Using Deep Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09763v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study offers a revolutionary strategy to developing wheelchairs based on the Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) that incorporates Artificial Intelligence (AI) using a The device uses electroencephalogram (EEG) data to mimic wheelchair navigation. Five different models were trained on a pre-filtered dataset that was divided into fixed-length windows using a sliding window technique. Each window contained statistical measurements, FFT coefficients for different frequency bands, and a label identifying the activity carried out during that window that was taken from an open-source Kaggle repository. The XGBoost model outperformed the other models, CatBoost, GRU, SVC, and XGBoost, with an accuracy of 60%. The CatBoost model with a major difference between training and testing accuracy shows overfitting, and similarly, the best-performing model, with SVC, was implemented in a tkinter GUI. The wheelchair movement could be simulated in various directions, and a Raspberry Pi-powered wheelchair system for brain-computer interface is proposed here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09763v4</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biplov Paneru, Bishwash Paneru, Bipul Thapa, Khem Narayan Poudyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuIC: Quantum-Inspired Compound Adapters for Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06916v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scaling full finetuning of large foundation models strains GPU memory and training time. Parameter Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) methods address this issue via adapter modules which update only a small subset of model parameters. In this work, we introduce Quantum-Inspired Compound Adapters (QuIC Adapters), a PEFT approach inspired from Hamming-weight preserving quantum circuits that can effectively finetune a model using less than 0.02\% memory footprint of the base model. QuIC adapters preserve pretrained representations by enforcing orthogonality in weight parameters, and have native deployment mechanisms on quantum computers. We test QuIC adapters by finetuning large language models like LLaMA and vision transformers on language, math, reasoning and vision benchmarks. In its first-order configuration, QuIC recovers the performance of existing orthogonal methods, while higher-order configurations enable substantial parameter compression (over 40x smaller than LoRA) for a modest performance trade-off, unlocking applications in highly resource-constrained environments. Through ablation studies, we determine that combining multiple Hamming-weight orders with orthogonality and matrix compounding are essential for performant finetuning. Our findings suggest that QuIC adapters offers a promising direction for efficient finetuning of foundation models in resource-constrained environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06916v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Snehal Raj, Brian Coyle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TolerantECG: A Foundation Model for Imperfect Electrocardiogram</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09887v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The electrocardiogram (ECG) is an essential and effective tool for diagnosing heart diseases. However, its effectiveness can be compromised by noise or unavailability of one or more leads of the standard 12-lead recordings, resulting in diagnostic errors or uncertainty. To address these challenges, we propose TolerantECG, a foundation model for ECG signals that is robust to noise and capable of functioning with arbitrary subsets of the standard 12-lead ECG. TolerantECG training combines contrastive and self-supervised learning frameworks to jointly learn ECG signal representations alongside their corresponding knowledge-retrieval-based text report descriptions and corrupted or lead-missing signals. Comprehensive benchmarking results demonstrate that TolerantECG consistently ranks as the best or second-best performer across various ECG signal conditions and class levels in the PTB-XL dataset, and achieves the highest performance on the MIT-BIH Arrhythmia Database.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09887v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3746027.3755287</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Huynh Dang Nguyen, Trong-Thang Pham, Ngan Le, Van Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contrastive-KAN: A Semi-Supervised Intrusion Detection Framework for Cybersecurity with scarce Labeled Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10808v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the era of the Fourth Industrial Revolution, cybersecurity and intrusion detection systems are vital for the secure and reliable operation of IoT and IIoT environments. A key challenge in this domain is the scarcity of labeled cyberattack data, as most industrial systems operate under normal conditions. This data imbalance, combined with the high cost of annotation, hinders the effective training of machine learning models. Moreover, the rapid detection of attacks is essential, especially in critical infrastructure, to prevent large-scale disruptions. To address these challenges, we propose a real-time intrusion detection system based on a semi-supervised contrastive learning framework using the Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (KAN). Our method leverages abundant unlabeled data to effectively distinguish between normal and attack behaviors. We validate our approach on three benchmark datasets, UNSW-NB15, BoT-IoT, and Gas Pipeline, using only 2.20%, 1.28%, and 8% of labeled samples, respectively, to simulate real-world conditions. Experimental results show that our method outperforms existing contrastive learning-based approaches. We further compare KAN with a traditional multilayer perceptron (MLP), demonstrating KAN's superior performance in both detection accuracy and robustness under limited supervision. KAN's ability to model complex relationships, along with its learnable activation functions, is also explored and visualized, offering interpretability and the potential for rule extraction. The method supports multi-class classification and proves effective in safety, critical environments where reliability is paramount.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10808v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Alikhani, Reza Kazemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Defect Detection for Mass-Produced Electronic Components Based on YOLO Object Detection Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01914v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Since the defect detection of conventional industry components is time-consuming and labor-intensive, it leads to a significant burden on quality inspection personnel and makes it difficult to manage product quality. In this paper, we propose an automated defect detection system for the dual in-line package (DIP) that is widely used in industry, using digital camera optics and a deep learning (DL)-based model. The two most common defect categories of DIP are examined: (1) surface defects, and (2) pin-leg defects. However, the lack of defective component images leads to a challenge for detection tasks. To solve this problem, the ConSinGAN is used to generate a suitable-sized dataset for training and testing. Four varieties of the YOLO model are investigated (v3, v4, v7, and v9), both in isolation and with the ConSinGAN augmentation. The proposed YOLOv7 with ConSinGAN is superior to the other YOLO versions in accuracy of 95.50\%, detection time of 285 ms, and is far superior to threshold-based approaches. In addition, the supervisory control and data acquisition (SCADA) system is developed, and the associated sensor architecture is described. The proposed automated defect detection can be easily established with numerous types of defects or insufficient defect data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01914v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JSEN.2024.3418618</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Sensors Journal, vol. 24, no. 16, Aug. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Lung Mao, Chun-Chi Wang, Po-Heng Chou, Yen-Ting Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
