<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP</link>
    <description>eess.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Neural Network Architectures for Electrocardiogram Classification: A Comprehensive Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the rising prevalence of cardiovascular diseases, electrocardiograms (ECG) remain essential for the non-invasive detection of cardiac abnormalities. This study presents a comprehensive evaluation of deep neural network architectures for automated arrhythmia classification, integrating temporal modeling, attention mechanisms, and ensemble strategies. To address data scarcity in minority classes, the MIT-BIH Arrhythmia dataset was augmented using a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN). We developed and compared four distinct architectures, including Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN), CNN combined with Long Short-Term Memory (CNN-LSTM), CNN-LSTM with Attention, and 1D Residual Networks (ResNet-1D), to capture both local morphological features and long-term temporal dependencies. Performance was rigorously evaluated using accuracy, F1-score, and Area Under the Curve (AUC) with 95\% confidence intervals to ensure statistical robustness, while Gradient-weighted Class Activation Mapping (Grad-CAM) was employed to validate model interpretability. Experimental results indicate that the CNN-LSTM model achieved the optimal stand-alone balance between sensitivity and specificity, yielding an F1-score of 0.951. Conversely, the CNN-LSTM-Attention and ResNet-1D models exhibited higher sensitivity to class imbalance. To mitigate this, a dynamic ensemble fusion strategy was introduced; specifically, the Top2-Weighted ensemble achieved the highest overall performance with an F1-score of 0.958. These findings demonstrate that leveraging complementary deep architectures significantly enhances classification reliability, providing a robust and interpretable foundation for intelligent arrhythmia detection systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17701v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Song, Wenjia Zheng, Tiedan Chen, Ziyu Wang, Jiazhao Shi, Yisong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wavenumber-domain signal processing for holographic MIMO: Foundations, methods, and future directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Holographic multiple-input multiple-output (H-MIMO) systems represent a paradigm shift in wireless communications by enabling quasi-continuous apertures. Unlike conventional MIMO systems, H-MIMO with subwavelength antenna spacing operates in both far-field and near-field regimes, where classical discrete Fourier transform (DFT) representations fail to sufficiently capture the channel characteristics. To address this challenge, this article provides an overview of the emerging wavenumber-domain signal processing framework. Specifically, by leveraging spatial Fourier plane-wave decomposition to model H-MIMO channels, the wavenumber domain offers a unified and physically consistent basis for characterizing subwavelength-level spatial correlation and spherical wave propagation. This article first introduces the concept of H-MIMO and the wavenumber representation of H-MIMO channels. Next, it elaborates on wavenumber-domain signal processing technologies reported in the literature, including multiplexing, channel estimation, and waveform designs. Finally, it highlights open challenges and outlines future research directions in wavenumber-domain signal processing for next-generation wireless systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17705v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Zhang, Linglong Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driving-Over Detection in the Railway Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To enable fully automated driving of trains, numerous new technological components must be introduced into the railway system. Tasks that are nowadays carried out by the operating stuff, need to be taken over by automatic systems. Therefore, equipment for automatic train operation and observing the environment is needed. Here, an important task is the detection of collisions, including both (1) collisions with the front of the train as well as (2) collisions with the wheel, corresponding to an driving-over event. Technologies for detecting the driving-over events are barely investigated nowadays. Therefore, detailed driving-over experiments were performed to gather knowledge for fully automated rail operations, using a variety of objects made from steel, wood, stone and bones. Based on the captured test data, three methods were developed to detect driving-over events automatically. The first method is based on convolutional neural networks and the other two methods are classical threshold-based approaches. The neural network based approach provides an mean accuracy of 99.6% while the classical approaches show 85% and 88.6%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17745v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The 12th International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Applications (Europe), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Herrmann, Nikolay Chenkov, Florian Stark, Matthias H\"arter, Martin K\"oppel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Reconfigurable and Movable Antennas for Wireless Communications and Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reconfigurable antennas (RAs) and movable antennas (MAs) have been recognized as promising technologies to enhance the performance of wireless communication and sensing systems by introducing additional degrees of freedom (DoFs) in tuning antenna radiation and/or placement. This paradigm shift from conventional non-reconfigurable/movable antennas offers tremendous new opportunities for realizing multi-functional, more adaptive, and efficient next-generation wireless networks. In this paper, we provide a comprehensive survey on the fundamentals, architectures, and applications of these two emerging antenna technologies. First, we provide a chronological overview of the parallel historical development of both RA and MA technologies. Next, we review and classify the state-of-the-art hardware architectures for implementing RAs and MAs, followed by a detailed comparison of their distinct mechanisms, performance metrics, and functionalities. Subsequently, we focus on various applications of RAs and MAs in wireless communication systems, analyzing their respective performance advantages and key design considerations such as mode selection, movement optimization, and channel acquisition. We also explore the significant roles of RAs and MAs in advancing wireless sensing and integrated sensing and communication (ISAC). Furthermore, we present numerical performance comparisons to illustrate the distinct characteristics and complementary advantages of RA and MA systems. Finally, we outline key challenges and identify promising future research directions to inspire further innovations in this burgeoning field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17977v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/COMST.2026.3663021</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wenyan Ma, Lipeng Zhu, Yanhua Tan, Beixiong Zheng, Yujie Zhang, Yuchen Zhang, Keke Ying, Zhen Gao, He Sun, Xiaodan Shao, Zhenyu Xiao, Dusit Niyato, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning While Transmitting: Pilotless Polar Coded Modulation for Short Packet Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17979v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Short packets make channel learning expensive. In pilot-aided transmission (PAT), a non-negligible fraction of the packet is consumed by pilots, creating a direct pre-log loss and tightening the reliability margin needed for ultra-reliable low-latency communication. We propose a pilot-free polar-coded framework that replaces explicit pilots with \emph{coded pilots}. The message is carried by two polar-coded segments: a quadrature phase shift keying (QPSK) segment that is decodable without channel state information (CSI), and a higher-order quadrature amplitude modulation (QAM) segment that provides high spectral efficiency. The receiver employs \emph{hybrid decoding}: it first jointly infers CSI during successive-cancellation-based decoding of the QPSK segment by exploiting QPSK phase-rotation invariance together with polar frozen-bit constraints; the decoded QPSK symbols then act as \emph{implicit pilots} for coherent detection and decoding of the QAM segment. The split also makes rate adaptation practical by confining the symmetry/frozen-bit requirements for phase resolution to the QPSK segment, enabling puncturing and shortening without breaking the pilot-free mechanism. For multi-block fading, we optimize the split and code parameters via density evolution with Gaussian approximation (DEGA); for higher-order modulation, we use bit-interleaved coded modulation capacity approximation to obtain equivalent channel parameters. Incorporating channel-estimation error variance into the DEGA-based analysis, simulations over practical multi-block block-fading channels show gains up to $1.5$~dB over PAT in the short-blocklength regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17979v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geon Choi, Namyoon Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Modal Sensing Residual-Corrected GNN for mmWave Path Loss Prediction via Synesthesia of Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To support sixth-generation (6G)-enabled intelligent transportation systems (ITSs), a multi-modal sensing residual-corrected graph neural network (MM-ResGNN) framework is proposed for millimeter-wave (mmWave) path loss prediction in vehicular communications for the first time. The propagation environment is formulated as an environment sensing path loss graph (ESPL-Graph), where nodes represent the transmitter (Tx) and receiver (Rx) entities and edges jointly describe Tx--Rx transmission links and Rx--Rx spatial correlation links. Meanwhile, a geometry-driven physical baseline is introduced to decouple deterministic attenuation trends from stochastic residual variations. A vehicular multi-modal path loss dataset (VMMPL) is constructed, which covers three representative scenarios, including the urban wide lane, urban crossroad, and suburban forking road environments, and achieves precise alignment between RGB images and global semantic information in the physical space, and link-level ray-tracing (RT)-based path loss data in the electromagnetic space. In MM-ResGNN, topology-aware graph representations and fine-grained visual semantics are synergistically integrated through a gated fusion mechanism to estimate the path loss residual relative to the physical baseline. Experimental results demonstrate that MM-ResGNN achieves significant improvements over empirical models and conventional data-driven baselines, with a normalized mean squared error (NMSE) of 0.0098, a mean absolute error (MAE) of 5.7991~dB, and a mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) of 5.0498\%. Furthermore, MM-ResGNN exhibits robust cross-scenario generalization through a few-shot fine-tuning strategy, enabling accurate path loss prediction in unseen vehicular environments with limited labeled data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18005v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyuan Lu, Lu Bai, Xiang Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Multi-User Tracking and Signal Detection in Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface-Assisted Cell-Free ISAC Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the cell-free multi-user integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system, where multiple base stations collaboratively track the users and detect their signals. Moreover, reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) are deployed to serve as additional reference nodes to overcome the line-of-sight blockage issue of mobile users for accomplishing seamless sensing. Due to the high-speed user mobility, the multi-user tracking and signal detection performance can be significantly deteriorated without elaborated online user kinematic state updating principles. To tackle this challenge, we first manage to establish a probabilistic signal model to comprehensively characterize the interdependencies among user states, transmit signals, and received signals during the tracking procedure. Based on the Bayesian problem formulation, we further propose a novel hybrid variational message passing (HVMP) algorithm to realize computationally efficient joint estimation of user states and transmit signals in an online manner, which integrates VMP and standard MP to derive the posterior probabilities of estimated variables. Furthermore, the Bayesian Cramer-Rao bound is provided to characterize the performance limit of the multi-user tracking problem, which is also utilized to optimize RIS phase profiles for tracking performance enhancement. Numerical results demonstrate that the proposed algorithm can significantly improve both tracking and signal detection performance over the representative Bayesian estimation counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18018v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weifeng Zhu, Junyuan Gao, Shuowen Zhang, Meixia Tao, Liang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremely Large Antenna Spacing Method for Enhanced Wideband Near-Field Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a monostatic wideband system for integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) at millimeter-wave frequencies, based on multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) orthogonal frequency-division multiplexing (OFDM). The system operates in a hybrid near-/far-field regime. The transmitter (Tx) operates in the far field (FF) and uses low-complexity beam steering. The receiver (Rx), on the other hand, operates in a pervasive near field (NF), enabled by a very large effective array aperture. To enable a fully digital implementation, we introduce an extremely large antenna spacing (ELAS) design. This design attains the required aperture with only a few widely spaced antenna elements while avoiding grating lobes in the composite Tx-Rx response. We analytically characterize the NF range-angle response of this architecture and study the interplay between NF effects and waveform bandwidth. This leads to the definition of a super-resolution region, where NF propagation at the Rx dominates the achievable range resolution and surpasses the classical, bandwidth-limited resolution. As a case study, we consider an extended target modeled as a collection of scatterers and assess localization performance via maximum-likelihood estimation. Numerical results evaluated in terms of root mean square error (RMSE) and generalized optimal sub-pattern assignment (GOSPA) show that operating in NF conditions with the ELAS-based design yields significant gains compared to a conventional FF baseline at both the Tx and Rx.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18076v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Bacchielli, Lorenzo Pucci, Andrea Giorgetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Contiguous Wi-Fi Spectrum for ISAC: Impact on Multipath Delay Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Leveraging channel state information from multiple Wi-Fi bands can improve delay resolution for ranging and sensing when a wide contiguous spectrum is unavailable. However, frequency gaps shape the delay response, introducing sidelobes and secondary peaks that can obscure closely spaced multipath components. This paper examines multipath delay estimation for Wi-Fi-compliant multiband configurations using channel state information (CSI). For a two-path model with unknown complex gains and delays, the Cram\'er-Rao lower bound (CRLB) for delay separation is derived and analyzed, confirming the benefit of larger frequency aperture, while revealing pronounced, separation-dependent oscillations driven by gap geometry and inter-path coupling. Given the local nature of Cram\'er-Rao lower bound, the delay response is analyzed next. In the single-path case, the combined subband responses determine how delay-domain sidelobe levels are distributed. The dominant peak spacing is set primarily by the separation between subband center frequencies. In the two-path case, increased aperture sharpens the mainlobe but also intensifies sidelobes and leakage, yielding competing peaks and, in some regimes, a dominant peak shifted from the true delay. Finally, a normalized leakage metric is introduced to predict problematic separations and to identify regimes where local Cram\'er-Rao lower bound analysis does not capture practical peak-leakage behavior in delay estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18086v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Jekni\'c, Ale\v{s} \v{S}vigelj, Toma\v{z} Javornik, Andrej Hrovat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>m^3TrackFormer: Transformer-based mmWave Multi-Target Tracking with Lost Target Re-Acquisition Capability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper considers a millimeter wave (mmWave) integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system, where a base station (BS) equipped with a large number of antennas but a small number of radio-frequency (RF) chains emits pencillike narrow beams for persistent tracking of multiple moving targets. Under this model, the tracking lost issue arising from the misalignment between the pencil-like beams and the true target positions is inevitable, especially when the trajectories of the targets are complex, and the conventional Kalman filter-based scheme does not work well. To deal with this issue, we propose a Transformer-based mmWave multi-target tracking framework, namely m3TrackFormer, with a novel re-acquisition mechanism, such that even if the echo signals from some targets are too weak to extract sensing information, we are able to re-acquire their locations quickly with small beam sweeping overhead. Specifically, the proposed framework can operate in two modes of normal tracking and target re-acquisition during the tracking procedure, depending on whether the tracking lost occurs. When all targets are hit by the swept beams, the framework works in the Normal Tracking Mode (N-Mode) with a Transformer encoder-based Normal Tracking Network (N-Net) to accurately estimate the positions of these targets and predict the swept beams in the next time block. While the tracking lost happens, the framework will switch to the Re-Acquisition Mode (R-Mode) with a Transformer decoder-based Re-Acquisition Network (RNet) to adjust the beam sweeping strategy for getting back the lost targets and maintaining the tracking of the remaining targets. Thanks to the ability of global trajectory feature extraction, the m3TrackFormer can achieve high beam prediction accuracy and quickly re-acquire the lost targets, compared with other tracking methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18254v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tongkai Li, Weifeng Zhu, Shuowen Zhang, Jiannong Cao, Shuguang Cui, Liang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Channel Estimation for Double-BD-RIS-Assisted Multi-User MIMO Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deploying multiple beyond diagonal reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (BD-RISs) can potentially improve the communication performance thanks to inter-element connections of each BD-RIS and inter-surface cooperative beamforming gain among BD-RISs. However, a major issue for multi-BD-RISassisted communication lies in the channel estimation overhead - the channel coefficients associated with the off-diagonal elements in each BD-RIS's scattering matrix as well as those associated with the reflection links among BD-RISs have to be estimated. In this paper, we propose an efficient channel estimation framework for double-BD-RIS-assisted multi-user multipleinput multiple-output (MIMO) systems. Specifically, we reveal that high-dimensional cascaded channels are characterized by five low-dimensional matrices by exploiting channel correlation properties. Based on this novel observation, in the ideal noiseless case, we develop a channel estimation scheme to recover these matrices sequentially and characterize the closed-form overhead required for perfect estimation as a function of the numbers of users and each BD-RIS's elements and channel ranks, which is with the same order as that in double-diagonal-RIS-aided communication systems. This exciting result implies the superiority of cooperative BD-RIS-aided communication over the diagonal- RIS counterpart even when channel estimation overhead is considered. We further extend the proposed scheme to practical noisy scenarios and provide extensive numerical simulations to validate its effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18263v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junyuan Gao, Shuowen Zhang, Liang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MD-AirComp+: Adaptive Quantization for Blind Massive Digital Over-the-Air Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent research has shown that unsourced massive access (UMA) is naturally well-suited for over-the-air computation (AirComp), as it does not require knowledge of each individual signal, as demonstrated by the massive digital AirComp (MD-AirComp) scheme proposed in prior work. The MD-AirComp scheme has proven effective in federated edge learning and is highly compatible with current digital wireless networks. However, it depends on channel pre-equalization, which may amplify computation errors in the presence of channel estimation inaccuracies, thus limiting its practical use. In this paper, we propose a blind MD-AirComp+ scheme, which takes advantage of the channel hardening effect in massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems. We provide an upper bound on the computation mean square error, analyze the trade-off between computation accuracy and communication overhead, and determine the optimal quantization level. Additionally, we introduce a deep unfolding algorithm to reduce the computational complexity of solving the underdetermined detection problem formulated as a least absolute shrinkage and selection operator optimization problem. Simulation results confirm the effectiveness of the proposed MD-AirComp+ framework, the optimal quantization selection strategy, and the low-complexity detection algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18332v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Qiao, Yueqing Wang, Hanjun Jiang, Xinhua Liu, Yixuan Xing, Yongpeng Wu, Zhen Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GS-SBL: Bridging Greedy Pursuit and Sparse Bayesian Learning for Efficient 3D Wireless Channel Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robust cognitive radio development requires accurate 3D path loss models. Traditional empirical models often lack environment-awareness, while deep learning approaches are frequently constrained by the scarcity of large-scale training datasets. This work leverages the inherent sparsity of wireless propagation to model scenario-specific channels by identifying a discrete set of virtual signal sources. We propose a novel Greedy Sequential Sparse Bayesian Learning (GS-SBL) framework that bridges the gap between the computational efficiency of Orthogonal Matching Pursuit (OMP) and the robust uncertainty quantification of SBL. Unlike standard top-down SBL, which updates all source hyperparameters simultaneously, our approach employs a ``Micro-SBL'' architecture. We sequentially evaluate candidate source locations in isolation by executing localized, low-iteration SBL loops and selecting the source that minimizes the $L_2$ residual error. Once identified, the source and its corresponding power are added to the support set, and the process repeats on the signal residual to identify subsequent sources. Experimental results on real-world 3D propagation data demonstrate that the GS-SBL framework significantly outperforms OMP in terms of generalization. By utilizing SBL as a sequential source identifier rather than a global optimizer, the proposed method preserves Bayesian high-resolution accuracy while achieving the execution speeds necessary for real-time 3D path loss characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18339v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mushfiqur Rahman, Ismail Guvenc, David Matolak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling UAV-aided Roadside Cell-Free Networks with Mat\'ern Hard-Core Point Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates a uncrewed aerial vehicles (UAV)-assisted cell-free architecture for vehicular networks in road-constrained environments. Roads are modeled using a Poisson Line Process (PLP), with multi-layer roadside access points (APs) deployed via 1-D Poisson Point Process (PPP). Each user forms a localized cell-free cluster by associating with the nearest AP in each layer along its corresponding road. This forms a road-constrained cell-free architecture. To enhance coverage, UAV act as an aerial tier, extending access from 1-D road-constrained layouts (embedded in 2-D) to 3-D. We employ a Mat\'ern Hard-Core (MHC) point process to model the spatial distribution of UAV base stations, ensuring a minimum safety distance between them. In order to enable tractable analysis of the aggregate signal from multiple APs, a distance-based power control scheme is introduced. Leveraging tools from stochastic geometry, we have studied the coverage probability. Furthermore, we analyze the impact of key system parameters on coverage performance, providing useful insights into the deployment and optimization of UAV-assisted cell-free vehicular networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18408v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenrui Qiu, Yongxu Zhu, Bo Tan, George K. Karagiannidis, Tasos Dagiuklas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIRUP: A diffusion-based virtual upmixer of steering vectors for highly-directive spatialization with first-order ambisonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents virtual upmixing of steering vectors captured by a fewer-channel spherical microphone array. This challenge has conventionally been addressed by recovering the directions and signals of sound sources from first-order ambisonics (FOA) data, and then rendering the higher-order ambisonics (HOA) data using a physics-based acoustic simulator. This approach, however, struggles to handle the mutual dependency between the spatial directivity of source estimation and the spatial resolution of FOA ambisonics data. Our method, named SIRUP, employs a latent diffusion model architecture. Specifically, a variational autoencoder (VAE) is used to learn a compact encoding of the HOA data in a latent space and a diffusion model is then trained to generate the HOA embeddings, conditioned by the FOA data. Experimental results showed that SIRUP achieved a significant improvement compared to FOA systems for steering vector upmixing, source localization, and speech denoising.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17732v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICASSP, May 2026, Barcelone, Spain</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Emilio Picard (RIKEN AIP, UP1 EMS), Diego Di Carlo (RIKEN AIP, IP Paris), Aditya Arie Nugraha (RIKEN AIP), Mathieu Fontaine (LTCI, IP Paris), Kazuyoshi Yoshii (RIKEN AIP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-Aware Jamming Mitigation with Active RIS: A Robust Stackelberg Game Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18165v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Malicious jamming presents a pervasive threat to the secure communications, where the challenge becomes increasingly severe due to the growing capability of the jammer allowing the adaptation to legitimate transmissions. This paper investigates the jamming mitigation by leveraging an active reconfigurable intelligent surface (ARIS), where the channel uncertainties are particularly addressed for robust anti-jamming design. Towards this issue, we adopt the Stackelberg game formulation to model the strategic interaction between the legitimate side and the adversary, acting as the leader and follower, respectively. We prove the existence of the game equilibrium and adopt the backward induction method for equilibrium analysis. We first derive the optimal jamming policy as the follower's best response, which is then incorporated into the legitimate-side optimization for robust anti-jamming design. We address the uncertainty issue and reformulate the legitimate-side problem by exploiting the error bounds to combat the worst-case jamming attacks. The problem is decomposed within a block successive upper bound minimization (BSUM) framework to tackle the power allocation, transceiving beamforming, and active reflection, respectively, which are iterated towards the robust jamming mitigation scheme. Simulation results are provided to demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed scheme in protecting the legitimate transmissions under uncertainties, and the superior performance in terms of jamming mitigation as compared with the baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18165v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Tang, Zhen Ma, Limeng Dong, Yichen Wang, Qinghe Du, Dusit Niyato, Zhu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRISM-FCP: Byzantine-Resilient Federated Conformal Prediction via Partial Sharing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.18396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.18396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose PRISM-FCP (Partial shaRing and robust calIbration with Statistical Margins for Federated Conformal Prediction), a Byzantine-resilient federated conformal prediction framework that utilizes partial model sharing to improve robustness against Byzantine attacks during both model training and conformal calibration. Existing approaches address adversarial behavior only in the calibration stage, leaving the learned model susceptible to poisoned updates. In contrast, PRISM-FCP mitigates attacks end-to-end. During training, clients partially share updates by transmitting only $M$ of $D$ parameters per round. This attenuates the expected energy of an adversary's perturbation in the aggregated update by a factor of $M/D$, yielding lower mean-square error (MSE) and tighter prediction intervals. During calibration, clients convert nonconformity scores into characterization vectors, compute distance-based maliciousness scores, and downweight or filter suspected Byzantine contributions before estimating the conformal quantile. Extensive experiments on both synthetic data and the UCI Superconductivity dataset demonstrate that PRISM-FCP maintains nominal coverage guarantees under Byzantine attacks while avoiding the interval inflation observed in standard FCP with reduced communication, providing a robust and communication-efficient approach to federated uncertainty quantification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.18396v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Lari, Reza Arablouei, Stefan Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenGERT: Open Source Automated Geometry Extraction with Geometric and Electromagnetic Sensitivity Analyses for Ray-Tracing Propagation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06945v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate RF propagation modeling in urban environments is critical for developing digital spectrum twins and optimizing wireless communication systems. We introduce OpenGERT, an open-source automated Geometry Extraction tool for Ray Tracing, which collects and processes terrain and building data from OpenStreetMap, Microsoft Global ML Building Footprints, and USGS elevation data. Using the Blender Python API, it creates detailed urban models for high-fidelity simulations with NVIDIA Sionna RT. We perform sensitivity analyses to examine how variations in building height, position, and electromagnetic material properties affect ray-tracing accuracy. Specifically, we present pairwise dispersion plots of channel statistics (path gain, mean excess delay, delay spread, link outage, and Rician K-factor) and investigate how their sensitivities change with distance from transmitters. We also visualize the variance of these statistics for selected transmitter locations to gain deeper insights. Our study covers Munich and Etoile scenes, each with 10 transmitter locations. For each location, we apply five types of perturbations: material, position, height, height-position, and all combined, with 50 perturbations each. Results show that small changes in permittivity and conductivity minimally affect channel statistics, whereas variations in building height and position significantly alter all statistics, even with noise standard deviations of 1 meter in height and 0.4 meters in position. These findings highlight the importance of precise environmental modeling for accurate propagation predictions, essential for digital spectrum twins and advanced communication networks. The code for geometry extraction and sensitivity analyses is available at github.com/serhatadik/OpenGERT/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06945v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serhat Tadik, Rajib Bhattacharjea, Johnathan Corgan, David Johnson, Jacobus Van der Merwe, Gregory D. Durgin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-View Wireless Sensing via Conditional Generative Learning: Framework and Model Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12664v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we incorporate physical knowledge into learning-based high-precision target sensing using the multi-view channel state information (CSI) between multiple base stations (BSs) and user equipment (UEs). Such kind of multi-view sensing problem can be naturally cast into a conditional generation framework. To this end, we design a bipartite neural network architecture, the first part of which uses an elaborately designed encoder to fuse the latent target features embedded in the multi-view CSI, and then the second uses them as conditioning inputs of a powerful generative model to guide the target's reconstruction. Specifically, the encoder is designed to capture the physical correlation between the CSI and the target, and also be adaptive to the numbers and positions of BS-UE pairs. Therein the view-specific nature of CSI is assimilated by introducing a spatial positional embedding scheme, which exploits the structure of electromagnetic(EM)-wave propagation channels. Finally, a conditional diffusion model with a weighted loss is employed to generate the target's point cloud from the fused features. Extensive numerical results demonstrate that the proposed generative multi-view (Gen-MV) sensing framework exhibits excellent flexibility and significant performance improvement on the reconstruction quality of target's shape and EM properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12664v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqing Xing, Zhaoyang Zhang, Zirui Chen, Hongning Ruan, Zhaohui Yang, Zhiyong Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constellation Shaping for OFDM-ISAC Systems: From Theoretical Bounds to Practical Implementation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04055v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Integrated sensing and communications (ISAC) promises new use cases for mobile communication systems by reusing the communication signal for radar-like sensing. However, sensing and communications (S&amp;C) impose conflicting requirements on the modulation format, resulting in a tradeoff between their corresponding performance. This paper investigates constellation shaping as a means to simultaneously improve S&amp;C performance in orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM)-based ISAC systems. We begin by deriving how the transmit symbols affect detection performance and derive theoretical lower and upper bounds on the maximum achievable information rate under a given sensing constraint. Using an autoencoder-based optimization, we investigate geometric, probabilistic, and joint constellation shaping, where joint shaping combines both approaches, employing both optimal maximum a-posteriori decoding and practical bit-metric decoding. Our results show that constellation shaping enables a flexible trade-off between S&amp;C, can approach the derived upper bound, and significantly outperforms conventional modulation formats. Motivated by its practical implementation feasibility, we review probabilistic amplitude shaping (PAS) and propose a generalization tailored to ISAC. For this generalization, we propose a low-complexity log-likelihood ratio computation with negligible rate loss. We demonstrate that combining conventional and generalized PAS enables a flexible and low-complexity tradeoff between S&amp;C, closely approaching the performance of joint constellation shaping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04055v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt Geiger, Fan Liu, Shihang Lu, Andrej Rode, Daniel Gil Gaviria, Charlotte Muth, Laurent Schmalen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kalman Filter-based Mobile User-RIS Channel Estimation and User Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17112v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In communication networks, channel estimation and user localization are challenging problems in harsh environments or signal-blocked areas. This paper introduces a novel approach to minimize the Mean Squared Error (MSE) in channel estimation between mobile users and rectangular Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces (RIS) within wireless communication systems. Meanwhile, the user localization is realized based on the estimated Channel State Information (CSI). In this paper, we assume a non-linear, user's position-dependent system model, for a user with high mobility, an RIS with multiple elements, and a base station (BS) with multiple antennas. After that, we apply the Kalman Filtering (KF) like algorithms to reduce MSE in estimating parameters of this time-variant channel model. Additionally, we propose a Non-Circular Noise Kalman Filter (NCNKF) to address scenarios with non-circular complex state-space noise. Furthermore, we apply the Discrete Space Fourier Transform (DSFT) method, combined with the interpolation techniques to decrease the Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) for the user localization based on the estimated CSI. Finally, we extend the single-user case into the multi-user situation. Results show that KF can achieve lower MSE in estimating the channel than other known approaches, while the NCNKF algorithm has better performance in non-circular state-space noise scenarios. At the same time, the DSFT interpolation outperforms the other approaches with lower complexity. The study concludes with numerical comparisons and an in-depth discussion of the performance improvements enabled by our approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17112v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ju Zhuoxuan, Doroslovacki Milos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SeaSpoofFinder -- Potential GNSS Spoofing Event Detection Using AIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates whether large-scale GNSS spoofing activity can be inferred from maritime Automatic Identification System (AIS) position reports. A data-processing framework, called SeaSpoofFinder, available here: seaspooffinder.github.io/ais_data, was developed to ingest and post-process global AIS streams and to detect candidate anomalies through a two-stage procedure. In Stage 1, implausible position jumps are identified using kinematic and data-quality filters; in Stage 2, events are retained only when multiple vessels exhibit spatially consistent source and target clustering, thereby reducing false positives from single-vessel artifacts. The resulting final potential spoofing events (FPSEs) reveal recurrent patterns in several regions, including the Baltic Sea, the Black Sea, Murmansk, Moscow, and the Haifa area, with affected footprints that can span large maritime areas. The analysis also highlights recurring non-spoofing artifacts (e.g., back-to-port jumps and data gaps) that can still pass heuristic filters in dense traffic regions. These results indicate that AIS-based monitoring can provide useful evidence for identifying and characterizing potential spoofing activity at scale, while emphasizing that AIS-only evidence does not provide definitive attribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16257v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'on Winkel, Tom Willems, Cillian O'Driscoll, Ignacio Fernandez-Hernandez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VaN3Twin: the Multi-Technology V2X Digital Twin with Ray-Tracing in the Loop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14184v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents VaN3Twin-the first open-source, full-stack Network Digital Twin (NDT) framework for simulating the coexistence of multiple Vehicle-to-Everything (V2X) communication technologies with accurate physical-layer modeling via ray tracing. VaN3Twin extends the ms-van3t simulator by integrating Sionna Ray Tracer (RT) in the loop, enabling high-fidelity representation of wireless propagation, including diverse Line-of-Sight (LoS) conditions with focus on LoS blockage due to other vehicles' meshes, Doppler effect, and site-dependent effects-e.g., scattering and diffraction. Unlike conventional simulation tools, the proposed framework supports realistic coexistence analysis across DSRC and C-V2X technologies operating over shared spectrum. A dedicated interference tracking module captures cross-technology interference at the time-frequency resource block level and enhances signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) estimation by eliminating artifacts such as the bimodal behavior induced by separate LoS/NLoS propagation models. Compared to field measurements, VaN3Twin reduces application-layer disagreement by 50% in rural and over 70% in urban environments with respect to current state-of-the-art simulation tools, demonstrating its value for scalable and accurate digital twin-based V2X coexistence simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14184v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Pegurri, Diego Gasco, Francesco Linsalata, Marco Rapelli, Eugenio Moro, Francesco Raviglione, Claudio Casetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Adversarial Robustness of Learning-based Conformal Novelty Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00463v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the adversarial robustness of conformal novelty detection. In particular, we focus on two powerful learning-based frameworks that come with finite-sample false discovery rate (FDR) control: one is AdaDetect (by Marandon et al., 2024) that is based on the positive-unlabeled classifier, and the other is a one-class classifier-based approach (by Bates et al., 2023). While they provide rigorous statistical guarantees under benign conditions, their behavior under adversarial perturbations remains underexplored. We first formulate an oracle attack setup, under the AdaDetect formulation, that quantifies the worst-case degradation of FDR, deriving an upper bound that characterizes the statistical cost of attacks. This idealized formulation directly motivates a practical and effective attack scheme that only requires query access to the output labels of both frameworks. Coupling these formulations with two popular and complementary black-box adversarial algorithms, we systematically evaluate the vulnerability of both frameworks on synthetic and real-world datasets. Our results show that adversarial perturbations can significantly increase the FDR while maintaining high detection power, exposing fundamental limitations of current error-controlled novelty detection methods and motivating the development of more robust alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00463v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daofu Zhang, Mehrdad Pournaderi, Hanne M. Clifford, Yu Xiang, Pramod K. Varshney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact-Anchored Proprioceptive Odometry for Quadruped Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.17393v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reliable odometry for legged robots without cameras or LiDAR remains challenging due to IMU drift and noisy joint velocity sensing. This paper presents a purely proprioceptive state estimator that uses only IMU and motor measurements to jointly estimate body pose and velocity, with a unified formulation applicable to biped, quadruped, and wheel-legged robots. The key idea is to treat each contacting leg as a kinematic anchor: joint-torque--based foot wrench estimation selects reliable contacts, and the corresponding footfall positions provide intermittent world-frame constraints that suppress long-term drift. To prevent elevation drift during extended traversal, we introduce a lightweight height clustering and time-decay correction that snaps newly recorded footfall heights to previously observed support planes. To improve foot velocity observations under encoder quantization, we apply an inverse-kinematics cubature Kalman filter that directly filters foot-end velocities from joint angles and velocities. The implementation further mitigates yaw drift through multi-contact geometric consistency and degrades gracefully to a kinematics-derived heading reference when IMU yaw constraints are unavailable or unreliable. We evaluate the method on four quadruped platforms (three Astrall robots and a Unitree Go2 EDU) using closed-loop trajectories. On Astrall point-foot robot~A, a $\sim$200\,m horizontal loop and a $\sim$15\,m vertical loop return with 0.1638\,m and 0.219\,m error, respectively; on wheel-legged robot~B, the corresponding errors are 0.2264\,m and 0.199\,m. On wheel-legged robot~C, a $\sim$700\,m horizontal loop yields 7.68\,m error and a $\sim$20\,m vertical loop yields 0.540\,m error. Unitree Go2 EDU closes a $\sim$120\,m horizontal loop with 2.2138\,m error and a $\sim$8\,m vertical loop with less than 0.1\,m vertical error. github.com/ShineMinxing/Ros2Go2Estimator.git</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.17393v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minxing Sun, Yao Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
