<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex</link>
    <description>nucl-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 14:38:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Findings from Heavy-Flavor Angular Correlation Measurements in Hadronic Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of angular correlations of heavy-flavor particles in hadronic collisions can provide crucial insight into the heavy quark production, showering, and hadronization processes. The comparison with model predictions allows us to discriminate among different approaches for heavy quark production and hadronization, as well as different treatments of the underlying event employed by the models to reproduce correlation observables. In ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions, where a deconfined state of matter, the quark--gluon plasma (QGP), is created, heavy-flavor correlations can shed light on the modification of the heavy quark fragmentation due to the interaction between charm and beauty quarks with the QGP constituents, as well as characterize their energy loss processes while traversing the medium. Insight into the possible emergence of collective-like mechanisms in smaller systems, resembling those observed in heavy-ion collisions, can also be obtained by performing correlation studies in high-multiplicity proton--proton and proton--nucleus collisions. In this review, the most recent and relevant measurements of heavy-flavor correlations performed in all collision systems at the LHC and RHIC will be presented, and the new understandings that they provide will be discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01035v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10030109</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10(3), 109</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Deepa Thomas, Fabio Colamaria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electroproduction of the Lambda/Sigma^0 hyperons at Q^2~0.5 (GeV/c)^2 in forward angles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2018, the E12-17-003 experiment was conducted at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab) to explore the possible existence of an nnLambda state in the reconstructed missing mass distribution from a tritium gas target. As part of this investigation, data was also collected using a gaseous hydrogen target, not only for a precise absolute mass scale calibration but also for the study of Lambda/Sigma^0 electroproduction. This dataset was acquired at Q^2~0.5 (GeV/c)^2, W=2.14 GeV, and theta_{gamma K}^{c.m.}~8 deg. It covers forward angles where photoproduction data is scarce and a low-Q^2 region that is of interest for hypernuclear experiments. On the other hand, this kinematic region is at a slightly higher Q^2 than previous hypernuclear experiments, thus providing crucial information for understanding the Q^2 dependence of the differential cross sections for Lambda/Sigma^0 hyperon electroproduction. This paper reports on the Q^2 dependence of the differential cross section for the e + p -&gt; e' + K^+ + Lambda/Sigma^0 reaction in the 0.2-0.8 (GeV/c)^2, and provides comparisons with the currently available theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01173v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Okuyama, K. Itabashi, S. Nagao, S. N. Nakamura, K. N. Suzuki, T. Gogami, B. Pandey, L. Tang, P. Byd\v{z}ovsk\'y, D. Skoupil, T. Mart, D. Abrams, T. Akiyama, D. Androic, K. Aniol, C. Ayerbe Gayoso, J. Bane, S. Barcus, J. Barrow, V. Bellini, H. Bhatt, D. Bhetuwal, D. Biswas, A. Camsonne, J. Castellanos, J-P. Chen, J. Chen, S. Covrig, D. Chrisman, R. Cruz-Torres, R. Das, E. Fuchey, K. Gnanvo, F. Garibaldi, T. Gautam, J. Gomez, P. Gueye, T. J. Hague, O. Hansen, W. Henry, F. Hauenstein, D. W. Higinbotham, C. E. Hyde, M. Kaneta, C. Keppel, T. Kutz, N. Lashley-Colthirst, S. Li, H. Liu, J. Mammei, P. Markowitz, R. E. McClellan, F. Meddi, D. Meekins, R. Michaels, M. Mihovilovic, A. Moyer, D. Nguyen, M. Nycz, V. Owen, C. Palatchi, S. Park, T. Petkovic, S. Premathilake, P. E. Reimer, J. Reinhold, S. Riordan, V. Rodriguez, C. Samanta, S. N. Santiesteban, B. Sawatzky, S. \v{S}irca, K. Slifer, T. Su, Y. Tian, Y. Toyama, K. Uehara, G. M. Urciuoli, D. Votaw, J. Williamson, B. Wojtsekhowski, S. A. Wood, B. Yale, Z. Ye, J. Zhang, Z. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abatement of Ionizing Radiation for Superconducting Quantum Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ionizing radiation has been shown to reduce the performance of superconducting quantum circuits. In this report, we evaluate the expected contributions of different sources of ambient radioactivity for typical superconducting qubit experiment platforms. Our assessment of radioactivity inside a typical cryostat highlights the importance of selecting appropriate materials for the experiment components nearest to qubit devices, such as packaging and electrical interconnects. We present a shallow underground facility (30-meter water equivalent) to reduce the flux of cosmic rays and a lead shielded cryostat to abate the naturally occurring radiogenic gamma-ray flux in the laboratory environment. We predict that superconducting qubit devices operated in this facility could experience a reduced rate of correlated multi-qubit errors by a factor of approximately 20 relative to the rate in a typical above-ground, unshielded facility. Finally, we outline overall design improvements that would be required to further reduce the residual ionizing radiation rate, down to the limit of current generation direct detection dark matter experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01032v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. LoerPacific Northwest National Laboratory, P. M. HarringtonResearch Laboratory of Electronics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, B. ArchambaultPacific Northwest National Laboratory, E. FullerPacific Northwest National Laboratory, B. PiersonPacific Northwest National Laboratory, I. ArnquistPacific Northwest National Laboratory, K. HarouakaPacific Northwest National Laboratory, T. D. SchliederPacific Northwest National Laboratory, D. K. Kimc, A. J. Melvillec, B. M. NiedzielskiMIT Lincoln Laboratory, J. K. YoderMIT Lincoln Laboratory, K. SerniakResearch Laboratory of Electronics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT Lincoln Laboratory, W. D. OliverResearch Laboratory of Electronics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT Lincoln Laboratory, J. L. OrrellPacific Northwest National Laboratory, R. BunkerPacific Northwest National Laboratory, B. A. VanDevenderPacific Northwest National Laboratory, M. WarnerPacific Northwest National Laboratory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-number projected generator coordinate method for $^{21}$Ne with a chiral two-nucleon-plus-three-nucleon interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01177v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report a study of the low-lying states of deformed $^{21}$Ne within the framework of quantum-number projected generator coordinate method (PGCM), starting from a chiral two-nucleon-plus-three-nucleon (NN+3N) interaction. The wave functions of states are constructed as a linear combination of a set of axially-deformed Hartree-Fock-Bogliubov (HFB) wave functions with different quadrupole deformations. These HFB wave functions are projected onto different angular momenta and the correct neutron and proton numbers for $^{21}$Ne. The results of calculations based on the effective Hamiltonians derived by normal-ordering the 3N interaction with respect to three different reference states, including the quantum-number projected HFB wave functions for $^{20}$Ne, $^{22}$Ne, and an ensemble of them with equal weights, are compared. This study serves as a key step towards ab initio calculations of odd-mass deformed nuclei with the in-medium GCM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01177v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Lin, E. F. Zhou, J. M. Yao, H. Hergert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strangeness plus-one ($S=+1$) resonance-state $P^{+*}_0$ via $K^+n\to K^{*0}p$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In our current study, we delve into the peak-like structure observed during the reaction process of $K^+n\to K^{0}p$ at approximately $\sqrt{s}\sim2.5$ GeV. Our focus centers on exploring the potential $S=+1$ resonance $P^{+*}_0\equiv P^*_0$ as an excited state within the extended vector-meson and baryon ($VB$) antidecuplet. To achieve this aim, we employ the effective Lagrangian method in conjunction with the $(u,t)$-channel Regge approach, operating within the tree-level Born approximation. We thoroughly examine various spin-parity quantum numbers for the resonance, resulting in a compelling description of the data, where $M_{P^*_0}\approx2.5$ GeV and $\Gamma_{P^*_0}\approx100$ MeV. Furthermore, we propose an experimental technique to amplify the signal-to-noise ratio ($S/N$) for accurately measuring the resonance. Notably, our findings reveal that background interference diminishes significantly within the $K^*$ forward-scattering region in the center-of-mass frame when the $K^*$ is perpendicularly polarized to the reaction plane. Additionally, we explore the recoil-proton spin asymmetry to definitively determine the spin and parity of the resonance. This study stands to serve as a valuable reference for designing experimental setups aimed at investigating and comprehending exotic phenomena in QCD. Specifically, our insights will inform future J-PARC experiments, particularly those employing higher kaon beam energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01191v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dayoung Lee, Seung-il Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypertriton Production in Au+Au Collisions from STAR BES-II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15768v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hypernuclei are bound states of nuclei with one or more hyperons. Precise measurements of hypernuclei properties and their production yields in heavy ion collisions are crucial for the understanding of their production mechanisms. The second phase of the Beam Energy Scan at RHIC (BES-II) offers us a great opportunity to investigate collision energy and system size dependence of hypernuclei production. In these proceedings, we present new measurements on transverse momentum ($p_{T}$), rapidity (y), and centrality dependence of $\rm {}^{3}_{\Lambda}H$ production yields in Au+Au collisions from $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$ = 3 to 7.7 GeV. These results are compared with phenomenological model calculations, and physics implications on the hypernuclei production mechanism are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15768v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanjing Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\gamma Z$-Exchange Contributions in Low-Energy Parity-Violating $ep$ Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01813v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, the $\gamma Z$-exchange contributions in the low-energy elastic parity-violating $ep$ scattering are discussed with the approximation $m_e=0$. By expanding the $\gamma pp$ and $Zpp$ interactions on the momentum of photon and considering both the leading-order and the next-to-leading order interactions, we calculate the amplitudes of the $\gamma Z$-exchange diagrams. After performing the loop integral, we expand the results in the low energy limit, and obtain the analytic expressions for the amplitudes. Numerical comparisons show that the analytic expressions are very close to the full results over a large region. We investigate the power behaviors of these contributions and find that some are enhanced by a kinematic factor in the low energy limit. Additionally, in some cases, the imaginary parts of the contributions from the next-to-leading-order interactions are at the same order as those from the leading-order interactions. Furthermore, the corresponding contributions to the physical observable quantity $A_{\textrm{PV}}$ are also discussed. Combining all the properties together, we conclude that these analytic expressions describe the leading-order contributions of all $\gamma Z$-exchange helicity amplitudes in the region with $\alpha_e\ll Q/M_N\sim \delta/M_N^2\ll 1$, where $\alpha_{e}$ is the fine structure constant, $M_N$ is the mass of proton, $Q$ and $\delta$ are the small quantities related to the momentum transfer and the center-of-mass energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01813v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian-Qian Guo, Hai-Qing Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corrections to the Forward Limit Dispersion Relations for $\gamma Z$-Exchange Contributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16294v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The weak charge of the proton $Q_{\textrm{w}}$ is one of the most fundamental quantities in physics. It can be determined by measuring the parity asymmetry $A_{\textrm{PV}}$ in elastic $ep$ scattering, where the $\gamma Z$-exchange contributions are crucial. For the past fifteen years, dispersion relations (DRs) in the forward limit have been widely used as a model-independent method to estimate these contributions. In this work, we study corrections to these forward-limit DRs. We first estimate these corrections using pointlike interactions as an illustrative example. We then estimate the $\gamma Z$-exchange contributions for the upcoming P2 experiment through both direct calculation and the forward-limit DRs, within the framework of low-energy effective interactions. The results indicate that the correction to the forward-limit DR for $\Box_{\gamma Z}^{V}$ is around 47\% for the upcoming P2 experiment, which will significantly modify the extracted value of $Q_{\textrm{w}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16294v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian-Qian Guo, Hai-Qing Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon axial-vector form factor and radius from future neutrino experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02509v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Precision measurements of antineutrino elastic scattering on hydrogen from future neutrino experiments offer a unique opportunity to access the low-energy structure of protons and neutrons. We discuss the determination of the nucleon axial-vector form factor and radius from antineutrino interactions on hydrogen that can be collected at the future Long-Baseline Neutrino Facility, and study the sources of theoretical and experimental uncertainties. The projected accuracy would improve existing measurements by $1$ order of magnitude and be competitive with contemporary lattice-QCD determinations, potentially helping to resolve the corresponding tension with measurements from (anti)neutrino elastic scattering on deuterium. We find that the current knowledge of the nucleon vector form factors could be one of the dominant sources of uncertainty. We also evaluate the constraints that can be simultaneously obtained on the absolute $\bar \nu_\mu$ flux normalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02509v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109 (2023), L051301</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Petti, Richard J. Hill, Oleksandr Tomalak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detailed Report on the Measurement of the Positive Muon Anomalous Magnetic Moment to 0.20 ppm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15410v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present details on a new measurement of the muon magnetic anomaly, $a_\mu = (g_\mu -2)/2$. The result is based on positive muon data taken at Fermilab's Muon Campus during the 2019 and 2020 accelerator runs. The measurement uses $3.1$ GeV$/c$ polarized muons stored in a $7.1$-m-radius storage ring with a $1.45$ T uniform magnetic field. The value of $ a_{\mu}$ is determined from the measured difference between the muon spin precession frequency and its cyclotron frequency. This difference is normalized to the strength of the magnetic field, measured using Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR). The ratio is then corrected for small contributions from beam motion, beam dispersion, and transient magnetic fields. We measure $a_\mu = 116 592 057 (25) \times 10^{-11}$ (0.21 ppm). This is the world's most precise measurement of this quantity and represents a factor of $2.2$ improvement over our previous result based on the 2018 dataset. In combination, the two datasets yield $a_\mu(\text{FNAL}) = 116 592 055 (24) \times 10^{-11}$ (0.20 ppm). Combining this with the measurements from Brookhaven National Laboratory for both positive and negative muons, the new world average is $a_\mu$(exp) $ = 116 592 059 (22) \times 10^{-11}$ (0.19 ppm).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15410v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. P. Aguillard, T. Albahri, D. Allspach, A. Anisenkov, K. Badgley, S. Bae{\ss}ler, I. Bailey, L. Bailey, V. A. Baranov, E. Barlas-Yucel, T. Barrett, E. Barzi, F. Bedeschi, M. Berz, M. Bhattacharya, H. P. Binney, P. Bloom, J. Bono, E. Bottalico, T. Bowcock, S. Braun, M. Bressler, G. Cantatore, R. M. Carey, B. C. K. Casey, D. Cauz, R. Chakraborty, A. Chapelain, S. Chappa, S. Charity, C. Chen, M. Cheng, R. Chislett, Z. Chu, T. E. Chupp, C. Claessens, M. E. Convery, S. Corrodi, L. Cotrozzi, J. D. Crnkovic, S. Dabagov, P. T. Debevec, S. Di Falco, G. Di Sciascio, S. Donati, B. Drendel, A. Driutti, V. N. Duginov, M. Eads, A. Edmonds, J. Esquivel, M. Farooq, R. Fatemi, C. Ferrari, M. Fertl, A. T. Fienberg, A. Fioretti, D. Flay, S. B. Foster, H. Friedsam, N. S. Froemming, C. Gabbanini, I. Gaines, M. D. Galati, S. Ganguly, A. Garcia, J. George, L. K. Gibbons, A. Gioiosa, K. L. Giovanetti, P. Girotti, W. Gohn, L. Goodenough, T. Gorringe, J. Grange, S. Grant, F. Gray, S. Haciomeroglu, T. Halewood-Leagas, D. Hampai, F. Han, J. Hempstead, D. W. Hertzog, G. Hesketh, E. Hess, A. Hibbert, Z. Hodge, K. W. Hong, R. Hong, T. Hu, Y. Hu, M. Iacovacci, M. Incagli, P. Kammel, M. Kargiantoulakis, M. Karuza, J. Kaspar, D. Kawall, L. Kelton, A. Keshavarzi, D. S. Kessler, K. S. Khaw, Z. Khechadoorian, N. V. Khomutov, B. Kiburg, M. Kiburg, O. Kim, N. Kinnaird, E. Kraegeloh, V. A. Krylov, N. A. Kuchinskiy, K. R. Labe, J. LaBounty, M. Lancaster, S. Lee, B. Li, D. Li, L. Li, I. Logashenko, A. Lorente Campos, Z. Lu, A. Luc\`a, G. Lukicov, A. Lusiani, A. L. Lyon, B. MacCoy, R. Madrak, K. Makino, S. Mastroianni, J. P. Miller, S. Miozzi, B. Mitra, J. P. Morgan, W. M. Morse, J. Mott, A. Nath, J. K. Ng, H. Nguyen, Y. Oksuzian, Z. Omarov, R. Osofsky, S. Park, G. Pauletta, G. M. Piacentino, R. N. Pilato, K. T. Pitts, B. Plaster, D. Po\v{c}ani\'c, N. Pohlman, C. C. Polly, J. Price, B. Quinn, M. U. H. Qureshi, S. Ramachandran, E. Ramberg, R. Reimann, B. L. Roberts, D. L. Rubin, M. Sakurai, L. Santi, C. Schlesier, A. Schreckenberger, Y. K. Semertzidis, D. Shemyakin, M. Sorbara, J. Stapleton, D. Still, D. St\"ockinger, C. Stoughton, D. Stratakis, H. E. Swanson, G. Sweetmore, D. A. Sweigart, M. J. Syphers, D. A. Tarazona, T. Teubner, A. E. Tewsley-Booth, V. Tishchenko, N. H. Tran, W. Turner, E. Valetov, D. Vasilkova, G. Venanzoni, V. P. Volnykh, T. Walton, A. Weisskopf, L. Welty-Rieger, P. Winter, Y. Wu, B. Yu, M. Yucel, Y. Zeng, C. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
