<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex</link>
    <description>nucl-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous impacts of nuclear shell structure and collectivity on $\beta$-decay: evidence from $^{80}$Ga$_{49}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Gamow-Teller strength distribution covering the entire $\beta$-decay window, up to 10.312(4) MeV, of $^{80g+m}$Ga was measured for the first time in photo-fission of UC$_x$ induced by 50 MeV electron beam. The new data show significant enhancement in the high-energy region with a jump-structure. Simultaneously, the $\gamma$ de-exciting behavior of $\beta$-populated states presents a competition between de-excitation to 2$_1^+$ [$\beta_2$ = 0.155(9)] and to 2$_2^+$ [$\beta_2$ = 0.053$_{0.009}^{0.008}$)] in $^{80}$Ge. Based on these facts and combined with a realistic shell model calculation and systematic analysis of logft ratio between precursor $\beta$-decay to 2$_2^+$ and to 2$_1^+$ of Ga isotopes, we conclude that these phenomena evidence simultaneous impacts of nuclear shell structure and collectivity on B(GT) and its distribution and, therefore, the half-life of the precursor. These data prove that the nucleus as a multi-nucleon correlated quantum system reacts as a whole when $\beta$-decay occurs in contrast to simple single-particle excitation. Additionally, the comparison with the theoretical results evidence how challenging is the description of the experimental data obtained, and render this experimental outcome a sound test for the theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20490v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Li, D. Verney, G. De Gregorio, R. Mancino, I. Matea, L. Coraggio, N. Itaco., M. N. Harakeh, C. Delafosse, F. Didierjean, L. A. Ayoubi, H. Al Falou, G. Benzoni, F. Le Blanc, V. Bozkurt, M. Ciema{\l}a, I. Deloncle, M. Fallot, C. Gaulard, A. Gottardo, V. Guadilla, J. Guillot, K. Hady\'nska-Kl\k{e}k, F. Ibrahim, N. Jovancevic, A. Kankainen, M. Lebois, T. Mart\'inez, P. Napiorkowski, B. Roussiere, Yu. G. Sobolev, I. Stefan, S. Stukalov, D. Thisse, G. Tocabens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Highlights from STAR BES Phase II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The second phase of the RHIC Beam Energy Scan (BES-II) was conducted between 2019 and 2021. High statistics data was collected by the STAR experiment for Au+Au collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$ from 7.7 to 27 GeV in collider mode and from 3 to 13.7 GeV in fixed target mode. A selection of results from the various BES-II analyses are presented here to showcase the wide range of physics accessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20928v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Neff (for the STAR Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the nature of the QCD phase transition with higher-order net-proton number fluctuation and local parton density fluctuation measurements at RHIC-STAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The moments of proton and net-proton multiplicity distributions are observables expected to be sensitive to the QCD critical point and the nature of the QCD phase transition from QGP to hadron gas. Hyper-order cumulants are measured in wide centrality bins in STAR BES-I data and found to be qualitatively consistent with trends predicted by lattice QCD which finds a cross-over phase transition at low $\mu_\text{B}$. Data collected at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=3$ GeV in BES-II exhibit trends opposite of those observed in higher energy collisions which may suggest the dominance of hadronic interactions at this energy. The variance of proton multiplicity distributions in azimuthal partitions is measured to search for signals of clustering indicative of a first-order phase transition. A strong dependence on the event multiplicity is observed. This dependence is independent of energy in AMPT while in STAR data a significant trend with energy is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20929v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Neff (for the STAR Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First evidence for chiral wobbling of triaxial nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The appearance of wobbling motion and chirality in rotating triaxial nuclei is explained. The discovery of a new mode, chiral wobbling, in $^{74}$Br, is commented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20802v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Frauendorf</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
