<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex</link>
    <description>nucl-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Compton Edge Convolutional Model and Algorithm for Energy-channel Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06950v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scintillation detectors are essential tools for radiation measurement, but calibrating them accurately can be challenging, especially when full-energy peaks are not prominent. This is common in detectors like plastic scintillators. Current methods for calibrating these detectors often require manual adjustments. To address this, we propose a new method called the convolution model. This model accurately calibrates the energy-channel relationship of the Compton edge in various detectors. We tested it with plastic scintillator BC408, NaI crystal, and LaBr$_3$ crystal. Using ${}^{137}$Cs radioactive sources, we calibrated NaI and LaBr$_3$ detectors using full-energy peaks, then applied the convolution model to fit the Compton edge. Our results show errors within 1\% when compared to full-energy peak calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06950v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanbiao Zhang, Yeqi Fang, Fanjie Zeng, Dehua Kong, Lian Lei, Zhonghai Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio investigation of the $^7$Li($p,e^+e^-$)$^8$Be process and the X17 boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13751v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Observations of anomalies in the electron-positron angular correlations in high-energy decays in $^4$He, $^8$Be, and $^{12}$C have been reported recently by the ATOMKI collaboration. These could be explained by the creation and subsequent decay of a new boson with a mass of ${\sim}17$ MeV. Theoretical understanding of pair creation in the proton capture reactions used in these experiments is important for the interpretation of the anomalies. We apply the ab initio No-Core Shell Model with Continuum (NCSMC) to the proton capture on $^7$Li. The NCSMC describes both bound and unbound states in light nuclei in a unified way with chiral two- and three-nucleon interactions as the only input. We investigate the structure of $^8$Be, the $p+^7$Li elastic scattering, the $^7$Li($p,\gamma$)$^8$Be cross section and the internal pair creation $^7$Li($p,e^+ e^-$)$^8$Be. We discuss the impact of a proper treatment of the initial scattering state on the electron-positron angular correlation spectrum and compare our results to available ATOMKI data sets. Finally, we calculate $^7$Li($p,X$)$^8$Be cross sections for several proposed models of the hypothetical X17 particle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13751v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Gysbers, P. Navratil, K. Kravvaris, G. Hupin, S. Quaglioni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin asymmetry and dipole moments in $\tau$-pair production with ultraperipheral heavy ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14153v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The anomalous magnetic (MDM) and electric (EDM) dipole moments of the $\tau$ lepton serve as crucial indicators of new physics beyond the Standard Model. Leveraging azimuthal angular asymmetry as a novel tool in ultraperipheral collisions (UPCs), we attain unparalleled precision in the study of these key properties. Driven by the highly linear polarization of coherent photons, this method uniquely enables both the MDM and EDM to contribute to the $\cos2\phi$ angular distribution in similar magnitudes. Importantly, our approach substantially narrows the parameter space, excluding more than half of it compared to expected UPC-based measurements reliant solely on the total cross-section. This method not only provides improved constraints but also minimizes the need for additional theoretical assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14153v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ding Yu Shao, Bin Yan, Shu-Run Yuan, Cheng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
