<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-ex updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex</link>
    <description>nucl-ex updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-ex" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 03:29:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Improved $S$-factor of the $^{13}$C(p,$\gamma$)$^{14}$N reaction at $E_{\mathrm{p}}\,=\,$330-740 keV and parameters of resonances at 448 keV and 551 keV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $^{13}$C(p,$\gamma$)$^{14}$N reaction is the second reaction of the CNO cycle. This cycle takes place in our Sun and fuels massive, Red, and Asymptotic Giant Branch stars. The $^{13}$C(p,$\gamma$)$^{14}$N rate affects the final abundances of $^{12,13}$C and $^{19}$F nuclides, with impact on our understanding of the i- and s-process, giant star nucleosynthesis and mixing processes, and ultimately the chemical evolution of the Galaxy. Here, we report on a new measurement of the $^{13}$C(p,$\gamma$)$^{14}$N cross-section, which has been performed at the Felsenkeller shallow-underground laboratory in Dresden (Germany). The present $S$-factor results agree at low energy with LUNA data but are about 20% lower than previous literature data over the whole energy range explored, $E\,=\,$310-680 keV. The narrow resonance corresponding to the 7966.9(5) keV excited state has been investigated and we report a new resonance strength, $\omega \gamma\,=\,$18(2) meV. In addition a new R-matrix fit is presented, from which new parameters for the broad resonance corresponding to the 8062.0(10) keV excited state are derived and a new extrapolation for the total $S$-factor down to zero energy is obtained, $S_{\mathrm{tot}}$(0) = 6.4(4) keV b. Finally a new reaction rate is calculated and reported here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17288v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Skowronski, E. Masha, D. Piatti, M. Aliotta, D. Bemmerer, A. Boeltzig, A. Caciolli, F. Cavanna, L. Csedreki, R. Depalo, P. Hempel, M. Hilz, G. Imbriani, T. Lossin, M. Osswald, B. Poser, D. Rapagnani, S. R\"ummler, K. Schmidt, R. S. Sidhu, T. Sz\"ucs, A. T\'oth, S. Turkat, S. Vincent, S. Werner, A. Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The anomalous magnetic moment of the muon: status and perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the status of the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon as a precision probe of physics beyond the Standard Model (SM) after the release of the final results from the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (FNAL) Muon $g-2$ experiment and the second White Paper of the Muon $g-2$ Theory Initiative. While the SM prediction requires further improvements by a factor of four to fully leverage the sensitivity achieved in experiment, the FNAL measurement will set the standard for many years to come, and we discuss a variety of features of the experimental campaign that made this achievement possible. In going forward, we discuss current efforts to improve the SM prediction, and imagine how an experiment would have to be devised to surpass 124 ppb in precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16980v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1146/annurev-nucl-102422-040841</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David W. Hertzog, Martin Hoferichter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From closed shells to open shells: Coupled-cluster calculations of atomic nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coupled-cluster theory is a powerful tool for first-principles calculations of atomic nuclei, enabling accurate predictions of nuclear observables across the Segr\`e chart. While coupled-cluster computations are especially efficient at shell closures, extensions have been developed to tackle open-shell nuclei, by exploiting the equation-of-motion method or by expanding the coupled-cluster wave function on top of a symmetry-breaking (either deformed or superfluid) reference state. In this study, we provide a comprehensive comparison of these different formulations applied to the calcium and nickel isotopes using nuclear two- and three-body interactions from chiral effective field theory. Based on ground-state energies, two-neutron separation energies, and two-neutron shell gaps, different coupled-cluster computations - based on symmetry-broken reference states and equation-of-motion techniques - offer consistent descriptions of bulk properties across medium-mass isotopic chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17311v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Marino, F. Bonaiti, P. Demol, S. Bacca, T. Duguet, G. Hagen, G. R. Jansen, T. Papenbrock, A. Tichai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Final SeaQuest results on the flavor asymmetry of the proton light-quark sea with proton-induced Drell-Yan process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Fermilab E906/SeaQuest collaboration performed measurements of the Drell-Yan process using 120 GeV proton beams bombarding liquid hydrogen and liquid deuterium targets. A combined analysis of all collected data was performed to obtain the final results for the $\sigma_{pd}/2\sigma_{pp}$ Drell-Yan cross section ratio covering the kinematic region of $0.13 &lt; x &lt; 0.45$. The $x$-dependencies of $\bar{d}\left(x\right) / \bar{u}\left(x\right)$ and $\bar{d}\left(x\right) - \bar{u}\left(x\right)$ are extracted from these cross section ratios. It is found that $\bar{d}\left(x\right)$ is greater than $\bar{u}\left(x\right)$ over the entire measured $x$ range, with improved statistical accuracy compared to previous measurements. The new results on $\bar{d}\left(x\right) / \bar{u}\left(x\right)$ and $\bar{d}\left(x\right) - \bar{u}\left(x\right)$ are compared to various parton distribution functions and theoretical calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17564v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> SeaQuest Collaboration, C. H. Leung, J. Dove, K. Nagai, K. Nakano, S. Prasad, A. S. Tadepalli, C. A. Aidala, J. Arrington, C. Ayuso, C. L. Barker, W. C. Chang, A. Chen, D. C. Christian, B. P. Dannowitz, L. El Fassi, D. F. Geesaman, R. Gilman, Y. Goto, R. S. Guo, L. Guo, T. J. Hague, R. J. Holt, M. F. Hossain, L. D. Isenhower, E. R. Kinney, A. Klein, D. Kleinjan, P. -J. Lin, K. Liu, M. X. Liu, W. Lorenzon, R. E. McClellan, P. L. McGaughey, M. M. Medeiros, Y. Miyachi, S. Miyasaka, D. H. Morton, K. Nakahara, J. C. Peng, A. J. R. Puckett, A. Pun, B. J. Ramson, P. E. Reimer, J. G. Rubin, F. Sanftl, S. Sawada, T. Sawada, M. B. C. Scott, T. -A. Shibata, D. -S. Su, M. Teo, R. Towell, S. Uemura, S. G. Wang, J. Wu, N. Wuerfel, Z. H. Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active learning emulators for nuclear two-body scattering in momentum space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17842v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the active learning emulators for two-body scattering in coordinate space with error estimation, recently developed by Maldonado et al. in Phys. Rev. C \textbf{112}, 024002, to coupled-channel scattering in momentum space. Our full-order model (FOM) solver is based on the Lippmann-Schwinger integral equation for the scattering $t$-matrix as opposed to the radial Schr\"odinger equation. We use (Petrov-)Galerkin projections and high-fidelity calculations at a few snapshots across the parameter space of the interaction to construct efficient reduced-order models (ROMs), trained by a greedy algorithm for locally optimal snapshot selection. Both the FOM solver and the corresponding ROMs are implemented efficiently in Python using Google's JAX library. We present results for emulating scattering phase shifts in coupled and uncoupled channels and cross sections, and assess the accuracy of the developed ROMs and their computational speed-up factors. We also develop emulator error estimation for both the $t$-matrix and the total cross section. The software framework for reproducing and extending our results will be made publicly available. Together with our recent advances in developing active-learning emulators for three-body scattering, these emulator frameworks set the stage for full Bayesian calibrations of chiral nuclear interactions and optical models against scattering data with quantified emulator errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17842v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Giri, J. Kim, C. Drischler, Ch. Elster, R. J. Furnstahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triplet of kindred prompt-2p emitters in mass-8 proton-rich nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.15598v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A triplet of kindred prompt-2p emitters in A=8 nuclei has been demonstrated. Two of these are the ground state of 8C and its isobaric analog state in 8B, both of which are analogs of the halo or thick-skinned nucleus 8He. The third member is the recently found fourth 1+ state in 8B. This new 8B state at E*=8.4 MeV was observed to decay to the ground state of 6Li by 2p emission. Momentum correlations between the decay products indicate that it is not a sequential 2p decay through a 7Be intermediate state, but indicative of prompt 2p emission with correlations similar to those of the other members of the triplet. Ab initio calculations with the symmetry-adapted nocore shell model indicate that these three states have very similar spatial wavefunctions, but with nucleons coupling to different spins, isospins, and isospin projections. The triplet of 2p emitters all have oblate shapes and by stripping two protons equatorially, decay to states which have prolate shapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.15598v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. J. Charity, G. H. Sargsyan, K. D. Launey, T. B. Webb, K. W. Brown, L. G. Sobotka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
