<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-lat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat</link>
    <description>hep-lat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement entropy of a color flux tube in (2+1)D Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a novel flux tube entanglement entropy (FTE$^2$), defined as the excess entanglement entropy relative to the vacuum of a region of color flux stretching between a heavy quark-anti-quark pair in pure gauge Yang-Mills theory. We show that FTE$^2$ can be expressed in terms of correlators of Polyakov loops, is manifestly gauge-invariant, and therefore free of the ambiguities in computations of the entanglement entropy in gauge theories related to the choice of the center algebra. Employing the replica trick, we compute FTE$^2$ for $SU(2)$ Yang-Mills theory in (2+1)D and demonstrate that it is finite in the continuum limit. We explore the properties of FTE$^2$ for a half-slab geometry, which allows us to vary the width and location of the slab, and the extent to which the slab cross-cuts the color flux tube. Following the intuition provided by computations of FTE$^2$ in (1+1)D, and in a thin string model, we examine the extent to which our FTE$^2$ results can be interpreted as the sum of an internal color entropy and a vibrational entropy corresponding to the transverse excitations of the string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00112v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rocco Amorosso, Sergey Syritsyn, Raju Venugopalan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking higher-order moments of parton distribution functions from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new method to calculate moments of parton distribution functions of any order with lattice QCD computations. This method leverages the gradient flow for fermion and gauge fields. The flowed matrix elements of twist-2 operators renormalize multiplicatively, and the matching with physical matrix elements is achieved through the use of continuum symmetries. We derive the matching coefficients at one-loop in perturbation theory for moments of any order in the flavor non-singlet case and provide specific examples of operators suitable for lattice QCD computations. The multiplicative renormalization and matching are independent of the choice of Lorentz indices, allowing the use of temporal indices for twist-2 operators of any dimension. This approach should then also significantly enhance the signal-to-noise ratio in the computation of moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00198v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Shindler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A practical guide to fitting correlation functions from lattice data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This guide contains a collection of the tips, tricks, and techniques that we have found to be useful when performing very large, correlated Bayesian fits of two, and three-point correlation functions for semileptonic decays, in this case $B\to K$ and $D\to K$. It is written explicitly with the use of gvar, lsqfit and corrfitter in mind, but many techniques are transferable to other fitting software, and other correlator fits. The guide is by no means comprehensive, and many problems can be approached from different angles and points of view. The intention here is simply to present ideas which may be useful to others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00802v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. G. Parrott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden charm-bottom structures $bc\overline{b}\overline{c}$: Axial-vector case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mass and width of a hidden charm-bottom axial-vector structure $T$ containing $bc \overline{b}\overline{c}$ quarks are calculated in QCD sum rule framework. It is treated as a diquark-antidiquark state built of scalar diquark and axial-vector antidiquark components. The mass of $T$ is computed using the two-point sum rule method. The width of this particle is evaluated by considering eight decay modes: The decays to $\eta _{b}J/\psi $, $\eta _{c}\Upsilon (1S)$, $B_{c}^{-}B_{c}^{\ast +}$, and $B_{c}^{+}B_{c}^{\ast -}$ are dissociation processes, in which all initial quarks are distributed between the final-state particles. Four decays to $DD$ mesons with appropriate charges and spin-parities are channels generated due to the annihilation of $b$ and $\overline{b}$ quarks from $T$. Partial widths for all of these processes are obtained by employing the three-point sum rule approach necessary to find the strong couplings at relevant tetraquark-meson-meson vertices. Our results for the mass $m=(12715\pm 90)~\mathrm{MeV}$ and width $\Gamma[T] =(104.2 \pm 11.2)~ \mathrm{MeV}$ of the tetraquark $T$, as well as its numerous decay channels explored in this article are useful for ongoing and future experimental investigations of fully heavy resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00575v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Agaev, K. Azizi, H. Sundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector interaction bounds in NJL-like models from LQCD estimated curvature of the chiral crossover line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00653v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We obtain improved bounds on both the flavor-independent and -dependent vector interactions in a $2+1$-flavor Nambu\textendash Jona-Lasinio (NJL) model using the latest precise LQCD results of the curvature coefficients of the chiral crossover line. We find that these lattice estimated curvature coefficients allow for both attractive and repulsive types of interactions in both the cases. With this constrained ranges of vector interactions, we further predict the behavior of the second $(\kappa_2^B)$ and fourth $(\kappa_4^B)$ order curvature coefficients as a function of the strangeness chemical potential $(\mu_S)$. We observe that the flavor mixing effects, arising from the flavor-independent vector interaction as well as from the 't Hooft interaction, play an important role in $k_2^B$. We propose that the mixing effects due to the vector interaction can be separated from those arising from the 't Hooft interaction by analyzing the behavior of $k_2^B$ as a function of $\mu_S$. Finally, we locate the critical endpoint in the $T-\mu_B$ plane using the model-estimated ranges of vector interactions and find the model's predictions to be consistent with the latest LQCD bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00653v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahammad Sabir Ali, Deeptak Biswas, Chowdhury Aminul Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A variational study of two-nucleon systems with lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.10835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.10835v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The low-energy spectrum and scattering of two-nucleon systems are studied with lattice quantum chromodynamics using a variational approach. A wide range of interpolating operators are used: dibaryon operators built from products of plane-wave nucleons, hexaquark operators built from six localized quarks, and quasi-local operators inspired by two-nucleon bound-state wavefunctions in low-energy effective theories. Sparsening techniques are used to compute the timeslice-to-all quark propagators required to form correlation-function matrices using products of these operators. Projection of these matrices onto irreducible representations of the cubic group, including spin-orbit coupling, is detailed. Variational methods are applied to constrain the low-energy spectra of two-nucleon systems in a single finite volume with quark masses corresponding to a pion mass of 806 MeV. Results for S- and D-wave phase shifts in the isospin singlet and triplet channels are obtained under the assumption that partial-wave mixing is negligible. Tests of interpolating-operator dependence are used to investigate the reliability of the energy spectra obtained and highlight both the strengths and weaknesses of variational methods. These studies and comparisons to previous studies using the same gauge-field ensemble demonstrate that interpolating-operator dependence can lead to significant effects on the two-nucleon energy spectra obtained using both variational and non-variational methods, including missing energy levels and other discrepancies. While this study is inconclusive regarding the presence of two-nucleon bound states at this quark mass, it provides robust upper bounds on two-nucleon energy levels that can be improved in future calculations using additional interpolating operators and is therefore a step toward reliable nuclear spectroscopy from the underlying Standard Model of particle physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.10835v4</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.107.094508</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 107, 094508 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saman Amarasinghe, Riyadh Baghdadi, Zohreh Davoudi, William Detmold, Marc Illa, Assumpta Parreno, Andrew V. Pochinsky, Phiala E. Shanahan, Michael L. Wagman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the finite volume two-nucleon spectrum at $m_\pi \approx 806$ MeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12039v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The low-energy finite-volume spectrum of the two-nucleon system at a quark mass corresponding to a pion mass of $m_\pi \approx 806$ MeV is studied with lattice quantum chromodynamics (LQCD) using variational methods. The interpolating-operator sets used in [Phys.Rev.D 107 (2023) 9, 094508] are extended by including a complete basis of local hexaquark operators, as well as plane-wave dibaryon operators built from products of both positive- and negative-parity nucleon operators. Results are presented for the isosinglet and isotriplet two-nucleon channels. In both channels, noticably weaker variational bounds on the lowest few energy eigenvalues are obtained from operator sets which contain only hexaquark operators or operators constructed from the product of two negative-parity nucleons, while other operator sets produce low-energy variational bounds which are consistent within statistical uncertainties. The consequences of these studies for the LQCD understanding of the two-nucleon spectrum are investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12039v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Detmold, Marc Illa, William I. Jay, Assumpta Parre\~no, Robert J. Perry, Phiala E. Shanahan, Michael L. Wagman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Dark Energy from Lattice Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the behavior of the vacuum in Euclidean dynamical triangulations (EDT). Algorithmic improvements and better lattice spacing determinations allow us to test the properties of the emergent de Sitter geometries of our simulations to higher precision than previously possible. Although the agreement with de Sitter is good, the improved precision reveals deviations that can be interpreted as non-trivial vacuum dynamics, well-described by a cosmological constant that runs with scale. The simulations show that the dominant running is quadratic and that the scale can be identified with the Hubble rate. Several key cross-checks support this picture, including consistent results across multiple lattice spacings and the fact that the null energy condition is not violated. The parameters of the running are fully determined by simulations, enabling predictions when extrapolated to the scales relevant for our universe. This leads to a model for dark energy that is compatible with current observations, but which predicts deviations from $\Lambda$CDM at the ${\cal O}(10^{-3})$ level in cosmological observables that could be tested with future improvements in precision measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08963v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingwei Dai, Walter Freeman, Jack Laiho, Marc Schiffer, Judah Unmuth-Yockey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectrum of open strings in the Hard-Wall model of AdS/QCD: the role of $S^5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10183v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of a classical open string representing a meson in the hard-wall geometry and consider the $S^5$ compact space. The existence of a confining region leads to a discrete set of string configurations parameterized by the number $n$ of complete turnarounds $S^5$ great circles. Unlike the conformal case, the string in the bulk can explore $S^5$ even in the case of equal boundary conditions on its endpoints. The string solutions are parameterized by an internal dimensionless conserved charge $l_n$. The $q\bar{q}$ potential is linear for large separations, and the string tension is sensitive to $l_n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10183v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saulo Diles</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
