<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-lat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat</link>
    <description>hep-lat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-taste representation of minimally doubled fermions from first principles: Karsten-Wilczek fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Minimally doubled fermions realize one pair of Dirac fermions on the lattice. Similarities to Kogut-Susskind fermions exist, namely, spin and taste degrees of freedom become intertwined, and a peculiar non-singlet chiral symmetry and ultralocality are maintained. However, charge conjugation, some space-time reflection symmetries and isotropy are broken by the cutoff. We address the most simple variant, Karsten-Wilczek fermions, in its parallel and in its perpendicular version. We derive the correct spin-taste representation from first principles. The spin-taste representation on the quark level permits construction of local or extended hadron interpolating operators for any spin-taste combination, albeit with contamination by parity partners and taste-symmetry breaking. We classify all interpolating operator for mesons and diquarks, and give examples for baryons. We also discuss the appropriate discretizations for taste-singlet or taste-isovector mass or chemical potential terms. We explain the counterterms in the spin-taste framework, and derive generic constraints on the parametric form and cutoff effects from the KW determinant and hadronic correlation functions. We derive how and why non-perturbative tuning schemes for the counterterms work, and obtain analytic, assumption-free, non-perturbative predictions for taste-symmetry breaking and other hadronic properties from first principles. In particular, we identify the origin and nature of two different types of taste-symmetry breaking cutoff effects. The few available numerical results for KW fermions validate these predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16500v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Heinrich Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon electromagnetic form factors at large momentum from Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Proton and neutron electric and magnetic form factors are the primary characteristics of their spatial structure and have been studied extensively over the past half-century. At large values of the momentum transfer $Q^2$ they should reveal transition from nonperturbative to perturbative QCD dynamics as well as effects of quark orbital angular momenta and diquark correlations. Currently, these form factors are being measured at JLab at momentum transfer up to $Q^2=18$ GeV$^2$ for the proton and up to 14 GeV$^2$ for the neutron. We report preliminary results of our lattice calculations of these form factors, including $G_E$ and $G_M$ nucleon form factors with momenta up to $Q^2=8$ GeV$^2$, pion masses down to the almost-physical $m_\pi$=170 MeV, several lattice spacings down to $a=0.073$ fm, and high $O(10^5)$ statistics. Specifically, we study individual form factors, the $G_E/G_M$ ratios, and flavor dependence of contributions to the form factors. We observe qualitative agreement of our ab initio theory calculations with experiment. Comparison of our calculations and upcoming JLab experimental results will be an important test of nonperturbative QCD methods in the almost-perturbative regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17283v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Pos(LATTICE2024)340</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Syritsyn, M. Engelhardt, S. Krieg, J. Negele, A. Pochinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Corrections to Quark TMDPDFs in the Background-Field Method: Gauge Invariance, Equations of Motion, and Multiple Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We calculate the perturbative corrections in the strong coupling to the unpolarized quark transverse-momentum dependent parton distribution function (TMDPDF) operator within a background-field framework, extending the approach of Ref. [1]. We focus on ensuring gauge invariance, identifying two key components needed: a gauge-invariant TMDPDF operator with a transverse gauge link at spatial infinity, and accounting of the equations of motion (EoM) of the background fields. We go beyond next-to-leading order in strong coupling expansion, considering multiple interactions with the background field at all orders of strong coupling. By examining the interplay between quark and gluon contributions, we show that spurious singularities, proportional to EoM, can be misinterpreted as genuine divergences in QCD factorization unless properly identified and removed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15889v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swagato Mukherjee, Vladimir V. Skokov, Andrey Tarasov, Shaswat Tiwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuating Lattice, Several Energy Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In part I: We find a series physical scales such as 1) Planck scale, 2) Minimal approximate grand unification SU(5), 3) the mass scale of the see saw model right handed or Majorana neutrinoes, some invented scale with many scalar bosons, etc., and get the logarithms of these energy scales fitted by a quantity q related to the dimensions of to thescales related dimensionalities of coefficients in Lagrangian densities,or some generalization of this q to something similar in the variouscases of the scales. The logarithm of the energies behave as a straight line versus the dimension related number q. This is being explained by an ontologically existing lattice, which fluctuates in lattice canstant a from place to place in space time or more precisely, it fluctuates quantum mechanically. In Part II: We find a fitting of the three fine structure constantsin the Standard Model by means of a no-susy and SU(5)-like - but only accurately SU(5) symmetric in the classical approximation - by means of three other parameters for each of which, however, we have speculative predictions: Quantum corrections due to the lattice whichare three times as large as naive quantum corrections, because the lattice is supposed to lie in layers, one layer for each fermion-family; criticallity of the unified coupling, using the satnadrd model group S(U (2) x U (3)); the unification scale is fitted inot the scale-system of part I</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16369v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Bech Nielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non(anti)Commutative Superspace, Baker-Campbell-Hausdorff Closed Forms, and Dirac-K\"ahler Twisted Supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting from an elementary calculation of super Lie group elements associating with non(anti)-commutative Grassmann parameters, we derive several closed expressions of Baker-Campbell-Hausdorff (BCH) formula which represent multiplication properties of super Lie group elements in the corresponding superspace. We then show that parametrization of superspace in general may become infinite dimensional due to the presence of non(anti)commutativity. We show that a Dirac-K\"ahler Twisted SUSY Algebra (also referred to as Marcus B-type Twisted SUSY Algebra or Geometric Langlands Twisted SUSY Algebra) with a certain type of deformation, which we call an exponential deformation, may circumvent this problem. We also provide, in terms of gauge covariantization of the SUSY algebra, a geometric understanding of the exponential deformation, and see that the framework constructed in this paper may serve as a non(anti)commutative superspace framework providing the gauge covariant link formulation of twisted super Yang-Mills on a lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16410v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuhiro Nagata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical properties of proton using flavor-decomposed gravitational form factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the mechanical properties of the proton by extracting its flavor-decomposed gravitational form factors (GFFs) using Light-Cone QCD sum rules (LCSR). These form factors encode critical information about the internal dynamics and spatial distribution of energy, momentum, and internal forces within the proton. The flavor decomposition of the quark sector indicates the role of each flavor in the proton's pressure and shear force distributions. Our results show that the up quark contributes more significantly compared to the down quark in the three conserved proton GFFs, as well as in the energy and shear force distributions. Additionally, we define the non-conserved form factor $\bar{c}^q (t)$, which takes part in the distributions of energy and pressure; the latter is essential for maintaining proton stability. Furthermore, we determine the proton's mass and mechanical radii, providing valuable insight into its internal structure and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16689v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeinab Dehghan, F. Almaksusi, K. Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Z boson production in proton-lead collisions: A study utilizing MRW nuclear TMDs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the production of Z bosons in proton-lead collisions at a center of mass energy of $\sqrt{s} = 8.16$ TeV, utilizing various transverse momentum dependent parton distribution functions (TMDs), including the leading order Martin-Ryskin-Watt (LO-MRW), next-to-leading order MRW (NLO-MRW), and parton branching (PB) approaches. By comparing theoretical predictions with experimental data from the CMS collaboration, we assess the performance of these TMD models across different kinematic regions. Our analysis reveals that while both LO-MRW and NLO-MRW models generally align well with experimental data, the LO-MRW model tends to overestimate in certain kinematic regions. The NLO-MRW model, with its strong ordering constraint, provides better agreement in these areas. This study highlights the impact of different impositions of angular and strong ordering constraints in the LO-MRW and NLO-MRW approaches in describing Z boson production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16878v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Rezaie, K. Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet transport coefficient $\hat{q}$ in lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.14463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.14463v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the first calculation of the jet transport coefficient $\hat{q}$ in quenched and (2+1)-flavor QCD on a 4-D Euclidean lattice. The light-like propagation of an energetic parton is factorized from the mean square gain in momentum transverse to the direction of propagation, which is expressed in terms of the thermal field-strength field-strength correlator. The leading-twist term in its operator product expansion is calculated on the lattice. Continuum extrapolated quenched results, and full QCD estimates based on un-renormalized lattice data, over multiple lattice sizes, are compared with (non) perturbative calculations and phenomenological extractions of $\hat{q}$. The lattice data for $\hat{q}$ show a temperature dependence similar to the entropy density. Within uncertainties, these are consistent with phenomenological extractions, contrary to calculations using perturbation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.14463v4</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Kumar (Wayne State University,McGill University), Abhijit Majumder (Wayne State University), Johannes Heinrich Weber (Michigan State University,Humboldt University of Berlin)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Centre vortex evidence for a second finite-temperature QCD transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19446v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Evidence for the existence of a second finite-temperature transition in quantum chromodynamics (QCD) is obtained through the study of centre vortex geometry and its evolution with temperature. The dynamical anisotropic ensembles of the FASTSUM Collaboration are utilised to conduct a comprehensive analysis at eight temperatures beyond the established chiral transition. Visualisations of the centre vortex structure in temporal and spatial slices of the lattice reveal that vortex percolation persists through the chiral transition and ceases at a temperature that is approximately twice the chiral transition temperature $T_c$. This implies that confinement is retained through temperatures up to $T \approx 2\,T_c$, pointing toward a second transition corresponding to deconfinement. The loss of percolation is quantified by the vortex cluster extent, providing a clear signal for the deconfinement transition. Additional vortex statistics, including temporal correlations, vortex and branching point densities, the number of secondary clusters and vortex chain lengths between branching points, are scrutinised as a function of temperature. All ten measures investigated herein show the characteristics of two transitions in QCD, encompassing the chiral transition at $T_c$ and the deconfinement transition at $T \approx 2\,T_c$. Performing an inflection point analysis on the vortex and branching point densities produces an estimate of $T_c$ that agrees with the known FASTSUM value. By the same procedure, a precise estimate of the deconfinement point is extracted as $T_d = 321(6)\,$MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19446v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.034508</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 034508 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jackson A. Mickley, Chris Allton, Ryan Bignell, Derek B. Leinweber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward extracting scattering phase shift from integrated correlation functions III: coupled-channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00812v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formalism developed in Refs.\cite{Guo:2023ecc,Guo:2024zal} that connects integrated correlation function of a trapped two-particle system to infinite volume scattering phase shift is further extended to coupled-channel systems in the present work. Using a trapped non-relativistic two-channel system as an example, a new relation is derived that retains the same structure as in the single channel, and has explicit dependence on the phase shifts in both channels but not on the inelasticity. The relation is illustrated by an exactly solvable coupled-channel quantum mechanical model with contact interactions. It is further validated by path integral Monte Carlo simulation of a quasi-one-dimensional model that can admit general interaction potentials. In all cases, we found rapid convergence to the infinite volume limit as the trap size is increased, even at short times, making it potentially a good candidate to overcome signal-to-noise issues in Monte Carlo applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00812v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Guo, Frank X. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NRQCD Bottomonium at non-zero temperature using time-derivative moments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03951v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A well-known challenge for the lattice community is calculating the spectral function from the Euclidean correlator. We have approximated the spectral function and derived the mass and thermal width of particles through the time derivatives of the lattice correlator moments. We have focused on extracting the properties of bottomonium states, specifically $\Upsilon$ and $\chi_{b1}$. We will give an overview of the time-derivative moments approach and present results for the temperature dependence of the mass and width of both bottomonium states. The zero temperature results are consistent with experimental values, while results at higher temperatures are similar to those obtained using other methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03951v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Horohan D'arcy, Gert Aarts, Chris Allton, Ryan Bignell, Timothy Burns, Benjamin Jaeger, Seyong Kim, Maria Paola Lombardo, Sin\'ead Ryan, Antonio Smecca, Jon-Ivar Skullerud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qubit Regularization of Quantum Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05716v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To study quantum field theories on a quantum computer, we must begin with Hamiltonians defined on a finite-dimensional Hilbert space and then take appropriate limits. This approach can be seen as a new type of regularization for quantum field theories, which we refer to as qubit regularization. A related finite-dimensional regularization, known as the D-theory approach, was proposed long ago as a general framework for all quantum field theories. In this framework, the dimensionality of the local Hilbert space at each spatial point can increase as needed through an additional flavor index. To reproduce asymptotically free QFTs, most studies assume that qubit-regularized theories require extending the local Hilbert space to infinity. However, contrary to this common belief, recent discoveries in (1+1) dimensions have revealed two examples where asymptotic freedom appears to emerge within a strictly finite-dimensional local Hilbert space through a novel renormalization group (RG) flow. These findings motivate further investigation into whether asymptotically free gauge theories could also emerge within a strictly finite-dimensional local Hilbert space. To support these explorations, we propose an orthonormal basis called the monomer-dimer-tensor-network (MDTN) basis and use it to construct new types of qubit-regularized lattice gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05716v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shailesh Chandrasekharan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violation of non-Abelian Bianchi identity and QCD topology -- An Abelian mechanism without instantons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When Abelian monopoles due to violation of the non-Abelian Bianchi identity J{\mu}(x) condense in the vacuum, color confinement of QCD is realized by the Abelian dual Meissner effect. Recently VNABI affects also topological features of QCD drastically. Firstly, self-dual instantons can not be a classical solution of QCD. Secondly, the topological charge density is not expressed by a total derivative of the Chern-Simons density K{\mu}(x), but has an additional term L(x)=2Tr(J{\mu}(x)A{\mu}(x)). Thirdly, the axial U(1) anomaly is similarly modified, while keeping the Atiyah-Singer index theorem unchanged. These suggest that the Abelian mechanism based on the Abelian monopoles from VNABI play an important role in these topological quantities instead of instantons. The additional term L(x) is evaluated in the framework of Monte-Carlo simulations on SU(2) lattices in details with partial gauge fixings such as the Maximal Center gauge (MCG) and the Maximal Abelian +U(1) gauge (MAU1) in addition to the gradient flow. The additional term tends to vanish after small gradient flow time ({\tau}) when infrared monopoles responsible for color confinement are also suppressed. The topological charge Qt and its Abelian counterpart Qa are discussed also on lattice. Theoretically Qa(A)=3Qt(A) is expected, but a simple lattice definition of Qa(A) is fluctuating between -2 and -3 in MCG and around -2 in MAU1 in a typical configuration where Qt(A) is stabilized around -1 after the flow time {\tau} is larger than 2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13434v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsuneo Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate SU(5), Fine Structure Constants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14034v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We fit the three finestructure constants of the Standard Model with three, in first approximation theoretically estimable parameters, 1) a "unifiedscale",turning out not equal to the Planck scale and thus only estimable by a very speculative story, 2) a "number of layers" being a priori the number of families, and 3) a unified coupling related to a critical coupling on a lattice. So formally we postdict the three fine structure constants! In the philosophy of our model there is a physically lattice theory with link variables taking values in a (or in the various) "small" representations of the Standard Model Group. We argue for that these representations functio in first approximation as were the theory a genuine $SU(5)$ theory. Next we take into account fluctuation of the gauge fields in the lattice and obtain a correction to the a priori $SU(5)$ approximation, because of course the link fluctuations not corresponding any Standard model Lie algebra, but only to the SU(5), do not exist. The model is a development of our old anti-grand-unification model having as its genuine gauge group, close to fundamental scale, a cross product of the standard model group S(U(3)x U(2)) with itself, there being one Cartesian product factor for each family. In these old works we included the hypotesis of "multiple point criticallity principle" which here effectively means the coupling constants be critical on the lattice. Counted relative to the Higgs scale we suggest the in our sense "unified scale" (where the deviations between the inverse fine structure constants deviate by quantum fluctuations being only from standard model groups, not SU(5)) makes up the 2/3 th power of the Planck scale relative to the Higgs scale, or better the top quark mass scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14034v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Bech Nielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Real-Time Computation of Timelike Hadronic Vacuum Polarization and Light-by-Light Scattering: Schwinger Model Tests</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03536v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hadronic vacuum polarization (HVP) and light-by-light scattering (HLBL) are crucial for evaluating the Standard Model predictions concerning the muon's anomalous magnetic moment. However, direct first-principle lattice gauge theory-based calculations of these observables in the timelike region remain challenging. Discrepancies persist between lattice quantum chromodynamics (QCD) calculations in the spacelike region and dispersive approaches relying on experimental data parametrization from the timelike region. Here, we introduce a methodology employing 1+1-dimensional quantum electrodynamics (QED), i.e. the Schwinger Model, to investigate the HVP and HLBL. To that end, we use both tensor network techniques, specifically matrix product states, and classical emulators of digital quantum computers. Demonstrating feasibility in a simplified model, our approach sets the stage for future endeavors leveraging digital quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03536v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Barata, Kazuki Ikeda, Swagato Mukherjee, Jonathan Raghoonanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semileptonic $B \to D^*$ decays from light to $\tau$ leptons: the extraction of the form factor $F_2$ from data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17974v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend the Standard Model (SM) analysis of Ref. [1], which was limited to light leptons in the final state, to the semileptonic $B \to D^* \tau \nu_\tau$ decay. By using quantities that can be analised without the knowledge of $\vert V_{cb}\vert$, we derive important information about the helicity amplitudes and the hadronic form factors that can be compared with the predictions of lattice QCD calculations. In particular, there is a difficulty in reproducing simultaneously the experimental values of $R(D^*)$ and of other quantities relevant for the semitauonic decays within the SM. As a byproduct of our analysis, we also present a determination of $\vert V_{cb}\vert$ from the total decay rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17974v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Martinelli, S. Simula, L. Vittorio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decays of the light hybrid meson $1^{\mathrm{-+}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11331v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The full width of the light isovector hybrid meson $H_{\mathrm{V}}$ with spin-parities $1^{\mathrm{-+}}$ and content $(\overline{u}gu-\overline{d}gd)/ \sqrt{2}$ is evaluated by considering the decays $H_{\mathrm{V}} \to \rho^{\pm}\pi^{\mp}$, $b_1^{\pm}\pi^{\mp}$, $f_1(1285)\pi$, $f_1(1420)\pi$, $ \eta \pi$, and $\eta^{\prime} \pi$. To calculate the partial widths of these channels, we use QCD three-point sum rule method which is necessary to determine strong couplings at the corresponding hybrid-meson-meson vertices. It turns out that the main contribution to the full width $\Gamma[H_{\mathrm{ V}}]=(109.7 \pm 16.0)~\mathrm{MeV}$ of the hybrid meson comes from the processes $H_{\mathrm{V}} \to \rho^{\pm}\pi^{\mp}$ partial width of which amounts to $\approx 67~\mathrm{MeV}$. The effects of the decays $H_{\mathrm{V }} \to b_1\pi $ and $H_{\mathrm{V}} \to f_1\pi, f_1^{\prime} \pi$ are also sizeable: Their partial widths are equal to $13~\mathrm{MeV}$ and $20~ \mathrm{MeV}$, respectively. The decays to $\eta \pi$ and $\eta^{\prime} \pi$ mesons are subdominant reactions, nevertheless they form $\approx 9\%$ of the full width $\Gamma[H_{\mathrm{V}}]$. Results obtained in this work may be interesting to unravel the tangle of predictions about $H_{\mathrm{V}}$ existing in the literature, as well as useful in analyses of different resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11331v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Daylan Esmer, K. Azizi, H. Sundu, S. T\"urkmen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Packaged Quantum States for Quantum Simulation of Lattice Gauge Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14654v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a mathematical framework for the quantum simulation of lattice gauge theories using gauge-invariant packaged quantum states \cite{Ma2017,Ma2025}. In this formalism, every single excitation transforms as a complete \textbf{irreducible representation (irrep)} of the local gauge group, preventing any appearance of fractional or partial \textbf{internal quantum numbers (IQNs)}. Multi-particle excitations can form nontrivial packaged entangled states that are also gauge invariant, thereby forbidding partial or fractional IQNs. In other words, all IQNs of such packaged entangled states remain inseparably entangled. This ``packaging principle'' ensures that physical states remain confined to the correct gauge sector and excludes partial charges or colors, even when multiple excitations are entangled.
  We illustrate this approach for $\mathrm{U}(1)$, $\mathrm{SU}(2)$, and $\mathrm{SU}(3)$ lattice gauge theories, discussing explicit constructions, Trotterized Hamiltonian evolution, and gauge-invariant measurements on a quantum simulator. We also outline how packaged states can mitigate gauge-violating errors and serve as natural building blocks for gauge-invariant coding schemes, while noting that standard quantum error correction is still required against typical local noise that respects gauge symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14654v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongchao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
