<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-lat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat</link>
    <description>hep-lat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-Precision Scale Setting with the Omega-Baryon Mass and Gradient Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The gradient-flow scale $w_0$ in lattice QCD is determined using the mass of the $\Omega^-$ baryon to set the physical scale. Nine ensembles using the highly improved staggered quark (HISQ) action with lattice spacings of 0.15 fm down to 0.04 fm are used, seven of which have nearly physical light-quark masses. Electromagnetic corrections to the $\Omega^-$ mass are defined in order to compute a pure-QCD $\Omega$ mass. The final result is $w_0 = 0.17187(68)$ fm, corresponding to a relative uncertainty of 0.40% and a central value in good agreement with previous calculations in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14367v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexei Bazavov, Claude W. Bernard, David A. Clarke, Carleton DeTar, Aida X. El-Khadra, Elvira G\'amiz, Steven Gottlieb, Anthony V. Grebe, Urs M. Heller, Leon Hostetler, William I. Jay, Hwancheol Jeong, Andreas S. Kronfeld, Yin Lin, Shaun Lahert, Jack Laiho, Michael Lynch, Andrew T. Lytle, Aaron S. Meyer, Ethan T. Neil, Curtis T. Peterson, James N. Simone, Jacob W. Sitison, Ruth S. Van de Water, Alejandro Vaquero, Michael L. Wagman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate bootstrap bounds from optimal interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14307v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop new methods for approximating conformal blocks as positive functions times polynomials, with applications to the numerical bootstrap. We argue that to obtain accurate bootstrap bounds, conformal block approximations should minimize a certain error norm related to the asymptotics of dispersive functionals. This error norm can be made small using interpolation nodes with an appropriate optimal density. The optimal density turns out to satisfy a kind of force-balance equation for charges in one dimension, which can be solved using standard techniques from large-N matrix models. We also describe how to use optimal density interpolation nodes to improve condition numbers inside the semidefinite program solver SDPB. Altogether, our new approximation scheme and improvements to condition numbers lead to more accurate bootstrap bounds with fewer computational resources. They were crucial in the recent bootstrap study of stress tensors in the 3d Ising CFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14307v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyuan-Han Chang, Vasiliy Dommes, Petr Kravchuk, David Poland, David Simmons-Duffin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase structure of self-dual lattice gauge theories in 4d</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.14774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.14774v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss U(1) lattice gauge theory models based on a modified Villain formulation of the gauge action, which allows coupling to bosonic electric and magnetic matter. The formulation enjoys a duality which maps electric and magnetic sectors into each other. We propose several generalizations of the model and discuss their 't~Hooft anomalies. A particularly interesting class of theories is the one where electric and magnetic matter fields are coupled with identical actions, such that for a particular value of the gauge coupling the theory has a self-dual symmetry. The self-dual symmetry turns out to be a generator of a group which is a central extension of $\mathbb Z_4$ by the lattice translation symmetry group. The simplest case amenable to numerical simulations is the case when there is exactly one electrically and one magnetically charged boson. We discuss the phase structure of this theory and the nature of the self-dual symmetry in detail. Using a suitable worldline representation of the system we present the results of numerical simulations that support the conjectured phase diagram.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.14774v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP06(2022)149</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mariia Anosova, Christof Gattringer, Nabil Iqbal, Tin Sulejmanpasic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing Universal Thermalization Dynamics in a (2+1)D Lattice Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00069v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulating non-equilibrium phenomena in strongly-interacting quantum many-body systems, including thermalization, is a promising application of near-term and future quantum computation. By performing experiments on a digital quantum computer consisting of fully-connected optically-controlled trapped ions, we study the role of entanglement in the thermalization dynamics of a $Z_2$ lattice gauge theory in 2+1 spacetime dimensions. Using randomized-measurement protocols, we efficiently learn a classical approximation of non-equilibrium states that yields the gap-ratio distribution and the spectral form factor of the entanglement Hamiltonian. These observables exhibit universal early-time signals for quantum chaos, a prerequisite for thermalization. Our work, therefore, establishes quantum computers as robust tools for studying universal features of thermalization in complex many-body systems, including in gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00069v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-60177-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 5492 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Mueller, Tianyi Wang, Or Katz, Zohreh Davoudi, Marko Cetina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing the Page Curve and Entanglement Dynamics of Black Holes in Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15180v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum computers are emerging technologies expected to become important tools for exploring various aspects of fundamental physics in the future. Therefore, we pose the question of whether quantum computers can help us to study the Page curve and the black hole information dynamics, which has been a key focus in fundamental physics. In this regard, we rigorously examine the qubit transport model, a toy qubit model of black hole evaporation on IBM's superconducting quantum computers, to shed light on this question. Specifically, we implement the quantum simulation of the scrambling dynamics in black holes using an efficient random unitary circuit. Furthermore, we employ the swap-based many-body interference protocol and the randomized measurement protocol to measure the entanglement entropy of Hawking radiation qubits in this model. Finally, by incorporating quantum error mitigation techniques into our challenging implementation of entanglement entropy measurement protocols on the IBM quantum hardware, we accurately determine the R\'enyi entropy in the qubit transport model, thus showcasing the utility of quantum computers for future investigations of complex quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15180v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.117112</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Talal Ahmed Chowdhury, Kwangmin Yu, Muhammad Asaduzzaman, Raza Sabbir Sufian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review on recent progress in the study of the $N^*(920)$ subthreshold singularity and the $\sigma/f_0(500)$ meson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24674v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We summarize recent results on studies of $\pi\pi$ and $\pi N$ scatterings. They include the finding of a negative-parity nucleon pole with a mass lower than the nucleon mass, and the pole trajectory of $f_0(500)$ as the pion mass varies. The results are obtained from model-independent dispersion analyses. We also study the thermal properties of $f_0(500)$ based on the $O(N)$ $\sigma$ model and $N/D$ method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24674v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qu-Zhi Li, Zhiguang Xiao, Han-Qing Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric analysis of Ising models, Part III</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02850v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The random current representation of the Ising model, along with a related path expansion, has been a source of insight on the stochastic geometric underpinning of the ferromagnetic model's phase structure and critical behavior in different dimensions. This representation is extended here to systems with a mild amount of frustration, such as generated by disorder operators and external field of mixed signs. Further examples of the utility of such stochastic geometric representations are presented in the context of the deconfinement transition of the $Z_2$ lattice gauge model -- particularly in three dimensions-- and in streamlined proofs of correlation inequalities with wide-ranging applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02850v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Aizenman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-theoretic versus data-driven evaluations of electromagnetic corrections to hadronic vacuum polarization in $(g-2)_\mu$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Standard Model prediction of the muon $g-2$ increasingly depends on lattice QCD computations of the hadronic vacuum polarization (HVP), where the isospin-breaking (IB) effects remain a significant source of uncertainty. To complement the lattice QCD evaluations, the data-driven approach to HVP has been used to assess some of the electromagnetic IB effects, in particular from the channels with a photon in the final state, e.g., $e^+e^-\to\pi^0 \gamma$. Here we argue that such contributions are largely canceled by virtual electromagnetic corrections to the purely hadronic channels: $\pi^+ \pi^-$, $\pi^+ \pi^- \pi^0$, etc. We identify these leading corrections by performing a field-theoretical calculation in a vector-meson dominance model, thereby reconciling the timelike and spacelike approaches to electromagnetic effects. Although these virtual corrections are more difficult to extract in a systematic manner, addressing them is essential for the data-driven method to consistently complement the lattice QCD program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08115v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volodymyr Biloshytskyi, Dominik Erb, Harvey B. Meyer, Julian Parrino, Vladimir Pascalutsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
