<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-lat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat</link>
    <description>hep-lat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 03:27:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Shear viscosity from quenched to full lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The shear viscosity of the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) plays a crucial role in interpreting current measurements from heavy-ion collisions and is a key input to hydro-dynamical models. The interest in shear viscosity also lies in the fact that QGP is the most ideal fluid ever observed and has the shear viscosity to entropy ratio ($\eta / s$) close to the theoretical bound $\eta / s \geq 1/ 4 \pi$ in the strong coupling region within AdS/CFT formalism. The lattice determination of $\eta / s$ has been explored for the pure gauge case, but its determination in full QCD remains unexplored, despite its significant importance. In this proceeding, we present updates on extending our quenched findings to full QCD. Specifically, we focus on the renormalization of the energy-momentum tensor with the gradient flow method and provide a progress update on determining the relevant renormalization coefficients for shear viscosity. For this purpose, we have used an imaginary isospin chemical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11395v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Pavan, Olaf Kaczmarek, Guy D. Moore, Christian Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\pi^0\to \gamma^\ast \gamma^\ast$ transition form factor and the pion pole contribution to $a_{\mu}$ on CLS ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the status of the Mainz group's lattice QCD calculation of the pion transition form factor $\mathcal{F}_{\pi^0\gamma^\ast\gamma^\ast}$, which describes the interaction of an on-shell pion with two off-shell photons. This form factor is the main ingredient in the calculation of the pion-pole contribution to hadronic light-by-light scattering in the muon $g-2$.
  We use the $N_f = 2 + 1$ CLS gauge ensembles, and we update our previous work by including a physical pion mass ensemble (E250). We compute the transition form factor in the pion rest frame as well as in a moving frame in order to have access to a wider range of photon virtualities. In addition to the quark-line connected correlator we also compute the quark-line disconnected diagrams that contribute to the form factor.
  In this final stage of the analysis, we combine the result on E250 with the previous work published in 2019 to extrapolate the form factor to the continuum and to physical quark masses. Testing different ans\"atze for the fit, we explore the systematic uncertainties of the extrapolation. The contribution from the disconnected diagrams is also scrutinized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11428v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonna Koponen, Antoine Gerardin, Harvey B. Meyer, Konstantin Ottnad, Georg von Hippel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching Lagrangian and Hamiltonian Simulations in (2+1)-dimensional U(1) Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At finite lattice spacing, Lagrangian and Hamiltonian predictions differ due to discretization effects. In the Hamiltonian limit, i.e. at vanishing temporal lattice spacing $a_t$, the path integral approach in the Lagrangian formalism reproduces the results of the Hamiltonian theory. In this work, we numerically calculate the Hamiltonian limit of a U$(1)$ gauge theory in $(2+1)$ dimensions. This is achieved by Monte Carlo simulations in the Lagrangian formalism with lattices that are anisotropic in the time direction. For each ensemble, we determine the ratio between the temporal and spatial scale with the static quark potential and extrapolate to $a_t \to 0$. Our results are compared with the data from Hamiltonian simulations at small volumes, showing agreement within $&lt;2\sigma$. These results can be used to match the two formalisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11480v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. F. Gro{\ss}, S. Romiti, L. Funcke, K. Jansen, A. Kan, S. K\"uhn, C. Urbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeuMC -- a package for neural sampling for lattice field theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the \texttt{NeuMC} software package, based on \pytorch, aimed at facilitating the research on neural samplers in lattice field theories. Neural samplers based on normalizing flows are becoming increasingly popular in the context of Monte-Carlo simulations as they can effectively approximate target probability distributions, possibly alleviating some shortcomings of the Markov chain Monte-Carlo methods. Our package provides tools to create such samplers for two-dimensional field theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11482v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Bialas, Piotr Korcyl, Tomasz Stebel, Dawid Zapolski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational form factors in the perturbative limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The generalized distribution amplitudes (GDAs) have been paid attention in recent years because of their relation with the energy momentum tensor (EMT) form factors (FFs). The GDAs can be experimentally accessed through the study of amplitudes in $\gamma^{\ast} \gamma \to M_1 M_2$ and $\gamma^{\ast} \to M_1 M_2 \gamma$, where $M_1M_2$ is a pseudoscalar meson pair such as $\pi \eta $ and $\eta \eta^{\prime}$. In this paper we calculate these amplitudes in the perturbative limit where the $M_1M_2$ GDAs are expressed in terms of meson distribution amplitudes which have been constrained in the past experiments. Our explicit calculation verifies the existence of a new EMT FF which breaks the conservation law of EMT for each quark flavor in its hadronic matrix element. In addition, our result shows that the $M_1M_2$ GDAs are identical between $\gamma^{\ast} \gamma \to M_1 M_2$ and $\gamma^{\ast} \to M_1 M_2 \gamma$, which confirms the universality of GDAs. In future, the GDAs and EMT FFs studied in this paper can be investigated at Belle II. Our study enhances the accessibility to the $P$-wave GDAs in $\gamma^{\ast} \gamma \to M_1 M_2$ and $\gamma^{\ast} \to M_1 M_2 \gamma$ and gives a promising way to search for exotic hybrid mesons in the future experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11316v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qin-Tao Song, O. V. Teryaev, Shinsuke Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative quantum Yang--Mills at finite temperature beyond lattice: a Dyson--Schwinger approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15258v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using a Dyson--Schwinger approach, we perform an analysis of the non-trivial ground state of thermal $SU(N)$ Yang--Mills theory in the non-perturbative regime where chiral symmetry is spontaneously broken. Basic thermodynamic observables such as energy density and pressure are derived analytically, using Jacobi Elliptic functions. The results are compared with lattice results. Good agreement is found at low temperatures, providing a viable scenario of a gas of massive glue states populating higher levels of the spectrum of the theory. At high temperatures a scenario without glue states consistent with a massive scalar field is observed, showing an interesting agreement with lattice data. The possibility is discussed that the results derived in this analysis open up a novel pathway beyond lattice to precision studies of phase transitions with false vacuum and cosmological relics that depend on QCD-like equations of state in strongly coupled gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15258v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Frasca, Anish Ghoshal, Stefan Groote</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
