<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-lat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat</link>
    <description>hep-lat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-lat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 02:42:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Center vortices in the novel phase of staggered fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The geometry of center vortices is studied in the novel lattice-artefact phase that appears with staggered fermions to elucidate any insight provided by the center-vortex degrees of freedom. For various numbers of fermion flavors, the single-site shift symmetry of the staggered-fermion action is broken in a finite region of the $(\beta, m)$ phase space. Simulations are performed with six degenerate fermion flavors and a range of $\beta$ values that span the phase boundary. Center vortices are demonstrated to capture the broken shift symmetry that manifests in the unphysical phase. This persists at the level of each individual plaquette orientation, where it is revealed only the plaquettes that span the broken dimension are affected. Several bulk center-vortex quantities, including the vortex and branching point densities, are considered to highlight other aspects of vortex geometry sensitive to the unphysical phase. A slight preference for the plaquettes affected by the broken shift symmetry to be pierced by a vortex is observed. This translates also to a greater branching point density in three-dimensional slices that span the broken dimension. Combined, these findings provide a novel characterization of the unphysical phase in terms of the fundamental center degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05807v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson A. Mickley, Derek B. Leinweber, Daniel Nogradi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SESaMo: Symmetry-Enforcing Stochastic Modulation for Normalizing Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19619v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep generative models have recently garnered significant attention across various fields, from physics to chemistry, where sampling from unnormalized Boltzmann-like distributions represents a fundamental challenge. In particular, autoregressive models and normalizing flows have become prominent due to their appealing ability to yield closed-form probability densities. Moreover, it is well-established that incorporating prior knowledge - such as symmetries - into deep neural networks can substantially improve training performances. In this context, recent advances have focused on developing symmetry-equivariant generative models, achieving remarkable results. Building upon these foundations, this paper introduces Symmetry-Enforcing Stochastic Modulation (SESaMo). Similar to equivariant normalizing flows, SESaMo enables the incorporation of inductive biases (e.g., symmetries) into normalizing flows through a novel technique called stochastic modulation. This approach enhances the flexibility of the generative model, allowing to effectively learn a variety of exact and broken symmetries. Our numerical experiments benchmark SESaMo in different scenarios, including an 8-Gaussian mixture model and physically relevant field theories, such as the $\phi^4$ theory and the Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19619v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janik Kreit, Dominic Schuh, Kim A. Nicoli, Lena Funcke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pathfinding Quantum Simulations of Neutrinoless Double-$\beta$ Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present results from co-designed quantum simulations of the neutrinoless double-$\beta$ decay of a simple nucleus in 1+1D quantum chromodynamics using IonQ's Forte-generation trapped-ion quantum computers. Electrons, neutrinos, and up and down quarks are distributed across two lattice sites and mapped to 32 qubits, with an additional 4 qubits used for flag-based error mitigation. A four-fermion interaction is used to implement weak interactions, and lepton-number violation is induced by a neutrino Majorana mass. Quantum circuits that prepare the initial nucleus and time evolve with the Hamiltonian containing the strong and weak interactions are executed on IonQ Forte Enterprise. A clear signal of neutrinoless double-$\beta$ decay is measured, making this the first quantum simulation to observe lepton-number violation in real time. This was made possible by co-designing the simulation to maximally utilize the all-to-all connectivity and native gate-set available on IonQ's quantum computers. Quantum circuit compilation techniques and co-designed error-mitigation methods, informed from executing benchmarking circuits with up to 2,356 two-qubit gates, enabled observables to be extracted with high precision. We discuss the potential of future quantum simulations to provide yocto-second resolution of the reaction pathways in these, and other, nuclear processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05757v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan A. Chernyshev, Roland C. Farrell, Marc Illa, Martin J. Savage, Andrii Maksymov, Felix Tripier, Miguel Angel Lopez-Ruiz, Andrew Arrasmith, Yvette de Sereville, Aharon Brodutch, Claudio Girotto, Ananth Kaushik, Martin Roetteler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD Equation of State with $N_f=3$ Flavors up to the Electroweak Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The equation of state of Quantum Chromodynamics with $N_f=3$ flavors is determined non-perturbatively in the range of temperatures between $3$ and $165$~GeV with a precision of about $0.5$-$1.0$\%. The calculation is carried out by numerical simulations of lattice gauge theory discretized \`a la Wilson with shifted boundary conditions in the compact direction. At each given temperature the entropy density is computed at several lattice spacings in order to extrapolate the results to the continuum limit. Taken at face value, data point straight to the Stefan-Boltzmann value by following a linear behavior in the strong coupling constant squared. They are also compatible with the known perturbative formula supplemented by higher order terms in the coupling constant, a parametrization which describes well our data together with those present in the literature down to $500$ MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11603v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Bresciani (Milan Bicocca U.,INFN, Milan Bicocca), Mattia Dalla Brida (Milan Bicocca U.,INFN, Milan Bicocca), Leonardo Giusti (Milan Bicocca U.,INFN, Milan Bicocca), Michele Pepe (INFN, Milan Bicocca)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
