<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Splitting Hypergeometric Functions over Roots of Unity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine hypergeometric functions in the finite field, p-adic and classical settings. In each setting, we prove a formula which splits the hypergeometric function into a sum of lower order functions whose arguments differ by roots of unity. We provide multiple applications of these results, including new reduction and summation formulas for finite field hypergeometric functions, along with classical analogues; evaluations of special values of these functions which apply in both the finite field and p-adic settings; and new relations to Fourier coefficients of modular forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17678v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dermot McCarthy, Mohit Tripathi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier Coefficients and Algebraic Cusp Forms on $\mathrm{U}(2,n)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a theory of scalar Fourier coefficients for a class of non-holomorphic, automorphic forms on the quaternionic real Lie group $\mathrm{U}(2,n)$. By studying the theta lifts of holomorphic modular forms from $\mathrm{U}(1,1)$, we apply this theory to obtain examples of non-holomorphic cusp forms on $\mathrm{U}(2,n)$ whose Fourier coefficients are algebraic numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17743v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Hilado, Finn McGlade, Pan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monogenic Cyclic Quartic Trinomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A monic polynomial $f(x)\in {\mathbb Z}[x]$ of degree $N$ is called monogenic if $f(x)$ is irreducible over ${\mathbb Q}$ and $\{1,\theta,\theta^2,\ldots ,\theta^{N-1}\}$ is a basis for the ring of integers of ${\mathbb Q}(\theta)$, where $f(\theta)=0$. In this brief note, we prove that there exist exactly three distinct monogenic trinomials of the form $x^4+bx^2+d$ whose Galois group is the cyclic group of order 4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17869v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lenny Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monogenic Even Octic Polynomials and Their Galois Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A monic polynomial $f(x)\in {\mathbb Z}[x]$ of degree $N$ is called monogenic if $f(x)$ is irreducible over ${\mathbb Q}$ and $\{1,\theta,\theta^2,\ldots ,\theta^{N-1}\}$ is a basis for the ring of integers of ${\mathbb Q}(\theta)$, where $f(\theta)=0$. In a series of recent articles, a complete classification of the Galois groups was given for irreducible polynomials \[{\mathcal F}(x):=x^8+ax^4+b\in {\mathbb Q}[x],\] while a partial classification was given for irreducible polynomials \[{\mathcal G}(x):=x^8+ax^6+bx^4+ax^2+1\in {\mathbb Q}[x], \quad a\ne 0.\] In this article, for each Galois group $G$ arising in these classifications, we either construct an infinite family of octic monogenic polynomials ${\mathcal F}(x)$ or ${\mathcal G}(x)$ having Galois group $G$, or we prove that only a finite such family exists, or we prove that no such octic monogenic polynomial exists. Here, a ``family" means that no two polynomials in the family generate the same octic field.
  We also provide a minor contribution to the existing partial classification of the Galois groups of ${\mathcal G}(x)$ by giving simple conditions on the coefficients $a$ and $b$ to determine when ${\mathcal G}(x)$ is monogenic and the Galois group of ${\mathcal G}(x)$ is $C_2\times D_4$ versus $C_2^2\wr C_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17921v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lenny Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relations of multiple $\tilde{T}$-values involving the total numbers of certain permutations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kaneko and Tsumura proved a relation of multiple $\tilde{T}$-values involving Entringer numbers counting the total number of down-up permutations starting with a fixed value. In the present paper, we generalize this relation and provide some relations involving Entringer numbers and the total number of Dumont permutations of the first kind starting with a fixed value. For this purpose, we also provide explicit formulas for the total numbers of those permutations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18281v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Umezawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a conjecture of Levesque and Waldschmidt II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Related to Shank's notion of simplest cubic fields, the family of parametrised Diophantine equations,
  \[
x^3 - (n-1) x^2 y - (n+2) xy^2 - 1 = \left( x - \lambda_0 y\right) \left(x-\lambda_1 y\right) \left(x - \lambda_2 y\right) = \pm 1,
  \]
was studied and solved effectively by Thomas and later solved completely by Mignotte.
  An open conjecture of Levesque and Waldschmidt states that taking these parametrised Diophantine equations and twisting them not only once but twice, in the sense that we look at
  \[
f_{n,s,t}(x,y) = \left( x - \lambda_0^s \lambda_1^t y \right) \left( x - \lambda_1^s\lambda_2^t y \right) \left( x - \lambda_2^s\lambda_0^t y \right) = \pm 1,
  \]
retains a result similar to what Thomas obtained in the original or Levesque and Waldschidt in the once-twisted ($t = 0$) case; namely, that non-trivial solutions can only appear in equations where the parameters are small. We confirm this conjecture, given that the absolute values of the exponents $s, t$ are not too large compared to the base parameter $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18642v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Hilgart, Volker Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Beurling-Malliavin density, the Polya density and their connection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we present a new formulation of the Beurling-Malliavin density (Proposition 1). Then we consider the upper Polya density and show how its existence is connected with the concept of subadditivity; moreover, by means of some quantities introduced for proving Proposition 1, a theorem is presented that clarifies the connection between the upper Polya and the Beurling-Malliavin densities. In the last section we discuss the classical definition of the upper Polya density and we prove a result which seems to be new.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18711v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rita Giuliano, Georges Grekos, Ladislav Misik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary forms with the same value set III. The case of ${\bf D}_3$ and ${\bf D_6}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $F, G \in \mathbb{Z}[X, Y]$ be binary forms of degree $\geq 3$ with automorphism groups isomorphic to the dihedral group of cardinality $6$ or $12$. We characterize exactly when $F$ and $G$ have the same value set, i.e. $F(\mathbb{Z}^2) = G(\mathbb{Z}^2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18725v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Etienne Fouvry, Peter Koymans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuity of the continued fraction mapping revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The continued fraction mapping maps a number in the interval $[0,1)$ to the sequence of its partial quotients. When restricted to the set of irrationals, which is a subspace of the Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}$, the continued fraction mapping is a homeomorphism onto the product space $\mathbb{N}^{\mathbb{N}}$, where $\mathbb{N}$ is a discrete space. In this short note, we examine the continuity of the continued fraction mapping, addressing both irrational and rational points of the unit interval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18853v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Woong Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional sets to Shallit's law of leap years in Pierce expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In his 1994 work, Shallit introduced a rule for determining leap years that generalizes both the historically used Julian calendar and the contemporary Gregorian calendar. This rule depends on a so-called intercalation sequence. According to what we term Shallit's law of leap years, almost every point of the interval $[0,1]$ with respect to Lebesgue measure has the same limsup and liminf, respectively, of a quotient defined in terms of the number of leap years determined by the rule using the Pierce expansion digit sequence as an intercalation sequence. In this paper, we show that the set of exceptions to this law is dense and has full Hausdorff dimension in $[0,1]$, and that the exceptional set intersected with any non-empty open subset of $[0,1]$ has full Hausdorff dimension in $[0,1]$. As a more general result, we establish that for certain subsets of $[0,1]$ concerning the limiting behavior of Pierce expansion digits, intersecting with a non-empty open subset of $[0,1]$ preserves the Hausdorff dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18855v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Woong Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Nygaard Approach to Values of Zeta Functions of Schemes over Finite Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we discuss a streamlined proof of a result due to Milne computing special values of zeta functions for smooth proper schemes over a finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$. The proof will give a natural interpretation of the correction factor in terms of invariants constructed from prismatic cohomology, studied by Morin. We then discuss the modifications needed when passing from the smooth case to an arbitrary qcqs scheme $X$ of finite type over $\mathbb{F}_q$, at least assuming a strong form of resolution of singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18367v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Logan Hyslop</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weierstrass semigroups and automorphism group of a maximal function field with the third largest possible genus, $q \equiv 1 \pmod 3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we continue the work started in arXiv:2303.00376v1, explicitly determining the Weierstrass semigroup at any place and the full automorphism group of a known $\mathbb{F}_{q^2}$-maximal function field $Y_3$ having the third largest genus, for $q \equiv 1 \pmod 3$. This function field arises as a Galois subfield of the Hermitian function field, and its uniqueness (with respect to the value of its genus) is a well-known open problem. Knowing the Weierstrass semigroups may provide a key towards solving this problem. Surprisingly enough, $Y_3$ has many different types of Weierstrass semigroups and the set of its Weierstrass places is much richer than its set of $\mathbb{F}_{q^2}$-rational places. We show that a similar exceptional behaviour does not occur in terms of automorphisms, that is, $\mathrm{Aut}(Y_3)$ is exactly the automorphism group inherited from the Hermitian function field, apart from small values of $q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18808v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Beelen, Maria Montanucci, Lara Vicino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uncommonness of minimal rank-2 systems of linear equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that suitably generic pairs of linear equations on an even number of variables are uncommon. This verifies a conjecture of Kam\v{c}ev, Morrison and the second author. Moreover, we prove that any large system containing such a $(2\times k)$-system as a minimal subsystem is uncommon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18908v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Altman, Anita Liebenau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic multiple zeta values, Grothendieck-Teichm\"uller and mould theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1506.09050</link>
      <description>arXiv:1506.09050v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we define an elliptic double shuffle Lie algebra $ds_{ell}$ that generalizes the well-known double shuffle Lie algebra $ds$ to the elliptic situation. The double shuffle, or dimorphic, relations satisfied by elements of the Lie algebra $ds$ express two families of algebraic relations between multiple zeta values that conjecturally generate all relations. In analogy with this, elements of the elliptic double shuffle Lie algebra $ds_{ell}$ are Lie polynomials having a dimorphic property called $\Delta$-bialternality that conjecturally describes the (dual of the) set of algebraic relations between elliptic multiple zeta values, periods of objects of the category $MEM$ of mixed elliptic motives defined by Hain and Matsumoto. We show that one of Ecalle's major results in mould theory can be reinterpreted as yielding the existence of an injective Lie algebra morphism $ds\rightarrow ds_{ell}$. Our main result is the compatibility of this map with the tangential-base-point section ${\rm Lie}\,\pi_1(MTM)\rightarrow {\rm Lie}\,\pi_1(MEM)$ constructed by Hain and Matsumoto and with the section $grt\rightarrow grt_{ell}$ mapping the Grothendieck-Teichm\"uller Lie algebra $grt$ into the elliptic Grothendieck-Teichm\"uller Lie algebra $grt_{ell}$ constructed by Enriquez.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1506.09050v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leila Schneps</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative arithmetic functions and the generalized Ewens measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.00601</link>
      <description>arXiv:1909.00601v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Random integers, sampled uniformly from $[1,x]$, share similarities with random permutations, sampled uniformly from $S_n$. These similarities include the Erd\H{o}s--Kac theorem on the distribution of the number of prime factors of a random integer, and Billingsley's theorem on the largest prime factors of a random integer. In this paper we extend this analogy to non-uniform distributions.
  Given a multiplicative function $\alpha \colon \mathbb{N} \to \mathbb{R}_{\ge 0}$, one may associate with it a measure on the integers in $[1,x]$, where $n$ is sampled with probability proportional to the value $\alpha(n)$. Analogously, given a sequence $\{ \theta_i\}_{i \ge 1}$ of non-negative reals, one may associate with it a measure on $S_n$ that assigns to a permutation a probability proportional to a product of weights over the cycles of the permutation. This measure is known as the generalized Ewens measure.
  We study the case where the mean value of $\alpha$ over primes tends to some positive $\theta$, as well as the weights $\alpha(p) \approx (\log p)^{\gamma}$. In both cases, we obtain results in the integer setting which are in agreement with those in the permutation setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1909.00601v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11856-024-2609-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dor Elboim, Ofir Gorodetsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential transcendence of Bell numbers and relatives: a Galois theoretic approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.15292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.15292v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 2003 Klazar proved that the ordinary generating function of the sequence of Bell numbers is differentially transcendental over the field $\mathbb{C}(\{t\})$ of meromorphic functions at $0$. We show that Klazar's result is an instance of a general phenomenon that can be proven in a compact way using difference Galois theory. We present the main principles of this theory in order to prove a general result about differential transcendence over $\mathbb{C}(\{t\})$, that we apply to many other (infinite classes of) examples of generating functions, including as very special cases the ones considered by Klazar. Most of our examples belong to Sheffer's class, well studied notably in umbral calculus. They all bring concrete evidence in support to the Pak-Yeliussizov conjecture, according to which a sequence whose both ordinary and exponential generating functions satisfy nonlinear differential equations with polynomial coefficients necessarily satisfies a linear recurrence with polynomial coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.15292v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alin Bostan, Lucia Di Vizio, Kilian Raschel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering the Picard group of quadratic algebras from Wood's binary quadratic forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.13422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.13422v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $S$ be a scheme such that $2$ is not a zero divisor. In this paper, we address the following question: given a quadratic algebra over $S$, how can we parametrize its Picard group in terms of quadratic forms? In 2011, Wood established a set-theoretical bijection between isomorphism classes of primary binary quadratic forms over $S$ and isomorphism classes of pairs $(\mathcal{C},\mathcal{M})$ where $\mathcal{C}$ is a quadratic algebra over $S$ and $\mathcal{M}$ is an invertible $\mathcal{C}$-module. Unexpectedly, examples suggest that a refinement of Wood's bijection is needed in order to parametrize Picard groups. This is why we start by classifying quadratic algebras over $S$; this is achieved by using two invariants, the discriminant and the parity. Extending the notion of orientation of quadratic algebras to the non-free case is another key step, eventually leading us to the desired parametrization. All along the paper, we illustrate various notions and obstructions with a wide range of examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.13422v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Dallaporta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic forms and Genus Theory : a link with 2-descent and an application to non-trivial specializations of ideal classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.13045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.13045v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Genus Theory is a classical feature of integral binary quadratic forms. Using the author's generalization of the well-known correspondence between quadratic form classes and ideal classes of quadratic algebras, we extend it to the case when quadratic forms are twisted and have coefficients in any PID $R$. When ${R = \mathbb{K}[X]}$, we show that the Genus Theory map is the quadratic form version of the $2$-descent map on a certain hyperelliptic curve. As an application, we make a contribution to a question of Agboola and Pappas regarding a specialization problem of divisor classes on hyperelliptic curves. Under suitable assumptions, we prove that the set of non-trivial specializations has density $1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.13045v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Dallaporta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summing the sum of digits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit and generalize inequalities for the summatory function of the sum of digits in a given integer base. We prove that several known results can be deduced from a theorem in a 2023 paper by Mohanty, Greenbury, Sarkany, Narayanan, Dingle, Ahnert, and Louis, whose primary scope is the maximum mutational robustness in genotype-phenotype maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16806v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Paul Allouche, Manon Stipulanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Elementary Method For Fast Modular Exponentiation With Factored Modulus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10497v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a fast algorithm for modular exponentiation when the factorization of the modulus is known. Let $a,n,m$ be positive integers and suppose $m$ factors canonically as $\prod_{i=1}^k p_i^{e_i}$. Choose integer parameters $t_i\in [0, e_i]$ for $1\le i\le k$. Then we can compute the modular exponentiation $a^n\pmod{m}$ in $O(\max(e_i/t_i)+\sum_{i=1}^k t_i\log p_i)$ steps (i.e. modular operations). We go on to analyze this algorithm mathematically and programmatically, showing significant asymptotic improvement in specific cases. Specifically, for an infinite family of $m$ we achieve a complexity of $O(\sqrt{\log m})$. Additionally, we extend our algorithm to matrices and hence general linear recurrences. The complexity is similar; with the same setup we can exponentiate matrices in $GL_d(\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z})$ in less than $O(\max(e_i/t_i)+d^2\sum_{i=1}^k t_i\log p_i)$ steps. This improves Fiduccia's algorithm and the results of Bostan and Mori in the case of $\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}$. Finally, we prove analogous results for $\mathbb{Z}/p^k\mathbb{Z}$ ring extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10497v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anay Aggarwal, Manu Isaacs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signed $p$-adic $L$-functions of Bianchi modular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15881v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $p\geq 3$ be a prime number and $K$ be a quadratic imaginary field in which $p$ splits as $\mathfrak{p}\overline{\mathfrak{p}}$. Let $\mathcal{F}$ be a cuspidal Bianchi eigenform over $K$ of weight $(k,k)$, where $k\geq 2$ is an integer, level $\mathfrak{n}$ coprime to $(p)$, and non-ordinary at both of the primes above $p$. We assume $\mathcal{F}$ has trivial nebentypus. For $\mathfrak{q}\in\{\mathfrak{p}, \overline{\mathfrak{p}}\}$, let $a_{\mathfrak{q}}$ be the $T_{\mathfrak{q}}$ Hecke eigenvalue of $\mathcal{F}$ and let $\alpha_{\mathfrak{q}},\beta_{\mathfrak{q}}$ be the roots of polynomial $X^{2} -a_{\mathfrak{q}}X+ p^{k-1}$. Then we have four $p$-stabilizations of $\mathcal{F}$: $\mathcal{F}^{\alpha_{\mathfrak{p}},\alpha_{\overline{\mathfrak{p}}}}, \mathcal{F}^{\alpha_{\mathfrak{p}},\beta_{\overline{\mathfrak{p}}}}, \mathcal{F}^{\beta_{\mathfrak{p}},\alpha_{\overline{\mathfrak{p}}}},$ and $ \mathcal{F}^{\beta_{\mathfrak{p}},\beta_{\overline{\mathfrak{p}}}}$ which are Bianchi cusp forms of level $p\mathfrak{n}$. Due to Williams, to each $p$-stabilization $\mathcal{F}^{*,\dagger}$, we can attach a locally analytic distribution $L_{p}(\mathcal{F}^{*,\dagger})$ over the ray class group $\text{Cl}(K,p^{\infty})$. On viewing $L_{p}(\mathcal{F}^{*,\dagger})$ as a two-variable power series with coefficients in some $p$-adic field having unbounded denominators satisfying certain growth conditions, we decompose this power series into a linear combination of power series with bounded coefficients in the spirit of Pollack, Sprung, and Lei-Loeffler-Zerbes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15881v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihir Deo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sum of the reciprocals of the prime divisors of an odd perfect or odd primitive non-deficient number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14234v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Write $T(n)$ as the sum of the reciprocals of the primes which divide $n$. Write $H(n) = \prod_{p|n}p/(p-1)$ where the product is over the prime divisors of $n$. We prove new bounds for $T(n)$ and $H(n)$ in terms of the smallest prime factor of $n$, under the assumption that $n$ is an odd perfect number. Some of the results also apply under the weaker assumption that $n$ is odd and primitive non-deficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14234v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Zelinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digamma function and general Fischer series in the theory of Kempner sums</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03912v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The harmonic sum of the integers which are missing $p$ given digits in a base $b$ is expressed as $b\log(b)/p$ plus corrections indexed by the excluded digits and expressed as integrals involving the digamma function and a suitable measure. A number of consequences are derived, such as explicit bounds, monotony, series representations and asymptotic expansions involving the zeta values at integers, and suitable moments of the measure. In the classic Kempner case of $b=10$ and $9$ as the only excluded digit, the series representation turns out to be exactly identical with a result obtained by Fischer already in 1993. Extending this work is indeed the goal of the present contribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03912v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Burnol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary quadratic forms with the same value set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a binary quadratic form $F \in \mathbb{Z}[X, Y]$, we define its value set $F(\mathbb{Z}^2)$ to be $\{F(x, y) : (x, y) \in \mathbb{Z}^2\}$. If $F$ and $G$ are two binary quadratic forms with integer coefficients, we give necessary and sufficient conditions on $F$ and $G$ for $F(\mathbb{Z}^2) = G(\mathbb{Z}^2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09575v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Etienne Fouvry, Peter Koymans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Un d\'eveloppement asymptotique des sommes harmoniques de Kempner-Irwin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $I(b,d,k)$ be the subseries of the harmonic series keeping only those denominators having exactly $k$ occurrences of the digit $d$ in base $b$. We prove the existence of an asymptotic development to all orders in descending powers of $b$, for $d$ and $k$ fixed, of $I(b,d,k)-b \log(b)$ or rather, if $k=0$ and $d&gt;0$, of $I(b,d,0)- (b\log(b) - b\log(1+1/d))$. We give explicitly, according to cases, the first four or first five terms. The coefficients of these developments involve the values of the Riemann zeta function at positive integers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13763v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Burnol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cyclotomic matrices involving Gauss sums over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15063v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by the works of L. Carlitz and Z.-W. Sun on cyclotomic matrices, in this paper, we investigate certain cyclotomic matrices involving Gauss sums over finite fields, which can be viewed as finite field analogues of certain matrices related to the Gamma function.
  For example, let $q=p^n$ be an odd prime power with $p$ prime and $n\in\mathbb{Z}^+$. Let $\zeta_p=e^{2\pi{\bf i}/p}$ and let $\chi$ be a generator of the group of all mutiplicative characters of the finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$. For the Gauss sum
  $$G_q(\chi^{r})=\sum_{x\in\mathbb{F}_q}\chi^{r}(x)\zeta_p^{{\rm Tr}_{\mathbb{F}_q/\mathbb{F}_p}(x)},$$
  we prove that
  $$\det \left[G_q(\chi^{2i+2j})\right]_{0\le i,j\le (q-3)/2}=(-1)^{\alpha_p}\left(\frac{q-1}{2}\right)^{\frac{q-1}{2}}2^{\frac{p^{n-1}-1}{2}},$$
  where
  $$\alpha_p=
  \begin{cases}
  1 &amp; \mbox{if}\ n\equiv 1\pmod 2,
  (p^2+7)/8 &amp; \mbox{if}\ n\equiv 0\pmod 2.
  \end{cases}$$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15063v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Liang Wu, Jie Li, Li-Yuan Wang, Chi Hoi Yip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Mochizuki's idea of Anabelomorphy and its applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.01890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2003.01890v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I coined the term anabelomorphy (pronounced as anabel-o-morphy) as a concise way of expressing Mochizuki's idea of "anabelian way of changing ground field, rings etc." which was he has introduced in his work on his Inter-Universal Teichmuller Theory. This paper demonstrates the usefulness of this idea by studying its ramifications in the more familiar arithmetic contexts such as the theory of Galois representations, automorphic forms and related areas and establish a number of results which are of independent arithmetic interest. I also introduce the notion of anabelomorphically connected number fields in which two number fields are related by the existence of topological isomorphism between the local Galois groups at a finite list of primes of both the number fields and prove some results illustrating arithmetic consequences of this notion. The Introduction provides a detailed discussion and summary of all the results proved in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2003.01890v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirti Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform approximation of Betti numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05104v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that Lefschetz's principle of approximating the cohomology of a possibly singular affine scheme of finite type over a field by the cohomology of a suitable (thickening of a) hyperplane section can be made uniform: in the affine case, we can choose the hyperplane section independently of the cohomology. Using Jouanolou's trick, this gives a new way to bound the Betti numbers of quasi-projective schemes over a field, independently of the cohomology. This is achieved through a motivic version of Deligne's generic base change formula and an axiomatic presentation of the theory of perverse sheaves. These methods produce generating families of Voevodsky motivic sheaves that are realized in perverse sheaves over any base of equal characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05104v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis-Charles Cisinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certain conjectures of Clozel and Shahidi on Arthur packets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05773v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, applying the intersection theory of local Arthur packets, for symplectic and split odd special orthogonal groups $\mathrm{G}_n$, we prove the enhanced Shahidi conjecture on generic representations in local Arthur packets. As an application, we show that given any automorphic representation in the discrete spectrum of $\mathrm{G}_n(\mathbb{A})$, if a finite local component is generic, then almost all local components are generic. Next, we give a classification of the unramified representations of Arthur type for $\mathrm{G}_n$ and show that any unramified representation of $\mathrm{G}_n$ of Arthur type lies in exactly one local Arthur packet, moreover, it lies in the $L$-packet associated to an anti-generic local Arthur packet. As applications, we prove a reciprocal conjecture of Clozel and confirm a conjecture of Arthur and Clozel on the local components of automorphic representations in the discrete spectrum of $\mathrm{G}_n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05773v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Hazeltine, Baiying Liu, Chi-Heng Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the number of subsequence sums related to the support of a sequence in finite abelian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11307v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a finite abelian group and $S$ a sequence with elements of $G$. Let $|S|$ denote the length of $S$ and $\mathrm{supp}(S)$ the set of all the distinct terms in $S$. For an integer $k$ with $k\in [1, |S|]$, let $\Sigma_{k}(S) \subset G$ denote the set of group elements which can be expressed as a sum of a subsequence of $S$ with length $k$. Let $\Sigma(S)=\cup_{k=1}^{|S|}\Sigma_{k}(S)$ and $\Sigma_{\geq k}(S)=\cup_{t=k}^{|S|}\Sigma_{t}(S)$. It is known that if $0\not\in \Sigma(S)$, then $|\Sigma(S)|\geq |S|+|\mathrm{supp}(S)|-1$. In this paper, we determine the structure of a sequence $S$ satisfying $0\notin \Sigma(S)$ and $|\Sigma(S)|= |S|+|\mathrm{supp}(S)|-1$. As a consequence, we can give a counterexample of a conjecture of Gao, Grynkiewicz, and Xia. Moreover, we prove that if $|S|&gt;k$ and $0\not\in \Sigma_{\geq k}(S)\cup \mathrm{supp}(S)$, then $|\Sigma_{\geq k}(S)|\geq |S|-k+|\mathrm{supp}(S)|$. Then we can give an alternative proof of a conjecture of Hamidoune, which was first proved by Gao, Grynkiewicz, and Xia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11307v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Wang, Han Chao, Jiangtao Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
