<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 05:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Eisenstein degeneration of Beilinson--Kato classes and circular units</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this note is to explore the Euler system of Beilinson--Kato elements in families passing through the critical $p$-stabilization of an Eisenstein series attached to two Dirichlet characters $(\psi,\tau)$. In this context, we establish an explicit connection with the system of circular units, utilizing suitable factorization formulas in a situation where several of the $p$-adic $L$-functions vanish. In that regard, our main results may be seen as an Euler system incarnation of the factorization formula of Bella\"iche and Dasgupta. One of the most significant aspects is that, depending on the parity of $\psi$ and $\tau$, different phenomena arise; while some can be addressed with our methods, others pose new questions. Finally, we discuss analogous results in the framework of Beilinson--Flach classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01514v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Polo, \'Oscar Rivero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Pell sequence and cyclotomic matrices involving squares over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, by some arithmetic properties of the Pell sequence and some $p$-adic tools, we study certain cyclotomic matrices involving squares over finite fields. For example, let $1=s_1,s_2,\cdots,s_{(q-1)/2}$ be all the nonzero squares over $\mathbb{F}_{q}$, where $q=p^f$ is an odd prime power with $q\ge7$. We prove that the matrix
  $$B_q((q-3)/2)=\left[\left(s_i+s_j\right)^{(q-3)/2}\right]_{2\le i,j\le (q-1)/2}$$
  is a singular matrix whenever $f\ge2$. Also, for the case $q=p$, we show that
  $$\det B_p((p-3)/2)=0\Leftrightarrow Q_p\equiv 2\pmod{p^2\mathbb{Z}},$$
  where $Q_p$ is the $p$-th term of the Pell sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01667v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Liang Wu, Li-Yuan Wang, He-Xia Ni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Very well approximable matrices are singular on average</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish upper bounds on the dimension of sets of singular-on-average and $\omega$-singular affine forms in singly metric settings, where either the matrix or the shift is fixed. These results partially address open questions posed by Das, Fishman, Simmons, and Urba\'nski, as well as Kleinbock and Wadleigh. Furthermore, we extend our results to the generalized weighted setup and derive bounds for the intersection of these sets with a wide class of fractals. Combined with the results of Chow, Ghosh, Guan, Marnat, and Simmons, our results shows that very well approximable matrices are singular on average.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01713v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sets preserved by a large subgroup of the special linear group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01697v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $E$ be a subset of the the affine plane over a finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$. We bound the size of the subgroup of $SL_2(\mathbb{F}_q)$ that preserves $E$. As a consequence, we show that if $E$ has size $\ll q^\alpha$ and is preserved by $\gg q^\beta$ elements of $SL_2(\mathbb{F}_q)$ with $\beta\geq 3\alpha/2$, then $E$ is contained in a line. This result is sharp in general, and will be proved by using a point-line incidence bound in $\mathbb{F}_q^3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01697v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Quang Hung, Thang Pham, Kaloyan Slavov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fields of definition for triangle groups as Fuchsian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01780v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The compact hyperbolic triangle group $\Delta(p,q,r)$ admits a canonical representation to $\mathrm{PSL}_2(\mathbf{R})$ with discrete image which is unique up to conjugation. The trace field of this representation is \[K = \mathbf{Q}(\cos(\pi/p), \cos(\pi/q), \cos(\pi/r)).\] We prove that there are exactly eleven such groups which are conjugate to subgroups of $\mathrm{PSL}_2(K)$. Moreover, we prove that there are no additional compact hyperbolic triangle groups which are conjugate to subgroups of $\mathrm{PSL}_2(L)$ for any totally real field $L$. This answers a question first raised by Waterman and Machlachlan, and also resolves (in the positive) five (interrelated) recent conjectures of McMullen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01780v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank Calegari, Qiankang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypersurfaces passing through the Galois orbit of a point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Asgarli, Ghioca, and Reichstein recently proved that if $K$ is a field with $|K|&gt;2$, then for any positive integers $d$ and $n$, and separable field extension $L/K$ with degree $m=\binom{n+d}{d}$, there exists a point $P\in \mathbb{P}^n(L)$ which does not lie on any degree $d$ hypersurface defined over $K$. They asked whether the result holds when $|K| = 2$. We answer their question in the affirmative by combining various ideas from arithmetic geometry. More generally, we show that for each positive integer $r$ and separable field extension $L/K$ with degree $r$, there exists a point $P \in \mathbb{P}^n(L)$ such that the vector space of degree $d$ forms over $K$ that vanish at $P$ has the expected dimension. We also discuss applications to linear systems of hypersurfaces with special properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01906v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shamil Asgarli, Jonathan Love, Chi Hoi Yip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On deformation rings of residual Galois representations with three Jordan-Holder factors and modularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02708v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study Fontaine-Laffaille, self-dual deformations of a mod p non-semisimple Galois representation of dimension n with its Jordan-Holder factors being three mutually non-isomorphic absolutely irreducible representations. We show that under some conditions regarding the orders of certain Selmer groups, the universal deformation ring is a discrete valuation ring. Given enough information on the Hecke algebra, we also prove an R = T theorem in the general context. We then apply our results to abelian surfaces with cyclic rational isogenies and certain 6-dimensional representations arising from automorphic forms congruent to Ikeda lifts. Assuming the Bloch-Kato conjecture, our result identifies special L-value conditions for the existence of a unique abelian surface isogeny class and an R = T theorem for certain 6-dimensional Galois representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02708v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Torsion Subgroups of Elliptic Curves over Quartic, Quintic and Sextic Number Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02351v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The list of all groups that can appear as torsion subgroups of elliptic curves over number fields of degree $d$, $d=4,5,6$, is not completely determined. However, the list of groups $\Phi^{\infty}(d)$, $d=4,5,6$, that can be realized as torsion subgroups for infinitely many non-isomorphic elliptic curves over these fields are known. We address the question of which torsion subgroups can arise over a given number field of degree $d$. In fact, given $G\in\Phi^{\infty}(d)$ and a number field $K$ of degree $d$, we give explicit criteria telling whether $G$ is realized finitely or infinitely often over $K$. We also give results on the field with the smallest absolute value of its discriminant such that there exists an elliptic curve with torsion $G$. Finally, we give examples of number fields $K$ of degree $d$, $d=4,5,6$, over which the Mordell-Weil rank of elliptic curves with prescribed torsion is bounded from above.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02351v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Umut Kazanc{\i}o\u{g}lu, Mohammad Sadek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Problems in additive number theory, VI: Sizes of sumsets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02365v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper describes problems concerning the range of cardinalities of sumsets and restricted sumsets of finite subsets of the integers and finite subsets of ordered abelian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02365v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melvyn B. Nathanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic-geometric mean sequences over finite fields $\mathbb{F}_q$, where $q\equiv5\pmod{8}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Arithmetic-geometric mean sequences were already studied over real and complex numbers, and recently, Michael J. Griffin, Ken Ono, Neelam Saikia and Wei-Lun Tsai considered them over finite fields $\mathbb{F}_q$ such that $q \equiv 3 \pmod 4$. In this paper, we extend the definition of arithmetic-geometric mean sequences over $\mathbb{F}_q$ such that $q \equiv 5 \pmod 8$. We explain the connection of these sequences with graphs and show the properties of the corresponding graphs in the case $q \equiv 5 \pmod 8$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00577v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nat\'alia B\'atorov\'a, Stevan Gajovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting subgroups of $\mathrm{PSL}_2$ to $\mathrm{SL}_2$ over local fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05192v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a non-archimedean local field. We show that discrete subgroups without 2-torsion in $\mathrm{PSL}_2(K)$ can always be lifted to $\mathrm{SL}_2(K)$, and provide examples (when $\mathrm{char}(K) \neq 2$) which cannot be lifted if either of these conditions is removed. We also briefly discuss lifting representations of groups into $\mathrm{PSL}_2(K)$ to $\mathrm{SL}_2(K)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05192v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naomi Andrew, Matthew J. Conder, Ari Markowitz, Jeroen Schillewaert</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
