<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 03:12:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial progressions in the generalized twin primes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17375v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By Maynard's theorem and the subsequent improvements by the Polymath Project, there exists a positive integer $b\leq 246$ such that there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $p+b$ is also prime. Let $P_1,...,P_t\in \mathbb{Z}[y]$ with $P_1(0)=\cdots=P_t(0)=0$. We use the transference argument of Tao and Ziegler to prove there exist positive integers $x, y,$ and $b \leq 246 $ such that $x+P_1(y),x+P_2(y),...,x+P_t(y)$ and $x+P_1(y)+b,x+P_2(y)+b,...,x+P_t(y)+b$ are all prime. Our work is inspired by Pintz, who proved a similar result for the special case of arithmetic progressions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17375v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Lott, Nagendar Reddy Ponagandla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of conjectures on heavenly elliptic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17474v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavenly abelian varieties are abelian varieties defined over number fields that exhibit constrained $\ell$-adic Galois representations for some rational prime $\ell$. At the ICMS Workshop held in November 2024, we presented evidence for two finiteness conjectures around the distribution of heavenly elliptic curves over quadratic number fields, one in terms of isomorphism classes of curves, and a second in terms of quadratic fields which admit heavenly elliptic curves. We prove these two conjectures are equivalent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17474v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cam McLeman, Christopher Rasmussen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cones of Weights and Minimal Cones of the Goren-Oort Strata in Hilbert modular varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime, $F$ a totally real field in which $p$ is unramified, and $X/\overline{\mathbb{F}}_p$ a Shimura variety associated to ${\rm Res}_{F/\mathbb{Q}} {\rm GL}_2$ (or a PEL Hilbert modular variety). A mod $p$ Hilbert modular form of weight $\kappa$ can be defined as a section of an automorphic line bundle $\mathcal{L}_\kappa$ on $X$. We consider sections of $\mathcal{L}_\kappa$ (forms) over a Goren-Oort stratum $X_T$ inside $X$, and define the cone of weights of $X_T$ to be the $\mathbb{Q}^{\geq 0}$-cone generated by the weights of all nonzero forms on $X_T$. We explicitly determine the cone of weights of all strata, showing in particular that they are not in general generated by the weights of the associated Hasse invariants. Using this, we define a notion of minimal cone for each stratum, and explicitly determine the minimal cones of all strata. When $X$ is a Shimura variety associated to ${\rm Res}_{F/\mathbb{Q}} {\rm GL}_2$, we prove that for every nonzero eigenform $f$ for the prime-to-$p$ Hecke algebra on a stratum $X_T$, there is another eigenform with the same Hecke eigenvalues which has weight in the minimal cone of $X_T$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17523v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fred Diamond, Payman L Kassaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting quadratic points on Fano varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper initiates the systematic study of the number of points of bounded height on symmetric squares of weak Fano varieties. We provide a general framework for establishing the point count on $\text{Sym}^2 X$. In the specific case of surfaces, we relate this to the Manin--Peyre conjecture for $\text{Hilb}^2 X$, and prove the conjecture for an infinite family of non-split quadric surfaces. In order to achieve the predicted asymptotic, we show that a type II thin set of a new flavour must be removed.
  To establish our counting result for the specific family of surfaces, we generalise existing lattice point counting techniques to lattices defined over rings of integers. This reduces the dimension of the problem and yields improved error terms. Another key tool we develop is a collection of results for summing Euler products over quadratic extensions. We use this to show moments of $L$-functions at $s=1$ are constant on average in quadratic twist families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17940v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Balestrieri, Kevin Destagnol, Julian Lyczak, Jennifer Park, Nick Rome</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving quadratic forms in restricted variables with the circle method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $f(\mathbf x)$ be a non-singular quadratic form with sufficiently many mixed terms and $t$ an integer. For a sequence of weights $\mathcal A$ we study the number of weighted solutions to $f(\mathbf x) = t$. In particular, we give conditions on both $\mathcal A$ and $f$ such that we can use the circle method to count such solutions of bounded height.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17949v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mieke Wessel, Svenja zur Verth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mock Modularity Of Twisted Index In CHL Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17182v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the twisted partition function of quarter BPS states in CHL models and show that for a large class of single-centered black holes, the degeneracy of microstates is given by the Fourier coefficients of mock Jacobi forms. Our analysis is a continuation of the programme initiated by Dabholkar, Murthy and Zagier (DMZ) for $1/4$-BPS dyons in $\mathcal{N} = 4$ string theory and further extended by Bhand, Sen and Singh (BSS) to quarter BPS states in CHL models. We also present the multiplicative lift construction of the partition function and comment on the additive lift of the same.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17182v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nabamita Banerjee, Vedant Bhutra, Ranveer Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On genus theory for 3-manifolds in arithmetic topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17486v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Based on the analogies of arithmetic topology, we show a topological analogue for 3-manifolds of the Hilbert theorem 90 and the genus theory in number theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17486v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirotaka Tashiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavenly elliptic curves over quadratic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18389v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by a long-standing question of Ihara, we investigate heavenly abelian varieties, i.e., abelian varieties whose arithmetic behavior resembles that of the Jacobians of curves in the pro-$\ell$ etale tower of coverings of the projective line minus three points. Introducing the notion of a balanced heavenly abelian variety, characterized by the structure of its $\ell$-torsion as a group scheme, we show that for sufficiently large $\ell$ all heavenly abelian varieties are balanced, with this result holding uniformly once the degree of the number field and the dimension of the abelian variety are fixed. We study the traces of Frobenius elements for balanced heavenly elliptic curves, showing they satisfy certain congruences modulo $\ell$ akin to trace behavior for elliptic curves with complex multiplication. We conjecture that all balanced elliptic curves over quadratic number fields must possess complex multiplication and among curves with complex multiplication characterize those that are heavenly. Finally, we produce an explicit list of elliptic curves with irrational $j$-invariants that contain all heavenly elliptic curves with complex multiplication defined over quadratic fields, supported by computational evidence that every curve on the list is heavenly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18389v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cam McLeman, Christopher Rasmussen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds for the relative class number problem for function fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12467v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish bounds on a finite separable extension of function fields in terms of the relative class number, thus reducing the problem of classifying extensions with a fixed relative class number to a finite computation. We also solve the relative class number two problem in all cases where the base field has constant field not equal to $\mathbb{F}_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12467v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Arango-Pi\~neros, Mar\'ia Chara, Asimina S. Hamakiotes, Kiran S. Kedlaya, Gustavo Rama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First moments of ${\rm{GL}} (3) \times {\rm{GL}} (2)$ and ${\rm{GL}} (2)$ $L$-functions and their applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15886v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $F$ be a self-dual Hecke-Maa\ss\ form for ${\rm{GL}}(3)$ underlying the symmetric square lift of a ${\rm{GL}}(2)$-newform of square-free level and trivial nebentypus. In this paper, we are interested in the first moments of the central values of ${\rm{GL}}(3) \times {\rm{GL}}(2)$ $L$-functions and ${\rm{GL}}(2)$ $L$-functions. As a result, we obtain an estimate for the first moment for $L(1/2, F\otimes f)$ over a family, where $F$ is of the level $q^2$, and $f\in \mathcal{B}^\ast_k(M)$ for any primes $q,M\ge 2$ such that $(q,M)=1$. We prove the subconvex bound for $L(1/2, F\otimes f)$ involving the levels aspects simultaneously in the range $M^{13/64+\varepsilon }\le q \le M^{11/40-\varepsilon}$ and $M&gt; q^\delta$ for any $\varepsilon, \delta&gt;0$ for the first time. Moreover, we further investigate the first moments of these $L$-functions in the weight $k$ aspect over $K\le k\le 2K$, with $K$ being a large number. As the results, we obtain a Lindel\"of average bound for the first moment of $L(1/2, f)L(1/2, F\otimes f)$ of degree 8 and an asymptotic formula for the first moment of $L(1/2, F\otimes f)$ with an error term of $O(K^{-1/4+\varepsilon})$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15886v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Berndt-Type Integrals and Generalized Barnes Multiple Zeta Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15173v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we define and study four families of Berndt-type integrals, called mixed Berndt-type integrals, which contains (hyperbolic) sine and cosine functions in the integrand function. By contour integration, these integrals are first converted to some hyperbolic (infinite) sums of Ramanujan type, all of which can be calculated in closed forms by comparing both the Fourier series expansions and the Maclaurin series expansions of a few Jacobi elliptic functions. These sums can be expressed as rational polynomials of {\Gamma}(1/4) and {\pi}^{-1} which give rise to the closed formulas of the mixed Berndt-type integrals we are interested in. Moreover, we also present some interesting consequences and illustrative examples. Further, we define a generalized Barnes multiple zeta function, and find a classic integral representation of the generalized Barnes multiple zeta function. Furthermore, we give an alternative evaluation of the mixed Berndt-type integrals in terms of the generalized Barnes multiple zeta function. Finally, we obtain some direct evaluations of rational linear combinations of the generalized Barnes multiple zeta function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15173v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianing Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the complementary Arthur representations and unitary dual for p-adic classical groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11381v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In [HJLLZ24], we proposed a new conjecture on the structure of the unitary dual of connected reductive groups over non-Archimedean local fields of characteristic zero based on their Arthur representations and verified it for all the known cases on the unitary dual problem. One step towards this conjecture involves the question whether certain complementary Arthur representations are unitary. In this paper, we give an explicit characterization of the complementary Arthur representations for symplectic and split odd special orthogonal groups. As applications, we obtain interesting constraints on local components of irreducible self-dual cuspidal automorphic representations of GL(N), especially when N=2,3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11381v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Hazeltine, Dihua Jiang, Baiying Liu, Chi-Heng Lo, Qing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
