<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On prime-producing sieves and distribution of $\alpha p-\beta$ mod $1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The author proves that there are infinitely many primes $p$ such that $\| \alpha p - \beta \| &lt; p^{-\frac{28}{87}}$, where $\alpha$ is an irrational number and $\beta$ is a real number. This sharpens a result of Jia (2000) and provides a new triple $(\gamma, \theta, \nu)=(\frac{59}{87}, \frac{28}{87}, \frac{1}{29})$ that can produce primes in Ford and Maynard's work on prime-producing sieves. Our minimum amount of Type-II information required ($\nu = \frac{1}{29}$) is less than any previous work on this topic using only traditional Type-I and Type-II information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13195v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runbo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Functions and Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this expository note, we revisit several classical arithmetic functions - namely Euler's totient function, the divisor sum functions and Dedekind's $\psi$-function - within a unifying algebraic framework that highlights their connections to geometry. This framework builds on prior work involving zeta functions and M\"obius inversion. While our main goal is to provide a clear context for similar constructions in the future, we also make an original observation regarding Dedekind's $\psi$-function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13328v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Kobin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersingular primes and Bogomolov property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $E$ be an elliptic curve over a number field $K$ with at least one real embedding and $L$ be a finite extension of $K$. We generalize a result of Habegger to show that $L(E_{\text{tor}})$, the field generated by the torsion points of $E$ over $L$, has the Bogomolov property. Moreover, the N\'eron-Tate height on $E\big(L(E_{\text{tor}})\big)$ also satisfies a similar discreteness property. Our main tool is a general criterion of Plessis that reduces the problem to the existence of a supersingular prime for $E$ satisfying certain conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13498v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumyadip Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How often is $x\mapsto x^3$ one-to-one in $\mathbb{Z}/n\mathbb{Z}$?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the integers n such that $x\mapsto x^3$ describes a bijection from the set $\mathbb{Z}/n\mathbb{Z}$ to itself and we determine the frequency of these integers. Precisely, denoting by $W$ the set of these integers, we prove that an integer belongs to $W$ if and only if it is square-free with no prime factor that is congruent to 1 modulo 3, and that there exists $C&gt;0$ such that $$|W\cap\{1,\dots,n\}|\sim C\frac{n}{\sqrt{\log n}}\ .$$ These facts (or equivalent facts) are stated without proof on the OEIS website. We give the explicit value of $C$, which did not seem to be known. Analogous results are also proved for families of integers for which congruence classes for prime factors are imposed. The proofs are based on a Tauberian Theorem by Delange.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13511v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Garet (IECL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Hasse-Arf property of local fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $F/K$ be a finite Galois totally &amp; wildly ramified extension of complete discrete valuation fields. We say that the extension has the Hasse-Arf property if the ramification jumps in upper numbering are integers. We give necessary defining equations for $F$ in terms of the ramification jumps. In order for the Hasse-Arf property to hold, these equations become very strict. We prove that the last assertion is an equivalence condition, thus in terms of these defining equations, the Hasse-Arf property becomes an equivalence condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13606v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis Tsouknidas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number system in rational base $3/2$ and the $3x+1$ problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The representation of numbers in rational base $p/q$ was introduced in 2008 by Akiyama, Frougny &amp; Sakarovitch, with a special focus on the case $p/q=3/2$. Unnoticed since then, natural questions related to representations in that specific base turn out to intimately involve the Collatz $3x+1$ function. Our purpose in this note is to expose these links and motivate further research into them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13716v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalom Eliahou, Jean-Louis Verger-Gaugry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Bottlenecks in Homomorphic Encryption for the 2024 Mexican Federal Election</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On June 2, 2024, Mexico held its federal elections. The majority of Mexican citizens voted in person at the polls in this historic election. For the first time though, Mexican citizens living outside their country were able to vote online via a web app, either on a personal device or using an electronic voting kiosk at one of 23 embassies and consulates in the U.S., Canada, and Europe. In total, 144,734 people voted outside of Mexico: 122,496 on a personal device and 22,238 in-person at a kiosk. Voting was open for remote voting from 8PM, May 18, 2024 to 6PM, June 2, 2024 and was open for in-person voting from 8AM-6PM on June 2, 2024. This article describes the technical and cryptographic tools applied to secure the ex-patriate component of the election and to enable INE (Mexico's National Electoral Institute) to generate provable election results within minutes of the close of the election. This article will also describe how the solutions we present scale to elections on a national level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13198v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Blockchain Technical Briefs, (2024). https://blockchain.ieee.org/images/files/pdf/techbriefs/tb-2024/</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eric Landquist, Nimit Sawhney, Simer Sawhney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An algorithm to compute Selmer groups via resolutions by permutations modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13506v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a number field with absolute Galois group $\mathcal{G}$, a finite Galois module $M$, and a Selmer system $\mathcal{L}$, this article gives a method to compute Sel$_\mathcal{L}$, the Selmer group of $M$ attached to $\mathcal{L}$. First we describe an algorithm to obtain a resolution of $M$ where the morphisms are given by Hecke operators. Then we construct another group $H^1_S(\mathcal{G}, M)$ and we prove, using the properties of Hecke operators, that $H^1_S(\mathcal{G}, M)$ is a Selmer group containing Sel$_\mathcal{L}$. Then, we discuss the time complexity of this method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13506v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrice Etienne (UB, CANARI, IMB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $\ell-$regular and $2-$color partition triples modulo powers of $3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13507v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $T_\ell(n)$ denote the number of $\ell-$regular partition triples of $n$ and let $p_{\ell, 3}(n)$ enumerates the number of 2--color partition triples of $n$ where one of the colors appear only in parts that are multiples of $\ell$. In this paper, we prove several infinite families of congruences modulo powers of 3 for $T_\ell(n)$ and $p_{\ell, 3}(n)$, where $\ell \geq 1$ and $\equiv 0\pmod{3^k}$, and $\equiv \pm 3^k \pmod{3^{k+1}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13507v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Hemanthkumar, D. S. Gireesh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\alpha$-numbers, diophantine exponent and factorisations of sturmian words</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of $\alpha$-numbers and formal intercept of sturmian words, and derive from this study general factorisations formula for sturmian words. Sturmian words are defined as infinite words with lowest unbound complexity, and are characterized by two parameters, the first one being well-known as the slope, and the second being their formal intercepts. We build this formalism by a study of Rauzy graphs of sturmian words, and we use this caracterisation to compute the repetition function of sturmian words and their diophantine exponent. We then develop these techniques to provide general factorisations formulas for sturmian words.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13636v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caius Wojcik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Descent for algebraic stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13642v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that algebraic stacks satisfy 2-descent for fppf coverings. We generalize Galois descent for schemes to stacks, by considering the case where the fppf covering is a finite Galois covering and reformulating 2-descent data for stacks in terms of group actions on the stack.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13642v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier de Gaay Fortman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Springer theorem and $n$-universality under field extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09560v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Based on BONGs theory, we prove the norm principle for integral and relative integral spinor norms of quadratic forms over general dyadic local fields, respectively. By virtue of these results, we further establish the arithmetic version of Springer's theorem for indefinite quadratic forms. Moreover, we solve the lifting problems on $n$-universality over arbitrary local fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09560v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilong He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On invariants of Artin-Schreier curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08843v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main goal of this article is to expand the theory of invariants of Artin-Schreier curves by giving a complete classification in genus 3 and 4. To achieve this goal, we first establish standard forms of Artin-Schreier curves and determine all isomorphisms between curves in this form. We then compute reconstructing systems of invariants for curves in each connected component of the strata of the moduli spaces for Artin-Schreier curves of genus 3 and 4 for $p&gt;2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08843v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juanita Duque-Rosero, Heidi Goodson, Elisa Lorenzo Garc\'ia, Beth Malmskog, Renate Scheidler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galois theory of quadratic rational functions with periodic critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14862v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a number field $k$, and a quadratic rational function $f(x) \in k(x)$, the associated arboreal representation of the absolute Galois group of $k$ is a subgroup of the automorphism group of a regular rooted binary tree. Boston and Jones conjectured that the image of such a representation for $f \in \mathbb{Z}[x]$ contains a dense set of settled elements. An automorphism is settled if the number of its orbits on the $n\text{th}$ level of the tree remains small as $n$ goes to infinity.
  In this article, we exhibit many quadratic rational functions whose associated Arboreal Galois groups are not densely settled. These examples arise from quadratic rational functions whose critical points lie in a single periodic orbit. To prove our results, we present a detailed study of the iterated monodromy groups (IMG) of $f$, which also allows us to provide a negative answer to Jones and Levy's question regarding settled pairs.
  Furthermore, we study the iterated extension $k(f^{-\infty}(t))$ generated by adjoining to $k(t)$ all roots of $f^n(x) = t$ for $n \geq 1$ for a parameter $t$. We call the intersection of $k(f^{-\infty}(t))$ with $\bar{k}$, the field of constants associated with $f$. When one of the two critical points of $f$ is the image of the other, we show that the field of constants is contained in the cyclotomic extension of $k$ generated by all $2$-power roots of unity. In particular, we prove the conjecture of Ejder, Kara, and Ozman regarding the rational function $\frac{1}{(x-1)^2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14862v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\"Ozlem Ejder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An elementary proof that the set of exceptions to the law of large numbers in Pierce expansions has full Hausdorff dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02174v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The digits of the Pierce expansion satisfy the law of large numbers. It is known that the Hausdorff dimension of the set of exceptions to the law of large numbers is 1. We provide an elementary proof of this fact by adapting Jun Wu's method, which was originally used for Engel expansions. Our approach emphasizes the fractal nature of exceptional sets and avoids advanced machinery, thereby relying instead on explicit sequences and constructive techniques. Furthermore, our method opens the possibility of extending similar analyses to other real number representation systems, such as the Engel, L\"uroth, and Sylvester expansions, thus paving the way for further explorations in metric number theory and fractal geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02174v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/math.2025275</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>AIMS Math. 10 (2025), 6025-6039</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Min Woong Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomology of Fuchsian groups and Fourier interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19511v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a new proof of a Fourier interpolation result first proved by Radchenko-Viazovska, deriving it from a vanishing result of the first cohomology of a Fuchsian group with coefficients in the Weil representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19511v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathilde Gerbelli-Gauthier, Akshay Venkatesh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A polynomial identity and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07911v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel polynomial identity and use it to prove an unexpected result on linear algebra of quadratic forms. Besides its counterintuitive nature which is of independent interest, our result happens to be closely related to Druzkowski's reduction of the Jacobian Conjecture to which the mystery can be partially attributed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07911v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial layer of the anti-cyclotomic $\mathbb{Z}_{3}$-extension of $\mathbb{Q}( \sqrt{-m})$ and capitulation phenomenon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08214v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $k=\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{-m})$ be an imaginary quadratic field. We consider the properties of capitulation of the $p$-class group of $k$ in the anti-cyclotomic $\mathbb{Z}_{p}$-extension $k^{ac}$ of $k$; for this, using a new method based on the Log$_p$-function (Theorems 1.3 and 2.3), we determine, for $p = 3$, the first layer $k_{1}^{ac}$ of $k^{ac}$ over $k$, and we examine if, at least, some partial capitulation may exist in $k_{1}^{ac}$. The answer is obviously yes, even when $k^{ac}/k$ is totally ramified. We have conjectured that this phenomenon of capitulation is specific of all the $\mathbb{Z}_{p}$-extensions of $k$, distinct from the cyclotomic one. We characterize a sub-family of fields $k$ (Normal Split cases) for which $k^{ac}$ is not linearly disjoint from the Hilbert class field (Theorem 3.1). No assumptions are made on the structure of the 3-class group of $k$, nor on the splitting of 3 in $k$ and in its mirror field $k*=\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{3m})$. Four pari/gp programs are given with numerical illustrations to cover all cases without any limitation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08214v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georges Gras (LMB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic quadratic equations in three variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $f(x_1, x_2, x_3)$ be an indefinite anisotropic integral quadratic form with determinant $d(f)$, and $t$ a non-zero integer such that $d(f)t$ is square-free. It is proved in this paper that, as long as there is one integral solution to $f(x_1, x_2, x_3) = t$, there are infinitely many such solutions for which (i) $x_1$ has at most $6$ prime factors, and (ii) the product $x_1 x_2$ has at most $16$ prime factors. Various methods, such as algebraic theory of quadratic forms, harmonic analysis, Jacquet-Langlands theory, as well as combinatorics, interact here, and the above results come from applying the sharpest known bounds towards Selberg's eigenvalue conjecture. Assuming the latter the number $6$ or $16$ may be reduced to $5$ or $14$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15033v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiamin Li, Jianya Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Division polynomials for arbitrary isogenies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following work of Mazur-Tate and Satoh, we extend the definition of division polynomials to arbitrary isogenies of elliptic curves, including those whose kernels do not sum to the identity. In analogy to the classical case of division polynomials for multiplication-by-n, we demonstrate recurrence relations, identities relating to classical elliptic functions, the chain rule describing relationships between division polynomials on source and target curve, and generalizations to higher dimension (i.e., elliptic nets).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15428v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katherine E. Stange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Unforeseen Congruence Relationships Between PEND and POND Partitions via an Atkin--Lehner Involution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For the past several years, numerous authors have studied POD and PED partitions from a variety of perspectives. These are integer partitions wherein the odd parts must be distinct (in the case of POD partitions) or the even parts must be distinct (in the case of PED partitions).
  More recently, Ballantine and Welch were led to consider POND and PEND partitions, which are integer partitions wherein the odd parts cannot be distinct (in the case of POND partitions) or the even parts cannot be distinct (in the case of PEND partitions). Soon after, the first author proved the following results via elementary $q$-series identities and generating function manipulations, along with mathematical induction: For all $\alpha \geq 1$ and all $n\geq 0,$
  $$\mathrm{pend}\left(3^{2\alpha +1}n+\frac{17\cdot 3^{2\alpha}-1}{8}\right) \equiv 0 \pmod{3}, \textrm{ and}$$ $$\mathrm{pond}\left(3^{2\alpha +1}n+\frac{23\cdot 3^{2\alpha}+1}{8}\right) \equiv 0 \pmod{3},$$ where $\mathrm{pend}(n)$ counts the number of PEND partitions of weight $n$ and $\mathrm{pond}(n)$ counts the number of POND partitions of weight $n$.
  In this work, we revisit these families of congruences, and we show a relationship between them via an Atkin--Lehner involution. From this relationship, we can show that, once one of the above families of congruences is known, the other follows immediately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16019v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James A. Sellers, Nicolas Allen Smoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Sums by Irrationality Exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06726v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we give an asymptotic bound for the exponential sum of the M\"obius function $\sum_{n \le x} \mu(n) e(\alpha n)$ for a fixed irrational number $\alpha\in\mathbb{R}$. This exponential sum was originally studied by Davenport and he obtained an asymptotic bound of $x(\log x)^{-A}$ for any $A\ge0$. Our bound depends on the irrationality exponent $\eta$ of $\alpha$. If $\eta \le 5/2$, we obtain a bound of $x^{4/5 + \varepsilon}$ and, when $\eta \ge 5/2$, our bound is $x^{(2\eta-1)/2\eta + \varepsilon}$. This result extends a result of Murty and Sankaranarayanan, who obtained the same bound in the case $\eta = 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06726v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byungchul Cha, Dong Han Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational and integral points on Markoff-type K3 surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10992v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following recent works by E. Fuchs et al. and by the author, we study rational and integral points on Markoff-type K3 (MK3) surfaces, i.e., Wehler K3 surfaces of Markoff type. In particular, we construct a family of MK3 surfaces which have a Zariski dense set of rational points but fail the integral Hasse principle due to the Brauer-Manin obstruction and provide some counting results for this family. We also give some remarks on Brauer groups, Picard groups, and failure of strong approximation on MK3 surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10992v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quang-Duc Dao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On certain sums involving the largest prime factor over integer sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12435v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given an integer $ n \geq 2 $, its prime factorization is expressed as $ n = \prod p_i^{a_i} $. We define the function $ f(n) $ as the smallest positive integer satisfying the following condition: \[ \nu_{p}\left(\frac{f(n)!}{n}\right) \geq 1, \quad \forall p \in \{p_1, p_2, \dots, p_s\}, \] where $ \nu_{p}(m) $ denotes the $ p $-adic valuation of $ m $. The main objective of this paper is to derive an asymptotic formula for both sums $ \sum_{n\leq x} f(n) $ and $ \sum_{n \leq x, n \in S_k} f(n) $, where $ S_k $ denotes the set of all $ k $-free integers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12435v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihoub Bouderbala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Nori and Hodge realisations of Voevodsky motives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11999v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the derived category of perverse Nori motives and mixed Hodge modules are the derived categories of their constructible hearts. This enables us to construct $\infty$-categorical lifts of the six operations and therefore to obtain realisation functors from the category of Voevodsky \'etale motives to the derived categories of perverse Nori motives and mixed Hodge modules that commute with the operations. We give a proof that the realisation induces an equivalence of categories between Artin motives in the category of \'etale motives and Artin motives in the derived category of Nori motives. We also prove that if a motivic $t$-structure exists then Voevodsky \'etale motives and the derived category of perverse Nori motives are equivalent. Finally we give a presentation of the indization of the derived category of perverse Nori motives as a category of modules in Voevodsky \'etale motives that gives a continuity result for perverse Nori motives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11999v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swann Tubach</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
