<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme values of derivatives of the Dedekind zeta function of a cyclotomic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a lower bound for the maximum of derivatives of the Dedekind zeta function of a cyclotomic field on the critical line. Employing a double version convolution formula and combing special GCD sums, our result generalizes the work of Bondarenko et al. and Fonga in 2023. We also set a lower bound by the resonance method when the real part is near the critical line, both of the above results refine part of Yang's work in 2022.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12342v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhonghua Li, Yutong Song, Qiyu Yang, Shengbo Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hopf-Galois module structure of monogenic orders in cubic number fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a cubic number field $L$, we consider the $\mathbb{Z}$-order in $L$ of the form $\mathbb{Z}[\alpha]$, where $\alpha$ is a root of a polynomial of the form $x^3-ax+b$ and $a,b\in\mathbb{Z}$ are integers such that $v_p(a)\leq 2$ or $v_p(b)\leq 3$ for all prime numbers $p$. We characterize the freeness of $\mathbb{Z}[\alpha]$ as a module over its associated order in the unique Hopf-Galois structure $H$ on $L$ in terms of the solvability of at least one between two generalized Pell equations in terms of $a$ and $b$. We determine when the equality $\mathcal{O}_L=\mathbb{Z}[\alpha]$ is satisfied in terms of congruence conditions for $a$ and $b$. For such cases, we specialize our result so as to obtain criteria for the freeness of $\mathcal{O}_L$ as a module over its associated order in $H$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12451v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gil-Mu\~noz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposition of real numbers into sums of L\"uroth sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the decomposition of real numbers into sums of L\"uroth sets, which are defined by numbers whose L\"uroth expansions have prescribed digit constraints. We establish several results on the congruence modulo 1 of sums of L\"uroth sets, including summands with digits bounded above, below, and combinations of the two. We also analyse the Hausdorff dimension of L\"uroth sets and their sums. The results extend classical findings on continued fractions to L\"uroth expansions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12513v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maiken Gravgaard, Ying Wai Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abelianization of $\text{SL}_2$ over Dedekind domains of arithmetic type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine the exact group structure of the abelianization of $\text{SL}_2(A)$, where $A$ is a Dedekind domain of arithmetic type with infinitely many units. In particular, our results show that $\text{SL}_2(A)^\text{ab}$ is finite, with exponent dividing $12$ when $\text{char}(A)=0$, and dividing $6$ when $\text{char}(A)&gt;0$. As illustrative cases, we compute $\text{SL}_2(A)^\text{ab}$ explicitly for instances where $A$ is the ring of integers of a real quadratic field or a cyclotomic extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12638v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Behrooz Mirzaii, Bruno R. Ramos, Thiago Verissimo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting residual Galois representations with the same semi-simplification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If a $p$-adic Galois representation $\rho_{f,\nu}:\Gamma_{\mathbb Q} \to \GL_2(E_{f,\nu})$ attached to some eigenform $f$ is residually reducible it will have 2 non-isomorphic reductions, which have the same semi-simplification. In this paper, we answer a version of the inverse question, first brought up by Toby Gee and Alice Pozzi. Starting with two modulo $p$ non-semi-simple representations $\overline{\rho_1},\overline{\rho_2}:\Gamma_{\mathbb Q} \to \GL_2(k)$, which have the same semi-simplification we show that under some mild conditions that they are reductions of representations attached to newforms of the same weight $r \ge 2$, the same level $N \ge 1$, and the same Neben character $\varepsilon$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12644v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Nikoloski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Choosing iteration maps for the parallel Pollard rho method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pollard's rho method finds a prime factor $p$ of an integer $N$ by searching for a collision in a map of the form $x \mapsto x^{2k} + c$ modulo $N$. This search can be parallelized to multiple machines, which may use distinct parameters $k$ and $c$. In this paper, we give an asymptotic estimate for the expected running time of the parallel rho method depending on the choice of $k$ for each machine. We also prove that $k = 1$ is the best choice for one machine, if nothing about $p$ is known in advance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12844v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finn Rudolph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded Exponential Sums with Multiplicative Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate when the exponential sum $\sum_{n \leq x}f(n)e^{2 \pi i n \alpha}$ is bounded, for a multiplicative function $f$ and $\alpha \in \mathbb{R}$. We show that under certain natural assumptions, this exponential sum is bounded only when $f$ closely resembles a periodic function. For completely multiplicative functions or those taking only finitely many values, we obtain sharper classification results, including a full classification (up to a measure-zero set of $\alpha$) in the completely multiplicative case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12845v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ihor Pylaiev, Fred Tyrrell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positional numeral systems over polyadic rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct positional numeral systems that work natively over nonderived polyadic $\left( m,n\right) $-rings whose addition takes $m$ arguments and multiplication takes $n$. In such rings, the length of an admissible additive word and a multiplicative tower are not arbitrary (as in the binary case), but \textquotedblleft quantized\textquotedblright. Our main contributions are the following. Existence: every commutative $\left( m,n\right) $-ring admits a base-$p$ place-value expansion that respects the word length constraint in terms of numbers of operation compositions) $\ell_{mult}=\ell_{add}(m-1)+1$. Lower bound: the minimum number of digits is greater than or equal to the arity of addition $m$. Representability gap: for $m,n\geq3$ only a proper subset of ring elements possess finite expansions, characterized by congruence-class arity shape invariants $I^{(m)}$ and $J^{(n)}$. Mixed-base \textquotedblleft polyadic clocks\textquotedblright: allowing a different base at each position enlarges the design space quadratically in the digit count. Catalogues: explicit tables for the integer rings $\mathbb{Z}_{4,3}$ and $\mathbb{Z}_{6,5}$ illustrate how ordinary integers lift to distinct polyadic variables. These results lay the groundwork for faster arity-aware arithmetic, exotic coding schemes, and hardware that exploits operations beyond the binary pair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12930v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Duplij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equidistribution of realizable Steinitz classes for cyclic Kummer extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\ell$ be prime, and $K$ be a number field containing the $\ell$-th roots of unity. We use techniques from classical algebraic number theory to prove that the Steinitz classes of $\mathbb Z/\ell\mathbb Z$ extensions of $K$ are equidistributed among realizable classes in the ideal class group of $K$. For $\ell = 2$, this was proved by Kable and Wright using the deep theory of prehomogeneous vector spaces. Foster proved that Steinitz classes are uniformly distributed between realizable classes for tamely ramified elementary-$m$ extensions using the theory of Galois modules; our approach eliminates this tameness hypothesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12999v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brody Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On polynomial progressions via transference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove new cases of reasonable bounds for the polynomial Szemer\'{e}di theorem both over $\mathbb{Z}/N\mathbb{Z}$ with $N$ prime and over the integers. In particular, we prove reasonable bounds for Szemer\'edi's theorem in the integers with fixed polynomial common difference. That is, we prove for any polynomial $P(y)\in \mathbb{Z}[y]$ with $P(0) = 0$, that the largest subset $A\subseteq [N]$ avoiding the pattern \[x, x+P(y),\ldots, x+ kP(y)\] has size bounded by $\ll_{P,k}N(\log\log\log N)^{-\Omega_{P,k}(1)}.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13010v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Altman, Mehtaab Sawhney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-recurrence sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend previous work on anti-recurrence sequences of Kimberling and Moses, Zaslavsky, and Bosma et al. Kimberling and Moses have formulated several questions on these sequences, which can be combined into the meta-conjecture that anti-recurrence sequences are sums of linear progressions and automatic sequences. We solve this conjecture under a restriction on the linear form that generates the anti-recurrence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13337v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robbert Fokkink, Gandhar Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The exceptional set in the abc conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the size of the exceptional set in the $abc$ conjecture, improving on and simplifying work of Browning, Lichtman and Ter\"av\"ainen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13364v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Bernert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serre's question on thin sets in projective space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We answer a question of Serre on rational points of bounded height on projective thin sets in degree at least $4$. For degrees $2$ and $3$ we improve the known bounds in general. The focus is on thin sets of type II, namely corresponding to the images of ramified dominant quasi-finite covers of projective space, as thin sets of type I are already well understood via dimension growth results. We obtain a uniform affine variant of Serre's question which implies the projective case and for which the implicit constant is polynomial in the degree. We are able to avoid logarithmic factors when the degree is at least $5$ and we prove our results over any global field. To achieve this we adapt the determinant method to the case of weighted polynomials and we use recently obtained quadratic dependence on the degree when bounding rational points on curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13471v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tijs Buggenhout, Raf Cluckers, Tim Santens, Floris Vermeulen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weil polynomials of abelian varieties over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate Weil polynomials and their relationship with isogeny classes of abelian varieties over finite fields. We give a necessary condition for a degree 12 polynomial with integer coefficients to be a Weil polynomial. Moreover, we provide explicit criteria that determine when a Weil polynomial of degree 14 occurs as the characteristic polynomial of a Frobenius endomorphism acting on an abelian variety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13706v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Cerchia, Zeyu Liu, Diana Mocanu, Haodong Yao, Jing Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hecke reciprocity and class groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When the $C_3$-extensions $F = K(\sqrt[3]{n})$ of $K = \mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{-3})$ are ordered by the norm of $n \in O_K$, we show that the average size of $\mathrm{Cl}_F[2]$ is $3/2$, confirming a prediction of Cohen--Martinet. Over $\mathbb{Q}$, we prove that as $F$ varies over the pure cubic fields $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt[3]{n})$ that are tamely (resp.\ wildly) ramified at $3$, the average size of $\mathrm{Cl}_F[2]$ is $3/2$ (resp.\ $2$). This tame/wild dichotomy is not accounted for by the Cohen--Lenstra type heuristics in the literature.
  Underlying this phenomenon is a reciprocity law for the relative class group $\mathrm{Cl}_{F/K}[2]$ of odd degree extensions of number fields $F/K$. This leads to a random model for $\mathrm{Cl}_{F/K}[2]$ that recovers Malle's heuristics for $\mathrm{Cl}_{F/K}[2]$ in families of $K$-extensions with fixed Galois group. More generally, we formulate a heuristic for families with a fixed Galois $K$-group that explains the aberrant behavior in the family $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt[3]{n})$ and predicts similar behavior in other special families. The other main ingredient in our proof is the work of Alp\"oge--Bhargava--Shnidman, on the number of integral $G(\mathbb{Q})$-orbits in a $G$-invariant quadric with bounded invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13749v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ari Shnidman, Artane Siad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction theorems for coadmissible D-cap-modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a Riemann-Hilbert correspondence for Ardakov-Wadsley's coadmissible D-cap-modules and, more generally, for Bode's $\mathcal{C}$-complexes. More precisely, we show that any given $\mathcal{C}$-complex can be reconstructed out of its solutions. As a corollary, we find that slight modifications of the solution and de Rham functors introduced by the author are fully faithful on $\mathcal{C}$-complexes and, in particular, on coadmissible D-cap-modules. One of the many steps of our proof is the explicit computation of the continuous Galois cohomology of a certain decompletion of $B_{dR}^{+}$ which we call the positive overconvergent de Rham period ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12601v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finn Wiersig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounding crystalline torsion from \'etale torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13543v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we prove that given a smooth proper family over a $p$-adic ring of integers, one gets a control of its crystalline torsion in terms of its \'{e}tale torsion, the cohomological degree, and the ramification. Our technical core result is a boundedness result concerning annihilator ideals of $u^{\infty}$-torsion in Breuil--Kisin prismatic cohomology, which might be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13543v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofer Gabber, Shizhang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the $l$-fold Bailey Lemma and Mixed Mock Modular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1406.3394</link>
      <description>arXiv:1406.3394v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we present a method for constructing multiple-sum $q$-series for what is known as Mixed Mock Modular forms. We also present some multi-sum analogues of the Durfee identity, and discuss a construction of its combinatorial interpretation in terms of partitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1406.3394v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander E. Patkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solution and de Rham functors for D-cap-modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.13769v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We lay the groundwork for a Riemann-Hilbert correspondence for Ardakov-Wadsley's D-cap-modules by introducing corresponding solution and de Rham functors. Our constructions rely on Scholze's $p$-adic Hodge theory for rigid-analytic varieties, but we work over a decompletion of $B_{dR}^{+}$ which we call the positive overconvergent de Rham period ring. The main result of this article is the compatibility of our de Rham functor with Scholze's horizontal sections functor. This may be regarded as a generalisation of the classical non-Archimedean Cauchy Theorem, which roughly states that $p$-adic differential equations on unit discs have nonzero radius of convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.13769v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finn Wiersig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chai's conjectures on base change conductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01289v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The base change conductor is an invariant introduced by Chai which measures the failure of a semiabelian variety to have semiabelian reduction. We investigate the behaviour of this invariant in short exact sequences, as well as under duality and isogeny. Our results imply Chai's conjecture on the additivity of the base change conductor in short exact sequences, while also showing that a proposed generalisation of this conjecture fails. We use similar methods to show that the base change conductor is invariant under duality of Abelian varieties in equal positive characteristic (answering a question of Chai), as well as giving a new short proof of a formula due to Chai, Yu, and de Shalit which expresses the base change conductor of a torus in terms of its (rational) cocharacter module.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01289v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Otto Overkamp, Takashi Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supercongruences using modular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03301v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many generating series of combinatorially interesting numbers have the property that the sum of the terms of order $&lt;p$ at some suitable point is congruent to a zero of a zeta-function modulo infinitely many primes $p$. Surprisingly, very often these congruences turn out to hold modulo $p^2$ or even $p^3$. We call such congruences supercongruences and in the past 15 years an abundance of them have been discovered. In this paper we show that a large proportion of them can be explained by the use of modular functions and forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03301v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frits Beukers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metaplectic cusp forms and the large sieve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13151v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a power saving upper bound for the sum of Fourier coefficients $\rho_f(\cdot)$ of a fixed cubic metaplectic cusp form $f$ over primes. Our result is the cubic analogue of a celebrated 1990 Theorem of Duke and Iwaniec, and the cuspidal analogue of a Theorem due to the author and Radziwill for the bias in cubic Gauss sums.
  The proof has two main inputs, both of independent interest. Firstly, we prove a new large sieve estimate for a bilinear form whose kernel function is $\rho_f(\cdot)$. The proof of the bilinear estimate uses a number field version of circle method due to Browning and Vishe, Voronoi summation, and Gauss-Ramanujan sums. Secondly, we use Voronoi summation and the cubic large sieve of Heath-Brown to prove an estimate for a linear form involving $\rho_f(\cdot)$. Our linear estimate overcomes a bottleneck occurring at level of distribution $2/3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13151v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Dunn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-global principle for 11-isogenies of elliptic curves is true over quadratic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17602v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that the local-global principle of $11$-isogenies for elliptic curves over quadratic fields does not fail. This gives a positive answer to a conjecture by Banwait and Cremona. The proof is based on the determination of the set of quadratic points on the modular curve $X_{D_{10}}(11)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17602v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stevan Gajovi\'c, Jeroen Hanselman, Angelos Koutsianas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotational beta expansions and Schmidt games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04149v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider rotational beta expansions in dimensions 1, 2 and 4 and view them as expansions on real numbers, complex numbers, and quaternions, respectively. We give sufficient conditions on the parameters $\alpha, \beta \in (0,1)$ so that particular cylinder sets arising from the expansions are winning or losing Schmidt $(\alpha,\beta)$-game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04149v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Kaneko, Jonathan Caalim, Nathaniel Nollen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Jacobian Criterion for Artin $v$-stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.07495v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a generalization of the Jacobian criterion of Fargues-Scholze for spaces of sections of a smooth quasi-projective variety over the Fargues-Fontaine curve. Namely, we show how to use their criterion to deduce an analogue for spaces of sections of a smooth Artin stack over the (schematic) Fargues-Fontaine curve obtained by taking the stack quotient of a smooth quasi-projective variety by the action of a linear algebraic group. As an application, we show various moduli stacks appearing in the Fargues-Scholze geometric Langlands program are cohomologically smooth Artin $v$-stacks and compute their $\ell$-dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.07495v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linus Hamann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Number of Regular Integers Modulo $n$ and Its Significance to Cryptography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.02471v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give four alternative proofs to a formula on the number of non-congruent regular integers modulo $n$, where an integer $m$ is regular modulo $n$ if $m^2 x \equiv m \pmod{n}$ has a solution for $x$ in $\mathbb{Z}$. The formula, which expresses this number in terms of Euler totients of unitary divisors of $n$, is related to some recent variant of the RSA cryptosystem for regular integers modulo $n$, which is briefly outlined to underpin its significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.02471v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Dohmen, Mandy Lange-Geisler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the proportion of metric matroids whose Jacobians have nontrivial $\mathbf{p}$-torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.10172v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the proportion of metric matroids whose Jacobians have nontrivial $p$-torsion. We establish a correspondence between these Jacobians and the $\mathbb{F}_p$-rational points on configuration hypersurfaces, thereby relating their proportions. By counting points over finite fields, we prove that the proportion of these Jacobians is asymptotically equivalent to $1/p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.10172v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Ricardo Zapata Ceballos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The motivic Hecke algebra for PEL Shimura varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a motivic lift of the action of the Hecke algebra on the cohomology of PEL Shimura varieties $S_K$. To do so, when $S_K$ is associated with a reductive algebraic group $G$ and $V$ is a local system on $S_K$ coming from a $G$-representation, we define a motivic Hecke algebra $\mathcal{H}^M(G,K)$ as a natural sub-algebra of the endomorphism algebra, in the triangulated category of motives, of the constructible motive associated with $S_K$ and $V$. The algebra $\mathcal{H}^M(G,K)$ is such that realizations induce an epimorphism from it onto the classical Hecke algebra. We then consider Wildeshaus' theory of interior motives, along with the necessary hypotheses for it to be employed. Whenever those assumptions hold, one gets a Chow motive realizing to interior $V$-valued cohomology of $S_K$, equipped with an action of $\mathcal{H}^M(G,K)$ as an algebra of correspondences modulo rational equivalence. We give a list of known cases where this applies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19568v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Cavicchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristic cycle and wild Lefschetz theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11064v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By relying on a new approach to Lefschetz type questions based on Beilinson's singular support and Saito's characteristic cycle, we prove an instance of the wild Lefschetz theorem envisioned by Deligne. Our main tool are new finiteness results for the characteristic cycles of perverse sheaves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11064v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Hu, Jean-Baptiste Teyssier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic automorphisms of Markov-type surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Every complex surface of Markov type, i.e.\ the variety given by $x^2 + y^2 + z^2 + Exyz - Ax - By - Cz - D = 0$, has the symplectic density property and the Hamiltonian density property. We prove a singular symplectic version of the Anders{\'e}n--Lempert theorem for normal reduced affine complex varieties and apply it to describe the holomorphic symplectic automorphisms of a complex surface of Markov type. To this end, we also investigate the germs of vector fields in isolated singularities of type $A_k$ and $D_k$. Moreover, we show that any injective self-map of the set of ordered Markov triples can be realized by a holomorphic symplectic automorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15101v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael B. Andrist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Euler to AI: Unifying Formulas for Mathematical Constants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17533v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The constant $\pi$ has fascinated scholars throughout the centuries, inspiring numerous formulas for its evaluation, such as infinite sums and continued fractions. Despite their individual significance, many of the underlying connections among formulas remain unknown, missing unifying theories that could unveil deeper understanding. The absence of a unifying theory reflects a broader challenge across math and science: knowledge is typically accumulated through isolated discoveries, while deeper connections often remain hidden. In this work, we present an automated framework for the unification of mathematical formulas. Our system combines large language models (LLMs) for systematic formula harvesting, an LLM-code feedback loop for validation, and a novel symbolic algorithm for clustering and eventual unification. We demonstrate this methodology on the hallmark case of $\pi$, an ideal testing ground for symbolic unification. Applying this approach to 455,050 arXiv papers, we validate 407 distinct formulas for $\pi$ and prove relations between 381 (94%) of them, of which 188 (46%) can be derived from a single mathematical object$\unicode{x2014}$linking canonical formulas by Euler, Gauss, Brouncker, and newer ones from algorithmic discoveries by the Ramanujan Machine. Our method generalizes to other constants, including $e$, $\zeta(3)$, and Catalan's constant, demonstrating the potential of AI-assisted mathematics to uncover hidden structures and unify knowledge across domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17533v2</guid>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomer Raz, Michael Shalyt, Elyasheev Leibtag, Rotem Kalisch, Shachar Weinbaum, Yaron Hadad, Ido Kaminer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
