<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.NT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT</link>
    <description>math.NT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.NT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 02:48:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>New Types of Sturm bounds via $p$-adic transfer methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10240v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sturm's theorem states that a modular form with coefficients in $\mathbb{Z}$ or $\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}$ can only have an explicitly bounded order of vanishing at infinity. This result is one of the most powerful computational tools in the study of modular forms, and has widespread applications to congruences and other kinds of explicit calculations in mathematics and physics. In this paper, we formulate a new ``$p$-adic transfer method" that lifts Sturm-type bounds from one space to another using exclusively non-geometric inputs. As an application, we transfer the Sturm bounds for classical modular forms to the space of quasimodular forms of level one. These bounds are applicable uniformly for quasimodular forms with coefficients in $\mathbb{Z}$ or $\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}$, which extends the non-uniform results for $\mathbb{Z}/m\mathbb{Z}$ only which can be derived from classical theories. We also discuss the potential for future applications to other quasi- and mixed-weight modular objects, and perhaps even entirely non-modular objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10240v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Craig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision of Orbits on an Elliptic Surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10383v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $C$ be a smooth projective curve defined over $\Qbar$, let $\pi:\mathcal{E}\lra C$ be an elliptic surface and let $\sigma_{P_1},\sigma_{P_2},\sigma_{Q}$ be sections of $\pi$ (corresponding to points $P_1,P_2, Q$ of the generic fiber $E$ of $\mathcal{E}$). We obtain a precise characterization, expressed solely in terms of the dynamical relations between the points $P_1,P_2,Q$ with respect to the endomorphism ring of $E$, so that there exist infinitely many $\l\in C(\Qbar)$ with the property that for some nonzero integers $m_{1,\l},m_{2,\l}$, we have that $[m_{i,\l}](\sigma_{{P_{i}}}(\l))=\sigma_{Q}(\l)$ (for $i=1,2$) on the smooth fiber $E_\l$ of $\mathcal{E}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10383v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dragos Ghioca, Negin Shadgar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Results for Cyclotomic Multiple Hurwitz Zeta Values via Contour Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper provides a systematic study of symmetry properties for cyclotomic multiple Hurwitz zeta values with multiple variables and parameters by applying the methods of contour integration and the residue theorem. The main contributions are the derivation of explicit symmetry formulas for cyclotomic multiple (Hurwitz) zeta values, which are obtained directly through analytic residue calculations, without reliance on algebraic regularization. As a concrete application, we deduce analogous symmetry theorems for cyclotomic multiple zeta values and cyclotomic multiple $t$-values. The results extend and complement recent symmetry investigations by Charlton and Hoffman, offering completely explicit and regularization-free formulas in the convergent setting. Moreover, the results of this paper can be used to prove the symmetry conjecture for cyclotomic multiple Hurwitz zeta values with multiple variables and a single parameter. Furthermore, several illustrative corollaries and examples are included, and an open problem concerning possible extensions to other variants of multiple zeta values is posed at the conclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10391v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ce Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An improved algorithm for checking the Collatz conjecture for all n &lt; 2^N</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe a new algorithm for verifying the Collatz conjecture for all n &lt; 2^N for some fixed N. The algorithm takes less than twice as long to verify convergence for all n &lt; 2^{N+1} as it does to verify convergence for all n &lt; 2^N.
  We also discuss verification of the analogue of the Collatz conjecture for negative numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10466v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vigleik Angeltveit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eisenstein-prime Obstruction Sieve for Monogenicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alp\"oge--Bhargava--Shnidman showed that even a strengthened \emph{no local obstruction} condition for monogenicity does not force a global power integral basis: in the full spaces of cubic and quartic fields, a positive proportion are non-monogenic yet satisfy this ABS fixed-sign condition. This raises a natural family-level question: does the same phenomenon persist inside one-parameter families, where the local structure varies in a highly constrained way?
  In this paper we answer this in the negative for the pure fields $K_m=\mathbb Q(\alpha)$ with $\alpha^n=m$ ($n\ge 4$) and $m$ square-free. Writing $g(m)=[\mathcal O_{K_m}:\mathbb Z[\alpha]]$, we prove that the set of square-free $m$ for which $g(m)&gt;1$ but $K_m$ has no ABS local obstruction has natural density $0$. Consequently, in the pure family monogenicity and $\alpha$--monogenicity have the same natural density. The proof isolates a reusable mechanism, which we call the Eisenstein-prime obstruction sieve. The argument is packaged in an abstract template and transfers to other Eisenstein parameter families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10488v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khai-Hoan Nguyen-Dang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inequalities involving polynomials and quasimodular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study inequalities involving polynomials and quasimodular forms. More precisely, we focus on the monotonicity of the functions of the form $t \mapsto t^m F(it)$ where $F$ is a quasimodular form and $m &gt; 0$. As an application, we construct infinitely many positive quasimodular forms of level $&gt; 1$. We also give alternative proofs of modular form inequalities used in the proof of optimality of Leech lattice packing and universal optimality of the lattice by Cohn, Kumar, Miller, Radchenko, and Viazovska.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10536v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seewoo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Siegel modular forms associated to Weil representations: $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathbb{R}) \&amp; \operatorname{GL}_2(\mathbb{R})$ cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate explicit modular forms of weights $1/2$ and $3/2$-classical, minus, and fermionic theta series-arising from the classical Weil representation associated to $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathbb{R})$ via the $2$-cocycles of Rao, Kudla, Perrin, Lion--Vergne and Satake--Takase. We reorganize these forms using (tensor) induction, and subsequently extend our study to the similitude group $\operatorname{GL}_2(\mathbb{R})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10769v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun-Hui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the infinitude of elliptic curves over a number field with prescribed small rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For any number field $K$ and integer $0\leq r \leq 4$, we prove that there are infinitely many elliptic curves over $K$ of rank $r$. Our elliptic curves are obtained by specializing well-chosen nonisotrivial elliptic curves over the function field $K(T)$. We use a result of Kai, which generalizes work of Green, Tao and Ziegler to number fields, to choose our specializations so that we have control over the bad primes and can perform a $2$-descent to compute ranks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10865v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Zywina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational Points in Hyperbolic Regions and Multiplicative Diophantine Approximation on Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the convergence theory of multiplicative Diophantine approximation for all non-degenerate, smooth manifolds. We also settle said convergence theory for all affine subspaces satisfying a highly generic and essentially optimal Diophantine condition. This answers a question of Beresnevich and Velani from 2005, while simultaneously sharpening results of Kleinbock and Margulis on the strong extremality of non-degenerate manifolds, and of Kleinbock on the strong extremality of affine subspaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11012v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Chow, Rajula Srivastava, Niclas Technau, Han Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Diophantine approximation on manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a weighted simultaneous Khintchine-type theorem, both convergence and divergence, for all nondegenerate manifolds, which answers a problem posed in [Math. Ann., 337(4):769-796, 2007]. This extends the main results of [Acta Math., 231:1-30, 2023] and [Ann. of Math. (2), 175(1):187-235, 2012] in the weighted set-up. As a by-product of our method, we also obtain a multiplicative Khintchine-type convergence theorem for all nondegenerate manifolds, which is a simultaneous analogue of the celebrated result of Bernik, Kleinbock, and Margulis for dual approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11045v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Beresnevich, Shreyasi Datta, Lei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Totally decomposable algebras with involution and R-triviality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the group of proper projective similitudes of a totally decomposable algebra with involution of the first kind over a field of characteristic different from 2 is R-trivial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10302v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Archita, Karim Johannes Becher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform bound on common periodic points for families of regular plane polynomial automorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given two one-dimensional families $f$ and $g$ of regular plane polynomial automorphisms parameterised by an algebraic curve $B$, all defined over some number field $K$, such that one of them is dissipative, we prove that at any parameter $b\in B(\mathbb{C})$, either $f_b$ and $g_b$ share a common iterate, or the number of their common periodic points $\mathrm{Per}(f_b) \cap \mathrm{Per}(g_b)$ is bounded by a uniform constant $D$ (independent of the parameter $b$). We thus extend a result of Mavraki and Schmidt for rational maps to our setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10310v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Abboud, Yugang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admissibility of H\"ormander--Bernhardsson extremal zeros</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10497v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\varphi$ be the H\"ormander--Bernhardsson extremal function, and let $(\pm\tau_n)_{n\ge1}$ be its real zeros. Using the recent analytic description of the zero set ${\tau_n}$, we prove that the squared zeros $\lambda_n=\tau_n^{2}$ form an admissible sequence in the sense of Quine--Heydari--Song: the heat trace $\Theta(t)=\sum_{n\ge1}e^{-\lambda_n t}$ has a full $t\to0^{+}$ expansion in pure powers of $t^{1/2}$. The proof is based on an analytic normal form \[ \lambda_n=\Bigl(n+\tfrac12\Bigr)^2+q!\Bigl(\Bigl(n+\tfrac12\Bigr)^{-2}\Bigr), \] a uniform Taylor expansion in $t$, and a Mellin--Hurwitz zeta analysis of the resulting weighted Gaussian sums. As applications we obtain meromorphic continuation and special-value information for the associated spectral zeta function and zeta-regularized product, sharp large-parameter asymptotics for the canonical product $\prod_{n}(1+z/\lambda_n)$. In particular, we deduce the conjecture by Bondarenko--Ortega-Cerd\`a--Radchenko--Seip for the special values of the Dirichlet-type series attached to $\varphi$. We also establish a parity dichotomy: sequences $(\tau_n^m)$ are QHS--admissible for even $m$, while for odd $m$ a nonzero $t\log t$ term obstructs admissibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10497v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khai-Hoan Nguyen-Dang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Touchard's Identity: Generalizations and Related Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10558v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting with a known polynomial identity, we derive two generalizations of Touchard's identity concerning Catalan numbers; one obtained using the Beta function and the other via a connection with Stirling numbers of the second kind. We subsequently establish several new combinatorial identities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10558v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunle Adegoke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Golombic and Levine sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10992v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate and generalise Levine sequences like A011784, A061892 and A061894 and develop an algebraic theory for them. We thereby also cover other fast growing sequences like A014644, which we call golombic due to their strong ties with Golomb's sequence A001462.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10992v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan Claes, Roland Miyamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divided powers on abelian varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11135v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the existence of divided powers in \'etale Chow groups of abelian varieties over a separably closed field, and hence of an integral lift of the Fourier transform, away from the characteristic and up to $2$-torsion. The method is to lift the Deninger-Murre Chow-K\"unneth projectors to integral ones, and draw consequences. Several techniques used here are new.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11135v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Kahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the number of binary quadratic forms having discriminant $1-4p$, $p$ prime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.06559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2011.06559v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we obtain an asymptotic formula for the number of $\operatorname{SL}_2(\mathbb{Z})$-equivalence classes of positive definite binary quadratic forms over $\bZ$ having bounded discriminant $\Delta = 1-4p$, with $p$ a prime. We also give a random Euler product model for the distribution of Hurwitz class numbers, which is supported by our formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2011.06559v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alison Beth Miller, Stanley Yao Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congruence properties modulo prime powers for a class of partition functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03663v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $p$ be prime, and let $p_{[1,p]}(n)$ denote the function whose generating function is $\prod (1-q^n)^{-1}(1 - q^{pn})^{-1}$. This function and its generalizations $p_{[c^{\ell}, d^m]}(n)$ are the subject of study in several recent papers. Let $\ell\geq 5$, let $j\geq 1$, and let $p \in \{2, 3, 5\}$. In this paper, we prove that the generating function for $p_{[1, p]}(n)$ in the progression $\beta_{p, \ell, j}$ modulo $\ell^j$ with $24\beta_{p, \ell, j} \equiv p + 1 \pmod{\ell^j}$ lies in a Hecke-invariant subspace of type $\{\eta(Dz)\eta(Dpz)F(Dz) : F(z) \in M_{s}(\Gamma_0(p), \chi)\}$ for suitable $D\geq 1$, $s\geq 0$, and character~$\chi$. When $p\in \{2, 3, 5\}$, we use the Hecke-invariance of these subspaces proved in [21] to prove, for distinct primes $\ell$ and $m\geq 5$ and $j\geq 1$, congruences of the form \[ p_{[1, p]}\left(\frac{\ell^jm^k n + 1}{D}\right)\equiv 0 \pmod{\ell^j} \] for all $n\geq 1$ with $m\nmid n$, where $k$ is explicitly computable and depends on the forms in the invariant subspace. Our proofs require adapting and extending analogous level one results on $p(n)$ in [1] and [22] to level $p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03663v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Boylan,  Swati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indices of nilpotency in certain spaces of modular forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24182v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the index of nilpotency relative to certain Hecke operators in spaces of modular forms with integer weight and level $N$ with integer coefficients modulo primes $p$ for $(p, N) \in \{(3, 1), (5, 1), (7, 1), (3, 4)\}$. In these settings, we prove upper bounds on certain indices of nilpotency. As an application of our bounds, we prove infinite families of congruences for $p^t$-core partition functions modulo $p$ for $p\in \{3, 5, 7\}$ and $t\geq 1$, and we prove an infinite family of congruences modulo $3$ for the $r$th power partition function, $p_r(n)$, when $r = 12k$ with $\gcd(k,6) = 1$. We also include conjectures on a function which quantifies degree lowering on powers of the Delta function by the relevant Hecke operators in these settings, and on the index of nilpotency relative to a modification of this degree-lowering function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24182v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Boylan,  Swati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalization of Ramanujan's formula for sums of half-integer powers of consecutive integers via formal Bernoulli series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05961v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Faulhaber's formula expresses the sum of the first $n$ positive integers, each raised to an integer power $p\geq 0$, as a polynomial in $n$ of degree $p+1$. Ramanujan expressed this sum for $p\in\{\frac12,\frac32,\frac52,\frac72\}$ as the sum of a polynomial in $\sqrt{n}$ and a certain infinite series. In the present work, we explore the connection to Bernoulli polynomials, and by generalizing those to formal series, we extend the Ramanujan result to all positive half-integers $p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05961v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11139-025-01259-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Ramanujan Journal 68 (2025), 106</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Max A. Alekseyev, Rafael Gonzalez, Keryn Loor, Aviad Susman, Cesar Valverde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the densities of covering numbers and abundant numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23041v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the densities of the sets of abundant numbers and of covering numbers, integers $n$ for which there exists a distinct covering system where every modulus divides $n$. We establish that the set $\mathcal{C}$ of covering numbers possesses a natural density $d(\mathcal{C})$ and prove that $0.103230 &lt; d(\mathcal{C}) &lt; 0.103398.$ Our approach adapts methods developed by Behrend and Del\'eglise for bounding the density of abundant numbers, by introducing a function $c(n)$ that measures how close an integer $n$ is to being a covering number with the property that $c(n) \leq h(n) = \sigma(n)/n$. However, computing $d(\mathcal{C})$ to three decimal digits requires some new ideas to simplify the computations. As a byproduct of our methods, we obtain significantly improved bounds for $d(\mathcal{A})$, the density of abundant numbers, namely $0.247619608 &lt; d(\mathcal{A}) &lt; 0.247619658$. We also show the count of primitive covering numbers up to $x$ is $O\left( x\exp\left(\left(-\tfrac{1}{2\sqrt{\log 2}} + \epsilon\right)\sqrt{\log x} \log \log x\right)\right)$, which is substantially smaller than the corresponding bound for primitive abundant numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23041v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan McNew, Jai Setty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wieferich primes in number fields and the conjectures of Ankeny--Artin--Chowla and Mordell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08472v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a prime $p\equiv 1 \,(\bmod{4})$, let \[ \varepsilon = \frac{1}{2}\left( t + u\sqrt{p}\right) \] be the fundamental unit of the real quadratic field $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{p})$. In 1951, N. Ankeny, E. Artin, and S. Chowla asked whether $p$ can divide $u$. They suggested that this can never happen and this has since been called the Ankeny--Artin--Chowla (AAC) conjecture.
  We show that if $\mathfrak{p}$ is the prime above $p$ in $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{p})$, then the AAC conjecture is false if and only if \[ \varepsilon^{p-1} \equiv 1\, (\bmod{\mathfrak{p}^2}). \] Thus, the AAC conjecture is related to the existence of number field analogues of Wieferich primes. Therefore, in the second part of this paper, we investigate the infinitude of Wieferich primes in number fields. Subject to Masser's $abc$-conjecture for number fields, we prove that for any fixed $\alpha\in \mathcal{O}_K\setminus\{0\}$ that is not a root of unity, there are infinitely many primes ideals $\mathfrak{p}\subseteq \mathcal{O}_K$ for which \[ \alpha^{N(\mathfrak{p})-1} \not\equiv 1\, (\bmod{\mathfrak{p}^2}). \] Additionally, we show under the weaker assumption that there are finitely many base-$\alpha$ super-Wieferich primes, and that there are infinitely many base-$\alpha$ non-Wieferich primes. In both cases, we obtain the lower bound
  \[ \#\left\{\text{prime ideals } \mathfrak{p} : N(\mathfrak{p})\leq x \text{ and } \alpha^{N(\mathfrak{p})-1}\not\equiv 1 \,(\bmod{\mathfrak{p}^2})\right\} \gg_{K, \alpha, \varepsilon} \frac{\log x}{\log\log x} \]
  as $x\to \infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08472v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nic Fellini, M. Ram Murty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curves of genus two with maps of every degree to a fixed elliptic curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.19050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that up to isomorphism there are exactly twenty pairs $(C,E)$, where $C$ is a genus-$2$ curve over ${\mathbf C}$, where $E$ is an elliptic curve over ${\mathbf C}$, and where for every integer $n&gt;1$ there is a map of degree $n$ from $C$ to $E$. We also show that the intersection of the Humbert surfaces $H_{n^2}$, for $n$ ranging from 2 to 1811, is empty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.19050v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Everett W. Howe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A motivic Fundamental Lemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12195v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we prove motivic versions of the Langlands-Shelstad Fundamental Lemma and Ng\^o's Geometric Stabilization. To achieve this, we follow the strategy from the recent proof by Groechenig, Wyss and Ziegler which avoided the use of perverse sheaves using instead $p$-adic integration and Tate duality. We make a key use of a construction of Denef and Loeser which assigns a virtual motive to any definable set in the theory of pseudo-finite fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12195v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Forey, Fran\c{c}ois Loeser, Dimitri Wyss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$q$-analogues of Wilf-Zeilberger seeds and Ramanujan $1/\pi^k$-formulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04555v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop the notion of Wilf-Zeilberger seeds as a powerful framework for generating WZ-pairs and for lifting classical hypergeometric identities to the $q$-setting. As an application, we systematically obtain a large family of $q$-analogues of Ramanujan-type $1/\pi^k$ formulas, extending a literature previously limited to sporadic examples. While the majority of these $q$-analogues are modular, we also uncover several curious instances of mock modularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04555v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kam Cheong Au</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hensel's lemma for the norm principle for spinor groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15737v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a complete discretely valued field with residue field $k$ with $char \ k \ne 2$. Assuming that the norm principle holds for spinor groups $Spin(\mathfrak{h})$ for every regular skew-hermitian form $\mathfrak{h}$ over every quaternion algebra $\mathfrak{D}$ (with respect to the canonical involution on $\mathfrak{D}$) defined over any finite extension of $k$, we show that the norm principle holds for spinor groups $Spin(h)$ for every regular skew-hermitian form $h$ over every quaternion algebra $D$ (with respect to the canonical involution on $D$) defined over $K$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15737v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Soofiani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morphisms on the modular curve $X_0(p)$ and degree $6$ points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21166v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime. We study non-constant morphisms $f:X_0(p)_\mathbb \to Y$, where $Y/\mathbb Q$ is a curve of genus $\geq 2$. We prove that for $p&lt;3000$ such an $f$ of degree $d&gt;1$ must be isomorphic to the quotient map $X_0(p)\to X_0^+(p)$. Supported by computational and theoretical evidence, we also conjecture that this is true for all primes $p$.
  These results allow us to classify all points of degree $\leq 25$ on $X_0(p)$ that come from a map to some curve of genus $\geq 2$. As an application, we were able to determine all curves $X_0(p)$ with infinitely many points of degree $6$ over $\mathbb Q$ except for $p=193$, continuing the previous results on small degree points on $X_0(N)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21166v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maarten Derickx, Petar Orli\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
