<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY</link>
    <description>eess.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 02:40:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>RIS-Aided Monitoring With Cooperative Jamming: Design and Performance Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS) aided wireless surveillance system. In this system, a monitor not only receives signal from suspicious transmitter via a RIS-enhanced legitimate surveillance (LS) link but also simultaneously takes control of multiple jammers to degrade the quality of received suspicious signal. Under this setup, to enhance monitoring performance requires improvements of both the received signal quality at the monitor and the cooperative jamming (CJ). Considering that the surveillance system is aided by one RIS, whose phase shift optimization involves both channel state information (CSI) of the LS and CJ links, we utilize partial CSI to alleviate the CSI acquisition burden in our design. We propose two RIS-aided monitoring schemes with optimal jammer selection (OJS), and derive their closed-form expressions of surveillance success probability (SSP), respectively. Furthermore, we consider RIS-aided monitoring schemes with random jammer selection as corresponding benchmarks. Thereafter, we analyze special cases where the jammers are using power control to avoid being found, making it appears like passive monitoring. Also, the effect of RIS is highlighted by considering asymptotically large number of RIS elements. Numerical results verify that the proposed OJS strategy further enhances the RIS-aided monitoring performance compared with non-jammer-selection RISLR and RISCR schemes, where the superiority comes at the cost of CSI knowledge and becomes marginal in the region of high jamming power. In addition, the RISLO shows surveillance performance advantage overRISCOwhen the suspicious power is low or when the number of RIS elements is large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12473v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuying Lin, Yulong Zou, Zhiyang Li, Eduard E. Bahingayi, Le-Nam Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Intrinsic State Variable in Fundamental Lemma and Its Use in Stability Design for Data-based Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the data-based setting, analysis and control design of dynamical systems using measured data are typically based on overlapping trajectory segments of the input and output variables. This could lead to complex designs because the system internal dynamics, which is typically reflected by the system state variable, is unavailable. In this paper, we will show that the coefficient vector in a modified version of Willems' fundamental lemma is an intrinsic and observable state variable for the system behavior. This argument evolves from the behavioral framework without the requirement of prior knowledge on the causality among system variables or any predefined representation structure (e.g., a state space representation). Such a view allows for the construction of a state map based on the fundamental lemma, bridging the trajectory space and the state space. The state property of the coefficient vector allows for a simple stability design approach using memoryless quadratic functions of it as Lyapunov functions, from which the control action for each step can be explicitly constructed. Using the coefficient vector as a state variable could see wide applications in the analysis and control design of dynamical systems including directions beyond the discussions in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12626v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitao Yan, Jie Bao, Biao Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Urban Priority Pass: Fair Signalized Intersection Management Accounting For Passenger Needs Through Prioritization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past few decades, efforts of road traffic management and practice have predominantly focused on maximizing system efficiency and mitigating congestion from a system perspective. This efficiency-driven approach implies the equal treatment of all vehicles, which often overlooks individual user experiences, broader social impacts, and the fact that users are heterogeneous in their urgency and experience different costs when being delayed. Existing strategies to account for the differences in needs of users in traffic management cover dedicated transit lanes, prioritization of emergency vehicles, transit signal prioritization, and economic instruments. Even though they are the major bottleneck for traffic in cities, no dedicated instrument that enables prioritization of individual drivers at intersections. The Priority Pass is a reservation-based, economic controller that expedites entitled vehicles at signalized intersections, without causing arbitrary delays for not-entitled vehicles and without affecting transportation efficiency de trop. The prioritization of vulnerable road users, emergency vehicles, commercial taxi and delivery drivers, or urgent individuals can enhance road safety, and achieve social, environmental, and economic goals. A case study in Manhattan demonstrates the feasibility of individual prioritization (up to 40\% delay decrease), and quantifies the potential of the Priority Pass to gain social welfare benefits for the people. A market for prioritization could generate up to 1 million \$ in daily revenues for Manhattan, and equitably allocate delay reductions to those in need, rather than those with a high income.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12769v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Riehl, Anastasios Kouvelas, Michail Makridis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbit-Attitude Predictive Control in the Vicinity of Asteroids with In Situ Gravity Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12830v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an integrated model-learning predictive control scheme for spacecraft orbit-attitude station-keeping in the vicinity of asteroids. The orbiting probe relies on optical and laser navigation while attitude measurements are provided by star trackers and gyroscopes. The asteroid gravity field inhomogeneities are assumed to be unknown a priori. The state and gravity model parameters are estimated simultaneously using an unscented Kalman filter. The proposed gravity model identification enables the application of a learning-based predictive control methodology. The predictive control allows for a high degree of accuracy because the predicted model is progressively identified in situ. Consequently, the tracking errors decrease over time as the model accuracy increases. Finally, a constellation mission concept is analyzed in order to speed up the model identification process. Numerical results are shown and discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12830v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2514/1.G005572</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Guidance, Control and Dynamics, Volume 45, Number 2, February 2022</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julio C. Sanchez, Rafael Vazquez, James D. Biggs, Franco Bernelli-Zazzera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A coupled FE-BE multi-scale method for the dynamics of jointed structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The damping of built-up structures stems largely from the microscopic dry frictional interactions in the contact interfaces. The accurate prediction of friction damping has been an important scientific aim of the past several decades. Recent research indicates that very good agreement with vibration measurements is to be expected if the actual contact surface topography is sufficiently well known and finely resolved, and frictional-unilateral interactions are modeled in terms of the Coulomb-Signorini conditions. Resolving all relevant length scales in one finite element model leads to enormous or even prohibitive computation effort and regularization of the set-valued contact laws might be needed to ensure numerical stability. In this work, we propose a multi-scale approach: The stress and deformation field in the contact region is modeled using elastic half-space theory, implemented on a regular and fine grid of boundary elements (BE), so that the compliance matrix can be expressed in closed form. The vibration behavior of the remaining region is described using a relatively coarse finite element (FE) model, which is further reduced via component mode synthesis. The two models are coupled by enforcing compatibility and equilibrium conditions in the far field. The set-valued Coulomb-Signorini conditions are enforced robustly and efficiently using a projected over-relaxation scheme in conjunction with an appropriate active-set strategy. For the S4 beam benchmark, very good agreement with regard to the amplitude-dependent frequency and damping ratio of the first few modes is achieved, while the computation effort is reduced by several orders of magnitude compared to the full-FE reference. The proposed multi-scale method permits a very fine resolution of the contact surface topography without suffering from numerical instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12833v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hendrik D. Linder, Johann Gross, Malte Krack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-loop robust control of long-term diabetes progression via physical activity management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large clinical evidence acknowledges the crucial role played by physical activity in delaying the progression of type-2 diabetes. However, the literature lacks control approaches that leverage exercise for type-2 diabetes control and more in general lacks a quantitative assessment of medical guidelines on the recommended amount of physical activity to be performed, mainly due to the absence of mathematical models that suitably estimate its benefits on diabetes progression. In this work, in order to provide a control-theoretical formulation of the exercise, we design a feedback law in terms of recommended physical activity, following a model predictive control approach, based on a widespread compact diabetes progression model, suitably modified to properly account for the long-term effect of the exercise. Moreover we illustrate how the proposed approach proves to show reliable robustness properties with respect to initial conditions and parameter perturbations, which may be used to reflect inter-patient variability. Results are encouraging in view of the validation of the control law on comprehensive high-dimensional models of diabetes progression, with the aim of translating the prediction of the controller into reasonable recommendations and to quantitatively support medical decision-making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12892v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierluigi Francesco De Paola, Alessandro Borri, Fabrizio Dabbene, Pasquale Palumbo, Alessia Paglialonga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Optimize Joint Chance-constrained Power Dispatch Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ever-increasing integration of stochastic renewable energy sources into power systems operation is making the supply-demand balance more challenging. While joint chance-constrained methods are equipped to model these complexities and uncertainties, solving these models using the traditional iterative solvers is time-consuming and can hinder real-time implementation. To overcome the shortcomings of today's solvers, we propose a fast, scalable, and explainable machine learning-based optimization proxy. Our solution, called Learning to Optimize the Optimization of Joint Chance-Constrained Problems (LOOP-JCCP), is iteration-free and solves the underlying problem in a single-shot. Our model uses a polyhedral reformulation of the original problem to manage constraint violations and ensure solution feasibility across various scenarios through customizable probability settings. To this end, we build on our recent deterministic solution (LOOP-LC 2.0) by incorporating a set aggregator module to handle uncertain sample sets of varying sizes and complexities. Our results verify the feasibility of our near-optimal solutions for joint chance-constrained power dispatch scenarios. Additionally, our feasibility guarantees increase the transparency and interpretability of our method, which is essential for operators to trust the outcomes. We showcase the effectiveness of our model in solving the stochastic energy management problem of Virtual Power Plants (VPPs). Our numerical findings complement our theoretical justifications and demonstrate great flexibility in parameter tuning, adaptability to diverse datasets, and increased computational speed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12902v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meiyi Li, Javad Mohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set-point control and local stability for flat nonlinear systems using model-following control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the set-point control problem for nonlinear systems with flat output that are subject to perturbations. The nonlinear dynamics as well as the perturbations are locally Lipschitz. We apply the model-following control (MFC) approach which consists of a model control loop (MCL) for a feedforward generation and a process control loop (PCL) that compensates the perturbations using high-gain feedback. We analyse the resulting closed-loop system and discuss its relation to a standard flatness-based high-gain approach. In particular we analyse the estimated region of attraction provided by a quadratic Lyapunov function. A case study illustrates the approach and quantifies the region of attraction obtained for each control approach. Using the initial condition of the model control loop as tuning parameter for the MFC design, provides that a significantly larger region of attraction can be guaranteed compared to a conventional single-loop high-gain design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12913v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Willkomm, Kai Wulff, Johann Reger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A control system framework for counterfactuals: an optimization based approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Counterfactuals are a concept inherited from the field of logic and in general attain to the existence of causal relations between sentences or events. In particular, this concept has been introduced also in the context of interpretability in artificial intelligence, where counterfactuals refer to the minimum change to the feature values that changes the prediction of a classification model. The artificial intelligence framework of counterfactuals is mostly focused on machine learning approaches, typically neglecting the physics of the variables that determine a change in class. However, a theoretical formulation of counterfactuals in a control system framework - i.e., able to account for the mechanisms underlying a change in class - is lacking. To fill this gap, in this work we propose an original control system, physics-informed, theoretical foundation for counterfactuals, by means of the formulation of an optimal control problem. We apply the proposed methodology to a general glucose-insulin regulation model and results appear promising and pave the way to the possible integration with artificial intelligence techniques, with the aim of feeding machine learning models with the physics knowledge acquired through the system framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12914v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierluigi Francesco De Paola, Jared Miller, Alessandro Borri, Alessia Paglialonga, Fabrizio Dabbene</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory tracking model-following control using Lyapunov redesign with output time-derivatives to compensate unmatched uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study trajectory tracking for flat nonlinear systems with unmatched uncertainties using the model-following control (MFC) architecture. We apply state feedback linearisation control for the process and propose a simplified implementation of the model control loop which results in a simple model in Brunovsky-form that represents the nominal feedback linearised dynamics of the nonlinear process. To compensate possibly unmatched model uncertainties, we employ Lyapunov redesign with numeric derivatives of the output. It turns out that for a special initialisation of the model, the MFC reduces to a single-loop control design. We illustrate our results by a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12916v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niclas Tietze, Kai Wulff, Johann Reger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lipschitz Safe Bayesian Optimization for Automotive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controller tuning is a labor-intensive process that requires human intervention and expert knowledge. Bayesian optimization has been applied successfully in different fields to automate this process. However, when tuning on hardware, such as in automotive applications, strict safety requirements often arise. To obtain safety guarantees, many existing safe Bayesian optimization methods rely on assumptions that are hard to verify in practice. This leads to the use of unjustified heuristics in many applications, which invalidates the theoretical safety guarantees. Furthermore, applications often require multiple safety constraints to be satisfied simultaneously. Building on recently proposed Lipschitz-only safe Bayesian optimization, we develop an algorithm that relies on readily interpretable assumptions and satisfies multiple safety constraints at the same time. We apply this algorithm to the problem of automatically tuning a trajectory-tracking controller of a self-driving car. Results both from simulations and an actual test vehicle underline the algorithm's ability to learn tracking controllers without leaving the track or violating any other safety constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12969v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Menn, Pietro Pelizzari, Michael Fleps-Dezasse, Sebastian Trimpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning-based Distributed Model Predictive Control using Multi-Agent Bayesian Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12989v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a fusion of Multi-agent Bayesian Optimization (MABO) and Distributed Model Predictive Control (DMPC) aiming at learning the DMPC schemes with imperfect local models in a distributed manner. In the proposed method, we use a dual-decomposition method for a DMPC and leverage an Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM)-based MABO for coordinated learning of the parameterized DMPC scheme to improve the closed-loop performance of the local MPC schemes even if their models cannot capture the real multi-agent system perfectly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12989v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Nejatbakhsh Esfahani, Kai Liu, Javad Mohammadpour Velni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>European Energy Vision 2060: Charting Diverse Pathways for Europe's Energy Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Europe is warming at the fastest rate of all continents, experiencing a temperature increase of about 1{\deg}C higher than the corresponding global increase. Aiming to be the first climate-neutral continent by 2050 under the European Green Deal, Europe requires an in-depth understanding of the potential energy transition pathways. In this paper, we develop four qualitative long-term scenarios covering the European energy landscape, considering key uncertainty pillars -- categorized under social, technological, economic, political, and geopolitical aspects. First, we place the scenarios in a three-dimensional space defined by Social dynamics, Innovation, and Geopolitical instabilities. These scenarios are brought to life by defining their narratives and focus areas according to their location in this three-dimensional space. The scenarios envision diverse futures and include distinct features. The EU Trinity scenario pictures how internal divisions among EU member states, in the context of global geopolitical instability, affect the EU climate targets. The REPowerEU++ scenario outlines the steps needed for a self-sufficient, independent European energy system by 2050. The Go RES scenario examines the feasibility of achieving carbon neutrality earlier than 2050 given favourable uncertain factors. The NECP Essentials scenario extends current national energy and climate plans until 2060 to assess their role in realizing climate neutrality. The scenarios are extended by incorporating policies and economic factors and detailed in a Qualitative to Quantitative (Q2Q) matrix, linking narratives to quantification. Finally, two scenarios are quantified to illustrate the quantification process. All the scenarios are in the process of being quantified and will be openly available and reusable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12993v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mostafa Barani, Konstantin L\"offler, Pedro Crespo del Granado, Nikita Moskalenko, Evangelos Panos, Franziska M. Hoffart, Christian von Hirschhausen, Maria Kannavou, Hans Auer, Karlo Hainsch, Tatiana Gonz\'alez Grand\'on, Siri Mathisen, Asgeir Tomasgard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication-Efficient Distributed Kalman Filtering using ADMM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of optimal linear filtering in a network of local estimators, commonly referred to as distributed Kalman filtering (DKF). The DKF problem is formulated within a distributed optimization framework, where coupling constraints require the exchange of local state and covariance updates between neighboring nodes to achieve consensus. To address these constraints, the problem is transformed into an unconstrained optimization form using the augmented Lagrangian method. The distributed alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) is then applied to derive update steps that achieve the desired performance while exchanging only the primal variables. Notably, the proposed method enhances communication efficiency by eliminating the need for dual variable exchange. We show that the design parameters depend on the maximum eigenvalue of the network's Laplacian matrix, yielding a significantly tighter bound compared to existing results. A rigorous convergence analysis is provided, proving that the state estimates converge to the true state and that the covariance matrices across all local estimators converge to a globally optimal solution. Numerical results are presented to validate the efficacy of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13003v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Iqbal, Kundan Kumar, Simo S\"arkk\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control-ITRA: Controlling the Behavior of a Driving Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12408v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating realistic driving behavior is crucial for developing and testing autonomous systems in complex traffic environments. Equally important is the ability to control the behavior of simulated agents to tailor scenarios to specific research needs and safety considerations. This paper extends the general-purpose multi-agent driving behavior model ITRA (Scibior et al., 2021), by introducing a method called Control-ITRA to influence agent behavior through waypoint assignment and target speed modulation. By conditioning agents on these two aspects, we provide a mechanism for them to adhere to specific trajectories and indirectly adjust their aggressiveness. We compare different approaches for integrating these conditions during training and demonstrate that our method can generate controllable, infraction-free trajectories while preserving realism in both seen and unseen locations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12408v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasileios Lioutas, Adam Scibior, Matthew Niedoba, Berend Zwartsenberg, Frank Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning Constrained Beam Search for Parameter Optimization of Paper Drying Under Flexible Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12542v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Existing approaches to enforcing design constraints in Reinforcement Learning (RL) applications often rely on training-time penalties in the reward function or training/inference-time invalid action masking, but these methods either cannot be modified after training, or are limited in the types of constraints that can be implemented. To address this limitation, we propose Reinforcement Learning Constrained Beam Search (RLCBS) for inference-time refinement in combinatorial optimization problems. This method respects flexible, inference-time constraints that support exclusion of invalid actions and forced inclusion of desired actions, and employs beam search to maximize sequence probability for more sensible constraint incorporation. RLCBS is extensible to RL-based planning and optimization problems that do not require real-time solution, and we apply the method to optimize process parameters for a novel modular testbed for paper drying. An RL agent is trained to minimize energy consumption across varying machine speed levels by generating optimal dryer module and air supply temperature configurations. Our results demonstrate that RLCBS outperforms NSGA-II under complex design constraints on drying module configurations at inference-time, while providing a 2.58-fold or higher speed improvement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12542v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Chen, Hanshen Yu, Jamal Yagoobi, Chenhui Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Landscape Shaping for Robust Control of Atoms in Optical Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Robust quantum control is crucial for realizing practical quantum technologies. Energy landscape shaping offers an alternative to conventional dynamic control, providing theoretically enhanced robustness and simplifying implementation for certain applications. This work demonstrates the feasibility of robust energy landscape control in a practical implementation with ultracold atoms. We leverage a digital mirror device (DMD) to shape optical potentials, creating complex energy landscapes. To achieve a desired objective, such as efficient quantum state transfer, we formulate a novel hybrid optimization approach that effectively handles both continuous (laser power) and discrete (DMD pixel activation) control parameters. This approach combines constrained quasi-Newton methods with surrogate models for efficient exploration of the vast parameter space. Furthermore, we introduce a framework for analyzing the robustness of the resulting control schemes against experimental uncertainties. By modeling uncertainties as structured perturbations, we systematically assess controller performance and identify robust solutions. We apply these techniques to maximize spin transfer in a chain of trapped atoms, achieving high-fidelity control while maintaining robustness. Our findings provide insights into the experimental viability of controlled spin transfer in cold atom systems. More broadly, the presented optimization and robustness analysis methods apply to a wide range of quantum control problems, offering a toolkit for designing and evaluating robust controllers in complex experimental settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12564v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. A. Weidner, S. P. O'Neil, E. A. Jonckheere, F. C. Langbein, S. G. Schirmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging LLMs to Create a Haptic Devices' Recommendation System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Haptic technology has seen significant growth, yet a lack of awareness of existing haptic device design knowledge hinders development. This paper addresses these limitations by leveraging advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) to develop a haptic agent, focusing specifically on Grounded Force Feedback (GFF) devices recommendation. Our approach involves automating the creation of a structured haptic device database using information from research papers and product specifications. This database enables the recommendation of relevant GFF devices based on user queries. To ensure precise and contextually relevant recommendations, the system employs a dynamic retrieval method that combines both conditional and semantic searches. Benchmarking against the established UEQ and existing haptic device searching tools, the proposed haptic recommendation agent ranks in the top 10\% across all UEQ categories with mean differences favoring the agent in nearly all subscales, and maintains no significant performance bias across different user groups, showcasing superior usability and user satisfaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12573v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Liu, Haiwei Dong, Abdulmotaleb El Saddik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Return Distributions with Distributional Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13028v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce distributional dynamic programming (DP) methods for optimizing statistical functionals of the return distribution, with standard reinforcement learning as a special case. Previous distributional DP methods could optimize the same class of expected utilities as classic DP. To go beyond expected utilities, we combine distributional DP with stock augmentation, a technique previously introduced for classic DP in the context of risk-sensitive RL, where the MDP state is augmented with a statistic of the rewards obtained so far (since the first time step). We find that a number of recently studied problems can be formulated as stock-augmented return distribution optimization, and we show that we can use distributional DP to solve them. We analyze distributional value and policy iteration, with bounds and a study of what objectives these distributional DP methods can or cannot optimize. We describe a number of applications outlining how to use distributional DP to solve different stock-augmented return distribution optimization problems, for example maximizing conditional value-at-risk, and homeostatic regulation. To highlight the practical potential of stock-augmented return distribution optimization and distributional DP, we combine the core ideas of distributional value iteration with the deep RL agent DQN, and empirically evaluate it for solving instances of the applications discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13028v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernardo \'Avila Pires, Mark Rowland, Diana Borsa, Zhaohan Daniel Guo, Khimya Khetarpal, Andr\'e Barreto, David Abel, R\'emi Munos, Will Dabney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which Sensor to Observe? Timely Tracking of a Joint Markov Source with Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the problem of remote estimation of a discrete-time joint Markov process using multiple sensors. Each sensor observes a different component of the joint Markov process, and in each time slot, the monitor obtains a partial state value by sending a pull request to one of the sensors. The monitor chooses the sequence of sensors to observe with the goal of minimizing the mean of age of incorrect information (MAoII) by using the partial state observations obtained, which have different freshness levels. For instance, a monitor may be interested in tracking the location of an object by obtaining observations from two sensors, which observe the $x$ and $y$ coordinates of the object separately, in different time slots. The monitor, then, needs to decide which coordinate to observe in the next time slot given the history. In addition to this partial observability of the state of Markov process, there is an erasure channel with a fixed one-slot delay between each sensor and the monitor. First, we obtain a sufficient statistic, namely the \emph{belief}, representing the joint distribution of the age of incorrect information (AoII) and the current state of the observed process by using the history of all pull requests and observations. Then, we formulate the problem with a continuous state-space Markov decision problem (MDP), namely belief MDP. To solve the problem, we propose two model predictive control (MPC) methods, namely MPC without terminal costs (MPC-WTC) and reinforcement learning MPC (RL-MPC), that have different advantages in implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismail Cosandal, Sennur Ulukus, Nail Akar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Data-Driven Kalman Filtering for Unknown Linear Systems using Maximum Likelihood Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18096v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the state estimation problem for unknown linear systems subject to both process and measurement noise. Based on a prior input-output trajectory sampled at a higher frequency and a prior state trajectory sampled at a lower frequency, we propose a novel robust data-driven Kalman filter (RDKF) that integrates model identification with state estimation for the unknown system. Specifically, the state estimation problem is formulated as a non-convex maximum likelihood optimization problem. Then, we slightly modify the optimization problem to get a problem solvable with a recursive algorithm. Based on the optimal solution to this new problem, the RDKF is designed, which can estimate the state of a given but unknown state-space model. The performance gap between the RDKF and the optimal Kalman filter based on known system matrices is quantified through a sample complexity bound. In particular, when the number of the pre-collected states tends to infinity, this gap converges to zero. Finally, the effectiveness of the theoretical results is illustrated by numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18096v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peihu Duan, Tao Liu, Yu Xing, Karl Henrik Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Electromagnetic Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06012v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic navigation offers wireless control over magnetic objects, which has important medical applications, such as targeted drug delivery and minimally invasive surgery. Magnetic navigation systems are categorized into systems using permanent magnets and systems based on electromagnets. Electromagnetic Navigation Systems (eMNSs) are believed to have a superior actuation bandwidth, facilitating trajectory tracking and disturbance rejection. This greatly expands the range of potential medical applications and includes even dynamic environments as encountered in cardiovascular interventions. To showcase the dynamic capabilities of eMNSs, we successfully stabilize a (non-magnetic) inverted pendulum on the tip of a magnetically driven arm. Our approach employs a model-based framework that leverages Lagrangian mechanics to capture the interaction between the mechanical dynamics and the magnetic field. Using system identification, we estimate unknown parameters, the actuation bandwidth, and characterize the system's nonlinearity. To explore the limits of electromagnetic navigation and evaluate its scalability, we characterize the electrical system dynamics and perform reference measurements on a clinical-scale eMNS, affirming that the proposed dynamic control methodologies effectively translate to larger coil configurations. A state-feedback controller stabilizes the inherently unstable pendulum, and an iterative learning control scheme enables accurate tracking of non-equilibrium trajectories. Furthermore, to understand structural limitations of our control strategy, we analyze the influence of magnetic field gradients on the motion of the system. To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration to stabilize a 3D inverted pendulum through electromagnetic navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06012v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasan Zughaibi, Bradley J. Nelson, Michael Muehlebach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks: a Plug and Play Integration into Power System Dynamic Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13325v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-domain simulations are crucial for ensuring power system stability and avoiding critical scenarios that could lead to blackouts. The next-generation power systems require a significant increase in the computational cost and complexity of these simulations due to additional degrees of uncertainty, non-linearity and states. Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINN) have been shown to accelerate single-component simulations by several orders of magnitude. However, their application to current time-domain simulation solvers has been particularly challenging since the system's dynamics depend on multiple components. Using a new training formulation, this paper introduces the first natural step to integrate PINNs into multi-component time-domain simulations. We propose PINNs as an alternative to other classical numerical methods for individual components. Once trained, these neural networks approximate component dynamics more accurately for longer time steps. Formulated as an implicit and consistent method with the transient simulation workflow, PINNs speed up simulation time by significantly increasing the time steps used. For explanation clarity, we demonstrate the training, integration, and simulation framework for several combinations of PINNs and numerical solution methods using the IEEE 9-bus system, although the method applies equally well to any power system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13325v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignasi Ventura Nadal, Jochen Stiasny, Spyros Chatzivasileiadis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Charging Coordination for Electric Trucks under Limited Facilities and Travel Uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10307v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we address the problem of charging coordination between electric trucks and charging stations. The problem arises from the tension between the trucks' nontrivial charging times and the stations' limited charging facilities. Our goal is to reduce the trucks' waiting times at the stations while minimizing individual trucks' operational costs. We propose a distributed coordination framework that relies on computation and communication between the stations and the trucks, and handles uncertainties in travel times and energy consumption. Within the framework, the stations assign a limited number of charging ports to trucks according to the first-come, first-served rule. In addition, each station constructs a waiting time forecast model based on its historical data and provides its estimated waiting times to trucks upon request. When approaching a station, a truck sends its arrival time and estimated arrival-time windows to the nearby station and the distant stations, respectively. The truck then receives the estimated waiting times from these stations in response, and updates its charging plan accordingly while accounting for travel uncertainties. We performed simulation studies for $1,000$ trucks traversing the Swedish road network for $40$ days, using realistic traffic data with travel uncertainties. The results show that our method reduces the average waiting time of the trucks by $46.1\%$ compared to offline charging plans computed by the trucks without coordination and update, and by $33.8\%$ compared to the coordination scheme assuming zero waiting times at distant stations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10307v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Bai, Yuchao Li, Andreas A. Malikopoulos, Karl Henrik Johansson, Jonas M{\aa}rtensson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certifiable Deep Learning for Reachability Using a New Lipschitz Continuous Value Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07866v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new reachability learning framework for high-dimensional nonlinear systems, focusing on reach-avoid problems. These problems require computing the reach-avoid set, which ensures that all its elements can safely reach a target set despite any disturbance within pre-specified bounds. Our framework has two main parts: offline learning of a newly designed reach-avoid value function and post-learning certification. Compared to prior works, our new value function is Lipschitz continuous and its associated Bellman operator is a contraction mapping, both of which improve the learning performance. To ensure deterministic guarantees of our learned reach-avoid set, we introduce two efficient post-learning certification methods. Both methods can be used online for real-time local certification or offline for comprehensive certification. We validate our framework in a 12-dimensional crazyflie drone racing hardware experiment and a simulated 10-dimensional highway takeover example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07866v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingqi Li, Donggun Lee, Jaewon Lee, Kris Shengjun Dong, Somayeh Sojoudi, Claire Tomlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexibility Options: A Proposed Product for Managing Imbalance Risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19559v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The presence of variable renewable energy resources with uncertain outputs in day-ahead electricity markets results in additional balancing needs in real-time. Addressing those needs cost-effectively and reliably within a competitive market with unbundled products is challenging as both the demand for and the availability of flexibility depends on day-ahead energy schedules. Existing approaches for reserve procurement usually rely either on oversimplified demand curves that do not consider how system conditions that particular day affect the value of flexibility, or on bilateral trading of hedging instruments that are not co-optimized with day-ahead schedules. This article proposes a new product, `Flexibility Options', to address these two limitations. The demand for this product is endogenously determined in the day-ahead market and it is met cost-effectively by considering real-time supply curves for product providers, which are co-optimized with the energy supply. As we illustrate with numerical examples and mathematical analysis, the product addresses the hedging needs of participants with imbalances cost-effectively, provides a less intermittent revenue stream for participants with flexible outputs, promotes value-driven pricing of flexibility, and ensures that the system operator is revenue-neutral. This article provides a comprehensive design that can be further tested and applied in large-scale systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19559v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elina Spyrou, Qiwei Zhang, Robin B. Hytowitz, Ben F. Hobbs, Siddharth Tyagi, Mengmeng Cai, Michael Blonsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman-based control of nonlinear systems with closed-loop guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide a tutorial overview and an extension of a recently developed framework for data-driven control of unknown nonlinear systems with rigorous closed-loop guarantees. The proposed approach relies on the Koopman operator representation of the nonlinear system, for which a bilinear surrogate model is estimated based on data. In contrast to existing Koopman-based estimation procedures, we state guaranteed bounds on the approximation error using the stability- and certificate-oriented extended dynamic mode decomposition (SafEDMD) framework. The resulting surrogate model and the uncertainty bounds allow us to design controllers via robust control theory and sum-of-squares optimization, guaranteeing desirable properties for the closed-loop system. We present results on stabilization both in discrete and continuous time, and we derive a method for controller design with performance objectives. The benefits of the presented framework over established approaches are demonstrated with a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10359v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Str\"asser, Julian Berberich, Manuel Schaller, Karl Worthmann, Frank Allg\"ower</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady-State Initialization of Object-Oriented Advanced Thermal Power Generation System Models with Application to the Case of the SOS-CO2 Cycle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12666v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The forthcoming energy transition calls for a new generation of thermal power generation systems with low- or zero-emission and highly flexible operation. Dynamic modelling and simulation is a key enabling factor in this field, as controlling such plants is a difficult task for which there is no previous experience and very short design times are expected. The steady-state initialization of those dynamic models is an essential step in the design process, but is unfortunately a difficult task which involves the numerical solution of large systems of nonlinear equations with iterative Newton methods, which is often prone to numerical failures.
  In this work, several strategies and methodologies are discussed to successfully achieve steady-state initialization of first-principles equation-based, object-oriented models of advanced thermal power generation systems. These are presented in the context of the Modelica modelling language, but could be applied to other equation-based, object-oriented modelling and simulation environments.
  Finally, the successful application of such strategies and methodologies to the SOS-CO2 advanced power generation system is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12666v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Luigi De Pascali, Francesco Casella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Joint Chance-Constrained Optimal Power Flow using Relative Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03543v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Designing robust algorithms for the optimal power flow (OPF) problem is critical for the control of large-scale power systems under uncertainty. The chance-constrained OPF (CCOPF) problem provides a natural formulation of the trade-off between the operating cost and the constraint satisfaction rate. In this work, we propose a new data-driven algorithm for the CCOPF problem, based on distributionally robust optimization (DRO). \revise{We show that the proposed reformulation of the distributionally robust chance constraints is exact, whereas other approaches in the CCOPF literature rely on conservative approximations. We establish out-of-sample robustness guarantees for the distributionally robust solution and prove that the solution is the most efficient among all approaches enjoying the same guarantees.} We apply the proposed algorithm to the the CCOPF problem and compare the performance of our approach with existing methods using simulations on IEEE benchmark power systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03543v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eli Brock, Haixiang Zhang, Javad Lavaei, Somayeh Sojoudi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
