<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY</link>
    <description>eess.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 05:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dependent Reachable Sets for the Constant Bearing Pursuit Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel reachability problem for the scenario where one agent follows another agent using the constant bearing pursuit strategy, and analyzes the geometry of the reachable set of the follower. Key theoretical results are derived, providing bounds for the associated dependent reachable set. Simulation results are presented to empirically establish the shape of the dependent reachable set. In the process, an original optimization problem for the constant bearing strategy is formulated and analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00273v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Venkata Ramana Makkapati, Tulasi Ram Vechalapu, Vinodhini Comandur, Seth Hutchinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Datamodel-Based Data Selection for Nonlinear Data-Enabled Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00276v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data-Enabled Predictive Control (DeePC) has emerged as a powerful framework for controlling unknown systems directly from input-output data. For nonlinear systems, recent work has proposed selecting relevant subsets of data columns based on geometric proximity to the current operating point. However, such proximity-based selection ignores the control objective: different reference trajectories may benefit from different data even at the same operating point. In this paper, we propose a datamodel-based approach that learns a context-dependent influence function mapping the current initial trajectory and reference trajectory to column importance scores. Adapting the linear datamodel framework from machine learning, we model closed-loop cost as a linear function of column inclusion indicators, with coefficients that depend on the control context. Training on closed-loop simulations, our method captures which data columns actually improve tracking performance for specific control tasks. Experimental results demonstrate that task-aware selection substantially outperforms geometry-based heuristics, particularly when using small data subsets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00276v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Li, Shihao Li, Dongmei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Observer and Controller Design for Linear Systems: A Separation-Based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the problem of consensus-based distributed control of linear time-invariant multi-channel systems subject to unknown inputs. A distributed observer-based control framework is proposed, within which observer nodes and controller nodes collaboratively perform state estimation and control tasks. Consensus refers to a distributed cooperative mechanism by which each observer node compares its state estimate with those of neighboring nodes, and use the resulting discrepancies to update its own state estimate. One key contribution of this work is to show that the distributed observers and the distributed controllers can be designed independently, which parallels the classical separation principle. This separability within the distributed framework is enabled by a discontinuous consensus strategy and two adaptive algorithms developed specifically for handling the unknown inputs. Theoretical analysis and numerical simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed framework in achieving state estimation, stabilization, and tracking control objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00393v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ganghui Cao, Xunyuan Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Acceleration Control Barrier Filter for Efficient UAV Obstacle Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamic obstacle avoidance (DOA) for unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) requires fast reaction under limited onboard resources. We introduce the distributionally robust acceleration control barrier function (DR-ACBF) as an efficient collision avoidance method maintaining safety regions. The method constructs a second-order control barrier function as linear half-space constraints on commanded acceleration. Latency, actuator limits, and obstacle accelerations are handled through an effective clearance that considers dynamics and delay. Uncertainty is mitigated using Cantelli tightening with per-obstacle risk. A DR-conditional value at risk (DR-CVaR)based early trigger expands margins near violations to improve DOA. Real-time execution is ensured via constant-time Gauss-Southwell projections. Simulation studies achieve similar avoidance performance at substantially lower computational effort than state-of-the-art baseline approaches. Experiments with Crazyflie drones demonstrate the feasibility of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00462v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dnyandeep Mandaokar, Bernhard Rinner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Highly Configurable Framework for Large-Scale Thermal Building Data Generation to drive Machine Learning Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data-driven modeling of building thermal dynamics is emerging as an increasingly important field of research for large-scale intelligent building control. However, research in data-driven modeling using machine learning (ML) techniques requires massive amounts of thermal building data, which is not easily available. Neither empirical public datasets nor existing data generators meet the needs of ML research in terms of data quality and quantity. Moreover, existing data generation approaches typically require expert knowledge in building simulation. To fill this gap, we present a thermal building data generation framework which we call BuilDa. BuilDa is designed to produce synthetic data of adequate quality and quantity for ML research. The framework does not require profound building simulation knowledge to generate large volumes of data. BuilDa uses a single-zone Modelica model that is exported as a Functional Mock-up Unit (FMU) and simulated in Python. We demonstrate BuilDa by generating data and utilizing it for a transfer learning study involving the fine-tuning of 486 data-driven models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00483v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Krug, Fabian Raisch, Dominik Aimer, Markus Wirnsberger, Ferdinand Sigg, Felix Koch, Benjamin Sch\"afer, Benjamin Tischler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Safety Intelligence in V2X-Enabled Transportation: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vehicle-to-Everything (V2X) cooperation is reshaping traffic safety from an ego-centric sensing problem into one of collective intelligence. This survey structures recent progress within a unified Sensor-Perception-Decision (SPD) framework that formalizes how safety emerges from the interaction of distributed sensing, cooperative perception, and coordinated decision-making across vehicles and infrastructure. Rather than centering on link protocols or message formats, we focus on how shared evidence, predictive reasoning, and human-aligned interventions jointly enable proactive risk mitigation. Within this SPD lens, we synthesize advances in cooperative perception, multi-modal forecasting, and risk-aware planning, emphasizing how cross-layer coupling turns isolated detections into calibrated, actionable understanding. Timing, trust, and human factors are identified as cross-cutting constraints that determine whether predictive insights are delivered early enough, with reliable confidence, and in forms that humans and automated controllers can use. Compared with prior V2X safety surveys, this work (i) organizes the literature around a formal SPD safety loop and (ii) systematically analyzes research evolution and evaluation gaps through a PRISMA-guided bibliometric study of hundreds of publications from 2016-2025. The survey concludes with a roadmap toward cooperative safety intelligence, outlining SPD-based design principles and evaluation practices for next-generation V2X safety systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00490v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxun Zhang, Qian Xu, Zhenning Li, Chengzhong Xu, Keqiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Range Loss to Recovery - Cold Weather Challenges and Design Strategies for Commercial Electric Vehicle Fleets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The North American commercial electric vehicle (EV) sector is undergoing rapid expansion, with unit sales rising from 21,120 in 2022 to 36,491 in 2023 - a 73% increase, according to the International Energy Agency. However, this accelerating adoption brings emerging technical challenges. One critical concern is the impact of low to extreme winter temperatures (25 degree F to -25 degree F) on EV performance, including reduced energy efficiency and extended charging times. This paper presents a systematic analysis of commercial EV performance degradation under cold weather conditions and its broader implications on grid operations. Monte Carlo simulations, applied using real-world fleet parameters, indicate that approximately 200 MWh of additional daily energy demand may be required in the U.S. alone to offset efficiency losses during severe cold events. The resulting strain on an already stressed winter grid could exacerbate reliability risks. Moreover, increased harmonic distortion associated with cold weather charging behaviors has also been observed, raising concerns about power quality. To address these challenges, this study proposes two practical mitigation strategies: (1) a 'design-integrated safety' battery swapping station model operating in thermally controlled environments to significantly reduce charging downtime, and (2) a hybrid architecture combining roadside fast charging with depot-based deep charging to support continuous fleet utilization without compromising range. Together, these interventions provide a robust foundation for resilient commercial EV integration in cold climates, supporting fleet operators and utilities in managing seasonal performance variability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00541v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Ghosh, Arpit Bohra, Karthik Saikumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KinesCeTI: A Modular and Size-Adaptable Force Feedback Glove with Interchangeable Actuation for the Index and Thumb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Force feedback gloves in haptic applications remain constrained by limited adaptability, simplified feedback and fixed architectures that limit force feedback versatility. To address these challenges, we present KinesCeTI, a modular force feedback exoskeleton for the index and thumb, designed as a multipurpose device adaptable to a wide range of hand sizes. The glove incorporates interchangeable thimbles for fingertip or phalanx attachment and a bidirectional tendon transmission that supports both passive and active feedback. It is combined with a modular actuation design, where different feedback systems may be attached. The system was tested with two actuation modules: a compliant ratchet-pawl braking mechanism for passive feedback and a novel one-way clutch for variable active feedback, newly introduced here. The system was evaluated in three user studies with 20 participants each, assessing ergonomics, actuation performance and usability in both real and virtual tasks. Results indicate that the glove adapts to different hand sizes and provides effective feedback with both mechanisms, highlighting its potential as a versatile platform for haptic research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00622v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Alvarez Romeo, Mehmet Ercan Altinsoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Computation of Polytopic Invariant Sets for Noisy Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a data-driven framework for computing robust, convex polytopic contractive set for constrained noisy nonlinear systems where an analytical model is not available. Our approach utilizes a finite set of collected noisy measurements to construct a polytopic set that bounds all possible system parameters compatible to available information. Based on previous results, we contribute to provide a sufficient condition for a set to be contractive using Difference of Convex functions for a noisy nonlinear system, while the model is not available. Robustness with respect to unknown model of system is guaranteed by requiring that the computed contractive set is invariant for all possible system models that are compatible with the noisy measurements. We present a tractable, optimization-based algorithm that implements this condition to compute the largest possible contractive set within the state constraint set for the unknown, noisy nonlinear system which is subjected to both state and input constraints. The effectiveness of the proposed methodology is demonstrated with a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00629v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahand Kiani, Constantino M. Lagoa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraint-Aware Grid-Forming Control for Current Limiting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work develops a constraint-aware grid-forming (GFM) control that explicitly accounts for current limits and modulation limits within the GFM oscillator dynamics generating the GFM voltage reference (i.e., phase angle and magnitude). Broadly speaking, the voltage reference generated by the constraint-aware GFM control minimizes the deviation from conventional unconstrained GFM droop control, while respecting current and modulation limits. The resulting GFM control achieves fast current limiting while preserving transient stability, e.g., exhibiting infinite critical clearing time. To develop the control, we first characterize and analyze the set of converter voltages that do not result in constraint violations. Next, an efficient algorithm for projecting voltages onto the feasible set is developed. Subsequently, these results are used to restrict the dynamics of GFM droop control to the set of feasible voltages. Finally, detailed simulation studies and hardware experiments are used to illustrate and validate the response to short-circuit faults and phase jumps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00644v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic Gro{\ss}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Learning of Fractional-Order Viscoelastic Model Parameters for Realistic Haptic Rendering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective medical simulators necessitate realistic haptic rendering of biological tissues that display viscoelastic material properties, such as creep and stress relaxation. Fractional-order models provide an effective means of describing intrinsically time-dependent viscoelastic dynamics with few parameters, as these models can naturally capture memory effects. However, due to the unintuitive frequency-dependent coupling between the order of the fractional element and the other parameters, determining appropriate parameters for fractional-order models that yield high perceived realism remains a significant challenge. In this study, we propose a systematic means of determining the parameters of fractional-order viscoelastic models that optimizes the perceived realism of haptic rendering across general populations. First, we demonstrate that the parameters of fractional-order models can be effectively optimized through active learning, via qualitative feedback-based human-in-the-loop~(HiL) optimizations, to ensure consistently high realism ratings for each individual. Second, we propose a rigorous method to combine HiL optimization results to form an aggregate perceptual map trained on the entire dataset and demonstrate the selection of population-level optimal parameters from this representation that are broadly perceived as realistic across general populations. Finally, we provide evidence of the effectiveness of the generalized fractional-order viscoelastic model parameters by characterizing their perceived realism through human-subject experiments. Overall, generalized fractional-order viscoelastic models established through the proposed HiL optimization and aggregation approach possess the potential to significantly improve the sim-to-real transition performance of medical training simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00667v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harun Tolasa, Gorkem Gemalmaz, Volkan Patoglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DM-MPPI: Datamodel for Efficient and Safe Model Path Integral Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the Datamodels framework from supervised learning to Model Predictive Path Integral (MPPI) control. Whereas Datamodels estimate sample influence via regression on a fixed dataset, we instead learn to predict influence directly from sample cost features, enabling real-time estimation for newly generated samples without online regression. Our influence predictor is trained offline using influence coefficients computed via the Datamodel framework across diverse MPPI instances, and is then deployed online for efficient sample pruning and adaptive constraint handling. A single learned model simultaneously addresses efficiency and safety: low-influence samples are pruned to reduce computational cost, while monitoring the influence of constraint-violating samples enables adaptive penalty tuning. Experiments on path-tracking with obstacle avoidance demonstrate up to a $5\times$ reduction in the number of samples while maintaining control performance and improving constraint satisfaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00759v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Li, Shihao Li, Xu Duan, Dongmei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Optimal Thrust to Mass Ratio Requirement for Maximizing Payload Mass of Lunar Landing Mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent successful lunar landing missions have generated significant interest among space agencies in establishing a permanent human settlement on the Moon. Building a lunar base requires multiple and frequent landing missions to support logistics and mobility applications. In these missions, maximizing payload mass defined as the useful cargo for human settlement is crucial. The landing mass depends on several factors, with the most critical being the maximum thrust available for braking and the engine's specific impulse (ISP). Generally, increasing engine thrust for braking reduces flight duration and, consequently, gravity losses. However, higher thrust also introduces trade-offs, such as increased engine weight and lower ISP, which can negatively impact payload capacity. Therefore, optimizing the descent trajectory requires careful consideration of these parameters to achieve a global solution that maximizes payload mass. Most existing research focuses on solving optimal control problems that minimize propellant consumption for a given thrust. These problems are typically addressed through trajectory optimization, where a minimum-fuel solution is obtained. The optimized trajectory is then executed onboard using polynomial guidance. In this paper, we propose an outer-layer optimization approach based on a Pareto-optimal solution. This method iterates on the maximum available thrust for descent trajectory optimization while incorporating a loss function that accounts for engine mass and ISP losses. By applying this approach, we identify a globally optimal solution that maximizes payload mass while ensuring an optimal landing trajectory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00767v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.52202/080560-0005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Rallapalli, Suraj Kumar, Rijesh MP, C K Koteswar Rao, Bharat Kumar GVP</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechatronic Design, Dynamic Modeling, and Real-Time Control of a Movable Scaffold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents mechatronic design, dynamic modeling, simulations and real-time control experiments of a new movable scaffolding system. The proposed system consists of a 3 degrees-of-freedom movable platform, which can be positioned on the outer surface of buildings. The platform is supported and driven by cords that are wound on pulleys and coupled to servo controlled dc-motors located at four corners of the building surface. A mathematical model considering the actuator dynamics for this cable-driven mechanism is obtained and its simulation results are presented. Design, manufacture and real-time control tests of a prototype has been done. Both numerical simulations and experiments provide good positioning performance of the proposed cable-driven mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00906v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. \"Ozg\"un G\"ule\c{c}, Koray K. \c{S}afak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Advances in Short-Circuit Measurement: A Novel Time-Resolved Diode-Clamp Circuit Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional electrical fault models, which rely on static thresholds and instantaneous trip mechanisms, fail to capture the time-evolving dynamics of real faults, creating vulnerabilities in modern power systems. This paper introduces a diode-clamp circuit architecture that reconceives short-circuits as governed, sustained processes and establishes a physics-consistent, measurement system. An Arduino-based data acquisition system recorded continuous fault evolution across multiple input voltages and durations. Multi-resolution sampling at 10ms, 50ms, and 100ms enabled high-fidelity capture of both transients and sustained-state dynamics. The clamped mechanism constrained the circuit to a bounded regime, enabling repeatable observation. Experiments yielded definitive, measurable minima and maxima for voltage, current, and resistance, empirically refuting the classical assumption of instantaneous, unbounded current. Newly introduced metrics quantify this performance: the Sustained-to-Capacitive Energy Ratio (SCER ~1.53x10^12) proves fault energy originates from sustained dynamics, not transient discharge. The Sustained Fault Efficiency (SFE&gt;1) demonstrates that governed fault power can exceed nominal operating power. This work provides the first fully validated short-circuit quantification system, yielding empirical data for next-generation battery management, adaptive grid protection, and fault-tolerant electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00959v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Mwololo Kimuya, Dickson Mwenda Kinyua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fault-Tolerant Temperature Control of HRSG Superheaters: Stability Analysis Under Valve Leakage Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Faults and operational disturbances in Heat Recovery Steam Generators (HRSGs), such as valve leakage, present significant challenges, disrupting steam temperature regulation and potentially causing efficiency losses, safety risks, and unit shutdowns. Traditional PI controllers often struggle due to inherent system delays, nonlinear dynamics, and static gain limitations. This paper introduces a fault-tolerant temperature control framework by integrating a PI plus feedforward control strategy with Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs). The feedforward component anticipates disturbances, preemptively adjusting control actions, while the PINN adaptively tunes control gains in real-time, embedding thermodynamic constraints to manage varying operating conditions and valve leakage faults. A Lyapunov-based stability analysis confirms the asymptotic convergence of temperature tracking errors under bounded leakage conditions. Simulation results using operational data from the Pareh-Sar combined cycle power plant demonstrate significantly improved response times, reduced temperature deviations, enhanced fault resilience, and smooth gain adjustments. The proposed adaptive, data-driven methodology shows strong potential for industrial deployment, ensuring reliable operation, autonomous fault recovery, and enhanced performance in HRSG systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00990v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mojtaba Fanoodi, Farzaneh Abdollahi, Mahdi Aliyari Shoorehdeli, Mohsen Maboodi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating Analytically-Intractable Likelihood Densities with Deterministic Arithmetic for Optimal Particle Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Particle filtering algorithms have enabled practical solutions to problems in autonomous robotics (self-driving cars, UAVs, warehouse robots), target tracking, and econometrics, with further applications in speech processing and medicine (patient monitoring). Yet, their inherent weakness at representing the likelihood of the observation (which often leads to particle degeneracy) remains unaddressed for high-frequency and resource-constrained systems. Improvements such as the optimal proposal and auxiliary particle filter mitigate this issue under specific circumstances and with increased computational cost. This work presents a new particle filtering method and its implementation, which enables tunably-approximative representation of arbitrary likelihood densities as program transformations of parametric distributions. Our method leverages a recent computing platform that can perform deterministic computation on probability distribution representations (UxHw) without relying on stochastic methods. For non-Gaussian non-linear systems and with an optimal-auxiliary particle filter, we benchmark the likelihood evaluation error and speed for a total of 294840 evaluation points. For such models, the results show that the UxHw method leads to as much as 37.7x speedup compared to the Monte Carlo alternative. For narrow uniform observation noise, the particle filter falsely assigns zero likelihood as much as 81.89% of the time whereas UxHw achieves 1.52% false-zero rate. The UxHw approach achieves filter RMSE improvement of as much as 18.9% (average 3.3%) over the Monte Carlo alternative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01023v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orestis Kaparounakis, Yunqi Zhang, Phillip Stanley-Marbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Silence that Speaks: Neural Estimation via Communication Gaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01056v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate remote state estimation is a fundamental component of many autonomous and networked dynamical systems, where multiple decision-making agents interact and communicate over shared, bandwidth-constrained channels. These communication constraints introduce an additional layer of complexity, namely, the decision of when to communicate. This results in a fundamental trade-off between estimation accuracy and communication resource usage. Traditional extensions of classical estimation algorithms (e.g., the Kalman filter) treat the absence of communication as 'missing' information. However, silence itself can carry implicit information about the system's state, which, if properly interpreted, can enhance the estimation quality even in the absence of explicit communication. Leveraging this implicit structure, however, poses significant analytical challenges, even in relatively simple systems. In this paper, we propose CALM (Communication-Aware Learning and Monitoring), a novel learning-based framework that jointly addresses the dual challenges of communication scheduling and estimator design. Our approach entails learning not only when to communicate but also how to infer useful information from periods of communication silence. We perform comparative case studies on multiple benchmarks to demonstrate that CALM is able to decode the implicit coordination between the estimator and the scheduler to extract information from the instances of 'silence' and enhance the estimation accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01056v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Aggarwal, Dipankar Maity, Tamer Ba\c{s}ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Viability of Fresnel Lenses for Weed Control in Prickly Pear Cactus Cultivation: A Spatiotemporal Coverage Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In tropical semiarid regions, prickly pear cactus has emerged as a vital forage resource due to its high drought tolerance and minimal water requirements. However, even limited weed infestation can severely compromise cactus productivity, as the species are highly sensitive to competition for essential resources, which includes water, mineral nutrients, and sun exposure. Conventional herbicide-based weed control strategies face growing limitations due to resistance development and environmental concerns, underscoring the need for sustainable alternatives. This study revisits the historically underexplored application of linear Fresnel lenses for thermal weed control and establishes the technical feasibility of a contemporary autonomous weed management system that incorporates LFL technology within an unmanned ground vehicle platform. Leveraging real-time image processing, georeferencing, and mechanical actuation, the system can perform a two-phase operation-weed mapping during non-optimal solar hours and targeted solar termination during peak irradiance. Analytical modeling quantifies the effective area coverage and time constraints imposed by the solar window. Preliminary results indicate that, while unsuitable for dense weed infestations, the system presents a viable solution for precision, post-emergent weed control in sparse infestations. The favorable solar geometry in tropical zones, especially in the Brazilian semiarid region, and the targeted nature of the approach make this technology particularly well-suited for sustainable agriculture in under-resourced regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01069v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Euzeli C. dos Santos Jr., Josinaldo Lopes Araujo Rocha, Anielson dos Santos Souza, Isaac Soares de Freitas, Hudson E. Alencar Menezes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negotiating Highway Interchange Traffic with a Decentralized Instability-Driven CBF-based Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider an interchange lane-swap scenario, a limited stretch of highway with two parallel lanes where most vehicles want to change lanes. We show that a particular decentralized Control Barrier Function based algorithm executes lane swaps efficiently, with minimal speed change, within the specified (short) road segment at high traffic densities (3,500 vehicles per hour per lane). Our main point is that controller tuning, the speed of inter-agent instability, plays a major role in the performance of the vehicle group. This is illustrated by comparing two different tunings of the controller and a third one where the lane swap is enforced by virtual guard rails. Like fighter jet dynamic instability improving maneuverability, the inter-agent instability improves agility of a group of vehicles. We emphasize that the controllers considered are decentralized: agents do not know if others want to change lanes or not.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01098v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mrdjan Jankovic, Shreshta Rajakumar Deshpande, Gopika Ajaykumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervisory control synthesis for multilevel DES with local buses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In multilevel supervisor synthesis, dependency structure matrix techniques can be used to transform the models of plants and requirements into a tree-structured hierarchical decomposition of the synthesis problem and thus efficiently synthesize local supervisors. A bus component, which has many dependencies across a system, tends to lead to an undesirable clustering of many components in one synthesis subproblem. Prior work showed how to recognize and properly treat a global bus structure. In this paper we leverage this work from global to local bus structures through a novel multilevel discrete-event system (MLDES) architecture. Specifically, the hierarchical system decomposition is revisited by allowing bus detection not only on the top level but at each level of the system hierarchy. Given this architecture, an algorithm is introduced that constructs a tree-structured MLDES. A case study on a production line shows the effectiveness of the proposed method through significantly improved synthesis performance, measured by the sum of the controlled state-space sizes of the local supervisors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01101v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marzhan M. Baubekova, Martijn A. Goorden, Michel A. Reniers, Joanna M. v. d. Mortel-Fronczak, Jacobus E. Rooda, Wan J. Fokkink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Communications for Vehicle-Based Mission-Critical Services: Challenges and Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01102v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As mission-critical (MC) services such as Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) based emergency communication and Internet of Vehicles (IoVs) enabled autonomous driving emerge, the traditional communication framework can not meet the growing demands for higher reliability and lower latency and the increasing transmission loads. Semantic Communication (SemCom), an emerging communication paradigm that shifts the focus from bit-level data to its context and intended task at the receiver (i.e., semantic level), is envisioned to be a key revolution in Sixth Generation (6G) networks. However, an explicit and systematic SemCom framework specifically tailored for Vehicle-based MC (VbMC) services has yet to be proposed, primarily due to the complexity and lack of analysis on their MC characteristics. In this article, we first present the key information-critical and infrastructure-critical vehicle-based services within the SemCom framework. We then analyze the unique characteristics of MC services and the corresponding challenges they present for SemCom. Building on this, we propose a novel SemCom framework designed to address the specific needs of MC services in vehicle systems, offering potential solutions to existing challenges. Finally, we present a case study on UAV-based rapid congestion relief, utilizing eXplainable AI (XAI) to validate the effectiveness of the proposed SemCom framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01102v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Zhou, Jiaying Guo, Marios Aristodemou, Zhaoyang Du, Shen Wang, Xiaolan Liu, Soufiene Djahel, Celimuge Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Neuromodulable Current-Mode Silicon Neuron for Robust and Adaptive Neuromorphic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neuromorphic engineering makes use of mixed-signal analog and digital circuits to directly emulate the computational principles of biological brains. Such electronic systems offer a high degree of adaptability, robustness, and energy efficiency across a wide range of tasks, from edge computing to robotics. Within this context, we investigate a key feature of biological neurons: their ability to carry out robust and reliable computation by adapting their input response and spiking pattern to context through neuromodulation. Achieving analogous levels of robustness and adaptation in neuromorphic circuits through modulatory mechanisms is a largely unexplored path. We present a novel current-mode neuron design that supports robust neuromodulation with minimal model complexity, compatible with standard CMOS technologies. We first introduce a mathematical model of the circuit and provide tools to analyze and tune the neuron behavior; we then demonstrate both theoretically and experimentally the biologically plausible neuromodulation adaptation capabilities of the circuit over a wide range of parameters. All the theoretical predictions were verified in experiments on a low-power 180 nm CMOS implementation of the proposed neuron circuit. Due to the analog underlying feedback structure, the proposed adaptive neuromodulable neuron exhibits a high degree of robustness, flexibility, and scalability across operating ranges of currents and temperatures, making it a perfect candidate for real-world neuromorphic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01133v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Loris Mendolia, Chenxi Wen, Elisabetta Chicca, Giacomo Indiveri, Rodolphe Sepulchre, Jean-Michel Redout\'e, Alessio Franci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Navigation and Station-Keeping on Near-Rectilinear Halo Orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01182v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article develops an optical navigation (OPNAV) and station-keeping pipeline for the near-rectilinear halo orbit (NRHO) in high-fidelity ephemeris model dynamics. The pipeline involves synthetic images used by the non-iterative horizon-based OPNAV algorithm, fed into an extended Kalman filter. The state estimate is used by a controller to maintain the spacecraft's motion within the vicinity of a reference NRHO. We study differential correction-based and minimization-based implementations of the x-axis crossing control scheme, and propose an improved targeting prediction scheme by incorporating the filter's state covariance with an unscented transform. We also introduce a hysteresis mechanism, which improves station-keeping cost and provides insight into the difference in performance between the differential correction-based and minimization-based approaches. We perform Monte-Carlo experiments to assess the pipeline's tracking and {\Delta}V performances. We report several key findings, including the variability of the filter performance with the sensor field of view and measurement locations, station-keeping cost reduction achieved by the unscented transform-based prediction and hysteresis, as well as variability of the cumulative {\Delta}V as a function of maneuver location due to the periodic structure in the OPNAV-based filter's estimation accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01182v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Shimane, Karl Berntorp, Stefano Di Cairano, Avishai Weiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Constrained Neural Dynamics: A Unified Manifold Framework for Large-Scale Power Flow Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01207v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Power flow analysis is a fundamental tool for power system analysis, planning, and operational control. Traditional Newton-Raphson methods suffer from limitations such as initial value sensitivity and low efficiency in batch computation, while existing deep learning-based power flow solvers mostly rely on supervised learning, requiring pre-solving of numerous cases and struggling to guarantee physical consistency. This paper proposes a neural physics power flow solving method based on manifold geometry and gradient flow, by describing the power flow equations as a constraint manifold, and constructing an energy function \(V(\mathbf{x}) = \frac{1}{2}\|\mathbf{F}(\mathbf{x})\|^2\) and gradient flow \(\frac{d\mathbf{x}}{dt} = -\nabla V(\mathbf{x})\), transforming power flow solving into an equilibrium point finding problem for dynamical systems. Neural networks are trained in an unsupervised manner by directly minimizing physical residuals, requiring no labeled data, achieving true "end-to-end" physics-constrained learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01207v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuezhi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Input-Output Data-Driven Representation: Non-Minimality and Stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many recent data-driven control approaches for linear time-invariant systems are based on finite-horizon prediction of output trajectories using input-output data matrices. When applied recursively, this predictor forms a dynamic system representation. This data-driven representation is generally non-minimal, containing latent poles in addition to the system's original poles. In this article, we show that these latent poles are guaranteed to be stable through the use of the Moore-Penrose inverses of the data matrices, regardless of the system's stability and even in the presence of small noise in data. This result obviates the need to eliminate the latent poles through procedures that resort to low-rank approximation in data-driven control and analysis. It is then applied to construct a stabilizable and detectable realization from data, from which we design an output feedback linear quadratic regulator (LQR) controller. Furthermore, we extend this principle to data-driven inversion, enabling asymptotic unknown input estimation for minimum-phase systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01238v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joowon Lee, Nam Hoon Jo, Hyungbo Shim, Florian D\"orfler, Jinsung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Bayesian Framework for Stochastic Data-Driven Smoothing, Prediction, and Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extending data-driven algorithms based on Willems' fundamental lemma to stochastic data often requires empirical and customized workarounds. This work presents a unified Bayesian framework that provides a systematic and general method for handling stochastic data-driven tasks, including smoothing, prediction, and control, via maximum a posteriori estimation. %This extends behavioral systems theory to stochastic data. This framework formulates a unified trajectory estimation problem for the three tasks by specifying different types of trajectory knowledge. Then, a Bayesian problem is solved that optimally combines trajectory knowledge with a data-driven characterization of the trajectory from offline data for a general class of stochastic disturbances. Under specific conditions, this problem is shown to generalize existing data-driven prediction and control algorithms. Numerical examples demonstrate the performance of the unified approach for all three tasks against other data-driven and system identification approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01475v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzhou Yin, Andrea Iannelli, Seyed Ali Nazari, Matthias A. M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An innovative circuit for testing hot carrier and trap generation in GaN Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Microelectronic devices in modern systems are working continuously for prolonged periods of many years. Thus, there is a crucial need for reliability model that will enable us to predict precisely the life cycle of the device and point out on the governing failure mechanisms that are responsible for degradation and failure. This is even more important when high power and frequency devices, especially Normally Off Switch Power transistors are concerned, since the reliability research on those devices lay far behind that of low power digital devices. Our main goal in our lab is to investigate the failure mechanisms of GaN transistors, aimed at determining the reliability factors of the innovative MTOL model. The main goal is to understand the reason for the transformation of the failure mechanism. Employing the recorded data may enable us to predict the performance and life time of the device at different operation parameters such as current, voltage, frequency and temperatures. In this study we employ a new different use for the well-known boost convertor circuit, based on GaN Devices in order to stress the transistor to the maximum values of voltage and current which allows us to examine the reliability of the transistor and accelerating Hot Carrier And Trap Generation failures mechanisms. The acceleration of the failure mechanism should be done in a way that will not affect the electronic device detrimentally and on the other hand we would not need to wait a long time in order to observe the degradation. In this work we will present our new boost converter circuit based on high power GaN HEMT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01683v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moshe Azoulay, Gilad Orr, Gady Golan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Capture Human Preference: Commissioning of a Robotic Use-Case via Preferential Bayesian Optimisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The popularity of Bayesian Optimization (BO) to automate or support the commissioning of engineering systems is rising. Conventional BO, however, relies on the availability of a scalar objective function. The latter is often difficult to define and rarely captures the nuanced judgement of expert operators in industrial settings. Preferential Bayesian Optimization (PBO) addresses this limitation by relying solely on pairwise preference feedback of a human expert, so-called duels. In this paper, we study PBO's capacity to commission a particular setup where a manipulator needs to push a block towards a target position. We benchmark state-of-the-art algorithms in both simulations and in the real world. Our results confirm that PBO can commission the set-up to the satisfaction of an expert operator whilst relying solely on binary preference feedback. To evaluate to what extend the same result can be achieved using conventional BO we investigate the experts decision consistency against an expert-designed cost function. Our study reveals that the experts fail to define a cost function that is in full agreement with their own decision process as witnessed in the PBO experiments. We then show that the auxiliary cost function that is constructed as a by-product of the PBO algorithms outperforms the expert-designed cost function in terms of decision consistency. Furthermore we demonstrate that this cost function can be used with conventional BO algorithms in an effort to reproduce the optimal design. This proofs the preference based cost function captures the experts' preferences perhaps more effectively than the experts could articulate preference themselves. In conclusion, we discuss downsides and propose directions for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01754v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sander De Witte, Jeroen Taets, Andras Retzler, Guillaume Crevecoeur, Tom Lefebvre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency-Dynamics-Aware Economic Dispatch with Optimal Grid-Forming Inverter Allocation and Reserved Power Headroom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The high penetration of inverter-based resources (IBRs) reduces system inertia, leading to frequency stability concerns, especially during synchronous generator (SG) outages. To maintain frequency dynamics within secure limits while ensuring economic efficiency, frequency-constrained optimal power flow (FCOPF) is employed. However, existing studies either neglect the frequency support capability and allocation of grid-forming (GFM) IBRs or suffer from limited accuracy in representing frequency dynamics due to model simplifications. To address this issue, this paper proposes a deep learning (DL)-based FCOPF (DL-FCOPF) framework. A DL model is first developed as a predictor to accurately estimate frequency-related metrics: the required reserved headroom and allocation of GFM IBRs, the rate of change of frequency and frequency nadir. After being trained with data obtained from electromagnetic transient simulations, the DL model is reformulated and incorporated into FCOPF. Case studies conducted on two test systems demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach. Compared with the traditional OPF and linear FCOPF benchmarks, the DL-FCOPF can optimally coordinate SGs and IBRs with minimum cost, achieving desired frequency response, within an acceptable computing time. Further-more, sensitivity analyses are conducted to identify the most suit-able structure and linearization approach of the DL-based frequency predictor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01814v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Jiang, Xingpeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty quantification in load profiles with rising EV and PV adoption: the case of residential, industrial, and office buildings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integration of photovoltaic (PV) generation and electric vehicle (EV) charging intro- duces significant uncertainty in electricity consumption patterns, particularly at the distribution level. This paper presents a comparative study for selecting metrics for uncertainty quantification (UQ) for net load profiles of residential, industrial, and office buildings under increased DER penetration. A variety of statistical metrics is evaluated for their usefulness in quantifying un- certainty, including, but not limited to, standard deviation, entropy, ramps, and distance metrics. The proposed metrics are classified into baseline-free, with baseline and error-based. These UQ metrics are evaluated for increased penetration of EV and PV. The results highlight suitable metrics to quantify uncertainty per consumer type and demonstrate how net load uncertainty is affected by EV and PV adoption. Additionally, it is observed that joint consideration of EV and PV can reduce overall uncertainty due to compensatory effects of EV charging and PV generation due to temporal alignment during the day. Uncertainty reduction is observed across all datasets and is most pronounced for the office building dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01914v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiko Fias, Md Umar Hashmi, Geert Deconinck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Event-triggered control of nonlinear systems from data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent paper [8], we introduced a data-based approach to design event-triggered controllers for linear systems directly from data. Here, we extend the results in [8] to a class of nonlinear systems. We provide two data-based designs certified by a (classical) Lyapunov function. For these two designs, we devise event-triggered policies that rely on the previously found Lyapunov function, have parameters tuned from data, ensure a positive minimum inter-event time, and act based either on the state error or on the library error. These two different policies, and their respective advantages, are illustrated numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01938v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hailong Chen, Claudio De Persis, Andrea Bisoffi, Pietro Tesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI-Driven Optimization under Uncertainty for Mineral Processing Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The global capacity for mineral processing must expand rapidly to meet the demand for critical minerals, which are essential for building the clean energy technologies necessary to mitigate climate change. However, the efficiency of mineral processing is severely limited by uncertainty, which arises from both the variability of feedstock and the complexity of process dynamics. To optimize mineral processing circuits under uncertainty, we introduce an AI-driven approach that formulates mineral processing as a Partially Observable Markov Decision Process (POMDP). We demonstrate the capabilities of this approach in handling both feedstock uncertainty and process model uncertainty to optimize the operation of a simulated, simplified flotation cell as an example. We show that by integrating the process of information gathering (i.e., uncertainty reduction) and process optimization, this approach has the potential to consistently perform better than traditional approaches at maximizing an overall objective, such as net present value (NPV). Our methodological demonstration of this optimization-under-uncertainty approach for a synthetic case provides a mathematical and computational framework for later real-world application, with the potential to improve both the laboratory-scale design of experiments and industrial-scale operation of mineral processing circuits without any additional hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01977v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Xu, Amir Eskanlou, Mansur Arief, David Zhen Yin, Jef K. Caers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECO: Energy-Constrained Operator Learning for Chaotic Dynamics with Boundedness Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chaos is a fundamental feature of many complex dynamical systems, including weather systems and fluid turbulence. These systems are inherently difficult to predict due to their extreme sensitivity to initial conditions. Many chaotic systems are dissipative and ergodic, motivating data-driven models that aim to learn invariant statistical properties over long time horizons. While recent models have shown empirical success in preserving invariant statistics, they are prone to generating unbounded predictions, which prevent meaningful statistics evaluation. To overcome this, we introduce the Energy-Constrained Operator (ECO) that simultaneously learns the system dynamics while enforcing boundedness in predictions. We leverage concepts from control theory to develop algebraic conditions based on a learnable energy function, ensuring the learned dynamics is dissipative. ECO enforces these algebraic conditions through an efficient closed-form quadratic projection layer, which provides provable trajectory boundedness. To our knowledge, this is the first work establishing such formal guarantees for data-driven chaotic dynamics models. Additionally, the learned invariant level set provides an outer estimate for the strange attractor, a complex structure that is computationally intractable to characterize. We demonstrate empirical success in ECO's ability to generate stable long-horizon forecasts, capturing invariant statistics on systems governed by chaotic PDEs, including the Kuramoto--Sivashinsky and the Navier--Stokes equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01984v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Goertzen, Sunbochen Tang, Navid Azizan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-SYCON: Xylem-Inspired Passive Gradient Control for Communication-Free Swarm Response in Dynamic Disaster Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00018v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present X-SYCON, a xylem-inspired multi-agent architecture in which coordination emerges from passive field dynamics rather than explicit planning or communication. Incidents (demands) and obstructions (hazards) continually write diffusing and decaying scalar fields, and agents greedily ascend a local utility $U=\phi_{\mathrm{DE}}-\kappa\,\phi_{\mathrm{HZ}}$ with light anti-congestion and separation. A beaconing rule triggered on first contact temporarily deepens the local demand sink, accelerating completion without reducing time-to-first-response. Across dynamic, partially blocked simulated environments, we observe low miss rates and stable throughput with interpretable, tunable trade-offs over carrier count, arrival rate, hazard density, and hazard sensitivity $\kappa$. We derive that a characteristic hydraulic length scale $\ell\approx\sqrt{D/\lambda}$ predicts recruitment range in a continuum approximation, and we provide a work-conservation (Ohm-law) bound consistent with sublinear capacity scaling with team size. Empirically: (i) soft hazard penalties yield fewer misses when obstacles already block motion; (ii) throughput saturates sublinearly with carriers while reliability improves sharply; (iii) stronger arrivals can reduce misses by sustaining sinks that recruit help; and (iv) phase-stability regions shrink with hazard density but are recovered by more carriers or higher arrivals. We refer to X-SYCON as an instance of Distributed Passive Computation and Control, and we evaluate it in simulations modeling communication-denied disaster response and other constrained sensing-action regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00018v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Ji Sung Baek, Geoffrey Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling and Control of Magnetic Forces between Microrobots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00051v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The independent control of multiple magnetic microrobots under a shared global signal presents critical challenges in biomedical applications such as targeted drug delivery and microsurgeries. Most existing systems only allow all agents to move synchronously, limiting their use in applications that require differentiated actuation. This research aims to design a controller capable of regulating the radial distance between micro-agents using only the angle \psi of a global magnetic field as the actuation parameter, demonstrating potential for practical applications. The proposed cascade control approach enables faster and more precise adjustment of the inter-agent distance than a proportional controller, while maintaining smooth transitions and avoiding abrupt changes in the orientation of the magnetic field, making it suitable for real-world implementation. A bibliographic review was conducted to develop the physical model, considering magnetic dipole-dipole interactions and velocities in viscous media. A PID controller was implemented to regulate the radial distance, followed by a PD controller in cascade to smooth changes in field orientation. These controllers were simulated in MATLAB, showing that the PID controller reduced convergence time to the desired radius by about 40%. When adding the second controller, the combined PID+PD scheme achieved smooth angular trajectories within similar timeframes, with fluctuations of only \pm 5^\circ. These results validate the feasibility of controlling the radial distance of two microrobots using a shared magnetic field in a fast and precise manner, without abrupt variations in the control angle. However, the model is limited to a 2D environment and two agents, suggesting future research to extend the controller to 3D systems and multiple agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00051v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amelia Fern\'andez Seguel (School of Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile), Alejandro I. Maass (School of Engineering, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing AI-Driven IoT Energy Management Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Power consumption has become a critical aspect of modern life due to the consistent reliance on technological advancements. Reducing power consumption or following power usage predictions can lead to lower monthly costs and improved electrical reliability. The proposal of a holistic framework to establish a foundation for IoT systems with a focus on contextual decision making, proactive adaptation, and scalable structure. A structured process for IoT systems with accuracy and interconnected development would support reducing power consumption and support grid stability. This study presents the feasibility of this proposal through the application of each aspect of the framework. This system would have long term forecasting, short term forecasting, anomaly detection, and consideration of qualitative data with any energy management decisions taken. Performance was evaluated on Power Consumption Time Series data to display the direct application of the framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00321v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Mruthyunjaya, Anandi Dutta, Kazi Sifatul Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive prediction theory combining offline and online learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Real-world intelligence systems usually operate by combining offline learning and online adaptation with highly correlated and non-stationary system data or signals, which, however, has rarely been investigated theoretically in the literature. This paper initiates a theoretical investigation on the prediction performance of a two-stage learning framework combining offline and online algorithms for a class of nonlinear stochastic dynamical systems. For the offline-learning phase, we establish an upper bound on the generalization error for approximate nonlinear-least-squares estimation under general datasets with strong correlation and distribution shift, leveraging the Kullback-Leibler divergence to quantify the distributional discrepancies. For the online-adaptation phase, we address, on the basis of the offline-trained model, the possible uncertain parameter drift in real-world target systems by proposing a meta-LMS prediction algorithm. This two-stage framework, integrating offline learning with online adaptation, demonstrates superior prediction performances compared with either purely offline or online methods. Both theoretical guarantees and empirical studies are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00342v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haizheng Li, Lei Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TenonOS: A Self-Generating Intelligent Embedded Operating System Framework for Edge Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00400v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid evolution of edge computing has exposed fundamental limitations in traditional operating system and hypervisor architectures, particularly in managing heterogeneous platforms and meeting the constraints of limited resources. Existing solutions often rely on monolithic or layered combinations of hypervisors and guest OSes, which are difficult to tailor for the diverse and dynamic requirements of edge scenarios. To address these challenges, we propose TenonOS, a demand-driven, self-generating, and lightweight operating system framework that fundamentally rethinks and reconstructs both the hypervisor and OS architectures. TenonOS introduces a novel LibOS-on-LibOS approach, in which both virtualization and OS functionalities are modularized into fine-grained, reusable micro-libraries. A dynamic orchestration engine composes these modules on demand to construct customized, application-specific runtime environments. At the core of TenonOS are two key components: Mortise, a minimal, modularized hypervisor, and Tenon, a real-time LibOS. Mortise provides low-overhead resource isolation, fast inter-VM communication, and manages the full lifecycle of Tenon instances - including on-demand creation, suspension, and termination - enabling TenonOS to flexibly adapt its runtime layout to workload variations. Tenon delivers deterministic scheduling and multi-process support for time-critical applications. Through this unified and modular architecture, TenonOS eliminates redundant layers, reduces system overhead, and enhances scalability, security, and maintainability. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that TenonOS achieves superior real-time scheduling (40.28% improvement), a compact memory footprint (361 KiB), and high adaptability to dynamic edge workloads, making it an ideal foundation for heterogeneous, resource-constrained edge systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00400v1</guid>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinkui Zhao, Yifan Zhang, Haidan Zhao, Hao Zhang, Qingyu Ma, Lufei Zhang, Guanjie Cheng, Shuiguang Deng, Jianwei Yin, Zuoning Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAGAS: Semantic-Aware Graph-Assisted Stitching for Offline Temporal Logic Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear Temporal Logic (LTL) provides a rigorous framework for complex robotic tasks, yet existing methods often rely on accurate dynamics models or expensive online interactions. In this work, we address LTL-constrained control in a challenging offline, model-free setting, utilizing only fixed, task-agnostic datasets of fragmented trajectories. We propose SAGAS, a novel framework combining graph-assisted trajectory stitching with automata-guided planning. First, we construct a latent reachability graph from a learned temporal-distance representation. To bridge the semantic gap, we augment this graph with certified anchor nodes and probabilistic soft labels. We then translate the specification into a B\"uchi automaton and search the implicit product space to derive a cost-minimal prefix-suffix plan. Finally, a subgoal-conditioned low-level policy is deployed to execute these latent waypoints. Experiments on OGBench locomotion domains demonstrate that SAGAS successfully synthesizes efficient trajectories for diverse LTL tasks, effectively bridging the gap between fragmented offline data and complex logical constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00775v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijia Liu, Ancheng Hou, Shaoyuan Li, Xiang Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel MDP Decomposition Framework for Scalable UAV Mission Planning in Complex and Uncertain Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a scalable and fault-tolerant framework for unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) mission management in complex and uncertain environments. The proposed approach addresses the computational bottleneck inherent in solving large-scale Markov Decision Processes (MDPs) by introducing a two-stage decomposition strategy. In the first stage, a factor-based algorithm partitions the global MDP into smaller, goal-specific sub-MDPs by leveraging domain-specific features such as goal priority, fault states, spatial layout, and energy constraints. In the second stage, a priority-based recombination algorithm solves each sub-MDP independently and integrates the results into a unified global policy using a meta-policy for conflict resolution. Importantly, we present a theoretical analysis showing that, under mild probabilistic independence assumptions, the combined policy is provably equivalent to the optimal global MDP policy. Our work advances artificial intelligence (AI) decision scalability by decomposing large MDPs into tractable subproblems with provable global equivalence. The proposed decomposition framework enhances the scalability of Markov Decision Processes, a cornerstone of sequential decision-making in artificial intelligence, enabling real-time policy updates for complex mission environments. Extensive simulations validate the effectiveness of our method, demonstrating orders-of-magnitude reduction in computation time without sacrificing mission reliability or policy optimality. The proposed framework establishes a practical and robust foundation for scalable decision-making in real-time UAV mission execution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00838v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Muzakkir Quamar, Ali Nasir, Sami ELFerik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Causal Foundation Model in Prescriptive Maintenance Framework for Optimizing Production Line OEE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00969v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The transition to prescriptive maintenance in manufacturing is critically constrained by a dependence on predictive models. These models tend to rely on spurious correlations rather than identifying the true causal drivers of failures, often leading to costly misdiagnoses and ineffective interventions. This fundamental limitation results in a key-challenge: while we can predict that a failure may occur, we lack a systematic method to understand why a failure occurs, thereby providing the basis for identifying the most effective intervention. This paper proposes a model based on causal machine learning to bridge this gap. Our objective is to move beyond diagnosis to active prescription by simulating and evaluating potential fixes toward optimizing KPIs such as Overall Equipment Effectiveness (OEE). For this purpose a pre-trained causal foundation model is used as a "what-if" model to estimate the effects of potential fixes. By measuring the causal effect of each intervention on system-level KPIs, it provides a data-driven ranking of actions to recommend at the production line. This process not only identifies root causes but also quantifies their operational impact. The model is evaluated using semi-synthetic manufacturing data and compared with a baseline machine learning model. This paper sets the technical basis for a robust prescriptive maintenance framework, allowing engineers to test potential solutions in a causal environment to make more effective operational decisions and reduce costly downtimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00969v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Saretzky, Lucas Andersen, Thomas Engel, Fazel Ansari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LPWAN based IoT Architecture for Distributed Energy Monitoring in Deep Indoor Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00998v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Continuous energy monitoring is essential for identifying potential savings and predicting the energy requirements of buildings. Energy meters are often located in underground spaces that are difficult to reach with wireless technology. This paper presents an experimental study comparing different Low Power Wide Area Networks (LPWAN) technologies in terms of building penetration and radio coverage. The technologies Low Power Long Range Wide Area Networks (LoRaWAN), Narrow Band Internet of Things (NB-IoT), Sigfox 0G and Wireless Smart Ubiquitous Networks (Wi-SUN) are evaluated experimentally. It also proposes a distributed hybrid IoT architecture that combines multiple LPWAN technologies using an abstraction layer to optimize cost and coverage. Communication is message-based using the publish-subscribe messaging pattern. It is implemented using the MQTT protocol. The abstraction layer decodes the proprietary binary data and converts it to a normalized JSON format.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00998v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christof R\"ohrig, Benz Cramer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning for Gliding Projectile Guidance and Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the development of a control law, which is intended to be implemented on an optical guided glider. This guiding law follows an innovative approach, the reinforcement learning. This control law is used to make navigation more flexible and autonomous in a dynamic environment. The final objective is to track a target detected with the camera and then guide the glider to this point with high precision. Already applied on quad-copter drones, we wish by this study to demonstrate the applicability of reinforcement learning for fixed-wing aircraft on all of its axis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01066v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel Cahn, Antonin Thomas, Philippe Pastor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian dynamic scheduling of multipurpose batch processes under incomplete look-ahead information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multipurpose batch processes become increasingly popular in manufacturing industries since they adapt to low-volume, high-value products and shifting demands. These processes often operate in a dynamic environment, which faces disturbances such as processing delays and demand changes. To minimise long-term cost and system nervousness (i.e., disruptive changes to schedules), schedulers must design rescheduling strategies to address such disturbances effectively. Existing methods often assume complete look-ahead information over the scheduling horizon. This assumption contrasts with realistic situations where schedulers can only access incomplete look-ahead information. Sticking with existing methods may lead to suboptimal long-term costs and high-level system nervousness. In this work we propose a Bayesian dynamic scheduling method. Our method relies on learning a Bayesian Network from the probability distribution of disturbances. Specifically, the Bayesian Network represents how likely each operation will be impacted by disturbances. During the online execution, when new disturbances become observed, this method updates the posterior distribution and therefore guides the rescheduling strategy. We compare our method with the existing periodic rescheduling strategy (which generates new schedules from scratch at fixed intervals) on four benchmark problems. Computational results show that our method achieves statistically better long-term costs and system nervousness. In the theoretical aspect, we prove that if disturbances are mutually independent, the impact-quantifying variables inherently satisfy the independence assumptions required by Bayesian Networks. As an implication, practitioners can extend the method to other scheduling problems (such as job shop scheduling and continuous processes), given that they define the problem-specific dependencies between operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01093v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taicheng Zheng, Dan Li, Jie Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reverse Engineering and Control-Aware Security Analysis of the ArduPilot UAV Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV) technologies are gaining high interest for many domains, which makes UAV security of utmost importance. ArduPilot is among the most widely used open-source autopilot UAV frameworks; yet, many studies demonstrate the vulnerabilities affecting such systems. Vulnerabilities within its communication subsystems (including WiFi, telemetry, or GPS) expose critical entry points, and vulnerabilities in Ardupilot can affect the control procedure. In this paper, we reconstruct the software architecture and the control models implemented by ArduPilot and then examine how these control models could potentially misused to induce malicious behaviors while relying on legitimate inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01164v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasaswini Konapalli, Lotfi Ben Othmane, Cihan Tunc, Feras Benchellal, Likhita Mudagere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A TinyML Reinforcement Learning Approach for Energy-Efficient Light Control in Low-Cost Greenhouse Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01167v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study presents a reinforcement learning (RL)-based control strategy for adaptive lighting regulation in controlled environments using a low-power microcontroller. A model-free Q-learning algorithm was implemented to dynamically adjust the brightness of a Light-Emitting Diode (LED) based on real-time feedback from a light-dependent resistor (LDR) sensor. The system was trained to stabilize at 13 distinct light intensity levels (L1 to L13), with each target corresponding to a specific range within the 64-state space derived from LDR readings. A total of 130 trials were conducted, covering all target levels with 10 episodes each. Performance was evaluated in terms of convergence speed, steps taken, and time required to reach target states. Box plots and histograms were generated to analyze the distribution of training time and learning efficiency across targets. Experimental validation demonstrated that the agent could effectively learn to stabilize at varying light levels with minimal overshooting and smooth convergence, even in the presence of environmental perturbations. This work highlights the feasibility of lightweight, on-device RL for energy-efficient lighting control and sets the groundwork for multi-modal environmental control applications in resource-constrained agricultural systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01167v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/INTCEC65580.2025.11256135</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Abdallah Salem (North Dakota State University), Manuel Cuevas Perez (North Dakota State University), Ahmed Harb Rabia (North Dakota State University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pascal-Weighted Genetic Algorithms: A Binomially-Structured Recombination Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01249v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new family of multi-parent recombination operators for Genetic Algorithms (GAs), based on normalized Pascal (binomial) coefficients. Unlike classical two-parent crossover operators, Pascal-Weighted Recombination (PWR) forms offsprings as structured convex combination of multiple parents, using binomially shaped weights that emphasize central inheritance while suppressing disruptive variance. We develop a mathematical framework for PWR, derive variance-transfer properties, and analyze its effect on schema survival. The operator is extended to real-valued, binary/logit, and permutation representations.
  We evaluate the proposed method on four representative benchmarks: (i) PID controller tuning evaluated using the ITAE metric, (ii) FIR low-pass filter design under magnitude-response constraints, (iii) wireless power-modulation optimization under SINR coupling, and (iv) the Traveling Salesman Problem (TSP). We demonstrate how, across these benchmarks, PWR consistently yields smoother convergence, reduced variance, and achieves 9-22% performance gains over standard recombination operators. The approach is simple, algorithm-agnostic, and readily integrable into diverse GA architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01249v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Otman A. Basir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RE-LLM: Integrating Large Language Models into Renewable Energy Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy system models are increasingly employed to guide long-term planning in multi-sectoral environments where decisions span electricity, heat, transport, land use, and industry. While these models provide rigorous quantitative insights, their outputs are often highly technical, making them difficult to interpret for non-expert stakeholders such as policymakers, planners, and the public. This communication gap limits the accessibility and practical impact of scenario-based modeling, particularly as energy transitions grow more complex with rising shares of renewables, sectoral integration, and deep uncertainties. To address this challenge, we propose the Renewable Energy Large Language Model (RE-LLM), a hybrid framework that integrates Large Language Models (LLMs) directly into the energy system modeling workflow. RE-LLM combines three core elements: (i) optimization-based scenario exploration, (ii) machine learning surrogates that accelerate computationally intensive simulations, and (iii) LLM-powered natural language generation that translates complex results into clear, stakeholder-oriented explanations. This integrated design not only reduces computational burden but also enhances inter-pretability, enabling real-time reasoning about trade-offs, sensitivities, and policy implications. The framework is adaptable across different optimization platforms and energy system models, ensuring broad applicability beyond the case study presented. By merging speed, rigor, and interpretability, RE-LLM advances a new paradigm of human-centric energy modeling. It enables interactive, multilingual, and accessible engagement with future energy pathways, ultimately bridging the final gap between data-driven analysis and actionable decision-making for sustainable transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01392v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Forootani, Mohammad Sadr, Danial Esmaeili Aliabadi, Daniela Thraen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Value of Communication in Goal-Oriented Semantic Communications: A Pareto Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Emerging cyber-physical systems increasingly operate under stringent communication constraints that preclude the reliable transmission of their extensive machine-type data streams. Since raw measurements often contain correlated or redundant components, effective operation depends not on transmitting all available data but on selecting the information that contributes to achieving the objectives of the system. Beyond accuracy, goal-oriented semantic communication assesses the \emph{value of information} and aims to generate and transmit only what is relevant and at the right time. Motivated by this perspective, this work studies the \emph{value of communication} through the canonical setting of remote estimation of Markov sources, where a value-of-information measure quantifies the relevance of information. We investigate how optimal estimation performance varies with the available communication budget and determine the marginal performance gain attributable to additional communication. Our approach is based on a \emph{Pareto analysis} that characterizes the complete set of policies that achieve optimal trade-offs between estimation performance and communication cost. The value of communication is defined as the absolute slope of the resulting Pareto frontier. Although computing this frontier is non-trivial, we demonstrate that in our setting it admits a notably tractable structure: it is strictly decreasing, convex, and piecewise linear, and its slope is governed by a finite collection of constants. Moreover, each Pareto-optimal operating point is realizable as a convex combination of two stationary deterministic policies, enabling practical implementation. Leveraging these structural insights, we introduce SPLIT, an efficient and provably optimal algorithm for constructing the complete Pareto frontier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01454v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiping Luo, Bowen Li, Nikolaos Pappas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On robotic manipulators with time-dependent inertial parameters: From physical consistency to boundedness of the mass matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01482v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We generalize the robotics equation describing the dynamics of an open kinematic chain to include the effect of time-dependent change of inertial parameters as well as the effects of its cause, i.e. time dependency of the distributions of mass originating from parasitic movements of mass-carrying particles. The results generate insight that allows linking the novel concepts of uniform physical consistency and upper boundedness of inertial parameters -- ruling out approaching the edge to physical inconsistency or to diverge -- with the existence of finite, positive uniform bounds of the mass matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01482v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Kaufmann, Johann Reger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combined Effects of Transient Ionizing and Electromagnetic Pulse on Vertical NPN Bipolar Transistor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Combined effects of transient ionizing and electromagnetic pulse on vertical NPN bipolar transistor were experimentally investigated under pulsed X-ray irradiation. Technology computer-aided design (TCAD) simulation method was also employed to explore the underlying physical mechanisms. The results demonstrate that the combined effect of a positive pulse injected into the collector (CEMP) and pulsed X-ray irradiation exceeds the linear superposition of their individual effects. Conversely, the combined effect of a positive pulse injected into the base (BEMP) and pulsed X-ray irradiation aligns closely with the results observed under BEMP acting alone. Mechanism analysis reveals that when CEMP and pulsed X-ray irradiation act simultaneously, there is a significant increase in both the drift photocurrent at the collector junction and the diffusion photocurrent near the collector junction. However, when BEMP and pulsed X-ray irradiation act simultaneously, these photocurrent components remain small, leading to a combined effect similar to the results observed when BEMP acts alone. These findings provide critical insights for the radiation-hardening design of bipolar circuits in harsh radiation environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01573v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meiqing Zhong, Cui Meng, Yinong Liu, Lanfeng Yuan, Chicheng Liu, Bolun Feng, Maoxing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Multi-Layer Defence Framework for Securing Near-Real-Time Operations in Open RAN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01596v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Securing the near-real-time (near-RT) control operations in Open Radio Access Networks (Open RAN) is increasingly critical, yet remains insufficiently addressed, as new runtime threats target the control loop while the system is operational. In this paper, we propose a multi-layer defence framework designed to enhance the security of near-RT RAN Intelligent Controller (RIC) operations. We classify operational-time threats into three categories, message-level, data-level, and control logic-level, and design and implement a dedicated detection and mitigation component for each: a signature-based E2 message inspection module performing structural and semantic validation of signalling exchanges, a telemetry poisoning detector based on temporal anomaly scoring using an LSTM network, and a runtime xApp attestation mechanism based on execution-time hash challenge-response. The framework is evaluated on an O-RAN testbed comprising FlexRIC and a commercial RAN emulator, demonstrating effective detection rates, low latency overheads, and practical integration feasibility. Results indicate that the proposed safeguards can operate within near-RT time constraints while significantly improving protection against runtime attacks, introducing less than 80 ms overhead for a network with 500 User Equipment (UEs). Overall, this work lays the foundation for deployable, layered, and policy-driven runtime security architectures for the near-RT RIC control loop in Open RAN, and provides an extensible framework into which future mitigation policies and threat-specific modules can be integrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01596v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Alimohammadi, Samara Mayhoub, Sotiris Chatzimiltis, Mohammad Shojafar, Muhammad Nasir Mumtaz Bhutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated YOLOP Perception and Lyapunov-based Control for Autonomous Mobile Robot Navigation on Track</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents a real-time autonomous track navigation framework for nonholonomic differential-drive mobile robots by jointly integrating multi-task visual perception and a provably stable tracking controller. The perception pipeline reconstructs lane centerlines using 2D-to-3D camera projection, arc-length based uniform point resampling, and cubic polynomial fitting solved via robust QR least-squares optimization. The controller regulates robot linear and angular velocities through a Lyapunov-stability grounded design, ensuring bounded error dynamics and asymptotic convergence of position and heading deviations even in dynamic and partially perceived lane scenarios, without relying on HD prior maps or global satellite localization. Real-world experiments on embedded platforms verify system fidelity, real-time execution, trajectory smoothness, and closed-loop stability for reliable autonomous navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mo Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Ambiguity Contraction-based Adaptive Robust Markov Decision Processes for Adversarial Surveillance Missions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Collaborative Combat Aircraft (CCAs) are envisioned to enable autonomous Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance (ISR) missions in contested environments, where adversaries may act strategically to deceive or evade detection. These missions pose challenges due to model uncertainty and the need for safe, real-time decision-making. Robust Markov Decision Processes (RMDPs) provide worst-case guarantees but are limited by static ambiguity sets that capture initial uncertainty without adapting to new observations. This paper presents an adaptive RMDP framework tailored to ISR missions with CCAs. We introduce a mission-specific formulation in which aircraft alternate between movement and sensing states. Adversarial tactics are modeled as a finite set of transition kernels, each capturing assumptions about how adversarial sensing or environmental conditions affect rewards. Our approach incrementally refines policies by eliminating inconsistent threat models, allowing agents to shift from conservative to aggressive behaviors while maintaining robustness. We provide theoretical guarantees showing that the adaptive planner converges as credible sets contract to the true threat and maintains safety under uncertainty. Experiments under Gaussian and non-Gaussian threat models across diverse network topologies show higher mission rewards and fewer exposure events compared to nominal and static robust planners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01660v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jimin Choi, Max Z. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Log-Gaussian Process Control Barrier Function for Safe Robotic Navigation in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01668v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) have emerged as efficient tools to address the safe navigation problem for robot applications. However, synthesizing informative and obstacle motion-aware CBFs online using real-time sensor data remains challenging, particularly in unknown and dynamic scenarios. Motived by this challenge, this paper aims to propose a novel Gaussian Process-based formulation of CBF, termed the Dynamic Log Gaussian Process Control Barrier Function (DLGP-CBF), to enable real-time construction of CBF which are both spatially informative and responsive to obstacle motion. Firstly, the DLGP-CBF leverages a logarithmic transformation of GP regression to generate smooth and informative barrier values and gradients, even in sparse-data regions. Secondly, by explicitly modeling the DLGP-CBF as a function of obstacle positions, the derived safety constraint integrates predicted obstacle velocities, allowing the controller to proactively respond to dynamic obstacles' motion. Simulation results demonstrate significant improvements in obstacle avoidance performance, including increased safety margins, smoother trajectories, and enhanced responsiveness compared to baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01668v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Yin, Chenyang Liang, Yanning Guo, Jie Mei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experiment design using prior knowledge on controllability and stabilizability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01876v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the problem of designing input signals for an unknown linear time-invariant system in such a way that the resulting input-state data is suitable for identification or stabilization. We will take into account prior knowledge on system-theoretic properties of the system, in particular, controllability and stabilizability. For this, we extend the notion of universal inputs to incorporate prior knowledge on the system. An input is called universal for identification (resp., stabilization) if, when applied to any system complying with the prior knowledge, it results in data suitable for identification (resp., stabilization) regardless of the initial condition. We provide a full characterization of such universal inputs. In addition, we discuss online experiment design using prior knowledge, and we study cases where this approach results in the shortest possible experiment for identification and stabilization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01876v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Shakouri, Henk J. van Waarde, M. Kanat Camlibel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeuroHJR: Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability-based Obstacle Avoidance in Complex Environments with Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous ground vehicles (AGVs) must navigate safely in cluttered environments while accounting for complex dynamics and environmental uncertainty. Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability (HJR) offers formal safety guarantees through the computation of forward and backward reachable sets, but its application is hindered by poor scalability in environments with numerous obstacles. In this paper, we present a novel framework called NeuroHJR that leverages Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) to approximate the HJR solution for real-time obstacle avoidance. By embedding system dynamics and safety constraints directly into the neural network loss function, our method bypasses the need for grid-based discretization and enables efficient estimation of reachable sets in continuous state spaces. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach through simulation results in densely cluttered scenarios, showing that it achieves safety performance comparable to that of classical HJR solvers while significantly reducing the computational cost. This work provides a new step toward real-time, scalable deployment of reachability-based obstacle avoidance in robotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01897v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Granthik Halder, Rudrashis Majumder, Rakshith M R, Rahi Shah, Suresh Sundaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Markov Models for Stock Market Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03775v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The stock market presents a challenging environment for accurately predicting future stock prices due to its intricate and ever-changing nature. However, the utilization of advanced methodologies can significantly enhance the precision of stock price predictions. One such method is Hidden Markov Models (HMMs). HMMs are statistical models that can be used to model the behavior of a partially observable system, making them suitable for modeling stock prices based on historical data. Accurate stock price predictions can help traders make better investment decisions, leading to increased profits. In this article, we trained and tested a Hidden Markov Model for the purpose of predicting a stock closing price based on its opening price and the preceding day's prices. The model's performance has been evaluated using two indicators: Mean Average Prediction Error (MAPE), which specifies the average accuracy of our model, and Directional Prediction Accuracy (DPA), a newly introduced indicator that accounts for the number of fractional change predictions that are correct in sign.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03775v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Catello, Ludovica Ruggiero, Lucia Schiavone, Mario Valentino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing Demand Response Capability of Thermostatically Controlled Loads with Reach and Hold Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aggregations of thermostatically controlled loads (TCLs), such as air conditioners, offer valuable flexibility to the power grid. The aggregate power consumption of a TCL fleet can be controlled by adjusting thermostat setpoints. An ex-ante quantification of the flexibility that results from such setpoint change can inform grid operator decisions. This paper develops a rigorous, yet practical method to quantify flexibility in terms of the `reach-and-hold' set of TCL aggregations, which defines how much power can be shifted (reach) and for how long (hold). To quantify the reach-and-hold set, we employ a Markov-chain-based model of the TCL aggregation that captures second-order TCL dynamics, enabling accurate characterization of reach-and-hold sets. A tractable optimization problem is then formulated to numerically compute an inner approximation of these sets. Simulation results validate that our method accurately characterizes the fleet's flexibility and effectively controls its power consumption. Furthermore, a robustness analysis is carried out to investigate the effects of uncertainty in initial conditions and TCL parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12444v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mazen Elsaadany, Hamid R. Ossareh, Mads R. Almassalkhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Dissipative Chaotic Dynamics with Boundedness Guarantee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00976v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chaotic dynamics, commonly seen in weather systems and fluid turbulence, are characterized by their sensitivity to initial conditions, which makes accurate prediction challenging. Recent approaches have focused on developing data-driven models that attempt to preserve invariant statistics over long horizons since many chaotic systems exhibit dissipative behaviors and ergodicity. Despite the recent progress in such models, they are still often prone to generating unbounded trajectories, leading to invalid statistics evaluation. To address this fundamental challenge, we introduce a modular framework that provides formal guarantees of trajectory boundedness for neural network chaotic dynamics models. Our core contribution is a dissipative projection layer that leverages control-theoretic principles to ensure the learned system is dissipative. Specifically, our framework simultaneously learns a dynamics emulator and an energy-like function, where the latter is used to construct an algebraic dissipative constraint within the projection layer. Furthermore, the learned invariant level set provides an outer estimate for the system's strange attractor, which is known to be difficult to characterize due to its complex geometry. We demonstrate our model's ability to produce bounded long-horizon forecasts that preserve invariant statistics for chaotic dynamical systems, including Lorenz 96 and a reduced-order model of the Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00976v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunbochen Tang, Themistoklis Sapsis, Navid Azizan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aggregative games with bilevel structures: Distributed algorithms and convergence analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13776v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the problem of distributively seeking the equilibria of aggregative games with bilevel structures is studied. Different from the traditional aggregative games, here the aggregation is determined by the minimizer of a virtual leader's objective function in the inner level, which depends on the actions of the players in the outer level. Moreover, the global objective function of the virtual leader is formed by the sum of some local functions with two arguments, each of which is strongly convex with respect to the second argument. When making decisions, each player in the outer level only has access to a local part of the virtual leader's objective function. To handle this problem, first, we propose a second order gradient-based distributed algorithm, where the Hessian matrices associated with the objective functions of the leader are involved. By the algorithm, players update their actions while cooperatively minimizing the objective function of the virtual leader to estimate the aggregation by communicating with their neighbors via a connected graph. Under mild assumptions on the graph and cost functions, we prove that the actions of players asymptotically converge to the Nash equilibrium point. Then, for the case where the Hessian matrices associated with the objective functions of the virtual leader are not available, we propose a first order gradient-based distributed algorithm, where a distributed two-point estimate strategy is developed to estimate the gradients of players' cost functions in the outer level. Under the same conditions, we prove that the convergence errors of players' actions to the Nash equilibrium point are linear with respect to the estimate parameters. Finally, simulations are provided to demonstrate the effectiveness of our theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13776v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaihong Lu, Huanshui Zhang, Long Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Hierarchical Multi-Agent Decision-Making for Uncertainty-Aware EV Charging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18047v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in bidirectional EV charging and discharging systems have spurred interest in workplace applications. However, real-world deployments face various dynamic factors, such as fluctuating electricity prices and uncertain EV departure times, that hinder effective energy management. To address these issues and minimize building electricity costs while meeting EV charging requirements, we design a hierarchical multi-agent structure in which a high-level agent coordinates overall charge or discharge decisions based on real-time pricing, while multiple low-level agents manage individual power level accordingly. For uncertain EV departure times, we propose a novel uncertainty-aware critic augmentation mechanism for low-level agents that improves the evaluation of power-level decisions and ensures robust control under such uncertainty. Building upon these two key designs, we introduce HUCA, a real-time charging control framework that coordinates energy supply among the building and EVs. Experiments on real-world electricity datasets show that HUCA significantly reduces electricity costs and maintains competitive performance in meeting EV charging requirements under both simulated certain and uncertain departure scenarios. The results further highlight the importance of hierarchical control and the proposed critic augmentation under the uncertain departure scenario. A case study illustrates HUCA's capability to allocate energy between the building and EVs in real time, underscoring its potential for practical use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18047v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo Pang-Yun Ting, Ali \c{S}enol, Huan-Yang Wang, Hsu-Chao Lai, Kun-Ta Chuang, Huan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Experiment Design for Nonlinear System Identification with Operational Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20941v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the joint problem of online experiment design and parameter estimation for identifying nonlinear system models, while adhering to system constraints. We utilize a receding horizon approach and propose a new adaptive input design criterion, which is tailored to continuously updated parameter estimates, along with a new sequential estimator. We demonstrate the ability of the method to design informative experiments online, while steering the system within operational constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20941v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingwei Hu, Dave Zachariah, Torbj\"orn Wigren, Petre Stoica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set-based and Dynamical Feedback-augmented Hands-off Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11795v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A novel set-theoretical approach to hands-off control is proposed, focusing on spatial arguments for command limitation rather than temporal ones. By employing dynamical feedback alongside invariant set-based constraints, actuation is employed only to drive the system's state within a "hands-off region" of its state-space, where the plant can freely evolve in open-loop configuration. A computationally-efficient procedure with strong theoretical guarantees is devised, and its effectiveness is showcased via an intuitive practical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11795v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Speril\u{a}, Sorin Olaru, St\'ephane Drobot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L2RU: a Structured State Space Model with prescribed L2-bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23818v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Structured state-space models (SSMs) have recently emerged as a powerful architecture at the intersection of machine learning and control, featuring layers composed of discrete-time linear time-invariant (LTI) systems followed by pointwise nonlinearities. These models combine the expressiveness of deep neural networks with the interpretability and inductive bias of dynamical systems, offering strong performance on long-sequence tasks with favorable computational complexity. However, their adoption in applications such as system identification and optimal control remains limited by the difficulty of enforcing stability and robustness in a principled and tractable manner.
  We introduce L2RU, a class of SSMs endowed with a prescribed $\mathcal{L}_2$-gain bound, guaranteeing input--output stability and robustness for all parameter values. The L2RU architecture is derived from free parametrizations of LTI systems satisfying an $\mathcal{L}_2$ constraint, enabling unconstrained optimization via standard gradient-based methods while preserving rigorous stability guarantees. Specifically, we develop two complementary parametrizations: a non-conservative formulation that provides a complete characterization of square LTI systems with a given $\mathcal{L}_2$-bound, and a conservative formulation that extends the approach to general (possibly non-square) systems while improving computational efficiency through a structured representation of the system matrices.
  Both parametrizations admit efficient initialization schemes that facilitate training long-memory models. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed framework on a nonlinear system identification benchmark, where L2RU achieves improved performance and training stability compared to existing SSM architectures, highlighting its potential as a principled and robust building block for learning and control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23818v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Massai, Muhammad Zakwan, Giancarlo Ferrari-Trecate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature-Constrained Vector Field for Motion Planning of Nonholonomic Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02852v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vector fields are advantageous in handling nonholonomic motion planning as they provide reference orientation for robots. However, additionally incorporating curvature constraints becomes challenging, due to the interconnection between the design of the curvature-bounded vector field and the tracking controller under underactuation. In this paper, we present a novel framework to co-develop the vector field and the control laws, guiding the nonholonomic robot to the target configuration with curvature-bounded trajectory. First, we formulate the problem by introducing the target positive limit set, which allows the robot to converge to or pass through the target configuration, depending on different dynamics and tasks. Next, we construct a curvature-constrained vector field (CVF) via blending and distributing basic flow fields in workspace and propose the saturated control laws with a dynamic gain, under which the tracking error's magnitude decreases even when saturation occurs. Under the control laws, kinematically constrained nonholonomic robots are guaranteed to track the reference CVF and converge to the target positive limit set with bounded trajectory curvature. Numerical simulations show that the proposed CVF method outperforms other vector-field-based algorithms. Experiments on Ackermann UGVs and semi-physical fixed-wing UAVs demonstrate that the method can be effectively implemented in real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02852v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yike Qiao, Xiaodong He, An Zhuo, Zhiyong Sun, Weimin Bao, Zhongkui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cyber Insurance Policy for Hedging Against Load-Altering Attacks and Extreme Load Variations in Distribution Grids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04287v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Uncertainties in renewable energy resources (RES) and load variations can lead to elevated system operational costs. Moreover, the emergence of large-scale distributed threats, such as load-altering attacks (LAAs), can induce substantial load variations, further exacerbating these costs. Although traditional defense measures can reduce the likelihood of such attacks, considerable residual risks remain. Thus, this paper proposes a cyber insurance framework designed to hedge against additional operational costs resulting from LAAs and substantial load variations in renewable-rich grids. The insurance framework determines both the insurance coverage and premium based on the Value at Risk (VaR) and Tail Value at Risk (TVaR). These risk metrics are calculated using the system failure probability and the probability density function (PDF) of the system operation cost. The system failure probability is assessed through a semi-Markov process (SMP), while the cost distribution is estimated through a cost minimization model of a distribution grid combined with a Monte Carlo simulation to capture load variability. Furthermore, we employ a bi-level optimization scheme that identifies the specific load distribution leading to the maximum system cost, thereby enhancing the accuracy of the operation cost PDF estimation. The effectiveness and scalability of the proposed cyber insurance policy are evaluated considering a modified IEEE 118-bus test system and the IEEE European low-voltage (LV) test feeder model. The case study shows that with a relatively low premium, the network operator can hedge against additional operational costs caused by malicious load manipulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04287v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijie Pan, Zaint A. Alexakis, S Subhash Lakshminarayana, Charalambos Konstantinou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A distributed motion planning approach to cooperative underwater acoustic source tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate tracking of underwater acoustic sources is critical for a variety of marine applications, yet remains a challenging task due to communication constraints and environmental uncertainties. In this regard, this paper addresses the problem of underwater acoustic source tracking using a team of autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs). The core idea is to optimize the guidance of each agent to achieve coordinated motion planning that leads to optimal geometric configurations with respect to the target, thereby enhancing tracking performance. To tackle this, we propose a Distributed Model Predictive Control (DMPC) framework to improve performance and robustness. The control problem is formulated as a multi-objective optimization task, incorporating geometric observability, proximity to the target, and communication connectivity. A Receding Horizon Control (RHC) approach, coupled with an Unscented Transform (UT)-based prediction scheme, is employed to ensure longterm tracking accuracy while accounting for uncertainties. The optimization is distributed using the sequential multi-agent decision-making framework, combined with the Time-Division Multiple Access (TDMA) communication protocol. The proposed methodology is implemented in a simulation environment that accounts for the constraints of acoustic communication. The approach is compared with existing methods such as decentralized MPC and Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07877v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.oceaneng.2025.123305</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Tiranti, Andrea, et al. "A distributed motion planning approach to cooperative underwater acoustic source tracking." Ocean Engineering 344 (2026): 123305</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Tiranti, Francesco Wanderlingh, Enrico Simetti, Marco Baglietto, Giovanni Indiveri, Antonio Pascoal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make Your AUV Adaptive: An Environment-Aware Reinforcement Learning Framework For Underwater Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15082v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents a novel environment-aware reinforcement learning (RL) framework designed to augment the operational capabilities of autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs) in underwater environments. Departing from traditional RL architectures, the proposed framework integrates an environment-aware network module that dynamically captures flow field data, effectively embedding this critical environmental information into the state space. This integration facilitates real-time environmental adaptation, significantly enhancing the AUV's situational awareness and decision-making capabilities. Furthermore, the framework incorporates AUV structure characteristics into the optimization process, employing a large language model (LLM)-based iterative refinement mechanism that leverages both environmental conditions and training outcomes to optimize task performance. Comprehensive experimental evaluations demonstrate the framework's superior performance, robustness and adaptability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15082v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yimian Ding, Jingzehua Xu, Guanwen Xie, Shuai Zhang, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision-Focused Learning for Neural Network-Constrained HVAC Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19717v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning (HVAC) is a major electricity end-use with a substantial potential for providing grid services, such as demand response. Harnessing this flexibility requires accurate modeling of the thermal dynamics of buildings, a difficult task because nonlinear heat transfer and recurring daily cycles make historical data highly correlated and insufficient to generalize to new weather, occupancy, and control scenarios. This paper presents an HVAC management system formulated as a Mixed Integer Quadratic Program (MIQP), where Neural Network (NN) models of thermal dynamics are embedded as exact mixed-integer linear constraints. Unlike traditional training approaches that minimize prediction errors, we employ Decision-Focused Learning (DFL) to learn the NN parameters with the objective of directly improving the HVAC cost performance. However, the discrete nature of MIQP hinders DFL, as it leads to undefined and discontinuous gradients, thus impeding standard gradient-based training. We leverage Stochastic Smoothing (SS) to enable efficient gradient computation without the need to differentiate the MIQP. Experiments on a realistic five-zone building using a high-fidelity simulator demonstrate that the proposed SS-DFL approach outperforms conventional identify-then-optimize (i.e., the thermal dynamics model is identified on historical data then used in optimization) and relaxed DFL methods in both cost savings and grid service performance, highlighting its potential for scalable, grid-aware building control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19717v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Favaro, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Toubeau, Fran\c{c}ois Vall\'ee, Yury Dvorkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Linear Programming Framework for Optimal Event-Triggered LQG Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10671v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This letter explores intelligent scheduling of sensor-to-controller communication in networked control systems, particularly when data transmission incurs a cost. While the optimal controller in a standard linear quadratic Gaussian (LQG) setup can be computed analytically, determining the optimal times to transmit sensor data remains computationally and analytically challenging. We show that, through reformulation and the introduction of auxiliary binary variables, the scheduling problem can be cast as a computationally efficient mixed-integer linear program (MILP). This formulation not only simplifies the analysis but also reveals structural insights and provides clear decision criteria at each step. Embedding the approach within a model predictive control (MPC) framework enables dynamic adaptation, and we prove that the resulting scheduler performs at least as well as any deterministic strategy (e.g., periodic strategy). Simulation results further demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms traditional periodic scheduling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10671v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Hashemi, Dipankar Maity</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Convergence of Policy Gradient for Entropy Regularized Linear-Quadratic Control with Multiplicative Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02896v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) has emerged as a powerful framework for sequential decision-making in dynamic environments, particularly when system parameters are unknown. This paper investigates RL-based control for entropy-regularized linear-quadratic (LQ) control problems with multiplicative noise over an infinite time horizon. First, we adapt the regularized policy gradient (RPG) algorithm to stochastic optimal control settings, proving that despite the non-convexity of the problem, RPG converges globally under conditions of gradient domination and almost-smoothness. Second, based on zero-order optimization approach, we introduce a novel model free RL algorithm: Sample-based regularized policy gradient (SB-RPG). SB-RPG operates without knowledge of system parameters yet still retains strong theoretical guarantees of global convergence. Our model leverages entropy regularization to address the exploration versus exploitation trade-off inherent in RL. Numerical simulations validate the theoretical results and demonstrate the efficiency of SB-RPG in unknown-parameters environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02896v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Diaz, Lucky Li, Wenhao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PolyOCP.jl -- A Julia Package for Stochastic OCPs and MPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19084v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The consideration of stochastic uncertainty in optimal and predictive control is a well-explored topic. Recently Polynomial Chaos Expansions (PCE) have seen a lot of considerations for problems involving stochastically uncertain system parameters and also for problems with additive stochastic i.i.d. disturbances. While there exist a number of open-source PCE toolboxes, tailored open-source codes for the solution of OCPs involving additive stochastic i.i.d. disturbances in julia are not available. Hence, this paper introduces the toolbox \texttt{PolyOCP.jl} which enables to efficiently solve stochastic OCPs for a large class of disturbance distributions. We explain the main mathematical concepts between the PCE transcription of stochastic OCPs and how they are provided in the toolbox. We draw upon two examples to illustrate the functionalities of \texttt{PolyOCP.jl}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19084v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruchuan Ou, Learta Januzi, Jonas Schie{\ss}l, Michael Heinrich Baumann, Lars Gr\"une, Timm Faulwasser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Technical and Environmental Impacts of Energy Management Systems in Smart Ports</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20043v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A vital strategy for ports to mitigate the environmental impact of the maritime industry, while complying with frameworks such as the European Green Deal and the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), entails the systematic implementation of comprehensive energy management solutions. This paper provides a baseline evaluation of the energy management systems (EMSs) implementation and their impact on energy consumption, carbon emissions, and operational costs in smart ports. Initially, we provide a systematic review of the literature focusing on case studies from prominent ports, including Hamburg, Genoa, Jurong, and Shanghai Yangshan Phase IV. The analysis emphasises key aspects such as energy efficiency, reductions in emissions, and the minimization of operational costs. Subsequently, we formulate an optimisation model to simulate load dispatch, carbon emission reduction, and transport scheduling. Results indicate that EMS deployment reduces annual energy consumption and carbon emissions significantly by approximately 7%-8% and 11%-12% respectively, while achieving substantial cost savings of 30%. The study also identifies critical challenges, including system integration, data quality issues, cybersecurity risks, and the need for standardization. These findings provide valuable insights for port authorities and policymakers, supporting the transition toward more sustainable and efficient port operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20043v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youzhe Yang, Hafiz Majid Hussain, Juha Haakana, Pedro Nardelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Exact, Finite Dimensional Representation for Full-Block, Circle Criterion Multipliers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20995v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper provides the first finite-dimensional characterization for the complete set of full-block, circle criterion multipliers. We consider the interconnection of a discrete-time, linear time-invariant system in feedback with a non-repeated, sector-bounded nonlinearity. Sufficient conditions for stability and performance can be derived using: (i) dissipation inequalities, and (ii) Quadratic Constraints (QCs) that bound the input/output pairs of the nonlinearity. Larger classes of QCs (or multipliers) reduce the conservatism of the conditions. Full-block, circle criterion multipliers define the complete set of all possible QCs for non-repeated, sector-bounded nonlinearities. These provide the least conservative conditions. However, full-block multipliers are defined by an uncountably infinite number of constraints and hence do not lead to computationally tractable solutions if left in this raw form. This paper provides a new finite-dimensional characterization for the set of full-block, circle criterion multipliers. The key theoretical insight is: the set of all input/output pairs of non-repeated sector-bounded nonlinearities is equal to the set of all incremental pairs for an appropriately constructed piecewise linear function. Our new description for the complete set of multipliers only requires a finite number of matrix copositivity constraints. These conditions have an exact, computationally tractable implementation for problems where the nonlinearity has small input/output dimensions $(\le 4)$. We illustrate the use of our new characterization via a simple example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20995v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Biert\"umpfel, Bin Hu, Geir Dullerud, Peter Seiler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Reinforcement Learning for Building Energy Management System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.12590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.12590v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The building sector is one of the largest contributors to global energy consumption. Improving its energy efficiency is essential for reducing operational costs and greenhouse gas emissions. Energy management systems (EMS) play a key role in monitoring and controlling building appliances efficiently and reliably. With the increasing integration of renewable energy, intelligent EMS solutions have received growing attention. Reinforcement learning (RL) has recently been explored for this purpose and shows strong potential. However, most RL-based EMS methods require a large number of training steps to learn effective control policies, especially when adapting to unseen buildings, which limits their practical deployment. This paper introduces MetaEMS, a meta-reinforcement learning framework for EMS. MetaEMS improves learning efficiency by transferring knowledge from previously solved tasks to new ones through group-level and building-level adaptation, enabling fast adaptation and effective control across diverse building environments. Experimental results demonstrate that MetaEMS adapts more rapidly to unseen buildings and consistently outperforms baseline methods across various scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.12590v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 IEEE Electrical Power and Energy Conference (EPEC)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Benoit Boulet Huiliang Zhang, Di Wu, Arnaud Zinflou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical State Feedback Control for Linear Input Delay Systems, Part I: Dissipative Stabilization via Semidefinite Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14944v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an SDP-based framework to address the stabilization of input delay systems while taking into account dissipative constraints. A key to our approach is the introduction of the concept of parameterized linear dynamical state feedbacks (LDSFs), which draws inspiration from recent advancements in the analyses of distributed delays. The parameterized LDSFs generalize conventional predictor controllers, where the interpretation of state prediction is concealed and their degree of parameterization can be increased by adjusting the integral kernels. A sufficient condition for the existence of dissipative LDSFs is formulated as matrix inequalities by constructing a complete type Krasovski\u{\i} functional. To solve the bilinear matrix inequality in the synthesis condition, we employ an off-line inner convex approximation algorithm that can be initialized using the gains of predictor controllers obtained via explicit construction. So the unknowns of our LTDS can be computed by solving convex semidefinite programs. Numerical examples and simulations were experimented to demonstrate the validity and effectiveness of our methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14944v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Feng, Cong Zhang, Bo Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiable Optimization for Deep Learning-Enhanced DC Approximation of AC Optimal Power Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01970v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The growing scale of power systems and the increasing uncertainty introduced by renewable energy sources necessitates novel optimization techniques that are significantly faster and more accurate than existing methods. The AC Optimal Power Flow (AC-OPF) problem, a core component of power grid optimization, is often approximated using linearized DC Optimal Power Flow (DC-OPF) models for computational tractability, albeit at the cost of suboptimal and inefficient decisions. To address these limitations, we propose a novel deep learning-based framework for network equivalency that enhances DC-OPF to more closely mimic the behavior of AC-OPF. The approach utilizes recent advances in differentiable optimization, incorporating a neural network trained to predict adjusted nodal shunt conductances and branch susceptances in order to account for nonlinear power flow behavior. The model can be trained end-to-end using modern deep learning frameworks by leveraging the implicit function theorem. Results demonstrate the framework's ability to significantly improve prediction accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01970v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Rosemberg, Michael Klamkin, Pascal Van Hentenryck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Adapt Control Barrier Functions? A Learning-Based Approach with Applications to a VTOL Quadplane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03038v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel theoretical framework for online adaptation of Control Barrier Function (CBF) parameters, i.e., of the class K functions included in the CBF condition, under input constraints. We introduce the concept of locally validated CBF parameters, which are adapted online to guarantee finite-horizon safety, based on conditions derived from Nagumo's theorem and tangent cone analysis. To identify these parameters online, we integrate a learning-based approach with an uncertainty-aware verification process that account for both epistemic and aleatoric uncertainties inherent in neural network predictions. Our method is demonstrated on a VTOL quadplane model during challenging transition and landing maneuvers, showcasing enhanced performance while maintaining safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03038v5</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taekyung Kim, Randal W. Beard, Dimitra Panagou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Fully Onboard State Estimation and Trajectory Tracking for UAVs with Suspended Payloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11547v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of tracking the position of a cable-suspended payload carried by an unmanned aerial vehicle, with a focus on real-world deployment and minimal hardware requirements. In contrast to many existing approaches that rely on motion-capture systems, additional onboard cameras, or instrumented payloads, we propose a framework that uses only standard onboard sensors--specifically, real-time kinematic global navigation satellite system measurements and data from the onboard inertial measurement unit--to estimate and control the payload's position. The system models the full coupled dynamics of the aerial vehicle and payload, and integrates a linear Kalman filter for state estimation, a model predictive contouring control planner, and an incremental model predictive controller. The control architecture is designed to remain effective despite sensing limitations and estimation uncertainty. Extensive simulations demonstrate that the proposed system achieves performance comparable to control based on ground-truth measurements, with only minor degradation (&lt; 6%). The system also shows strong robustness to variations in payload parameters. Field experiments further validate the framework, confirming its practical applicability and reliable performance in outdoor environments using only off-the-shelf aerial vehicle hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11547v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5220/0013789200003982</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Informatics in Control, Automation and Robotics (ICINCO 2025), Vol. 2, SciTePress, pp. 128-138, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martin Jirou\v{s}ek, Tom\'a\v{s} B\'a\v{c}a, Martin Saska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distance Between Stochastic Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04014v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While the existing stochastic control theory is well equipped to handle dynamical systems with stochastic uncertainties, a paradigm shift using distance measure based decision making is required for the effective further exploration of the field. As a first step, a distance measure between two stochastic linear time invariant systems is proposed here, extending the existing distance metrics between deterministic linear dynamical systems. In the frequency domain, the proposed distance measure corresponds to the worst-case point-wise in frequency Wasserstein distance between distributions characterising the uncertainties using inverse stereographic projection on the Riemann sphere. For the time domain setting, the proposed distance corresponds to the gap metric induced type-q Wasserstein distance between the distributions characterising the uncertainty of plant models. Apart from providing lower and upper bounds for the proposed distance measures in both frequency and time domain settings, it is proved that the former never exceeds the latter. The proposed distance measures will facilitate the provision of probabilistic guarantees on system robustness and controller performances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04014v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Venkatraman Renganathan, Sei Zhen Khong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Filters for Efficient Economic MPC of Non-dissipative Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11869v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This note presents a novel, efficient economic model predictive control (EMPC) scheme for non-dissipative systems subject to state and input constraints. A new conception of convergence filters is defined to address the stability issue of EMPC for constrained non-dissipative systems. Three convergence filters are designed accordingly to be imposed into the receding horizon optimization problem of EMPC. To improve online computational efficiency, the variable horizon idea without explicit terminal state constraints is adopted to compromise the convergence speed, economic performance, and computational burden of EMPC. Moreover, sufficient conditions are derived to guarantee the recursive feasibility and stability of the EMPC. The advantages of the proposed EMPC are validated by a classical non-dissipative continuous stirred-tank reactor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11869v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Defeng He, Weiliang Xiong, Shiqiang He, Haiping Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiable-by-design Nonlinear Optimization for Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12692v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear optimization-based control policies, such as those those arising in nonlinear Model Predictive Control, have seen remarkable success in recent years. These policies require solving computationally demanding nonlinear optimization programs online at each time-step. The resulting solution map, viewed as a function of the measured state of the system and design parameters, may not be differentiable, which poses significant challenges if the control policy is embedded in a gradient-based policy optimization scheme. We propose a principled way to regularize the nonlinear optimization problem, obtaining a surrogate derivative even if when the original problem is not differentiable. The surrogate problem is differentiable by design and its solution map coincides with the solution of the unregularized problem. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in a free-final-time optimal control problem and a receding-horizon nonlinear MPC example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12692v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Zuliani, Efe C. Balta, John Lygeros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Ethical AI in Power Electronics: How Engineering Practice and Roles Must Adapt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09439v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) is rapidly transforming power electronics, with AI-related publications in IEEE Power Electronics Society selected journals increasing more than fourfold from 2020 to 2025. However, the ethical dimensions of this transformation have received limited attention. This article underscores the urgent need for an ethical framework to guide responsible AI integration in power electronics, not only to prevent AI-related incidents but also to comply with legal and regulatory responsibilities. In this context, this article identifies four core pillars of AI ethics in power electronics: Security &amp; Safety, Explainability &amp; Transparency, Energy Sustainability, and Evolving Roles of Engineers. Each pillar is supported by practical and actionable insights to ensure that ethical principles are embedded in algorithm design, system deployment, and the preparation of an AI-ready engineering workforce. The authors advocate for power electronics engineers to lead the ethical discourse, given their deep technical understanding of both AI systems and power conversion technologies. The paper concludes by calling on the IEEE Power Electronics Society to spearhead the establishment of ethical standards, talent development initiatives, and best practices that ensure AI innovations are not only technically advanced but also oriented toward human and societal benefit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09439v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fanfan Lin, Peter Wilson, Xinze Li, Alan Mantooth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Legged Locomotion via Online Learning for Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15626v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide an algorithm for adaptive legged locomotion via online learning and model predictive control. The algorithm is composed of two interacting modules: model predictive control (MPC) and online learning of residual dynamics. The residual dynamics can represent modeling errors and external disturbances. We are motivated by the future of autonomy where quadrupeds will autonomously perform complex tasks despite real-world unknown uncertainty, such as unknown payload and uneven terrains. The algorithm uses random Fourier features to approximate the residual dynamics in reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces. Then, it employs MPC based on the current learned model of the residual dynamics. The model is updated online in a self-supervised manner using least squares based on the data collected while controlling the quadruped. The algorithm enjoys sublinear \textit{dynamic regret}, defined as the suboptimality against an optimal clairvoyant controller that knows how the residual dynamics. We validate our algorithm in Gazebo and MuJoCo simulations, where the quadruped aims to track reference trajectories. The Gazebo simulations include constant unknown external forces up to $12\boldsymbol{g}$, where $\boldsymbol{g}$ is the gravity vector, in flat terrain, slope terrain with $20\degree$ inclination, and rough terrain with $0.25m$ height variation. The MuJoCo simulations include time-varying unknown disturbances with payload up to $8~kg$ and time-varying ground friction coefficients in flat terrain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15626v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongyu Zhou, Xiaoyu Zhang, Vasileios Tzoumas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAD-Flower: Flow Matching for Safe, Admissible, and Dynamically Consistent Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05355v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Flow matching (FM) has shown promising results in data-driven planning. However, it inherently lacks formal guarantees for ensuring state and action constraints, whose satisfaction is a fundamental and crucial requirement for the safety and admissibility of planned trajectories on various systems. Moreover, existing FM planners do not ensure the dynamical consistency, which potentially renders trajectories inexecutable. We address these shortcomings by proposing SAD-Flower, a novel framework for generating Safe, Admissible, and Dynamically consistent trajectories. Our approach relies on an augmentation of the flow with a virtual control input. Thereby, principled guidance can be derived using techniques from nonlinear control theory, providing formal guarantees for state constraints, action constraints, and dynamic consistency. Crucially, SAD-Flower operates without retraining, enabling test-time satisfaction of unseen constraints. Through extensive experiments across several tasks, we demonstrate that SAD-Flower outperforms various generative-model-based baselines in ensuring constraint satisfaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05355v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tzu-Yuan Huang, Armin Lederer, Dai-Jie Wu, Xiaobing Dai, Sihua Zhang, Stefan Sosnowski, Shao-Hua Sun, Sandra Hirche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCI: A Metacognitive Control for Signal Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12240v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern deep learning systems are typically deployed as open-loop function approximators: they map inputs to outputs in a single pass, without regulating how much computation or explanatory effort is spent on a given case. In safety-critical settings, this is brittle: easy and ambiguous inputs receive identical processing, and uncertainty is only read off retrospectively from raw probabilities. We introduce the Surgical Cognitive Interpreter (SCI), a lightweight closed-loop metacognitive control layer that wraps an existing stochastic model and turns prediction into an iterative process. SCI monitors a scalar interpretive state SP(t), here instantiated as a normalized entropy-based confidence signal, and adaptively decides whether to stop, continue sampling, or abstain. The goal is not to improve accuracy per se, but to regulate interpretive error {\Delta}SP and expose a safety signal that tracks when the underlying model is likely to fail. We instantiate SCI around Monte Carlo dropout classifiers in three domains: vision (MNIST digits), medical time series (MIT-BIH arrhythmia), and industrial condition monitoring (rolling-element bearings). In all cases, the controller allocates more inference steps to misclassified inputs than to correct ones (up to about 3-4x on MNIST and bearings, and 1.4x on MIT-BIH). The resulting {\Delta}SP acts as a usable safety signal for detecting misclassifications (AUROC 0.63 on MNIST, 0.70 on MIT-BIH, 0.86 on bearings). Code and reproducibility: https://github.com/vishal-1344/sci</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12240v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishal Joshua Meesala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APULSE: A Scalable Hybrid Algorithm for the RCSPP on Large-Scale Dense Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18236v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The resource-constrained shortest path problem (RCSPP) is a fundamental NP-hard optimization challenge with broad applications, from network routing to autonomous navigation. This problem involves finding a path that minimizes a primary cost subject to a budget on a secondary resource. While various RCSPP solvers exist, they often face critical scalability limitations when applied to the large, dense graphs characteristic of complex, real-world scenarios, making them impractical for time-critical planning. This challenge is particularly acute in domains like mission planning for unmanned ground vehicles (UGVs), which demand solutions on large-scale terrain graphs. This paper introduces APULSE, a hybrid label-setting algorithm designed to efficiently solve the RCSPP on such challenging graphs. APULSE integrates a best-first search guided by an A* heuristic with aggressive, Pulse-style pruning mechanisms and a time-bucketing strategy for effective state-space reduction. A computational study, using a large-scale UGV planning scenario, benchmarks APULSE against state-of-the-art algorithms. The results demonstrate that APULSE consistently finds near-optimal solutions while being orders of magnitude faster and more robust, particularly on large problem instances where competing methods fail. This superior scalability establishes APULSE as an effective solution for RCSPP in complex, large-scale environments, enabling capabilities such as interactive decision support and dynamic replanning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18236v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuno Soares, Ant\'onio Grilo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
