<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY</link>
    <description>eess.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 05:18:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Power sector models featuring individual BEV profiles: Assessing the time-accuracy trade-off</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrifying passenger cars will impact future power systems. To understand the challenges and opportunities that arise, it is necessary to reflect "sector coupling" in the modeling space. This paper focuses on a specific modeling approach that includes dozens of individual BEV profiles rather than one aggregated BEV profile. Although including additional BEV profiles increases model complexity and runtime, it avoids losing information in the aggregation process. We investigate how many profiles are needed to ensure the accuracy of the results and the extent to which fewer profiles can be traded for runtime efficiency gains. We also examine whether selecting specific profiles influences optimal results. We demonstrate that including too few profiles may result in distorted optimal solutions. However, beyond a certain threshold, adding more profiles does not significantly enhance the robustness of the results. More generally, for fleets of 5 to 20 million BEVs, we derive a rule of thumb consisting in including enough profiles such that each profile represents 200,000 to 250,000 vehicles, ensuring accurate results without excessive runtime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19449v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adeline Gu\'eret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Duality and Dual Ascent Approach to Continuous-Time Chance-Constrained Stochastic Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper addresses a continuous-time continuous-space chance-constrained stochastic optimal control (SOC) problem where the probability of failure to satisfy given state constraints is explicitly bounded. We leverage the notion of exit time from continuous-time stochastic calculus to formulate a chance-constrained SOC problem. Without any conservative approximation, the chance constraint is transformed into an expectation of an indicator function which can be incorporated into the cost function by considering a dual formulation. We then express the dual function in terms of the solution to a Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman partial differential equation parameterized by the dual variable. Under a certain assumption on the system dynamics and cost function, it is shown that a strong duality holds between the primal chance-constrained problem and its dual. The Path integral approach is utilized to numerically solve the dual problem via gradient ascent using open-loop samples of system trajectories. We present simulation studies on chance-constrained motion planning for spatial navigation of mobile robots and the solution of the path integral approach is compared with that of the finite difference method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19451v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apurva Patil, Alfredo Duarte, Fabrizio Bisetti, Takashi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Data-Driven Model Predictive Control Framework for Multi-Aircraft TMA Routing Under Travel Time Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a closed-loop framework for conflict-free routing and scheduling of multi-aircraft in Terminal Manoeuvring Areas (TMA), aimed at reducing congestion and enhancing landing efficiency. Leveraging data-driven arrival inputs (either historical or predicted), we formulate a mixed-integer optimization model for real-time control, incorporating an extended TMA network spanning a 50-nautical-mile radius around Changi Airport. The model enforces safety separation, speed adjustments, and holding time constraints while maximizing runway throughput. A rolling-horizon Model Predictive Control (MPC) strategy enables closed-loop integration with a traffic simulator, dynamically updating commands based on real-time system states and predictions. Computational efficiency is validated across diverse traffic scenarios, demonstrating a 7-fold reduction in computation time during peak congestion compared to onetime optimization, using Singapore ADS-B dataset. Monte Carlo simulations under travel time disturbances further confirm the framework's robustness. Results highlight the approach's operational resilience and computational scalability, offering actionable decision support for Air Traffic Controller Officers (ATCOs) through real-time optimization and adaptive replanning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19452v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhang, Yushen Long, Liping Huang, Yicheng Zhang, Sheng Zhang, Yifang Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A K-means Inspired Solution Framework for Large-Scale Multi-Traveling Salesman Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19454v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Multi-Traveling Salesman Problem (MTSP) is a commonly used mathematical model for multi-agent task allocation. However, as the number of agents and task targets increases, existing optimization-based methods often incur prohibitive computational costs, posing significant challenges to large-scale coordination in unmanned systems. To address this issue, this paper proposes a K-means-inspired task allocation framework that reformulates the MTSP as a spatially constrained classification process. By leveraging spatial coherence, the proposed method enables fast estimation of path costs and efficient task grouping, thereby fundamentally reducing overall computational complexity. Extensive simulation results demonstrate that the framework can maintain high solution quality even in extremely large-scale scenarios-for instance, in tasks involving 1000 agents and 5000 targets. The findings indicate that this "cluster-then-route" decomposition strategy offers an efficient and reliable solution for large-scale multi-agent task allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19454v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiubin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Secure Neighbor Selection in Multi-Agent Systems with Byzantine Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the problem of resilient control for multi-agent systems in the presence of Byzantine adversaries via an active secure neighbor selection framework. A pre-discriminative graph is first constructed to characterize the admissible set of candidate neighbors for each agent. Based on this graph, a dynamic in-neighbor selection strategy is proposed, wherein each agent actively selects a subset of its pre-discriminative neighbors. The number of selected neighbors is adjustable, allowing for a trade-off between communication overhead and robustness, with the minimal case requiring only a single in-neighbor. The proposed strategy facilitates the reconstruction of a directed spanning tree among normal agents following the detection and isolation of Byzantine agents. It achieves resilient consensus without imposing any assumptions on the initial connectivity among normal agents. Moreover, the approach significantly reduces communication burden while maintaining resilience to adversarial behavior. A numerical example is provided to illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19522v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinming Gao, Yijing Wang, Wentao Zhang, Rui Zhao, Yang Shi, Zhiqiang Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Feedback Controllers with Operational Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, a state feedback control design with min/max operational limiting constraints is developed for multi-input-multi-output linear time invariant systems. Specifically, servo-tracking control problems with input and output constraints are considered. For static servo-controllers, the output design limits are imposed component-wise on the system selected output, which is of the same dimension as the control input. For dynamic servo-controllers, operational constraints are applied to the system inputs and outputs. The proposed control solution also includes an anti-windup protection logic for dynamic servo-controllers with integral action. The developed method is based on the Nagumo Theorem for forward invariance, the Comparison Lemma for inclusion of input/output inequality constraints, and on the min-norm optimal controllers for synthesis. The derived design is similar and directly related to the method of Control Barrier Functions. Simulation trade studies are presented to illustrate benefits of the proposed control methodology for aerial flight critical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19683v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Lavretsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Risk and Revenue in the Nordic 15-minute mFRR market: An EV Aggregation Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decarbonisation, decentralisation, and intermittency are driving the development of flexibility markets towards shorter market time units (MTU). Shorter MTUs and shorter gate closures lower the entrance barriers of demand side aggregators that face significant uncertainty on longer time scales. We study the business case for aggregated EV fleets participating in the Nordic 15-minute mFRR Energy Activation Market (EAM). Motivated by increasing system granularity and rapid EV uptake, we represent fleet flexibility as a virtual battery with time-varying power and energy envelopes and formulate a risk-aware stochastic optimisation that co-ordinates day-ahead scheduling with quarter-hour mFRR bidding. Using synthetic residential charging cohorts and observed day-ahead prices on two stylised days, we compare an independent day-ahead baseline to a co-optimised strategy under conservative availability and a CVaR-augmented objective. Across both price cases, co-optimisation increases expected profit and lowers downside risk: the model buys less energy day-ahead and shifts procurement toward mFRR down while flattening the charging plan to retain eligibility for mFRR up. Profit decomposition shows that the uplift is driven by higher mFRR down revenues and reduced reliance on unwinding day-ahead positions. We discuss operational implications for bidding and outline two extensions: rolling 45-minute re-optimisation and a V2G framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19715v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>9th E-Mobility Power System Integration Symposium, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Theodor Hagstr\"om, Lars Herre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Hypotheses Ego-Tracking for Resilient Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous robots relying on radio frequency (RF)-based localization such as global navigation satellite system (GNSS), ultra-wide band (UWB), and 5G integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) are vul- nerable to spoofing and sensor manipulation. This paper presents a resilient navigation architecture that combines multi-hypothesis estimation with a Poisson binomial windowed-count detector for anomaly identi- fication and isolation. A state machine coordinates transitions between operation, diagnosis, and mitigation, enabling adaptive response to adversarial conditions. When attacks are detected, trajectory re-planning based on differential flatness allows information-gathering maneuvers minimizing performance loss. Case studies demonstrate effective detection of biased sensors, maintenance of state estimation, and recovery of nominal operation under persistent spoofing attacks</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19770v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Iwer Hoedt Karstensen, Roberto Galeazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Exact Solution Algorithm for the Bi-Level Optimization Problem of Electric Vehicles Charging Station Placement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work addresses electric vehicle (EV) charging station placement through a bi-level optimization model, where the upper-level planner maximizes net revenue by selecting station locations under budget constraints, while EV users at the lower level choose routes and charging stations to minimize travel and charging costs. To account for range anxiety, we construct a battery-expanded network and apply a shortest path algorithm with Frank-Wolfe traffic assignment. Our primary contribution is developing the first exact solution algorithm for large scale EV charging station placement problems. We propose a Branch-and-Price-and-Cut algorithm enhanced with value function cuts and column generation. While existing research relies on heuristic methods that provide no optimality guarantees or exact algorithms that require prohibitively long runtimes, our exact algorithm delivers globally optimal solutions with mathematical certainty under a reasonable runtime. Computational experiments on the Eastern Massachusetts network (74 nodes, 248 links), the Anaheim network (416 nodes, 914 links), and the Barcelona network (110 zones, 1,020 nodes, and 2,512 links) demonstrate exceptional performance. Our algorithm terminates within minutes rather than hours, while achieving optimality gaps below 1% across all instances. This result represents a computational speedup of over two orders of magnitude compared to existing methods. The algorithm successfully handles problems with over 300,000 feasible combinations, which transform EV charging infrastructure planning from a computationally prohibitive problem into a tractable optimization task suitable for practical decision making problem for real world networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19884v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mobina Nankali, Michael W. Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Trustworthy Digital Twins in Agentic AI-based Wireless Network Optimization: Challenges, Solutions, and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimizing modern wireless networks is exceptionally challenging due to their high dynamism and complexity. While the agentic artificial intelligence (AI) powered by reinforcement learning (RL) offers a promising solution, its practical application is limited by prohibitive exploration costs and potential risks in the real world. The emerging digital twin (DT) technology provides a safe and controlled virtual environment for agentic AI training, but its effectiveness critically depends on the DT's fidelity. Policies trained in a low-fidelity DT that does not accurately represent the physical network may experience severe performance degradation upon real-world deployment. In this article, we introduce a unified DT evaluation framework to ensure trustworthy DTs in agentic AI-based network optimization. This evaluation framework shifts from conventional isolated physical accuracy metrics, such as wireless channel and user trajectory similarities, to a more holistic, task-centric DT assessment. We demonstrate it as an effective guideline for design, selection, and lifecycle management of wireless network DTs. A comprehensive case study on a real-world wireless network testbed shows how this evaluation framework is used to pre-filter candidate DTs, leading to a significant reduction in training and testing costs without sacrificing deployment performance. Finally, potential research opportunities are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19961v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyu Tao, Wei Xu, Xiaohu You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Technical and Environmental Impacts of Energy Management Systems in Smart Ports</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20043v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A vital strategy for ports to mitigate the environmental impact of the maritime industry, while complying with frameworks such as the European Green Deal and the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), entails the systematic implementation of comprehensive energy management solutions. This paper provides a baseline evaluation of the energy management systems (EMSs) implementation and their impact on energy consumption, carbon emissions, and operational costs in smart ports. Initially, we provide a systematic review of the literature focusing on case studies from prominent ports, including Hamburg, Genoa, Jurong, and Shanghai Yangshan Phase IV. The analysis emphasises key aspects such as energy efficiency, reductions in emissions, and the minimization of operational costs. Subsequently, we formulate an optimisation model to simulate load dispatch, carbon emission reduction, and transport scheduling. Results indicate that EMS deployment reduces annual energy consumption and carbon emissions significantly by approximately 7%-8% and 11%-12% respectively, while achieving substantial cost savings of 30%. The study also identifies critical challenges, including system integration, data quality issues, cybersecurity risks, and the need for standardization. These findings provide valuable insights for port authorities and policymakers, supporting the transition toward more sustainable and efficient port operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20043v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youzhe Yang, Hafiz Majid Hussain, Juha Haakana, Pedro Nardelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Enhanced Reinforcement Learning for Accelerating Newton-Raphson Convergence with Ising Machines: A Case Study for Power Flow Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Newton-Raphson (NR) method is widely used for solving power flow (PF) equations due to its quadratic convergence. However, its performance deteriorates under poor initialization or extreme operating scenarios, e.g., high levels of renewable energy penetration. Traditional NR initialization strategies often fail to address these challenges, resulting in slow convergence or even divergence. We propose the use of reinforcement learning (RL) to optimize the initialization of NR, and introduce a novel quantum-enhanced RL environment update mechanism to mitigate the significant computational cost of evaluating power system states over a combinatorially large action space at each RL timestep by formulating the voltage adjustment task as a quadratic unconstrained binary optimization problem. Specifically, quantum/digital annealers are integrated into the RL environment update to evaluate state transitions using a problem Hamiltonian designed for PF. Results demonstrate significant improvements in convergence speed, a reduction in NR iteration counts, and enhanced robustness under different operating conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20237v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeynab Kaseb, Matthias Moller, Lindsay Spoor, Jerry J. Guo, Yu Xiang, Peter Palensky, Pedro P. Vergara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Occlusion-Aware Multi-Object Tracking via Expected Probability of Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses multi-object systems, where objects may occlude one another relative to the sensor. The standard point-object model for detection-based sensors is enhanced so that the probability of detection considers the presence of all objects. A principled tracking method is derived, assigning each object an expected probability of detection, where the expectation is taken over the reduced Palm density, which means conditionally on the object's existence. The assigned probability thus considers the object's visibility relative to the sensor, under the presence of other objects. Unlike existing methods, the proposed method systematically accounts for uncertainties related to all objects in a clear and manageable way. The method is demonstrated through a visual tracking application using the multi-Bernoulli mixture (MBM) filter with marks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20239v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Krej\v{c}\'i, Oliver Kost, Yuxuan Xia, Lennart Svensson, Ond\v{r}ej Straka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-Driven Transient Stability Assessment: From Automated Simulation to Neural Architecture Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20276v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an LLM-driven, end-to-end workflow that addresses the lack of automation and intelligence in power system transient stability assessment (TSA). The proposed agentic framework integrates large language models (LLMs) with a professional simulator (ANDES) to automatically generate and filter disturbance scenarios from natural language, and employs an LLM-driven Neural Network Design (LLM-NND) pipeline to autonomously design and optimize TSA models through performance-guided, closed-loop feedback. On the IEEE 39-bus system, the LLM-NND models achieve 93.71% test accuracy on four-class TSA with only 4.78M parameters, while maintaining real-time inference latency (less than 0.95 ms per sample). Compared with a manually designed DenseNet (25.9M parameters, 80.05% accuracy), the proposed approach jointly improves accuracy and efficiency. Ablation studies confirm that the synergy among domain-grounded retrieval, reasoning augmentation, and feedback mechanisms is essential for robust automation. The results demonstrate that LLM agents can reliably accelerate TSA research from scenario generation and data acquisition to model design and interpretation, offering a scalable paradigm that is readily extensible to other power system tasks such as optimal power flow, fault analysis, and market operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20276v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lianzhe Hu, Yu Wang, Bikash Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAFE-IMM: Robust and Lightweight Radar-Based Object Tracking on Mobile Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tracking maneuvering targets requires estimators that are both responsive and robust. Interacting Multiple Model (IMM) filters are a standard tracking approach, but fusing models via Gaussian mixtures can lag during maneuvers. Recent winnertakes-all (WTA) approaches react quickly but may produce discontinuities. We propose SAFE-IMM, a lightweight IMM variant for tracking on mobile and resource-limited platforms with a safe covariance-aware gate that permits WTA only when the implied jump from the mixture to the winner is provably bounded. In simulations and on nuScenes front-radar data, SAFE-IMM achieves high accuracy at real-time rates, reducing ID switches while maintaining competitive performance. The method is simple to integrate, numerically stable, and clutter-robust, offering a practical balance between responsiveness and smoothness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20294v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dnyandeep Mandaokar, Bernhard Rinner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Time-Optimal Trajectory Planning for Connected and Automated Vehicles with Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a learning-based framework that accelerates time- and energy-optimal trajectory planning for connected and automated vehicles (CAVs) using graph neural networks (GNNs). We formulate the multi-agent coordination problem encountered in traffic scenarios as a cooperative trajectory planning problem that minimizes travel time, subject to motion primitives derived from energy-optimal solutions. The effectiveness of this framework can be further improved through replanning at each time step, enabling the system to incorporate newly observed information. To achieve real-time execution of such a multi-agent replanning scheme, we employ a GNN architecture to learn the solutions of the time-optimal trajectory planning problem from offline-generated data. The trained model produces online predictions that serve as warm-start solutions for numerical optimization, thereby enabling rapid computation of minimal exit times and the associated feasible trajectories. This learning-augmented approach substantially reduces computation time while ensuring that all state, input, and safety constraints are satisfied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20383v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viet-Anh Le, Andreas A. Malikopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Meshing for CPA Lyapunov Function Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuous piecewise affine (CPA) Lyapunov function synthesis is one method to perform Lyapunov stability analysis for nonlinear systems. This method first generates a mesh over the region of interest in the system's state space and then solves a linear program (LP), which enforces constraints on each vertex of the mesh, to synthesize a Lyapunov function. Finer meshes broaden the class of Lyapunov function candidates, but CPA function synthesis is more computationally expensive for finer meshes -- particularly so in higher dimensional systems. This paper explores methods to mesh the region of interest more efficiently so that a Lyapunov function can be synthesized using less computational effort. Three methods are explored -- adaptive meshing, meshing using knowledge of the system model, and a combination of the two. Numerical examples for two and three dimensional nonlinear dynamical systems are used to compare the efficacy of the three methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20443v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amy K. Strong, Samuel Akinwande, Leila Bridgeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Control Barrier Functions with Deterministic Safety Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20463v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Barrier functions (BFs) characterize safe sets of dynamical systems, where hard constraints are never violated as the system evolves over time. Computing a valid safe set and BF for a nonlinear (and potentially unmodeled), non-autonomous dynamical system is a difficult task. This work explores the design of BFs using data to obtain safe sets with deterministic assurances of control invariance. We leverage ReLU neural networks (NNs) to create continuous piecewise affine (CPA) BFs with deterministic safety guarantees for Lipschitz continuous, discrete-time dynamical system using sampled one-step trajectories. The CPA structure admits a novel classifier term to create a relaxed \ac{bf} condition and construction via a data driven constrained optimization. We use iterative convex overbounding (ICO) to solve this nonconvex optimization problem through a series of convex optimization steps. We then demonstrate our method's efficacy on two-dimensional autonomous and non-autonomous dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20463v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amy K. Strong, Ali Kashani, Claus Danielson, Leila Bridgeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Feature Selection for Weather-Driven Residential Load Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20508v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weather is a dominant external driver of residential electricity demand, but adding many meteorological covariates can inflate model complexity and may even impair accuracy. Selecting appropriate exogenous features is non-trivial and calls for a principled selection framework, given the direct operational implications for day-to-day planning and reliability. This work investigates whether causal feature selection can retain the most informative weather drivers while improving parsimony and robustness for short-term load forecasting. We present a case study on Southern Ontario with two open-source datasets: (i) IESO hourly electricity consumption by Forward Sortation Areas; (ii) ERA5 weather reanalysis data. We compare different feature selection regimes (no feature selection, non-causal selection, PCMCI-causal selection) on city-level forecasting with three different time series forecasting models: GRU, TCN, PatchTST. In the feature analysis, non-causal selection prioritizes radiation and moisture variables that show correlational dependence, whereas PCMCI-causal selection emphasizes more direct thermal drivers and prunes the indirect covariates. We detail the evaluation pipeline and report diagnostics on prediction accuracy and extreme-weather robustness, positioning causal feature selection as a practical complement to modern forecasters when integrating weather into residential load forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20508v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elise Zhang, Fran\c{c}ois Mirall\`es, St\'ephane Dellacherie, Di Wu, Benoit Boulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Features to States: Data-Driven Selection of Measured State Variables via RFE-DMDc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The behavior of a dynamical system under a given set of inputs can be captured by tracking the response of an optimal subset of process variables (\textit{state variables}). For many engineering systems, however, first-principles, model-based identification is impractical, motivating data-driven approaches for Digital Twins used in control and diagnostics. In this paper, we present RFE-DMDc, a supervised, data-driven workflow that uses Recursive Feature Elimination (RFE) to select a minimal, physically meaningful set of variables to monitor and then derives a linear state-space model via Dynamic Mode Decomposition with Control (DMDc). The workflow includes a cross-subsystem selection step that mitigates feature \textit{overshadowing} in multi-component systems. To corroborate the results, we implement a GA-DMDc baseline that jointly optimizes the state set and model fit under a common accuracy cost on states and outputs. Across a truth-known RLC benchmark and a realistic Integrated Energy System (IES) with multiple thermally coupled components and thousands of candidate variables, RFE-DMDc consistently recovers compact state sets (\(\approx 10\) variables) that achieve test errors comparable to GA-DMDc while requiring an order of magnitude less computational time. The selected variables retain clear physical interpretation across subsystems, and the resulting models demonstrate competitive predictive accuracy, computational efficiency, and robustness to overfitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20552v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Wang, Andrea Alfonsi, Roberto Ponciroli, Richard Vilim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Urban Air Mobility Adoption Potential in San Francisco Bay Area Region: A Systems of Systems Level Case Study on Passenger Waiting Times and Travel Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Urban Air mobility has gained momentum with recent advancements in the electric vertical take-off and landing (eVTOL) vehicles, offering faster point-to-point air taxi services that could help relieve traffic congestion in chronically overburdened cities. The research assesses the feasibility and systems-of-systems level adoption potential of UAM operations in the San Francisco Bay Area by comparing passenger departure, waiting, travel, and arrival times across key regional nodes, including San Francisco, Oakland, San Jose, and Palo Alto airports, with conventional ground transportation. A multi-agent simulation was developed in MATLAB to evaluate the fleet operations and to model demand arrival using a Poisson process under stochastic passenger flows and turnaround constraints. Results indicate that utilizing UAM during peak demand could reduce total travel times up to eighty percent across the region. The findings of this paper highlight the critical operational factors for fleet schedule optimization. Especially how the fleet size, passengers' request volumes, and turnaround time directly influence waiting time, operating cost, and overall user acceptance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20603v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Winfrey Paul Sagayam Dennis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systemic approach for modeling a generic smart grid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Smart grid technological advances present a recent class of complex interdisciplinary modeling and increasingly difficult simulation problems to solve using traditional computational methods. To simulate a smart grid requires a systemic approach to integrated modeling of power systems, energy markets, demand-side management, and much other resources and assets that are becoming part of the current paradigm of the power grid. This paper presents a backbone model of a smart grid to test alternative scenarios for the grid. This tool simulates disparate systems to validate assumptions before the human scale model. Thanks to a distributed optimization of subsystems, the production and consumption scheduling is achieved while maintaining flexibility and scalability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19460v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3368926.3369665</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the 10th International Symposium on Information and Communication Technology 2019</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sofiane Ben Amor, Guillaume Guerard, Loup-No\'e Levy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Convex Programming for Multimode Spacecraft Trajectory Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19505v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spacecraft equipped with multiple propulsion modes or systems can offer enhanced performance and mission flexibility compared with traditional configurations. Despite these benefits, the trajectory optimization of spacecraft utilizing such configurations remains a complex challenge. This paper presents a sequential convex programming (SCP) approach for the optimal design of multi-mode and multi-propulsion spacecraft trajectories. The method extends the dynamical linearization within SCP using sparse automatic differentiation, enabling efficient inclusion of multiple propulsion modes or systems without complex manual reformulation while maintaining comparable computational efficiency. New constraint formulations are introduced to ensure selection of a single propulsion mode at each time step and limit the total number of modes used. The approach is demonstrated for (i) a low-thrust Earth-67P rendezvous using the SPT-140 thruster with 20 discrete modes, and (ii) an Earth-Mars transfer employing both a low-thrust engine and a solar sail. Results confirm that the proposed method can efficiently compute optimal trajectories for these scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19505v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Yarndley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anytime-Feasible First-Order Optimization via Safe Sequential QCQP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the Safe Sequential Quadratically Constrained Quadratic Programming (SS-QCQP) algorithm, a first-order method for smooth inequality-constrained nonconvex optimization that guarantees feasibility at every iteration. The method is derived from a continuous-time dynamical system whose vector field is obtained by solving a convex QCQP that enforces monotonic descent of the objective and forward invariance of the feasible set. The resulting continuous-time dynamics achieve an $O(1/t)$ convergence rate to first-order stationary points under standard constraint qualification conditions. We then propose a safeguarded Euler discretization with adaptive step-size selection that preserves this convergence rate while maintaining both descent and feasibility in discrete time. To enhance scalability, we develop an active-set variant (SS-QCQP-AS) that selectively enforces constraints near the boundary, substantially reducing computational cost without compromising theoretical guarantees. Numerical experiments on a multi-agent nonlinear optimal control problem demonstrate that SS-QCQP and SS-QCQP-AS maintain feasibility, exhibit the predicted convergence behavior, and deliver solution quality comparable to second-order solvers such as SQP and IPOPT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19675v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiarui Wang, Mahyar Fazlyab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Accelerated Distributed Algorithm with Equality and Inequality Coupling Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19708v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies distributed convex optimization with both affine equality and nonlinear inequality couplings through the duality analysis. We first formulate the dual of the coupling-constraint problem and reformulate it as a consensus optimization problem over a connected network. To efficiently solve this dual problem and hence the primal problem, we design an accelerated linearized algorithm that, at each round, a look-ahead linearization of the separable objective is combined with a quadratic penalty on the Laplacian constraint, a proximal step, and an aggregation of iterations. On the theory side, we prove non-ergodic rates for both the primal optimality error and the feasibility error. On the other hand, numerical experiments show a faster decrease of optimality error and feasibility residual than augmented-Lagrangian tracking and distributed subgradient baselines under the same communication budget.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19708v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyang Qiu, Yangyang Qian, Zongli Lin, Yacov A. Shamash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Ergodic Convergence Algorithms for Distributed Consensus and Coupling-Constrained Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study distributed convex optimization with two ubiquitous forms of coupling: consensus constraints and global affine equalities. We first design a linearized method of multipliers for the consensus optimization problem. Without smoothness or strong convexity, we establish non-ergodic sublinear rates of order O(1/\sqrt{k}) for both the objective optimality and the consensus violation. Leveraging duality, we then show that the economic dispatch problem admits a dual consensus formulation, and that applying the same algorithm to the dual economic dispatch yields non-ergodic O(1/\sqrt{k}) decay for the error of the summation of the cost over the network and the equality-constraint residual under convexity and Slater's condition. Numerical results on the IEEE 118-bus system demonstrate faster reduction of both objective error and feasibility error relative to the state-of-the-art baselines, while the dual variables reach network-wide consensus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19714v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyang Qiu, Zongli Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Distributed Gradient-based Algorithm for Optimization Problems with Coupled Equality Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19723v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies a class of distributed optimization problems with coupled equality constraints in networked systems. Many existing distributed algorithms rely on solving local subproblems via the $\operatorname{argmin}$ operator in each iteration. Such approaches become computationally burdensome or intractable when local cost functions are complex. To address this challenge, we propose a novel distributed gradient-based algorithm that avoids solving a local optimization problem at each iteration by leveraging first-order approximations and projection onto local feasible sets. The algorithm operates in a fully distributed manner, requiring only local communication without exchanging gradients or primal variables. We rigorously establish sublinear convergence for general convex cost functions and linear convergence under strong convexity and smoothness conditions. Numerical simulation on the IEEE 118-bus system demonstrates the superior computational efficiency and scalability of the proposed method compared to several state-of-the-art distributed optimization algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19723v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyang Qiu, Zongli Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive, Data-Integrated Agent-Based Modeling Framework for Explainable and Contestable Policy Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-agent systems often operate under feedback, adaptation, and non-stationarity, yet many simulation studies retain static decision rules and fixed control parameters. This paper introduces a general adaptive multi-agent learning framework that integrates: (i) four dynamic regimes distinguishing static versus adaptive agents and fixed versus adaptive system parameters; (ii) information-theoretic diagnostics (entropy rate, statistical complexity, and predictive information) to assess predictability and structure; (iii) structural causal models for explicit intervention semantics; (iv) procedures for generating agent-level priors from aggregate or sample data; and (v) unsupervised methods for identifying emergent behavioral regimes. The framework offers a domain-neutral architecture for analyzing how learning agents and adaptive controls jointly shape system trajectories, enabling systematic comparison of stability, performance, and interpretability across non-equilibrium, oscillatory, or drifting dynamics. Mathematical definitions, computational operators, and an experimental design template are provided, yielding a structured methodology for developing explainable and contestable multi-agent decision processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19726v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Garrone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Satellite Power Consumption and Handover Optimization for LEO Constellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In satellite constellation-based communication systems, continuous user coverage requires frequent handoffs due to the dynamic topology induced by the Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellites. Each handoff between a satellite and ground users introduces additional signaling and power consumption, which can become a significant burden as the size of the constellation continues to increase. This work focuses on the optimization of the total transmission rate in a LEO-to-user system, by jointly considering the total transmitted power, user-satellite associations, and power consumption, the latter being handled through a penalty on handoff events. We consider a system where LEO satellites serve users located in remote areas with no terrestrial connectivity, and formulate the power allocation problem as a mixed-integer concave linear program (MICP) subject to power and association constraints. Our approach can be solved with off-the-shelf solvers and is benchmarked against a naive baseline where users associate to their closest visible satellite. Extensive Monte Carlo simulations demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed method in controlling the handoff frequency while maintaining high user throughput. These performance gains highlight the effectiveness of our handover-aware optimization strategy, which ensures that user rates improve significantly, by about 40%, without incurring a disproportionate rise in the handoff frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19745v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/WiSEE57913.2025.11229869</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 IEEE International Conference on Wireless for Space and Extreme Environments (WiSEE)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yassine Afif, Mohammed Almekhlafi, Antoine Lesage-Landry, Gunes Karabulut Kurt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iRadioDiff: Physics-Informed Diffusion Model for Indoor Radio Map Construction and Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20015v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radio maps (RMs) serve as environment-aware electromagnetic (EM) representations that connect scenario geometry and material properties to the spatial distribution of signal strength, enabling localization without costly in-situ measurements. However, constructing high-fidelity indoor RMs remains challenging due to the prohibitive latency of EM solvers and the limitations of learning-based methods, which often rely on sparse measurements or assumptions of homogeneous material, which are misaligned with the heterogeneous and multipath-rich nature of indoor environments. To overcome these challenges, we propose iRadioDiff, a sampling-free diffusion-based framework for indoor RM construction. iRadioDiff is conditioned on access point (AP) positions, and physics-informed prompt encoded by material reflection and transmission coefficients. It further incorporates multipath-critical priors, including diffraction points, strong transmission boundaries, and line-of-sight (LoS) contours, to guide the generative process via conditional channels and boundary-weighted objectives. This design enables accurate modeling of nonstationary field discontinuities and efficient construction of physically consistent RMs. Experiments demonstrate that iRadioDiff achieves state-of-the-art performance in indoor RM construction and received signal strength based indoor localization, which offers effective generalization across layouts and material configurations. Code is available at https://github.com/UNIC-Lab/iRadioDiff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20015v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiucheng Wang, Tingwei Yuan, Yang Cao, Nan Cheng, Ruijin Sun, Weihua Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication-Efficient Learning for Satellite Constellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20220v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Satellite constellations in low-Earth orbit are now widespread, enabling positioning, Earth imaging, and communications. In this paper we address the solution of learning problems using these satellite constellations. In particular, we focus on a federated approach, where satellites collect and locally process data, with the ground station aggregating local models. We focus on designing a novel, communication-efficient algorithm that still yields accurate trained models. To this end, we employ several mechanisms to reduce the number of communications with the ground station (local training) and their size (compression). We then propose an error feedback mechanism that enhances accuracy, which yields, as a byproduct, an algorithm-agnostic error feedback scheme that can be more broadly applied. We analyze the convergence of the resulting algorithm, and compare it with the state of the art through simulations in a realistic space scenario, showcasing superior performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20220v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruxandra-Stefania Tudose, Moritz H. W. Gr\"uss, Grace Ra Kim, Karl H. Johansson, Nicola Bastianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Identifying Internal Model-Based Online Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20411v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a novel online optimization algorithm built by combining ideas from control theory and system identification. The foundation of our algorithm is a control-based design that makes use of the internal model of the online problem. Since such prior knowledge of this internal model might not be available in practice, we incorporate an identification routine that learns this model on the fly. The algorithm is designed starting from quadratic online problems but can be applied to general problems. For quadratic cases, we characterize the asymptotic convergence to the optimal solution trajectory. We compare the proposed algorithm with existing approaches, and demonstrate how the identification routine ensures its adaptability to changes in the underlying internal model. Numerical results also indicate strong performance beyond the quadratic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20411v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wouter J. A. van Weerelt, Lantian Zhang, Silun Zhang, Nicola Bastianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonuniform-Grid Markov Chain Approximation of Continuous Processes with Time-Linear Moments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20416v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a method to approximate continuous-time, continuous-state stochastic processes by a discrete-time Markov chain defined on a nonuniform grid. Our method provides exact moment matching for processes whose first and second moments are linear functions of time. In particular, we show that, under certain conditions, the transition probabilities of a Markov chain can be chosen so that its first two moments match prescribed linear functions of time. These conditions depend on the grid points of the Markov chain and the coefficients of the linear mean and variance functions. Our proof relies on two recurrence relations for the expectation and variance across time. This approach enables simulation-based numerical analysis of continuous processes while preserving their key characteristics. We illustrate its efficacy by approximating continuous processes describing heat diffusion and geometric Brownian motion (GBM). For heat diffusion, we show that the heat profile at a set of points can be investigated by embedding those points inside the nonuniform grid of our Markov chain. For GBM, numerical simulations demonstrate that our approach, combined with suitable nonuniform grids, yields accurate approximations, with consistently small empirical Wasserstein-1 distances at long time horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20416v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do Hyun Kim, Ahemt Cetinkaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin-Assisted High-Precision Massive MIMO Localization in Urban Canyons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-precision wireless localization in urban canyons is challenged by noisy measurements and severe non-line-of-sight (NLOS) propagation. This paper proposes a robust three-stage algorithm synergizing a digital twin (DT) model with the random sample consensus (RANSAC) algorithm to overcome these limitations. The method leverages the DT for geometric path association and employs RANSAC to identify reliable line-of-sight (LOS) and single-bounce NLOS paths while rejecting multi-bounce outliers. A final optimization on the resulting inlier set estimates the user's position and clock bias. Simulations validate that by effectively turning NLOS paths into valuable geometric information via the DT, the approach enables accurate localization, reduces reliance on direct LOS, and significantly lowers system deployment costs, making it suitable for practical deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20453v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqin Zhou, Hui Chen, Gerhard Steinb\"ock, Henk Wymeersch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-Efficient Autonomous Mobile Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20467v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents pNav, a novel power-management system that significantly enhances the power/energy-efficiency of Autonomous Mobile Robots (AMRs) by jointly optimizing their physical/mechanical and cyber subsystems. By profiling AMRs' power consumption, we identify three challenges in achieving CPS (cyber-physical system) power-efficiency that involve both cyber (C) and physical (P) subsystems: (1) variabilities of system power consumption breakdown, (2) environment-aware navigation locality, and (3) coordination of C and P subsystems. pNav takes a multi-faceted approach to achieve power-efficiency of AMRs. First, it integrates millisecond-level power consumption prediction for both C and P subsystems. Second, it includes novel real-time modeling and monitoring of spatial and temporal navigation localities for AMRs. Third, it supports dynamic coordination of AMR software (navigation, detection) and hardware (motors, DVFS driver) configurations. pNav is prototyped using the Robot Operating System (ROS) Navigation Stack, 2D LiDAR, and camera. Our in-depth evaluation with a real robot and Gazebo environments demonstrates a &gt;96% accuracy in predicting power consumption and a 38.1% reduction in power consumption without compromising navigation accuracy and safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20467v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liangkai Liu, Weisong Shi, Kang G. Shin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe and Stable Neural Network Dynamical Systems for Robot Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning safe and stable robot motions from demonstrations remains a challenge, especially in complex, nonlinear tasks involving dynamic, obstacle-rich environments. In this paper, we propose Safe and Stable Neural Network Dynamical Systems S$^2$-NNDS, a learning-from-demonstration framework that simultaneously learns expressive neural dynamical systems alongside neural Lyapunov stability and barrier safety certificates. Unlike traditional approaches with restrictive polynomial parameterizations, S$^2$-NNDS leverages neural networks to capture complex robot motions providing probabilistic guarantees through split conformal prediction in learned certificates. Experimental results on various 2D and 3D datasets -- including LASA handwriting and demonstrations recorded kinesthetically from the Franka Emika Panda robot -- validate S$^2$-NNDS effectiveness in learning robust, safe, and stable motions from potentially unsafe demonstrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20593v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen Emmanuel Binny, Mahathi Anand, Hugo T. M. Kussaba, Lingyun Chen, Shreenabh Agrawal, Fares J. Abu-Dakka, Abdalla Swikir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse-to-Field Reconstruction via Stochastic Neural Dynamic Mode Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20612v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many consequential real-world systems, like wind fields and ocean currents, are dynamic and hard to model. Learning their governing dynamics remains a central challenge in scientific machine learning. Dynamic Mode Decomposition (DMD) provides a simple, data-driven approximation, but practical use is limited by sparse/noisy observations from continuous fields, reliance on linear approximations, and the lack of principled uncertainty quantification. To address these issues, we introduce Stochastic NODE-DMD, a probabilistic extension of DMD that models continuous-time, nonlinear dynamics while remaining interpretable. Our approach enables continuous spatiotemporal reconstruction at arbitrary coordinates and quantifies predictive uncertainty. Across four benchmarks, a synthetic setting and three physics-based flows, it surpasses a baseline in reconstruction accuracy when trained from only 10% observation density. It further recovers the dynamical structure by aligning learned modes and continuous-time eigenvalues with ground truth. Finally, on datasets with multiple realizations, our method learns a calibrated distribution over latent dynamics that preserves ensemble variability rather than averaging across regimes. Our code is available at: https://github.com/sedan-group/Stochastic-NODE-DMD</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20612v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujin Kim, Sarah Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterated Invariant Extended Kalman Filter (IterIEKF)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10665v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the mathematical properties of the Invariant Extended Kalman Filter (IEKF) when iterating on the measurement update step, following the principles of the well-known Iterated Extended Kalman Filter. This iterative variant of the IEKF (IterIEKF) systematically improves its accuracy through Gauss-Newton-based relinearization, and exhibits additional theoretical properties, particularly in the low-noise regime, that resemble those of the linear Kalman filter. We apply the proposed approach to the problem of estimating the extended pose of a crane payload using an inertial measurement unit. Our results suggest that the IterIEKF significantly outperforms the IEKF when measurements are highly accurate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10665v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Goffin, Axel Barrau, Silv\`ere Bonnabel, Olivier Br\"uls, Pierre Sacr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive Method for Contextual Stochastic Multi-armed Bandits with Rewards Generated by a Linear Dynamical System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10418v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Online decision-making can be formulated as the popular stochastic multi-armed bandit problem where a learner makes decisions (or takes actions) to maximize cumulative rewards collected from an unknown environment. This paper proposes to model a stochastic multi-armed bandit as an unknown linear Gaussian dynamical system, as many applications, such as bandits for dynamic pricing problems or hyperparameter selection for machine learning models, can benefit from this perspective. Following this approach, we can build a matrix representation of the system's steady-state Kalman filter that takes a set of previously collected observations from a time interval of length $s$ to predict the next reward that will be returned for each action. This paper proposes a solution in which the parameter $s$ is determined via an adaptive algorithm by analyzing the model uncertainty of the matrix representation. This algorithm helps the learner adaptively adjust its model size and its length of exploration based on the uncertainty of its environmental model. The effectiveness of the proposed scheme is demonstrated through extensive numerical studies, revealing that the proposed scheme is capable of increasing the rate of collected cumulative rewards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10418v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Gornet, Mehdi Hosseinzadeh, Bruno Sinopoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shaping Frequency Dynamics in Modern Power Systems with Grid-forming Converters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08161v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, frequency dynamics in modern power systems with a high penetration of converter-based generation is analysed. A fundamental analysis of the frequency dynamics is performed to identify the limitations and challenges when the converter penetration is increased. The voltage-source behaviour is found as an essential characteristic of converters to improve the initial frequency derivative of Synchronous Generators (SGs). A detailed small-signal analysis, based on the system's eigenvalues, participation factors and mode shapes, is then performed in a reduced system for different converter penetrations, showing that the flexibility of grid-forming (GFOR) converters as well as the system's inertia reduction may lead to have a more controllable system frequency. First-order frequency responses can be programmed for high converter penetrations, when GFOR operation can impose their dominance over SGs. These results have been validated in the IEEE 118-bus system simulated in PSCAD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08161v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Collados-Rodriguez, Daniel Westerman Spier, Marc Cheah-Mane, Eduardo Prieto-Araujo, Oriol Gomis-Bellmunt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KKL Observer Synthesis for Nonlinear Systems via Physics-Informed Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11655v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel learning approach for designing Kazantzis-Kravaris/Luenberger (KKL) observers for autonomous nonlinear systems. The design of a KKL observer involves finding an injective map that transforms the system state into a higher-dimensional observer state, whose dynamics is linear and stable. The observer's state is then mapped back to the original system coordinates via the inverse map to obtain the state estimate. However, finding this transformation and its inverse is quite challenging. We propose learning the forward mapping using a physics-informed neural network, and then learning its inverse mapping with a conventional feedforward neural network. Theoretical guarantees for the robustness of state estimation against approximation error and system uncertainties are provided, including non-asymptotic learning guarantees that link approximation quality to finite sample sizes. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is demonstrated through numerical simulations on benchmark examples, showing superior generalization capability outside the training domain compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11655v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Umar B. Niazi, John Cao, Matthieu Barreau, Karl Henrik Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of High-Order Quarter-Wave Plate for Residual Birefringence Suppression in FOCS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11386v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fiber optic current sensors (FOCS) are widely adopted in modern power grids due to high sensitivity, excellent insulation, and strong immunity to electromagnetic interference. This prominence necessitates precise investigation into their error sources and corresponding optimization. This study examines reflective FOCS based on the Faraday effect. A theoretical model is established to simulate phase error caused by linear birefringence from the quarter-wave plate. Conventional methods using circular birefringence are analyzed, revealing inherent limitations. Innovatively, a compensation strategy employing high-order quarter-wave plates is proposed to effectively eliminate linear birefringence effects. This approach significantly enhances the accuracy and practicality of FOCS in precision metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11386v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuechen Liu, Boqi Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangled Control of Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05900v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a general framework for multi-agent control synthesis, which applies to a wide range of problems with convergence guarantees, regardless of the complexity of the underlying graph topology and the explicit time dependence of the objective function. The proposed framework systematically addresses a particularly challenging problem in multi-agent systems, i.e., decentralization of entangled dynamics among different agents, and it naturally supports multi-objective robotics and real-time implementations. To demonstrate its generality and effectiveness, the framework is implemented across three experiments, namely time-varying leader-follower formation control, decentralized coverage control for time-varying density functions without any approximations, which is a long-standing open problem, and safe formation navigation in dense environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05900v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruoyu Lin, Gennaro Notomista, Magnus Egerstedt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computable Characterisations of Scaled Relative Graphs of Closed Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08420v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scaled Relative Graphs (SRGs) provide a promising tool for stability and robustness analysis of multi-input-multi-output systems. In this paper, we provide tools for exact and computable constructions of the SRG for closed linear operators, based on maximum and minimum gain computations. The results are suitable for bounded and unbounded operators, and we specify how they can be used to draw SRGs for the typical operators that are used to model linear-time-invariant dynamical systems. Furthermore, for the special case of state-space models, we show how the Bounded Real Lemma can be used to construct the SRG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08420v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Talitha Nauta, Richard Pates</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SafePR: Unified Approach for Safe Parallel Robots by Contact Detection and Reaction with Redundancy Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17773v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fast and safe motion is crucial for the successful deployment of physically interactive robots. Parallel robots (PRs) offer the potential for higher speeds while maintaining the same energy limits due to their low moving masses. However, they require methods for contact detection and reaction while avoiding singularities and self-collisions. We address this issue and present SafePR - a unified approach for the detection and localization, including the distinction between collision and clamping to perform a reaction that is safe for humans and feasible for PRs. Our approach uses information from the encoders and motor currents to estimate forces via a generalized-momentum observer. Neural networks and particle filters classify and localize the contacts. We introduce reactions with redundancy resolution to avoid self-collisions and type-II singularities. Our approach detected and terminated 72 real-world collision and clamping contacts with end-effector speeds of up to 1.5 m/s, each within 25-275 ms. The forces were below the thresholds from ISO/TS 15066. By using built-in sensors, SafePR enables safe interaction with already assembled PRs without the need for new hardware components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17773v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aran Mohammad, Tim-Lukas Habich, Thomas Seel, Moritz Schappler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons Learned from Developing a Privacy-Preserving Multimodal Wearable for Local Voice-and-Vision Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11811v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many promising applications of multimodal wearables require continuous sensing and heavy computation, yet users reject such devices due to privacy concerns. This paper shares our experiences building an ear-mounted voice-and-vision wearable that performs local AI inference using a paired smartphone as a trusted personal edge. We describe the hardware-software co-design of this privacy-preserving system, including challenges in integrating a camera, microphone, and speaker within a 30-gram form factor, enabling wake word-triggered capture, and running quantized vision-language and large-language models entirely offline. Through iterative prototyping, we identify key design hurdles in power budgeting, connectivity, latency, and social acceptability. Our initial evaluation shows that fully local multimodal inference is feasible on commodity mobile hardware with interactive latency. We conclude with design lessons for researchers developing embedded AI systems that balance privacy, responsiveness, and usability in everyday settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11811v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonatan Tussa, Andy Heredia, Nirupam Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
