<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY</link>
    <description>eess.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 04:01:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>ES-HPC-MPC: Exponentially Stable Hybrid Perception Constrained MPC for Quadrotor with Suspended Payloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aerial transportation using quadrotors with cable-suspended payloads holds great potential for applications in disaster response, logistics, and infrastructure maintenance. However, their hybrid and underactuated dynamics pose significant control and perception challenges. Traditional approaches often assume a taut cable condition, limiting their effectiveness in real-world applications where slack-to-taut transitions occur due to disturbances. We introduce ES-HPC-MPC, a model predictive control framework that enforces exponential stability and perception-constrained control under hybrid dynamics.
  Our method leverages Exponentially Stabilizing Control Lyapunov Functions (ES-CLFs) to enforce stability during the tasks and Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) to maintain the payload within the onboard camera's field of view (FoV). We validate our method through both simulation and real-world experiments, demonstrating stable trajectory tracking and reliable payload perception. We validate that our method maintains stability and satisfies perception constraints while tracking dynamically infeasible trajectories and when the system is subjected to hybrid mode transitions caused by unexpected disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08841v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis F. Recalde, Mrunal Sarvaiya, Giuseppe Loianno, Guanrui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Effects of Load Altering Attacks on Load Frequency Control through Python and RTDS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The modern power grid increasingly depends on advanced information and communication technology (ICT) systems to enhance performance and reliability through real-time monitoring, intelligent control, and bidirectional communication. However, ICT integration also exposes the grid to cyber-threats. Load altering attacks (LAAs), which use botnets of high-wattage devices to manipulate load profiles, are a notable threat to grid stability. While previous research has examined LAAs, their specific impact on load frequency control (LFC), critical for maintaining nominal frequency during load fluctuations, still needs to be explored. Even minor frequency deviations can jeopardize grid operations. This study bridges the gap by analyzing LAA effects on LFC through simulations of static and dynamic scenarios using Python and RTDS. The results highlight LAA impacts on frequency stability and present an eigenvalue-based stability assessment for dynamic LAAs (DLAAs), identifying key parameters influencing grid resilience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08951v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Forystek, Andrew D. Syrmakesis, Alkistis Kontou, Panos Kotsampopoulos, Nikos D. Hatziargyriou, Charalambos Konstantinou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sample Efficient Algorithms for Linear System Identification under Noisy Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we focus on learning linear dynamical systems under noisy observations. In this setting, existing algorithms either yield biased parameter estimates, or suffer from large sample complexities. To address these issues, we adapt the instrumental variable method and the bias compensation method, originally proposed for error-in-variables models, to our setting and provide refined non-asymptotic analysis. Under mild conditions, our algorithms achieve superior sample complexities that match the best-known sample complexity for learning a fully observable system without observation noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09057v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuyang Zhang, Xinhe Zhang, Jia Liu, Na Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HARQ-based Quantized Average Consensus over Unreliable Directed Network Topologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a distributed algorithm (herein called HARQ-QAC) that enables nodes to calculate the average of their initial states by exchanging quantized messages over a directed communication network. In our setting, we assume that our communication network consists of unreliable communication links (i.e., links suffering from packet drops). For countering link unreliability our algorithm leverages narrowband error-free feedback channels for acknowledging whether a packet transmission between nodes was successful. Additionally, we show that the feedback channels play a crucial role in enabling our algorithm to exhibit finite-time convergence. We analyze our algorithm and demonstrate its operation via an example, where we illustrate its operational advantages. Finally, simulations corroborate that our proposed algorithm converges to the average of the initial quantized values in a finite number of steps, despite the packet losses. This is the first quantized consensus algorithm in the literature that can handle packet losses and converge to the average. Additionally, the use of the retransmission mechanism allows for accelerating the convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09117v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neofytos Charalampous, Evagoras Makridis, Apostolos I. Rikos, Themistoklis Charalambous</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic stabilization under homomorphic encryption: A re-encryption free method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose methods to encrypted a pre-given dynamic controller with homomorphic encryption, without re-encrypting the control inputs. We first present a preliminary result showing that the coefficients in a pre-given dynamic controller can be scaled up into integers by the zooming-in factor in dynamic quantization, without utilizing re-encryption. However, a sufficiently small zooming-in factor may not always exist because it requires that the convergence speed of the pre-given closed-loop system should be sufficiently fast. Then, as the main result, we design a new controller approximating the pre-given dynamic controller, in which the zooming-in factor is decoupled from the convergence rate of the pre-given closed-loop system. Therefore, there always exist a (sufficiently small) zooming-in factor of dynamic quantization scaling up all the controller's coefficients to integers, and a finite modulus preventing overflow in cryptosystems. The process is asymptotically stable and the quantizer is not saturated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09248v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Feng, Qian Ma, Junsoo Kim, Shengyuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Scrap Composition in Electric Arc and Basic Oxygen Furnaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article aims to determine the composition of scrap (recycled material) used in an Electric Arc Furnace (EAF) or basic Oxygen Furnace (BOF) based on the assumption of mass balance. Accurate knowledge of this composition can increase the usage of recycled material to produce steel, reducing the need for raw ore extraction and minimizing environmental impact by conserving natural resources and lowering carbon emissions. The study develops two models to describe the behavior of elements in the EAF or BOF process. A linear state space model is used for elements transferring completely from scrap to steel, while a non-linear state space model is applied to elements moving into both steel and slag. The Kalman filter and unscented Kalman filter are employed to approximate these models, respectively. Importantly, the models leverage only data already collected as part of the standard production process, avoiding the need for additional measurements that are often costly. This article outlines the formulation of both models, the algorithms used, and discusses the hyperparameters involved. We provide practical suggestions on how to choose appropriate hyperparameters based on expert knowledge and historical data. The models are applied to real BOF data. Cu and Cr are chosen as examples for linear and non-linear models, respectively. The results show that both models can reconstruct the composition of scrap for these elements. The findings provide valuable insights for improving process control and ensuring product quality in steelmaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09382v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqing Zhou, Karsten Naert, Dirk Nuyens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Appointed-Time Fault-Tolerant Control for Flexible Hypersonic Vehicles with Unmeasurable States Independent of Initial Errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article aims to derive a practical tracking control algorithm for flexible air-breathing hypersonic vehicles (FAHVs) with lumped disturbances, unmeasurable states and actuator failures. Based on the framework of the backstepping technique, an appointed-time fault-tolerant protocol independent of initial errors is proposed. Firstly, a new type of a state observer is constructed to reconstruct the unmeasurable states. Then, an error transformation function is designed to achieve prescribed performance control that does not depend on the initial tracking error. To deal with the actuator failures, practical fixed-time neural network observers are established to provide the estimation of the lumped disturbances. Finally, the proposed control strategy can ensure the practical fixed-time convergence of the closed-loop system, thereby greatly enhancing the transient performance. The proposed method addresses the challenges of ensuring real-time measurement accuracy for angle of attack and flight path angle in hypersonic vehicles, coupled with potential sudden actuator failures, effectively overcoming the drawback of prescribed performance control that requires knowledge of initial tracking errors. Some simulation results are provided to demonstrate the feasibility and the effectiveness of the proposed strategy</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09414v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianlong Zhao, Fei Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HBS -- Hardware Build System: A Tcl-based, minimal common abstraction approach for build system for hardware designs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Build systems become an indispensable part of the software implementation and deployment process. New programming languages are released with the build system integrated into the language tools, for example, Go, Rust, or Zig. However, in the hardware description domain, no official build systems have been released with the predominant Hardware Description Languages (HDL) such as VHDL or SystemVerilog. Moreover, hardware design projects are often multilanguage.
  The paper proposes a new build system for the hardware description domain. The system is called the Hardware Build System (HBS). The main goals of the system include simplicity, readability, a minimal number of dependencies, and ease of integration with the existing Electronic Design Automation (EDA) tools. The system proposes a novel, minimal common abstraction approach, whose particular implications are described in the article. All the core functionalities are implemented in Tcl. Only the EDA tool's independent features, such as dependency graph generation, are implemented in a Python wrapper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09642v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Kruszewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Online Optimization for Vehicle-Home-Grid Integration including Household Load Prediction and Battery Degradation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the economic impact of vehicle-home-grid integration, by proposing an online energy management algorithm that optimizes energy flows between an electric vehicle (EV), a household, and the electrical grid. The algorithm leverages vehicle-to-home (V2H) for self-consumption and vehicle-to-grid (V2G) for energy trading, adapting to real-time conditions through a hybrid long short-term memory (LSTM) neural network for accurate household load prediction, alongside a comprehensive nonlinear battery degradation model accounting for both cycle and calendar aging. Simulation results reveal significant economic advantages: compared to smart unidirectional charging, the proposed method yields an annual economic benefit of up to EUR 3046.81, despite a modest 1.96% increase in battery degradation. Even under unfavorable market conditions, where V2G energy selling generates no revenue, V2H alone ensures yearly savings of EUR 425.48. A systematic sensitivity analysis investigates how variations in battery capacity, household load, and price ratios affect economic outcomes, confirming the consistent benefits of bidirectional energy exchange. These findings highlight the potential of EVs as active energy nodes, enabling sustainable energy management and cost-effective battery usage in real-world conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09657v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Popolizio, Torsten Wik, Chih Feng Lee, Changfu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Input and State Estimation under Output Quantization: A Gaussian Mixture approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simultaneous Input and State Estimation (SISE) enables the reconstruction of unknown inputs and internal states in dynamical systems, with applications in fault detection, robotics, and control. While various methods exist for linear systems, extensions to systems with output quantization are scarce, and formal connections to limit Kalman filters in this context are lacking. This work addresses these gaps by proposing a novel SISE algorithm for linear systems with quantized output measurements that is based on a Gaussian mixture model formulation. The observation model is represented as a Gaussian sum density, leading to closed-form recursive equations in the form of a Gaussian sum filter. In the absence of input prior knowledge, the recursions converge to a limit-case SISE algorithm, implementable as a bank of linear SISE filters running in parallel. A simulation example is presented to illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09711v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo A. Gonz\'alez, Angel L. Cede\~no</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning-based decentralized control with collision avoidance for multi-agent systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a learning-based tracking controller based on Gaussian processes (GP) for collision avoidance of multi-agent systems where the agents evolve in the special Euclidean group in the space SE(3). In particular, we use GPs to estimate certain uncertainties that appear in the dynamics of the agents. The control algorithm is designed to learn and mitigate these uncertainties by using GPs as a learning-based model for the predictions. In particular, the presented approach guarantees that the tracking error remains bounded with high probability. We present some simulation results to show how the control algorithm is implemented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09730v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omayra Yago Nieto, Alexandre Anahory Simoes, Juan I. Giribet, Leonardo J. Colombo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Lyapunov and Barrier Function-Based Control with Stabilization Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Control Lyapunov Functions (CLFs) and Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) can be combined, typically by means of Quadratic Programs (QPs), to design controllers that achieve performance and safety objectives. However, a significant limitation of this framework is the introduction of asymptotically stable equilibrium points besides the minimizer of the CLF, leading to deadlock situations even for simple systems and bounded convex unsafe sets. To address this problem, we propose a hybrid CLF-CBF control framework with global asymptotic stabilization and safety guarantees, offering a more flexible and systematic design methodology compared to current alternatives available in the literature. We further extend this framework to higher-order systems via a recursive procedure based on a joint CLF-CBF backstepping approach. The proposed solution is assessed through several simulation examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09760v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Matias, Daniel Silvestre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Output-Feedback MPC for Nonlinear Systems with Applications to Robotic Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel method for robust output-feedback model predictive control (MPC) for a class of nonlinear discrete-time systems. We propose a novel interval-valued predictor which, given an initial estimate of the state, produces intervals which are guaranteed to contain the future trajectory of the system. By parameterizing the control input with an initial stabilizing feedback term, we are able to reduce the width of the predicted state intervals compared to existing methods. We demonstrate this through a numerical comparison where we show that our controller performs better in the presence of large amounts of noise. Finally, we present a simulation study of a robot navigation scenario, where we incorporate a time-varying entropy term into the cost function in order to autonomously explore an uncertain area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09768v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott Brown, Mohammad Khajenejad, Aamodh Suresh, Sonia Martinez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computationally Efficient State and Model Estimation via Interval Observers for Partially Unknown Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the synthesis of interval observers for partially unknown nonlinear systems subject to bounded noise, aiming to simultaneously estimate system states and learn a model of the unknown dynamics. Our approach leverages Jacobian sign-stable (JSS) decompositions, tight decomposition functions for nonlinear systems, and a data-driven over-approximation framework to construct interval estimates that provably enclose the true augmented states. By recursively computing tight and tractable bounds for the unknown dynamics based on current and past interval framers, we systematically integrate these bounds into the observer design. Additionally, we formulate semi-definite programs (SDP) for observer gain synthesis, ensuring input-to-state stability and optimality of the proposed framework. Finally, simulation results demonstrate the computational efficiency of our approach compared to a method previously proposed by the authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09784v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Khajenejad, Zeyuan Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov Clustering based Fully Automated Nonblocking Hierarchical Supervisory Control of Large-Scale Discrete-Event Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we revisit the abstraction-based approach to synthesize a hierarchy of decentralized supervisors and coordinators for nonblocking control of large-scale discrete-event systems (DES), and augment it with a new clustering method for automatic and flexible grouping of relevant components during the hierarchical synthesis process. This method is known as Markov clustering, which not only automatically performs grouping but also allows flexible tuning the sizes of the resulting clusters using a single parameter. Compared to the existing abstraction-based approach that lacks effective grouping method for general cases, our proposed approach based on Markov clustering provides a fully automated and effective hierarchical synthesis procedure applicable to general large-scale DES. Moreover, it is proved that the resulting hierarchy of supervisors and coordinators collectively achieves global nonblocking (and maximally permissive) controlled behavior under the same conditions as those in the existing abstraction-based approach. Finally, a benchmark case study is conducted to empirically demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09884v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingying Liu, Zhaojian Cai, Kai Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient modelling of memristive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a gradient modeling framework for memristive systems. Our focus is on memristive systems as they appear in neurophysiology and neuromorphic systems. Revisiting the original definition of Chua, we regard memristive elements as gradient operators of quadratic functionals with respect to a metric determined by the memristance. We explore the consequences of gradient properties for the analysis and design of neuromorphic circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10093v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fulvio Forni, Rodolphe Sepulchre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Structure in MIMO Scaled Graph Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scaled graphs offer a graphical tool for analysis of nonlinear feedback systems. Although recently substantial progress has been made in scaled graph analysis, at present their use in multivariable feedback systems is limited by conservatism. In this paper, we aim to reduce this conservatism by introducing multipliers and exploit system structure in the analysis with scaled graphs. In particular, we use weighted inner products to arrive at a weighted scaled graph and combine this with a commutation property to formulate a stability result for multivariable feedback systems. We present a method for computing the weighted scaled graph of Lur'e systems based on solving sets of linear matrix inequalities, and demonstrate a significant reduction in conservatism through an example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10135v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timo de Groot, Tom Oomen, Sebastiaan van den Eijnden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Paradigm in IBR Modeling for Power Flow and Short Circuit Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fault characteristics of inverter-based resources (IBRs) are different from conventional synchronous generators. The fault response of IBRs is non-linear due to saturation states and mainly determined by fault ride through (FRT) strategies of the associated voltage source converter (VSC). This results in prohibitively large solution times for power flows considering these short circuit characteristics, especially when the power system states change fast due to uncertainty in IBR generations. To overcome this, a phasor-domain steady state (SS) short circuit (SC) solver for IBR dominated power systems is proposed in this paper, and subsequently the developed IBR models are incorporated with a novel Jacobian-based Power Flow (PF) solver. In this multiphase PF solver, any power system components can be modeled by considering their original non-linear or linear mathematical representations. Moreover, two novel FRT strategies are proposed to fully utilize the converter capacity and to comply with IEEE-2800 2022 std and German grid code. The results are compared with the Electromagnetic Transient (EMT) simulation on the IEEE 34 test network and the 120 kV EPRI benchmark system. The developed IBR sequence domain PF model demonstrates more accurate behavior compared to the classical IBR generator model. The error in calculating the short circuit current with the proposed SC solver is less than 3%, while achieving significant speed improvements of three order of magnitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10181v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahid Javid, Firdous Ul Nazir, Wentao Zhu, Diptargha Chakravorty, Ahmed Aboushady, Mohamed Galeela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A moving horizon estimator for aquifer thermal energy storages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10203v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aquifer thermal energy storages (ATES) represent groundwater saturated aquifers that store thermal energy in the form of heated or cooled groundwater. Combining two ATES, one can harness excess thermal energy from summer (heat) and winter (cold) to support the building's heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) technology. In general, a dynamic operation of ATES throughout the year is beneficial to avoid using fossil fuel-based HVAC technology and maximize the ``green use'' of ATES. Model predictive control (MPC) with an appropriate system model may become a crucial control approach for ATES systems. Consequently, the MPC model should reflect spatial temperature profiles around ATES' boreholes to predict extracted groundwater temperatures accurately. However, meaningful predictions require the estimation of the current state of the system, as measurements are usually only at the borehole of the ATES. In control, this is often realized by model-based observers. Still, observing the state of an ATES system is non-trivial, since the model is typically hybrid. We show how to exploit the specific structure of the hybrid ATES model and design an easy-to-solve moving horizon estimator based on a quadratic program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10203v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes van Randenborgh, Moritz Schulze Darup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reactive power flow optimization in AC drive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores a limit avoidance approach in the case of input (modulation) and output (current) constraints with the aim of enhancing system availability of AC drives. Drawing on the observation that, in a certain range of reactive power, there exists a trade-off between current and modulation magnitude, we exploit this freedom and define a constrained optimization problem. We propose two approaches, one in the form of an activation-function which drives the reactive power set-point towards safety, and an approach which uses online feedback optimization to set the reactive power dynamically. Both methods compromise reactive power tracking accuracy for increased system robustness. Through a high fidelity simulation, we compare the benefits of the two methods, highlighting their effectiveness in industrial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10360v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Chandrasekaran, Catalin Arghir, Pieder Joerg, Florian Doerfler, Silvia Mastellone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A 10.8mW Mixed-Signal Simulated Bifurcation Ising Solver using SRAM Compute-In-Memory with 0.6us Time-to-Solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Combinatorial optimization problems are funda- mental for various fields ranging from finance to wireless net- works. This work presents a simulated bifurcation (SB) Ising solver in CMOS for NP-hard optimization problems. Analog domain computing led to a superior implementation of this algorithm as inherent and injected noise is required in SB Ising solvers. The architecture novelties include the use of SRAM compute-in-memory (CIM) to accelerate bifurcation as well as the generation and injection of optimal decaying noise in the analog domain. We propose a novel 10-T SRAM cell capable of performing ternary multiplication. When measured with 60- node, 50% density, random, binary MAXCUT graphs, this all- to-all connected Ising solver reliably achieves above 93% of the ground state solution in 0.6us with 10.8mW average power in TSMC 180nm CMOS. Our chip achieves an order of magnitude improvement in time-to-solution and power compared to previously proposed Ising solvers in CMOS and other platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10384v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alana Marie Dee, Sajjad Moazeni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Order Reduction of Linear Systems via $(\gamma,\delta)$-Similarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10437v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Model order reduction aims to determine a low-order approximation of high-order models with least possible approximation errors. For application to physical systems, it is crucial that the reduced order model (ROM) is robust to any disturbance that acts on the full order model (FOM) -- in the sense that the output of the ROM remains a good approximation of that of the FOM, even in the presence of such disturbances. In this work, we present a framework for model order reduction for a class of continuous-time linear systems that ensures this property for any $L_2$ disturbance. Apart from robustness to disturbances in this sense, the proposed framework also displays other desirable properties for model order reduction: (1) a provable bound on the error defined as the $L_2$ norm of the difference between the output of the ROM and FOM, (2) preservation of stability, (3) compositionality properties and a provable error bound for arbitrary interconnected systems, (4) a provable bound on the output of the FOM when the controller designed for the ROM is used with the FOM, and finally, (5) compatibility with existing approaches such as balanced truncation and moment matching. Property (4) does not require computation of any gap metric and property (5) is beneficial as existing approaches can also be equipped with some of the preceding properties. The theoretical results are corroborated on numerical case studies, including on a building model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10437v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Bajaj, Carolyn L. Beck, Vijay Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Analysis of Interpretable Aging across Thousands of Lithium-ion Battery Cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Doyle-Fuller-Newman (DFN) model is a common mechanistic model for lithium-ion batteries. The reaction rate constant and diffusivity within the DFN model are key parameters that directly affect the movement of lithium ions, thereby offering explanations for cell aging. This work investigates the ability to uniquely estimate each electrode's diffusion coefficients and reaction rate constants of 95 Tesla Model 3 cells with a nickel cobalt aluminum oxide (NCA) cathode and silicon oxide--graphite (LiC$_\text{6}$--SiO$_{\text{x}}$) anode. The parameters are estimated at intermittent diagnostic cycles over the lifetime of each cell. The four parameters are estimated using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) for uncertainty quantification (UQ) for a total of 7776 cycles at discharge C-rates of C/5, 1C, and 2C. While one or more anode parameters are uniquely identifiable over every cell's lifetime, cathode parameters become identifiable at mid- to end-of-life, indicating measurable resistive growth in the cathode. The contribution of key parameters to the state of health (SOH) is expressed as a power law. This model for SOH shows a high consistency with the MCMC results performed over the overall lifespan of each cell. Our approach suggests that effective diagnosis of aging can be achieved by predicting the trajectories of the parameters contributing to cell aging. As such, extending our analysis with more physically accurate models building on DFN may lead to more identifiable parameters and further improved aging predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10439v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc D. Berliner, Minsu Kim, Xiao Cui, Vivek N. Lam, Patrick A. Asinger, Martin Z. Bazant, William C. Chueh, Richard D. Braatz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layered Multirate Control of Constrained Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10461v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Layered control architectures have been a standard paradigm for efficiently managing complex constrained systems. A typical architecture consists of: i) a higher layer, where a low-frequency planner controls a simple model of the system, and ii) a lower layer, where a high-frequency tracking controller guides a detailed model of the system toward the output of the higher-layer model. A fundamental problem in this layered architecture is the design of planners and tracking controllers that guarantee both higher- and lower-layer system constraints are satisfied. Toward addressing this problem, we introduce a principled approach for layered multirate control of linear systems subject to output and input constraints. Inspired by discrete-time simulation functions, we propose a streamlined control design that guarantees the lower-layer system tracks the output of the higher-layer system with computable precision. Using this design, we derive conditions and present a method for propagating the constraints of the lower-layer system to the higher-layer system. The propagated constraints are integrated into the design of an arbitrary planner that can handle higher-layer system constraints. Our framework ensures that the output constraints of the lower-layer system are satisfied at all high-level time steps, while respecting its input constraints at all low-level time steps. We apply our approach in a scenario of motion planning, highlighting its critical role in ensuring collision avoidance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10461v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charis Stamouli, Anastasios Tsiamis, Manfred Morari, George J. Pappas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Topic Analysis in Academic Journals using Convex Non-negative Matrix Factorization Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the rapid advancement of large language models, academic topic identification and topic evolution analysis are crucial for enhancing AI's understanding capabilities. Dynamic topic analysis provides a powerful approach to capturing and understanding the temporal evolution of topics in large-scale datasets. This paper presents a two-stage dynamic topic analysis framework that incorporates convex optimization to improve topic consistency, sparsity, and interpretability. In Stage 1, a two-layer non-negative matrix factorization (NMF) model is employed to extract annual topics and identify key terms. In Stage 2, a convex optimization algorithm refines the dynamic topic structure using the convex NMF (cNMF) model, further enhancing topic integration and stability. Applying the proposed method to IEEE journal abstracts from 2004 to 2022 effectively identifies and quantifies emerging research topics, such as COVID-19 and digital twins. By optimizing sparsity differences in the clustering feature space between traditional and emerging research topics, the framework provides deeper insights into topic evolution and ranking analysis. Moreover, the NMF-cNMF model demonstrates superior stability in topic consistency. At sparsity levels of 0.4, 0.6, and 0.9, the proposed approach improves topic ranking stability by 24.51%, 56.60%, and 36.93%, respectively. The source code (to be open after publication) is available at https://github.com/meetyangyang/CDNMF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08743v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Yang, Tong Zhang, Jian Wu, Lijie Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Graph-Enhanced DeepONet Approach for Real-Time Estimating Hydrogen-Enriched Natural Gas Flow under Variable Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Blending green hydrogen into natural gas presents a promising approach for renewable energy integration and fuel decarbonization. Accurate estimation of hydrogen fraction in hydrogen-enriched natural gas (HENG) pipeline networks is crucial for operational safety and efficiency, yet it remains challenging due to complex dynamics. While existing data-driven approaches adopt end-to-end architectures for HENG flow state estimation, their limited adaptability to varying operational conditions hinders practical applications. To this end, this study proposes a graph-enhanced DeepONet framework for the real-time estimation of HENG flow, especially hydrogen fractions. First, a dual-network architecture, called branch network and trunk network, is employed to characterize operational conditions and sparse sensor measurements to estimate the HENG state at targeted locations and time points. Second, a graph-enhance branch network is proposed to incorporate pipeline topology, improving the estimation accuracy in large-scale pipeline networks. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed method achieves superior estimation accuracy for HCNG flow under varying operational conditions compared to conventional approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08816v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sicheng Liu, Hongchang Huang, Bo Yang, Mingxuan Cai, Xu Yang, Xinping Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Slip AI-Driven Model-Free Control with Global Exponential Stability in Skid-Steering Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Undesired lateral and longitudinal wheel slippage can disrupt a mobile robot's heading angle, traction, and, eventually, desired motion. This issue makes the robotization and accurate modeling of heavy-duty machinery very challenging because the application primarily involves off-road terrains, which are susceptible to uneven motion and severe slippage. As a step toward robotization in skid-steering heavy-duty robot (SSHDR), this paper aims to design an innovative robust model-free control system developed by neural networks to strongly stabilize the robot dynamics in the presence of a broad range of potential wheel slippages. Before the control design, the dynamics of the SSHDR are first investigated by mathematically incorporating slippage effects, assuming that all functional modeling terms of the system are unknown to the control system. Then, a novel tracking control framework to guarantee global exponential stability of the SSHDR is designed as follows: 1) the unknown modeling of wheel dynamics is approximated using radial basis function neural networks (RBFNNs); and 2) a new adaptive law is proposed to compensate for slippage effects and tune the weights of the RBFNNs online during execution. Simulation and experimental results verify the proposed tracking control performance of a 4,836 kg SSHDR operating on slippery terrain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08831v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Heydari Shahna, Pauli Mustalahti, Jouni Mattila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InterQ: A DQN Framework for Optimal Intermittent Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09035v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we explore the communication-control co-design of discrete-time stochastic linear systems through reinforcement learning. Specifically, we examine a closed-loop system involving two sequential decision-makers: a scheduler and a controller. The scheduler continuously monitors the system's state but transmits it to the controller intermittently to balance the communication cost and control performance. The controller, in turn, determines the control input based on the intermittently received information. Given the partially nested information structure, we show that the optimal control policy follows a certainty-equivalence form. Subsequently, we analyze the qualitative behavior of the scheduling policy. To develop the optimal scheduling policy, we propose InterQ, a deep reinforcement learning algorithm which uses a deep neural network to approximate the Q-function. Through extensive numerical evaluations, we analyze the scheduling landscape and further compare our approach against two baseline strategies: (a) a multi-period periodic scheduling policy, and (b) an event-triggered policy. The results demonstrate that our proposed method outperforms both baselines. The open source implementation can be found at https://github.com/AC-sh/InterQ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09035v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Aggarwal, Dipankar Maity, Tamer Ba\c{s}ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonconvex Obstacle Avoidance using Efficient Sampling-Based Distance Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider nonconvex obstacle avoidance where a robot described by nonlinear dynamics and a nonconvex shape has to avoid nonconvex obstacles. Obstacle avoidance is a fundamental problem in robotics and well studied in control. However, existing solutions are computationally expensive (e.g., model predictive controllers), neglect nonlinear dynamics (e.g., graph-based planners), use diffeomorphic transformations into convex domains (e.g., for star shapes), or are conservative due to convex overapproximations. The key challenge here is that the computation of the distance between the shapes of the robot and the obstacles is a nonconvex problem. We propose efficient computation of this distance via sampling-based distance functions. We quantify the sampling error and show that, for certain systems, such sampling-based distance functions are valid nonsmooth control barrier functions. We also study how to deal with disturbances on the robot dynamics in our setting. Finally, we illustrate our method on a robot navigation task involving an omnidirectional robot and nonconvex obstacles. We also analyze performance and computational efficiency of our controller as a function of the number of samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09038v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Lutkus, Michelle S. Chong, Lars Lindemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Robot Coordination with Adversarial Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09047v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the resilience of perception-based multi-robot coordination with wireless communication to online adversarial perception. A systematic study of this problem is essential for many safety-critical robotic applications that rely on the measurements from learned perception modules. We consider a (small) team of quadrotor robots that rely only on an Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) and the visual data measurements obtained from a learned multi-task perception module (e.g., object detection) for downstream tasks, including relative localization and coordination. We focus on a class of adversarial perception attacks that cause misclassification, mislocalization, and latency. We propose that the effects of adversarial misclassification and mislocalization can be modeled as sporadic (intermittent) and spurious measurement data for the downstream tasks. To address this, we present a framework for resilience analysis of multi-robot coordination with adversarial measurements. The framework integrates data from Visual-Inertial Odometry (VIO) and the learned perception model for robust relative localization and state estimation in the presence of adversarially sporadic and spurious measurements. The framework allows for quantifying the degradation in system observability and stability in relation to the success rate of adversarial perception. Finally, experimental results on a multi-robot platform demonstrate the real-world applicability of our methodology for resource-constrained robotic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09047v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayan Bahrami, Hamidreza Jafarnejadsani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compliant Explicit Reference Governor for Contact Friendly Robotic Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the Compliant Explicit Reference Governor (C-ERG), an extension of the Explicit Reference Governor that allows the robot to operate safely while in contact with the environment.
  The C-ERG is an intermediate layer that can be placed between a high-level planner and a low-level controller: its role is to enforce operational constraints and to enable the smooth transition between free-motion and contact operations. The C-ERG ensures safety by limiting the total energy available to the robotic arm at the time of contact. In the absence of contact, however, the C-ERG does not penalize the system performance.
  Numerical examples showcase the behavior of the C-ERG for increasingly complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09188v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaashia Gautam, Nataliya Nechyporenko, Chi-Hui Lin, Alessandro Roncone, Marco M. Nicotra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Implementation of Reinforcement Learning over Homomorphic Encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate encrypted control policy synthesis over the cloud. While encrypted control implementations have been studied previously, we focus on the less explored paradigm of privacy-preserving control synthesis, which can involve heavier computations ideal for cloud outsourcing. We classify control policy synthesis into model-based, simulator-driven, and data-driven approaches and examine their implementation over fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) for privacy enhancements. A key challenge arises from comparison operations (min or max) in standard reinforcement learning algorithms, which are difficult to execute over encrypted data. This observation motivates our focus on Relative-Entropy-regularized reinforcement learning (RL) problems, which simplifies encrypted evaluation of synthesis algorithms due to their comparison-free structures. We demonstrate how linearly solvable value iteration, path integral control, and Z-learning can be readily implemented over FHE. We conduct a case study of our approach through numerical simulations of encrypted Z-learning in a grid world environment using the CKKS encryption scheme, showing convergence with acceptable approximation error. Our work suggests the potential for secure and efficient cloud-based reinforcement learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.11499/sicejl.64.223</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of The Society of Instrument and Control Engineers, vol. 64, no. 4, pp. 223-229, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jihoon Suh, Takashi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computationally Efficient Signal Detection with Unknown Bandwidths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Signal detection in environments with unknown signal bandwidth and time intervals is a basic problem in adversarial and spectrum-sharing scenarios. This paper addresses the problem of detecting signals occupying unknown degrees of freedom from non-coherent power measurements where the signal is constrained to an interval in one dimension or hypercube in multiple dimensions. A Generalized Likelihood Ratio Test (GLRT) is derived, resulting in a straightforward metric involving normalized average signal energy on each candidate signal set. We present bounds on false alarm and missed detection probabilities, demonstrating their dependence on signal-to-noise ratios (SNR) and signal set sizes. To overcome the inherent computational complexity of exhaustive searches, we propose a computationally efficient binary search method, reducing the complexity from O(N2) to O(N) for one-dimensional cases. Simulations indicate that the method maintains performance near exhaustive searches and achieves asymptotic consistency, with interval-of-overlap converging to one under constant SNR as measurement size increases. The simulation studies also demonstrate superior performance and reduced complexity compared to contemporary neural network-based approaches, specifically outperforming custom-trained U-Net models in spectrum detection tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09342v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Rasteh, Sundeep Rangan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expressivity of Quadratic Neural ODEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09385v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work focuses on deriving quantitative approximation error bounds for neural ordinary differential equations having at most quadratic nonlinearities in the dynamics. The simple dynamics of this model form demonstrates how expressivity can be derived primarily from iteratively composing many basic elementary operations, versus from the complexity of those elementary operations themselves. Like the analog differential analyzer and universal polynomial DAEs, the expressivity is derived instead primarily from the "depth" of the model. These results contribute to our understanding of what depth specifically imparts to the capabilities of deep learning architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09385v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Hanson, Maxim Raginsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble-Enhanced Graph Autoencoder with GAT and Transformer-Based Encoders for Robust Fault Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fault classification in industrial machinery is vital for enhancing reliability and reducing downtime, yet it remains challenging due to the variability of vibration patterns across diverse operating conditions. This study introduces a novel graph-based framework for fault classification, converting time-series vibration data from machinery operating at varying horsepower levels into a graph representation. We utilize Shannon's entropy to determine the optimal window size for data segmentation, ensuring each segment captures significant temporal patterns, and employ Dynamic Time Warping (DTW) to define graph edges based on segment similarity. A Graph Auto Encoder (GAE) with a deep graph transformer encoder, decoder, and ensemble classifier is developed to learn latent graph representations and classify faults across various categories. The GAE's performance is evaluated on the Case Western Reserve University (CWRU) dataset, with cross-dataset generalization assessed on the HUST dataset. Results show that GAE achieves a mean F1-score of 0.99 on the CWRU dataset, significantly outperforming baseline models-CNN, LSTM, RNN, GRU, and Bi-LSTM (F1-scores: 0.94-0.97, p &lt; 0.05, Wilcoxon signed-rank test for Bi-LSTM: p &lt; 0.05) -- particularly in challenging classes (e.g., Class 8: 0.99 vs. 0.71 for Bi-LSTM). Visualization of dataset characteristics reveals that datasets with amplified vibration patterns and diverse fault dynamics enhance generalization. This framework provides a robust solution for fault diagnosis under varying conditions, offering insights into dataset impacts on model performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09427v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moirangthem Tiken Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Two-Stage Distributionally Robust Dispatch of Multi-Energy Microgrid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies adaptive distributionally robust dispatch (DRD) of the multi-energy microgrid under supply and demand uncertainties. A Wasserstein ambiguity set is constructed to support data-driven decision-making. By fully leveraging the special structure of worst-case expectation from the primal perspective, a novel and high-efficient decomposition algorithm under the framework of column-and-constraint generation is customized and developed to address the computational burden. Numerical studies demonstrate the effectiveness of our DRD approach, and shed light on the interrelationship of it with the traditional dispatch approaches through stochastic programming and robust optimization schemes. Also, comparisons with popular algorithms in the literature for two-stage distributionally robust optimization verify the powerful capacity of our algorithm in computing the DRD problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09638v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunhang Sun, Xiaoyu Cao, Bo Zeng, Miaomiao Li, Xiaohong Guan, Tamer Ba\c{s}ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UruBots RoboCup Work Team Description Paper</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents a team description paper for the RoboCup Work League. Our team, UruBots, has been developing robots and projects for research and competitions in the last three years, attending robotics competitions in Uruguay and around the world. In this instance, we aim to participate and contribute to the RoboCup Work category, hopefully making our debut in this prestigious competition. For that, we present an approach based on the Limo robot, whose main characteristic is its hybrid locomotion system with wheels and tracks, with some extras added by the team to complement the robot's functionalities. Overall, our approach allows the robot to efficiently and autonomously navigate a Work scenario, with the ability to manipulate objects, perform autonomous navigation, and engage in a simulated industrial environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09755v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiago Sodre, Juan Deniz, Pablo Moraes, William Moraes, Igor Nunes, Vincent Sandin, Ahilen Mazondo, Santiago Fernandez, Gabriel da Silva, Monica Rodriguez, Sebastian Barcelona, Ricardo Grando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Score Matching Diffusion Based Feedback Control and Planning of Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel control-theoretic framework that leverages principles from generative modeling -- specifically, Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models (DDPMs) -- to stabilize control-affine systems with nonholonomic constraints. Unlike traditional stochastic approaches, which rely on noise-driven dynamics in both forward and reverse processes, our method crucially eliminates the need for noise in the reverse phase, making it particularly relevant for control applications. We introduce two formulations: one where noise perturbs all state dimensions during the forward phase while the control system enforces time reversal deterministically, and another where noise is restricted to the control channels, embedding system constraints directly into the forward process.
  For controllable nonlinear drift-free systems, we prove that deterministic feedback laws can exactly reverse the forward process, ensuring that the system's probability density evolves correctly without requiring artificial diffusion in the reverse phase. Furthermore, for linear time-invariant systems, we establish a time-reversal result under the second formulation. By eliminating noise in the backward process, our approach provides a more practical alternative to machine learning-based denoising methods, which are unsuitable for control applications due to the presence of stochasticity. We validate our results through numerical simulations on benchmark systems, including a unicycle model in a domain with obstacles, a driftless five-dimensional system, and a four-dimensional linear system, demonstrating the potential for applying diffusion-inspired techniques in linear, nonlinear, and settings with state space constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09836v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karthik Elamvazhuthi, Darshan Gadginmath, Fabio Pasqualetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling &amp; Steady State Compliance Testing of an Improved Time Synchronized Phasor Measurement Unit Based on IEEE Standard C37.118.1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09883v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Synchrophasor technology is an emerging and developing technology for monitoring and control of wide area measurement systems (WAMS). In an elementary WAMS, two identical phasors measured at two different locations have difference in the phase angles measured since their reference waveforms are not synchronized with each other. Phasor measurement units (PMUs) measure input phasors with respect to a common reference wave based on the atomic clock pulses received from global positioning system (GPS) satellites, eliminating variation in the measured phase angles due to distant locations of the measurement nodes. This has found tremendous applications in quick fault detection, fault location analysis, accurate current, voltage, frequency and phase angle measurements in WAMS. Commercially available PMU models are often proven to be expensive for research and development as well as for grid integration projects. This research article proposes an economic PMU model optimized for accurate steadystate performance based on recursive discrete Fourier transform (DFT) and provides results and detailed analysis of the proposed PMU model as per the steady state compliance specifications of IEEE standard C37.118.1. Results accurate up to 13 digits after decimal point are obtained through the developed PMU model for both nominal and off-nominal frequency inputs in steady state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09883v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/IICPE.2018.8709617</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE India International Conference on Power Electronics (IICPE) 2018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nisarg Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully-Adaptive and Semi-Adaptive Frequency Sweep Algorithm Exploiting Loewner-State Model for EM Simulation of Multiport Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09942v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper employs a fully adaptive and semi-adaptive frequency sweep algorithm using the Loewner matrix-based state model for the electromagnetic simulation. The proposed algorithms use two Loewner matrix models with different or the same orders with small frequency perturbation for adaptive frequency selection. The error between the two models is calculated in each iteration, and the next frequency points are selected to minimize maximum error. With the help of memory, the algorithm terminates when the error between the model and the simulation result is reached within the specified error tolerance. In the fully adaptive frequency sweep algorithm, the method starts with the minimum and maximum frequency of simulation. In the semi-adaptive algorithm, a novel approach has been proposed to determine the initial number of frequency points necessary for system interpolation based on the electrical size of the structure. The proposed algorithms have been compared with the Stoer-Bulirsch algorithm and Pradovera's minimal sampling algorithm for electromagnetic simulation. Four examples are presented using MATLAB R2024b. The results show that the proposed methods offer better performance in terms of speed, accuracy and the requirement of the minimum number of frequency samples. The proposed method shows remarkable consistency with full-wave simulation data, and the algorithm can be effectively applicable to electromagnetic simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09942v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TMTT.2025.3557208</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shilpa T. N., Rakesh Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Resilient Tracking in Autonomous Vehicles: A Distributionally Robust Input and State Estimation Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09974v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel framework for the distributionally robust input and state estimation (DRISE) for autonomous vehicles operating under model uncertainties and measurement outliers. The proposed framework improves the input and state estimation (ISE) approach by integrating distributional robustness, enhancing the estimator's resilience and robustness to adversarial inputs and unmodeled dynamics. Moment-based ambiguity sets capture probabilistic uncertainties in both system dynamics and measurement noise, offering analytical tractability and efficiently handling uncertainties in mean and covariance. In particular, the proposed framework minimizes the worst-case estimation error, ensuring robustness against deviations from nominal distributions. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is validated through simulations conducted in the CARLA autonomous driving simulator, demonstrating improved performance in state estimation accuracy and robustness in dynamic and uncertain environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09974v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kasra Azizi, Kumar Anurag, Wenbin Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Human-Sensitive Controller: Adapting to Human Ergonomics and Physical Constraints via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10102v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Work-Related Musculoskeletal Disorders continue to be a major challenge in industrial environments, leading to reduced workforce participation, increased healthcare costs, and long-term disability. This study introduces a human-sensitive robotic system aimed at reintegrating individuals with a history of musculoskeletal disorders into standard job roles, while simultaneously optimizing ergonomic conditions for the broader workforce. This research leverages reinforcement learning to develop a human-aware control strategy for collaborative robots, focusing on optimizing ergonomic conditions and preventing pain during task execution. Two RL approaches, Q-Learning and Deep Q-Network (DQN), were implemented and tested to personalize control strategies based on individual user characteristics. Although experimental results revealed a simulation-to-real gap, a fine-tuning phase successfully adapted the policies to real-world conditions. DQN outperformed Q-Learning by completing tasks faster while maintaining zero pain risk and safe ergonomic levels. The structured testing protocol confirmed the system's adaptability to diverse human anthropometries, underscoring the potential of RL-driven cobots to enable safer, more inclusive workplaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10102v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitor Martins (Center for MicroElectroMechanical Systems), Sara M. Cerqueira (Center for MicroElectroMechanical Systems), Mercedes Balcells (IMES, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, USA, GEVAB, IQS School of Engineering, Barcelona, Spain), Elazer R Edelman (IMES, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, USA, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School Boston, MA, USA), Cristina P. Santos (Center for MicroElectroMechanical Systems, LABBELS-Associate Laboratory, University of Minho, Guimar\~aes, Portugal)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STLCCP: Efficient Convex Optimization-based Framework for Signal Temporal Logic Specifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09441v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Signal temporal logic (STL) is a powerful formalism for specifying various temporal properties in dynamical systems. However, existing methods, such as mixed-integer programming and nonlinear programming, often struggle to efficiently solve control problems with complex, long-horizon STL specifications. This study introduces \textit{STLCCP}, a novel convex optimization-based framework that leverages key structural properties of STL: monotonicity of the robustness function, its hierarchical tree structure, and correspondence between convexity/concavity in optimizations and conjunctiveness/disjunctiveness in specifications. The framework begins with a structure-aware decomposition of STL formulas, transforming the problem into an equivalent difference of convex (DC) programs. This is then solved sequentially as a convex quadratic program using an improved version of the convex-concave procedure (CCP). To further enhance efficiency, we develop a smooth approximation of the robustness function using a function termed the \textit{mellowmin} function, specifically tailored to the proposed framework. Numerical experiments on motion planning benchmarks demonstrate that \textit{STLCCP} can efficiently handle complex scenarios over long horizons, outperforming existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09441v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAC.2025.3555949</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yoshinari Takayama, Kazumune Hashimoto, Toshiyuki Ohtsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hybrid Algorithm for Iterative Adaptation of Feedforward Controllers: an Application on Electromechanical Switches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00036v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electromechanical switching devices such as relays, solenoid valves, and contactors offer several technical and economic advantages that make them widely used in industry. However, uncontrolled operations result in undesirable impact-related phenomena at the end of the stroke. As a solution, different soft-landing controls have been proposed. Among them, feedforward control with iterative techniques that adapt its parameters is a solution when real-time feedback is not available. However, these techniques typically require a large number of operations to converge or are computationally intensive, which limits a real implementation. In this paper, we present a new algorithm for the iterative adaptation that is able to eventually adapt the search coordinate system and to reduce the search dimensional size in order to accelerate convergence. Moreover, it automatically toggles between a derivative-free and a gradient-based method to balance exploration and exploitation. To demonstrate the high potential of the proposal, each novel part of the algorithm is compared with a state-of-the-art approach via simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00036v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eloy Serrano-Seco (Universidad de Zaragoza), Eduardo Moya-Lasheras (Universidad de Zaragoza), Edgar Ramirez-Laboreo (Universidad de Zaragoza)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEAD: Towards Learning-Based Equity-Aware Decarbonization in Ridesharing Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10201v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ridesharing platforms such as Uber, Lyft, and DiDi have grown in popularity due to their on-demand availability, ease of use, and commute cost reductions, among other benefits. However, not all ridesharing promises have panned out. Recent studies demonstrate that the expected drop in traffic congestion and reduction in greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions have not materialized. This is primarily due to the substantial distances traveled by the ridesharing vehicles without passengers between rides, known as deadhead miles. Recent work has focused on reducing the impact of deadhead miles while considering additional metrics such as rider waiting time, GHG emissions from deadhead miles, or driver earnings. However, most prior studies consider these environmental and equity-based metrics individually despite them being interrelated. In this paper, we propose a Learning-based Equity-Aware Decarabonization approach, LEAD, for ridesharing platforms. LEAD targets minimizing emissions while ensuring that the driver's utility, defined as the difference between the trip distance and the deadhead miles, is fairly distributed. LEAD uses reinforcement learning to match riders with drivers based on the expected future utility of drivers and the expected carbon emissions of the platform without increasing the rider waiting times. Extensive experiments based on a real-world ridesharing dataset show that LEAD improves the defined notion of fairness by 150% when compared to emission-aware ride-assignment and reduces emissions by 14.6% while ensuring fairness within 28--52% of the fairness-focused baseline. It also reduces the rider wait time, by at least 32.1%, compared to a fairness-focused baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10201v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahsa Sahebdel, Ali Zeynali, Noman Bashir, Prashant Shenoy, Mohammad Hajiesmaili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Reinforcement Learning and Model Predictive Control with Applications to Microgrids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11267v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work proposes an approach that integrates reinforcement learning and model predictive control (MPC) to solve finite-horizon optimal control problems in mixed-logical dynamical systems efficiently. Optimization-based control of such systems with discrete and continuous decision variables entails the online solution of mixed-integer linear programs, which suffer from the curse of dimensionality. Our approach aims to mitigate this issue by decoupling the decision on the discrete variables from the decision on the continuous variables. In the proposed approach, reinforcement learning determines the discrete decision variables and simplifies the online optimization problem of the MPC controller from a mixed-integer linear program to a linear program, significantly reducing the computational time. A fundamental contribution of this work is the definition of the decoupled Q-function, which plays a crucial role in making the learning problem tractable in a combinatorial action space. We motivate the use of recurrent neural networks to approximate the decoupled Q-function and show how they can be employed in a reinforcement learning setting. Simulation experiments on a microgrid system using real-world data demonstrate that the proposed method substantially reduces the online computation time of MPC while maintaining high feasibility and low suboptimality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11267v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caio Fabio Oliveira da Silva, Azita Dabiri, Bart De Schutter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculation of time-optimal motion primitives for systems exhibiting oscillatory internal dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19148v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An algorithm for planning near time-optimal trajectories for systems with an oscillatory internal dynamics has been developed in previous work. It is based on assembling a complete trajectory from motion primitives called jerk segments, which are the time-optimal solution to an optimization problem. To achieve the shortest overall transition time, it is advantageous to recompute these segments for different acceleration levels within the motion planning procedure. This publication presents a numerical calculation method enabling fast and reliable calculation. This is achieved by explicitly evaluating the optimality conditions that arise for the problem, and further by reducing the evaluation of these conditions to a line-search problem on a bounded interval. This reduction guarantees, that a valid solution if found after a fixed number of computational steps, making the calculation time constant and predictable. Furthermore, the algorithm does not rely on optimisation algorithms, which allowed its implementation on a laboratory system for measurements with the purpose of validating the approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19148v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Auer, Frank Woittennek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Filtering against Spatio-Temporal False Data Attacks under Asynchronous Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19765v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses the secure state estimation problem for continuous linear time-invariant systems with non-periodic and asynchronous sampled measurements, where the sensors need to transmit not only measurements but also sampling time-stamps to the fusion center. This measurement and communication setup is well-suited for operating large-scale control systems and, at the same time, introduces new vulnerabilities that can be exploited by adversaries through (i) manipulation of measurements, (ii) manipulation of time-stamps, (iii) elimination of measurements, (iv) generation of completely new false measurements, or a combination of these attacks. To mitigate these attacks, we propose a decentralized estimation algorithm in which each sensor maintains its local state estimate asynchronously based on its measurements. The local states are synchronized through time prediction and fused after time-stamp alignment. In the absence of attacks, state estimates are proven to recover the optimal Kalman estimates by solving a weighted least square problem. In the presence of attacks, solving this weighted least square problem with the aid of $\ell_1$ regularization provides secure state estimates with uniformly bounded error under an observability redundancy assumption. The effectiveness of the proposed algorithm is demonstrated using a benchmark example of the IEEE 14-bus system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19765v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zishuo Li, Anh Tung Nguyen, Andr\'e M. H. Teixeira, Yilin Mo, Karl H. Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Prescribed-Time Observer for Nonlinear Systems in Block-Triangular Form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02669v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a distributed prescribed-time observer for nonlinear systems representable in a block-triangular observable canonical form. Using a weighted average of neighbor estimates exchanged over a strongly connected digraph, each observer estimates the system state despite the limited observability of local sensor measurements. The proposed design guarantees that distributed state estimation errors converge to zero at a user-specified convergence time, irrespective of observers' initial conditions. To achieve this prescribed-time convergence, distributed observers implement time-varying local output injection gains that monotonically increase and approach infinity at the prescribed time. The theoretical convergence is rigorously proven and validated through numerical simulations, where some implementation issues due to increasing gains have also been clarified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02669v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent de Heij, M. Umar B. Niazi, Karl H. Johansson, Saeed Ahmed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning-based hybrid dynamic modeling and economic predictive control of carbon capture process for ship decarbonization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05833v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implementing carbon capture technology on-board ships holds promise as a solution to facilitate the reduction of carbon intensity in international shipping, as mandated by the International Maritime Organization. In this work, we address the energy-efficient operation of shipboard carbon capture processes by proposing a hybrid modeling-based economic predictive control scheme. Specifically, we consider a comprehensive shipboard carbon capture process that encompasses the ship engine system and the shipboard post-combustion carbon capture plant. To accurately and robustly characterize the dynamic behaviors of this shipboard plant, we develop a hybrid dynamic process model that integrates available imperfect physical knowledge with neural networks trained using process operation data. An economic model predictive control approach is proposed based on the hybrid model to ensure carbon capture efficiency while minimizing energy consumption required for the carbon capture process operation. The cross-entropy method is employed to efficiently solve the complex non-convex optimization problem associated with the proposed hybrid model-based economic model predictive control method. Extensive simulations, analyses, and comparisons are conducted to verify the effectiveness and illustrate the superiority of the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05833v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuewen Zhang, Kuniadi Wandy Huang, Dat-Nguyen Vo, Minghao Han, Benjamin Decardi-Nelson, Xunyuan Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Spectrahedral Shadows for State Estimation and Reachability Analysis: Set Operations, Validations and Order Reductions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18941v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Set representations are the foundation of various set-based approaches in state estimation, reachability analysis and fault diagnosis. In this paper, we investigate spectrahedral shadows, a class of nonlinear geometric objects previously studied in semidefinite programming and real algebraic geometry. We demonstrate spectrahedral shadows generalize traditional and emerging set representations like ellipsoids, zonotopes, constrained zonotopes and ellipsotopes. Analytical forms of set operations are provided including linear map, linear inverse map, Minkowski sum, intersection, Cartesian product, Minkowski-Firey Lp sum, convex hull, conic hull and polytopic map, all of which are implemented without approximation in polynomial time. In addition, we develop set validation and order reduction techniques for spectrahedral shadows, thereby establishing spectrahedral shadows as a set representation applicable to a range of set-based tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18941v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengrui Wang, Haohao Qiu, Sibo Yao, James Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Velocity-free task-space regulator for robot manipulators with external disturbances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02634v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of task-space robust regulation of robot manipulators subject to external disturbances. A velocity-free control law is proposed by combining the internal model principle and the passivity-based output-feedback control approach. The resulting controller not only ensures asymptotic convergence of the regulation error but also rejects unwanted external sinusoidal disturbances. The potential of the proposed method lies in its simplicity, intuitiveness, and straightforward gain selection criteria for the synthesis of multi-joint robot manipulator control systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02634v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiwen Wu, Bayu Jayawardhana, Dabo Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Control under Voltage Drop for Rotor Drones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09017v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This letter proposes an anti-disturbance control scheme for rotor drones to counteract voltage drop (VD) disturbance caused by voltage drop of the battery, which is a common case for long-time flight or aggressive maneuvers. Firstly, the refined dynamics of rotor drones considering VD disturbance are presented. Based on the dynamics, a voltage drop observer (VDO) is developed to accurately estimate the VD disturbance by decoupling the disturbance and state information of the drone, reducing the conservativeness of conventional disturbance observers. Subsequently, the control scheme integrates the VDO within the translational loop and a fixed-time sliding mode observer (SMO) within the rotational loop, enabling it to address force and torque disturbances caused by voltage drop of the battery. Sufficient real flight experiments are conducted to demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed control scheme under VD disturbance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09017v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhang Liu, Jindou Jia, Zihan Yang, Kexin Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and Controllability of Revenue Systems via the Bode Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23663v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In online revenue systems, e.g. an advertising system, budget pacing plays a critical role in ensuring that the spend aligns with desired financial objectives. Pacing systems dynamically control the velocity of spending to balance auction intensity, traffic fluctuations, and other stochastic variables. Current industry practices rely heavily on trial-and-error approaches, often leading to inefficiencies and instability. This paper introduces a principled methodology rooted in Classical Control Theory to address these challenges. By modeling the pacing system as a linear time-invariant (LTI) proxy and leveraging compensator design techniques using Bode methodology, we derive a robust controller to minimize pacing errors and enhance stability. The proposed methodology is validated through simulation and tested by our in-house auction system, demonstrating superior performance in achieving precise budget allocation while maintaining resilience to traffic and auction dynamics. Our findings bridge the gap between traditional control theory and modern advertising systems in modeling, simulation, and validation, offering a scalable and systematic approach to budget pacing optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23663v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichuan Niu, Jianhui Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Safety Verification using Barrier Certificates and Matrix Zonotopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01007v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ensuring safety in cyber-physical systems (CPSs) is a critical challenge, especially when system models are difficult to obtain or cannot be fully trusted due to uncertainty, modeling errors, or environmental disturbances. Traditional model-based approaches rely on precise system dynamics, which may not be available in real-world scenarios. To address this, we propose a data-driven safety verification framework that leverages matrix zonotopes and barrier certificates to verify system safety directly from noisy data. Instead of trusting a single unreliable model, we construct a set of models that capture all possible system dynamics that align with the observed data, ensuring that the true system model is always contained within this set. This model set is compactly represented using matrix zonotopes, enabling efficient computation and propagation of uncertainty. By integrating this representation into a barrier certificate framework, we establish rigorous safety guarantees without requiring an explicit system model. Numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in verifying safety for dynamical systems with unknown models, showcasing its potential for real-world CPS applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01007v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Adib Oumer, Amr Alanwar, Majid Zamani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InstructMPC: A Human-LLM-in-the-Loop Framework for Context-Aware Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05946v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Model Predictive Control (MPC) is a powerful control strategy widely utilized in domains like energy management, building control, and autonomous systems. However, its effectiveness in real-world settings is challenged by the need to incorporate context-specific predictions and expert instructions, which traditional MPC often neglects. We propose InstructMPC, a novel framework that addresses this gap by integrating real-time human instructions through a Large Language Model (LLM) to produce context-aware predictions for MPC. Our method employs a Language-to-Distribution (L2D) module to translate contextual information into predictive disturbance trajectories, which are then incorporated into the MPC optimization. Unlike existing context-aware and language-based MPC models, InstructMPC enables dynamic human-LLM interaction and fine-tunes the L2D module in a closed loop with theoretical performance guarantees, achieving a regret bound of $O(\sqrt{T\log T})$ for linear dynamics when optimized via advanced fine-tuning methods such as Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) using a tailored loss function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05946v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruixiang Wu, Jiahao Ai, Tongxin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Neural Koopman Operator-based Economic Model Predictive Control of Shipboard Carbon Capture System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06818v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Shipboard carbon capture is a promising solution to help reduce carbon emissions in international shipping. In this work, we propose a data-driven dynamic modeling and economic predictive control approach within the Koopman framework. This integrated modeling and control approach is used to achieve safe and energy-efficient process operation of shipboard post-combustion carbon capture plants. Specifically, we propose a deep neural Koopman operator modeling approach, based on which a Koopman model with time-varying model parameters is established. This Koopman model predicts the overall economic operational cost and key system outputs, based on accessible partial state measurements. By leveraging this learned model, a constrained economic predictive control scheme is developed. Despite time-varying parameters involved in the formulated model, the formulated optimization problem associated with the economic predictive control design is convex, and it can be solved efficiently during online control implementations. Extensive tests are conducted on a high-fidelity simulation environment for shipboard post-combustion carbon capture processes. Four ship operational conditions are taken into account. The results show that the proposed method significantly improves the overall economic operational performance and carbon capture rate. Additionally, the proposed method guarantees safe operation by ensuring that hard constraints on the system outputs are satisfied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06818v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghao Han, Xunyuan Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secondary Safety Control for Systems with Sector Bounded Nonlinearities [Extended Version]</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08535v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of safety verification and safety-aware controller synthesis for systems with sector bounded nonlinearities. We aim to keep the states of the system within a given safe set under potential actuator and sensor attacks. Specifically, we adopt the setup that a controller has already been designed to stabilize the plant. Using invariant sets and barrier certificate theory, we first give sufficient conditions to verify the safety of the closed-loop system under attacks. Furthermore, by using a subset of sensors that are assumed to be free of attacks, we provide a synthesis method for a secondary controller that enhances the safety of the system. The sufficient conditions to verify safety are derived using Lyapunov-based tools and the S-procedure. Using the projection lemma, the conditions are then formulated as linear matrix inequality (LMI) problems which can be solved efficiently. Lastly, our theoretical results are illustrated through numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08535v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yankai Lin, Michelle S. Chong, Carlos Murguia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Policy Gradient Framework for Stochastic Optimal Control Problems with Global Convergence Guarantee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.05816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.05816v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider policy gradient methods for stochastic optimal control problem in continuous time. In particular, we analyze the gradient flow for the control, viewed as a continuous time limit of the policy gradient method. We prove the global convergence of the gradient flow and establish a convergence rate under some regularity assumptions. The main novelty in the analysis is the notion of local optimal control function, which is introduced to characterize the local optimality of the iterate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.05816v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mo Zhou, Jianfeng Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment-based Density Elicitation with Applications in Probabilistic Loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.09094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.09094v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose the K-series estimation approach for the recovery of unknown univariate and multivariate distributions given knowledge of a finite number of their moments. Our method is directly applicable to the probabilistic analysis of systems that can be represented as probabilistic loops; i.e., algorithms that express and implement non-deterministic processes ranging from robotics to macroeconomics and biology to software and cyber-physical systems. K-series statically approximates the joint and marginal distributions of a vector of continuous random variables updated in a probabilistic non-nested loop with nonlinear assignments given a finite number of moments of the unknown density. Moreover, K-series automatically derives the distribution of the systems' random variables symbolically as a function of the loop iteration. K-series density estimates are accurate, easy and fast to compute. We demonstrate the feasibility and performance of our approach on multiple benchmark examples from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.09094v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3728648</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Kofnov, Ezio Bartocci, Efstathia Bura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning-based Observer for Coupled Disturbance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13229v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Achieving high-precision control for robotic systems is hindered by the low-fidelity dynamical model and external disturbances. Especially, the intricate coupling between internal uncertainties and external disturbances further exacerbates this challenge. This study introduces an effective and convergent algorithm enabling accurate estimation of the coupled disturbance via combining control and learning philosophies. Concretely, by resorting to Chebyshev series expansion, the coupled disturbance is firstly decomposed into an unknown parameter matrix and two known structures dependent on system state and external disturbance respectively. A regularized least squares algorithm is subsequently formalized to learn the parameter matrix using historical time-series data. Finally, a polynomial disturbance observer is specifically devised to achieve a high-precision estimation of the coupled disturbance by utilizing the learned portion. The proposed algorithm is evaluated through extensive simulations and real flight tests. We believe this work can offer a new pathway to integrate learning approaches into control frameworks for addressing longstanding challenges in robotic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13229v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jindou Jia, Meng Wang, Zihan Yang, Bin Yang, Yuhang Liu, Kexin Guo, Xiang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online-Score-Aided Federated Learning: Taming the Resource Constraints in Wireless Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05886v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While federated learning (FL) is a widely popular distributed machine learning (ML) strategy that protects data privacy, time-varying wireless network parameters and heterogeneous configurations of the wireless devices pose significant challenges. Although the limited radio and computational resources of the network and the clients, respectively, are widely acknowledged, two critical yet often ignored aspects are (a) wireless devices can only dedicate a small chunk of their limited storage for the FL task and (b) new training samples may arrive in an online manner in many practical wireless applications. Therefore, we propose a new FL algorithm called online-score-aided federated learning (OSAFL), specifically designed to learn tasks relevant to wireless applications under these practical considerations. Since clients' local training steps differ under resource constraints, which may lead to client drift under statistically heterogeneous data distributions, we leverage normalized gradient similarities and exploit weighting clients' updates based on optimized scores that facilitate the convergence rate of the proposed OSAFL algorithm without incurring any communication overheads to the clients or requiring any statistical data information from them. Our extensive simulation results on two different datasets with four popular ML models validate the effectiveness of OSAFL compared to five modified state-of-the-art FL baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05886v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md-Ferdous Pervej, Minseok Choi, Andreas F. Molisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consensus in Multiagent Systems under communication failure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10486v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider multi-agent systems with cooperative interactions and study the convergence to consensus in the case of time-dependent connections, with possible communication failure.
  We prove a new condition ensuring consensus: we define a graph in which directed arrows correspond to connection functions that converge (in the weak sense) to some function with a positive integral on all intervals of the form $[t,+\infty)$. If the graph has a node reachable from all other indices, i.e.~``globally reachable'', then the system converges to consensus. We show that this requirement generalizes some known sufficient conditions for convergence, such as Moreau's or the Persistent Excitation one. We also give a second new condition, transversal to the known ones: total connectedness of the undirected graph formed by the non-vanishing of limiting functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10486v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Bentaibi, Laura Caravenna, Jean-Paul A. Gauthier, Francesco Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards safe Bayesian optimization with Wiener kernel regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02253v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian Optimization (BO) is a data-driven strategy for minimizing/maximizing black-box functions based on probabilistic surrogate models. In the presence of safety constraints, the performance of BO crucially relies on tight probabilistic error bounds related to the uncertainty surrounding the surrogate model. For the case of Gaussian Process surrogates and Gaussian measurement noise, we present a novel error bound based on the recently proposed Wiener kernel regression. We prove that under rather mild assumptions, the proposed error bound is tighter than bounds previously documented in the literature, leading to enlarged safety regions. We draw upon a numerical example to demonstrate the efficacy of the proposed error bound in safe BO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02253v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksii Molodchyk, Johannes Teutsch, Timm Faulwasser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Feedback Control for Global Navigation with Locally Optimal Obstacle Avoidance in n-Dimensional Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20320v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a hybrid feedback control framework for autonomous robot navigation in n-dimensional Euclidean spaces cluttered with spherical obstacles. The proposed approach ensures safe navigation and global asymptotic stability (GAS) of the target location by dynamically switching between two operational modes: motion-to-destination and locally optimal obstacle-avoidance. It produces continuous velocity inputs, ensures collision-free trajectories and generates locally optimal obstacle avoidance maneuvers. Unlike existing methods, the proposed framework is compatible with range sensors, enabling navigation in both a priori known and unknown environments. Extensive simulations in 2D and 3D settings, complemented by experimental validation on a TurtleBot 4 platform, confirm the efficacy and robustness of the approach. Our results demonstrate shorter paths and smoother trajectories compared to state-of-the-art methods, while maintaining computational efficiency and real-world feasibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20320v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishak Cheniouni, Soulaimane Berkane, Abdelhamid Tayebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRAMC: General-purpose and reconfigurable analog matrix computing architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01586v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In-memory analog matrix computing (AMC) with resistive random-access memory (RRAM) represents a highly promising solution that solves matrix problems in one step. However, the existing AMC circuits each have a specific connection topology to implement a single computing function, lack of the universality as a matrix processor. In this work, we design a reconfigurable AMC macro for general-purpose matrix computations, which is achieved by configuring proper connections between memory array and amplifier circuits. Based on this macro, we develop a hybrid system that incorporates an on-chip write-verify scheme and digital functional modules, to deliver a general-purpose AMC solver for various applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01586v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lunshuai Pan, Shiqing Wang, Pushen Zuo, Zhong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging Impulse Control of Piecewise Deterministic Markov Processes and Markov Decision Processes: Frameworks, Extensions, and Open Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04120v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Control theory plays a pivotal role in understanding and optimizing the behavior of complex dynamical systems across various scientific and engineering disciplines. Two key frameworks that have emerged for modeling and solving control problems in stochastic systems are piecewise deterministic Markov processes (PDMPs) and Markov decision processes (MDPs). Each framework has its unique strengths, and their intersection offers promising opportunities for tackling a broad class of problems, particularly in the context of impulse controls and decision-making in complex systems.
  The relationship between PDMPs and MDPs is a natural subject of exploration, as embedding impulse control problems for PDMPs into the MDP framework could open new avenues for their analysis and resolution. Specifically, this integration would allow leveraging the computational and theoretical tools developed for MDPs to address the challenges inherent in PDMPs. On the other hand, PDMPs can offer a versatile and simple paradigm to model continuous time problems that are often described as discrete-time MDPs parametrized by complex transition kernels. This transformation has the potential to bridge the gap between the two frameworks, enabling solutions to previously intractable problems and expanding the scope of both fields. This paper presents a comprehensive review of two research domains, illustrated through a recurring medical example. The example is revisited and progressively formalized within the framework of thevarious concepts and objects introduced</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04120v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Cleynen, Beno\^ite de Saporta, Orlane Rossini, R\'egis Sabbadin, Am\'elie Vernay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Developing Socially Compliant Automated Vehicles: Advances, Expert Insights, and A Conceptual Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06089v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Automated Vehicles (AVs) hold promise for revolutionizing transportation by improving road safety, traffic efficiency, and overall mobility. Despite the steady advancement in high-level AVs in recent years, the transition to full automation entails a period of mixed traffic, where AVs of varying automation levels coexist with human-driven vehicles (HDVs). Making AVs socially compliant and understood by human drivers is expected to improve the safety and efficiency of mixed traffic. Thus, ensuring AVs' compatibility with HDVs and social acceptance is crucial for their successful and seamless integration into mixed traffic. However, research in this critical area of developing Socially Compliant AVs (SCAVs) remains sparse. This study carries out the first comprehensive scoping review to assess the current state of the art in developing SCAVs, identifying key concepts, methodological approaches, and research gaps. An informal expert interview was also conducted to discuss the literature review results and identify critical research gaps and expectations towards SCAVs. Based on the scoping review and expert interview input, a conceptual framework is proposed for the development of SCAVs. The conceptual framework is evaluated using an online survey targeting researchers, technicians, policymakers, and other relevant professionals worldwide. The survey results provide valuable validation and insights, affirming the significance of the proposed conceptual framework in tackling the challenges of integrating AVs into mixed-traffic environments. Additionally, future research perspectives and suggestions are discussed, contributing to the research and development agenda of SCAVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06089v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongqi Dong, Bart van Arem, Haneen Farah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing wheel loader performance -- an end-to-end approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06583v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Wheel loaders in mines and construction sites repeatedly load soil from a pile to load receivers. This task presents a challenging optimization problem since each loading's performance depends on the pile state, which depends on previous loadings. We investigate an end-to-end optimization approach considering future loading outcomes and transportation costs between the pile and load receivers. To predict the evolution of the pile state and the loading performance, we use world models that leverage deep neural networks trained on numerous simulated loading cycles. A look-ahead tree search optimizes the sequence of loading actions by evaluating the performance of thousands of action candidates, which expand into subsequent action candidates under the predicted pile states recursively. Test results demonstrate that, over a horizon of 15 sequential loadings, the look-ahead tree search is 6% more efficient than a greedy strategy, which always selects the action that maximizes the current single loading performance, and 14% more efficient than using a fixed loading controller optimized for the nominal case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06583v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koji Aoshima, Eddie Wadbro, Martin Servin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Convex Optimization and Integral Quadratic Constraints: A new approach to regret analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23600v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel approach for analyzing dynamic regret of first-order constrained online convex optimization algorithms for strongly convex and Lipschitz-smooth objectives. Crucially, we provide a general analysis that is applicable to a wide range of first-order algorithms that can be expressed as an interconnection of a linear dynamical system in feedback with a first-order oracle. By leveraging Integral Quadratic Constraints (IQCs), we derive a semi-definite program which, when feasible, provides a regret guarantee for the online algorithm. For this, the concept of variational IQCs is introduced as the generalization of IQCs to time-varying monotone operators. Our bounds capture the temporal rate of change of the problem in the form of the path length of the time-varying minimizer and the objective function variation. In contrast to standard results in OCO, our results do not require nerither the assumption of gradient boundedness, nor that of a bounded feasible set. Numerical analyses showcase the ability of the approach to capture the dependence of the regret on the function class condition number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23600v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Jakob, Andrea Iannelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Reachable Set Estimation for Saturated Systems with Unbounded Additive Disturbances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03443v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an analytical approach for the synthesis of ellipsoidal probabilistic reachable sets of saturated systems subject to unbounded additive noise. Using convex optimization methods, we compute a contraction factor of the saturated error dynamics that allows us to tightly bound its evolution and therefore construct accurate reachable sets. The proposed approach is applicable to independent, zero mean disturbances with a known covariance. A numerical example illustrates the applicability and effectiveness of the proposed design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03443v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Karam, Matteo Tacchi-B\'enard, Mirko Fiacchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Simulation of Singularly Perturbed Systems Using a Stabilized Multirate Explicit Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06371v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Singularly perturbed systems (SPSs) are prevalent in engineering applications, where numerically solving their initial value problems (IVPs) is challenging due to stiffness arising from multiple time scales. Classical explicit methods require impractically small time steps for stability, while implicit methods developed for SPSs are computationally intensive and less efficient for strongly nonlinear systems. This paper introduces a Stabilized Multirate Explicit Scheme (SMES) that stabilizes classical explicit methods without the need for small time steps or implicit formulations. By employing a multirate approach with variable time steps, SMES allows the fast dynamics to rapidly converge to their equilibrium manifold while slow dynamics evolve with larger steps. Analysis shows that SMES achieves numerical stability with significantly reduced computational effort and controlled error. Its effectiveness is illustrated with a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06371v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yibo Shi, Cristian R. Rojas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
