<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.EC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.EC</link>
    <description>q-fin.EC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.EC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 01:49:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging Climate Awareness and Sustainable Entrepreneurship: A Conceptual Framework Based on the Theory of Planned Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many studies have examined the connection between the intention to start a business and environmental values. However, there still needs to be more knowledge in the extant literature about how climate change campaigns influence sustainable entrepreneurial intention. This study uses the Theory of Planned Behavior (TPB) to develop a theoretical framework to explain how climate change campaigns affect the intention to start a sustainable business. This interdisciplinary conceptual research model bridges the gap between climate awareness, sustainable values, and entrepreneurial intentions, offering a robust framework for understanding and fostering sustainable entrepreneurial behaviors. Our study lays the groundwork for future empirical studies and real-world interventions to advance sustainability through entrepreneurship.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16838v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.56472/25835238/IRJEMS-V3I7P129</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. Research J. of Eco. and Mgt. Studies, Vol. 3, No. 7, pp. 266-275, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Rofiqul Islam, Abdullah Al Mehdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of National Cultures on Managerial Decisions of Engaging in Core Earnings Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the impact of Hofstede's cultural dimensions on abnormal core earnings management in multiple national cultural contexts. We employ an Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) regression model with abnormal core earnings as the dependent variable. The independent variables analyzed include Hofstede's dimensions: Power Distance Index (PDI), Individualism (IDV), Masculinity (MAS), and Uncertainty Avoidance Index (UAI). Our findings reveal that individualism is positively associated with abnormal core earnings, suggesting that cultures characterized by high individualism may encourage practices that inflate earnings due to the prominence of personal achievement and rewards. In contrast, masculinity negatively correlates with abnormal core earnings, indicating that the risk-taking attributes associated with masculine cultures may deter earnings management. Interestingly, uncertainty avoidance is positively linked to abnormal core earnings, supporting the notion that managers tend to engage more in earnings management to minimize fluctuations in financial reports in cultures with high uncertainty avoidance. The relationship between power distance and abnormal core earnings is found to be non-significant, indicating no substantial effect in this context. These findings contribute to the literature on cultural influences in financial reporting, providing valuable insights for policymakers and multinational firms concerning the cultural contexts within which financial decisions and reporting occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16854v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7176/EJBM/16-4-07</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Journal of Business and Management, 16(4):72-83 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Rofiqul Islam, Abdullah Al Mehdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation in discrete choice models evaluation: SDCM, a simulation tool for performance evaluation of DCMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17014v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Discrete choice models (DCMs) have been widely utilized in various scientific fields, especially economics, for many years. These models consider a stochastic environment influencing each decision maker's choices. Extensive research has shown that the agents' socioeconomic characteristics, the chosen options' properties, and the conditions characterizing the decision-making environment all impact these models. However, the complex interactions between these factors, confidentiality concerns, time constraints, and costs, have made real experimentation impractical and undesirable. To address this, simulations have gained significant popularity among academics, allowing the study of these models in a controlled setting using simulated data. This paper presents multidisciplinary research to bridge the gap between DCMs, experimental design, and simulation. By reviewing related literature, the authors explore these interconnected areas. We then introduce a simulation method integrated with experimental design to generate synthetic data based on behavioral models of agents. A utility function is used to describe the developed simulation tool. The paper investigates the discrepancy between simulated data and real-world data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17014v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirreza Talebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial intelligence and financial crises</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid adoption of artificial intelligence (AI) is transforming the financial industry. AI will either increase systemic financial risk or act to stabilise the system, depending on endogenous responses, strategic complementarities, the severity of events it faces and the objectives it is given. AI's ability to master complexity and respond rapidly to shocks means future crises will likely be more intense than those we have seen so far.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17048v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jon Danielsson, Andreas Uthemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Austerity Measures on Infant Mortality: Evidence from Greece</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines the effect of fiscal austerity measures on infant mortality in Greece. Austerity measures were initiated by the tripartite committee and implemented between 2010 and 2017 to counteract deep fiscal deficit and large public debt. By comparing Greece with a plausible donor pool of OECD and Mediterranean member states in the period 1991-2020, we estimate a series of missing counterfactual scenarios to evaluate the infant mortality effects of large-scale reduction in spending on health care. A series of hybrid synthetic control and difference-in-differences estimates indicate a unique and pervasive increase in infant mortality after the implementation of austerity measures. Compared to a plausible OECD and Mediterranean counterfactual scenario, pro-cyclical austerity measures are associated with derailed and permanently increased infant mortality up to the present day. Our estimates suggest that compared to a plausible counterfactual scenario, the cumulative infant mortality cost of austerity policies exceeds 10,000 infant deaths or slightly less than 850 deaths for each year of the austerity policies. Notably, mortality increases are concentrated among boys. The estimated impacts survive a battery of rigorous robustness and placebo tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17084v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J. Kolesar, Rok Spruk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fintech and MSEs Innovation: an Empirical Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Employing a comprehensive survey of micro and small enterprises (MSEs) and the Digital Financial Inclusion Index in China, this study investigates the influence of fintech on MSE innovation empirically. Our findings indicate that fintech advancement substantially enhances the likelihood of MSEs engaging in innovative endeavors and boosts both the investment and outcomes of their innovation processes. The underlying mechanisms are attributed to fintech's role in fostering long-term strategic incentives and investment in human capital. This includes the use of promotions and stock options as rewards, rather than traditional perks like gifts or trips, the attraction of a greater number of university graduates, and the increase in both training expenses and the remuneration of technical staff. Our heterogeneity analysis reveals that fintech exerts a more pronounced effect on MSEs situated in economically developed areas, those that are five years old or younger, and businesses with limited assets and workforce. Additionally, we uncover that fintech stimulates the innovation of MSEs' independent research and development (R\&amp;D) efforts. This paper contributes to the understanding of the nuanced ways in which fintech impacts MSE innovation and offers policy insights aimed at unleashing the full potential of MSEs' innovative capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17293v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyu Chen, Qing Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>School choice with independent versus consolidated districts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.13209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.13209v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies the welfare effects of school district consolidation. Using incomplete rank-ordered lists (ROLs) submitted for admission to the Hungarian secondary school system, we estimate complete ROLs assuming that parents do not use dominated strategies and that the matching outcome is stable. These estimates aid in constructing a counterfactual district-based assignment and discerning the factors driving parents' preferences over schools. We find that district consolidation leads to large welfare gains in Budapest, equivalent to students attending a school five kilometres closer to their residences. These gains offset the additional travel distances incurred in the consolidated assignment. 73\% of matched students benefit from district consolidation, while fewer than 3\% are assigned to a less preferred school. Students from smaller and less under-demanded districts benefit relatively more, as well as those with high academic ability. Using reported preferences instead of estimated ones also yields large gains from district consolidation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.13209v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.geb.2024.07.003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Volume 147, September 2024, Pages 170-205</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thilo Klein, Robert Aue, Josue Ortega</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
