<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.EC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.EC</link>
    <description>q-fin.EC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.EC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 04:15:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the techno-economic benefits of LEMs for different grid topologies and prosumer shares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The shift towards decentralized and renewable energy sources has introduced significant challenges to traditional power systems, necessitating innovative market designs. Local energy markets present a viable solution for integrating distributed energy resources such as photovoltaic systems, electric vehicles, and heat pumps within various grid topologies. This study investigates the techno-economic benefits of local energy markets compared to conventional market designs, focusing on their impact on average energy prices and operational peak power, using a self-developed agent-based energy system simulation tool. Through comprehensive simulations across the countryside, rural, suburban, and urban grid topologies with varying penetration levels of the distributed energy resources, totaling 400 simulation setups, we demonstrate that local energy markets can enhance economic efficiency and grid stability with 99 % of the scenarios boasting lower average energy prices and 80 % lower operational peak power levels. Our findings suggest that local energy markets can play a role in the future energy system, especially in areas with high shares of PV and HP, provided that additional infrastructure, management costs, and bureaucratic complexity are kept to a minimum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13330v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Doepfert, Soner Candas, Hermann Kraus, Peter Tzscheutschler, Thomas Hamacher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How do we measure trade elasticity for services?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08594v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is about our attempt of identifying trade elasticities through the variations in the exchange rate, for possible applications to the case of services whose physical transactions are veiled in the trade statistics. The regression analysis to estimate the elasticity entails a situation where the explanatory variable is leaked into the error term through the latent supply equation, causing an endogeneity problem for which an instrumental variable cannot be found. Our identification strategy is to utilize the normalizing condition, which enables the supply parameter to be identified, along with the reduced-form equation of the system of demand and supply equations. We evaluate the performances of the method proposed by applying to several different tangible goods, whose benchmark trade elasticities are estimable by utilizing the information on their physical transactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08594v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Empirical Economics 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Nakano, Kazuhiko Nishimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the Three-Child Policy and Delayed Retirement on the Transfer of Surplus Rural Labor under Xi Jinping's New Population Vision: A Re-examination of China's Lewis Turning Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14914v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chinese-style modernization involves the modernization of a large population, requiring top-level design in terms of scale and structure. The population perspective in Xi Jinping's Thought on Socialism with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era serves as the fundamental guide for population policies. The three-child policy and delayed retirement will affect the supply of labor in China and challenge the previous assessments of China's Lewis Turning Point. This study examines the rural surplus labor transfer from 2013 to 2022 based on urban and rural data. The results indicate that China's overall wage levels have continuously increased, the urban-rural income gap has narrowed, and the transfer of surplus rural labor has slowed. China has passed the first turning point and entered a transitional phase. Factors such as the level of agricultural mechanization, urbanization rate, and urban-rural income gap are more significant in influencing the transfer of surplus labor than the normal working-age population ratio. The delayed retirement policy has a more immediate impact on the supply and transfer of rural surplus labor than the three-child policy. Additionally, delayed retirement can offset the negative impact of the reduced relative surplus labor supply caused by the three-child policy, although the three-child policy could increase the future absolute surplus labor supply.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14914v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Dai, Guanqing Shi, Xiaoke Xie, Aitong Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
