<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.FL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.FL</link>
    <description>cs.FL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.FL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 02:39:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Agafonov and Schnorr-Stimm theorems for probabilistic automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a fixed alphabet $A$, an infinite sequence $X$ is said to be normal if every word $w$ over $A$ appears in $X$ with the same frequency as any other word of the same length. A classical result of Agafonov (1966) relates normality to finite automata as follows: a sequence $X$ is normal if and only if any subsequence of $X$ selected by a finite automaton is itself normal. Another theorem of Schnorr and Stimm (1972) gives an alternative characterization: a sequence $X$ is normal if and only if no gambler can win large amounts of money by betting on the sequence $X$ using a strategy that can be described by a finite automaton. Both of these theorems are established in the setting of deterministic finite automata. This raises the question as to whether they can be extended to the setting of probabilistic finite automata. In the case of the Agafonov theorem, this question was positively answered by L\'echine et al.\ (2024) in a restricted case of probabilistic automata with rational transition probabilities.
  In this paper, we settle the full conjecture by proving that both the Agafonov and the Schnorr-Stimm theorems hold true for arbitrary probabilistic automata. Specifically, we show that a sequence $X$ is normal if and only if any probabilistic automaton selects a normal subsequence of $X$ with probability $1$. We also show that a sequence $X$ is normal if and only if a probabilistic finite-state gambler fails to win on $X$ with probability $1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12307v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent Bienvenu, Hugo Gimbert, Subin Pulari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving Nondeterminism with Randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In automata theory, while determinisation provides a standard route to solving many common problems in automata theory, some weak forms of nondeterminism can be dealt with in some problems without costly determinisation. For example, the handling of specifications given by nondeterministic automata over infinite words for the problems of reactive synthesis or runtime verification requires resolving nondeterministic choices without knowing the future of the input word. We define and study classes of $\omega$-regular automata for which the nondeterminism can be resolved by a policy that uses a combination of memory and randomness on any input word, based solely on the prefix read so far.
  We examine two settings for providing the input word to an automaton. In the first setting, called adversarial resolvability, the input word is constructed letter-by-letter by an adversary, dependent on the resolver's previous decisions. In the second setting, called stochastic resolvability, the adversary pre-commits to an infinite word and reveals it letter-by-letter. In each setting, we require the existence of an almost-sure resolver, i.e., a policy that ensures that as long as the adversary provides a word in the language of the underlying nondeterministic automaton, the run constructed by the policy is accepting with probability 1.
  The class of automata that are adversarially resolvable is the well-studied class of history-deterministic automata. The case of stochastically resolvable automata, on the other hand, defines a novel class. Restricting the class of resolvers in both settings to stochastic policies without memory introduces two additional new classes of automata. We show that the new automaton classes offer interesting trade-offs between succinctness, expressivity, and computational complexity, providing a fine gradation between deterministic automata and nondeterministic automata.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12872v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas A. Henzinger, Aditya Prakash, K. S. Thejaswini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-way affine automata can verify every language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When used as verifiers in Arthur-Merlin systems, two-way quantum finite automata can verify membership in all languages with bounded error with double-exponential expected running time, which cannot be achieved by their classical counterparts. We obtain the same result for affine automata with single-exponential expected time. We show that every binary (and r-ary) language is verified by some two-way affine finite automata verifiers by presenting two protocols: A weak verification protocol uses a single affine register and the input is read once; and, a strong verification protocol uses two affine registers. These results reflects the remarkable verification capabilities of affine finite automata.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12879v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyu Chen, Abuzer Yakary{\i}lmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hallucinations are inevitable but statistically negligible</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hallucinations, a phenomenon where a language model (LM) generates nonfactual content, pose a significant challenge to the practical deployment of LMs. While many empirical methods have been proposed to mitigate hallucinations, a recent study established a computability-theoretic result showing that any LM will inevitably generate hallucinations on an infinite set of inputs, regardless of the quality and quantity of training datasets and the choice of the language model architecture and training and inference algorithms. Although the computability-theoretic result may seem pessimistic, its significance in practical viewpoints has remained unclear. In contrast, we present a positive theoretical result from a probabilistic perspective. Specifically, we prove that hallucinations can be made statistically negligible, provided that the quality and quantity of the training data are sufficient. Interestingly, our positive result coexists with the computability-theoretic result, implying that while hallucinations on an infinite set of inputs cannot be entirely eliminated, their probability can always be reduced by improving algorithms and training data. By evaluating the two seemingly contradictory results through the lens of information theory, we argue that our probability-theoretic positive result better reflects practical considerations than the computability-theoretic negative result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12187v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsushi Suzuki, Yulan He, Feng Tian, Zhongyuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Hostadter functions $G, H$ and beyond: numeration systems and discrepancy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12615v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hofstadter's G function is recursively defined via G(0) = 0 and then G(n) = n -G(G(n -1)). Following Hofstadter, a family (F\_k) of similar functions is obtained by varying the number k of nested recursive calls in this equation. We study here some Fibonacci-like sequences that are deeply connected with these functions F\_k . In particular, the Zeckendorf theorem can be adapted to provide digital expansions via sums of terms of these sequences. On these digital expansions, the functions F k are acting as right shifts of the digits. The Fibonacci-like sequences are then expressed in terms of zeros of the polynomial X^k -X^(k-1) -1. Thanks to that, we estimate the discrepancy of each function F\_k , i.e., the maximal distance between F\_k and its linear equivalent. This discrepancy is finite exactly when k $\le$ 4. This also solves some related questions, in particular two twenty-year-old OEIS conjectures stating how close the functions F\_3 and F\_4 are from the integer parts of their linear equivalents. Moreover F\_k can coincide exactly with such an integer part only when k $\le$ 2, while F\_k is almost additive exactly when k $\le$ 4. Finally, a nice fractal shape a la Rauzy has been encountered when investigating the discrepancy of F\_3 .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12615v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Letouzey (IRIF, PICUBE)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized De Bruijn Words, Invertible Necklaces, and the Burrows-Wheeler Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define generalized de Bruijn words, as those words having a Burrows--Wheeler transform that is a concatenation of permutations of the alphabet. We show how to interpret generalized de Bruijn words in terms of Hamiltonian cycles in the generalized de Bruijn graphs introduced in the early '80s in the context of network design. When the size of the alphabet is a prime, we give relations between generalized de Bruijn words, normal bases of finite fields, invertible circulant matrices, and Reutenauer groups. In particular, we highlight a correspondence between binary de Bruijn words of order $d+1$, binary necklaces of length $2^{d}$ having an odd number of $1$s, invertible BWT matrices of size $2^{d}\times 2^{d}$, and normal bases of the finite field $\mathbb{F}_{2^{2^{d}}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12844v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Fici, Est\'eban Gabory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Freeness Problem for Automaton Semigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the freeness problems for automaton semigroups and for automaton monoids are undecidable and, thereby, solve an open problem listed by Grigorchuk, Nekrashevych and Sush\-chansk\u{\i}i. We achieve this using a new technique to encode Post's Correspondence Problem into automaton semigroups and monoids and our result even holds if we restrict the alphabet of the input automata to a constant size. The encoding allows us to precisely control the relations in the generated semigroup/monoid and the construction is quite versatile. In fact, we obtain further undecidability results on various semigroup notions (left cancellativity, equidivisibility and extending homomorphisms). Our construction can also be adapted to show that the free presentation problem for automaton monoids is undecidable (and yields a weaker statement in the semigroup case).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01372v2</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4230/LIPIcs.MFCS.2024.44</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MFCS 2024; LIPIcs, Volume 306, 44:1-44:18</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniele D'Angeli, Emanuele Rodaro, Jan Philipp W\"achter</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
