<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.FL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.FL</link>
    <description>cs.FL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.FL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 02:36:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Word equations and the exponent of periodicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we study word equations in free semigroups and the conjecture that the existence of infinitely many solutions entails the existence of solutions with arbitrarily large exponent of periodicity. We examine this question in the broader framework of word equations with regular constraints and establish new positive results: the conjecture holds for all quadratic word equations with constraints in finite semigroups from the variety $\mathbf{DLG}$ and its left-right dual $\mathbf{DRG}$, encompassing, in particular, all finite groups, commutative semigroups, and $\mathcal{J}$-trivial semigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08208v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volker Diekert, Silas Natterer, Alexander Thumm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RESTL: Reinforcement Learning Guided by Multi-Aspect Rewards for Signal Temporal Logic Transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Signal Temporal Logic (STL) is a powerful formal language for specifying real-time specifications of Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS). Transforming specifications written in natural language into STL formulas automatically has attracted increasing attention. Existing rule-based methods depend heavily on rigid pattern matching and domain-specific knowledge, limiting their generalizability and scalability. Recently, Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) of large language models (LLMs) has been successfully applied to transform natural language into STL. However, the lack of fine-grained supervision on atomic proposition correctness, semantic fidelity, and formula readability often leads SFT-based methods to produce formulas misaligned with the intended meaning. To address these issues, we propose RESTL, a reinforcement learning (RL)-based framework for the transformation from natural language to STL. RESTL introduces multiple independently trained reward models that provide fine-grained, multi-faceted feedback from four perspectives, i.e., atomic proposition consistency, semantic alignment, formula succinctness, and symbol matching. These reward models are trained with a curriculum learning strategy to improve their feedback accuracy, and their outputs are aggregated into a unified signal that guides the optimization of the STL generator via Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO). Experimental results demonstrate that RESTL significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in both automatic metrics and human evaluations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08555v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Fang, Jin Zhi, Jie An, Hongshen Chen, Xiaohong Chen, Naijun Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
