<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ringdown amplitudes of nonspinning eccentric binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Closed-form expressions for the ringdown complex amplitudes of nonspinning unequal-mass binaries in arbitrarily eccentric orbits are presented. They are built upon 237 numerical simulations contained within the RIT catalog, through the parameterisation introduced in [Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 101401]. Global fits for the complex amplitudes, associated to linear quasinormal mode frequencies of the dominant ringdown modes, are obtained in a factorised form immediately applicable to any existing quasi-circular model. Similarly to merger amplitudes, ringdown ones increase by more than 50% compared to the circular case for high impact parameters (medium eccentricities), while strongly suppressed in the low impact parameter (highly eccentric) limit. Such reduction can be explained by a transition between an "orbital-type" and an "infall-type" dynamics. The amplitudes (phases) fits accuracy lies around a few percent (deciradians) for the majority of the dataset, comparable to the accuracy of current state-of-the-art quasi-circular ringdown models, and well within current statistical errors of current LIGO-Virgo-Kagra ringdown observations. These expressions constitute another building block towards the construction of complete general-relativistic inspiral-merger-ringdown semi-analytical templates, and allow to extend numerically-informed spectroscopic analyses beyond the circular limit. Such generalisations are key to achieve accurate inference of compact binaries astrophysical properties, and tame astrophysical systematics within observational investigations of strong-field general relativistic dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19442v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Carullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Light deflection with torsion effects caused by a spinning cosmic string"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19658v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this comment, we showed that the line element ("metric'') worked by Jusufi (Eur. Phys. J. C 76: 332, 2016) is incorrect since he worked with a spinning cosmic string with torsion in $(2+1)$-dimensions (and in polar coordinates), which cannot happen. Indeed, as in $(2+1)$-dimensions there are no screw dislocations or screw torsion (a consequence of the absence of the third spatial dimension, i.e., of the $z$-axis), and being a cosmic string with torsion a type of screw dislocation, but of cosmic origin (i.e., are cosmic dislocations), implies that a $(2+1)$-dimensional cosmic string does not have/carry torsion (since $dz=0$). Therefore, the line element worked by Jusufi is physically incoherent/unacceptable and inappropriate for the research/study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19658v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. R. S. Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Tensor Network Algorithms for Spin Foam Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19676v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerical computations and methods have become increasingly crucial in the study of spin foam models across various regimes. This paper adds to this field by introducing new algorithms based on tensor network methods for computing amplitudes, focusing on topological SU(2) BF and Lorentzian EPRL spin foam models. By reorganizing the sums and tensors involved, vertex amplitudes are recast as a sequence of matrix contractions. This reorganization significantly reduces computational complexity and memory usage, allowing for scalable and efficient computations of the amplitudes for larger representation labels on standard consumer hardware--previously infeasible due to the computational demands of high-valent tensors.
  We apply these tensor network algorithms to analyze the characteristics of various vertex configurations, including Regge and vector geometries for the SU(2) BF theory, demonstrating consistent scaling behavior and differing oscillation patterns. Our benchmarks reveal substantial improvements in computational time and memory allocations, especially for large representation labels. Additionally, these tensor network methods are applicable to generic 2-complexes with multiple vertices, where we introduce partial-coherent vertex amplitudes to streamline the computations. The implementation of these algorithms is available on GitHub for further exploration and use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19676v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seth K. Asante, Sebastian Steinhaus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Superpotential Method and the Amplification of Inflationary Perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The superpotential method is a reconstruction technique which has proven useful to build exact cosmological solutions. We here employ the superpotential method in order to reconstruct the features necessary for the inflaton potential to drive inflation and lead to the amplification of the curvature perturbations. Such an amplification, at wavelengths shorter than those observed in the CMB, is necessary in order to have a significant formation of Primordial Black Holes after inflation ends. The technique is applied to the cases of a minimally coupled inflaton, to the non-minimal coupling case and to f(R) theories of gravity. For such theories, a model dependent analysis of the features leading to the scalar spectrum enhancement is also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19762v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Y. Kamenshchik, Ekaterina O. Pozdeeva, Augustin Tribolet, Alessandro Tronconi, Giovanni Venturi, Sergey Yu. Vernov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced induced gravitational waves in Horndeski gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study secondary gravitational wave production in Horndenski gravity, when the scalar field dominates the very early universe. We find that higher derivative interactions easily dominate the source term on subhorizon scales and significantly enhance the amplitude of induced GWs. We analytically derive, for the first time, the Horndeski induced GW spectrum for a general class of power-law solutions. The main effect of modifications of gravity are stronger resonances and a growth of tensor fluctuations on small scales. The maximum attainable amplitude of the induced GW spectrum is bounded by the possible backreaction of higher derivatives on curvature fluctuations, thereby shutting down the source term to induced GWs. We argue that the maximum attainable amplitude depends linearly on the primordial curvature spectrum ($\Omega_{\rm GW}\propto {\cal P}_\zeta$), as opposed to the standard case where it depends quadratically. Resonances may further enhance the maximum amplitude by a factor $(k/{\cal H}_t)^2$ or $(k/{\cal H}_t)$ respectively for sharp and broad peaks (including a scale invariant) primordial spectrum, where ${\cal H}_t$ is the comoving horizon at the time when standard gravity is recovered. Remarkably, in the scale invariant case, the Horndeski-induced GW spectrum grows as $k^3$. This opens up the interesting possibility that induced GWs might be observable despite no enhancement of the primordial curvature spectrum. Our formalism can be generalized to a wider class of solutions and to more general scalar-tensor theories, such as DHOST and spatially covariant gravity. In the appendices we provide discussions on the gauge issue and disformal transformations of induced GWs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19950v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Dom\`enech, Alexander Ganz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge invariant quantum backreaction in U(1) axion inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We evaluate the quantum backreaction due to a gauge field coupled to a pseudo scalar field driving a slow-roll inflationary stage, the so-called axion inflation. The backreaction is evaluated for the first time using a gauge invariant approach, going to second order in perturbation theory and taking in consideration inflaton fluctuations as well as scalar perturbations of the metric. Within our gauge invariant, but observer-dependent approach, we naturally consider as physical observer the one comoving with the inflaton field. Considering the effective expansion rate consequent to the gauge fields bacreaction, we observe that the backreaction effect becomes significant quite rapidly, moving the system out of the perturbative regime and into what is often referred to the strong backreaction regime. This behavior also applies to the parameter which dictates the production of the gauge fields. The space-time dynamic is initially mainly influenced by the helicity contribution, with a significant response to the energy density which occurs much later with respect to the number of e-folds. As a final result, we see that the evaluated backreaction prolongs the inflationary period much more compared to the scenarios previously studied neglecting scalar metric perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19960v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Campanella Galanti, Pietro Conzinu, Giovanni Marozzi, Simony Santos da Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme horizon equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extremal horizons satisfy an equation induced by the Einstein vacuum equations that determines the shape of the horizon and the manner in which it rotates (the EEH equation). Until recently, however, the classification of solutions required the assumption of axial symmetry. Recently, there has been a breakthrough: Dunajski and Lucietti proved that every non-static solution possesses a one-dimensional symmetry group. The first part of our work is inspired by this result. An identity satisfied by the solutions of the EEH equation has been distilled (Master Identity), which is crucial for studying their properties. It is a bit stronger than the original Dunajski-Lucietti identity and leads directly to the rigidity theorem for any value of the cosmological constant. Master Identity is used for a simple derivation of the local form of the general static solution of the EEH equation with non-positive cosmological constant. All the globally defined compact static solutions are derived. Thus the list of solutions given in the literature is completed. In the two-dimensional case (which corresponds to horizons in four-dimensional spacetime), the Einstein-Maxwell equations of an extremal horizon (EMEH) and the equations of quasi-Einstein spaces are studied. The general solution on a compact surface with non-zero genus is derived. In the case of zero genus, the static solutions are investigated and their axial symmetry is proven. Together with the new results on non-static solutions on sphere of Colling, Katona and Lucietti that leads to the uniqueness of the Reissner-Nordstr\"om-(Anti)de-Sitter extremal horizons. Interestingly, the static rigidity result is also valid for non-compact spaces with a zero first cohomology group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20068v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Kami\'nski, Jerzy Lewandowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matter effects in Bianchi cosmologies: analytic solutions, asymptotic analysis, and Kasner map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to analyze the effects of the matter fields in the evolution of the Bianchi type I and IX cosmologies. For such a purpose, we consider several comoving barotropic perfect fluids with a linear equation of state. For Bianchi I it is possible to reduce the solution of the dynamics to a quadrature, which can be explicitly performed in certain cases. In particular, we obtain the explicit solution for one species, as well as for two species, given their barotropic indices obey certain relation. These solutions include and generalize different models studied in the literature. For completeness, we analyze all the different possible signs of the matter energy densities, and we obtain a particularly interesting model in which an exotic species produces a bounce of the scale factor, providing a singularity-free cosmology, and then decays to leave a nonexotic component as the dominant fluid for large volumes. Concerning Bianchi IX, although its dynamics is very involved, asymptotically, as the singularity is approached, it can be well approximated as a succession of Bianchi I periods connected by quick bounces against potential walls. Moreover, in such limit, matter fields (excluding stiff matter) are known to be subdominant with respect to the anisotropies. By performing an expansion around small volumes, we are able to obtain an approximate analytic solution of the dynamics, and compute the form of the transition (Kasner) map that relates the pre- and post-bounce Bianchi I periods including the leading matter effects. As an important conclusion, we observe that generically the presence of matter leads to a post-bounce velocity with a lower deflection angle than in the vacuum case, and thus effectively increases the convex curvature of the potential wall. This effect may have important consequences in the chaotic nature of general relativity near spacelike singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20070v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Brizuela, Sara F. Uria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrahigh-energy neutrino searches using next-generation gravitational wave detectors at radio neutrino detectors: GRAND, IceCube-Gen2 Radio, and RNO-G</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19440v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Binary neutron star (BNS) mergers can be sources of ultrahigh-energy (UHE) cosmic rays and potential emitters of UHE neutrinos. The upcoming and current radio neutrino detectors like the Giant Radio Array for Neutrino Detection (GRAND), IceCube-Gen2 Radio, and the Radio Neutrino Observatory in Greenland (RNO-G) are projected to reach the required sensitivities to search for these neutrinos. In particular, in conjunction with the next-generation of gravitational wave (GW) detectors like Cosmic Explorer (CE) and Einstein Telescope (ET), GW-triggered stacking searches can be performed with the UHE neutrino detectors. In this work, we explore the prospects of such searches by implementing in our analysis an upper distance limit based on the sky-localization capabilities of the GW detectors from which meaningful triggers can be collected. We find that if each GW burst is associated with a total isotropic-equivalent energy of $\sim 10^{50} - 10^{51}$ erg emitted in UHE neutrinos, along with a corresponding beaming fraction of $1$\%, GRAND and IceCube-Gen2 Radio have a large probability ($\sim 99$\%) to detect a coincident neutrino event using the joint combination of CE+ET in a timescale of less than 15 years of operation for our fiducial choice of parameters. In case of nondetections, the parameter spaces can be constrained at $3\sigma$ level in similar timescales of operation. We also highlight and discuss the prospects of such joint radio neutrino detector network, their importance, and their role in facilitating synergic GW and neutrino observations in the next era of multimessenger astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19440v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mainak Mukhopadhyay, Kumiko Kotera, Stephanie Wissel, Kohta Murase, Shigeo S. Kimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics around supermassive black holes: Extreme mass-ratio inspirals as gravitational-wave sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Supermassive black holes and their surrounding dense stellar environments nourish a variety of astrophysical phenomena. We focus on the distribution of stellar-mass black holes around the supermassive black hole and the consequent formation of extreme mass-ratio inspirals (EMRIs). We derive a steady-state distribution, considering the effects of two-body scatterings and gravitational wave emission, and calculate the EMRI formation rate, eccentricity distribution and EMRI-to-plunge ratio. Our model predicts: (I) A stronger segregation than previously estimated at the outskirts of the sphere of influence (at $\sim0.01\rm pc$ to $2\rm pc$ for a Milky-way like galaxy). (II) An increased EMRI-to-plunge ratio, favoring EMRIs at galaxies where stellar-mass black holes are scarce. (III) A detection of about $2\times10^3$ resolvable EMRIs, with a signal-to-noise ratio above $20$, along a $4$ year LISA mission time. (IV) A confusion noise, induced by a cosmological population of unresolved EMRIs, reducing LISA sensitivity in the $1-10\ \rm mHz$ frequency range by up to a factor of $\approx3.5$, relative to the instrumental noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19443v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barak Rom, Itai Linial, Karamveer Kaur, Re'em Sari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In LIGO's Sight? Vigorous Coherent Gravitational Waves from Cooled Collapsar Disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first numerical study of gravitational waves (GWs) from collapsar disks, using state-of-the-art 3D general-relativistic magnetohydrodynamic simulations of collapsing stars. These simulations incorporate a fixed Kerr metric for the central black hole (BH) and employ simplified prescriptions for disk cooling. We find that cooled disks with an expected scale height ratio of $H/R\gtrsim0.1$ at $\sim10$ gravitational radii induce Rossby instability in compact, high-density rings. The trapped Rossby vortices generate vigorous coherent emission regardless of disk magnetization and BH spin. For BH mass of $\sim10\,M_\odot$, the GW spectrum peaks at $\sim100\,{\rm Hz}$ with some breadth due to various non-axisymmetric modes. The spectrum shifts toward lower frequencies as the disk viscously spreads and the circularization radius of the infalling gas increases. Weaker-cooled disks with $H/R\gtrsim0.3$ form a low-density extended structure of spiral arms, resulting in a broader, lower-amplitude spectrum. Assuming an optimistic detection threshold with a matched-filter SNR of 20 and a rate similar to supernovae Ib/c, LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) could detect $\lesssim1$ event annually, suggesting that GW events may already be hidden in observed data. Third-generation GW detectors could detect dozens to hundreds of collapsar disks annually, depending on the cooling strength and the disk formation rate. The GW amplitudes from collapsar disks are $\gtrsim100$ times higher with a substantially greater event rate than those from core-collapse supernovae, making them potentially the most promising burst-type GW class for LVK and Cosmic Explorer. This highlights the importance of further exploration and modeling of disk-powered GWs, promising insights into collapsing star physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19452v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ore Gottlieb, Amir Levinson, Yuri Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$N$-bein formalism for the parameter space of quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work introduces a geometrical object that generalizes the quantum geometric tensor; we call it $N$-bein. Analogous to the vielbein (orthonormal frame) used in the Cartan formalism, the $N$-bein behaves like a ``square root'' of the quantum geometric tensor. Using it, we present a quantum geometric tensor of two states that measures the possibility of moving from one state to another after two consecutive parameter variations. This new tensor determines the commutativity of such variations through its anti-symmetric part. In addition, we define a connection different from the Berry connection, and combining it with the $N$-bein allows us to introduce a notion of torsion and curvature \`{a} la Cartan that satisfies the Bianchi identities. Moreover, the torsion coincides with the anti-symmetric part of the two-state quantum geometric tensor previously mentioned, and thus, it is related to the commutativity of the parameter variations. We also describe our formalism using differential forms and discuss the possible physical interpretations of the new geometrical objects. Furthermore, we define different gauge invariants constructed from the geometrical quantities introduced in this work, resulting in new physical observables. Finally, we present two examples to illustrate these concepts: a harmonic oscillator and a generalized oscillator, both immersed in an electric field. We found that the new tensors quantify correlations between quantum states that were unavailable by other methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19468v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Romero, Carlos A. Velasquez, J David Vergara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tomographic constraints on the production rate of gravitational waves from astrophysical sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using an optimal quadratic estimator, we measure the large-scale cross-correlation between maps of the stochastic gravitational-wave intensity, constructed from the first three LIGO-Virgo observing runs, and a suite of tomographic samples of galaxies covering the redshift range $z\lesssim 2$. We do not detect any statistically significant cross-correlation, but the tomographic nature of the data allows us to place constraints on the (bias-weighted) production rate density of gravitational waves by astrophysical sources as a function of cosmic time. Our constraints range from $\langle b\dot{\Omega}_{\rm GW}\rangle&lt;3.0\times10^{-9}\,{\rm Gyr}^{-1}$ at $z\sim0.06$ to $\langle b\dot{\Omega}_{\rm GW}\rangle&lt;2.7\times10^{-7}\,{\rm Gyr}^{-1}$ at $z\sim1.5$ (95\% C.L.), assuming a frequency spectrum of the form $f^{2/3}$ (corresponding to an astrophysical background of binary mergers), and a reference frequency $f_{\rm ref}=25\,{\rm Hz}$. Although these constraints are $\sim2$ orders of magnitude higher than the expected signal, we show that a detection may be possible with future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19488v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Alonso, Mehraveh Nikjoo, Arianna I. Renzini, Emilio Bellini, Pedro G. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing quantum theory on curved space-time with quantum networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19533v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum technologies present new opportunities for fundamental tests of nature. One potential application is to probe the interplay between quantum physics and general relativity - a field of physics with no empirical evidence yet. Here we show that quantum networks open a new window to test this interface. We demonstrate how photon mediated entanglement between atomic or atom-like systems can be used to probe time-dilation induced entanglement and interference modulation. Key are non-local measurements between clocks in a gravitational field, which can be achieved either through direct photon interference or by using auxiliary entanglement. The resulting observable depends on the interference between different proper times, and can only be explained if both quantum theory and general relativity are taken into account. The proposed protocol enables clock interferometry on km-scale separations and beyond. Our work thus shows a realistic experimental route for a first test of quantum theory on curved space-time, opening up new scientific opportunities for quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19533v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Borregaard, Igor Pikovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information content in anisotropic cosmological fields: Impact of different multipole expansion scheme for galaxy density and ellipticity correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19669v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multipole expansions have been often used for extracting cosmological information from anisotropic quantities in observation. However, which basis of the expansion is best suited to quantify the anisotropies is not a trivial question in any summary statistics. In this paper, using the Fisher matrix formalism, we investigate the information content in multipole moments of the power spectra of galaxy density and intrinsic ellipticity fields in linear theory from the Alcock-Paczynski effect and redshift-space distortions (RSD). We consider two expansion schemes, the associated Legendre basis as well as the standard Legendre basis conventionally used in literature. We find that the information in the multipoles of the intrinsic alignment (IA) power spectra in the associated Legendre basis converges more slowly to that in the full 2D power spectra than in the Legendre basis. This trend is particularly significant when we consider a high number density sample. In this high number density case, we show that the errors on the Hubble parameter obtained from the multipoles of the IA cross- and auto-power spectra in the associated Legendre basis are respectively about $6 \%$ and $10 \%$ larger than the full 2D case even when we use multipoles up to $\ell = 6$. Our results demonstrate that the choice of basis is arbitrary but changes the information content encoded in multipoles depending on the sample and statistics under consideration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19669v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Inoue, Teppei Okumura, Shohei Saga, Atsushi Taruya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality constraints on thermal spectra of 3d CFTs and 4d quasinormal modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19790v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal spectra of correlation functions in holographic 3d large-N CFTs correspond to quasinormal modes of classical gravity and other fields in asymptotically anti-de Sitter black hole spacetimes. Using general properties of such spectra along with constraints imposed by the S-duality (or the particle-vortex duality), we derive a spectral duality relation that all such spectra must obey. Its form is universal in that each such relation (expressed as an infinite product over QNMs) only depends on a single function of a spatial wavevector that corresponds to the bulk algebraically special frequencies. In the process, we also derive a new sum rule constraining products over QNMs. The spectral duality relation, which imposes an infinite set of constraints on the QNMs, is then investigated and a number of well-known holographic examples that demonstrate its validity are examined. Our results also allow us to understand several new aspects of the pole-skipping phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19790v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sa\v{s}o Grozdanov, Mile Vrbica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curbing PBHs with PTAs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20089v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sizeable primordial curvature perturbations needed to seed a population of primordial black holes (PBHs) will be accompanied by a scalar-induced gravitational wave signal that can be detectable by pulsar timing arrays (PTA). We derive conservative bounds on the amplitude of the scalar power spectrum at the PTA frequencies and estimate the implied constraints on the PBH abundance. We show that only a small fraction of dark matter can consist of stellar mass PBHs when the abundance is calculated using threshold statistics. The strength and the shape of the constraint depend on the shape of the power spectrum and the nature of the non-Gaussianities. We find that constraints on the PBH abundance arise in the mass range $0.1-10^3\, M_{\odot}$, with the sub-solar mass range being constrained only for narrow curvature power spectra. These constraints are softened when positive non-Gaussianity is introduced and can be eliminated when $f_{\rm NL} \gtrsim 5$. On the other hand, if the PBH abundance is computed via the theory of peaks, the PTA constraints on PBHs are significantly relaxed, signalling once more the theoretical uncertainties in assessing the PBH abundance. We further discuss how strong positive non-Gaussianites can allow for heavy PBHs to potentially seed supermassive BHs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20089v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. J. Iovino, G. Perna, A. Riotto, H. Veerm\"ae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting constraints on the no-hair theorem from the stochastic gravitational wave background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17767v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Although the constraints on general relativity (GR) from each individual gravitational-wave (GW) event can be combined to form a cumulative estimate of the deviations from GR, the ever-increasing number of GW events used also leads to the ever-increasing computational cost during the parameter estimation. Therefore, in this paper, we will introduce the deviations from GR into GWs from all events in advance and then create a modified stochastic gravitational-wave background (SGWB) to perform tests of GR. More precisely, we use the $\mathtt{pSEOBNRv4HM\_PA}$ model to include the model-independent hairs and calculate the corresponding SGWB with a given merger rate. Then we turn to the Fisher information matrix to forecast the constraints on the no-hair theorem from SGWB at frequency $10[{\rm Hz}]\lesssim f\lesssim10^3[{\rm Hz}]$ detected by the third-generation ground-based GW detectors, such as the Cosmic Explorer. We find that the forecasting constraints on hairs at $68\%$ confidence range are $\delta\omega_{220}=0\pm0.1296$ and $\delta\tau_{220}=0\pm0.0678$ when the flat priors about the merger rate are added but $\delta\omega_{220}=0\pm0.0903$ and $\delta\tau_{220}=0\pm0.0608$ when the non-flat priors about the merger rate are added.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17767v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Tan, Ke Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Binary Properties from Gravitational Wave Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11439v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This review provides a conceptual and technical survey of methods for parameter estimation of gravitational wave signals in ground-based interferometers such as LIGO and Virgo. We introduce the framework of Bayesian inference and provide an overview of models for the generation and detection of gravitational waves from compact binary mergers, focusing on the essential features that are observable in the signals. Within the traditional likelihood-based paradigm, we describe various approaches for enhancing the efficiency and robustness of parameter inference. This includes techniques for accelerating likelihood evaluations, such as heterodyne/relative binning, reduced-order quadrature, multibanding and interpolation. We also cover methods to simplify the analysis to improve convergence, via reparametrization, importance sampling and marginalization. We end with a discussion of recent developments in the application of likelihood-free (simulation-based) inference methods to gravitational wave data analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11439v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1146/annurev-nucl-121423-100725</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Javier Roulet, Tejaswi Venumadhav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact stars in Rastall gravity: hydrostatic equilibrium and radial pulsations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02440v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the context of Rastall gravity, we investigate the hydrostatic equilibrium and dynamical stability against radial pulsations of compact stars, where a free parameter $\beta$ measures the deviations from General Relativity (GR). We derive both the modified Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff (TOV) equations and the Sturm-Liouville differential equation governing the adiabatic radial oscillations. Such equations are solved numerically in order to obtain the compact-star properties for two realistic equations of state (EoSs). For hadronic matter, the fundamental mode frequency $\omega_0$ becomes unstable almost at the critical central energy density corresponding to the maximum gravitational mass. However, for quark matter, where larger values of $\vert\beta\vert$ are required to observe appreciable changes in the mass-radius diagram, there exist stable stars after the maximum-mass configuration for negative values of $\beta$. Using an independent analysis, our results reveal that the emergence of a cusp can be used as a criterion to indicate the onset of instability when the binding energy is plotted as a function of the proper mass. Specifically, we find that the central-density value where the binding energy is a minimum corresponds precisely to $\omega_0^2 =0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02440v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10714-024-03225-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Gen. Relativ. Gravit. 56 (2024) 43</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Juan M. Z. Pretel, Cl\'esio E. Mota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Monte Carlo algorithm for spin foam intertwiners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04836v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monte Carlo algorithms are barely considered in spin foam quantum gravity. Due to the quantum nature of spin foam amplitudes one cannot readily apply them, and the present sign problem is a threat to convergence and thus efficiency. Yet, ultimately the severity of the sign problem in spin foams is not known. In this article we propose a new probability distribution for coherent (boundary) intertwiners, which we use to define a Markov Chain Monte Carlo algorithm. We apply this algorithm to the SU(2) coherent vertex amplitude for various Regge-type boundary data and find convergent, accurate results at far lower costs than the explicit calculation. The resources are instead used to increase the size of boundary spins, bridging the gap to the asymptotic formulae. While the sign problem is not solved, it is under control in the vast majority of cases. We close by discussing how this algorithm can be extended to larger triangulations with boundary and 4d Lorentzian spin foam models. More speculatively, we discuss how this algorithm can be used to sample (Regge-geometric) bulk intertwiners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04836v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Steinhaus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on the photon mass via the Shapiro effect in the solar system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12286v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the effects of a finite mass for the photon on its propagation in a weak gravitational field. In particular, we analyse the gravitational time delay, also known as the Shapiro effect. We work in isotropic coordinates in the weak-field limit and find that the mass-dependent corrections enhance the gravitational time delay. Doppler-tracking data from the Cassini mission allow us to set an upper bound on the photon mass, namely $m_\gamma &lt; 4.9 \times 10^{-7} \, {\rm eV/c^2}$ at $95\%$ CL. We also discuss next-generation solar-system tests of general relativity that could improve this upper limit, potentially by a factor of ten. Though not competitive with the currently best limits, our bound is at the ballpark of earlier ones based on the gravitational bending of light by the Sun.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12286v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. C. Malta, C. A. D. Zarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for gravitational-wave signals from precessing black hole binaries with the GstLAL pipeline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17186v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Precession in Binary Black Holes (BBH) is caused by the failure of the Black Hole spins to be aligned and its study can open up new perspectives in gravitational waves (GW) astronomy, providing, among other advancements, a precise measure of distance and an accurate characterization of the BBH spins. However, detecting precessing signals is a highly non-trivial task, as standard matched filtering pipelines for GW searches are built on many assumptions that do not hold in the precessing case. This work details the upgrades made to the GstLAL pipeline to facilitate the search for precessing BBH signals. The implemented changes in the search statistics and in the signal consistency test are then described in detail. The performance of the upgraded pipeline is evaluated through two extensive searches of precessing signals, targeting two different regions in the mass space, and the consistency of the results is examined. Additionally, the benefits of the upgrades are assessed by comparing the sensitive volume of the precessing searches with two corresponding traditional aligned-spin searches. While no significant sensitivity improvement is observed for precessing binaries with mass ratio $q\lesssim 6$, a volume increase of up to 100\% is attainable for heavily asymmetric systems with largely misaligned spins. Furthermore, our findings suggest that the primary cause of degraded performance in an aligned-spin search targeting precessing signals is not a poor signal-to-noise-ratio recovery but rather the failure of the $\xi^2$ signal-consistency test. Our work paves the way for a large-scale search for precessing signals, which could potentially result in exciting future detections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17186v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Schmidt, Sarah Caudill, Jolien D. E. Creighton, Ryan Magee, Leo Tsukada, Shomik Adhicary, Pratyusava Baral, Amanda Baylor, Kipp Cannon, Bryce Cousins, Becca Ewing, Heather Fong, Richard N. George, Patrick Godwin, Chad Hanna, Reiko Harada, Yun-Jing Huang, Rachael Huxford, Prathamesh Joshi, James Kennington, Soichiro Kuwahara, Alvin K. Y. Li, Duncan Meacher, Cody Messick, Soichiro Morisaki, Debnandini Mukherjee, Wanting Niu, Alex Pace, Cort Posnansky, Anarya Ray, Surabhi Sachdev, Shio Sakon, Divya Singh, Ron Tapia, Takuya Tsutsui, Koh Ueno, Aaron Viets, Leslie Wade, Madeline Wade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum gravity modifications to the accretion onto a Kerr black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the framework of the Asymptotic Safety scenario for quantum gravity, we analyze quantum gravity modifications to the thermal characteristics of a thin accretion disk spiraling around a renormalization group improved (RGI-) Kerr black hole in the low energy regime. We focused on the quantum effects on the location of the innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO), the energy flux from the disk, the disk temperature, the observed redshifted luminosity, and the accretion efficiency. The deviations from the classical general relativity due to quantum effects are described for a free parameter that arises in the improved Kerr metric as a consequence of the fact that the Newton constant turns into a running coupling $G(r)$ depending on the energy scale. We find that, both for rapid and slow rotating black holes with accretion disks in prograde and retrograde circulation, increases in the value of this parameter are accompanied by a decreasing of the ISCO, by a lifting of the peaks of the radiation properties of the disk and by an increase of the accretion mass efficiency, as compared with the predictions of general relativity. Our results confirm previously established findings in Ref. \cite{r17} where we showed that these quantum gravity effects also occur for an accretion disk around a RGI-Schwarzschild black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05028v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis A. S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal modes in semi-open systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11013v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Astrophysical black holes are open systems which, when perturbed, radiate quasi-normal modes (QNMs) to infinity. By contrast, laboratory analogues are necessarily finite-sized, presenting a potential obstacle to exciting QNMs in the lab. In this study, we investigate how the QNM spectrum of a toy-model black hole is modified when the system is enclosed by a partially reflecting wall. Counter to expectation, we demonstrate that QNMs not only persist in finite-sized systems, but the number of accessible modes increases. Furthermore, we show that QNMs in this set-up can be easily excited by incoherent background noise. Our findings align with studies exploring the spectral stability of black holes, such as those examining small modifications of the surrounding gravitational field. Importantly, our work paves the way for exploring spectral stability in laboratory systems, enabling experimental investigation of black hole features in closed systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11013v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Solidoro, Sam Patrick, Ruth Gregory, Silke Weinfurtner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One loop to rule them all: Perturbativity in the presence of ultra slow-roll dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03491v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the issue of perturbativity in single-field inflationary models with a phase of ultra slow-roll (USR) tailor suited to generate an order-one abundance of primordial black holes (PBHs). More in detail, we impose the condition that loop corrections made up of short-wavelength modes enhanced by the USR dynamics do not alter the tree-level power spectrum of curvature perturbations. In our analysis, the USR phase is preceded and followed by two stages of ordinary slow-roll (SR), and we model the resulting SR/USR/SR dynamics using both instantaneous and smooth transitions. Focusing on scales relevant for CMB observations, we find that it is not possible, with these arguments, to rule out the scenario of PBH formation via USR, not even in the limit of instantaneous transition. However, we also find that loop corrections of short modes on the power spectrum of long modes, even though not large enough to violate perturbativity requirements, remain appreciable and, most importantly, are not tamed in realistic realisations of smooth SR/USR/SR transitions. This makes perturbativity a powerful theoretical tool to constrain USR dynamics. We extend the analysis at any scale beyond those relevant for CMB observations. We find that loop corrections of short modes remain within the few percent if compared to the tree-level power spectrum. However, we also find one notable exception of phenomenological relevance: we show that the so-called dip in the power spectrum of curvature perturbation is an artifact of the tree-level computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03491v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.123550</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 123550 Published 28 June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Franciolini, Antonio Junior Iovino, Marco Taoso, Alfredo Urbano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Complexity and Phase Transition for AdS Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09223v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, the complexity equals any gravitational observable conjecture has been proposed in [Phys. Rev. Lett. 128, 081602 (2022)], which is an extension of the complexity equals volume proposal. These gravitational observables are referred to as generalized volumes. In this paper, we investigate the generalized volume-complexity for black holes with one or two horizons respectively. We verify that the turning time is universal and independent of the Cauchy horizon. Not only does this phase transition occur once, but it may also occur two or more times depending on the number and height of the effective potential peaks. On the other hand, we confirm that the generalized volume-complexity can be divided based on the shape of the effective potential. We then discuss the non-smooth transition from the Reissner-Nordstr\"om-AdS black hole to the Schwarzschild-AdS black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09223v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yue Jiang, Meng-Ting Wang, Yu-Xiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General backreaction force of cosmological bubble expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07691v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational-wave energy-density spectra from cosmological first-order phase transitions crucially depend on the terminal wall velocity of asymptotic bubble expansion when the driving force from the effective potential difference is gradually balanced by the backreaction force from the thermal plasma. Much attention has previously focused on the backreaction force acting on the bubble wall alone but overlooked the backreaction forces on the sound shell and shockwave front, if any, which have been both numerically and analytically accomplished in our previous studies but only for a bag equation of state. In this paper, we will generalize the backreaction force on bubble expansion beyond the simple bag model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07691v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Chen Wang, Zi-Yan Yuwen, Yu-Shi Hao, Shao-Jiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological classes of thermodynamics of the static multi-charge AdS black holes in gauged supergravities: novel temperature-dependent thermodynamic topological phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00106v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate, in the framework of the topological approach to black hole thermodynamics, using the generalized off-shell Helmholtz free energy, the topological numbers of the static multi-charge AdS black holes in four- and five-dimensional gauged supergravities. We find that the topological number of the static-charged AdS black holes in four-dimensional Kaluza-Klein (K-K) gauged supergravity theory is $W = 0$, while that of the static-charged AdS black holes in four-dimensional gauged $-iX^0X^1$-supergravity and STU gauged supergravity theories, and five-dimensional Einstein-Maxwell-dilaton-axion (EMDA) gauged supergravity and STU gauged supergravity, and five-dimensional static-charged AdS Horowitz-Sen black hole are both $W = 1$. Furthermore, we observe a novel temperature-dependent thermodynamic topological phase transition that can happen in the four-dimensional static-charged AdS black hole in EMDA gauged supergravity theory, the four-dimensional static-charged AdS Horowitz-Sen black hole, and the five-dimensional static-charged AdS black hole in K-K gauged supergravity theory. We believe that the novel temperature-dependent thermodynamic topological phase transition could help us better understand black hole thermodynamics and, further, shed new light on the fundamental nature of gauged supergravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00106v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP06(2024)213</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 06 (2024) 213</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Di Wu, Shuang-Yong Gu, Xiao-Dan Zhu, Qing-Quan Jiang, Shu-Zheng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Primordial Black Hole Abundance: The Broader, the Better</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11033v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the abundance of primordial black holes, if formed through the collapse of large fluctuations generated during inflation and unless the power spectrum of the curvature perturbation is very peaked, is always dominated by the broadest profile of the compaction function, even though statistically it is not the most frequent. The corresponding threshold is therefore 2/5. This result exacerbates the tension when combining the primordial black hole abundance with the signal seen by pulsar timing arrays and originated from gravitational waves induced by the same large primordial perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11033v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.123549</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 123549 Published 28 June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Ianniccari, A. J. Iovino, A. Kehagias, D. Perrone, A. Riotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface growth approach for bulk reconstruction in AdS/BCFT correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12086v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the surface growth scheme in AdS spacetime with a boundary in the AdS/BCFT correspondence. We show that the entanglement wedge with a boundary can be constructed from the direct growth of bulk extremal surfaces layer by layer. In addition, we find that the surface growth configuration in BCFT can be connected with the defect multi scale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA) tensor network. Furthermore, we also investigate the entanglement of purification within the surface growth process, which reveals more refined structure of entanglement entropy and indicates a selection rule for surface growth in the bulk reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12086v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. H. Fang, F. Z. Chen, J. R. Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating metrics and new multipole moments from scattering amplitudes in arbitrary dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16574v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the vacuum metric generated by a generic rotating object in arbitrary dimensions up to third post-Minkowskian order by computing the classical contribution of scattering amplitudes describing the graviton emission by massive spin-1 particles up to two loops. The solution depends on the mass, angular momenta, and on up to two parameters related to generic quadrupole moments. In $D=4$ spacetime dimensions, we recover the vacuum Hartle-Thorne solution describing a generic spinning object to second order in the angular momentum, of which the Kerr metric is a particular case obtained for a specific mass quadrupole moment dictated by the uniqueness theorem. At the level of the effective action, the case of minimal couplings corresponds to the Kerr black hole, while any other mass quadrupole moment requires non-minimal couplings. In $D&gt;4$, the absence of black-hole uniqueness theorems implies that there are multiple spinning black hole solutions with different topology. Using scattering amplitudes, we find a generic solution depending on the mass, angular momenta, the mass quadrupole moment, and a new stress quadrupole moment which does not exist in $D=4$. As special cases, we recover the Myers-Perry and the single-angular-momentum black ring solutions, to third and first post-Minkowksian order, respectively. Interestingly, at variance with the four dimensional case, none of these solutions corresponds to the minimal coupling in the effective action. This shows that, from the point of view of scattering amplitudes, black holes are the "simplest" General Relativity vacuum solutions only in $D=4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16574v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Gambino, Paolo Pani, Fabio Riccioni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communicating multiverses in a holographic de Sitter braneworld</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00763v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct the wedge holography for the de-Sitter space as a bulk theory. First, we discuss a more general mathematical construction of wedge holography in parallel with wedge holography construction for the AdS bulk, and then we construct the wedge holography in the extended static patch. In the first case, we prove that one can construct wedge holography for the de-Sitter bulk for the static patch as well as global coordinate metric on end-of-the-world branes. Extended static patch wedge holography is constructed by joining the two copies of double holography in DS/dS correspondence. We find that wedge holography with extended static patch metric leads to the emergence of communicating universes. Further, we propose a model which provides the theoretical evidence of communicating multiverses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00763v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gopal Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large curvature fluctuations from no-scale supergravity with a spectator field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02295v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the large curvature perturbations which can lead to the formation of primordial black holes (PBHs) in the context of no-scale supergravity. Our study does not depend on any exotic scenario, such as scalar potentials with inflection points or bulks, and aims to avoid the fine-tuning of model parameters to achieve the formation of PBHs. This formation relies on the quantum fluctuations of a light spectator stochastic field after the inflationary period. Our analysis is based on the SU(2,1)/SU(2)$\times$U(1) symmetry, considering both the inflaton and the spectator field. Specifically, we examine existing no-scale models with Starobinsky-like scalar potentials that are consistent with observable constraints on inflation from measurements of the cosmic microwave background (CMB). These models involve two chiral fields: the inflaton and the modulus field. We propose a novel role for the modulus field as a spectator field, responsible for generating PBHs. Our hypothesis suggests that while the inflaton field satisfies the CMB constraints of inflation, it is the modulus field acting as the spectator that leads to large curvature perturbations, capable to explain the production of PBHs. Additionally, we prioritize retaining the inflationary constraints from the CMB through the consideration of spectator fluctuations. Therefore, by exploring the relationship between these fields within the framework of the SU(2,1)/SU(2)$\times$U(1) symmetry, our aim is to unveil their implications for the formation of PBHs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02295v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138798</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ioanna D. Stamou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Observational Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01669v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: What can be measured by an observer in our universe? We address this question by constructing an algebra of gravitationally-dressed observables accessible to a comoving observer in FLRW spacetimes that are asymptotically de Sitter in the past, describing an inflationary epoch. An essential quantized degree of freedom is the zero-mode of the inflaton, which leads to fluctuations in the effective cosmological constant during inflation and prevents the existence of a maximum entropy state in the semiclassical limit. Due to the inaccessibility of measurements beyond our cosmological horizon, we demonstrate that all states are mixed with well-defined von Neumann entropy (up to a state-independent constant). For semiclassical states, the von Neumann entropy corresponds to the generalized entropy of the observer's causal diamond, a fine-grained quantity that is sensitive to the initial conditions of the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01669v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonah Kudler-Flam, Samuel Leutheusser, Gautam Satishchandran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using gauge invariance to symmetrize the energy-momentum tensor of electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06785v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is shown that using Noether's Theorem explicitly employing gauge invariance for variations of the electromagnetic four-potential $A^\mu$ straightforwardly ensures that the resulting electromagnetic energy-momentum tensor is symmetric. The Belinfante symmetrization procedure is not necessary. The method is based on Bessel-Hagen's 1921 clarification of Noether's original procedure, suggesting that the symmetry problem arises from an incomplete implementation of Noether's Theorem. The derivation addresses in some detail where the usual application of Noether's Theorem falls short, what the Belinfante procedure actually does to fix the problem, and why the usual unsymmetric canonical energy-momentum tensor can only be used for extracting four-momentum conservation based on translational invariance, but will provide meaningless results when applied to rotations or boosts, unless modified appropriately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06785v2</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helmut Haberzettl</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
