<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:40:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic dark energy in Barrow cosmology with Granda-Oliveros IR cutoff</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21074v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Applying the modified Barrow entropy, inspired by the quantum fluctuation effects, to the cosmological background, and using thermodynamics-gravity conjuncture, the Friedmann equations get modified as well. In this paper, we explore the holographic dark energy with Granda-Oliveros (GO) IR cutoff, in the context of the modified Barrow cosmology. First, we assume two dark components of the universe evolves independently and obtain the cosmological parameters and explore the cosmic evolution. Second, we consider an interaction term between dark energy (DE) and dark matter (DM). We observe that the Barrow parameter $\delta$ crucially affects the cosmic dynamics, causes the transition from the decelerating phase to the accelerating phase occurs later. We find out that the equation of state parameter is in the quintessence region in the past and crosses the phantom divide at the present time. Finally, we examine the squared speed of sound analysis for this model. According to the squared sound speed diagrams, the results indicate that the presence of interaction between DM and DE as well as increasing in the value of $\delta$ leads to the manifestation of signs of instability in the past $(v_s^2&lt;0)$. Furthermore, by examining the statefinder, we find that presence of $\delta$ also makes a distinction between holographic dark energy in Barrow cosmology with GO-IR cutoff and the $\Lambda$CDM model. In fact, increasing $\delta$ causes the statefinder diagram move away from the point of $\left\lbrace r,s\right\rbrace= \left\lbrace 1,0\right\rbrace$ at $z=0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21074v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Motaghi, A. Sheykhi, E. Ebrahimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-singular naked solutions in quantum spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polymer models have been used to describe non-singular quantum black holes, where the classical singularity is replaced by a transition from a black hole to a white hole. In a previous letter, in the context of a uni-parametric model with asymptotic flat exterior metric, we fixed the radius of the transition surface through the identification of its area with the area gap of Loop Quantum Gravity. This revealed a dependence of the polymerisation parameter on the black hole mass, where the former increases as the latter decreases, and it also enabled the extension of the model to Planck-scale black holes. We have identified the existence of limiting states with masses $m \geq \sqrt{2}/4$ and zero surface gravity, showing that Hawking evaporation asymptotically leads to remnant black holes of Planck size. In the present paper we consider solutions with $m &lt; \sqrt{2}/4$, observing again the presence of a minimal radius, but without formation of horizons. Diversely from the previous mass range, only charged solutions are allowed in this case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21076v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. P. R. Baranov, H. A. Borges, F. C. Sobrinho, S. Carneiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Road to Singularity Theorems with Torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines the formulation of a singularity theorem for timelike curves including torsion, and establishes the foundational framework necessary for its derivation. We begin by deriving the relative acceleration for an arbitrary congruence of timelike curves. The resulting ``deviation equation'' offers an alternative pathway to the well-known Raychaudhuri equation with torsion. Conjugate points are then introduced and analyzed in relation to the behavior of the scalar expansion. Together with the sensible requirement of hypersurface orthogonality, the Raychaudhuri equation is examined for several specific cases of torsion that are prominent in the literature. Our findings indicate that a totally antisymmetric torsion tensor does not influence the behavior of the congruence of timelike curves. Finally, we formulate a singularity theorem for timelike curves and highlight the critical requirement of non-autoparallel curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21107v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armin van de Venn, Ujjwal Agarwal, David Vasak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Effects in 3+1 Schwarzschild-de Sitter Spacetime: Properties of the Hadamard Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a four-dimensional Schwarzschild-de Sitter background, the spherically symmetric ($\ell=0$) contribution to the Hadamard two-point correlation function is computed for a massless minimally-coupled scalar field in the Unruh state. Consideration is given to spacetime points located exterior to the black hole horizon, but within the cosmological horizon. Previously it was found in two dimensions for spatially separated points that the Hadamard function exhibits unbounded linear growth at late times, with a rate of growth proportional to the sum of the black hole and cosmological surface gravities. Here it is shown numerically that this behavior persists in four dimensions, where scattering effects associated with the scalar field modes lead to a modification of the two-dimensional result. An analytic approximation is derived for the growth rate in four dimensions and, in the limit that the black hole vanishes, the leading order contribution is equivalent to the rate of growth for the Hadamard function found previously for de Sitter space in cosmological coordinates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21108v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian M. Newsome, Silvia Pla, Paul R. Anderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>gwforge: A user-friendly package to generate gravitational-wave mock data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21109v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The next-generation gravitational-wave detectors, with their improved sensitivity and wider frequency bandwidth, will be capable of observing almost every compact binary signal from epochs before the first stars began to form, increasing the number of detectable binaries to hundreds of thousands annually. This will enable us to observe compact objects through cosmic time, probe extreme matter phenomena, do precision cosmology, study gravity in strong field dynamical regimes and potentially allow observation of fundamental physics beyond the standard model. However, the richer data sets produced by these detectors will pose new computational, physical and astrophysical challenges, necessitating the development of novel algorithms and data analysis strategies. To aid in these efforts, this paper introduces gwforge, a user-friendly, lightweight Python package, to generate mock data for next-generation detectors. We demonstrate the package's capabilities through data simulation examples and highlight a few potential applications: performance loss due to foreground noise, bright-siren cosmology and impact of waveform systematics on binary parameter estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21109v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koustav Chandra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hawking Temperature and the Inverse-Radius Scale of the Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hawking temperature of a Schwarzschild black hole can be heuristically derived by identifying the temperature with the inverse radius of the horizon up to a multiplicative constant. This does not work for more general black holes such as the Kerr and Reissner-Nordstr\"om solutions. Expounding on the details of how it fails to work nevertheless uncovers interesting connections with the "spring constant" of black holes and with black hole thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21114v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael R. R. Good, Yen Chin Ong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy production due to spacetime fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the quantum nature of the gravitational field is undoubtedly one of the greatest challenges in theoretical physics. Despite significant progress, a complete and consistent theory remains elusive. However, in the weak field approximation -- where curvature effects are small -- we can explore some expected properties of such a theory. Particularly relevant to this study is the quantum nature of gravitational waves, which are represented as small perturbations in flat spacetime. In this framework, a quantum description of these perturbations, as a quantum field, is feasible, leading to the emergence of the graviton. Here we consider a non-relativistic quantum system interacting with such a field. We employ the consistent histories approach to quantum mechanics, which allows us to frame classical questions in a quantum context, to define a fluctuation relation for this system. As a result, thermodynamic entropy must be produced in the system due to its unavoidable interaction with the quantum fluctuations of spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21186v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiago H Moreira, Lucas C. C\'eleri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test of the Equivalence Principle for Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We searched for violations of the weak equivalence principle using a cryogenic torsion balance with a pendulum comprised of superconducting niobium and copper. We constrain the E\"otv\"os parameter with 95\%-confidence to $\eta_{\text{Nb*-Cu}}~\leq~2.0\times10^{-9}$ and $\eta_{\text{CP-ee}}\leq6.9\times10^{-3}$ for superconducting niobium and Cooper pairs, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21232v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. P. Ross, S. M. Fleischer, I. A. Paulson, P. Lamb, B. M. Iritani, E. G. Adelberger, C. A. Hagedorn, K. Venkateswara, C. Gettings, E. A. Shaw, S. K. Apple, J. H. Gundlach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative of light propagation in Born-Infeld, Euler-Heisenberg and ModMax nonlinear electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compare light propagation through an intense electromagnetic background as described by three different nonlinear electrodynamics: Born-Infeld (BI), Euler-Heisenberg (EH), and Modified Maxwell (MM). We use the concept of effective metric to determine the phase velocities of a propagating wave from the BI and EH nonlinear electrodynamics and use them to set constraints on the MM nonlinear parameter. In a second part of the paper, we consider the black hole solutions of the nonlinear electrodynamics coupled with General Relativity and determine the shadows cast by the static black holes. Confronting the observations of the shadows of M87$^*$ and Sagittarius A$^*$ with our theoretical results allows us to set restrictions on the nonlinear parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21326v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elda Guzman-Herrera, Ariadna Montiel, Nora Breton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic relation of accelerating black holes in anti-de Sitter spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider accelerating black holes in four-dimensional anti-de Sitter spacetime and investigate the extremality relations by examining perturbative corrections to both the entropy of black holes and their extremality bounds. It is shown that the so-called Goon and Penco (univeral) relation is also valid for accelerating black holes. Furthermore, it is found that an appropriate matching condition is necessary between the perturbation parameter of the relation with the perturbative correction to such black holes, and the parameter with information about the conical deficits on the north and south poles with the cosmic string tensions in order to satisfy the extremality relations. This result indicates that the extremality (univeral) relation of a class of accelerating black holes holds exhibit behavior similar to the Weak Gravity Conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21329v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Oh Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starobinsky inflation beyond the leading order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Starobinsky model of cosmological inflation in four spacetime dimensions is reviewed with the emphasis on impact of quantum gravity corrections. As a specific example of the quantum corrections, the Grisaru-Zanon quartic curvature terms in the gravitational effective action of closed superstrings are chosen. Those quartic curvature terms are compared to the Bel-Robinson tensor squared in a flat Friedman universe, and the upper bound on the effective string coupling constant is found by demanding unitarity (causality) and the absence of ghosts. It is found that the quantum corrections to the observables (tilts) of the cosmic microwave background radiation in the Starobinsky inflation may be of the same order of magnitude as the next-to-next-to-next classical contributions in the Starobinsky model with respect to the inverse powers of the e-folding number at the horizon crossing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21349v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Toyama, Sergei V. Ketov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing a gauge-invariant formulation and a "conventional complete gauge-fixing approach" for $l=0,1$ mode perturbations on the Schwarzschild background spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21375v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Comparison of the gauge-invariant formulation for $l=0,1$-mode perturbations on the Schwarzschild background spacetime proposed in [K.~Nakamura, Class. Quantum Grav. {\bf 38} (2021), 145010.] and a ``conventional complete gauge-fixing approach'' in which we use the spherical harmonic functions $Y_{lm}$ as the scalar harmonics from the starting point is discussed. Although it is often said that ``gauge-invariant formulations in general-relativistic perturbations are equivalent to complete gauge-fixing approaches,'' as the result of this comparison, we conclude that the derived solutions through the proposed gauge-invariant formulation and those through a ``conventional complete gauge-fixing approach'' are different. It is pointed out that there is a case where the boundary conditions and initial conditions are restricted in a conventional complete gauge-fixing approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21375v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kouji Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical System Analysis Of Chameleon Mechanism in Brans-Dicke Scalar-Tensor Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21380v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the stability of the chameleon screening mechanism in the Brans-Dicke scalar-tensor model. We define a constraint on the Brans-Dicke parameter $\omega_{BD}^*$ identifying two stability groups, $\omega_{BD}&gt;\omega_{BD}^*$ and $0&lt;\omega_{BD}&lt;\omega_{BD}^*$. The first group achieves stability with both appropriate eigenvalues and a density profile consistent with dark energy dominance. The second exhibits eigenvalue stability but contradicts conditions for a stable universe. We explore the impact of variations in the scalar field potential and matter coupling by analyzing different parameter sets. Each unique set of parameters results in a distinct $\omega_{BD}^*$. Dynamic analysis reveals that stability is achieved when the scalar field dominates, highlighting the importance of the kinetic and potential terms while minimizing the influence of matter density. In high matter density regions, the scalar field's negligible presence aligns with standard gravitational behavior, whereas in low matter density regions, the scalar field grows exponentially, driving dark energy and cosmic acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21380v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azwar Sutiono, Agus Suroso, Freddy Permana Zen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonsingular universe through zero-point length cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Taking into account the zero-point length correction to the gravitational potential and using the entropic force scenario, we derive a modified expression for entropy that includes zero-point length correction terms. We then apply the thermodynamics-gravity conjecture and the emergent gravity scenario to derive the modified Friedmann equations. These equations describe the evolution of the universe with zero-point length corrections included in the entropy expression. Further, we examine the time evolution of the total entropy, including the entropy of the apparent horizon and the matter field entropy inside the horizon and find that the generalized second law of thermodynamics is satisfied. Besides, we investigate cosmological implications of the modified cosmology through zero-point length. We study several cases, including radiation dominated era, matter dominated era and universe filled with matter and cosmological constant. We observe that the zero-point length correction does not change the general profile of the universe evolution, however, it shifts the time of the phase transition in a universe filled with matter and cosmological constant. We explore the age of the universe for our model and observe that the predicted age of the universe becomes larger compared to the standard cosmology. By calculating the explicit form of Ricci and Kretchmann invariants, we confirm that in our model, the initial singularity of the universe is removed. This is an expected result, because the main motivation for considering zero-point length correction in the gravitational potential is to remove singularity at the origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21426v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Sheykhi, Leila Liravi, Kimet Jusufi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational-wave observations and primordial black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational-wave observations have the potential of allowing the identification of a population of merging primordial black-hole binaries. We provide an overview of the capabilities of present and future GW detectors, with a special emphasis on the perspective for observing quantities that are signatures of a primordial origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21442v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Iacovelli, Michele Maggiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurements of Gravitational Attractions at small Accelerations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational interactions were studied by measuring the influence of small external field masses on a microwave resonator. It consisted of two spherical mirrors, which acted as independent pendulumsindividually suspended by strings. Two identical field masses weremoved along the axis of the resonator symmetrically and periodically betweena near and a far position. Their gravitational interaction altered the distance between the mirrors, changing the resonance frequency, which was measured and found consistent with Newton's law of gravity.
  The acceleration of a single mirror caused by the two field masses at the closest position varied from $5.4 10^{-12} m/s^2$ to $259 10^{-12}\ m/s^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21482v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Bartel (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany), C. W. Elvers (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany), L. J\"onsson (Lund University, Sweden), G. Kempf (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany), H. Krause (Universit\"at Hamburg), B. Loehr (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany), E. Lohrmann (Universit\"at Hamburg), H. Meyer (Bergische Universit\"at, Wuppertal), P. Steffen (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany), E. Wuensch (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY, Hamburg, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness of equipotential photon surfaces in 4-dimensional static vacuum asymptotically flat spacetimes for positive, negative, and zero mass -- and a new partial proof of the Willmore inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present different proofs of the uniqueness of 4-dimensional static vacuum asymptotically flat spacetimes containing a connected equipotential photon surface or in particular a connected photon sphere. We do not assume that the equipotential photon surface is outward directed or non-degenerate and hence cover not only the positive but also the negative and the zero mass case which has not yet been treated in the literature. Our results partially reproduce and extend beyond results by Cederbaum and by Cederbaum and Galloway. In the positive and negative mass cases, we give three proofs which are based on the approaches to proving black hole uniqueness by Israel, Robinson, and Agostiniani--Mazzieri, respectively. In the zero mass case, we give four proofs. One is based on the positive mass theorem, the second one is inspired by Israel's approach and in particular leads to a new proof of the Willmore inequality in $(\mathbb{R}^3, \delta)$, under a technical assumption. The remaining two proofs are inspired by proofs of the Willmore inequality by Cederbaum and Miehe and by Agostiniani and Mazzieri, respectively. In particular, this suggests to view the Willmore inequality and its rigidity case as a zero mass version of equipotential photon surface uniqueness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21522v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carla Cederbaum, Albachiara Cogo, Axel Fehrenbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum cosmological spacetimes without CMC Cauchy surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we extend a construction of [6] to obtain a large class of vacuum cosmological spacetimes that do not contain any CMC Cauchy surfaces. The allowed spatial topologies for these examples are of the form $M \# M$, where $M$ is any closed, oriented, irreducible $3$-manifold which is not spherical. This complements the recent results of [19], where, instead of initial data methods, global spacetime gluing arguments were used. The study of such examples is sure to yield insight into Bartnik's cosmological splitting conjecture [1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21524v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Ling, Argam Ohanyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite distance effects on the Hellings-Downs curve in modified gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is growing interest in the overlap reduction function in pulsar timing array observations as a probe of modified gravity. However, current approximations to the Hellings-Downs curve for subluminal gravitational wave propagation, say $v&lt;1$, diverge at small angular pulsar separation. In this paper, we find that the ORF for the $v&lt;1$ case is sensitive to finite distance effects. First, we show that finite distance effects introduce an effective cut-off in the spherical harmonics decomposition at $\ell\sim \sqrt{1-v^2} \, kL$, where $\ell$ is the multipole number, $k$ the wavenumber of the gravitational wave and $L$ the distance to the pulsars. Then, we find that the overlap reduction function in the small angle limit approaches a value given by $\pi kL\,v^2\,(1-v^2)^2$ times a normalization factor, exactly matching the value for the autocorrelation recently derived. Although we focus on the $v&lt;1$ case, our formulation is valid for any value of $v$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21567v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Dom\`enech, Apostolos Tsabodimos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black bounces in Cotton gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, J. Harada proposed a theory relating gravity to the Cotton tensor, dubbed as ''Cotton gravity'' (CG). This is an extension of General Relativity such that every solution of the latter turns out to be a solution of the former (but the converse is not true) and, furthermore, it is possible to derive the cosmological constant as an integration constant within it. In this work we investigate CG by coupling it to both non-linear electrodynamics (NLED) and scalar fields. We study static and spherically symmetric solutions implementing a bouncing behaviour in the radial function so as to avoid the development of singularities, inspired by the Simpson-Visser black bounce and the Bardeen model, both interpreted as magnetic monopoles. We identify the NLED Lagrangian density and the scalar field potential generating such solutions, and investigate the corresponding gravitational configurations in terms of horizons, behaviour of the metric functions, and regularity of the Kretchsman curvature scalar. Our analysis extends the class of non-singular geometries found in the literature and paves the ground for further analysis of black holes in CG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21649v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ednaldo L. B. Junior, Jos\'e Tarciso S. S. Junior, Francisco S. N. Lobo, Manuel E. Rodrigues, Diego Rubiera-Garcia, Lu\'is F. Dias da Silva, Henrique A. Vieira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the $\gamma$-parameter for the vacuum solution of Cotton gravity with geodesics and shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a recently introduced extension of General Relativity dubbed as Cotton gravity (CG), based on the use of the Cotton tensor, to estimate the size of a new constant $\gamma$ appearing within a spherically symmetric, vacuum solution of the theory. Taking into account its non-asymptotically flat character, we use the inferred size of the central brightness depression of the supermassive object at the heart of the Milky Way galaxy (Sgr A*) by the Event Horizon Telescope to constrain at $2\sigma$ the CG parameter as $\gamma M \approx 3.5 \times 10^{-12}$. We study the potential observational consequences from the smallness of such a value using exact and numerical expressions for the deflection angle, optical images from optically and geometrically thin accretion disks, isoradials, and instability scales (Lyapunov index) of nearly bound geodesics associated to photon rings. Our results point towards the impossibility to distinguish between these two geometries using current and foreseeable techniques in the field of interferometric detection of optical sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21655v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ednaldo L. B. Junior, Jos\'e Tarciso S. S. Junior, Francisco S. N. Lobo, Manuel E. Rodrigues, Diego Rubiera-Garcia, Lu\'is F. Dias da Silva, Henrique A. Vieira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causality and stability in relativistic hydrodynamic theory -- a choice to be endured</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18997v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, it has been indicated that the key features requisite for preserving causality and stability of the popularly existing relativistic hydrodynamic theories, can be translated into each other. It has been shown here, that a generic `fluid frame transformation' including all orders of gradient corrections can recast a stable-causal hydrodynamic theory that (i) only includes fundamental fluid variables (velocity and temperature) but requires to be in a general hydrodynamic frame other than the Landau or Eckart, to a theory that is (ii) pathology free in Landau frame but needs newer degrees of freedom. Since frame choice provides the first principle field definitions and degrees of freedom indicate the number of conserved quantities, the causality and stability of a theory seem to require a consensus between the two unless the derivative correction goes to infinity. The key finding of this work is to indicate a connection between these different formalisms, that lead to a causal and stable hydrodynamic theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18997v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantani Bhattacharyya, Sukanya Mitra, Shuvayu Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separating deterministic and stochastic gravitational wave signals in realistic pulsar timing array datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21105v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent observations by pulsar timing arrays indicate the presence of gravitational wave signals, likely from supermassive black hole binaries. These binaries can produce two types of signals: a stochastic gravitational wave background (GWB) or deterministic continuous gravitational waves (CGW). Correctly separating these signals is essential for accurate signal recovery and interpretation. This paper investigates the interaction between GWB and CGW signals within current analysis pipelines, focusing on misinterpretations and biases in parameter estimation when these signals are analyzed separately or together. We conducted several simulations based on the European PTA 24.8-year dataset. First, we injected either a GWB or a CGW. We compared parameter estimation using different search models, including Earth term only, combined Earth and pulsar term CGW templates, and correlated (HD) or uncorrelated (CURN) power law GWB templates. Our findings show that, when searched independently, the GWB and CGW signals can be misinterpreted as each other, and only a combined search can recover the true signal present. For datasets containing both a GWB and a CGW, failure to account for the CGW biases the recovery of the GWB. However, a combined search allows for the recovery of both GWB and CGW parameters without significant bias. Care must be taken with the method used to perform combined searches on these multi-component datasets, as the CGW pulsar term can be misinterpreted as a CURN. This can be avoided by direct searches for an HD correlated GWB plus a CGW. Our study underscores the importance of combined searches to ensure unbiased recovery of GWB parameters in the presence of strong CGWs, which is crucial for interpreting signals recently found in PTA data and represents a step toward a robust framework for disentangling stochastic and deterministic GW signals in future, more sensitive datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21105v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irene Ferranti, Golam Shaifullah, Aurelien Chalumeau, Alberto Sesana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical generation of electroweak scale from the conformal sector: A strongly coupled Higgs via the Dyson--Schwinger approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21179v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel pathway to generate the electroweak (EW) scale via non-perturbative dynamics of a conformally invariant scalar sector at the classical level. We provide a method to estimate the non-perturbative EW scale generation using the exact solution of the background equations of motion in a scalar theory via the Dyson-Schwinger approach. Particularly, we find an analytical result for the Higgs mass in the strongly coupled regime in terms of its quartic self interaction term and the cut-off scale of the theory. We also show that the Higgs sector is an essential part of the Standard Model as, without it, a Yang--Mills gauge theory cannot acquire mass even if a self-interaction term is present. Our analysis lead to a more realistic model building with possible solutions to the gauge hierarchy problem and, in general, to the dynamical generation of any scales scales in nature, be it the visible sector or the dark sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21179v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Chatterjee, Marco Frasca, Anish Ghoshal, Stefan Groote</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Captured molecules could make a Bose star visible</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A Bose star passing through cold molecular clouds may capture atoms, molecules and dust particles. The observational signature of such an event would be a relatively small amount of matter that is gravitationally bound. This binding may actually be provided by invisible dark matter forming the Bose star. We may expect a relative excess of heavier atoms, molecules, and solid dust compared to the content of giant cold molecular clouds since the velocity of heavy particles at a given temperature is lower and it may be small compared to the escape velocity, $v_\mathrm{rms} = \sqrt{3k_\mathrm{B} T/m_\mathrm{gas}} \ll v_\mathrm{esc}=\sqrt{2GM/R}$. Finally, the velocity of this captured matter cloud may correlate with the expected velocity of free dark matter particles (e.g. expected axion wind velocity relative to Earth).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21262v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Flambaum, I. B. Samsonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supermassive blackhole-Ultralight dark matter connection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A novel proposal linking the origin of supermassive blackhole formation and ultralight dark matter. Ultralight bosons of mass $10^{-22}-10^{-24}$ eV which is one of the front running proposal for dark matter could also linked with the formation and evolution of supermassive blackholes at the center of all the galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21355v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T R Govindarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brane-vector dark matter and its connection to inflation and primordial gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scalar mode describing the fluctuation of the 3-brane (the observable universe) in a five-dimensional bulk spacetime compactified on a circle is absorbed by the Kaluza-Klein U(1) gauge field, leading to a massive brane-vector living on the 3-brane. The brane-vector can be responsible for dark matter because it is odd under a $\mathrm{Z}_2$ symmetry, neutral under the Standard Model (SM) symmetries, and couples extremely weak to the SM particles due to its gravitational origin. Interestingly, the brane-vector dark matter could leave particular imprints on the cosmic microwave background (CMB) and the primordial gravitational waves. Hence, the precise measurements of the CMB and the observations of the primordial gravitational waves generated during the inflation can provide a potential way to probe the extra-dimensions and branes which are the main ingredients of string/M theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21410v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cao H. Nam, Tran N. Hung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hairy dyonic Reissner-Nordstr\"om black holes in an Einstein-Maxwell-Friedberg-Lee-Sirlin type model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct spherically symmetric dyonic black holes in a generalized Maxwell-Friedberg-Lee-Sirlin type model with a complex scalar doublet and a symmetry breaking potential {for the real scalar field}, minimally coupled to Einstein gravity in asymptotically flat space.
  We analyze the properties of the hairy black holes and determine their domain of existence. Our discussion focuses mostly on the case of a long-ranged massless real scalar field.
  Our results indicate that in this case, depending on the coupling constants, the resonant hairy dyonic black holes may bifurcate from Reissner-Nordstr\"om black holes at maximal chemical potential, while the limiting solutions at minimal chemical potential may be related to the Penney solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21463v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jutta Kunz, Victor Loiko, Yakov Shnir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-extremal Island in de Sitter Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21617v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the challenges and resolutions in computing the entanglement entropy for the quantum field theory coupled to de Sitter (dS) gravity along a timelike boundary. The conventional island formula, originally designed to calculate the fine-grained entropy for a non-gravitational system coupled to anti-de Sitter (AdS) gravity, encounters difficulties in de Sitter gravitational spacetime, failing to provide a physically plausible extremal island. To overcome these problems, we introduce a doubly holographic model by embedding a dS$_2$ braneworld in an AdS$_3$ bulk spacetime. This approach facilitates the computation of entanglement entropy through holographic correlation functions, effectively circumventing the constraints of the island formula. We demonstrate that the correct recipe for calculating entanglement entropy with dS gravity involves the non-extremal island, whose boundary is instead defined at the edge of the dS gravitational region. Our findings indicate that, during the island phase, the entanglement wedge of the non-gravitational bath includes the entire dS gravitational space. Using the second variation formula, we further show that the existence of a locally minimal surface anchored on the gravitational brane is intrinsically linked to the extrinsic curvature of the brane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21617v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng-Xiang Hao, Taishi Kawamoto, Shan-Ming Ruan, Tadashi Takayanagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-time uncertainty relation from entropy measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21746v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) modifies the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle (HUP) between position and momentum by introducing a nonzero minimum uncertainty in position. In a previous study, we demonstrated the emergence of GUP from non-extensive entropies, particularly for $S_\pm$ dependent only on the probability. In this new research, we derive a generalized energy-time uncertainty relation from these entropies. Consequently, we observe that the dispersion relation undergoes modification due to the non-extensivity introduced by the entropies $S_{+}$ and $S_{-}$. These modifications play a significant role at the Planck scale, but are negligible in the classical regime of large distances and low energies. Moreover, the modified uncertainty relation results in a maximum uncertainty in energy, attributed to the negative deformation parameter associated with entropy $S_{+}$. Conversely, the deformation parameter linked with $S_{-}$ leads to the emergence of a minimum time interval. In the Planck regime, the minimum time interval is on the order of the Planck time, while the maximum uncertainty in energy reaches the Planck energy. These findings imply that quantum gravity effects can be connected with non-extensive statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21746v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nana Cabo Bizet, Octavio Obreg\'on, Wilfredo Yupanqui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spurious Solar-Wind Effects on Acceleration Noise in LISA Pathfinder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spurious solar-wind effects are a potential noise source in the measurements of the future Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA). Comparative models are used to predict the possible impact of this noise factor and estimate spurious solar-wind effects on acceleration noise in LISA Pathfinder (LPF). Data from NASA's Advanced Composition Explorer (ACE), situated at the L1 Lagrange point, served as a reliable source of solar-wind data. The data sets were compared over the 114-day time period from March 1, 2016 to June 23, 2016. To evaluate these effects, the data from both satellites were formatted, gap-filled, and adapted for comparison, and a coherence plot comparing the results of the Fast Fourier Transformations. The coherence plot suggested that solar-wind had a minuscule effect on the LPF, and higher frequency coherence (LISA's main observing band) can be attributed to random chance correlation. This result indicates that measurable correlation due to solar-wind noise over 3-month timescales can be ruled out as a noise source. This is encouraging, although another source of noise from the sun, solar irradiance pressure, is estimated to have a more significant effect and has yet to be analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21774v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnold Yang, Indie Desiderio-Sloane, Grant David Meadors</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing a nonlinear solution of the Israel-Stewart theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.08823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.08823v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we test the capability of an exact solution found in the framework of a nonlinear extension of the Israel-Stewart theory to fit the supernovae Ia, gravitational lensing, and black hole shadow data. This exact solution is a generalization of one previously found for a dissipative unified dark matter model in the context of the near-equilibrium description of dissipative processes, where we do not have the full regime of the nonlinear picture. This generalized solution is restricted to the case where a positive entropy production is guaranteed and is tested under the condition that ensures its causality, local existence, and uniqueness. From the observational constraints, we found that this generalized solution is a good candidate in the description of the observational late-time data used in this work, with best-fit values $H_{0}=73.2_{-0.9}^{+0.8}\,\frac{km/s}{Mpc}$, $q_{0}=-0.41_{-0.03}^{+0.03}$, $\hat{\xi}_{0}=0.88_{-0.17}^{+0.09}$, $\epsilon=0.34_{-0.04}^{+0.03}$, and $k=0.27_{-0.20}^{+0.37}$. Therefore, we show that the nonlinear regime of the Israel-Stewart theory consistently describes the recent accelerated expansion of the universe without the inclusion of some kind of dark energy component and also provides a more realistic description of the fluids that make up the late Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.08823v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Cruz, Norman Cruz, Esteban Gonz\'alez, Samuel Lepe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonexistence of quantum black and white hole horizons in an improved dynamic approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.14535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.14535v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the quantum geometric effects near the locations where classical black hole horizons used to appear in Einstein's classical theory, within the framework of an improved dynamic approach, in which the internal region of a black hole is modeled by the Kantowski-Sachs (KS) spacetime and the two polymerization parameters are functions of the phase space variables. Our detailed analysis shows that the effects are so strong that black and white hole horizons of the effective quantum theory do not exist at all and instead are replaced by transition surfaces, across which the metric coefficients and their inverses are smooth and remain finite, as are the corresponding curvatures, including the Kretschmann scalar. These surfaces always separate trapped regions from anti-trapped regions. The number of such surfaces is infinite, so the corresponding KS spacetimes become geodesically complete, and no black and white hole-like structures exist in this scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.14535v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-024-2386-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci.China Phys.Mech.Astron. 67 (2024) 8, 280411</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Cong Gan, Xiao-Mei Kuang, Zhen-Hao Yang, Yungui Gong, Anzhong Wang, Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The constraint tensor for null hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14813v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we provide a definition of the constraint tensor of a null hypersurface data which is completely explicit in the extrinsic geometry of the hypersurface. The definition is fully covariant and applies for any topology of the hypersurface. For data embedded in a spacetime, the constraint tensor coincides with the pull-back of the ambient Ricci tensor. As applications of the results, we find three geometric quantities on any transverse submanifold $S$ of the data with remarkably simple gauge behaviour, and prove that the restriction of the constraint tensor to $S$ takes a very simple form in terms of them. We also obtain an identity that generalizes the standard near horizon equation of isolated horizons to totally geodesic null hypersurfaces with any topology. Finally, we prove that when a null hypersurface has product topology, its extrinsic curvature can be uniquely reconstructed from the constraint tensor plus suitable initial data on a cross-section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14813v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Manzano, Marc Mars</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examples of cosmological spacetimes without CMC Cauchy surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13715v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: CMC (constant mean curvature) Cauchy surfaces play an important role in mathematical relativity as finding solutions to the vacuum Einstein constraint equations is made much simpler by assuming CMC initial data. However, in [2] Bartnik constructed a cosmological spacetime without a CMC Cauchy surface whose spatial topology is the connected sum of two three-dimensional tori. Similarly, in [9], Chru\'sciel, Isenberg, and Pollack constructed a vacuum cosmological spacetime without CMC Cauchy surfaces whose spatial topology was also the connected sum of two tori. In this article, we enlarge the known number of spatial topologies for cosmological spacetimes without CMC Cauchy surfaces by generalizing Bartnik's construction. Specifically, we show that there are cosmological spacetimes without CMC Cauchy surfaces whose spatial topologies are the connected sum of any compact oriented Euclidean or hyperbolic three-manifold with any another compact oriented Euclidean or hyperbolic three-manifold. We work with the Tolman-Bondi class of metrics and prove gluing results for variable marginal conditions, which allows for smooth gluing of Schwarzschild to FLRW models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13715v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11005-024-01843-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Eric Ling, Argam Ohanyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum loop corrections in the modified gravity model of Starobinsky inflation with primordial black hole production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02934v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A modified gravity model of Starobinsky inflation and primordial black hole production was proposed in good (within $1\sigma$) agreement with current measurements of the cosmic microwave background radiation. The model is an extension of the singularity-free Appleby-Battye-Starobinsky model by the $R^4$-term with different values of the parameters whose fine-tuning leads to efficient production of primordial black holes on smaller scales with the asteroid-size masses between $10^{16}$ g and $10^{20}$ g. Those primordial black holes may be part (or the whole) of the current dark matter, while the proposed model can be confirmed or falsified by detection or absence of the induced gravitational waves with the frequencies about $10^{-2}$ Hz. The main purpose of this paper was to estimate the size of quantum (loop) corrections in the model. It was found their relative contribution to the power spectrum of scalar perturbations is about $10^{-3}$ or less, so that the model is not ruled out by the quantum corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02934v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sultan Saburov, Sergei V. Ketov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability investigations of de Sitter inflationary solutions in power-law extensions of the Starobinsky model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02623v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we would like to examine whether stable de Sitter inflationary solutions appear within power-law extensions of the Starobinsky model. In particular, we will address general constraints for the existence along with the stability of de Sitter inflationary solutions in a general case involving not only the Starobinsky $R^2$ term but also an additional power-law $R^n$ one. According to the obtained results, we will be able to identify which extension is more suitable for an early inflationary phase rather than a late-time cosmic acceleration phase. To be more specific, we will consider several values of $n$ to see whether the corresponding de Sitter inflationary solutions are stable or not.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02623v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13083-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 729 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tuyen M. Pham, Duy H. Nguyen, Tuan Q. Do, W. F. Kao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole in a generalized Chaplygin-Jacobi dark fluid: shadow and light deflection angle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05650v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a generalized Chaplygin-like gas with an anisotropic equation of state, characterizing a dark fluid within which a static spherically symmetric black hole is assumed. By solving the Einstein equations for this black hole spacetime, we explicitly derive the metric function. The spacetime is parametrized by two critical parameters, $\mathcal{B}$ and $\alpha$, which measure the deviation from the Schwarzschild black hole and the extent of the dark fluid's anisotropy, respectively. We explore the behavior of light rays in the vicinity of the black hole by calculating its shadow and comparing our results with the Event Horizon Telescope observations. This comparison constrains the parameters to $0 \leq \mathcal{B} &lt; 0.03$ and $0 &lt; \alpha &lt; 0.1$. Additionally, we calculate the deflection angles to determine the extent to which light is bent by the black hole. These calculations are further utilized to formulate possible Einstein rings, estimating the angular radius of the rings to be approximately $37.6\,\mathrm{\mu as}$. Throughout this work, we present analytical solutions wherever feasible, and employ reliable approximations where necessary to provide comprehensive insights into the spacetime characteristics and their observable effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05650v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2024.101598</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Fathi, J. R. Villanueva, Gilberto Aguilar-P\'erez, Miguel Cruz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Scalarization of Schwarzschild Black Hole in Scalar-Torsion Teleparallel Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13557v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a scalar field coupled to the torsion in Teleparallel Gravity with a coupling function that does not allow for a tachyonic instability to occur, and it leads to the formation of new black holes with scalar hair. The scalarized black hole solutions are asymptotically flat, and they are studied under their thermodynamics, and we show that they are meta-stable solutions without phase transitions of first and second order. Also, we demonstrate the existence of distinct branches of solutions classified by the number of nodes of the scalar field. For the branches analysed, the scalarized solutions have lower free energy than the Schwarzschild black hole; therefore, they are always thermodinamically preferred. Also, we show that the scalarized black holes are entropically favoured compared to the Schwarzschild solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13557v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. A. Gonz\'alez, Eleftherios Papantonopoulos, Joaqu\'in Robledo, Yerko V\'asquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the non-canonical dynamics in a high-dimensional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Revisiting Einstein's gravitational theory, we build a five-dimensional braneworld. Within this framework, one announces the appearance of symmetric and asymmetric domain walls. Furthermore, it examines the emergent four-dimensional gravity from a theory with non-canonical dynamics. Exploring the physical and mathematical aspects, e.g., brane's energy density and the Kaluza-Klein (KK) spectrum, one verifies that brane splitting is absent in the canonical and non-canonical theories. Additionally, we note the localization of the four-dimensional fluctuation projection on the 3-branes, which ensures the theory's stability. Thereby, one can conclude that the behavior of gravitational perturbations of the domain wall maintains a profile similar to a stable and non-localizable tower of massive modes. In contrast, within the brane core, the matter sector generates new barriers and potential wells, resulting in massive modes with approximately symmetric amplitudes. However, the non-canonical dynamics generate massive modes with asymmetric amplitudes far from the 3-brane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14693v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. C. E. Lima, F. M. Belchior, C. A. S. Almeida, P. K. Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General backreaction force of cosmological bubble expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07691v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational-wave energy-density spectra from cosmological first-order phase transitions crucially depend on the terminal wall velocity of asymptotic bubble expansion when the driving force from the effective potential difference is gradually balanced by the backreaction force from the thermal plasma. Much attention has previously focused on the backreaction force acting on the bubble wall alone but overlooked the backreaction forces on the sound shell and shock-wave front, if any, which have been both numerically and analytically accomplished in our previous studies but only for a bag equation of state. In this paper, we will generalize the backreaction force on bubble expansion beyond the simple bag model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07691v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.016031</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110 (2024) 016031</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Chen Wang, Zi-Yan Yuwen, Yu-Shi Hao, Shao-Jiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Perturbation Theory Meets CFT$_2$: Kerr Compton Amplitudes from Nekrasov-Shatashvili Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05965v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a novel study of Kerr Compton amplitudes in a partial wave basis in terms of the Nekrasov-Shatashvili (NS) function of the confluent Heun equation (CHE). Remarkably, NS-functions enjoy analytic properties and symmetries that are naturally inherited by the Compton amplitudes. Based on this, we characterize the analytic dependence of the Compton phase-shift in the Kerr spin parameter and provide a direct comparison to the standard post-Minkowskian (PM) perturbative approach within General Relativity (GR). We also analyze the universal large frequency behavior of the relevant characteristic exponent of the CHE -- also known as the renormalized angular momentum -- and find agreement with numerical computations. Moreover, we discuss the analytic continuation in the harmonics quantum number $\ell$ of the partial wave, and show that the limit to the physical integer values commutes with the PM expansion of the observables. Finally, we obtain the contributions to the tree level, point-particle, gravitational Compton amplitude in a covariant basis through $O(a_{\text{BH}}^8)$, without the need to take the super-extremal limit for Kerr spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05965v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilber Fabian Bautista, Giulio Bonelli, Cristoforo Iossa, Alessandro Tanzini, Zihan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Half the Schwarzschild Entropy from Strominger-Vafa Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12496v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a regular bound state of two extremal black holes in type IIB supergravity with opposite charges. The bound state resembles the Schwarzschild black hole from the asymptotics to the photon ring and has the same mass and charges as the Schwarzschild black hole. On the one hand, we show that the bound-state entropy admits a microscopic description in terms of branes and antibranes in string theory. On the other hand, we demonstrate that the entropy approaches half of the Schwarzschild entropy as the mass becomes significantly larger than the Kaluza-Klein scales used to regularize the geometry. This opens up the possibility of a brane/antibrane interpretation of the Schwarzschild entropy in string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12496v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.126015</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Heidmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic Stability Versus Chaos Bound Violation in D-dimensional RN Black Holes: Angular Momentum Effects and Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18193v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the Lyapunov exponents for test particles orbiting in unstable circular trajectories around D-dimensional Reissner-Nordstr\"om (RN) black holes, scrutinizing instances of the chaos bound violation. Notably, we discover that an increase in particle angular momentum exacerbates the breach of the chaos bound. Our research centrally investigates the correlation between black hole thermodynamic phase transitions and the breaking of the chaos limit. Findings suggest that the chaos bound can only be transgressed within thermodynamically stable phases of black holes. Specifically, in the four-dimensional scenario, the critical point of the thermodynamic phase transition aligns with the threshold condition that delineates the onset of chaos bound violation. These outcomes underscore a deep-rooted link between the thermodynamic stability of black holes and the constraints imposed by the chaos bound on particle dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18193v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Qi Lei, Xian-Hui Ge, Surojit Dalui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building the Blocks of Schwarzschild</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18994v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the Schwarzschild black hole can be ``resolved'' into bound states of Reissner-Nordstr\"om black holes in four dimensions. These bound states closely resemble the Schwarzschild geometry from the asymptotic region up to an infinitesimal distance away from the Schwarzschild horizon. Below this scale, the horizon is replaced by novel spacetime structures supported by intense and entrapped electromagnetic flux. The flux originates from collinear black holes that can be brought arbitrarily close to extremality. We find that the charge distribution follows a universal pattern, with magnitudes scaling proportionally to the total mass and alternating in sign. Moreover, the bound states always have an entropy that constitutes a fraction of the Schwarzschild entropy. Constructed in four dimensions, the black holes are kept apart by struts, for which we analyze tensions and energies. These solutions pave the way for analogous constructions in supergravity and for a brane/anti-brane description of the Schwarzschild black hole in string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18994v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP07(2024)234</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Dulac, Pierre Heidmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviving Horndeski after GW170817 by Kaluza-Klein compactifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02281v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The application of Horndeski theory/ Galileons for late time cosmology is heavily constrained by the strict coincidence in the speed of propagation of gravitational and electromagnetic waves. These constraints presuppose that the minimally coupled photon is not modified, not even at the scales where General Relativity (GR) may need modification. We find that the 4D Galileon obtained from a Kaluza-Klein compactification of its higher dimensional version is a natural simultaneous modification of GR and electromagnetism with automatically "luminal" gravitational waves. This property follows without any fine tuning of Galileon potentials for a larger class of theories than previously thought. In particular, the $G_4$ potential is not constrained by the speed test and $G_5$ may also be present. In other words, some Galileon models that have been ruled out since the event GW170817 are, in fact, not necessarily constrained if they arise in 4D from compactifications of their higher dimensional Galileon counterparts. Besides their compelling luminality, the resulting vector Galileons are naturally $U(1)$ gauge invariant. We also argue that the Vainshtein screening that allows to recover GR predictions for solar system tests is also at work for electrodynamics in the dense region of laboratory tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02281v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mironov, A. Shtennikova, M. Valencia-Villegas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on primordial black holes from LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA O3 events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05732v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBH) can efficiently form black hole binaries in the early universe. We update the resulting constraints on PBH abundance using data from the third observational run (O3) of LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA. To capture a wide range of PBH scenarios, we consider a variety of mass functions, including critical collapse in the QCD epoch in the presence of non-Gaussianities. Applying hierarchical Bayesian analysis to a population binaries consisting of primordial and astrophysical black holes, we find that, in every scenario, the PBHs can make up at most $f_{\rm PBH} \lesssim 10^{-3}$ of dark matter in the mass range $1-200~M_\odot$. The shape and strength of the constraints are insensitive to the type of non-Gaussianities, the modifications to the mass function during the QCD epoch, or the modelling of the astrophysical PBH population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05732v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.023040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 023040 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Andr\'es-Carcasona, A. J. Iovino, V. Vaskonen, H. Veerm\"ae, M. Mart\'inez, O. Pujol\`as, Ll. M. Mir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Entropy for the Black 0-Brane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13336v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyse the entanglement entropy between the Black 0-Brane solution to supergravity and its Hawking radiation. The Black 0-Brane admits a dual Gauge theory description in terms of the Matrix model for M-Theory, named BFSS theory, which is the theory of open strings on a collection of N D0-branes. Recent studies of the model have highlighted a mechanism of Black Hole evaporation for this system, based on the chaotic nature of the theory and the existence of flat directions. This paper further explores this idea, through the computation of the von Neumann entropy of Hawking radiation. In particular, we show that the expected Page curve is indeed reproduced, consistently with a complete recovery of information after the Black Hole has fully evaporated. A pivotal step in the computation is the definition of a Hilbert space which allows for a quantum mechanical description of partially evaporated Black Holes. We find that the entanglement entropy depends on the choice of a parameter, which can be interpreted as summarizing the geometric features of the Black Hole, such as the size of the resolved singularity and the size of the horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13336v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angshuman Choudhury, Davide Laurenzano</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
