<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement entropy of coherent intertwiner in loop quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we carry out the entanglement calculations on the coherent intertwiners. We first consider the entanglement introduced by the group-averaging of the tensor-product type intertwiner on a four-valents vertex. The result shows that the entanglement is determined by the probability distribution of recoupling spin, and this probability distribution is a well-behaved peak for the highest (and lowest) weight states. Further, we calculated explicitly the entanglement on gauge-invariant coherent intertwiner with four legs. Our numerical results show that the shape of the semiclassical polyhedron described by the coherent intertwiner can be related to the entanglement; In other words, the entanglement is controlled by the face-angle of the semiclassical polyhedron. Finally, we extend our analytical calculation to the coherent intertwiners with arbitrary number of legs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18020v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaoping Long, Qian Chen, Jinsong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new look at AdS black holes with conformal scalar hair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit static, spherically symmetric solutions to AdS-Einstein gravity with a conformally coupled scalar field (and no self-interaction potential) in four dimensions. We first observe that a convenient choice of coordinates leads to a significant simplification of the field equations, which enables one to identify various roots of the indicial equations and thus distinct branches of solutions. Next, we construct an explicit 2-parameter hairy black hole solution in terms of an infinite power series around the event horizon. The black hole is non-extremal with a regular scalar field on and outside the event horizon, and it reduces to the Schwarzschild-AdS metric in the limit of vanishing hair. Its properties are illustrated for various values of the parameters and compared with previous numerical results by other authors. In addition, the analysis reveals the presence of a photon sphere and how the scalar field affects its size, in agreement with certain general bounds obtained in the literature. The thermodynamics of the solution is also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18048v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcello Ortaggio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the pre-inflationary dynamics in loop quantum cosmology with a DBI scalar field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18289v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Loop quantum cosmology is a symmetry-reduced application of loop quantum gravity. The theory predicts a bounce for the universe at the Planck scale and resolves the singularity of standard cosmology. The dynamics is also governed by an effective Hamiltonian, which predicts a modified Friedmann equation containing the quadratic terms of the energy density. The term plays an essential role in the high energy regime, but the equations return to the standard form in the low energy regime. The evolution of the universe in the pre-inflationary period is studied in the framework of loop quantum cosmology, where the DBI scalar field is assumed to be the dominant component of the universe. Using the numerical method, we provide the evolution of the DBI field. The background evolution shows that there are three phases as: bouncing phase, transition phase and slow-roll inflationary phase. There is also a short period of super-inflation just at the beginning of the bounce phase. The field first climbs the potential and then reaches the turning point where $\dot{\phi}$ disappears and the potential energy becomes the dominant part of the energy density. This is the time when the slow roll inflation begins and the field slowly rolls down the potential. The results indicate that there are a few e-fold expansions in the bounce phase, about $N = $, and the universe experiences about $N = 59$ e-fold expansions in the slow-roll inflation phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18289v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abolhassan Mohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Inflation From Fluctuating Baby-Skyrme Brane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the inflationary dynamics induced by small fluctuations on the Skyrme brane, characterized by a time-dependent perturbative function $\tilde{\phi}$. In the low-energy regime, the model successfully reproduces standard inflation, with a potential term dictated by the Skyrmion at the brane. Gravity localization is achieved at the brane, and the lowest energy scale is established at the asymptotic boundary. The model demonstrates the capability to emulate standard inflation dynamics, resembling $\tilde{\phi}^4$ potential characteristics under certain conditions. At higher energy levels, the behaviour of $\tilde{\phi}$ is contingent upon the Skyrme term coupling constant $\lambda$, influencing reheating phases. The wave-like nature of fluctuations allows for energy transfer, resulting in a possibly lower reheating temperature. We also discuss the prospect of $\lambda$ changing sign during inflation, presenting a non-standard coupling dependent on the matter field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18446v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emir Syahreza Fadhilla, Bobby Eka Gunara, Agus Suroso, Ardian Nata Atmaja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Innermost stable circular orbits around a spinning black hole binary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18533v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the exact solution that describes multi-centered rotating black holes, recently discovered by Teo and Wan, we investigate the innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO) for massive particles and the circular orbit for massless particles moving around a spinning black hole binary. We assume equal masses $M_1 = M_2=m$ and equal spin angular momenta $|J_1| = |J_2|$ for both black holes. Firstly, we examine the case where two black holes are spinning in the same direction ($J_1=J_2$). We clarify that that for particles rotating in the same direction as (opposite directions to) black holes' spin, the greater the spin angular momenta of the black holes, the more the radii of the ISCO for massive particles and the circular orbit for massless particles decrease (increase). We show that distinct ISCO transitions occur for particles rotating in the same direction as the black holes in three ranges of spin angular momenta: $0&lt;J_1/m^2=J_2/m^2&lt; 0.395...$, $0.395...&lt;J_1/m^2=J_2/m^2&lt; 0.483...$, and $0.483...&lt;J_1/m^2=J_2/m^2&lt;0.5$. Conversely, particles rotating in the opposite direction to the black holes exhibit a consistent transition pattern for the case $0&lt;J_1/m^2=J_2/m^2&lt;0.5$. Secondly, we study the situation where binary black holes are spinning in opposite directions ($J_1=-J_2$). We clarify that for large (small) separations between black holes, the ISCO appears near the black hole that is spinning in the same (opposite) direction as particles' rotation. Additionally, we show that different ISCO transitions occur in the three angular momentum ranges: $0&lt;J_1/m^2=-J_2/m^2&lt; 0.160...$, $0.160...&lt;J_1/m^2=-J_2/m^2&lt; 0.467...$, and $0.467...&lt;J_1/m^2=-J_2/m^2&lt;0.5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18533v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eiki Kagohashi, Ryotaku Suzuki, Shinya Tomizawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thin accretion disk around Kerr-Sen black hole in Einstein-Maxwell-dilaton-axion gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the accretion process in a thin disk surrounding a supermassive black hole in Einstein-Maxwell-dilaton-axion gravity by using the Novikov-Thorne model. Our exploration focuses on understanding the impact of the model parameter on various physical properties of the disk. The results reveal that as the dilaton parameter $r_2$ increases, the energy flux, radiation temperature, spectra luminosity, and conversion efficiency of the disk all increase. By narrowing down the dilaton parameter range to $0\leqslant r_2\leqslant0.4$ M, we discover that in the high-frequency region, the Kerr-Sen black hole demonstrates higher energy output compared to the Kerr black hole. This facilitates a more straightforward examination of the observational results for two black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18541v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiyuan Feng, Rong-Jia Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate analytical modeling of light rays in spherically symmetric spacetimes: Applications in the study of black hole accretion disks and polarimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present new, simple analytical formulas to accurately describe light rays in spherically symmetric static spacetimes. These formulas extend those introduced by Beloborodov and refined by Poutanen for the Schwarzschild metric. Our enhanced formulas are designed to be applicable to a broader range of spacetimes, making them particularly valuable for describing phenomena around compact objects like neutron stars and black holes. As an illustration of their application, we present analytical studies of images of thin accretion disks surrounding black holes and explore their associated polarimetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18543v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Claros, Emanuel Gallo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test the Loop Quantum Gravity Theory via the Lensing Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, scholars such as Lewandowski, Ma, and Yang have successfully derived a quantum-corrected black hole model in loop quantum gravity (Phys.Rev.Lett.130.101501 (2023)), which is a modification of the Schwarzschild black hole. In this paper, we calculate the strong/weak gravitational lensing effects under the quantum-corrected black hole model, taking the supermassive black holes M87* and SgrA* as the subjects of study to explore the impact of the quantum correction parameter $\alpha$ on the positions of images and the Einstein ring. Our calculations show that in the case of strong gravitational lensing, the lensing coefficient $\bar{a}$ increases with an increase in the quantum correction parameter, while the deflection angle and the lensing coefficient $\bar{b}$ decrease with an increase in the quantum correction parameter. The quantum correction parameter $\alpha$ has a significant impact in the context of supermassive black holes. In weak gravitational lensing, the quantum correction parameter $\alpha$ plays a suppressive role. Our theoretical analysis suggests that with advancements in future astrophysical observation techniques, it might be possible to test loop quantum gravity theory using the gravitational lensing effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18606v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lai Zhao, Meirong Tang, Zhaoyi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity Detection of Gravitational Waves: Where Do We Stand?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High frequency gravitational waves (HFGWs) are predicted in various exotic scenarios involving both cosmological and astrophysical sources. These elusive signals have recently sparked the interest of a diverse community of researchers, due to the possibility of HFGW detection in the laboratory through graviton-photon conversion in strong magnetic fields. Notable examples include the redesign of the resonant cavities currently under development to detect the cosmic axion. In this work, we derive the sensitivities of some existing and planned resonant cavities to detect a HFGW background. As a concrete scenario, we consider the collective signals that originate from the merging of compact objects, such as two primordial black holes (PBHs) in the asteroid mass window. Our findings improve over existing work by explicitly discussing and quantifying the loss in the experimental reach due to the actual coherence of the source. We elucidate on the approach we adopt in relation with recent literature on the topic. Most notably, we give a recipe for the estimate of the stochastic background that focuses on the presence of the signal in the cavity at all times and showing that, in the relevant PBH mass region, the signal is dominated by coherent binary mergers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18610v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Gatti, Luca Visinelli, Michael Zantedeschi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational helicity flux density from two-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The helicity flux density is a novel quantity which characterizes the angular distribution of the helicity of radiative gravitons and it may be tested by gravitational wave experiments in the future. We derive a quadrupole formula for the helicity flux density due to gravitational radiation in the slow motion and the weak field limit. We apply the formula to the bound and unbound orbits in two-body systems and find that the total radiative helicity fluxes are always zero. However, the helicity flux density still has non-trivial dependence on the angle. We also find a formula for the total helicity flux by including all contributions of the higher multipoles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18627v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinzhuang Dong, Jiang Long, Run-Ze Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A machine-learning pipeline for real-time detection of gravitational waves from compact binary coalescences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The promise of multi-messenger astronomy relies on the rapid detection of gravitational waves at very low latencies ($\mathcal{O}$(1\,s)) in order to maximize the amount of time available for follow-up observations. In recent years, neural-networks have demonstrated robust non-linear modeling capabilities and millisecond-scale inference at a comparatively small computational footprint, making them an attractive family of algorithms in this context. However, integration of these algorithms into the gravitational-wave astrophysics research ecosystem has proven non-trivial. Here, we present the first fully machine learning-based pipeline for the detection of gravitational waves from compact binary coalescences (CBCs) running in low-latency. We demonstrate this pipeline to have a fraction of the latency of traditional matched filtering search pipelines while achieving state-of-the-art sensitivity to higher-mass stellar binary black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18661v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Marx, William Benoit, Alec Gunny, Rafia Omer, Deep Chatterjee, Ricco C. Venterea, Lauren Wills, Muhammed Saleem, Eric Moreno, Ryan Raikman, Ekaterina Govorkova, Dylan Rankin, Michael W. Coughlin, Philip Harris, Erik Katsavounidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the inconsistency of the Proca theory with non-minimal coupling to gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the degrees of freedom of the Proca theory, non-minimally coupled to gravity. In the Minkowski background, this theory propagates five degrees of freedom - a massive longitudinal mode, two massive vector ones, and two massless tensor modes. At first sight, the non-linear coupling between the metric perturbations and the vector field indicates that both longitudinal and tensor modes become strongly coupled, at the same scale. This would imply that no matter how small the photon mass is if non-minimal coupling is taken into account, gravitational waves would necessarily be strongly coupled. We show that the way out of this inconsistency is through the introduction of the disformal coupling to the metric perturbations that resemble the vector-type disformal transformations. This way, the unphysical coupling between the two types of modes can be avoided, rendering the model consistent. As a result, we show that only the longitudinal modes enter a strong coupling regime, while both tensor and transverse modes remain weakly coupled at all scales up to the Planck length. Finally, we show how this cures recently reported runaway modes in curved spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18673v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anamaria Hell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Stochastic Gravitational-wave Background in the Strong Signal Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak-signal limit is often used in estimating stochastic gravitational-wave background (SGWB) intensities. This approximation fails and the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) can be much weaker when background signals are loud compared to the detector noise. In this work, we highlight this limitation for the SGWB detection using space-borne detector networks. For the TianQin + LISA network, the SNR estimated under the weak-signal limit might be off by as large as an order of magnitude. Contour plots of SNR over the parameter spaces are also presented to indicate regions susceptible to this discrepancy. Our results suggest that DA and DB type extragalactic double white dwarfs may yield an SGWB with SNR surpassing 100 after 1 year of operation in the weak-signal-limit scenario, with a redshift-independent merger rate of about $500\,\,{\rm Mpc^{-3}\,Myr^{-1}}$. In fact, this value falls significantly below the necessary threshold. Similar influences arise for first-order phase transitions, yet pinning down parameter regions remains formidable due to model uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18709v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Cheng Liang, Zhi-Yuan Li, En-Kun Li, Jian-dong Zhang, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Dark Matter on $f$-mode oscillations of Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this study is to investigate the effect of dark matter (DM) on $f$-mode oscillations in DM admixed neutron stars (NSs). We consider hadronic matter modeled by the relativistic mean field model and the DM model based on the neutron decay anomaly. We study the non-radial $f$-mode oscillations for such DM admixed NS in a full general relativistic framework. We investigate the impact of DM, DM self-interaction, and DM fraction on the $f$-mode characteristics. We derive relations encoding the effect of DM on $f$-mode parameters. We then perform a systematic study by varying all the model parameters within their known uncertainty range and obtain a universal relation for the DM fraction based on the total mass of the star and DM self-interaction strength. We also perform a correlation study among model parameters and NS observables, in particular, $f$-mode parameters. Finally, we check the $f$-mode universal relations (URs) for the case of DM admixed NSs and demonstrate the existence of a degeneracy between purely hadronic NSs and DM admixed NSs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18740v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swarnim Shirke, Bikram Keshari Pradhan, Debarati Chatterjee, Laura Sagunski, J\"urgen Schaffner-Bielich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron Stars Mass-Radius relations analysis in the Quintessence scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18752v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the effects of General Relativity modification on the Mass-Radius relations of Neutron Stars induced by the presence of the Quintessence field. We consider, in particular, the Kiselev model, according to which the Quintessence field, being present in the entire Universe, might also be present around massive objects. Considering the Equation of State (EoS) for Baryonic matter BSk22 derived by A. Y. Potekhin et al., we infer the upper limit for NS masses in the presence of Quintessence. The presence of Quintessence generates a peculiar effect for which the Mass-Radius relation is unvaried and therefore the presence of Quintessence is indistinguishable from ordinary matter, at least for the Kiselev model studied in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18752v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Campitelli, L. Mastrototaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the Lense-Thirring precession and the neutron star moment of inertia with pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutron stars (NSs) are compact objects that host the densest forms of matter in the observable universe, providing unique opportunities to study the behaviour of matter at extreme densities. While precision measurements of NS masses through pulsar timing have imposed effective constraints on the equation of state (EoS) of dense matter, accurately determining the radius or moment of inertia (MoI) of a NS remains a major challenge. This article presents a detailed review on measuring the Lense-Thirring (LT) precession effect in the orbit of binary pulsars, which would give access to the MoI of NSs and offer further constraints on the EoS. We discuss the suitability of certain classes of binary pulsars for measuring the LT precession from the perspective of binary star evolution, and highlight five pulsars that exhibit properties promising to realise these goals in the near future. Finally, discoveries of compact binaries with shorter orbital periods hold the potential to greatly enhance measurements of the MoI of NSs. The MoI measurements of binary pulsars are pivotal to advancing our understanding of matter at supranuclear densities as well as improving the precision of gravity tests, such as the orbital decay due to gravitational wave emission and of tests of alternative gravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18785v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanchen Hu, Paulo C. C. Freire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abelian Chern-Simons term as a Kaluza-Klein dimensional reduction of the Gibbons-Hawking surface term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17977v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is suggested that the original, minimal Kaluza-Klein theory should be extended by adding a 5-dimensional version of the Gibbons-Hawking gravitational surface term. It is then demonstrated that the usual dimensional reduction of the newly added surface (boundary) term leads to the emergence of the famous Abelian Chern-Simons term. It is stressed that the advent of this Chern-Simons term is not merely a parametrization artefact but a real thing. Finally, the issue of finite-ranged electromagnetic interaction due to massive photons on a plane has been interpreted in terms of the violation of the local gauge invariance of this extended version of Kaluza-Klein theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17977v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongsu Kim, Jae Sok Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum fields on projective geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Considering homogeneous four-dimensional space-time geometries within real projective geometry provides a mathematically well-defined framework to discuss their deformations and limits without the appearance of coordinate singularities. On Lie algebra level the related conjugacy limits act isomorphically to concatenations of contractions. We axiomatically introduce projective quantum fields on homogeneous space-time geometries, based on correspondingly generalized unitary transformation behavior and projectivization of the field operators. Projective correlators and their expectation values remain well-defined in all geometry limits, which includes their ultraviolet and infrared limits. They can degenerate with support on space-time boundaries and other lower-dimensional space-time subspaces. We explore fermionic and bosonic superselection sectors as well as the irreducibility of projective quantum fields. Dirac fermions appear, which obey spin-statistics as composite quantum fields. The framework might be of use for the consistent description of quantum fields in holographic correspondences and their flat limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17996v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Spitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial alignment between jets and megamasers: coherent or selective accretion?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spins play a crucial role in the appearance, evolution and occupation fraction of massive black holes. To date observational estimates of massive black hole spins are scarce, and the assumptions commonly made in such estimates have been recently questioned. Similarly, theoretical models for massive black hole spin evolution, while reproducing the few observational constraints, are based on possibly oversimplified assumptions. New independent constraints on massive black hole spins are therefore of primary importance. We present a rigorous statistical analysis of the relative orientation of radio jets and mega-maser discs in ten low-redshift galaxies. We find a strong preference for (partial) alignment between jets and mega-masers, that can be attributed to two different causes: "coherent" and "selective" accretion. In the first case the partial alignment is due to an anisotropy in the gas reservoir fueling the growth of MBHs. In the second case the spin-dependent anisotropic feedback allows for long-lived accretion only if the orbits of the gas inflows are almost aligned to the MBH equatorial plane. A discussion of the implications of the two accretion scenarios on the evolution of MBHs is presented, together with an outlook on future observational tests aiming at discriminating between the two scenarios and at checking if any of the two apply to different redshifts and black hole mass regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo Dotti, Riccardo Buscicchio, Francesco Bollati, Roberto Decarli, Walter Del Pozzo, Alessia Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Natural Metric-Affine Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider here natural inflation in the low energy (two-derivative) metric-affine theory containing only the minimal degrees of freedom in the inflationary sector, i.e. the massless graviton and the pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone boson (PNGB). This theory contains the Ricci-like and parity-odd Holst invariants together with non-minimal couplings between the PNGB and the above-mentioned invariants. The Palatini and Einstein-Cartan realizations of natural inflation are particular cases of our construction. Explicit models of this type are shown to admit an explicit UV completion in a QCD-like theory with a Planckian confining scale. Moreover, for these models, we find regions of the parameter space where the inflationary predictions agree with the most recent observations at the $2\sigma$ level. We find that in order to enter the $1\sigma$ region it is necessary (and sufficient) to have a finite value of the Barbero-Immirzi parameter and a sizable non-minimal coupling between the inflaton and the Holst invariant (with sign opposite to the Barbero-Immirzi parameter). Indeed, in this case the potential of the canonically normalized inflaton develops a plateau as shown analytically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18004v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Racioppi, Alberto Salvio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole thermodynamics in natural variables: the BTZ case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18008v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It has been recently shown for a wide range of black hole solutions in 4 and 5 dimensions that it is useful to reorganize the conventional thermodynamics on the inner and outer horizons in terms of left- and right-moving variables. The insight of arXiv:2310.13437 regarding the split of variables was loosely inspired by the example of the BTZ black hole and the corresponding dual CFT$_2$ thermodynamics governed by the Cardy formula. Here we revisit the BTZ case and its generalizations in 3d gravity theories with higher derivative corrections, and show formally the applicability of the newly defined variables and their direct relation to the Cardy formula, which is not a priori guaranteed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18008v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiril Hristov, Riccardo Giordana Pozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On AdS$_4$ deformations of celestial symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18011v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Celestial holography has led to the discovery of new symmetry algebras arising from the study of collinear limits of perturbative gravity amplitudes in flat space. We explain from the twistor perspective how a non-vanishing cosmological constant $\Lambda$ naturally modifies the celestial chiral algebra. The cosmological constant deforms the Poisson bracket on twistor space, so the corresponding deformed algebra of Hamiltonians under the new bracket is automatically consistent. This algebra is equivalent to that recently found by Taylor and Zhu. We find a number of variations of the deformed algebra. We give the Noether charges arising from the expression of this algebra as a symmetry of the twistor action for self-dual gravity with cosmological constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18011v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Bittleston, Giuseppe Bogna, Simon Heuveline, Adam Kmec, Lionel Mason, David Skinner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rindler Fluids from Gravitational Shockwaves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a correspondence between gravitational shockwave geometry and its fluid description near a Rindler horizon in Minkowski spacetime. Utilizing the Petrov classification that describes algebraic symmetries for Lorentzian spaces, we establish an explicit mapping between a potential fluid and the shockwave metric perturbation, where the Einstein equation for the shockwave geometry is equivalent to the incompressibility condition of the fluid, augmented by a shockwave source. Then we consider an Ansatz of a stochastic quantum source for the potential fluid, which has the physical interpretation of shockwaves created by vacuum energy fluctuations. Under such circumstance, the Einstein equation, or equivalently, the incompressibility condition for the fluid, becomes a stochastic differential equation. By smearing the quantum source on a stretched horizon in a Lorentz invariant manner with a Planckian width (similarly to the membrane paradigm), we integrate fluctuations near the Rindler horizon to find an accumulated effect of the variance in the round-trip time of a photon traversing the horizon of a causal diamond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18013v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sang-Eon Bak, Cynthia Keeler, Yiwen Zhang, Kathryn M. Zurek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flows in the Space of Interacting Chiral Boson Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study interacting theories of $N$ left-moving and $\overline{N}$ right-moving Floreanini-Jackiw bosons in two dimensions. A parameterized family of such theories is shown to enjoy (non-manifest) Lorentz invariance if and only if its Lagrangian obeys a flow equation driven by a function of the energy-momentum tensor. We discuss the canonical quantization of such theories along classical stress tensor flows, focusing on the case of the root-$T \overline{T}$ deformation, where we obtain perturbative results for the deformed spectrum in a certain large-momentum limit. In the special case $N = \overline{N}$, we consider the quantum effective action for the root-$T \overline{T}$-deformed theory by expanding around a general classical background, and we find that the one-loop contribution vanishes for backgrounds with constant scalar gradients. Our analysis can also be interpreted via dual $U(1)$ Chern-Simons theories in three dimensions, which might be used to describe deformations of charged $\mathrm{AdS}_3$ black holes or quantum Hall systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18242v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Ebert, Christian Ferko, Cian Luke Martin, Gabriele Tartaglino-Mazzucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing a Theoretical Model for the Resummation of Infrared Effects in the Pre- and Post-Reconstruction Galaxy Bispectra (https://youtu.be/bHdlIi3jQ4A)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While substantial progress has been made in studying the pre-reconstruction galaxy bispectrum, investigations of the post-reconstruction bispectrum are still in nascent stages. In this paper, we present a bispectrum model that incorporates one-loop corrections in the Standard Perturbation Theory (SPT), while simultaneously addressing infrared (IR) effects in the post-reconstruction density fluctuations in a non-perturbative approach. This model accurately captures the nonlinear behavior of the Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) signal within the post-reconstruction bispectrum framework. Furthermore, the incorporation of the one-loop correction extends its applicability to smaller scales. Given that the approach to addressing IR effects remains invariant before and after the reconstruction process, the resulting IR-resummed bispectrum model exhibits uniformity across both scenarios. Throughout this analysis, we achieve a comprehensive and unified description of the bispectrum that seamlessly spans the pre- and post-reconstruction phases. An explanatory video is available at https://youtu.be/bHdlIi3jQ4A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18262v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naonori Sugiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum gravity of the Heisenberg algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18333v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a simplified model of double scaled SYK (DSSYK) in which the Hamiltonian is the position operator of the Harmonic oscillator. This model captures the high temperature limit of DSSYK but could also be defined as a quantum theory in its own right. We study properties of the emergent geometry including its dynamics in response to inserting matter particles. In particular, we find that the model displays de Sitter-like properties such as that infalling matter reduces the rate of growth of geodesic slices between the two boundaries. The simplicity of the model allows us to compute the full generating functional for correlation functions of the length mode or any number of matter operators. We provide evidence that the effective action of the geodesic length between boundary points is non-local. Furthermore, we use the on-shell solution for the geodesic lengths between any two boundary points to reconstruct an effective bulk metric and reverse engineer the dilaton gravity theory that generates this metric as a solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18333v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Almheiri, Akash Goel, Xu-Yao Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded islands in dS$_{2}$ multiverse model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmological event horizons are observer-dependent, which might bring a paradox. As an example, in dS$_{2}$ multiverse model there are entanglement islands in crunching regions encoding the information of regions near future infinity of inflating or Minkowski bubbles, however, for two observers in different bubbles, since their island regions overlap, both observers will be able to get access to the information encoded in the overlapping region, indicating a violation of no-cloning theorem. In this paper, we present a different resolution to this paradox. Based on the Petz $\mathrm{R\acute{e}nyi}$ mutual information, we show that besides the quantum extremal surfaces there might be another boundary for the island in corresponding spacetime so that the island regions are bounded by ``division points" rather than extending to the rest of the entire spacetime. We also discuss the implications of our result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18420v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Hao Jiang, Yun-Song Piao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the quantum nature of gravity using a Bose-Einstein condensate; "Erste Abhandlung"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The effect of noise induced by gravitons has been investigated using a Bose-Einstein condensate. The gravitational wave perturbation is then considerd as a sum of discrete Fourier modes in the momentum space. Coming to an operatorial representation and quantizing the phase space variables via appropriately introduced canonincal commutation relations between the canonically conjugate variables corresponding to the graviton and bosonic part of the total system, one obtains a proper quantum gravity setup. Then we obtain the Bogoliubov coefficients from the solution of the time-dependent part of the pseudo-Goldstone boson and construct the covariance metric for the bosons initially being in a squeezed state. Using the stochastic average of the Fisher information, we obtain a lower bound on the amplitude parameter of the gravitational wave. As the entire calculation is done at zero temperature, the bosonic system, by construction, will behave as a Bose-Einstein condensate. For a Bose-Einstein condensate with a single mode, we observe that the lower bound of the expectation value of the square of the uncertainty in the amplitude measurement does not become infinite when the total observational term approaches zero. In order to sum over all possible momentum modes, we next consider a noise term with a suitable Gaussian weight factor which decays over time. We then obtain the lower bound on the final expectation value of the square of the variance in the amplitude parameter. Because of the noise induced by the graviton, there is a minimum value of the measurement time below which it is impossible to detect any gravitational wave using a Bose-Einstein condensate. Finally, we consider interaction between the phonon modes of the Bose-Einstein condensate which results in a decoherence. We observe that the decoherence effect becomes significant for gravitons with minimal squeezing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18460v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Sen, Sunandan Gangopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Velocity Distribution of Dark Matter Spike around Schwarzschild Black Holes and Effects on Gravitational Waves from EMRIs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18529v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark matter (DM) constitutes the predominant portion of matter in our universe. Despite compelling evidence, the precise characteristics of DM remain elusive. Among the leading DM candidates are weakly interacting massive particles, which may aggregate into steep concentrations around the central black holes of galaxies, forming dense spikes. Employing Schwarzschild geometry, we assess the density and velocity distribution of DM within such spikes. Through variations in black hole masses and dark halo parameters, we identify universal features in the density profile of DM and fit them with Gaussian distributions. Additionally, we investigate the impact of dynamical friction on gravitational waves (GWs) generated by extreme-mass-ratio inspirals (EMRIs) within DM spikes. Our findings uncover phase shifts in the time-domain waveform, potentially providing significant insights for the GW-based detection of DM in galactic centers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18529v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Chang Zhang, Yong Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Large Scale Structures of the Universe as a Phenomenology of a Fractal Turbulence: The Role of the Plasma Component</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18759v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new perspective on the symmetries that govern the formation of large-scale structures across the Universe, particularly focusing on the transition from the seeds of galaxy clusters to the seeds of galaxies themselves. We address two main features of cosmological fluid dynamics pertaining to both the linear and non-linear regimes. The linear dynamics of cosmological perturbations within the Hubble horizon is characterized by the Jeans length, which separates stable configurations from unstable fluctuations due to the gravitational effect on sufficiently large (and therefore, massive enough) overdensities. On the other hand, the non-linear dynamics of the cosmological fluid is associated with a turbulent behavior once the Reynolds numbers reach a sufficiently high level. This turbulent regime leads to energy dissipation across smaller and smaller scales, resulting in a fractal distribution of eddies throughout physical space. The proposed scenario suggests that the spatial scale of eddy formation is associated with the Jeans length of various levels of fragmentation from an original large-scale structure. By focusing on the fragmentation of galaxy cluster seeds versus galaxy seeds, we arrived at a phenomenological law that links the ratio of the two structure densities to the number of galaxies in each cluster and to the Hausdorff number of the Universe matter distribution. Finally, we introduced a primordial magnetic field and studied its influence on the Jeans length dynamics. The resulting anisotropic behavior of the density contrast led us to infer that the main features of the turbulence could be reduced to a 2D Euler equation. Numerical simulations showed that the two lowest wavenumbers contained the major energy contribution of the spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18759v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym16030306</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry 16, 306 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Montani, Nakia Carlevaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-local quantum field theory from doubly special relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18772v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-local quantum field theories could be a solution to the inconsistencies arising when quantizing gravity. Doubly special relativity is regarded as a low-energy limit of a quantum gravity theory with testable predictions. We present a new formulation of quantum field theories in doubly special relativity with non-local behavior. Our construction restricts the models to those showing linear Lorentz invariance. The deformed Klein--Gordon, Dirac, and electromagnetic Lagrangians are derived. The deformed Maxwell equations and the electric potential of a point charge are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18772v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. J. Relancio, L. Santamar\'ia-Sanz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bouncing and collapsing universes dual to late-time cosmological models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.02835v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the Jordan frame-Einstein frame correspondence to explore dual universes with contrasting cosmological evolutions. We study the mapping between Einstein and Jordan frames where the Einstein frame universe describes the late-time evolution of the physical universe, which is driven by dark energy and non-relativistic matter. The Brans-Dicke theory of gravity is considered to be the dual scalar-tensor theory in the Jordan frame. We show that an Einstein frame universe, with cosmological evolution of the $\Lambda$CDM model, always corresponds to a bouncing Jordan frame universe governed by a Brans-Dicke theory. On the other hand, quintessence models of dark energy with non-relativistic matter component are shown to be always dual to a Brans-Dicke Jordan frame with a turn-around, i.e., a bounce or a collapse. The evolution of the equation of state of the quintessence field determines whether the turn-around is a bounce or a collapse. The point of the Jordan frame turn-around for all the cases can be tuned anywhere by choosing an appropriate Brans-Dicke parameter. This essentially leads to alternative descriptions of the late-time evolution of the physical universe, in terms of bouncing or collapsing Brans-Dicke universes in the Jordan frame. Therefore,the effect of dark energy can equivalently be seen as collapse of space in a conformally connected universe. We further study the stability of such conformal maps against linear perturbations. The effective bouncing and collapsing descriptions of the current accelerating universe may have interesting implications for the evolutions of perturbations and quantum fluctuations in the cosmological background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.02835v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12673-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 318 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dipayan Mukherjee, H. K. Jassal, Kinjalk Lochan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonexistence of quantum black and white hole horizons in an improved dynamic approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.14535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.14535v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the quantum geometric effects near the locations where classical black hole horizons used to appear in Einstein's classical theory, within the framework of an improved dynamic approach, in which the internal region of a black hole is modeled by the Kantowski-Sachs (KS) spacetime and the two polymerization parameters are functions of the phase space variables. Our detailed analysis shows that the effects are so strong that black and white hole horizons of the effective quantum theory do not exist at all and instead are replaced by transition surfaces, across which the metric coefficients and their inverses are smooth and remain finite, as are the corresponding curvatures, including the Kretschmann scalar. These surfaces always separate trapped regions from anti-trapped regions. The number of such surfaces is infinite, so the corresponding KS spacetimes become geodesically complete, and no black and white hole-like structures exist in this scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.14535v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Cong Gan, Xiao-Mei Kuang, Zhen-Hao Yang, Yungui Gong, Anzhong Wang, Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for continuous gravitational waves directed at sub-threshold radiometer candidates in O3 LIGO data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12138v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present results of a follow-up search for continuous gravitational waves (CWs) associated with sub-threshold candidates from the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) All-Sky All-Frequency (ASAF) directed radiometer analysis, using Advanced LIGO data from the third observing run (O3). Each ASAF candidate corresponds to a $1/32\,\,\mathrm{Hz}$ frequency band and ${\sim}13\,\,\mathrm{deg}^2$ sky pixel. Assuming they represent possible CW sources, we analyze all $515$ ASAF candidates using a semi-coherent, $\mathcal{F}$-statistic-based matched filter search. The search algorithm incorporates a hidden Markov model (HMM), expanding the signal model to allow frequency spin-wandering, as well as unmodeled frequency evolution of less than $10^{-5}$ Hz per day that is not captured by the searched range of $\pm10^{-9}\,\,\mathrm{Hz/s}$ in frequency derivative. Significance thresholds with a $5\%$ probability of false alarm per ASAF candidate are determined empirically by searching detector noise at various off-target sky positions. We obtain $14$ outliers surviving a set of vetoes designed to eliminate instrumental artifacts. Upon further investigation, these outliers are deemed unlikely to represent astrophysical signals. We estimate the sensitivity of our search to both isolated and binary sources with orbital period greater than one year by recovering simulated signals added to detector data. The minimum detectable strain amplitude at $95\%$ confidence for isolated (long-period binary) sources is $h_0^{95\%} = 8.8\times 10^{-26}$ ($9.4\times 10^{-26}$) at a frequency of $222.6\,\,\mathrm{Hz}$. While this study focuses on ASAF sub-threshold candidates, the method presented could be applied to follow up candidates from future all-sky CW searches, complementing currently existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12138v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.062008</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alan M. Knee, Helen Du, Evan Goetz, Jess McIver, Julian B. Carlin, Ling Sun, Liam Dunn, Lucy Strang, Hannah Middleton, Andrew Melatos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Slip parameter and Gravitational Waves in Einstein-Cartan theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02129v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the evolution of scalar and tensor cosmological perturbations in the framework of the Einstein-Cartan theory of gravity. The value of the gravitational slip parameter which is defined as the ratio of the two scalar potentials in the Newtonian gauge, can be used to determine whether or not the gravity is modified. We calculate the value of slip parameter in the Einstein-Cartan cosmology and show that it falls within the observed range. We also discuss the evolution of the cosmic gravitational waves as another measure of the modification of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02129v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12670-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 316 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Ranjbar, Siamak Akhshabi, Mohsen Shadmehri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Gravitational Waveform Model for Detecting Accelerating Inspiraling Binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04175v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an analytic frequency-domain gravitational waveform model for an inspiraling binary whose center-of-mass undergoes a small acceleration, assumed to be constant during the detection, such as when it orbits a distant tertiary mass. The center-of-mass acceleration along the line of sight is incorporated as a new parameter that perturbs the standard TaylorF2 model. We calculate the wave phase to 3rd post-Newtonian order and first order in the acceleration. It is shown that acceleration most significantly modifies the wave phase in the low frequency portion of the signal, so ground-based detectors with a good sensitivity at low frequencies are the most effective at detecting this effect. We present a Fisher information calculation to quantify the detectability of this effect at advanced LIGO A Plus, Cosmic Explorer, and Einstein Telescope over the mass range of neutron stars and stellar-mass black holes, and discuss degeneracy between acceleration and other parameters. We also determine the parameter space where the acceleration is large enough that the wave phase model would have to be extended to nonlinear orders in the acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04175v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malcolm Lazarow, Nathaniel Leslie, Liang Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameterizing black hole orbits for adiabatic inspiral</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Adiabatic binary inspiral in the small mass ratio limit treats the small body as moving along a geodesic of a large Kerr black hole, with the geodesic slowly evolving due to radiative backreaction. Up to initial conditions, geodesics are typically parameterized in two ways: using the integrals of motion energy $E$, axial angular momentum $L_z$, and Carter constant $Q$; or, using orbit geometry parameters semi-latus rectum $p$, eccentricity $e$, and (cosine of ) inclination $x_I \equiv \cos I$. The community has long known how to compute orbit integrals as functions of the orbit geometry parameters, i.e., as functions expressing $E(p, e, x_I)$, and likewise for $L_z$ and $Q$. Mappings in the other direction -- functions $p(E, L_z, Q)$, and likewise for $e$ and $x_I$ -- have not yet been developed in general. In this note, we develop generic mappings from ($E$, $L_z$, $Q$) to ($p$, $e$, $x_I$). The mappings are particularly simple for equatorial orbits ($Q = 0$, $x_I = \pm1$), and can be evaluated efficiently for generic cases. These results make it possible to more accurately compute adiabatic inspirals by eliminating the need to use a Jacobian which becomes singular as inspiral approaches the last stable orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09577v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott A. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytically Separating the Source of the Teukolsky Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00604v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent gravitational wave detections from black hole mergers have underscored the critical role black hole perturbation theory and the Teukolsky equation play in understanding the behaviour of black holes. The separable nature of the Teukolsky equation has long been leveraged to study the vacuum linear Teukolsky equation; however, as theory and measurements advance, solving the sourced Teukolsky equation is becoming a frontier of research. In particular, second-order calculations, such as in quasi-normal mode and self-force problems, have extended sources. This paper presents a novel method for analytically separating the Teukolsky equation's source, aimed to improve efficiency. Separating the source is a non-trivial problem due to the angular and radial mixing of generic quantities in Kerr spacetime. We provide a proof-of-concept demonstration of our method and show that it is accurate, separating the Teukolsky source produced by the stress-energy tensor of an ideal gas cloud surrounding a Kerr black hole. The detailed application of our method is provided in an accompanying \textit{Mathematica} notebook. Our approach opens up a new avenue for accurate black hole perturbation theory calculations with sources in both the time and frequency domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00604v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Spiers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spacetime geometry from Dirac spinor theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quintet of Dirac $4\times 4$ matrices suggests that the fundamental dimension of the internal (spin) space is $n=5$, instead of the conventional dimension $n=4$. Then extending the usual $4\times 4$ tetrads (vierbein), gravity is described in terms of the 5-bein (f\"unfbein or five legs). We discuss the properties of the spacetime geometry induced from this 5-leg Dirac spinor theory, where the spin connection contains $10\times 4=40$ elements instead of 24 elements in the tetrad formulation of the general relativity theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11593v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.064076</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109 (2024) 064076</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuri N. Obukhov, G. E. Volovik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating Fermion-Boson Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13052v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rotating fermion-boson stars are hypothetical celestial objects that consist of both fermionic and bosonic matter interacting exclusively through gravity. Bosonic fields are believed to arise in certain models of particle physics describing dark matter and could accumulate within neutron stars, modifying some of their properties and gravitational wave emission. Fermion-boson stars have been extensively studied in the static non-rotating case, exploring their combined stability and their gravitational radiation in binary mergers. However, stationary rotating configurations were yet to be found and investigated. The presence of a bosonic component could impact the development of the bar-mode instability in differentially rotating neutron stars. Therefore, the study of rotating fermion-boson stars has important implications for astrophysics, as they could provide a new avenue for the detection of gravitational waves. In addition, these objects may shed light on the behavior of matter under extreme conditions, such as those found in the cores of neutron stars, and explain any tension in the determination of the dense-matter equation of state from multi-messenger observations. In this work we study a new consistent method of constructing uniformly rotating fermion-boson stars and we analyse some of their main properties. These objects might offer alternative explanations for current observations populating the lower black-hole mass gap, as the $2.6 M_\odot$ compact object involved in GW190814.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13052v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Castelo Mourelle, Christoph Adam, Juan Calder\'on Bustillo, Nicolas Sanchis-Gual</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Bianchi-I cosmology in the Horndeski theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15158v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the evolution of Bianchi-I space-times within the framework of the Horndeski theory with $G_5=\text{const}/X$. The space-times are filled a global unidirectional electromagnetic field interacting with a scalar field. We consider the minimal interaction and the non-minimal interaction by the law $f^2(\phi)F_{\mu\nu}F^{\mu\nu}$. The Horndeski theory allows anisotropy to grow over time, so the question arises of regulating the anisotropic level in this theory. Using the reconstruction method, we build models in which the anisotropic level tends to a small value as the Universe expands. One of the results is a model with a anisotropic bounce.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15158v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruslan K. Muharlyamov, Tatiana N. Pankratyeva, Shehabaldeen O. A. Bashir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Study of Massive Compact Star Admitting Conformal Motion Under Bardeen Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17716v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article primarily investigates the existence of the charged compact star under the conformal motion treatment within the context of f(Q) gravity. We have developed two models by implementing the power-law and linear form of conformal factor, enabling an in-depth comparison in our study. We have selected the MIT Bag model equation of state to describe the connection between pressure and energy density and matched the interior spherically symmetric space-time with the Bardeen space-time. In addition, the present research examines various physically valid characteristics of realistic stars, such as PSR J1614-2230, PSR J1903+327, Vela X-1, Cen X-3, and SMC X-1. We compare two constructed models by attributing the behavior of density, pressure, equilibrium conditions, and the adiabatic index. We have additionally included a brief analysis of the scenario involving Reissner-Nordstrom spacetime as an external geometry for the matching condition. In contrast to the Reissner-Nordstrom instance, the Bardeen model with the extra term in the asymptotic representations yields a more intriguing and viable result. The current analysis reveals that the resulting compact star solutions are physically acceptable and authentic when considering the presence of charge with conformal motion in f(Q) gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17716v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2024.116523</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Physics B, 1001 (2024) 116523</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sneha Pradhan, P. K. Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric resonance in abelian and non-abelian gauge fields via space-time oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.07456v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the evolution of abelian $U(1)$ electromagnetic as well as non-abelian $SU(2)$ gauge fields, in the presence of space-time oscillations. Analysis of the time evolution of abelian gauge fields shows the presence of parametric resonance in spatial modes. A similar analysis in the case of non-abelian gauge fields, in the linear approximation, shows the presence of the same resonant spatial modes. The resonant modes induce large fluctuations in physical observables including those that break the $CP-$symmetry. We also carry out time evolution of small random fluctuations of the gauge fields, using numerical simulations in $2+1$ and $3+1$ dimensions. These simulations help to study non-linear effects in the case of non-abelian gauge theories. Our results show that there is an increase in energy density with the coupling, at late times. These results suggest that gravitational waves may excite non-abelian gauge fields more efficiently than electromagnetic fields. Also, gravitational waves in the early Universe and from the merger of neutron stars, black holes etc. may enhance $CP-$violation and generate an imbalance in chiral charge distributions, magnetic fields etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.07456v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreyansh S. Dave, Sanatan Digal, Vinod Mamale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discreteness effects in $N$-body simulations of warm dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07778v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In cosmological $N$-body simulations of warm dark matter, thermal velocities of dark-matter particles are sometimes taken into account by adding random initial velocities to the particles of simulation. However, a particle in the $N$-body system represents a huge collection of dark-matter particles, whose average thermal velocity is very close to zero. We consider justification of the procedure of adding thermal velocities in $N$-body simulations and build a simple model of their influence on the power spectrum. Our model captures the physical effect of suppression of the power spectrum at small wave numbers and also explains its artificial enhancement at large wave numbers, observed in numerical simulations with added thermal velocities. The cause of this enhancement is the disturbance of the growth rate of the density profile introduced when adding random initial thermal velocities. Specifically, the model predicts a turnover in the behavior of the simulated power spectrum at a certain wave number $k_*$, beyond which it grows as $P (k) \propto k^2$. Our treatment is generalized to a system consisting of several matter components with different thermal velocity dispersion. We also estimate the effects of discreteness related to the bulk velocity field and establish the conditions under which these effects dominate over those of thermal velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07778v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.063031</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 063031 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Shtanov, Valery I. Zhdanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strings near black holes are Carrollian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14240v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that strings near the horizon of a Schwarzschild black hole, when viewed by a stationary observer at infinity, probe a string Carroll geometry, where the effective lightspeed is given by the distance from the horizon. We expand the Polyakov action in powers of this lightspeed to find a theory of Carrollian strings. We show that the string shrinks to a point to leading order near the horizon, which follows a null geodesic in a two-dimensional Rindler space. At the next-to-leading order the string oscillates in the embedding fields associated with the near-horizon two-sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14240v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Bagchi, Aritra Banerjee, Jelle Hartong, Emil Have, Kedar S. Kolekar, Mangesh Mandlik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observables from classical black hole scattering in Scalar-Tensor theory of gravity from worldline quantum field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05492v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we compute the two observables, impulse and waveform, in a black hole scattering event for the Scalar-Tensor theory of gravity with a generic scalar potential using the techniques of Worldline Quantum Field Theory. We mainly investigate the corrections to the above mentioned observables due to the extra scalar degree of freedom. For the computation of impulse, we consider the most general scenario by making the scalar field massive and then show that each computed diagram has a smooth massless limit. We compute the waveform for scalar and graviton up to 2PM, taking the scalar as massless. Furthermore, we discuss if the scalar has mass and how the radiation integrals get more involved than the massless case. We also arrive at some analytical results using stationary phase approximation. Interestingly, we also show that the $\lambda_4 \varphi^4$ interaction vertex does not contribute to the radiation by showing that the integral has no non-zero finite value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05492v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Bhattacharyya, Debodirna Ghosh, Saptaswa Ghosh, Sounak Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of Solar Chameleons in the Earth's Magnetic Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07563v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Chameleon dark energy models are a popular alternative to the standard cosmological constant model. These models consist of a new light degree of freedom, called chameleon, with a density dependent mass and a non-trivial coupling to both matter and photons. Owing to these couplings, chameleons can be produced inside the sun. However due to their density dependent mass, the chameleons produced in the solar core are screened and cannot escape whereas those produced outside the solar core, such as in the \textit{tachocline} region with energies of the order of few a keV, can escape from the sun and travel all the way towards Earth. Hence the Earth is expected to receive a flux of \textit{solar chameleons}. In this work we propose a \textit{light shining through wall} (LSW) type of experiment in which the Earth itself acts as a wall. Both photons and chameleons are incident on the light side of the Earth. While all the photons are stopped by the Earth, only a fraction of the chameleons are stopped by the earth due to screening. Those chameleons which are not screened by the earth pass directly through the Earth and exit the night side. Here these chameleons interact with the geomagnetic field and convert into X-ray photons. A space based X-ray telescope orbiting the Earth can detect these X-ray photons, while passing through the night side, thereby acting as a detector in this LSW type experiment. We show that such a kind of setup can be complementary to other terrestrial experiments looking for chameleons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07563v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.063033</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 109, 063033 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tanmoy Kumar, Sourov Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing pure and thermal states by Landauer's principle in open systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04628v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Starting from Polchinski's thought experiment on how to distinguish between pure and thermal states, we construct a specific system to study the interaction between qubit and cavity quantum field theory (QFT) in order to provide a more operational point of view. Without imposing any restrictions on the initial states of qubit and cavity QFT, we compute the evolution of the system order by order by the perturbation method. We choose Landauer's principle, an important bound in quantum computation and quantum measurement, as the basis for the determination of the thermal state. By backtracking the initial state form, we obtain the conditions that must be satisfied by the cavity QFT: the expectation value of the annihilation operator should be zero, and the expectation value of the particle number operator should satisfy the Bose-Einstein distribution. We also discuss the difference between the thermal state and a possible alternative to the thermal state: the canonical thermal pure quantum (CTPQ) state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04628v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor bispectrum mediated by an excited scalar field during inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04617v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We calculate the tensor bispectrum mediated by an excited scalar field during inflation and find that the bispectrum peaks in the squeezed configuration, which is different from that of gravitational waves induced by enhanced curvature perturbations re-entering the horizon in the radiation-dominated era. Measuring the bispectrum provides a promising way to distinguish the stochastic gravitational-wave background generated during inflation from that generated after inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04617v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Zhang Peng, Cheng-Jun Fang, Zong-Kuan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
