<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 04:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole-neutron star mergers in Einstein-scalar-Gauss-Bonnet gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational wave observations of black hole-neutron star binaries, particularly those where the black hole has a lower mass compared to other observed systems, have the potential to place strong constraints on modifications to general relativity that arise at small curvature length scales. Here we study the dynamics of black hole-neutron star mergers in shift-symmetric Einstein-scalar-Gauss-Bonnet gravity, a representative example of such a theory, by numerically evolving the full equations of motion. We consider quasi-circular binaries with different mass-ratios that are consistent with recent gravitational wave observations, including cases with and without tidal disruption of the star, and quantify the impact of varying the coupling controlling deviations from general relativity on the gravitational wave signal and scalar radiation. We find that the main effect on the late inspiral is the accelerated frequency evolution compared to general relativity, and that--even considering Gauss-Bonnet coupling values approaching those where the theory breaks down--the impact on the merger gravitational wave signal is mild, predominately manifesting as a small change in the amplitude of the ringdown. We compare our results to current post-Newtonian calculations and find consistency throughout the inspiral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18496v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxence Corman, William E. East</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Possible Quantum Effect of Gravitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Beginning from the standard Arnowitt-Deser-Misner (ADM) formulation of general relativity we construct a tentative model of quantum gravity from the point of view of an observer with constant proper acceleration, just outside of a horizon of spacetime. In addition of producing the standard results of black-hole thermodynamics, our model makes an entirely new prediction that there is a certain upper bound for the energies of massive particles. For protons, for instance, this upper bound is around $1.1\times 10^{21}eV$. The result is interesting, because this energy is roughly of the same order of magnitude as are the highest energies ever measured for protons in cosmic rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18502v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jarmo M\"akel\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring waveforms with non-GR deviations for extreme mass-ratio inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18508v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fundamental process of detecting and examining the polarization modes of gravitational waves plays a pivotal role in enhancing our grasp on the precise mechanisms behind their generation. A thorough investigation is essential for delving deeper into the essence of gravitational waves and rigorously evaluating and validating the range of modified gravity theories. In this line of interest, a general description of black holes in theories beyond general relativity can serve a meaningful purpose where distinct deviation parameters can be mapped to solutions representing distinct theories. Employing a refined version of the deformed Kerr geometry, which is free from pathological behaviours such as unphysical divergences in the metric, we explore an extreme mass-ratio inspiral system, wherein a stellar-mass object perturbs a supermassive black hole. We compute the effects of deformation parameters on gravitational wave fluxes, orbital evolution and phase dynamics with leading order post-Newtonian corrections. With the waveform analysis, we assess the plausibility of detecting deviations from general relativity through observations facilitated by the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA), simultaneously constraining the extent of these deviations. Therefore, this analysis provides an understanding while highlighting the essential role of observations in advancing gravitational phenomena beyond general relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18508v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shailesh Kumar, Rishabh Kumar Singh, Abhishek Chowdhuri, Arpan Bhattacharyya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metric Reconstruction in Kerr Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metric reconstruction is the general problem of parameterizing GR in terms of its two ``true degrees of freedom'', e.g., by a complex scalar ``potential'' -- in practice mostly with the aim of simplifying the Einstein equation (EE) within perturbative approaches. In this paper, we re-analyze the metric reconstruction procedure by Green, Hollands, and Zimmerman (GHZ) [Class. Quant. Grav. \textbf{37}, 075001 (2020)], which is a generalization of the Chrzanowski-Cohen-Kegeles (CCK) approach. Contrary to the CCK method, that by GHZ is applicable not only to the vacuum, but also to the sourced linearized Einstein equation (EE). Our main innovation is a version of the GHZ method giving an efficient integration scheme for the initial value problem of the sourced linear EE. By iteration, our scheme gives the metric to as high an order in perturbation theory around Kerr as one might wish, in principle. At each order, the metric perturbation is a sum of a corrector, obtained by solving a triangular system of transport equations, a reconstructed piece, obtained from a Hertz potential as in the CCK approach, and an algebraically special perturbation, determined by the ADM quantities. As a by-product, we determine the precise relations between the asymptotic tail of the Hertz potential in the GHZ and CCK schemes, and the quantities relevant for gravitational radiation, namely, the energy flux, news- and memory tensors, and their associated BMS-supertranslations. We also discuss ways of transforming the metric perturbation to Lorenz gauge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18604v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Hollands, Vahid Toomani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-classical imprints on quasinormal mode spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute quasinormal mode frequencies for static limits of physical black holes -- semi-classical black hole solutions to Einstein-Hilbert gravity characterized by the finite formation time of an apparent horizon and its weak regularity. These assumptions lead to a highly constrained yet non-trivial form of the metric and components of the energy-momentum tensor near the horizon, which contain as a special case many known models of black holes. Using a two-point M-fraction approximation to construct an interpolating metric which captures the essential near-horizon and asymptotic properties of black holes, we explore a large part of the parameter space that characterizes the near-horizon geometry. We cast the perturbation problem as a discretized homogeneous eigensystem and compute the low-lying quasinormal mode frequencies for perturbations of a massless scalar field. Working in spherical symmetry, we provide rough constraints on leading and subleading deviations from the Schwarzschild solution which arise in a semi-classical setting, and demonstrate the potential for mimicking signatures of axially-symmetric geometries from a spherically-symmetric source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18631v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fil Simovic, Daniel R. Terno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life on a closed timelike curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the internal dynamics of a hypothetical spaceship traveling on a close timelike curve in a G\"{o}del-type universe. We choose the curve so that the generator of evolution in proper time is the angular momentum. Using Wigner's theorem, we prove that the energy levels internal to the spaceship must undergo spontaneous discretization. The level separation turns out to be finely tuned so that, after completing a roundtrip of the curve, all systems are back to their initial state. This implies, for example, that the memories of an observer inside the spaceship are necessarily erased by the end of the journey. More in general, if there is an increase in entropy, a Poincar\'{e} cycle will eventually reverse it by the end of the loop, forcing entropy to decrease back to its initial value. We show that such decrease in entropy is in agreement with the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis. The non-existence of time-travel paradoxes follows as a rigorous corollary of our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18640v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Gavassino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Potential and Topological Photon Spheres: A Novel Approach to Black Hole Parameter Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we anchor our analysis on the premise that the presence of a photon sphere is an intrinsic characteristic of any ultra-compact gravitational structure with spherical symmetry. Utilizing the concept of a topological photon sphere, we categorize the behaviors of diverse gravitational models based on the structure of their photon spheres. This innovative approach enables us to define boundaries for black hole parameters, which subsequently allows us to classify the model as either a black hole or a naked singularity. Indeed, we will demonstrate that the existence of this reciprocal relationship between the gravitational structure and the presence of a photon sphere offers a unique advantage that can be directly and inversely harnessed. Furthermore, we present a precise correlation between the behavior of the defined effective potential and the total topological charge for each model. Through an independent examination of the effective potential, we show that a gravitational model typically exhibits naked singularity behavior when at least one effective potential minimum (a stable photon sphere) protrudes beyond the event horizon. Finally, we will compare the effect of adding perfect fluid dark matter to the models under study and observe the impact of this quantity on the behavior of the photon sphere and the extent of their dominance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18798v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jafar Sadeghi, Mohammad Ali S. Afshar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical States and Transition Amplitudes in Piecewise Flat Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18893v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how the path integral for gravity and matter on a piecewise flat spacetime can be used to define the physical quantum gravity states and the related transition amplitudes. The physical states are given by the path integrals for open manifolds from a certain topological class, while the corresponding transition amplitudes are obtained by gluing two such open manifolds into a closed one and calculating the corresponding path integral. We also solve the problem of how to associate a quantum gravity state to an effective action. This is done by using the path integral for a closed manifold from the transition-amplitude topological class so that the state which corresponds to the effective action can be choosen to be the Hartle-Hawking or the Vilenkin wavefunction for the vacuum manifold component of the transition-amplitude manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18893v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandar Mikovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a computationally-efficient follow-up pipeline for blind continuous gravitational-wave searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18934v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sensitivity of continuous gravitational-wave (CW) searches for unknown neutron stars (NSs) is limited by their parameter space breadth. To fit within reasonable computing budgets, hierarchical schemes are used to identify interesting candidates using affordable methods. The resulting sensitivity critically depends on the number of candidates selected to follow-up. In this work, we present a novel framework to evaluate the effectiveness of stochastic CW follow-ups. Our results in realistic datasets allow for a ten-fold reduction of the computing cost of pyfstat, a well-established follow-up method. We also simplify the setup of multi-stage follow-ups by removing the need for parameter-space metrics. The study was conducted on Gaussian and real O3 Advanced LIGO data using realistic durations, and covered both isolated and binary sources. These results will have a positive impact on the sensitivity of all-sky searches in the forthcoming observing runs of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA collaboration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18934v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Mirasola, Rodrigo Tenorio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing eccentric corrections to the radiation-reaction force in the test-mass limit of effective-one-body models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we test an effective-one-body radiation-reaction force for eccentric planar orbits of a test mass in a Kerr background, which contains third-order post-Newtonian (PN) non-spinning and second-order PN spin contributions. We compare the analytical fluxes connected to two different resummations of this force, truncated at different PN orders in the eccentric sector, with the numerical fluxes computed through the use of frequency- and time-domain Teukolsky-equation codes. We find that the different PN truncations of the radiation-reaction force show the expected scaling in the weak gravitational-field regime, and we observe a fractional difference with the numerical fluxes that is $&lt;5 \%$, for orbits characterized by eccentricity $0 \le e \le 0.7$, central black-hole spin $-0.99 M \le a \le 0.99 M$ and fixed orbital-averaged quantity $x=\langle M\Omega \rangle^{2/3} = 0.06$, corresponding to the mildly strong-field regime with semilatera recta $9 M&lt;p&lt;17 M$. Our analysis provides useful information for the development of spin-aligned eccentric models in the comparable-mass case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19006v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guglielmo Faggioli, Maarten van de Meent, Alessandra Buonanno, Aldo Gamboa, Mohammed Khalil, Gaurav Khanna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apparent horizon tracking in supercritical solutions of the Einstein-scalar field equations in spherical symmetry in affine-null coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Choptuik's critical phenomena in general relativity is revisited in the affine-null metric formulation of Einstein's equations for a massless scalar field in spherical symmetry. Numerical solutions are obtained by evolution of initial data using pseudo-spectral methods. The underlying system consists of differential equations along the outgoing null rays which can be solved in sequential form. A new two-parameter family of initial data is presented for which these equations can be integrated analytically. Specific choices of the initial data parameters correspond to either an asymptotically flat null cone, a black hole event horizon or the singular interior of a black hole. Our main focus is on the interior features of a black hole, for which the affine-null system is especially well adapted. We present both analytic and numerical results describing the geometric properties of the apparent horizon and final singularity. Using a re-gridding technique for the affine parameter, numerical evolution of initially asymptotically flat supercritical data can be continued inside the event horizon and track the apparent horizon up to the formation of the final singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19122v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas M\"adler, Olaf Baake, Hamideh Hosseini, Jeffrey Winicour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-Minkowskian Theory Meets the Spinning Effective-One-Body Approach for Bound-Orbit Waveforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Driven by advances in scattering amplitudes and worldline-based methods, recent years have seen significant progress in our ability to calculate gravitational two-body scattering observables. These observables effectively encapsulate the gravitational two-body problem in the weak-field and high-velocity regime (post-Minkowskian, PM), with applications to the bound two-body problem and gravitational-wave modeling. We leverage PM data to construct a complete inspiral-merger-ringdown waveform model for non-precessing spinning black holes within the effective-one-body (EOB) formalism: SEOBNR-PM. This model is closely based on the highly successful SEOBNRv5 model, used by the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Collaboration, with its key new feature being an EOB Hamiltonian derived by matching the two-body scattering angle in a perturbative PM expansion. The model performs remarkably well, showing a median mismatch against 441 numerical-relativity (NR) simulations that is somewhat lower than a similarly calibrated version of SEOBNRv5. Comparisons of the binding energy with NR also demonstrate better agreement than SEOBNRv5, despite the latter containing additional calibration to NR simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19181v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandra Buonanno, Gustav Mogull, Raj Patil, Lorenzo Pompili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass formulas for supergravity black holes with string singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the derivation of mass formulas for stationary axisymmetric asymptotically locally flat solutions with string singularities on the polar axis to general supergravity actions containing vector and scalar fields. It is based on the rod structure of the solutions in Weyl coordinates and is applicable to black holes with Dirac and Misner strings. The obtained formulas differ from the corresponding ones in Einstein-Maxwell theory only by summation over all independent electric charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19196v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Bogush, Dmitri Gal'tsov, G\'erard Cl\'ement</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the theory of relativistic Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The approach to the theory of a relativistic random process is considered by the path integral method as Brownian motion taking into account the boundedness of speed. An attempt was made to build a relativistic analogue of the Wiener measure as a weak limit of finite-difference approximations. A formula has been proposed for calculating the probability particle transition during relativistic Brownian motion. Calculations were carried out by three different methods with identical results. Along the way, exact and asymptotic formulas for the volume of some parts and sections of an N-1-dimensional unit cube were obtained. They can have independent value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19282v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>p-Adic Numbers, Ultrametric Analysis and Applications 16 (2024) 2</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. A. Kurianovich, A. I. Mikhailov, I. V. Volovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology Based on Finsler and Finsler-like Metric Structure of Gravitational Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we review some aspects of gravitational field and cosmology based on Finsler and Finsler-like generalized metric structures. The geometrical framework of these spaces allows further investigation of locally-anisotropic phenomena related to the gravitational field and cosmological considerations, e.g the extracted geodesics, deflection of light, Finsler-Einstein gravitational field equations , the Friedmann equations and the Raychaudhuri equations include extra anisotropic terms that in the Riemannian framework of General Relativity (GR) are not interpreted. This approach gives us the opportunity to extend the research with more degrees of freedom on the tangent bundle of a spacetime manifold. In the above mentioned generalizations omitting the extra anisotropic terms we recover the framework of GR. In addition, we study the gravitational Magnus effect in a generalized metric framework.
  Based on this approach, we describe further properties of Finsler-Randers (FR) and Schwarzschild Finsler Randers (SFR) cosmological models which are useful for the description and evolution of the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19318v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. C. Stavrinos, A. Triantafyllopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shedding Light on Dark Sectors with Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The nature of dark matter remains one of the greatest unsolved mysteries in elementary particle physics. It might well be that the dark matter particle belongs to a dark sector completely secluded or extremely weakly coupled to the visible sector. We demonstrate that gravitational waves arising from first order phase transitions in the early Universe can be used to look for signatures of such dark sector models connected to neutron physics. This introduces a new connection between gravitational wave physics and nuclear physics experiments. Focusing on two particular extensions of the Standard Model with dark U(1) and SU(2) gauge groups constructed to address the neutron lifetime puzzle, we show how those signatures can be searched for in future gravitational wave and astrometry experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17851v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nelleke Bunji, Bartosz Fornal, Kassandra Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Braneworlds: Cosmology and Wormholes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18465v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct 4D flat Big Bang-Big Crunch cosmologies and Anti-de Sitter (AdS) planar eternally traversable wormholes using braneworlds embedded in asymptotically AdS${}_5$ spacetimes. The background geometries are the AdS${}_5$ magnetic black brane and the magnetically charged AdS${}_5$ soliton, respectively. The two setups arise from different analytic continuations of the same saddle of the gravitational Euclidean path integral, in which the braneworld takes the form of a Maldacena-Maoz Euclidean wormhole. We show the existence of a holographic dual description of this setup in terms of a microscopic Euclidean boundary conformal field theory (BCFT) on a strip. By analyzing the BCFT Euclidean path integral, we show that the braneworld cosmology is encoded in a pure excited state of a CFT dual to a black brane microstate, whereas the braneworld wormhole is encoded in the ground state of the BCFT. The latter confines in the IR, and we study its confining properties using holography. We also comment on the properties of bulk reconstruction in the two Lorentzian pictures and their relationship via double analytic continuation. This work can be interpreted as an explicit, doubly-holographic realization of the relationship between cosmology, traversable wormholes, and confinement in holography, first proposed in arXiv:2102.05057, arXiv:2203.11220.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18465v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Antonini, Luis Gabriel C. Bariuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Time in Hamiltonian General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18486v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce a definition of time that emerges in terms of the geometry of the configuration space of a dynamical system. We illustrate this, using the Hamilton-Jacobi equation, in various examples: particle mechanics on a fixed energy surface; non-Abelian gauge theories for compact semi-simple Lie groups where the Gauss law presents new features; and General Relativity in $d+1$ dimensions with $d$ the dimension of space. The discussion in General Relativity is like the non-abelian gauge theory case except for the indefiniteness of the de Witt metric in the Einstein-Hamilton-Jacobi equation, which we discuss in some detail. We illustrate the general formula for the emergent time in various examples including de Sitter spacetime and asymptotically AdS spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18486v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anurag Kaushal, Naveen S. Prabhakar, Spenta R. Wadia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI Constraints on Exponential Quintessence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The DESI collaboration have recently analyzed their first year of data, finding a preference for thawing dark energy scenarios when using parameterized equations of state for dark energy. We investigate whether this preference persists when the data is analyzed within the context of a well-studied field theory model of thawing dark energy, exponential quintessence. No preference for this model over $\Lambda$CDM is found, and both models are poorer fits to the data than the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder $w_0$--$w_a$ parameterization. We demonstrate that the worse fit is due to a lack of sharp features in the potential that results in a slowly-evolving dark energy equation of state that does not have enough freedom to simultaneously fit the combination of the supernovae, DESI, and cosmic microwave background data. Our analysis provides guidance for constructing dynamical dark energy models that are able to better accommodate the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18747v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar F. Ramadan, Jeremy Sakstein, David Rubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum gravity signatures in gravitational wave detectors placed inside a harmonic trap potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18868v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we consider a general gravitational wave detector of gravitational wave interacting with an incoming gravitational wave carrying plus polarization only placed inside a harmonic trap. This model can be well acquainted with the description of a resonant detector of gravitational wave as well. The well known detector-gravitational wave interaction scenario uses the method of a semi classical approach where the detector is treated quantum mechanically but the gravitational wave is considered at a classical level. In our analysis, we use a discrete mode decomposition of the gravitational wave perturbation which results in a Hamiltonian involving the position and momentum operators corresponding to the gravitational wave and the harmonic oscillator. We have then calculated the transition probability for the harmonic oscillator-gravitational wave tensor product state for going from an initial state to some unknown final state. Using the energy flux relation of the gravitational waves, we observe that if we consider the total energy as a combination of the number of gravitons in the initial state of the detector then the transition probability for the resonant absorption case scenario takes the analytical form which is exactly similar to the semi-classical absorption case. In case of the emission scenario, we observe a spontaneous emission of a single graviton which was completely absent in the semi-classical analouge of this model. This therefore gives a direct signature of linearized quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18868v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Sen, Sunandan Gangopadhyay, Sukanta Bhattacharyya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent cosmological inference post DESI DR1 BAO measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19178v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we implement Gaussian process regression to reconstruct the expansion history of the universe in a model-agnostic manner, using the Pantheon-Plus SN-Ia compilation in combination with two different BAO measurements (SDSS-IV and DESI DR1). In both the reconstructions, the $\Lambda$CDM model is always included in the 95\% confidence intervals. We find evidence that the DESI LRG data at $z_{\text{eff}} = 0.51$ is not an outlier within our model-independent framework. We study the $\mathcal{O}m$-diagnostics and the evolution of the total equation of state (EoS) of our universe, which hint towards the possibility of a quintessence-like dark energy scenario with a very slowly varying EoS, and a phantom-crossing in higher $z$. The entire exercise is later complemented by considering two more SN-Ia compilations - DES-5YR and Union3 - in combination with DESI BAO. Reconstruction with the DESI BAO + DES-5YR SN data sets predicts that the $\Lambda$CDM model lies outside the 3$\sigma$ confidence levels, whereas with DESI BAO + Union3 data, the $\Lambda$CDM model is always included within 1$\sigma$. We also report constraints on $H_0 r_d$ from our model-agnostic analysis, independent of the pre-recombination physics. Our results point towards an $\approx$ 2$\sigma$ discrepancy between the DESI + Pantheon-Plus and DESI + DES-5YR data sets, which calls for further investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19178v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Purba Mukherjee, Anjan Ananda Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark matter admixed neutron stars with a realistic nuclear equation of state from chiral nuclear interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the effects of dark matter on the structural properties of neutron stars. In particular we investigate how the presence of a dark matter component influences the mass-radius relation, the value of the maximum mass of a neutron star and others stellar properties. To model ordinary matter we use a state-of-the-art equation of state of $\beta$-stable nuclear matter obtained using the Brueckner-Hartree-Fock quantum many-body approach starting from two-body and three-body nuclear interactions derived from chiral effective field theory. The dark matter component of the star is modeled as a non-self-annihilating system of spin $1/2$ fermions and its equation of state as an ideal relativistic Fermi gas. The equilibrium configurations of these dark matter admixed neutron stars (DANS) are calculated by solving a generalization of the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff equations to the case where the system consists of two perfect fluids interacting solely through gravity. We find that, depending on the dark matter particle mass $m_\chi$, one can have somehow opposite effects on the stellar properties. In the case $m_\chi = 1\, \mathrm{GeV}$, the stellar gravitational maximum mass $M_{max}$ decreases, whereas in the case $m_\chi = 0.1\, \mathrm{GeV}$, $M_{max}$ increases with respect to the maximum mass of ordinary neutron stars. We also show that the presence of dark matter has indirect sizeable effect on the proton fraction in the ordinary matter fluid and, in the case $m_\chi = 1\, \mathrm{GeV}$, results in a decrease of the threshold gravitational mass $M_{tot}^{durca}$ for having direct URCA processes and fast stellar cooling. Finally we study the stability of dark matter admixed neutron stars with respect to radial perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19251v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenico Scordino, Ignazio Bombaci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early universe in quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.06384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.06384v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new picture of the early universe in finite nonlocal quantum gravity, which is conformally invariant at the classical and quantum levels. The high-energy regime of the theory consists of two phases, a conformally invariant trans-Planckian phase and a post-Planckian or Higgs phase described by an action quadratic in the Ricci tensor and where the cosmos evolves according to the standard radiation-dominated model. In the first phase, all the issues of the hot big bang such as the singularity, flatness, and horizon problems find a universal and simple non-inflationary solution by means of Weyl (or scale, or conformal) invariance, regardless of the microscopic details of the theory. In the second phase, once conformal symmetry is spontaneously broken, primordial perturbations are generated around a background that asymptotically evolves as a radiation-dominated flat Friedmann--Lema\^{i}tre--Robertson--Walker universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.06384v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Modesto, Gianluca Calcagni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing quantum gravity with primordial gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.07066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.07066v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a testable alternative to inflation directly built in a very general class of ultraviolet complete theories of quantum gravity enjoying Weyl conformal invariance. After the latter is spontaneously broken, logarithmic quantum corrections to the action make both the primordial tensor spectrum (from graviton fluctuations) and the scalar spectrum (from thermal fluctuations) quasi scale invariant. We predict a scalar spectral index $n_{\rm s}$ which only depends on two parameters and is consistent with observations, a tensor index $n_{\rm t} =1-n_{\rm s}&gt;0$, a tensor-to-scalar ratio $r_{0.05}\approx 0.01$ detectable by BICEP Array and LiteBIRD in the immediate or near future, respectively, and a blue-tilted stochastic gravitational-wave background observable by DECIGO in the further future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.07066v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Calcagni, Leonardo Modesto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Bulk Rheology: From Neutron Star Mergers to Viscous Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.04119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.04119v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop the first causal and stable theory of a bulk-viscous relativistic pseudoplastic (or dilatant) fluid. This new formalism brings to light the rheological properties of several relativistic physical systems. Neutron star collisions can behave as a relativistic pseudoplastic material with viscous properties dictated by the non-conservation of lepton currents due to weak decay. Two-temperature relativistic plasmas, such as those surrounding supermassive galactic black holes, are predominantly pseudoplastic. Our framework can also be employed to construct novel viscous models for the evolution of the Universe with pseudoplastic or dilatant features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.04119v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.096040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 096040 (May 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Gavassino, Jorge Noronha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volume Singularities in General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16995v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new notion of singularity in General Relativity which complements the usual notions of geodesic incompleteness and curvature singularities. Concretely, we say that a spacetime has a volume singularity if there exist points whose future or past has arbitrarily small spacetime volume: in particular, smaller than a Planck volume. From a cosmological perspective, we show that the (geodesic) singularities predicted by Hawking's theorem are also volume singularities. In the black hole setting, we show that volume singularities are always hidden by an event horizon, prompting a discussion of Penrose's cosmic censorship conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16995v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11005-024-01814-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lett. Math. Phys. 114, 71 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Garc\'ia-Heveling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal Forces in Kerr-AdS and Grey Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14672v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a recent paper [arXiv:2305.08922], it has been proposed that the endpoint of the Kerr-AdS superradiant instability is a Grey Galaxy. The conjectured solutions are supposed to be made up of a black hole with critical angular velocity in the centre of AdS, surrounded by a large flat disk of thermal bulk gas that revolves around the black hole. In the analysis of the proposed solutions so far, gravitational effects due to the black hole on the thermal gas have been neglected. A way to estimate these effects is via computing tidal forces. With this motivation, we study tidal forces on objects moving in the Kerr-AdS spacetime. To do so, we construct a parallel-transported orthonormal frame along an arbitrary timelike or null geodesic. We then specialise to the class of fast rotating geodesics lying in the equatorial plane, and estimate tidal forces on the gas in the Grey Galaxies, modelling it as a collection of particles moving on timelike geodesics. We show that the tidal forces are small (and remain small even in the large mass limit), thereby providing additional support to the idea that the gas is weakly interacting with the black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14672v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad494b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quantum Grav. 41 125008 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anand Balivada, Pius Ranjan Padhi, Amitabh Virmani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement from superradiance and rotating quantum fluids of light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16031v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The amplification of radiation by superradiance is a universal phenomenon observed in numerous physical systems. We demonstrate that superradiant scattering generates entanglement for different input states, including coherent states, thereby establishing the inherently quantum nature of this phenomenon. To put these concepts to the test, we propose a novel approach to create horizonless ergoregions, which are nonetheless dynamically stable thanks to the dissipative dynamics of a polaritonic fluid of light. We numerically simulate the system to demonstrate the creation of a stable ergoregion. Subsequently, we investigate rotational superradiance within this system, with a primary focus on entanglement generation and the possibilities for its enhancement using current techniques. Our methods permit the investigation of quantum emission by rotational superradiance in state-of-the-art experiments, in which the input state can be controlled at will.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16031v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.105024</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Adri\`a Delhom, Killian Guerrero, Paula Calizaya, K\'evin Falque, Alberto Bramati, Anthony J. Brady, Maxime J. Jacquet, Ivan Agullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclidean self-dual gravity: Ashtekar variables without gauge fixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12947v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Gotay-Nester-Hinds method is used in this paper to study the Hamiltonian formulation of the Euclidean self-dual action. This action can be used to arrive at the complex Ashtekar formulation of General Relativity or a real connection formulation for Euclidean General Relativity. The main result of the paper is a derivation of the Ashtekar formulation for Euclidean gravity without using any gauge fixing. It is interesting to compare this derivation with the one corresponding to the Holst action. In particular it is worth noting that no ``tertiary'' constraints appear in the case considered in the present paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12947v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.064047</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D, 109 (2024) 064047</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Fernando Barbero G., Marc Basquens, Eduardo J. S. Villase\~nor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Signal Extraction Against Non-Stationary Instrumental Noises with Deep Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13091v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sapce-borne gravitational wave antennas, such as LISA and LISA-like mission (Taiji and Tianqin), will offer novel perspectives for exploring our Universe while introduce new challenges, especially in data analysis. Aside from the known challenges like high parameter space dimension, superposition of large number of signals and etc., gravitational wave detections in space would be more seriously affected by anomalies or non-stationarities in the science measurements. Considering the three types of foreseeable non-stationarities including data gaps, transients (glitches), and time-varying noise auto-correlations, which may come from routine maintenance or unexpected disturbances during science operations, we developed a deep learning model for accurate signal extractions confronted with such anomalous scenarios. Our model exhibits the same performance as the current state-of-the-art models do for the ideal and anomaly free scenario, while shows remarkable adaptability in extractions of coalescing massive black hole binary signal against all three types of non-stationarities and even their mixtures. This also provide new explorations into the robustness studies of deep learning models for data processing in space-borne gravitational wave missions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13091v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Xu, Minghui Du, Peng Xu, Bo Liang, He Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General properties of the electric Penrose process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12879v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the Penrose process with the charged particles in the Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m (RN) background. Let parent particle 0 decay to particles 1 and 2. With the assumption that all three particles move in the equatorial plane, the exact formulas for characteristics of particles 1 and 2 in terms of those of particle 0 are derived. We concentrate on scenarios in which particle 1 and 2 are ejected along the trajectory of particle 0. It is shown that such scenarios correspond to the extrema of energies $E_{1}$ or $E_{2}$ of daughter particles with respect to the angular momentum $L_{1}$ or $L_{2}$. We derive bounds on the values of angular momenta $L_{1}$ and $% L_{2}$. We give classification of these scenarios and discuss their properties including decay in the near-horizon region. We find that the maximum of efficiency is achieved on the horizon for some of these scenarios but not for all of them and with additional constraints on particle parameters. The results are reformulated in terms of velocities of daughter particles in the center of mass frame. The approach is applicable also to collisional Penrose process, in which a combination of particles 1 and 2 is considered as one effective particle. If the mass of particle 0 $% m_{0}\rightarrow \infty $, the situation corresponds to the Ba\~{n}% ados-Silk-West effect, the results agree with the ones known in literature before. In addition, we consider special cases when decay occurs in the turning point for one or all three particles. The formalism developed in this work has a model-independent character and applies not only to the RN metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12879v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. B. Zaslavskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graviton-Photon Oscillations as a Probe of Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01407v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Gertsenshtein effect could in principle be used to detect a single graviton by firing it through a region filled with a constant magnetic field that enables its conversion to a photon, which can be efficiently detected via standard techniques. The quantization of the gravitational field could then be inferred indirectly. We show that for currently available single-photon detector technology, the Gertsenshtein detector is generically inefficient, meaning that the probability of detection is $\ll 1$. The Gertsenshtein detector can become efficient on astrophysical scales for futuristic single-photon detectors sensitive to frequencies in the Hz to kHz range. It is not clear whether such devices are in principle possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01407v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Palessandro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Sets and an Emerging Continuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14059v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Causal set theory offers a simple and elegant picture of discrete physics. But the vast majority of causal sets look nothing at all like continuum spacetimes, and must be excluded in some way to obtain a realistic theory. I describe recent results showing that almost all non-manifoldlike causal sets are, in fact, very strongly suppressed in the gravitational path integral. This does not quite demonstrate the emergence of a continuum -- we do not yet understand the remaining unsuppressed causal sets well enough -- but it is a significant step in that direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14059v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Carlip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid detection of gravitational waves from binary black hole mergers using sparse dictionary learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17721v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current gravitational wave (GW) detection pipelines for compact binary coalescence based on matched-filtering have reported over 90 confident detections during the first three observing runs of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) detector network. Decreasing the latency of detection, in particular for future detectors anticipated to have high detection rates, remains an ongoing effort. In this paper, we develop and test a sparse dictionary learning (SDL) algorithm for the rapid detection of GWs. We evaluate the algorithms biases and estimate its GW detection rate for an astrophysical population of binary black holes. The SDL algorithm is assessed using both, simulated data injected into the proposed A+ detector sensitivity and real data containing confident detections from the third LVK observing run. We find that our SDL algorithm can reconstruct a single binary black hole signal in less than 1 s. This suggests that SDL could be regarded as a promising approach for rapid, efficient GW detection in future observing runs of ground-based detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17721v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Badger, Rahul Srinivasan, Alejandro Torres-Forn\'e, Marie Anne Bizouard, Jos\'e A. Font, Mairi Sakellariadou, Astrid Lamberts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homological aspects of topological gauge-gravity equivalence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.01672v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the works of A. Ach\'ucarro and P. K. Townsend and also by E. Witten, a duality between three-dimensional Chern-Simons gauge theories and gravity was established. In all cases, the results made use of the field equations. In a previous work, we were capable to generalize Witten's work to the off-shell cases, as well as to four dimensional Yang-Mills theory with de Sitter gauge symmetry. The price we paid is that curvature and torsion must obey some constraints under the action of the interior derivative. These constraints implied on the partial breaking of diffeomorphism invariance. In the present work, we, first, formalize our early results in terms of fiber bundle theory by establishing the formal aspects of the map between a principal bundle (gauge theory) and a coframe bundle (gravity) with partial breaking of diffeomorphism invariance. Then, we study the effect of the constraints on the homology defined by the interior derivative. The main result is the emergence of a nontrivial homology in Riemann-Cartan manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.01672v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0129055X24500284</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Thiago S. Assimos, Rodrigo F. Sobreiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Uncertainty Principle and Classical Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.07556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.07556v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the variance in the measurement of observables during scattering events, as computed using amplitudes. The classical regime, characterised by negligible uncertainty, emerges as a consequence of an infinite set of relationships among multileg, multiloop amplitudes in a momentum-transfer expansion. We discuss two non-trivial examples in detail: the six-point tree and the five-point one-loop amplitudes in scalar QED. We interpret these relationships in terms or a coherent exponentiation of radiative effects in the classical limit which generalises the eikonal formula, and show how to recover the impulse, including radiation reaction, from this generalised eikonal. Finally, we incorporate the physics of spin into our framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.07556v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cristofoli, Riccardo Gonzo, Nathan Moynihan, Donal O'Connell, Alasdair Ross, Matteo Sergola, Chris D. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete analysis of the background and anisotropies of scalar-induced gravitational waves: primordial non-Gaussianity $f_{\mathrm{NL}}$ and $g_{\mathrm{NL}}$ considered</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07792v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Investigation of primordial non-Gaussianity holds immense importance in testing the inflation paradigm and shedding light on the physics of the early Universe. In this study, we conduct the complete analysis of scalar-induced gravitational waves (SIGWs) by incorporating the local-type non-Gaussianity $f_{\mathrm{NL}}$ and $g_{\mathrm{NL}}$. We develop Feynman-like diagrammatic technique and derive semi-analytic formulas for both the energy-density fraction spectrum and the angular power spectrum. For the energy-density fraction spectrum, we analyze all the relevant Feynman-like diagrams, determining their contributions to the spectrum in an order-by-order fashion. As for the angular power spectrum, our focus lies on the initial inhomogeneities, giving rise to anisotropies in SIGWs, that arise from the coupling between short- and long-wavelength modes due to primordial non-Gaussianity. Our analysis reveals that this spectrum exhibits a typical multipole dependence, characterized by $\tilde{C}_{\ell}\propto[\ell(\ell+1)]^{-1}$, which plays a crucial role in distinguishing between different sources of gravitational waves. Depending on model parameters, significant anisotropies can be achieved. We also show that the degeneracies in model parameters can be broken. The findings of our study underscore the angular power spectrum as a robust probe for investigating primordial non-Gaussianity and the physics of the early Universe. Moreover, our theoretical predictions can be tested using space-borne gravitational-wave detectors and pulsar timing arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07792v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Peng Li, Sai Wang, Zhi-Chao Zhao, Kazunori Kohri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting primordial black holes formation from preheating instabilities: the case of Starobinsky inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02754v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, the formation of primordial black holes (PBH) in the early universe inflationary cosmology has garnered significant attention. One plausible scenario for primordial black hole (PBH) formation arises during the preheating stage following inflation. Notably, this scenario does not necessitate any ad-hoc fine-tuning of the scalar field potential. This paper focuses on the growth of primordial density perturbation and the consequent possibility of PBH formation in the preheating stage of the Starobinsky model for inflation. The typical mechanism for PBH formation during preheating is based on the collapse of primordial fluctuations that become super-horizon during inflation (type I) and re-enter the particle horizon in the different phases of cosmic expansion. In this work, we show that there exists a certain range of modes that remain in the sub-horizon (not exited) during inflation (type II modes) but evolve identically to type I modes if they fall into the instability band, leading to large density perturbation above the threshold and can potentially also contribute to the PBH formation. We detail the conditions determining the possible collapse of type I and/or type II modes whose wavelengths are larger than the Jeans length we derive from the effective sound speed of scalar field fluctuations. Since the preheating stage is an 'inflaton' (approximately) matter-dominated phase, we follow the framework of the critical collapse of fluctuations and compute the mass fraction using the well-known Press-Schechter and the Khlopov-Polnarev formalisms, and compare the two. Finally, we comment on the implications of our study for the investigations concerned with primordial accretion and consequent PBH contribution to the dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02754v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel del-Corral, Paolo Gondolo, K. Sravan Kumar, Jo\~ao Marto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Holographic Entanglement Entropy at Spi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16056v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Defining finite entanglement entropy for a subregion in quantum field theory requires the introduction of two logically independent scales: an IR scale that controls the size of the subregion, and a UV cut-off. In AdS/CFT, the IR scale is the AdS lengthscale, the UV cut-off is the bulk radial cut-off, and the subregion is specified by dimensionless angles. This is the data that determines Ryu-Takayanagi surfaces and their areas in AdS/CFT. We argue that in asymptotically flat space there exists the notion of a ``spi-subregion" that one can associate to spatial infinity (spi). Even though geometrically quite different from an AdS subregion, this angle data has the crucial feature that it allows an interpretation as a bi-partitioning of spi. Therefore, the area of the RT surface associated to the spi-subregion can be interpreted as the entanglement entropy of the reduced density matrix of the bulk state under this bi-partition, as in AdS/CFT. For symmetric spi-subregions, these RT surfaces are the waists of Asymptotic Causal Diamonds. In empty flat space they reduce to Rindler horizons, and are analogues of the AdS-Rindler horizons of Casini, Huerta \&amp; Myers. We connect these results to previous work on minimal surfaces anchored to screens in empty space, but also generalize the discussion to the case where there are black holes in the bulk. The phases of black hole RT surfaces as the spi-subregion is varied, naturally connect with those of black holes (small and large) in AdS. A key observation is that the radial cut-off is associated to an IR scale in flat space -- and in fact there are no UV divergences. We argue that this is consistent with previous suggestions that in sub-AdS scales the holographic duality is an IR/IR correspondence and that the degrees of freedom are {\em not} those of a local QFT, but those of long strings. Strings are of course, famously UV finite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16056v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abir Ghosh, Chethan Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interface Dynamics of Strongly interacting Binary Superfluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09189v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the interface dynamics in non-equilibrium quantum systems remains a challenge. We study the interface dynamics of strongly coupled immiscible binary superfluids by using holographic duality. The full nonlinear evolution of the binary superfluids with a relative velocity shows rich nonlinear patterns toward quantum turbulence, which is reminiscent of the quantum Kelvin-Helmholtz instability. The wave number of the fast growing modes $k_0$ extracted from the interface pattern yields a non-monotonic dependence of the relative velocity, independent of the temperature and interaction. The value of $k_0$ first increases with the velocity difference and then decreases, which stands in sharp contrast to the results of mean-field theory described by the Gross-Pitaevskii equation and is confirmed by using the linear analyses on top of the stationary configuration. We uncover that the critical velocity associated with the maximum correspond to the case when the mean separation of vortices generated by interface instabilities becomes comparable to the vortex size, which could be a universal physical mechanism at strongly interacting superfluids and is directly testable in laboratory experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09189v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.106022</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Ping An, Li Li, Chuan-Yin Xia, Hua-Bi Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical solution of black hole information paradox</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05617v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We resolve black hole information paradox within semiclassical gravity, in a manner that does not depend on details of unknown quantum gravity. Our crucial insight is that outgoing Hawking particles are physical only far from the black hole horizon, so they are created far from the horizon and entangled with degrees of freedom closer to the horizon. The latter degrees of freedom can be understood as quasi-classical coherent states, implying that Hawking radiation is accompanied with additional radiation similar to classical radiation by which the black hole loses hair during the classical gravitational collapse. The two kinds of radiation are entangled, which resolves black hole information paradox.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05617v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hrvoje Nikolic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fate of boundary terms in dimensional reductions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10363v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gibbons-Hawking-York (GHY) terms are typically neglected when performing dimensional reductions of gravitational theories. We consider the reduction of such terms for both two-derivative and four-derivative theories in general dimensions. We demonstrate a robust consistency wherein the GHY term in the original, higher-dimensional theory translates directly to the appropriate GHY term in the dimensionally reduced theory. In particular, this gives a novel way of generating such terms for higher-derivative corrections. We carry out this procedure for Gauss-Bonnet, Chern-Simons modified, and $f(R)$ gravities to derive novel boundary terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10363v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J. Saskowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
