<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Modified $f(Q)$ gravity models and their cosmological consequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we consider three different $f(Q)$ models, such as power-law, exponential, and logarithmic, to study which model better mimics $\Lambda$CDM evolution theoretically. Henceforth, we determine solutions to the $f(Q)$ gravity field equations in the isotropic and homogeneous universe. Since all the models contain two model parameters, we reduce the degrees of freedom using the first Friedman equation at the present time. Further, we check the behavior of cosmological parameters using the obtained solution to the field equations and compare it with the $\Lambda$CDM model. As a result, the power-law model shows a good match with $\Lambda$CDM model for $\lambda=-1$ and $\lambda=-2$, while the exponential model behaves well for the range $5\le \beta&lt;11$, and the logarithmic model matches for $3.8&lt;\gamma&lt;4.4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01594v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cjph.2024.04.037</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav N. Gadbail, P. K. Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon rings in the metamaterial analog of a gravitomagnetic monopole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After studying null geodesics in the equatorial plane in NUT spacetime, we show that there are unstable photon rings in this plane. Next we transform the metric of this plane to the isotropic coordinates and introduce its equivalent index of refraction. Using the analog gravity ideas we assign this index of refraction to a metamaterial analog of this plane, and by ray-tracing simulation find its photon rings. Furthermore, we employ wave optics to solve Maxwell's equations numerically for electromagnetic waves within an inhomogeneous medium characterized by the same index of refraction. Further we investigate the optical behavior of this medium in response to the radiation from an electric dipole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01764v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Parvizi, H. Forghani-Ramandy, E. Rahmani, M. Nouri-Zonoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinoptics in a curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study propagation of the high frequency electromagnetic waves in a curved spacetime. We discuss a so call spinoptics approach which generalizes a well known geometric optics approximation and allows one to take into account spin-dependent corrections. A new element proposed in this work is the use of effective action which allows one to derive spinoptics equations. This method is simpler and more transparent than the earlier proposed methods. It is explicitly covariant and can be applied to an arbitrary spacetime background. We also demonstrate how the initial value problem for the high frequency electromagnetiv wave can be soled in the developed spinoptics approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01777v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeri P. Frolov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic time delay analysis of pulsar signals near ultra-compact objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The upcoming discoveries of pulsars orbiting the center of the Milky Way will present unparalleled opportunities to examine the causal structure of the spacetime geometry of Sagittarius A*. In this paper, we investigate the fully relativistic propagation time delay of pulsar signals in the Joshi-Malafarina-Narayan (JMN-1) and Janis-Newman-Winicour (JNW) spacetimes. This delay arises basically from the spacetime curvatures in the vicinity of these ultra-compact objects, induced by the intense gravitational field near the Galactic Center (GC). Using the principles of gravitational lensing, we compute the arrival time of photons originating from a pulsar in orbit around the GC. To validate our approach, we compare our time delay analysis of the Schwarzschild black hole with the corresponding delay in the post-Newtonian framework. Subsequently, we find that the propagation time of pulsar signal is greater and lesser for the given horizon-less ultra-compact objects for direct and indirect propagation respectively. Therefore, our results suggest quite significant propagation time delay differences in JMN-1 and JNW spacetimes, when compared to the Schwarzschild black hole case. This can be inferred as a possible distinguishing feature for these ultra-compact objects' geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01835v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viraj Kalsariya, Parth Bambhaniya, Pankaj S. Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational field due a moving Schwarzschild object</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we analyze the spacetime geometry due to a Schwarzschild object having accelerated motion. In the beginning we investigated the gravitational field due to a uniformly moving Schwarzschild object and obtained the spacetime line element for such an object. After analyzing the necessary boundary conditions the obtained line element is found to be consistent. Next we extended our work to a uniformly accelerated Schwarzschild object. In that case we obtained the spacetime line element for both when the acceleration is along the $X-$direction and when the acceleration is in an arbitrary direction on the $XY$ plane. The boundary conditions of those line elements have been examined. Such work will have immense applications in astrophysics when we calculate the geodesic equations of test particles in the gravitational field of objects having uniform accelerated motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01932v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranchhaigiri Brahma, A. K. Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble wall velocity and gravitational wave in the minimal left-right symmetric model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bubble wall velocity in the first order phase transition plays an important role in determining both the amplitude and the pivot frequency of stochastic gravitational wave background. In the framework of the minimal left-right symmetric model, we study the wall velocity when the first order phase transition can occur. The wall velocity can be determined by matching the distribution functions in the free particle approximation and the local thermal equilibrium approximation. It is found that the wall velocity can be determined in the range $ 0.2 &lt; v_w &lt; 0.5 $ for the parameter space with the first order phase transition. It is also found that for the case when the wall velocity is close to the speed of sound, the peak amplitude of gravitational wave spectrum can be larger than that in the runaway case. Moreover, It is also found that there exists an approximate power law between the wall velocity and pressure difference between broken and symmetry phases, and the power index is equal to 0.41 or so.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01949v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dian-Wei Wang, Qi-Shu Yan, Mei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian orbital perturbation theory in Schwarzschild space-time in terms of elliptic functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General relativistic Gauss equations for osculating elements for bound orbits under the influence of a perturbing force in an underlying Schwarzschild space-time have been derived in terms of Weierstrass elliptic functions. Thereby, the perturbation forces are restricted to act within the orbital plane only. These equations are analytically solved in linear approximation for several different perturbations such as cosmological constant perturbations, quantum corrections to the Schwarzschild metric, and hybrid Schwarzschild/post-Newtonian $2.5$ order self-forces for binary systems in an effective one-body framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01991v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksii Yanchyshen, Claus L\"ammerzahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circular geodesic orbits in the equatorial plane of a charged rotating disc of dust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Equatorial circular geodesic orbits of neutral test particles in the exterior spacetime of the charged rotating disc of dust are analyzed in dependence of its specific charge and a relativity parameter. The charged rotating disc of dust is an axisymmetric, stationary solution of the Einstein-Maxwell equations in terms of a post-Newtonian expansion. In particular, photon, marginally bound and marginally stable orbits are discussed. It turns out that general formulae in closed form for angular velocity, specific energy and specific angular momentum of the test particles can be derived, which hold for any (exterior) asymptotically flat, axisymmetric, stationary and reflection symmetric (electro-)vacuum spacetime. Furthermore, circular motion in the exterior spacetime of the charged rotating disc of dust is qualitatively very similar to that around a Kerr-Newman black hole for sufficiently large radii, but differs strongly in the respective closer vicinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01998v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Rumler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology in Entangled Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General Relativity, in the absence of a cosmological constant, is an inevitable limit of Entangled Relativity, particularly when the universe is dominated by dust and/or electromagnetic radiation. In this communication, I emphasize that this arises from a specific type of decoupling termed \textit{intrinsic decoupling}. I then discuss what this implies for Dark Energy candidates within this framework. Furthermore, I introduce a novel and tantalizing hypothesis that the Lagrangian of Entangled Relativity represents merely the unperturbed term of an infinite series in a perturbative scheme. The terms of this series are dictated by the only dimensionful universal parameter of the theory, and notably, this series retains the \textit{intrinsic decoupling} of the original theory, non-perturbatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02051v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Minazzoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Weak measurements within the Einstein-Dirac Cosmological framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our study applies the Two-State Formalism alongside weak measurements within a spatially homogeneous and isotropic cosmological framework, wherein Dirac spinors are intricately coupled to classical gravity. To elucidate this, we provide detailed formulations for computing the weak values of the energy-momentum tensors, the Z component of spin, and the characterization of pure states. Weak measurements appear to be a generalization and extension of the computation already made by Finster an Hainzl, in A spatially homogeneous and isotropic Einstein-Dirac cosmology. Our analysis reveals that the acceleration of the Universe expansion can be understood as an outcome of postselection, underscoring the effectiveness of weak measurement as a discerning approach for gauging cosmic acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02108v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Williams Dhelonga-Biarufu, Dominique Lambert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relic gravitons and non-stationary processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02193v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stationary processes do not accurately describe the diffuse backgrounds of relic gravitons whose correlations are homogeneous in space (i.e. only dependent upon the distance between the two spatial locations) but not in time. The symmetries of the autocorrelations ultimately reflect the quantum mechanical origin of the diffuse backgrounds and lead to non-stationary observables at late time. In particular, large oscillations are believed to arise in the spectral energy density that is customarily (but approximately) related to the tensor power spectrum. When the full expression of the spectral energy density is employed the amplitudes of oscillation are instead suppressed in the large-scale limit and the non-stationary features of the late-time signal practically disappear. For similar reasons the relations between the spectral energy density and the spectral amplitude are ambiguous in the presence of non-stationary features. While it is debatable if the non-stationary features are (or will be) directly detectable, we argue that the spectral amplitude following from the Wiener-Khintchine theorem is generally inappropriate for a consistent description of the relic signal. Nevertheless the strong oscillatory behaviour of the late-time observables is naturally smeared out provided the spectral energy density is selected as pivotal variable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02193v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo Giovannini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible Causes of False General Relativity Violations in Gravitational Wave Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02197v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General relativity (GR) has proven to be a highly successful theory of gravity since its inception. The theory has thrivingly passed numerous experimental tests, predominantly in weak gravity, low relative speeds, and linear regimes, but also in the strong-field and very low-speed regimes with binary pulsars. Observable gravitational waves (GWs) originate from regions of spacetime where gravity is extremely strong, making them a unique tool for testing GR, in previously inaccessible regions of large curvature, relativistic speeds, and strong gravity. Since their first detection, GWs have been extensively used to test GR, but no deviations have been found so far. Given GR's tremendous success in explaining current astronomical observations and laboratory experiments, accepting any deviation from it requires a very high level of statistical confidence and consistency of the deviation across GW sources. In this paper, we compile a comprehensive list of potential causes that can lead to a false identification of a GR violation in standard tests of GR on data from current and future ground-based GW detectors. These causes include detector noise, signal overlaps, gaps in the data, detector calibration, source model inaccuracy, missing physics in the source and in the underlying environment model, source misidentification, and mismodeling of the astrophysical population. We also provide a rough estimate of when each of these causes will become important for tests of GR for different detector sensitivities. We argue that each of these causes should be thoroughly investigated, quantified, and ruled out before claiming a GR violation in GW observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02197v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuradha Gupta, K. G. Arun, Enrico Barausse, Laura Bernard, Emanuele Berti, Sajad A. Bhat, Alessandra Buonanno, Vitor Cardoso, Shun Yin Cheung, Teagan A. Clarke, Sayantani Datta, Arnab Dhani, Jose Mar\'ia Ezquiaga, Ish Gupta, Nir Guttman, Tanja Hinderer, Qian Hu, Justin Janquart, Nathan K. Johnson-McDaniel, Rahul Kashyap, N. V. Krishnendu, Paul D. Lasky, Andrew Lundgren, Elisa Maggio, Parthapratim Mahapatra, Andrea Maselli, Purnima Narayan, Alex B. Nielsen, Laura K. Nuttall, Paolo Pani, Lachlan Passenger, Ethan Payne, Lorenzo Pompili, Luca Reali, Pankaj Saini, Anuradha Samajdar, Shubhanshu Tiwari, Hui Tong, Chris Van Den Broeck, Kent Yagi, Huan Yang, Nicol\'as Yunes, B. S. Sathyaprakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on conformal ultralight dark matter couplings from the European Pulsar Timing Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Millisecond pulsars are extremely precise celestial clocks: as they rotate, the beamed radio waves emitted along the axis of their magnetic field can be detected with radio telescopes, which allows for tracking subtle changes in the pulsars' rotation periods. A possible effect on the period of a pulsar is given by a potential coupling to dark matter, in cases where it is modeled with an "ultralight" scalar field. In this paper, we consider a universal conformal coupling of the dark matter scalar to gravity, which in turn mediates an effective coupling between pulsars and dark matter. If the dark matter scalar field is changing in time, as expected in the Milky Way, this effective coupling produces a periodic modulation of the pulsar rotational frequency. By studying the time series of observed radio pulses collected by the European Pulsar Timing Array experiment, we present constraints on the coupling of dark matter, improving on existing bounds. These bounds can also be regarded as constraints on the parameters of scalar-tensor theories of the Fierz-Jordan-Brans-Dicke and Damour-Esposito-Far\`{e}se types in the presence of a (light) mass potential term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01633v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemente Smarra, Adrien Kuntz, Enrico Barausse, Boris Goncharov, Diana L\'opez Nacir, Diego Blas, Lijing Shao, J. Antoniadis, D. J. Champion, I. Cognard, L. Guillemot, H. Hu, M. Keith, M. Kramer, K. Liu, D. Perrodin, S. A. Sanidas, G. Theureau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Observables" in de Sitter Quantum Gravity: in Perturbation Theory and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A review of some errors made by the author and others in their search for quantum models of gravity in cosmological space-times that asymptote to de Sitter (dS) space in the future. The "static de Sitter Hamiltonian", which measures the energy of localized objects in a static patch, is not a conserved quantity. The static time translation diffeomorphism of eternal dS space is a gauge symmetry, and the static energy is an approximate property of meta-stable constrained states. It's not clear whether a theoretical model has to have a time independent Hamiltonian at all, but if it does, its eigenvalues are, {\it in principle}, not accessible to measurement by local detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01773v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Banks (NHETC,Department of Physics,Astronomy, Rutgers University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio calculation of hyper-neutron matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01887v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The equation of state (EoS) of neutron matter plays a decisive role in our understanding of the properties of neutron stars as well as the generation of gravitational waves in neutron star mergers. At sufficient densities, it is known that the appearance of hyperons generally softens the EoS, thus leading to a reduction in the maximum mass of neutron stars well below the observed values of about 2 solar masses. Even though repulsive three-body forces are known to solve this so-called "hyperon puzzle", so far performing \textit{ab initio} calculations with a substantial number of hyperons has remained elusive. In this work, we address this challenge by employing simulations based on Nuclear Lattice Effective Field Theory with up to 232 neutrons (pure neutron matter) and up to 116 $\Lambda$ hyperons (hyper-neutron matter) in a finite volume. We introduce a novel auxiliary field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm, allowing us to simulate for both pure neutron matter and hyper-neutron matter systems up to 5 times the density of nuclear matter using a single auxiliary field without any sign oscillations. Also, for the first time in {\em ab initio} calculations, we not only include $N\Lambda$ two-body and $NN\Lambda$ three-body forces, but also $\Lambda\Lambda$ and $N \Lambda\Lambda$ interactions. Consequently, we determine essential astrophysical quantities such as the mass-radius relation, the speed of sound and the tidal deformability of neutron stars. Our findings also confirm the existence of the $I$-Love-$Q$ relation, which gives access to the moment of inertia of the neutron star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01887v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Tong, Serdar Elhatisari, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spacelike initial data for black hole stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02071v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct initial data suitable for the Kerr stability conjecture, that is, solutions to the constraint equations on a spacelike hypersurface with boundary entering the black hole horizon that are arbitrarily decaying perturbations of a Kerr initial data set. This results from a more general perturbative construction on any asymptotically flat initial data set with the topology of $\mathbb{R}^3\setminus\{r&lt;1\}$ enjoying some analyticity near and at the boundary. In particular, we design a suitable mixed boundary condition for the elliptic operator of the conformal method in order to exclude the Killing initial data sets (KIDS).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02071v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen Juntao Fang, J\'er\'emie Szeftel, Arthur Touati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Axion-Saxion wormholes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02072v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We reconsider the perturbative stability of Euclidean axion wormholes. The quadratic action that governs linear perturbations is derived directly in Euclidean gravity. We demonstrate explicitly that a stability analysis in which one treats the axion as a normal two-form gauge field is equivalent to one performed in the Hodge-dual formulation, where one considers the axion as a scalar with a wrong-sign kinetic term. Both analyses indicate that axion wormholes are perturbatively stable, even in the presence of a massless dilaton, or saxion, field that couples to the axion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02072v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Hertog, S. Maenaut, B. Missoni, R. Tielemans, T. Van Riet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Relativistic Derivation of the Thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first fully and inherently relativistic derivation of the thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect. This work uses the formalism historically used to compute radiation spectra emerging from inverse Thomson/Compton sources of x-ray radiation. Comparing our results to the traditional approach based on relativistically-corrected classical Kompaneets equation, we find small, but systematic differences. Most notable are the modest (&lt; 10 %) differences in the crossover frequency where the spectral distortion due to the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect vanishes, and the energy increase of the distribution at high electron cloud temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02127v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bal\v{s}a Terzi\'c, Geoffrey A. Krafft, William Clark, Alexandre Deur, Emerson Rogers, Brandon Velasco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effective field theory of multi-field inflationary fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We build an effective field theory of multi-field inflationary fluctuations based on the adiabatic perturbation and on any number of matter fluctuations in the non-adiabatic sector, without imposing extra symmetries on the latter. Focusing on terms with at most two derivatives in fields' fluctuations, we argue that taking the decoupling limit -- in which gravitational interactions are neglected -- is justified in a quasi de Sitter spacetime with slow-varying Hubble scale. With these working hypotheses, we find simple forms of multi-field mixings (quadratic order) and interactions (cubic order). We explain how to break degeneracies amongst various terms, and we compare the predictions of the effective field theory to those of non-linear sigma models of inflation and more general multi-field Lagrangian in the traditional model approach. We stress that several multi-field cubic interactions are dictated by non-linearly realised spacetime symmetries and are therefore given in terms of parameters already present in the quadratic action. We propose various directions to systematically explore the phenomenology generic to multi-field inflation and beyond the lamppost of known models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02190v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Pinol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the decoherence effects due to black holes versus ordinary matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently a certain thought experiment was discussed which involves the decoherence of a quantum system due to a black hole. Here we show how this phenomenon is consistent with standard ideas about quantum black holes. In other words, modeling the black hole as a quantum system at finite temperature one obtains the same answer. We demonstrate this by analyzing the problem in terms of an effective theory that can apply both for the black hole case and for an ordinary matter system, showing that the same qualitative effect is present for ordinary matter at finite temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02227v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Biggs, Juan Maldacena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviving Horndeski after GW170817 by Kaluza-Klein compactifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02281v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The application of Horndeski theory/ Galileons for late time cosmology is heavily constrained by the strict coincidence in the speed of propagation of gravitational and electromagnetic waves. These constraints presuppose that the minimally coupled photon is not modified, not even at the scales where General Relativity (GR) may need modification. We find that the 4D Galileon obtained from a Kaluza-Klein compactification of its higher dimensional version is a natural unified modification of GR and electromagnetism with automatically "luminal" gravitational waves. This property follows without any fine tuning of Galileon potentials for a larger class of theories than previously thought. In particular, the $G_4$ potential is not constrained by the speed test and $G_5$ may also be present. In other words, some Galileon models that have been ruled out since the event GW170817 are, in fact, not necessarily constrained if they arise in 4D from compactifications of their higher dimensional Galileon counterparts. Besides their compelling luminality, the resulting vector Galileons are naturally $U(1)$ gauge invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02281v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mironov, A. Shtennikova, M. Valencia-Villegas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate standard siren cosmology with joint gravitational-wave and $\gamma$-ray burst observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Joint gravitational-wave and $\gamma$-ray bursts (GRB) observations are among the best prospects for standard siren cosmology. However, the strong selection effect for the coincident GRB detection, which is possible only for sources with small inclination angles, induces a systematic uncertainty that is currently not accounted for. We show that this severe source of bias can be removed by inferring the a-priori unknown electromagnetic detection probability directly from multimessenger data. This leads at the same time to an unbiased measurement of the Hubble constant, to constrain the properties of GRB emission, and to accurately measure the viewing angle of each source. Our inference scheme is applicable to real data already in the small-statistics regime, a scenario that might become reality in the near future. Additionally, we introduce a novel likelihood approximant for GW events which treats the dependence on distance and inclination as exact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02286v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Mancarella, Francesco Iacovelli, Stefano Foffa, Niccol\`o Muttoni, Michele Maggiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical approaches to analyzing PTA data: Cosmic strings with six pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12234v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We search for a stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) generated by a network of cosmic strings using six millisecond pulsars from Data Release 2 (DR2) of the European Pulsar Timing Array (EPTA). We perform a Bayesian analysis considering two models for the network of cosmic string loops, and compare it to a simple power-law model which is expected from the population of supermassive black hole binaries. Our main strong assumption is that the previously reported common red noise process is a SGWB. We find that the one-parameter cosmic string model is slightly favored over a power-law model thanks to its simplicity. If we assume a two-component stochastic signal in the data (supermassive black hole binary population and the signal from cosmic strings), we get a $95\%$ upper limit on the string tension of $\log_{10}(G\mu) &lt; -9.9$ ($-10.5$) for the two cosmic string models we consider. In extended two-parameter string models, we were unable to constrain the number of kinks. We test two approximate and fast Bayesian data analysis methods against the most rigorous analysis and find consistent results. These two fast and efficient methods are applicable to all SGWBs, independent of their source, and will be crucial for analysis of extended data sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12234v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.108.123527</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 108 (2023), 123527</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hippolyte Quelquejay Leclere, Pierre Auclair, Stanislav Babak, Aur\'elien Chalumeau, Dani\`ele A. Steer, J. Antoniadis, A. -S. Bak Nielsen, C. G. Bassa, A. Berthereau, M. Bonetti, E. Bortolas, P. R. Brook, M. Burgay, R. N. Caballero, D. J. Champion, S. Chanlaridis, S. Chen, I. Cognard, G. Desvignes, M. Falxa, R. D. Ferdman, A. Franchini, J. R. Gair, B. Goncharov, E. Graikou, J. -M. Grie{\ss}meier, L. Guillemot, Y. J. Guo, H. Hu, F. Iraci, D. Izquierdo-Villalba, J. Jang, J. Jawor, G. H. Janssen, A. Jessner, R. Karuppusamy, E. F. Keane, M. J. Keith, M. Kramer, M. A. Krishnakumar, K. Lackeos, K. J. Lee, K. Liu, Y. Liu, A. G. Lyne, J. W. McKee, R. A. Main, M. B. Mickaliger, I. C. Ni\c{t}u, A. Parthasarathy, B. B. P. Perera, D. Perrodin, A. Petiteau, N. K. Porayko, A. Possenti, A. Samajdar, S. A. Sanidas, A. Sesana, G. Shaifullah, L. Speri, R. Spiewak, B. W. Stappers, S. C. Susarla, G. Theureau, C. Tiburzi, E. van der Wateren, A. Vecchio, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, J. P. W. Verbiest, J. Wang, L. Wang, Z. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De Sitter-like configurations with asymptotic quintessence environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10060v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We examine a spherically-symmetric class of spacetimes carrying vacuum energy, while considering the influence of an external dark energy environment represented by a non-dynamical quintessence field. Our investigation focuses on a specific set of solutions affected by this field, leading to distinct kinds of spacetime deformations, resulting in regular, singular, and wormhole solutions. We thoroughly discuss the underlying physics associated with each case and demonstrate that more complex deformations are prone to instability. Ultimately, we find that our results lead to an \emph{isotropic de Sitter-like solution} that behaves as a quintessence fluid. To achieve this, we investigate the nature of the corresponding fluid, showing that it cannot provide the sound speed equal to a constant equation of state {parameter} near the center. Consequently, we reinterpret the fluid as a slow-roll quintessence by investigating its behavior in asymptotic regimes. Further, we explore the potential implications of violating the isotropy condition on the pressures and we finally compare our findings with the de Sitter and Hayward solutions, highlighting both the advantages and disadvantages of our scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10060v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Giamb\`o, Orlando Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting the Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background with Astrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Astrometry, the precise measurement of star motions, offers an alternative avenue to investigate low-frequency gravitational waves through the spatial deflection of photons, complementing pulsar timing arrays reliant on timing residuals. Upcoming data from Gaia and Roman can not only cross-check pulsar timing array findings but also explore the uncharted frequency range bridging pulsar timing arrays and LISA. We present an analytical framework to evaluate the feasibility of detecting a gravitational wave background, considering measurement noise and the intrinsic variability of the stochastic background. Furthermore, we highlight astrometry's crucial role in uncovering key properties of the gravitational wave background, such as spectral index and chirality, employing information-matrix analysis. Finally, we simulate the emergence of quadrupolar correlations, commonly referred to as the generalized Hellings-Downs curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03069v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/05/030</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 05 (2024) 030</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mesut \c{C}al{\i}\c{s}kan, Yifan Chen, Liang Dai, Neha Anil Kumar, Isak Stomberg, Xiao Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Einstein-Rosen bridge inside black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15870v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalize the notion of Einstein-Rosen bridge by defining it as a space-like connection between two universes with regions of asymptotically minkowskian space-time infinities. The corresponding symmetry and asymmetry properties of the generalized Einstein-Rosen bridge are considered at the cases of Reissner-Nordstr\"om and Kerr metrics. We elucidate the versatility of intriguing symmetry and asymmetry phenomena outside and inside black holes. For description of the test particle (planet and photon) motion it is used the Kerr-Newman metric of the rotating and electrically charged black hole. In particular, it is demonstrated the symmetry and asymmetry of the one-way Einstein-Rosen bridge inside black hole toward and through the plethora of endless and infinite universes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15870v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.31857/S0044451024060063</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Zh.Exp.Teor.Fiz. Vol. 165 (6) (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vyacheslav Ivanovich Dokuchaev, Konstantin Eduardovich Prokopev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite tower of higher-curvature corrections: Quasinormal modes and late-time behavior of D-dimensional regular black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07848v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, Bueno, Cano, and Hennigar [arXiv:2403.04827] proposed a generic approach for incorporating an infinite tower of higher-curvature corrections into the Einstein theory. In this study, we compute quasinormal modes for certain regular D-dimensional black holes resulting from this infinite series of higher-curvature corrections, specifically focusing on the $D$-dimensional extensions of the Bardeen and Hayward black holes. We demonstrate that while the fundamental mode is minimally affected by moderate coupling constants, the higher overtones exhibit significant sensitivity even to small coupling values, yielding unconventional modes characterized by vanishing real oscillation frequencies. When comparing the frequencies derived from the metric truncated at several orders of higher-curvature corrections with those resulting from the infinite series of terms, we observe a rapid convergence of the frequencies to their limit for the complete regular black hole. This validates the extensive research conducted on specific theories with a finite number of higher-curvature corrections, such as the Lovelock theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07848v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.104005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 104005 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Konoplya, A. Zhidenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions, critical behavior and microstructure of the FRW universe in the framework of higher order GUP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17624v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the the phase transition, critical behavior and microstructure of the FRW in the framework of a new higher order generalized uncertainty principle. Our initial step involves deriving the equation of state by defining the work density $W$ from GUP-corrected Friedmann equations as the thermodynamic pressure $P$. Based on the modified equation of state, we conduct an analysis of the $P-V$ phase transition in the FRW universe. Subsequently, we obtain the critical exponents and coexistence curves for the small and large phases of the FRW universe around the critical point. Finally, employing Ruppeiner geometry, we derive the thermodynamic curvature scalar $R_N$, investigating its sign-changing curve and spinodal curve. The results reveal distinctive thermodynamic properties for FRW universes with positive and negative GUP parameters $\beta$. In the case of $\beta&gt;0$, the phase transition, critical behavior and microstructure of FRW universe are consistent with those of Van der Waals fluids. Conversely, for $\beta&lt;0$, the results resemble those obtained through effective scalar field theory. These findings underscore the capacity of quantum gravity to induce phase transitions in the universe, warranting further in-depth exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17624v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Wen Feng, Shi-Yu Li, Xia Zhou, Haximjan Abdusattar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum time dilation in a gravitational field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.10609v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to relativity, the reading of an ideal clock is interpreted as the elapsed proper time along its classical trajectory through spacetime. In contrast, quantum theory allows the association of many simultaneous trajectories with a single quantum clock, each weighted appropriately. Here, we investigate how the superposition principle affects the gravitational time dilation observed by a simple clock - a decaying two-level atom. Placing such an atom in a superposition of positions enables us to analyze a quantum contribution to a classical time dilation manifest in spontaneous emission. In particular, we show that the emission rate of an atom prepared in a coherent superposition of separated wave packets in a gravitational field is different from the emission rate of an atom in a classical mixture of these packets, which gives rise to a quantum gravitational time dilation effect. We demonstrate that this nonclassical effect also manifests in a fractional frequency shift of the internal energy of the atom that is within the resolution of current atomic clocks. In addition, we show the effect of spatial coherence on the atom's emission spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.10609v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerzy Paczos, Kacper D\k{e}bski, Piotr T. Grochowski, Alexander R. H. Smith, Andrzej Dragan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of some mass-capacity inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06428v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Applying a family of mass-capacity related inequalities proved in \cite{M22}, we obtain sufficient conditions that imply the nonnegativity as well as positive lower bounds of the mass, on a class of manifolds with nonnegative scalar curvature, with or without a singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06428v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengzi Miao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial magnetic non-Gaussianity with generic vacua and detection prospects in CMB spectral distortions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10342v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Assuming a slow-roll inflationary model where conformal invariance of the Maxwell action is broken via a non-minimal kinetic coupling term, we investigate the non-Gaussian three-point cross-correlation function between the primordial curvature perturbation and the primordial magnetic field, under a fairly general choice of initial vacua for both the scalar and the gauge field sectors. Among the possible triangular configurations of the resulting cross-bispectrum, we find that the squeezed limit leads to local-type non-Gaussianity allowing a product form decomposition in terms of the scalar and magnetic power spectra, which is a generic result independent of any specific choice of the initial states. We subsequently explore its detection prospects in the CMB via correlations between pre-recombination $\mu$-type spectral distortions and temperature anisotropies, sourced by such a primordial cross-correlation. Our analysis with several proposed next-generation CMB missions forecasts a low value of the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) for the $\mu T$ spectrum if both the vacua are assumed to be pure Bunch-Davies. On the contrary, the SNR may be enhanced significantly for non-Bunch-Davies initial states for the magnetic sector within allowed bounds from current CMB data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10342v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arko Bhaumik, Supratik Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High angular momentum hot differentially rotating equilibrium star evolutions in conformally flat spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The conformal flatness approximation to the Einstein equations has been successfully used in many astrophysical applications such as initial data constructions and dynamical simulations. Although it has been shown that full general relativistic strongly differentially rotating equilibrium models deviate by at most a few percent from their conformally flat counterparts, whether those conformally flat solutions remain stable has not been fully addressed. To further understand the limitations of the conformal flatness approximation, in this work, we construct spatially-conformally-flat hot hypermassive neutron stars with post-merger-like rotation laws, and perform conformally flat evolutions and analysis over dynamical timescales. We find that enforcing conformally-flat spacetime could change the equilibrium of quasi-toroidal models with high angular momentum for $J \gtrsim 9 ~G M_{\odot}^2 / c$ compared to fully general relativistic cases. In contrast, all the quasi-spherical models considered in this work remain stable even with high angular momentum $J=9~G M_{\odot}^2 / c$. Our investigation suggests that the quasi-spherical models are suitable initial data for long-lived hypermassive neutron star modeling in conformally flat spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18529v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Chi-Kit Cheong, Nishad Muhammed, Pavan Chawhan, Matthew D. Duez, Francois Foucart, Lawrence E. Kidder, Harald P. Pfeiffer, Mark A. Scheel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
