<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge Dependence of Gravitational Waves Induced by Primordial Isocurvature Fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Primordial isocurvature perturbations, which can arise from various sources in the early Universe, have the potential to leave observable imprints on the gravitational-wave background and provide insights into the nature of primordial fluctuations. In this study, we investigate the gauge dependence of induced gravitational waves (IGWs) sourced by these isocurvature perturbations. We analyze the energy density spectra of IGWs in three different gauges: synchronous, Newtonian, and uniform curvature gauges. To facilitate this analysis, we derive analytical solutions for the perturbations that contribute to the IGW spectra. Our results reveal significant differences in the energy spectra across these gauges. We find that the energy density of IGWs increases with conformal time as $\eta^8$ and $\eta^4$ for synchronous and uniform curvature gauges, respectively, while it converges in the Newtonian gauge. These findings highlight the importance of gauge choice in calculating IGWs and have implications for the interpretation of future observations of the gravitational-wave background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18996v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yuan, Zu-Cheng Chen, Lang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid star with finite strange quark mass: favouring some recent observational results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we explore the properties of hybrid star composed of deconfined quarks and dark energy considering finite value of mass of strange quark ($m_s\neq0$). We have studied the various properties of such stars assuming a linear relation between dark energy pressure and density as $p^{de}=\omega\rho^{de}$, where $-1&lt;\omega&lt;-\frac{1}{3}$, within the framework of Finch-Skea ansatz of $g_{rr}$ component of line element by varying the dark energy coupling parameter ($\beta$). In this model, $\frac{\beta}{1+\beta}$ represents the percentage of dark energy. Following the relation $\rho^{de}=\beta\rho^Q$, we have noted some restriction on the coupling parameter $\beta$ as $0&lt;\beta&lt;-\frac{1}{3\omega}$. It is interesting to note that with the change of percentage composition of dark energy, there is a prominent change of phase within in such stars. Solving TOV equations, the maximum mass attainable in this model is $\approx2~M_{\odot}$ and radius $11.37~km$. Both mass and radius decrease with the increase of $m_s$ and $\beta$ for constant $\omega$. On the other hand, maximum mass increases with the decrease of $\omega$. Various stability conditions along with causality and energy conditions are studied and found to be in agreement with the conditions of a viable stellar model. We have predicted the radii of recently observed compact stars and lighter component of the GW event $170817$ and it is interesting to note that the predicted radius of the model is close to the estimated value of the radius from observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19029v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Roy, Koushik Ballav Goswami, Debadri Bhattacharjee, Pradip Kumar Chattopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged superradiant instability in a spherical symmetric regular black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the stability of a spherically symmetric regular black hole under charged scalar field perturbations. The findings reveal the presence of charged superradiant instability within specific parameter ranges, with the growth rate potentially reaching a high order of magnitude up to approximately $\text{Im} (M \omega) \sim 10^{-3}$. This value significantly surpasses the instability observed in ABG black holes reported in earlier studies, implying a potentially relevant timescale for observing this phenomenon in astrophysical scenarios. Furthermore, a detailed analysis is presented on how the model's three parameters affect the onset and intensity of the instability. Our study contributes further insights into the potential manifestation of this instability in spherical regular black holes and its correlation with the nonlinear effects of the electromagnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19261v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yizhi Zhan, Hengyu Xu, Shao-Jun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinoptics in the Schwarzschild spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study spinoptics equations in the Schwarzschild spacetime. We demonstrate that using the explicit and hidden symmetries of this metric one can explicitly solve the equations for complex null tetrad associated with null rays representing photon's and graviton's motion. This allows one to integrate the spinoptics equations both for the electromagnetic and gravitational waves. It is shown that the main effect of the interaction of the spin of these fields with the spacetime curvature is the tilt of the asymptotic planes of the massless particle orbit. The corresponding tilting angle is calculated. It is shown that this angle grows when a null ray passes in the vicinity of the circular null orbit located at $r=3M$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19413v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeri P. Frolov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doppler correlation-driven vetoes for the Frequency Hough analysis in continuous gravitational-wave searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an improved method for vetoing candidates of continuous gravitational-wave sources during all-sky searches utilizing the Frequency Hough pipeline. This approach leverages linear correlations between source parameters induced by the Earth Doppler effect, which can be effectively identified through the Hough Transform. Candidates that do not align with these patterns are considered spurious and can thus be vetoed, enhancing the depth and statistical significance of follow-up analyses. Additionally, we provide a comprehensive explanation of the method calibration, which intrinsically linked to the total duration of the observing run. On average, the procedure successfully vetoes $56\%$ of candidates. To assess the method performance, we conducted a Monte-Carlo simulation injecting fake continuous-wave signals into data from the third observing run of the LIGO detectors. This analysis allowed us to infer strain amplitude upper limits at a $90\%$ confidence level. We found that the optimal sensitivity is $h_0^{90\%} = 3.62^{+0.23}_{-0.22}\times 10^{-26}$ in the [128, 200] Hz band, which is within the most sensible frequency band of the LIGO detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19420v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Di Giovanni, Paola Leaci, Pia Astone, Stefano Dal Pra, Sabrina D'Atonio, Luca D'Onofrio, Sergio Frasca, Federico Muciaccia, Cristiano Palomba, Lorenzo Pierini, Francesco Safai Tehrani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-metric in a (nut)shell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of the C-metric in $2+1$ dimensions, placing it within a shell of stress energy and matching it to an exterior vacuum AdS metric. The $2+1$ C-metric is not circularly symmetric and hence neither are the constructed shells, which instead take on a cuspoidal or teardrop shape. We interpret the stress energy of the shells as a perfect fluid, calculating the energy density and pressure. For accelerating particles (Class I), we find the stress energy is concentrated on the part of shell farthest from the direction of acceleration and always respects the strong energy condition. For accelerating black holes (Class I$_{\mathrm{C}}$, II, and III), the shell stress energy may either respect or violate the energy conditions depending on the parameter of the exterior metric -- between the two regimes lies a critical value of the external parameter for which the shell stress energy vanishes, leading to new solutions of Einstein's field equations, which fall into three categories: an accelerated black hole pulled by a finite-length string with a point particle at the other end, an accelerated black hole pushed by a finite-length strut with a point particle at the other end, and an accelerated black hole pushed from one side by a finite-length strut and pulled from the other by a finite-length string, each with a point particle at the other end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19677v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cameron R D Bunney, Robert B Mann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary choices and one-loop Complex Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the path integral of the four-dimensional Einstein-Hilbert gravity for the deSitter-like Universe with fluctuations and study the transition amplitude from one boundary configuration to another for the gravitational system described by lapse, scale-factor and metric fluctuation field. For variational consistency, the bulk theory needs suitable augmentation of boundary action. A specific boundary choice on the scale-factor is achieved by an infinite family of covariant boundary actions, each restricting the boundary choices for the fluctuation field. The boundary choices for the two are intimately tied to each other via general covariance, and can't be independently chosen. In the background field formalism, the full gauge-fixed path-integral on ignoring back-reaction, decouples to a path-integral over scale-factor and fluctuation field, coupling to each other only via lapse. After exactly doing the path-integral over the scale factor, the fluctuation path-integral is computed to one-loop via mode-decomposition leading to a quantum corrected lapse action. Its complex saddles shows background saddles getting corrected due to contribution from fluctuations. ``No-boundary'' saddles are seen to be no longer the saddles of the full theory, implying a Universe starting with a non-vanishing size at the corrected saddles. One-loop contribution is seen to diverge logarithmically at the background ``no-boundary'' saddles. Counter term added to cancel divergence lead to finite lapse action and transition amplitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19724v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manishankar Ailiga, Shubhashis Mallik, Gaurav Narain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Neutrino Seesaw Scale with Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutrinos are the most elusive particles of the Standard Model. The physics behind their masses remains unknown and requires introducing new particles and interactions. An elegant solution to this problem is provided by the seesaw mechanism. Typically considered at a high scale, it is potentially testable in gravitational wave experiments by searching for a spectrum from cosmic strings, which offers a rather generic signature across many high-scale seesaw models. Here we consider the possibility of a low-scale seesaw mechanism at the PeV scale, generating neutrino masses within the framework of a model with gauged U(1) lepton number. In this case, the gravitational wave signal at high frequencies arises from a first order phase transition in the early Universe, whereas at low frequencies it is generated by domain wall annihilation, leading to a double-peaked structure in the gravitational wave spectrum. The signals discussed here can be searched for in upcoming experiments, including gravitational wave interferometers, pulsar timing arrays, and astrometry observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16463v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bartosz Fornal, Dyori Polynice, Luka Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on Kinematic Flow and Differential Equations for Two-Site One-Loop Graph in FRW Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17192v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the canonical differential equations governing the two-site one-loop wavefcuntion coefficient in conformally-coupled scalar theory within a general FRW cosmology. By utilizing relative twisted cohomology and integration by parts, we systematically derive these equations, providing a solid foundation for further analysis. Moreover, we extend the kinematic flow framework to the one-loop level, efficiently deriving the differential equations graphically through the family trees generated by tube graphs, which are associated with the singularities of the system. This approach provides valuable insights into the dynamical behavior of the differential system for the cosmological wavefunction coefficient at the loop level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17192v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanfeng Hang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic fluid dynamics in a 'hydro' frame</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19015v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we investigate how field redefinition influences the spectrum of linearized perturbations in relativistic fluid dynamics. We show that the hydrodynamic modes do not get affected under local field redefinition, whereas the non-hydrodynamic modes do. These non-hydrodynamic modes can be removed through a suitable all-order field redefinition. This process leads to a new frame containing only hydrodynamic modes, which we refer to as the hydro frame. Additionally, we demonstrate that the resulting stress-energy tensor may constitute an infinite series in momentum space, with the radius of convergence associated with the removed non-hydrodynamic mode, highlighting its role in the hydrodynamic expansion's validity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19015v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantani Bhattacharyya, Sukanya Mitra, Shuvayu Roy, Rajeev Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Characteristics of a three-point Roberts Linkage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19023v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Roberts linkage is recognized for enabling long-period pendulum motion in a compact format. Utilizing this characteristic, we are developing a three-point Roberts linkage for vibration isolation systems, with an eye towards its potential contribution to the development of next-generation interferometric gravitational wave antennas. In this article, we derived the equations to determine the essential parameters when using this linkage as a vibration isolation system, namely the equivalent pendulum length and the relationship between translational motion of the center of mass and rigid body rotation, from size parameters. Additionally, we analyzed the behavior in response to various errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19023v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0219859</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Munetake Otsuka, Kohei Mitsuhashi, Ryutaro Takahashi, Yohei Nishino, Yoichi Aso, Takayuki Tomaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle Acceleration in Collisionless Magnetically Arrested Disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first collisionless realization of black hole accretion consistent with a persistent magnetically arrested disk state. The accretion flow, consisting of an ion-electron disk plasma combined with magnetospheric pair creation effects, is simulated using first-principles general-relativistic particle-in-cell methods. The axisymmetric simulation is evolved over significant dynamical timescales during which a quasi-steady accretion state is reached with several magnetic flux eruption cycles. We include a realistic treatment of inverse Compton scattering and pair production, which allows for studying the interaction between the collisionless accretion flow and the pair-loaded jet. Our findings indicate that magnetic flux eruptions associated with equatorial magnetic reconnection within the black hole magnetosphere and the formation of spark gaps are locations of maximal particle acceleration. Flux eruptions, starting near the central black hole, can trigger Kelvin-Helmholtz-like vortices at the jet-disk interface that facilitate efficient mixing between disk and jet plasma. Transient periods of increased pair production following the magnetic flux eruptions and reconnection events are responsible for most of the highly accelerated particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19061v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Vos, Benoit Cerutti, Monika Moscibrodzka, Kyle Parfrey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Rotation Rate of Neutron Stars from Crust Breaking and Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19111v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars are not observed to spin faster than about half their breakup rate. This limiting rotational frequency may be related to the strength of their crusts. As a star spins up from accretion, centrifugal forces stress the crust. We perform finite-element simulations of rotating neutron stars and find that the crust fails at rotation rates about half the breakup rate. We argue that this crust failure is asymmetric and produces a significant ellipticity (fractional difference in moments of inertia). A rotating star, with this ellipticity, radiates gravitational waves that limit further spin up. These stars may be promising sources for LIGO / VIRGO and next generation gravitational wave detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19111v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Morales, C. J. Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observed Gravitational-Wave Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19145v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ground-based gravitational-wave detectors like the Advanced LIGO, Advanced Virgo, and KAGRA experiments now regularly witness gravitational waves from compact binary mergers: the relativistic collisions of neutron stars and/or stellar-mass black holes. With hundreds of such events observed to date, gravitational-wave observations are enabling increasingly precise surveys of the demographics of merging compact binaries, including the distributions of their masses, rotation rates, and positions throughout the Universe. This article will provide an overview of our observational knowledge of the compact binary population, as it stands today. I will discuss, in turn, observations of binary black holes, binary neutron stars, and neutron star-black hole mergers, describing what is currently known (or not yet known) about these different gravitational-wave sources. I will highlight emerging classes of binaries that do not fall cleanly into any of these existing categories. And I will conclude by reviewing the methodology by which population analyses of gravitational-wave sources are performed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19145v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. A. Callister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An independent hybrid imaging of Sgr A* from the data in EHT 2017 observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose that the ring structure found by the Event Horizon Telescope Collaboration (EHTC) as the black hole shadow of Sgr A*is an artifact by the bumpy PSF (Point Spread Function) of the EHT2017. The imaging using sparse u-v data requires detailed scrutiny of the PSF. The estimated shadow diameter (48.7 +- 7 muas) is equal to the spacing between the main beam and the first sidelobe of the PSF (49.09 muas), which immediately suggests a potential problem in the deconvolution of the PSF. We show that the ring image can be derived from non-ring simulated datasets (noise only; point source) with a narrow Field-of-View (FOV) and an assumed self-calibration suggesting the EHT2017's u-v coverage is insufficient for reliable imaging. The EHTC analysis, based on calibrations with assumptions about the source's size and properties, selected the final image by prioritizing appearance rate of the similar structure from a large imaging parameter space over data consistency. Our independent analysis with the conventional hybrid mapping reveals an elongated east-west structure, consistent with previous observations. We believe it to be more reliable than the EHTC image, due to half the residuals in normalized visibility amplitude. The eastern half is brighter, possibly due to a Doppler boost from the rapid rotating disk. We hypothesize our image shows a portion of the accretion disk about 2 to a few Rs away from the black hole, rotating with nearly 60 % of the speed of light viewed from an angle of 40 -45 degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19267v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1158</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, Vol. 534, Issue 4, Nov. 2024 p3237-3264</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Makoto Miyoshi, Yoshiaki Kato, Junichiro Makino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signal-to-noise Ratio Analytic Formulae of the Inspiral Massive Black Hole Binaries in TianQin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive black hole binaries are one of the important sources for the TianQin project. Our research has revealed that, for TianQin, the signal-to-noise ratio squared during the inspiral phase of massive black hole binaries exhibits a direct proportionality to the ratio of the observation duration to the time remaining until coalescence. This finding is expected to greatly simplify the estimation of detection capabilities for massive black hole binaries. In this paper, we demonstrated this relationship under both all-sky average and non-average conditions. The latter introduces only an additional term, which we refer to as the response factor. Although this term is not easily calculated analytically, we provide a simple estimation method with an error margin of within 2%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19401v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yu Chen, Han Wang, En-Kun Li, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A well-posed formulation of minimal dRGT massive gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19491v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ghost-free dRGT massive gravity is a subtle theory, even at the classical level. Its viability depends on Vainshtein screening, which is an intrinsically non-linear phenomenon, and thus understanding the full non-linear dynamics of the theory is crucial. The theory was not expected to have a well-posed hyperbolic formulation as it is usually interpreted as a low energy EFT, and hence its short distance physics would be modified by higher derivative operators. Here we study a new dynamical formulation of the theory for the case of the minimal mass term. This firstly involves using a harmonic formulation of the theory, and then writing it as a first order system. Surprisingly we are able to cast it in a form that we argue is strongly hyperbolic for generic metrics suitably close to Minkowski, so that its Cauchy evolution problem is well-posed. Interestingly, as part of the analysis, we find that the characteristics of the spin two graviton mode are simply governed by the inverse metric on a general background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19491v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Ko\.zuszek, Toby Wiseman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bose-Marletto-Vedral experiment with nanodiamond interferometers: an insight on entanglement detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, it has been proposed a new method [arXiv:2405.21029] to detect quantum gravity effects, based on generating gravitational entanglement between two nano-diamonds with Nitrogen-Vacancy defects, in a magnetically trapped configuration. Here we analyse in detail the proposed experimental setup, with a particular focus on implementing the detection of the gravitationally-induced entanglement using an optical readout based on measuring the position of the nano-diamonds and its complementary basis. We also summarise some of the key theoretical and experimental ideas on which this proposed scheme is based.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19601v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Di Pietra, Fabrizio Piacentini, Ettore Bernardi, Ekaterina Moreva, Carmine Napoli, Ivo Pietro Degiovanni, Marco Genovese, Vlatko Vedral, Chiara Marletto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geodesic completeness from string T-duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19613v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By studying the Raychaudhuri equation for the gravitational force resulting from a string T-duality modified propagator, we present an analysis of the geodesic compression beyond the conventional classical limit. The result is that gravity on short length scales is subject to a screening effect similar to the Debye screening in electrostatics, which prevents the formation of curvature singularities. Using model-independent arguments, we conclude that the conventional attractive nature of gravity is only a low-energy effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19613v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimet Jusufi, Piero Nicolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Refracted Gravity with kinematics of galaxy clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Refracted Gravity (RG) is a a classical theory of gravity where a gravitational permittivity $ a monotonically-increasing function of the local density rho , is introduced in the Poisson equation to mimic the effect of dark matter at astrophysical scales. We use high precision spectroscopic data of two massive galaxy clusters, MACS J1206.2-0847 at redshift z=0.44, and Abell S1063 (RXC J2248.7-4431) at z=0.35, to determine the total gravitational potential in the context of RG and to constrain the three, supposedly universal, free parameters of this model. Using an upgraded version of the MG-MAMPOSSt algorithm, we perform a kinematic analysis which combines the velocity distribution of the cluster galaxies and the velocity dispersion profile of the stars within the Brightest Cluster Galaxy (BCG). The unprecedented dataset used has been obtained by an extensive spectroscopic campaign carried out with the VIMOS and MUSE spectrographs at the ESO VLT. We found that RG describes the kinematics of these two clusters as well as Newtonian gravity, although the latter is slightly preferred. However, (i) each cluster requires a different set of the three free RG parameters, and (ii) the two sets are inconsistent with other results in the literature at different scales. We discuss the limitation of the method used to constrain the RG parameters as well as possible systematic effects which can give rise to the observed tension, notably deviations from the spherical symmetry and from the dynamical equilibrium of the clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19698v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Pizzuti, Federico Fantoccoli, Valeria Broccolato, Andrea Biviano, Antonaldo Diaferio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark energy and inflation invoked in CCGG by locally contorted space-time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01088</link>
      <description>arXiv:1910.01088v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The cosmological implications of the Covariant Canonical Gauge Theory of Gravity (CCGG) are investigated. We deduce that, in a metric compatible geometry, the requirement of covariant conservation of matter invokes torsion of space-time. In the Friedman model this leads to a scalar field built from contortion and the metric with the property of dark energy, which transforms the cosmological constant to a time-dependent function. Moreover, the quadratic, scale invariant Riemann-Cartan term in the CCGG Lagrangian endows space-time with kinetic energy, and in the field equations adds a geometrical curvature correction to Einstein gravity. Applying in the Friedman model the standard $\Lambda$CDM parameter set, those equations yield a cosmological field depending just on one additional, dimensionless ``deformation'' parameter of the theory that determines the strength of the quadratic term, viz. the deviation from the Einstein-Hilbert ansatz. Moreover, the apparent curvature of the universe differs from the actual curvature parameter of the metric. The numerical analysis in that parameter space yields three cosmology types: (I) A bounce universe starting off from a finite scale followed by a steady inflation, (II) a singular Big Bang universe undergoing a secondary inflation-deceleration phase, and (III) a solution similar to standard cosmology but with a different temporal profile. The common feature of all scenarios is the graceful exit to the current dark energy era. The value of the deformation parameter can be deduced by comparing theoretical calculations with observations, namely with the SNeIa Hubble diagram and the deceleration parameter. That comparison implies a considerable admixture of scale invariant quadratic gravity to Einstein gravity. This theory also sheds new light on the resolution of the cosmological constant problem and of the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1910.01088v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-020-00415-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The European Physical Journal Plus 2020</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Vasak, Johannes Kirsch, Juergen Struckmeier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sky localization of space-based detectors with time-delay interferometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.05923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.05923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The accurate sky localization of gravitational wave (GW) sources is an important scientific goal for space-based GW detectors. The main differences between future space-based GW detectors, such as Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA), Taiji, and TianQin, include the time-changing orientation of the detector plane, the arm length, the orbital period of the spacecraft and the noise curve. Because of the effects of gravity on three spacecraft, it is impossible to maintain the equality of the arm length, so the time-delay interferometry (TDI) method is needed to cancel out the laser frequency noise for space-based GW detectors. Extending previous work based on equal-arm Michelson interferometer, we explore the impacts of different first-generation TDI combinations and detector's constellations on the sky localization for monochromatic sources. We find that the sky localization power is almost unaffected by the inclusion of the TDI Michelson $(X, Y, Z)$ combination in the analysis. We also find that the variation in the sky localization power for different TDI combinations is entirely driven by the variation in the sensitivities of these combinations. For the six particular TDI combinations studied, the Michelson $(X, Y, Z)$ combination is the best for source localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.05923v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/10/067</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2024)067</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tong Jiang, Yungui Gong, Xuchen Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A phenomenological gravitational waveform model of binary black holes incorporating horizon fluxes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17554v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Subjected to the tidal field of its companion, each component of a coalescing black hole binary suffers a slow change in its mass (tidal heating) and spin (tidal torquing) during the inspiral and merger. This effect modifies the phase and amplitude of the gravitational waveform. Numerical relativity (NR) waveforms contain these effects inherently, whereas analytical approximants for the early inspiral phase have to include them manually in the energy balance equation. In this work, we construct a frequency-domain gravitational waveform model that incorporates this effect, by recalibrating the inspiral phase of the waveform model IMRPhenomD to incorporate the phase corrections for tidal heating. We also include corrections to the amplitude by adding them directly to the inspiral amplitude model of IMRPhenomD. We demonstrate that the inclusion of the corrections, especially in the phase, confers an overall improvement in the phase agreement between the analytical inspiral model (uncalibrated SEOBNRv2) and NR data. The model presented here is faithful, with less than $1\%$ mismatches against a set of hybrid waveforms (except for one outlier that barely breaches this limit). The recalibrated model shows mismatches of up to $\sim 16\%$ with IMRPhenomD for high mass ratios and spins. Amplitude corrections become less significant for higher mass ratios, whereas the phase corrections leave more impact -- suggesting that the former is practically irrelevant for gravitational wave data analysis in Advanced LIGO (aLIGO), Virgo and KAGRA. Comparing with a set of 219 numerical relativity waveforms, we find that the median of mismatches decreases by $\sim 4\%$ in aLIGO zero-detuned high power noise curve, and by $\sim 1.5\%$ with a flat noise curve. This implies a modest but notable improvement in waveform accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17554v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samanwaya Mukherjee, Sayak Datta, Khun Sang Phukon, Sukanta Bose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schr\"odinger Connections: From Mathematical Foundations Towards Yano-Schr\"odinger Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06167v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Schr\"odinger connections are a special class of affine connections, which despite being metric incompatible, preserve length of vectors under autoparallel transport. In the present paper, we introduce a novel coordinate-free formulation of Schr\"odinger connections. After recasting their basic properties in the language of differential geometry, we show that Schr\"odinger connections can be realized through torsion, non-metricity, or both. We then calculate the curvature tensors of Yano-Schr\"odinger geometry and present the first explicit example of a non-static Einstein manifold with torsion. We generalize the Raychaudhuri and Sachs equations to the Schr\"odinger geometry. The length-preserving property of these connections enables us to construct a Lagrangian formulation of the Sachs equation. We also obtain an equation for cosmological distances. After this geometric analysis, we build gravitational theories based on Yano-Schr\"odinger geometry, using both a metric and a metric-affine approach. For the latter, we introduce a novel cosmological hyperfluid that will source the Schr\"odinger geometry. Finally, we construct simple cosmological models within these theories and compare our results with observational data as well as the $\Lambda$CDM model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06167v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad871c</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lehel Csillag, Anish Agashe, Damianos Iosifidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher memory effects and the post-Newtonian calculation of their gravitational-wave signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new hierarchy of lasting gravitational-wave effects (the higher memory effects) was recently identified in asymptotically flat spacetimes, with the better-known displacement, spin, and center-of-mass memory effects included as the lowest two orders in the set of these effects. These gravitational-wave observables are determined by a set of temporal moments of the news tensor, which describes gravitational radiation from an isolated source. The moments of the news can be expressed in terms of changes in charge-like expressions and integrals over retarded time of flux-like terms, some of which vanish in the absence of radiation. In this paper, we compute expressions for the flux-like contributions to the moments of the news in terms of a set of multipoles that characterize the gravitational-wave strain. We also identify a part of the strain that gives rise to these moments of the news. In the context of post-Newtonian theory, we show that the strain related to the moments of the news is responsible for the many nonlinear, instantaneous terms and "memory" terms that appear in the post-Newtonian expressions for the radiative multipole moments of the strain. We also apply our results to compute the leading post-Newtonian expressions for the moments of the news and the corresponding strains that are generated during the inspiral of compact binary sources. These results provide a new viewpoint on the waveforms computed from the multipolar post-Minkowski formalism, and they could be used to assess the detection prospects of this new class of higher memory effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13907v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad7663</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Siddhant Siddhant, Alexander M. Grant, David A. Nichols</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finsler Geometry, Spacetime &amp; Gravity -- From Metrizability of Berwald Spaces to Exact Vacuum Solutions in Finsler Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This PhD dissertation covers a range of topics in Finsler geometry and Finsler gravity, most notably: (i) the characterization of Berwald spaces, (ii) pseudo-Riemann (non-)metrizability of Berwald spaces, (iii) $(\alpha,\beta)$-metrics, (iv) exact solutions to Pfeifer and Wohlfarth's vacuum field equation in Finsler gravity, and (v) Finsler gravitational waves and their observational signature. An extended abstract can be found in the dissertation itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09858v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sjors Heefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical collapse and black hole evaporation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider spherically symmetric gravity coupled to a spherically symmetric scalar field with a specific coupling which depends on the Areal Radius. Classical collapse is described by the Vaidya solution. The semiclassical Einstein equations are well defined. Their solution describes an evaporating black hole. A balance law at future null infinity relates the rate of change of a back reaction-corrected Bondi mass to a manifestly positive flux. Its detailed form suggests a quantum extension of future null infinity along which all information including that in the collapsing matter is expected to emerge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09176v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madhavan Varadarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Bayesian inference and model selection for continuous gravitational waves in pulsar timing array data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16331v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Finding and characterizing gravitational waves from individual supermassive black hole binaries is a central goal of pulsar timing array experiments, which will require analysis methods that can be efficient on our rapidly growing datasets. Here we present a novel approach built on three key elements: i) precalculating and interpolating expensive matrix operations; ii) semi-analytically marginalizing over the gravitational-wave phase at the pulsars; iii) numerically marginalizing over the pulsar distance uncertainties. With these improvements the recent NANOGrav 15yr dataset can be analyzed in minutes after an $\mathcal{O}(1\ \mathrm{hour})$ setup phase, instead of an analysis taking days-weeks with previous methods. The same setup can be used to efficiently analyze the dataset under any sinusoidal deterministic model. In particular, this will aid testing the binary hypothesis by allowing for efficient analysis of competing models (e.g. incoherent, monopolar, or dipolar sine wave model) and scrambled datasets for false alarm studies. The same setup can be updated in minutes for new realizations of the data, which enables large simulation studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16331v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad84b0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bence B\'ecsy 2024 Class. Quantum Grav. 41 225017</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bence B\'ecsy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canonical quantization of the dark positive-energy Dirac field (and time asymmetry)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16545v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform canonical quantization of the single-component, spin-zero field that was introduced by Dirac in 1971 and recently suggested as a candidate for dark matter by Bogomolny. The massive and massless cases are treated separately. Since in the massive case only positive-frequency modes are normalizable and regarded as physical, the mode expansion for the field involves annihilation operators only, making the quantization procedure particularly simple. The corresponding Hamiltonian turns out to be unambiguous, with no need for normal ordering. The positive-energy requirement imposed on the second-quantized system leads to equally acceptable Bose and Fermi choices for particle statistics. This suggests supersymmetric extension of original Dirac's theory in which Bose and Fermi single-component positive-energy Dirac fields are combined into a doublet whose members can transform into each other. Our model includes a Landau-Anderson-Higgs type potential which allows spontaneous selection of the universe with a given bose-to-fermi ratio of the positive-energy Dirac particles. The bosonic sector of proposed extension hints at the possibility of a dark, background spacetime condensate that endows the universe with its cosmological temporal asymmetry. In the massless case of Dirac's original theory, we explore the possibility of allowing the field expansion to involve both positive- and negative-frequency modes. This leads to the anticommutation relations for creation and annihilation operators associated with the negative energy solutions, resulting in supersymmetric behavior of the single-component field in the ultrarelativistic limit. Finally, we speculate on the possibility for the positive-energy Dirac particles to obey some exotic (such as non-abelian, Clifford) statistics in which the particles are neither created nor destroyed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16545v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Galiautdinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects of constraining on the polarizations of gravitational waves from binary black holes using space- and ground-based detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The theory of general relativity (GR) predicts the existence of gravitational waves (GWs) with two tensor modes, while alternative theories propose up to six polarization modes. In this study, we investigate constraints on GW polarization using a model-independent parametrized post-Einsteinian framework and consider both space- and ground-based detectors. By evaluating the capabilities and network performance of LISA, Taiji, TianQin, LIGO, Virgo, KAGRA, and the Einstein Telescope (ET), we analyze their respective contributions. Among space-based detectors, Taiji provides the most stringent constraints compared with LISA and TianQin.Regarding ground-based detectors, LIGO excels in vector modes while ET offers comprehensive constraints across all polarization modes. In network scenarios, LISA+TJm performs best, and ET surpasses second-generation detector combinations. Furthermore, multiband observations effectively mitigate scalar mode degeneracies thereby significantly enhancing the performance of ground-based detectors. Ultimately, combined space- and ground-based observations provide robust constraints on GW polarizations that advance tests for deviations from GR. Our findings underscore the potential of future GW missions in refining our understanding of gravitational physics through precise measurements of polarizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13590v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.084057</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 8, 084057</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Wu, Jin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry reduction of gravitational Lagrangians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11036v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze all possible symmetry reductions of Lagrangians that yield fully equivalent field equations for any 4-dimensional metric theory of gravity. Specifically, we present a complete list of infinitesimal group actions obeying the principle of symmetric criticality, identify the corresponding invariant metrics (and $l$-chains), discuss relations among them, and analyze simplifications allowed by the residual diffeomorphism group and Noether identities before and after variation of the reduced Lagrangian. We employ rigorous treatment of the symmetry reduction by Fels and Torre and use the Hicks classification of infinitesimal group actions by means of Lie algebras pairs of isometries and their isotropy subalgebras. The classification is recast in the coordinates in which the well-known symmetries and geometries are easily recognizable and relatable to each other. The paper is accompanied by a code for the symmetry reduction of Lagrangians that we developed in \texttt{xAct} package of \textsc{Mathematica}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11036v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Frausto, Ivan Kol\'a\v{r}, Tom\'a\v{s} M\'alek, Charles Torre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to define the moving frame of the Unruh-DeWitt detector on manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19160v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The vacuum of an accelerating observer is defined on the local inertial frame, which is called a ``moving frame''. However, in the discussion of the Unruh-deWitt detector, many papers define the vacuum on a fixed frame. This paper discusses the Unruh-deWitt detector by defining the vacuum directly on the local inertial frame, showing that the problem of the Stokes phenomenon can be solved by using the exact WKB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19160v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swampland Conjectures Constraints on Dark Energy from a Highly Curved Field Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05304v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the interplay of the trans-Planckian censorship conjecture (TCC) and the swampland distance conjecture (SDC) in the context of multifield dark energy in a curved field space. In this scenario, the phase of accelerated expansion is realized as non-geodesic motion in a highly-curved field space, reminiscent of models developed in the context of inflation. The model features a stable attractor solution with near constant equation of state $w\simeq -1$, and predicts that the current era of accelerated expansion is eternal. The latter implies an eventual conflict with the TCC, which holds that the duration of any epoch of cosmic acceleration is bounded by the requirement that the large-scale observable universe is blind to Planck-scale early universe physics. This tension can be resolved by an interplay with the distance conjecture: for suitable parameter values, the apparent violation of the TCC occurs well after the fields have traversed a Planckian distance. The SDC then predicts a breakdown of the effective field theory (EFT) before the TCC can be violated. We derive the constraints on the model arising from the SDC+TCC and the de Sitter conjecture. We demonstrate that the model can be consistent with both swampland conjectures and observational data from Planck 2018 and the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05304v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Payeur, Evan McDonough, Robert Brandenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole solutions in double field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11403v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study black hole solutions in double field theory. In the first part, we introduce a solution-generating method and classify black hole solutions into three categories in standard double field theory. To solve the problem of double time, we utilize space/time split double field theory in the second part to derive black hole solutions. By introducing a cosmological constant and imposing the strong constraint, our findings indicate that when considering the entire doubled spacetime, the curvature signifies a generalized AdS vacuum. However, in the subspace of the entire spacetime, black holes and curvature singularities emerge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11403v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuxuan Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double Field Theory and $\alpha'$ corrections: explicit examples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04833v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct several solutions of effective actions for string theories beyond the supergravity approximation utilizing the framework of the Double Field Theory (DFT). The DFT effective actions, which are well suited for accommodating abelian and non-abelian T dualities, are naturally written in terms of modified connections and curvatures with torsion. We construct the most general solutions with vanishing modified torsion, and such geometries don't receive quantum corrections. We also compute the leading $\alpha'$ corrections to several supergravity solutions, including a pair of geometries related by a non-abelian T duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04833v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Lunin, Parita Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New purely damped pairs of quasinormal modes in a hot and dense strongly-coupled plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09498v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Perturbed black holes exhibit damped oscillations whose eigenfrequencies define their quasinormal modes (QNMs). In the case of asymptotically Anti-de Sitter (AdS) black holes, the spectra of QNMs are related to the near-equilibrium behavior of specific strongly interacting quantum field theories via the holographic gauge-gravity duality. In the present work, we numerically obtain the spectra of homogeneous non-hydrodynamic QNMs of a top-down holographic construction called the 2 R-Charge Black Hole (2RCBH) model, which describes a hot and dense strongly-coupled plasma. The main result is the discovery of a new structure of pairs of purely imaginary QNMs. Those new purely damped QNMs dominate the late time equilibration of the strongly-coupled plasma at large values of the chemical potential, while at lower values the fundamental QNMs are instead ordinary poles with imaginary and real parts describing oscillatory decaying perturbations. We also observe a new phenomenon of asymptotic pole fusion for different pairs of purely imaginary QNMs at asymptotically large values of the chemical potential. This phenomenon corresponds to the asymptotic merging of the two poles within each pair of purely imaginary QNMs, with the different pairs of merged poles being evenly spaced by a constant value of $4\pi$ in all the different perturbation channels associated to different irreducible representations of the spatial $SO(3)$ rotation symmetry of the medium. In particular, this indicates that characteristic equilibration times for the plasma develop upper bounds that cannot be surpassed by further doping the medium with increasing values of the chemical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09498v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo de Oliveira, Romulo Rougemont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic gravitational wave background anisotropies from inflation with non-Bunch-Davies states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14664v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been known that stochastic gravitational wave backgrounds (SGWBs) have anisotropies generated by squeezed-type tensor non-Gaussianities originating from scalar-tensor-tensor (STT) and tensor-tensor-tensor cubic interactions. While the squeezed tensor non-Gaussianities in the standard slow-roll inflation with the Bunch-Davies vacuum state are suppressed due to the so-called consistency relation, those in extended models with the violation of the consistency relation can be enhanced. Among such extended models, we consider the inflation model with the non-Bunch-Davies state that has been known to enhance the squeezed tensor non-Gaussianities. We explicitly formulate the primordial STT bispectrum induced during inflation in the context of Horndeski theory with the non-Bunch-Davies state and show that the induced SGWB anisotropies can be enhanced. We then discuss the detectability of those anisotropies in future gravitational wave experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14664v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shingo Akama, Shin'ichi Hirano, Shuichiro Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
