<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 01:39:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Dark Matter: Covariant Brownian Motion from Planckian Discreteness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum gravity has long remained elusive from an observational standpoint. Developing effective cosmological models motivated by the fundamental aspects of quantum gravity is crucial for bridging theory with observations. One key aspect is the granularity of spacetime, which suggests that free particles would deviate from classical geodesics by following a covariant Brownian motion. This notion is further supported by swerves models in causal set theory, a discrete approach to quantum gravity. At an effective level, such deviations are described by a stochastic correction to the geodesic equation. We show that the form of this correction is strictly restricted by covariance and the mass-shell condition. Under minimal coupling to curvature, the resulting covariant Brownian motion is unique. The process is equivalently described by a covariant diffusion equation for the distribution of massive particles in their relativistic phase space. When applied to dark matter particles, covariant Brownian motion results in spontaneous warming at late times, suppressing the matter power spectrum at small scales in a time-dependent manner. Using bounds on the diffusion rate from CMB and growth history measurements of $f\sigma_8$, we show that the model offers a resolution to the $S_8$ tension. Future studies on the model's behavior at non-linear cosmological scales will provide further constraints and, therefore, critical tests for the viability of stochastic dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02188v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Albertini, Arad Nasiri, Emanuele Panella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes of type D revisited: relating their various metric forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a complete family of spacetimes which represent black holes with rotation, NUT twist, acceleration, electric and magnetic charges. These are exact solutions of the Einstein-Maxwell equations with any cosmological constant, such that the (non-null) electromagnetic field is aligned with both the double-degenerate principal null directions of the Weyl tensor. In particular, we explicitly relate various coordinates and the corresponding physical parameters of such solutions, namely the original Plebanski-Demianski (PD) form, the convenient Astorino (A) form which was found recently, and formally improved here (A+), the Griffiths-Podolsky (GP), and Podolsky-Vratny (PV) form of the metric. It is demonstrated that, if properly mapped and physically interpreted, all these representations cover the complete class of type D black holes. Using the new A-parameters, the two main PD quartic metric functions are factorized into the product of quadratic expressions, enabling thus an explicit analysis. Moreover, we clarify the role of the twist parameter $\omega$, related to both the Kerr-like rotation and the NUT parameters $a$ and $l$, respectively. Special attention is payed to the elusive subclass of accelerating NUT black holes with $a=0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02308v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hryhorii Ovcharenko, Jiri Podolsky, Marco Astorino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Dissipative Gravitational Collapse in the Morris-Thorne Wormhole Metric: One Scenario -- Several Outcomes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02441v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the dynamical Morris-Thorne metric with radiating heat flow. By matching the interior Morris-Thorne metric with an exterior Vaidya metric we trace out the collapse solutions for the corresponding spherically symmetric inhomogeneous distribution of matter. The solutions obtained are broadly of four different types, giving different end state dynamics. Corresponding to three of the solutions we elaborate the collapsing dynamics of the Morris-Thorne type evolving wormhole. We show that for all those cases where collapse upto zero proper volume is obtained in finite time, the ensuing singularity is always a black hole type. However our solutions can also show other end states, like oscillating wormhole-black hole pair or infinite time contracting universe or a conformal past matter dominated universe. In all the cases we have worked out the background dynamics and physics of the solution. All our solutions are illustrated with appropriate graphical descriptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02441v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhasis Nalui, Subhra Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gyroscopic Gravitational Memory from quasi-circular binary systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02624v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational waves cause a precession in a freely falling spinning object and a net change of orientation after the passage of the wave, dubbed as the gyroscopic memory. In this paper, we will consider isolated gravitational sources in the post-Newtonian framework and compute the gyroscopic precession and memory at leading post-Newtonian (PN) orders. We make a comparison between two competing contributions: the spin memory and the nonlinear helicity flux. At the level of the precession rate, the former is a 2PN oscillatory effect, while the latter is a 4PN adiabatic effect. However, the gyroscopic memory involves a time integration, which enhances subleading adiabatic effects by the fifth power of the velocity of light, leading to a 1.5PN memory effect. We explicitly compute the leading effects for a quasi-circular binary system and obtain the angular dependence of the memory on the celestial sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02624v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Faye, Ali Seraj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise asymptotics of the spin $+2$ Teukolsky field in the Kerr black hole interior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using a purely physical-space analysis, we prove the precise oscillatory blow-up asymptotics of the spin $+2$ Teukolsky field in the interior of a subextremal Kerr black hole. In particular, this work gives a new proof of the blueshift instability of the Kerr Cauchy horizon against linearized gravitational perturbations that was first shown by Sbierski \cite{sbierski}. In that sense, this work supports the Strong Cosmic Censorship conjecture in Kerr spacetimes. The proof is an extension to the Teukolsky equation of the work \cite{scalarMZ} by Ma and Zhang that treats the scalar wave equation in the interior of Kerr. The analysis relies on the generic polynomial decay on the event horizon of solutions of the Teukolsky equation that arise from compactly supported initial data, as recently proved by Ma and Zhang \cite{pricelaw} and Millet \cite{millet} in subextremal Kerr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02670v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Gurriaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Surface Tension as the Origin for the Black Hole Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the thermodynamics of black holes using the Gouy-Stodola theorem, traditionally applied to mechanical systems relating entropy production to the difference between reversible and irreversible work. We model black holes as gravitational bubbles with surface tension defined at the event horizon, deriving the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy relation for non-rotating black holes. One extends this approach to rotating black holes, incorporating the effects of angular momentum, demonstrating that the Gouy-Stodola theorem can similarly derive the entropy-area law in this case. Additionally, we analyze the merging of two black holes, showing that the resultant total entropy exceeds the sum of the individual entropies, thereby adhering to the second law of thermodynamics. Our results suggest that gravitational surface tension is a key factor in black hole thermodynamics, providing a novel and coherent framework for understanding the entropy production in these extreme astrophysical objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02694v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. D. Campos, R. H. Longaresi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Configurational entropy and stability conditions of fermion and boson stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a remarkable study by M. Gleiser and N. Jiang (Phys. Rev. D {\bf 92}, 044046, 2015), the authors demonstrated that the stability regions of neutron stars, within the framework of the simple Fermi gas model, and self-gravitating configurations of complex scalar field (boson stars) with various self couplings, obtained through traditional perturbation methods, correlates with critical points of the configurational entropy with an accuracy of a few percent. Recently, P. Koliogiannis \textit{et al.} (Phys. Rev. D {\bf 107}, 044069 2023) found that while the minimization of the configurational entropy generally anticipates qualitatively the stability point for neutron stars and quark stars, this approach lacks universal validity. In this work, we aim to further elucidate this issue by seeking to reconcile these seemingly contradictory findings. Specifically, we calculate the configurational entropy of bosonic and fermionic systems, described by interacting Fermi and Boson gases, respectively, that form compact objects stabilized by gravity. We investigate whether the minimization of configurational entropy coincides with the stability point of the corresponding compact objects. Our results indicate a strong correlation between the stability points predicted by configurational entropy and those obtained through traditional methods, with the accuracy of this correlation showing a slight dependence on the interaction strength. Consequently, the stability of compact objects, composed of components obeying Fermi or Boson statistics, can alternatively be assessed using the concept of configurational entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02803v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Koliogiannis, M. Vikiaris, C. Panos, V. Petousis, M. Veselsky, Ch. C. Moustakidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial regular black holes as all the dark matter (I): tr-symmetric metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs) are usually assumed to be described by the Schwarzschild or Kerr metrics, which however feature unwelcome singularities. We study the possibility that PBHs are non-singular objects, considering four phenomenological, regular tr-symmetric space-times, featuring either de Sitter or Minkowski cores. We characterize the evaporation of these PBHs and constrain their abundance from $\gamma$-ray observations. For three of the metrics, including the well-known Bardeen and Hayward ones, we show that constraints on $f_{\text{pbh}}$, the fraction of dark matter (DM) in the form of PBHs, weaken with respect to the Schwarzschild limits, because of modifications to the PBH temperature and greybody factors. This moves the lower edge of the asteroid mass window down by up to an order of magnitude, leading to a much larger region of parameter space where PBHs can make up all the DM. A companion paper is instead devoted to non-tr-symmetric metrics, including loop quantum gravity-inspired ones. Our work provides a proof-of-principle for the interface between the DM and singularity problems being a promising arena with a rich phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02804v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Calz\`a, Davide Pedrotti, Sunny Vagnozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial regular black holes as all the dark matter (II): non-tr-symmetric and loop quantum gravity-inspired metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is a common belief that a theory of quantum gravity should ultimately cure curvature singularities which are inevitable within General Relativity, and plague for instance the Schwarzschild and Kerr metrics, usually considered as prototypes for primordial black holes (PBHs) as dark matter (DM) candidates. We continue our study, initiated in a companion paper, of non-singular objects as PBHs, considering three regular non-tr-symmetric metrics, all of which are one-parameter extensions of the Schwarzschild space-time: the Simpson-Visser, Peltola-Kunstatter, and D'Ambrosio-Rovelli space-times, with the latter two motivated by loop quantum gravity. We study evaporation constraints on PBHs described by these regular metrics, deriving upper limits on $f_{\text{pbh}}$, the fraction of DM in the form of PBHs. Compared to their Schwarzschild counterparts, these limits are weaker, and result in a larger asteroid mass window where all the DM can be in the form of PBHs. Our work demonstrates as a proof-of-principle that quantum gravity-inspired space-times can simultaneously play an important role in the resolution of singularities and in the DM problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02807v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Calz\`a, Davide Pedrotti, Sunny Vagnozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational radiation from binary systems in Unimodular gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unimodular gravity (UG) is classically considered identical to General Relativity (GR). However, due to restricted diffeomorphism symmetry, the Bianchi identites do not lead to the conservation of energy-momentum tensor. Thus, the conservation of energy-momentum tensor needs to be separately assumed in order to reconcile with GR. Relaxing this assumption, one finds that the conservation violation can lead to differences with GR, which can be subsequently examined in astrophysical and cosmological scenarios. To this end, we examine the predictions of UG in the context of binary systems emitting gravitational radiation. Primarily, we show how the field equations involve a diffusion function which quantifies the measure of non-conservation. Due to this violation, the dispersion relation is modified. Incorporating these changes, we provide an expression for the energy loss by the binaries, which reduces to Peters-Mathews result in the GR limit. Using binary pulsar data, we constrain the theory parameter $\zeta$ (which signifies non-conservation) by determining the rate of orbital decay. The strongest constrain on $\zeta$ comes out to be $\vert \zeta \vert \leq 5\times 10^{-4}$ which is better by an order of magnitude than an existing equivalent constraint coming from the tidal deformability of the neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02909v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Chakraborty, Soumya Jana, Subhendra Mohanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accreting Black Holes in Dark Matter Halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11333v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine the thin accretion disk behaviors surrounding black holes embedded in cold dark matter halos and scalar field dark matter halos. We first calculate the event horizons and derive the equations of motion and effective potential in black hole geometries with different dark matter halos. We then compute the specific energy, specific angular momentum, and angular velocity of particles moving along circular orbits. We also derive the effective potentials to find the locations of the innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO) and compare them to the Schwarzschild and Kerr black holes without the dark matter haloes. We also use the observed ISCO of the supermassive black hole at the Galactic Center of the Milky Way, Sagittarius A*, to constrain the dark matter halos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11333v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.043034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 043034 - Published 26 August 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sobhan Kazempour, Sichun Sun, Chengye Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Dark Matter and Rotation on Neutron Star Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we examine the combined effects of dark matter (DM) and rotation on the properties of neutron stars (NSs). We employ a self-interacting dark matter model, motivated by the neutron decay anomaly, within the relativistic mean-field formalism to explore its impact on both static and rotating NSs. The Hartle-Thorne approach is utilized to model rotating NSs, treating the DM interaction strength ($G$) as a free parameter and considering angular velocity ($\Omega$) for rotation. We investigate how DM influences the mass-shedding limit, determined using the Keplerian frequency, and analyze the variations in angular velocity at different DM interaction strengths to assess their effects on NS mass, radius, central energy density, and eccentricity. Our results indicate that while rotation increases mass and radius due to centrifugal forces, DM softens the EOS, reducing these properties, particularly at higher DM fractions. DM also reduces rotational deformation, leading to lower eccentricity compared to DM-free NSs at the same angular velocity. Additionally, we calculate the relative deviations in maximum rotational mass and canonical equatorial radius from their baseline values, finding that high DM fractions combined with low angular velocities result in significant reductions, while low DM fractions with high rotational speeds lead to positive deviations, indicating greater deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02131v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pinku Routaray, Abirbhav Chakrawarty, Bharat Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black holes from an aborted phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02175v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a new mechanism of primordial black hole formation via an aborted phase transition during the early matter-dominated stage of reheating after inflation. In reheating, induced by the decay of a pressureless fluid dominating the Universe at the end of inflation, dubbed as reheaton, the temperature of the radiation bath typically increases, reaching a maximum temperature $T_{\rm max}$, and then decreases. We consider a first-order phase transition induced by the increase of the temperature that is aborted as $T_{\rm max}$ is higher than the critical temperature but not sufficiently high for the bubble nucleation rate to overcome the expansion of the Universe. Although bubbles never fully occupy the space, some may be nucleated and expand until the temperature once again decreases to the critical temperature. We argue that these bubbles shrink and disappear as the temperature drops further, leaving behind macroscopic spherical regions with positive density perturbations. These perturbed regions accrete the surrounding matter (reheatons) and eventually collapse into primordial black holes whose mass continues to grow until the onset of radiation domination. We estimate the abundance of these primordial black holes in terms of the bubble nucleation rate at $T_{\rm max}$, and demonstrate that the abundance can be significantly large from a phenomenological perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02175v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Yuan Ai, Lucien Heurtier, Tae Hyun Jung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravity from Pre-geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02200v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The gravitational interaction, as described by the Einstein-Cartan theory, is shown to emerge as the by-product of the spontaneous symmetry breaking of a gauge symmetry in a pre-geometric four-dimensional spacetime. Starting from a formulation \`a la Yang-Mills on an SO(1,4) or SO(3,2) principal bundle and not accounting for a spacetime metric, the Einstein-Hilbert action is recovered after the identification of the effective spacetime metric and spin connection for the residual SO(1,3) gauge symmetry of the spontaneously broken phase - i.e. the stabiliser of the SO(1,4) or SO(3,2) gauge group. Thus, the two fundamental tenets of General Relativity, i.e. diffeomorphism invariance and the equivalence principle, can arise from a more fundamental gauge principle. The two mass parameters that characterise Einstein gravity, namely the Planck mass and the cosmological constant, are likewise shown to be emergent, with the correct sign for the cosmological constant depending on whether the fundamental gauge group is taken to be either the de Sitter or the anti-de Sitter group. The phase transition from the unbroken to the spontaneously broken phase is expected to happen close to the Planck temperature. This is conjectured to be dynamically driven by a scalar field that implements a Higgs mechanism, hence providing mass to new particles, with consequences for cosmology and high-energy physics. The couplings of gravity to matter are discussed after drawing up a dictionary that interconnects pre-geometric and effective geometric quantities. In the unbroken phase where the fundamental gauge symmetry is restored, the theory is potentially power-counting renormalisable without matter, offering a novel path towards a UV completion of Einstein gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02200v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Addazi, Salvatore Capozziello, Antonino Marciano, Giuseppe Meluccio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic topology. Part Ic. Limits on lens spaces from circle searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cosmic microwave background (CMB) temperature and polarization observations indicate that in the best-fit $\Lambda$ Cold Dark Matter model of the Universe, the local geometry is consistent with at most a small amount of positive or negative curvature, i.e., $\vert\Omega_K\vert\ll1$. However, whether the geometry is flat ($E^3$), positively curved ($S^3$) or negatively curved ($H^3$), there are many possible topologies. Among the topologies of $S^3$ geometry, the lens spaces $L(p,q)$, where $p$ and $q$ ($p&gt;1$ and $0&lt;q&lt;p$) are positive integers, are quotients of the covering space of $S^3$ (the three-sphere) by ${\mathbb{Z}}_p$, the cyclic group of order $p$. We use the absence of any pair of circles on the CMB sky with matching patterns of temperature fluctuations to establish constraints on $p$ and $q$ as a function of the curvature scale that are considerably stronger than those previously asserted for most values of $p$ and $q$. The smaller the value of $\vert\Omega_K\vert$, i.e., the larger the curvature radius, the larger the maximum allowed value of $p$. For example, if $\vert\Omega_K\vert\simeq 0.05$ then $p\leq 9 $, while if $\vert\Omega_K\vert\simeq 0.02$, $p$ can be as high as 24. Future work will extend these constraints to a wider set of $S^{3}$ topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02226v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samanta Saha (COMPACT Collaboration), Craig J. Copi (COMPACT Collaboration), Glenn D. Starkman (COMPACT Collaboration), Stefano Anselmi (COMPACT Collaboration), Javier Carr\'on Duque (COMPACT Collaboration), Mikel Martin Barandiaran (COMPACT Collaboration), Yashar Akrami (COMPACT Collaboration), Fernando Cornet-Gomez (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrew H. Jaffe (COMPACT Collaboration), Arthur Kosowsky (COMPACT Collaboration), Deyan P. Mihaylov (COMPACT Collaboration), Thiago S. Pereira (COMPACT Collaboration), Amirhossein Samandar (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrius Tamosiunas (COMPACT Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-timelike loops in signature changing semi-Riemannian manifolds with a transverse radical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02403v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1983, Hartle and Hawking introduced a conceptually intriguing idea involving signature-type change, which led to the no-boundary proposal for the initial conditions of the universe. According to this proposal, the universe has no beginning because there is no singularity or boundary in spacetime; however, there is an origin of time. Mathematically, this entails signature-type changing manifolds where a Riemannian region smoothly transitions to a Lorentzian region at the surface where time begins.
  We present a coherent framework for signature-type changing manifolds characterized by a degenerate yet smooth metric. We then adapt firmly established Lorentzian tools and results to the signature-type changing scenario, introducing new definitions that carry unforeseen causal implications. A noteworthy consequence is the presence of locally closed time-reversing loops through each point on the hypersurface. By imposing the constraint of global hyperbolicity on the Lorentzian region, we demonstrate that for every point $p\in M$, there exists a pseudo-timelike loop with point of self-intersection $p$. Or put another way, there always exists a closed pseudo-timelike path in $M$ around which the direction of time reverses, and a consistent designation of future-directed and past-directed vectors cannot be defined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02403v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Hasse, N. E. Rieger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk Reconstruction and Gauge Invariance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02534v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss the concept of bulk reconstruction, which involves mapping bulk operators into CFT operators to understand the emergence of spacetime and gravity. We argue that the $N=\infty$ approximation fails to capture crucial aspects of gravity, as it does not respect gauge invariance and lacks direct connections between energy and boundary metrics. Key concepts such as entanglement wedge reconstruction and holographic error correction codes, which are based on the $N=\infty$ theory, may be incorrect or require significant revision when finite $N$ effects are considered. We present explicit examples demonstrating discrepancies in bulk reconstructions and suggest that a gauge-invariant approach is necessary for an accurate understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02534v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sotaro Sugishita, Seiji Terashima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the particle content of MHS theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02679v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Moyal-Higher-Spin (MHS) formalism, involving fields dependent on spacetime and auxiliary coordinates, is an approach to studying higher spin (HS)-like models. To determine the particle content of the MHS model of the Yang-Mills type, we calculate the quartic Casimir operator for on-shell MHS fields, finding it generally non-vanishing, indicative of infinite/continuous-spin degrees of freedom. We propose an on-shell basis for these infinite/continuous-spin states. Additionally, we analyse the content of a massive MHS model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02679v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maro Cvitan, Predrag Dominis Prester, Stefano Giaccari, Mateo Pauli\v{s}i\'c, Ivan Vukovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LIGO Detector Characterization in the first half of the fourth Observing run</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Progress in gravitational-wave astronomy depends upon having sensitive detectors with good data quality. Since the end of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA third Observing run in March 2020, detector-characterization efforts have lead to increased sensitivity of the detectors, swifter validation of gravitational-wave candidates and improved tools used for data-quality products. In this article, we discuss these efforts in detail and their impact on our ability to detect and study gravitational-waves. These include the multiple instrumental investigations that led to reduction in transient noise, along with the work to improve software tools used to examine the detectors data-quality. We end with a brief discussion on the role and requirements of detector characterization as the sensitivity of our detectors further improves in the future Observing runs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02831v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Soni, B. K. Berger, D. Davis, F. Di. Renzo, A. Effler, T. A. Ferreira, J. Glanzer, E. Goetz, G. Gonz\'alez, A. Helmling-Cornell, B. Hughey, R. Huxford, B. Mannix, G. Mo, D. Nandi, A. Neunzert, S. Nichols, K. Pham, A. I. Renzini, R. M. S. Schofield, A Stuver, M. Trevor, S. \'Alvarez-L\'opez, R. Beda, C. P. L. Berry, S. Bhuiyan, R. Bruntz, N. Christensen, L. Blagg, M. Chan, P. Charlton, G. Connolly, R. Dhatri, J. Ding, V. Garg, K. Holley-Bockelmann, S. Hourihane, K. Jani, K. Janssens, S. Jarov, A. M. Knee, A. Lattal, Y. Lecoeuche, T. Littenberg, A. Liyanage, B. Lott, R. Macas, D. Malakar, K. McGowan, J. McIver, M. Millhouse, L. Nuttall, D. Nykamp, I. Ota, C. Rawcliffe, B. Scully, J. Tasson, A. Tejera, S. Thiele, R. Udall, C. Winborn, Z. Yarbrough, Z. Zhang, R. Abbott, I. Abouelfettouh, R. X. Adhikari, A. Ananyeva, S. Appert, K. Arai, N. Aritomi, S. M. Aston, M. Ball, S. W. Ballmer, D. Barker, L. Barsotti, J. Betzwieser, G. Billingsley, S. Biscans, N. Bode, E. Bonilla, V. Bossilkov, A. Branch, A. F. Brooks, D. D. Brown, J. Bryant, C. Cahillane, H. Cao, E. Capote, F. Clara, J. Collins, C. M. Compton, R. Cottingham, D. C. Coyne, R. Crouch, J. Csizmazia, T. J. Cullen, L. P. Dartez, N. Demos, E. Dohmen, J. C. Driggers, S. E. Dwyer, A. Ejlli, T. Etzel, M. Evans, J. Feicht, R. Frey, W. Frischhertz, P. Fritschel, V. V. Frolov, P. Fulda, M. Fyffe, D. Ganapathy, B. Gateley, J. A. Giaime, K. D. Giardina, R. Goetz, A. W. Goodwin-Jones, S. Gras, C. Gray, D. Griffith, H. Grote, T. Guidry, E. D. Hall, J. Hanks, J. Hanson, M. C. Heintze, N. A. Holland, D. Hoyland, H. Y. Huang, Y. Inoue, A. L. James, A. Jennings, W. Jia, S. Karat, S. Karki, M. Kasprzack, K. Kawabe, N. Kijbunchoo, P. J. King, J. S. Kissel, K. Komori, A. Kontos, Rahul Kumar, K. Kuns, M. Landry, B. Lantz, M. Laxen, K. Lee, M. Lesovsky, F. Llamas, M. Lormand, H. A. Loughlin, R. Macas, M. MacInnis, C. N. Makarem, G. L. Mansell, R. M. Martin, K. Mason, F. Matichard, N. Mavalvala, N. Maxwell, G. McCarrol, R. McCarthy, D. E. McClelland, S. McCormick, L. McCuller, T. McRae, F. Mera, E. L. Merilh, F. Meylahn, R. Mittleman, D. Moraru, G. Moreno, A. Mullavey, M. Nakano, T. J. N. Nelson, J. Notte, J. Oberling, T. O'Hanlon, C. Osthelder, D. J. Ottaway, H. Overmier, W. Parker, A. Pele, H. Pham, M. Pirello, V. Quetschke, K. E. Ramirez, J. Reyes, J. W. Richardson, M. Robinson, J. G. Rollins, C. L. Romel, J. H. Romie, M. P. Ross, K. Ryan, T. Sadecki, A. Sanchez, E. J. Sanchez, L. E. Sanchez, R. L. Savage, D. Schaetzl, M. G. Schiworski, R. Schnabel, E. Schwartz, D. Sellers, T. Shaffer, R. W. Short, D. Sigg, B. J. J. Slagmolen, C. Soike, V. Srivastava, L. Sun, D. B. Tanner, M. Thomas, P. Thomas, K. A. Thorne, C. I. Torrie, G. Traylor, A. S. Ubhi, G. Vajente, J. Vanosky, A. Vecchio, P. J. Veitch, A. M. Vibhute, E. R. G. von Reis, J. Warner, B. Weaver, R. Weiss, C. Whittle, B. Willke, C. C. Wipf, V. A. Xu, H. Yamamoto, L. Zhang, M. E. Zucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Kaluza-Klein black hole and Kerr/CFT correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02892v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a new solution in the Einstein-Maxwell-dilaton theory describing accelerating, charged, and rotating black hole, i.e. the accelerating Kaluza-Klein black hole. Some properties the spacetime are discussed, such as the electromagnetic fields, the area-temperature product, and the holography according to Kerr/CFT correspondence. As expected, the macroscopic Bekenstein-Hawking entropy for an extremal accelerating Kaluza-Klein black hole can be recovered by using Cardy formula of a two dimensional conformal field theory. An interesting feature is found, namely the area-temperature product is just the the one belongs to the vacuum Einstein seed solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02892v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2024.169782</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Haryanto M. Siahaan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward 2D Dynamo Models Calibrated by Global 3D Relativistic Accretion Disk Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional models assuming axisymmetry are an economical way to explore the long-term evolution of black hole accretion disks, but they are only realistic if the feedback of the nonaxisymmetric turbulence on the mean momentum and magnetic fields is incorporated. Dynamo terms added to the 2D induction equation should be calibrated to 3D MHD simulations. For generality, the dynamo tensors should be calibrated as functions of local variables rather than explicit functions of spatial coordinates in a particular basis. In this paper, we study the feedback of non-axisymmetric features on the 2D mean fields using a global 3D, relativistic, Cartesian simulation from the IllinoisGRMHD code. We introduce new methods for estimating overall dynamo alpha and turbulent diffusivity effects as well as measures of the dominance of non-axisymmetric components of energies and fluxes within the disk interior. We attempt closure models of the dynamo EMF using least squares fitting, considering both models where coefficient tensors are functions of space and more global, covariant models. None of these models are judged satisfactory, but we are able to draw conclusions on what sorts of generalizations are and are not promising.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02899v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew D. Duez, Courtney L. Cadenhead, Zachariah B. Etienne, Bernard Kelly, Leonardo R. Werneck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining logarithmic $f(R,T)$ model using Dark Energy density parameter $\Omega_{\Lambda}$ and Hubble parameter $H_0$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.10610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.10610v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Of many extended theories of gravity, $f(R,T)$ gravity has gained reasonable interest in recent times as it provides interesting results in cosmology. Logarithmic corrections in modified theories of gravity has been studied extensively. In this work, we considered logarithmic correction to the trace term T and take the functional form as $f(R,T)=R + 16 \pi G \alpha \ln T$ where $\alpha$ is a free parameter. The free parameter is constrained using dark energy density parameter $\Omega_{\Lambda}$ and Hubble parameter $H_0$. The lower bound is found to be $\alpha \ge - 9.85 \times 10^{-29}$. The cosmological implications are also studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.10610v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.26565/2312-4334-2024-3-02</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>East Eur. J. Phys. 3, 21 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Biswajit Deb, Atri Deshamukhya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Gravitational-waves from Extreme Mass Ratio Inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Space-based gravitational wave detectors like TianQin or LISA could observe extreme-mass-ratio-inspirals (EMRIs) at millihertz frequencies. The accurate identification of these EMRI signals from the data plays a crucial role in enabling in-depth study of astronomy and physics. We aim at the identification stage of the data analysis, with the aim to extract key features of the signal from the data, such as the evolution of the orbital frequency, as well as to pinpoint the parameter range that can fit the data well for the subsequent parameter inference stage. In this manuscript, we demonstrated the identification of EMRI signals without any additional prior information on physical parameters. High-precision measurements of EMRI signals have been achieved, using a hierarchical search. It combines the search for physical parameters that guide the subsequent parameter inference, and a semi-coherent search with phenomenological waveforms that reaches precision levels down to $10^{-4}$ for the phenomenological waveform parameters $\omega_{0}$, $\dot{\omega}_{0}$, and $\ddot{\omega}_{0}$. As a result, we obtain measurement relative errors of less than 4% for the mass of the massive black hole, while keeping the relative errors of the other parameters within as small as 0.5%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03520v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.124034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 109.12 (2024): 124034</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chang-Qing Ye, Hui-Min Fan, Alejandro Torres-Orjuela, Jian-dong Zhang, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational memory signal from neutrino self-interactions in supernova</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03315v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neutrinos with large self-interactions, arising from exchange of light scalars or vectors with mass $M_\phi\simeq 10{\rm MeV}$, can play a useful role in cosmology for structure formation and solving the Hubble tension. It has been proposed that large self-interactions of neutrinos may change the observed properties of supernova like the neutrino luminosity or the duration of the neutrino burst. In this paper, we study the gravitational wave memory signal arising from supernova neutrinos. Our results reveal that memory signal for self-interacting neutrinos are weaker than free-streaming neutrinos in the high frequency range. Implications for detecting and differentiating between such signals for planned space-borne detectors, DECIGO and BBO, are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03315v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.L061501</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Bhattacharya, Debanjan Bose, Indranil Chakraborty, Arpan Hait, Subhendra Mohanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally-homogeneous Riemann-Cartan geometries with the largest symmetry group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02907v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The symmetry frame formalism is an effective tool for computing the symmetries of a Riemann-Cartan geometry and, in particular, in metric teleparallel geometries. In the case of non-vanishing torsion in a four dimensional Riemann-Cartan geometry, the Minkowski geometry is the only geometry admitting ten affine frame symmetries. Excluding this geometry, the maximal number of affine frame symmetries is seven. A natural question is to ask what four dimensional geometries admit a seven-dimensional group of affine frame symmetries. Such geometries are locally homogeneous and admit the largest isotropy group permitted, and hence are called maximally isotropic. Using the symmetry frame formalism to compute affine frame symmetries along with the additional structure of the torsion tensor, we employ the Cartan-Karlhede algorithm to determine all possible seven-dimensional symmetry groups for Riemann-Cartan geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02907v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0203079</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 65, 072502 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. D. McNutt, R. J. van den Hoogen, A. A. Coley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition of modified thermodynamics of the Kerr-AdS black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13662v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the critical phenomena of Kerr-AdS black holes in the modified first law of thermodynamics. The modified black hole thermodynamics exhibits the van der Waals-like phase structure. All the critical exponents are calculated, and the swallowtail diagram of free energy is plotted. Comparing with existing results, the main difference is the correspondence between thermal quantities of the Kerr-AdS black holes and the van der Waals system. In previous work[16], the correspondence was $(\Omega_HJ)\to (V, P)$. In our work, the correspondence is $(J,{\hat\Omega}_H)\to (V, P)$. This difference results from rotating effect. The modified black hole thermodynamics is associated with rotating observers. The free energy in such reference contains an extra rotating energy. This extra part induces a Legendre transformation in $({\hat\Omega}_H, J)$ cross-section, which yields the different correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13662v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qin Liu, Xiaoning Wu, Xiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Coordinate-Independent Formalism for Detecting High-Frequency Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In an external electric or magnetic field, a gravitational wave (GW) may be converted into electromagnetic radiation. We present a coordinate-invariant framework to describe the GW signal in a detector that is based on this effect, such as cavities for axion searches. In this framework, we pay special attention to the definition of manifestly coordinate-independent expressions for the electromagnetic fields that an external observer would detect. A careful assessment of the detector's perceived motion allows us to treat both its mechanical and its electromagnetic response to the GW consistently. We further introduce well-defined approximations for which this motion may be neglected, and hence provide suggestions on which coordinate frame is suitable to characterise the GW signal in practice. We illustrate our findings in two examples, an infinitesimally thin rod and a spherical electromagnetic cavity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08572v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfram Ratzinger, Sebastian Schenk, Pedro Schwaller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron Star in Covariant $f(Q)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03669v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assuming static and spherically symmetric stars with perfect fluid matter, we used realistic equations of state to study neutron stars in covariant $f(Q)$ gravity. The structure profiles and properties of neutron stars such as mass, radius and compactness are obtained through numerical methods using quadratic, exponential, and logarithmic $f(Q)$ models. The results indicate that nonmetricity affects the interior profile deviations of the star, which in turn influence the properties of stars, as illustrated in the mass-radius relation diagram. This effect allows the star to accommodate either more or less matter compared to GR, resulting in a different total mass. For the quadratic model, we cannot generate larger masses, whereas the other two models can give consistent results for both smaller and larger masses of the observed stars. By tuning model parameters, we obtain $\mathcal{M}-\mathcal{R}$ diagrams that are compatible with observational constraints from NICER and LIGO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03669v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/09/011</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 2024(09), 011</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Azzam Alwan, Tomohiro Inagaki, B. Mishra, S. A. Narawade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory-agnostic searches for non-gravitational modes in black hole ringdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08956v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In any extension of General Relativity (GR), extra fundamental degrees of freedom couple to gravity. Besides deforming GR forecasts in a theory-dependent way, this coupling generically introduces extra modes in the gravitational-wave signal. We propose a novel theory-agnostic test of gravity to search for these nongravitational modes in black hole merger ringdown signals. To leading order in the GR deviations, their frequencies and damping times match those of a test scalar or vector field in a Kerr background, with only amplitudes and phases as free parameters. This test will be highly valuable for future detectors, which will achieve signal-to-noise ratios higher than 100 (and as high as 1000 for space-based detectors such as LISA). Such sensitivity will allow measurement of these modes with amplitude ratios as low as 0.05 for ground-based detectors (and as low as 0.008 for LISA), relative to the fundamental mode, enabling stringent agnostic constraints or detection of scalar/vector modes. By applying this test to GW150914, GW190521, and GW200129, we find that the current evidence for an extra mode is comparable to that for the first gravitational overtone, but its inclusion modifies the inferred remnant spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08956v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Crescimbeni, Xisco Jimenez Forteza, Swetha Bhagwat, Julian Westerweck, Paolo Pani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes in Lorentz gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Black hole solutions are explored in the Lorentz gauge theory of gravity. The fields of the theory are the gauge potential in the adjoint and a scalar in the fundamental representation of the Lorentz group, a metric tensor then emerging as a composite field in a symmetry-broken phase. Three distinct such phases of the theory are considered. In an SO(3) phase, the fundamental field is identified with a generalised Painlev\'e-Gullstrand-Lema\^itre coordinate time. In the static spherically symmetric case it is a stealth scalar, and the general vacuum solution is then parameterised by two constants, one related to the black hole mass and the other to an observer. Also, formulations of pregeometric first order electromagnetism are considered in order to construct a consistent realisation of a charged black hole. In an SO(1,2) phase of the theory, the Schwarzschild solution is realised as a configuration wherein the fundamental field is real outside and imaginary inside the horizon. In this phase the field can be associated with an effective radial pressure resulting in additional singularities and asymptotic non-flatness. Finally, a symmetry-broken phase which would correspond to solutions in an alternative attempt at a Lorentz gauge theory is shown to be incompatible with black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10100v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomi S. Koivisto, Luxi Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wormhole formations in the galactic halos supported by dark matter models and global monopole charge within $f(Q)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper discusses the possibility of traversable wormholes in the galactic region supported by dark matter (DM) models and global monopole charge in the context of $f(Q)$ gravity. To understand the features of the wormholes, we comprehensively studied wormhole solutions with various redshift functions under different $f(Q)$ models. We obtained wormhole shape functions for Pseudo Isothermal (PI) and Navarro-Frenk-White (NFW) DM profiles under linear $f(Q)$ gravity. In contrast, we employed an embedding class I approach for the non-linear $f(Q)$ models to investigate wormholes. We noticed that our obtained shape functions satisfy the flare-out conditions under an asymptotic background for each DM profile. Moreover, we checked the energy conditions at the wormhole throat with a radius $r_0$ and noticed the influences of the global monopole's parameter $\eta$ in the violation of energy conditions, especially null energy conditions. Further, for the non-linear case, we observed that wormhole solutions could not exist for $f(Q)=Q+mQ^n$, $f(Q)=Q+\frac{\beta}{Q}$, and $f(Q)=\alpha_1+\beta_1 \log(Q)$ under embedding class I approach. Finally, we study the amount of exotic matter via the volume integral quantifier technique for the linear $f(Q)$ model, and we confirm that a small amount of exotic matter is required to sustain the traversable wormholes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00507v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjp/s13360-024-05572-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. Plus 139 (2024) 774</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Moreshwar Tayde, P. K. Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new framework for cosmological expansion in a reformulated Newtonian-Like gravity with variable G</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01468v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A Newtonian-like theory inspired by the Brans-Dicke gravitational Lagrangian has been recently proposed in Ref. arXiv:2009.04434(v4). We propose here a new variant of this theory such that the usual Newtonian second law is preserved. The cosmological solutions are analysed and accelerated cosmic expansion can be obtained in pure matter dominated universes. This happens due to the dynamical gravitational coupling of the introduced time varying field. We also analyse the matter density perturbations and find they exhibit an enhanced growth in comparison with the usual Newtonian like behavior in Einstein-de Sitter model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01468v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe S. Esc\'orcio, J\'ulio C. Fabris, J\'unior D. Toniato, Hermano Velten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining the effects of dark matter spikes on eccentric intermediate mass ratio inspirals using N-body simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02275v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies suggest that dark matter (DM) spikes around intermediate-mass black holes could cause observable dephasing in gravitational wave (GW) signals from Intermediate Mass Ratio Inspirals (IMRIs). Previous research primarily used non-self-consistent analytic methods to estimate the impact of DM spikes on eccentric IMRIs. Our study provides the first self-consistent treatment of this phenomenon using $N$-body simulations, incorporating Post-Newtonian effects up to the 2.5 order for accurate and robust results. Contrary to prior works, which posited that the cumulative effect of two-body encounters (dynamical friction; DF) is the primary mechanism for energy dissipation, we reveal that a three-body effect (slingshot mechanism) plays a more significant role in driving the binary system's energy loss and consequent orbital shrinkage. We find that binaries counter-rotating with respect to the DM spike merge faster, while co-rotating binaries merge slower, contrary to expectations from the DF theory. Using Fokker-Planck methods, we also assess the presence and detectability of spikes in realistic environments. When interacting with surrounding materials, DM spikes can have shallower slopes and lower densities than previously considered, leading to smaller signals and lower detection prospects via dephasing. Our results suggest that `deshifting' rather than dephasing might be a more optimistic signature, as it is more robust even in low-density environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02275v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1989</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Diptajyoti Mukherjee, A. Miguel Holgado, Go Ogiya, Hy Trac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Characteristics Near Event Horizons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12028v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate quantum characteristics around Schwarzschild black hole, exploring various quantum resources and their interplay in curved space-time. Our analysis reveals intriguing behaviors of quantum coherence, global and genuine multipartite entanglement, first-order coherence, and mutual information in different scenarios. Initially, we consider three particles shared among Alice, Bob, and Charlie in a Minkowski space far from the event horizon, where these particles are correlated via GHZ-type correlation. While Alice's particle remains in Minkowski space, Bob and Charlie accelerate towards the event horizon, experiencing black hole evaporation and generating antiparticles correlated via the Hawking effect. We employ the Kruskal basis formulation to derive a penta-partite pure state shared among particles inside and outside the event horizon. Investigating different scenarios among particles both inside and outside the event horizon, we observe how quantum resources evolve and distribute among consideration of different particles with Hawking temperature and mode frequency. The trade-off relationship between first-order coherence and concurrence fill persists, indicating the intricate interplay between coherence and entanglement. Notably, the mutual information between external observers and particles inside the black hole becomes non-zero, deepening our understanding of quantum effects in curved space-time and shedding light on the quantum nature of the black hole. We believe that these findings will pave the way for future investigations into the fundamental quantum mechanical aspects of gravity under extreme environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12028v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.064001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 064001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Asad Ali, Saif Al-Kuwari, Mehedad Ghominejad, M. T. Rahim, Dong Wang, Saeed Haddadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A possible late-time transition of $M_B$ inferred via neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The strengthening of tensions in the cosmological parameters has led to a reconsideration of fundamental aspects of standard cosmology. The tension in the Hubble constant can also be viewed as a tension between local and early Universe constraints on the absolute magnitude $M_B$ of Type Ia supernova. In this work, we reconsider the possibility of a variation of this parameter in a model-independent way. We employ neural networks to agnostically constrain the value of the absolute magnitude as well as assess the impact and statistical significance of a variation in $M_B$ with redshift from the Pantheon+ compilation, together with a thorough analysis of the neural network architecture. We find an indication for a possible transition redshift at the $z\approx 1$ region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10502v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Purba Mukherjee, Konstantinos F. Dialektopoulos, Jackson Levi Said, Jurgen Mifsud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of Hawking Evaporation opens new Mass Window for Primordial Black Holes as Dark Matter Candidate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17823v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The energy injection through Hawking evaporation has been used to put strong constraints on primordial black holes as a dark matter candidate at masses below $10^{17}\,\rm{g}$. However, Hawking's semiclassical approximation breaks down at latest after half-decay. Beyond this point, the evaporation could be significantly suppressed, as was shown in recent work. In this study, we review existing cosmological and astrophysical bounds on primordial black holes, taking this effect into account. We show that the constraints disappear completely for a reasonable range of parameters, which opens a new window below $10^{10}\,\rm{g}$ for light primordial black holes as a dark matter candidate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17823v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1098</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, Volume 532, Issue 1, July 2024, Pages 451-459</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Valentin Thoss, Andreas Burkert, Kazunori Kohri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-gravitating solutions in Yang-Mills-Chern-Simons theory coupled to 3D massive gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15569v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study self-gravitating solutions of 3-dimensional massive gravity coupled to Yang-Mills-Chern-Simons gauge theory. Among these, there is a family of asymptotically Warped-Anti de Sitter black holes that come to generalize previous solutions found in the literature and studied in the context of WAdS$_3$/CFT$_2$. We also present self-gravitating solutions to the 3-dimensional Einstein-Yang-Mills theory, as well as other self-gravitating solutions in the presence of higher-curvature terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15569v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Crist\'obal Corral, Daniel Flores-Alfonso, Gast\'on Giribet, Julio Oliva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli Dynamics in Effective Nested Warped Geometry in Four Dimensions and Some Cosmological Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17326v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the effective four-dimensional dynamics of the extra-dimensional moduli fields in curved braneworlds having nested warping, with particular emphasis on the doubly warped model which is interesting in the light of current collider constraints on the mass of the Kaluza-Klein graviton. The presence of a non-zero brane cosmological constant ($\Omega$) naturally induces an effective moduli potential in the four-dimensional action, which shows distinct features in dS ($\Omega&gt;0$) and AdS ($\Omega&lt;0$) branches. For the observationally interesting case of dS 4-branes, a metastable minimum in the potential arises along the first modulus, with no minima along the higher moduli. The underlying nested geometry also leads to interesting separable forms of the non-canonical kinetic terms in the Einstein frame, where the brane curvature directly impacts the kinetic properties of only the first modulus. The non-canonicity of the scenario has been illustrated via an explicit computation of the field space curvature. We subsequently explore the ability of curved multiply warped geometries to drive inflation with an in-built exit mechanism, by considering predominant slow roll along each modular direction on a case-by-case basis. We find slow roll on top of the metastable plateau along the first modular direction to be the most viable scenario, with the higher-dimensional moduli parametrically tuning the height of the potential without significant impact on the inflationary observables. On the other hand, while slow roll along the higher moduli can successfully inflate the background and eventually lead to an exit, consistency with observations seemingly requires unphysical hierarchies among the extra-dimensional radii, thus disfavouring such scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17326v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP09(2024)003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 09 (2024) 003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arko Bhaumik, Soumitra SenGupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperboloidal Method for Quasinormal Modes of Non-Relativistic Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01487v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The recently reported compactified hyperboloidal method has found wide use in the numerical computation of quasinormal modes, with implications for fields as diverse as gravitational physics and optics. We extend this intrinsically relativistic method into the non-relativistic domain, demonstrating its use to calculate the quasinormal modes of the Schr\"odinger equation and solve related bound-state problems. We also describe how to further generalize this method, offering a perspective on the importance of non-relativistic quasinormal modes for the programme of black hole spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01487v4</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fphy.2024.1457543</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Front. Phys. 12:1457543 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Burgess, Friedrich Koenig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General relativistic magnetohydrodynamic simulations of accretion onto exotic compact objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09893v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Some of the extensions to general relativity and to the Standard Model of particle physics predict families of hypothetical compact objects, collectively known as exotic compact objects (ECOs). This category can be defined to encompass non-Kerr black holes both within and beyond general relativity, as well as horizonless compact objects such as boson stars. In order to model observational signatures and identify possible detections, it is crucial to understand the interaction between these objects and their surrounding medium, usually plasmas described by the equations of general relativistic magnetohydrodynamics (GRMHD). To this end, we review the existent literature on GRMHD simulations of accretion onto these objects. These cover a variety of objects and accretion patterns. We conclude by listing possible directions to continue exploring this relatively young field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09893v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'ector R. Olivares-S\'anchez, Prashant Kocherlakota, Carlos A. R. Herdeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beltrami fields, dispersive electromagnetic waves and gravitational spheromaks from chiral anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14990v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this note we focus on the backreaction effects due to the chiral anomaly. The chiral anomaly gives rise to certain modifications in the conserved currents. In the case of the Maxwell gauge fields there appears a new contribution to the electric current proportional to the background magnetic field. This phenomenon is known as the chiral magnetic effect and it is widely discussed in the current literature. In the case of the gravitational field, the anomaly, as we show here, induces a new contribution to the stress-energy tensor. We analyze the possible manifestations of these modifications in the gravitational field and in hydrodynamics in the chiral media. We also make some comments regarding the backreaction effects in electrodynamics in the chiral media. In each of these directions we observe the systematical appearance of the Beltrami type fields. In electrodynamics or in hydrodynamics the Beltrami field (e.g., magnetic field or fluid velocity) is a vector that is parallel to its own curl. We suggest a generalization of the Beltrami fields for the tensorial gravitational perturbations. The respective solutions to the gravitational equations we call gravitational spheromaks by analogy with a similar phenomenon in electrodynamics. In the modified hydrodynamics in the chiral media the vorticity is asymptotically a Beltrami vector field in a generalized Gromeka-Beltrami flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14990v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey N. Solodukhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
