<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 01:40:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo generalized Ricci-recurrent spacetimes and modified gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce and characterize a pseudo generalized Ricci-recurrent spacetimes and produce an example to verify the existence of such a spacetime. Then we demonstrate that a conformally flat generalized Ricci-recurrent spacetime with certain condition is a pseudo quasi-Einstein spacetime. Besides, it is proved that a pseudo generalized Ricci-recurrent generalized Robertson-Walker spacetime represents a perfect fluid spacetime. Lastly, we study the impact of this spacetime under $f(\mathcal{R},T^2)$ and $f\left(\mathcal{R}^{\ast}\right)$ gravity scenario and deduce several energy conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07104v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0217732324500627</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Modern Physics Letters A (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Krishnendu De, Uday Chand De</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Parameter Estimation for Merging Massive Black Hole Binaries Using ODE-Based Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Detecting the coalescences of massive black hole binaries (MBHBs) is one of the primary targets for space-based gravitational wave observatories such as LISA, Taiji, and Tianqin. The fast and accurate parameter estimation of merging MBHBs is of great significance for both astrophysics and the global fitting of all resolvable sources. However, such analyses entail significant computational costs. To address these challenges, inspired by the latest progress in generative models, we proposed a novel artificial intelligence (AI) based parameter estimation method called Variance Preserving Flow Matching Posterior Estimation (VPFMPE). Specifically, we utilize triangular interpolation to maintain variance over time, thereby constructing a transport path for training continuous normalization flows. Compared to the simple linear interpolation method used in flow matching to construct the optimal transport path, our approach better captures continuous temporal variations, making it more suitable for the parameter estimation of MBHBs. Additionally, we creatively introduce a parameter transformation method based on the symmetry in the detector's response function. This transformation is integrated within VPFMPE, allowing us to train the model using a simplified dataset, and then perform parameter estimation on more general data, hence also acting as a crucial factor in improving the training speed. In conclusion, for the first time, within a comprehensive and reasonable parameter range, we have achieved a complete and unbiased 11-dimensional rapid inference for MBHBs in the presence of astrophysical confusion noise using ODE-based generative models. In the experiments based on simulated data, our model produces posterior distributions comparable to those obtained by nested sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07125v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Liang, Minghui Du, He Wang, Yuxiang Xu, Chang Liu, Xiaotong Wei, Peng Xu, Li-e Qiang, Ziren Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal Love numbers and Green's functions in black hole space-times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tidal interactions play a crucial role in deciphering gravitational wave signals emitted by the coalescence of binary systems. They are usually quantified by a set of complex coefficients which include tidal Love numbers, describing the conservative response to an external perturbation. In the static case, these are found to vanish exactly for asymptotically flat black holes in general relativity in four space-time dimensions, and recently they have been generalized to dynamical interactions. In the context of response theory, the retarded Green's function provides the complete description of the behavior of dynamical systems. In this work we investigate the relation between Love numbers and Green's functions, and highlight the relevance of radiation reaction effects to their connection. As a special case, we discuss BTZ black holes, where the absence of radiative modes allows us to make a direct link between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07156v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio De Luca, Alice Garoffolo, Justin Khoury, Mark Trodden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shadow of slowly rotating Kalb-Ramond black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real astronomical objects possess spin, yet deriving exact solutions for rotating black holes within gravitational theories is a formidable challenge. To understand the shadow of rotating black holes in Lorentz-violating spacetimes induced by antisymmetric tensor fields, known as Kalb-Ramond (KR) fields, we have focused on the slow-rotation approximation framework. Using this approach, we have obtained first-order rotation series solutions, which describe slowly rotating KR black holes. For this solutions, we have plotted the black hole shadow contours under various parameters using the numerical backward ray-tracing method. As the Lorentz-violating parameter increases, not only the apparent size of the black hole shadow decreases, but also the effects of rotation, such as the D-shaped structure and frame-dragging, are amplified. Furthermore, the KR field also enhances gravitational lensing, causing the shadow to occupy a larger area within the photon ring. This distinctive feature can differentiate KR gravity from general relativity. Additionally, using the latest observational data from EHT on M87* and Sgr A*, we have provided constraints on the Lorentz-violating parameter of rotating KR black holes. We found that, compared to static black holes, rotating black holes allow for the presence of stronger Lorentz violation effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07416v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wentao Liu, Di Wu, Jieci Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing new fundamental fields with Extreme Mass Ratio Inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine extreme mass ratio inspirals (EMRIs), where a charged compact object spirals into a supermassive black hole, in modified gravity theories with additional scalar or vector fields. Using the Teukolsky and generalized Sasaki-Nakamura formalisms, we provide the post-Newtonian expansion of the energy flux of the vector waves up to $O(v^5)$ beyond the quadrupole formula in the weak field and numerically calculate the energy flux in the strong field for a charged particle moving in circular orbits. Our findings reveal a degeneracy in the scalar and vector charge parameters for weak-field, slow-motion orbits. However, for strong-field, fast-motion orbits close to the innermost stable circular orbit, we observe distinct behaviors between scalar and vector fields. We investigate the potential of using EMRIs detected by space-based gravitational-wave detectors, such as the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna to identify whether a black hole carries a scalar or vector charge. The influence of scalar and vector flux on the orbital evolution and tensor GW phase can not help us distinguish scalar and vector fields. However, extra polarizations emitted by the scalar or vector field can break the correlations between the scalar field and vector field and then help us distinguish the scalar and vector field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07449v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Zhang, Yungui Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic rods and elastic spinning rings as gravitational wave detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linearised relativistic elasticity equations of motion are considered for a rod and a spinning ring encountering a gravitational wave. In the case of the rod, the equations reduce to a wave equation with appropriate boundary conditions. Using Fourier transforms, the resonant frequencies are found and an explicit distributional solution is given, both for a plus- and a cross-polarised gravitational wave. In the case of the spinning ring, the equations are coupled wave equations with periodic boundary conditions. Using a Fourier series expansion, the system of wave equations is recast as a family of ordinary differential equations for the Fourier coefficients, which are then solved via Fourier transforms. The resonant frequencies are found, including simple approximate expressions for slowly rotating rings, and an explicit distributional solution is obtained in the case of the non-spinning ring. Interestingly, it is possible to tune the resonant frequencies by adjusting the angular velocity of the spinning ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07547v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Nat\'ario, Amol Sasane, Rodrigo Vicente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonic and fermionic coherence of N-partite states in the background of a dilaton black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the N-partite coherences of GHZ and W states for free bosonic and fermionic fields when any n observers hover near the event horizon of a Garfinkle-Horowitz-Strominger (GHS) dilaton black hole. We derive the more general analytical expressions for N-partite coherence, encompassing both physically accessible and inaccessible coherences in the context of the dilaton black hole. It has been found that the coherence of the bosonic field is greater than that of the fermionic field, while the entanglement of the fermionic field is greater than that of the bosonic field in dilaton spacetime. Additionally, the coherence of the W state is greater than that of the GHZ state, whereas the entanglement of the GHZ state is greater than that of the W state in curved spacetime. These results suggest that we should utilize suitable quantum resources and different types of particles for relativistic quantum information tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07688v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Mei Li, Shu-Min Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational ringdown in the Minimal Theory of Massive Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work focuses on gravitational perturbations of black holes in the self-accelerating branch of the Minimal Theory of Massive Gravity (MTMG). This theory is a healthy extension of GR which displays the feature of massive tensor modes, without additional polarizations, strong-coupling issues nor requiring screening mechanisms. We proceed by implementing a newly developed technique that, instead of considering a second-order Schr\"odinger-like reformulation of perturbation equations, relies on a first-order formulation and solves it asymptotically, before numerically deriving the quasi-normal modes. We find that the black holes of MTMG are stable, and that their quasi-normal modes smoothly differ from the GR ones, for non-vanishing values of the graviton mass. This work hence confirms the fact that GR is a smooth limit of MTMG, and opens the exciting possibility of a clean test, performed for instance by the LISA detector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07792v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Roussille, Fran\c{c}ois Larrouturou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Gravitational Wave Discoveries Enabled by Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The detection of gravitational waves has revolutionized our understanding of the universe, offering unprecedented insights into its dynamics. A major goal of gravitational wave data analysis is to speed up the detection and parameter estimation process using machine learning techniques, in light of an anticipated surge in detected events that would render traditional methods impractical. Here, we present the first detections of new gravitational-wave candidate events in data from a network of interferometric detectors enabled by machine learning. We discuss several new enhancements of our ResNet-based deep learning code, AresGW, that increased its sensitivity, including a new hierarchical classification of triggers, based on different noise and frequency filters. The enhancements resulted in a significant reduction in the false alarm rate, allowing AresGW to surpass traditional pipelines in the number of detected events in its effective training range (single source masses between 7 and 50 solar masses and source chirp masses between 10 and 40 solar masses), when the new detections are included. We calculate the astrophysical significance of events detected with AresGW using a logarithmic ranking statistic and injections into O3 data. Furthermore, we present spectrograms, parameter estimation, and reconstruction in the time domain for our new candidate events and discuss the distribution of their properties. In addition, the AresGW code exhibited very good performance when tested across various two-detector setups and on observational data from the O1 and O2 observing periods. Our findings underscore the remarkable potential of AresGW as a fast and sensitive detection algorithm for gravitational-wave astronomy, paving the way for a larger number of future discoveries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07820v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra E. Koloniari, Evdokia C. Koursoumpa, Paraskevi Nousi, Paraskevas Lampropoulos, Nikolaos Passalis, Anastasios Tefas, Nikolaos Stergioulas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The principled-parameterized approach to gravitational collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New physics beyond General Relativity impacts black-hole spacetimes. The effects of new physics can be investigated in a largely theory-agnostic way by following the principled-parameterized approach. In this approach, a classical black-hole metric is upgraded by following a set of principles, such as regularity, i.e., the absence of curvature singularities. We expect these principles to hold in many theories beyond General Relativity. In the present paper, we implement this approach for time-dependent spacetimes describing gravitational collapse. We find that the Vaidya spacetime becomes regular through the same modification of the spacetime metric as stationary black-hole spacetimes [1-3]. We investigate null geodesics and find indications that the modification is even sufficient to render null geodesics future complete. Finally, we find that the modification of the spacetime structure results in violations of the null energy condition in a finite region inside the apparent horizon of the black hole that forms. Null geodesics are attracted to the boundary of this region, such that the new-physics effects are shielded from asymptotic observers. An exception occurs, if the classical spacetime has a naked singularity. Then, the upgraded spacetime is singularity-free and null geodesics from the regular core can escape towards asymptotic observers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07862v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'elo\"ise Delaporte, Astrid Eichhorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Third Structure Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We re-consider the graviton self-energy induced by a loop of massless, minimally coupled scalars on de Sitter background. On flat space background it can be represented as a sum of two tensor differential operators acting on scalar structure functions. On a general background these tensor differential operators can be constructed from the linearized Ricci scalar and the linearized Weyl tensor. However, in cosmology one requires a third contribution which we derive here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07864v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. P. Miao (NCKU), N. C. Tsamis (U. of Crete), R. P. Woodard (U. of Florida), B. Yesilyurt (U. of Florida)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal modes and gray-body factors of regular black holes in asymptotically safe gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, Bonanno et al. (2024) presented an explicit metric describing the exterior of a collapsing dust ball within the framework of asymptotically safe gravity. Based on this metric, we investigate in detail the properties of the quasinormal mode (QNM) spectra for test massless scalar, vector, and Dirac fields. We find accurate values for the fundamental QNM frequency and the first overtones, demonstrating the appearance of a peculiar spiral-like behavior of the overtones compared to the fundamental modes. Additionally, we study black hole shadows and show that they align with EHT observations. Finally, we study the grey-body factors and provide explicit lower bound estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07892v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Stashko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curved-spacetime dynamics of spin-$\tfrac{1}{2}$ particles in superposed states from a WKB approximation of the Dirac equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of spin-$\tfrac{1}{2}$ particles that are freely propagating in superposed states in curved spacetime. We first make use of a Wentzel-Kramers-Brillouin approximation of the Dirac equation in curved spacetime to extract the corresponding Mathisson-Papapetrou-Dixon equations that describe the deviation from geodesic motion as well as the spin precession of such particles. We then discuss, in light of our results, the case of flavour neutrinos which are, by nature, a superposition of mass eigenstates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07139v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Hammad, M. Simard, R. Saadati, A. Landry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warped AdS$_3$ black hole thermodynamics and the charged Cardy formula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the thermodynamic properties of black holes with warped AdS$_3$ asymptotics in topologically massive gravity. The holographically dual theory, often referred to as warped CFT$_2$, exhibits a single copy of the Virasoro-Kac-Moody algebra. Consequently, the asymptotic density of states in the right-moving sector is described by the charged Cardy formula that we review in detail. By defining specific linear combinations of the gravitational thermodynamic potentials, we are able to present the gravitational left- and right-moving on-shell actions directly in the grand-canonical ensemble. This allows us to demonstrate that, apart from the charged Cardy behavior in the right-moving sector, the dual field theory exhibits an additional frozen left-moving state giving rise to non-zero entropy contribution. Our findings elucidate the nature of warped CFTs and reveal subtle yet fundamental differences from the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07150v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiril Hristov, Riccardo Giordana Pozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping spinning two body problem in dynamical Chern-Simons gravity using worldline QFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we compute the WQFT partition function, specifically the eikonal phase in a black hole scattering event in the dynamical Chern-Simons theory, using the techniques of spinning worldline quantum field theory. We consider the scattering of spinning black holes and highlight the necessary details for the calculation of the partition function. We present the $\epsilon$-expansion of the essential two-loop integrals using Integration-by-Parts (IBP) reduction and differential equation techniques, which we then utilize to compute the linear-in-order spin eikonal phase up to 3PM. Additionally, we discuss the dependence of the phase on the spin orientations of the black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07195v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Bhattacharyya, Debodirna Ghosh, Saptaswa Ghosh, Sounak Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spatial correlations between pulsars for interfering sources in Pulsar Timing Array and evidence for gravitational-wave background in NANOGrav 15-year data set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pulsar timing arrays (PTAs), aimed at detecting gravitational waves (GWs) in the $1\sim 100$ nHz range, have recently made significant strides. Compelling evidence has emerged for a common spectrum signal spatially correlated among pulsars, following a Hellings-Downs (HD) pattern, which is crucial for detecting a gravitational-wave background (GWB). However, the HD curve is expected for discrete and non-interfering sources, which is unlikely to hold in realistic scenarios with potential interference among numerous GW sources, such as the supermassive black-hole binaries. Incorporating interference was previously expected to introduce an irreducible uncertainty (known as "cosmic variance") in discerning the HD correlation; however, our work reveals how this interference generates measurable frequency-dependent spatial correlations distinct from the HD curve. The spatial correlations for interfering sources (referred to as "ISC") still exhibit contributions in the quadrupole and higher orders, resembling the HD correlation and encoding the nature of GW radiations. We apply these novel correlations to search for a GWB in the NANOGrav 15-year data set. In an optimistic estimation, our findings show a Bayes factor of $33.7\pm 3.2$ comparing ISC to the HD correlation, and an improvement in optimal statistic signal-to-noise ratio from $4.9\pm 1.1$ for the HD correlation to $6.6\pm 1.7$ for the ISC, highlighting the significant enhancement in evidence for detecting a GWB through incorporating interference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07319v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Mei Wu, Yan-Chen Bi, Qing-Guo Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the cosmic distance duality relation using strong gravitational lensing time delays and Type Ia supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07336v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive test of the cosmic distance duality relation (DDR) using a combination of strong gravitational lensing (SGL) time delay measurements and Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) data. We investigate three different parameterizations of potential DDR violations. To bridge the gap between SGL and SNe Ia datasets, we implement an artificial neural network (ANN) approach to reconstruct the distance modulus of SNe Ia. Our analysis uniquely considers both scenarios where the absolute magnitude of SNe Ia ($M_B$) is treated as a free parameter and where it is fixed to a Cepheid-calibrated value. Using a sample of six SGL systems and the Pantheon+ SNe Ia dataset, we find no statistically significant evidence for DDR violations across all parameterizations. The consistency of our findings across different parameterizations not only reinforces confidence in the standard DDR but also demonstrates the robustness of our analytical approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07336v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Zhao Qi, Yi-Fan Jiang, Wan-Ting Hou, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the origin of escort distributions for q-entropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07499v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an argument about the origin of escort distributions used in conjunction with the q-entropy in non-additive thermo-statistics. The origin of the escort distributions is ascribed to the fact that the effective statistical description of the underlying system is provided by the measured Gromov-Hausdorff limit of a sequence of manifolds having a warped product metric structure. We interpret the entropic parameter \ q \ appearing in escort distributions as a "dimension" related to the fibration structure of the underlying phase spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07499v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Kalogeropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On boundary conditions for linearised Einstein's equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the properties of a fairly large class of boundary conditions for the linearised Einstein equations in the Riemannian setting, ones which generalise the linearised counterpart of boundary conditions proposed by Anderson. Through the prism of the quest to quantise gravitational waves in curved spacetimes, we study their properties from the point of view of ellipticity, gauge invariance, and the existence of a spectral gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07576v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aml.2024.109210</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Mathematics Letters (2024), 109210</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Capoferri, Simone Murro, Gabriel Schmid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Numerical Calculation of Entanglement Entropy in de Sitter Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07811v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The entanglement entropy of a massless scalar field in de Sitter space depends on multiple scales, such as the radius of the entangling surface, the Hubble constant and the UV cutoff. We perform a high-precision numerical calculation using a lattice model in order to determine the dependence on these scales in the Bunch-Davies vacuum. We derive the leading de Sitter corrections to the flat-space entanglement entropy for subhorizon entangling radii. We analyze the structure of the finite-size effects and we show that the contribution to the entanglement entropy of the sector of the theory with vanishing angular momentum depends logarithmically on the size of the overall system, which extends beyond the horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07811v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Boutivas, Dimitrios Katsinis, Georgios Pastras, Nikolaos Tetradis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Entropy as a Probe Beyond the Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The entanglement entropy of a free field in de Sitter space is enhanced by the squeezing of its modes. We show analytically that the expansion induces a term in the entanglement entropy that depends logarithmically on the size of the overall system, which may extend beyond the horizon. In cosmology the size of the system can be identified with the size of a spatially finite universe, or with the wavelength of the first mode that exited the horizon in the beginning of inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07824v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Boutivas, Dimitrios Katsinis, Georgios Pastras, Nikolaos Tetradis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probe and Prejudice: Classification of compact objects and model comparison using EOS knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07837v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nuclear theory and experiments, alongside astrophysical observations, constrain the equation of state (EOS) of supranuclear-dense matter. Conversely, knowledge of the EOS allows an improved interpretation of nuclear or astrophysical data. In this article, we use several established constraints on the EOS and the new NICER measurement of PSR J0437-4715 to comment on the nature of the primary companion in GW230529 and the companion of PSR J0514-4002E. We find that, with a probability of $\gtrsim 84\%$ and $\gtrsim 68\%$, respectively, both objects are black holes. These likelihoods increase to above $95\%$ when one uses GW170817's remnant as an upper limit on the TOV mass. We also demonstrate that the current knowledge of the EOS substantially disfavors high masses and radii for PSR J0030+0451, inferred recently when combining NICER with XMM-Newton background data and using particular hot-spot models. Finally, we also use our obtained EOS knowledge to comment on measurements of the nuclear symmetry energy, finding that the large value predicted by the PREX-II measurement displays some mild tension with other constraints on the EOS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07837v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hauke Koehn, Thibeau Wouters, Henrik Rose, Peter T. H. Pang, Rahul Somasundaram, Ingo Tews, Tim Dietrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galactic Halos and rotating bosonic dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rotating bosonic dark matter halos are considered as potential candidates for modeling dark matter in galactic halos. These bosonic dark matter halos can be viewed as a dilute and very extended version of bosonic stars, and the methods used for the calculation and analysis of the latter objects can be directly applied. Bosonic stars, a hypothetical type of astrophysical objects, are categorized into two primary families, based on the nature of the particles composing them: Einstein-Klein-Gordon stars and Proca stars. We examine various models from both families and the rotation curves which their contribution induces in different galaxies, to identify the most plausible candidates that explain the flattening of orbital velocities observed in galactic halos. By exploring different combinations of our dark matter models with observable galactic features, we propose an interesting source to compensate for the apparent lack of matter in dwarf and spiral galaxies, providing a possible explanation for this longstanding astronomical puzzle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07839v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Castelo Mourelle, Christoph Adam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Litmus tests of the flat $\Lambda$CDM model and model-independent measurement of $H_0r_\mathrm{d}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07847v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this analysis we apply a model-independent framework to test the flat $\Lambda$CDM cosmology using simulated SNIa data from the upcoming Large Synoptic Survey Telescope (LSST) and combined with simulated Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) five-years Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) data. We adopt an iterative smoothing technique to reconstruct the expansion history from SNIa data, which, when combined with BAO measurements, facilitates a comprehensive test of the Universe's curvature and the nature of dark energy. The analysis is conducted under three different mock true cosmologies: a flat $\Lambda$CDM universe, a universe with a notable curvature ($\Omega_{k,0} = 0.1$), and one with dynamically evolving dark energy. Each cosmology demonstrates different kinds and varying degrees of deviation from the standard model predictions. We forecast that our reconstruction technique can constrain cosmological parameters, such as the curvature ($\Omega_{k0}$) and $H_0 r_\mathrm{d}$, with a precision of approximately 0.52\% for $H_0 r_\mathrm{d}$ and between 0.032 to 0.037 for $\Omega_{k0}$, competitive with current cosmic microwave background constraints, without assuming any form of dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07847v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin L'Huillier, Ayan Mitra, Arman Shafieloo, Ryan E. Keeley, Hanwool Koo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity of a double null coordinate system for Kerr-Newman-de Sitter spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2008.13513v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a double null coordinate system $(u,v,\theta_\star,\phi_\star)$ for Kerr-Newman-de Sitter spacetimes and prove that the two-spheres given by the intersection of the hypersurfaces $u=\mbox{constant}$ and $v=\mbox{constant}$ are $C^\infty$ in Boyer-Lindquist coordinates (including at the "poles"). The null coordinates allow one to immediately extend some results previously proven for Kerr. As an example, we illustrate how Sbierski's result, for the wave equation on the black hole interior, for Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m and Kerr spacetimes, applies to Kerr-Newman-de Sitter spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2008.13513v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s40863-024-00421-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sao Paulo Journal of Mathematical Sciences, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anne T. Franzen, Pedro M. Gir\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Finslerian Wormhole Models in $f(\mathcal{R},\mathcal{T})$ Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.09788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.09788v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article explores wormhole solutions within the framework of Finsler geometry and the modified gravity theory. Modifications in gravitational theories, such as $f(\mathcal{R}, \mathcal{T})$ gravity, propose alternatives that potentially avoid the exotic requirements. We derive the field equations to examine the conditions for Finslerian wormhole existence and investigate geometrical and material characteristics of static wormholes using a polynomial shape function in Finslerian space-time. Furthermore, we address energy condition violations for different Finsler parameters graphically. We conclude that the proposed models, which assume a constant redshift function, satisfy the necessary geometric constraints and energy condition violations indicating the presence of exotic matter at the wormhole throat. The results are validated through analytical solutions and 3-D visualizations, contributing to the broader understanding of wormholes in Finsler-modified gravity contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.09788v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yashwanth B. R., Narasimhamurthy S. K., Z. Nekouee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological classes of higher-dimensional black holes in massive gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13286v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study topological numbers for five-, six- and seven-dimensional anti-de Sitter black holes in the ghost-free massive gravity. We find that when the black holes are charged, they have the same topological number. The topological numbers for the uncharged black holes are 0 or 1, and the specific values are determined by the values of the black holes' parameters. Since $k$ and $c_ 0^2c_2 m^2 $ appear together in the generalized free energy in the form of $k +c_ 0^2c_2 m^2 $, where $k$ characterizes the horizon curvature and $c_2 m^2 $ is the coefficient of the second term of massive potential associated with the graviton mass, this result is applicable to the black holes with the spherical, Ricci flat or hyperbolic horizons. This work shows that the parameters of the ghost-free massive gravity play an important role in topological classes of black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13286v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-023-11983-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C (2023) 83:872</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Deyou Chen, Yucheng He, Jun Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering and absorption by extra-dimensional black holes with GUP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09536v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Schwarzschild-Tangherlini black hole to investigate the process of scalar wave scattering by the black hole in a spacetime of (d + 1) dimensions and also with the generalized uncertainty principle (GUP). In this scenario, we analytically determine the phase shift and explore the effect of extra dimensions by calculating the differential scattering and absorption cross-section by applying the partial wave method at low and high-frequency limits. We show at high dimensions that the absorption is not zero as the mass parameter approaches zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09536v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2024.116617</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NPB, 116617 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Anacleto, J. A. V. Campos, F. A. Brito, E. Maciel, E. Passos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Future global existence of homogeneous solutions to the Einstein-Boltzmann system with soft potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03209v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the Cauchy problem for the Einstein-Boltzmann system with soft potentials in a cosmological setting. We assume the Bianchi I symmetry to describe a spatially homogeneous, but anisotropic universe and consider a cosmological constant $ \Lambda &gt; 0 $ to describe an accelerated expansion of the universe. For the Boltzmann equation we introduce a new weight function and apply the method of Illner and Shinbrot to obtain the future global existence of spatially homogeneous, small solutions. For the Einstein equations we assume that the initial value of the Hubble variable is close to $ ( \Lambda / 3 )^{ 1 / 2 } $. We obtain the future global existence and asymptotic behavior of spatially homogeneous solutions to the Einstein-Boltzmann system with soft potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03209v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ho Lee, Ernesto Nungesser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of fundamental constants from a spacetime-based perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09249v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit Duff, Okun, and Veneziano's divergent views on the number of fundamental constants and argue that the issue can be set to rest by having spacetime as the starting point. This procedure disentangles the resolution in what depends on the assumed spacetime (whether relativistic or not) from the theories built over it. By defining that the number of fundamental constants equals the minimal number of independent standards necessary to express all observables, as assumed by Duff, Okun, and Veneziano, it is shown that the same units fixed by the apparatuses used to construct the spacetimes are enough to express all observables of the physical laws defined over them. As a result, the number of fundamental constants equals two in Galilei spacetime and one in relativistic spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09249v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George E. A. Matsas, Vicente Pleitez, Alberto Saa, Daniel A. T. Vanzella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing the metric in group field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10016v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a group field theory (GFT) for quantum gravity coupled to four massless scalar fields, using these matter fields to define a (relational) coordinate system. We exploit symmetries of the GFT action, in particular under shifts in the values of the scalar fields, to derive a set of classically conserved currents, and show that the same conservation laws hold exactly at the quantum level regardless of the choice of state. We propose a natural interpretation of the conserved currents which implies that the matter fields always satisfy the Klein--Gordon equation in GFT. We then observe that in our matter reference frame, the same conserved currents can be used to extract all components of an effective GFT spacetime metric. Finally, we apply this construction to the simple example of a spatially flat homogeneous and isotropic universe, where we derive an effective Friedmann equation directly from this metric. The Friedmann equation displays a bounce and a late-time limit equivalent to general relativity with a single scalar field. Our proposal goes substantially beyond the GFT literature in which only specific geometric quantities such as the total volume or volume perturbations could be defined, opening up the possibility to study more general geometries as emerging from GFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10016v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad5bb6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Steffen Gielen, Lisa Mickel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbation Spectra of Warm Inflation in $f(Q, T)$ Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03446v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the warm inflationary scenario within the context of the linear version of f (Q, T ) gravity, coupled with both the inflaton scalar field and the radiation field, under the conditions of the strong dissipation regime. First, we calculate the modified Friedmann equations and the modified slow-roll parameters. Subsequently, we apply the slow-roll approximations to derive the scalar power spectrum and the tensor power spectrum. Also, we develop formulations of the scalar and tensor perturbations for the $f(Q, T)$ gravity with the warm inflation scenario. Furthermore, we scrutinize two different forms of the dissipation coefficient, a constant and a function of the inflaton field, to determine the scalar spectral index, the tensor-to-scalar ratio and the temperature for the power-law potential case. By imposing some constraints on the free parameters of the model, we attain results in good agreement with both the Planck 2018 data and the joint Planck, BK15 and BAO data for the tensor-to-scalar ratio, and consistent results aligned with the Planck 2018 data for the scalar spectral index. In addition, the obtained results are within the range of observational data for the amplitude of the scalar power spectrum. Consequently, we are able to revive the power-law potential that was previously ruled out by observational data. Moreover, for both dissipation coefficients, the model leads to a scalar spectral index with the blue and red tilts in agreement with the WMAP three years data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03446v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad554a</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Shiravand, Mehrdad Farhoudi, Parviz Goodarzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole capture, gravitational wave beats, and the nuclear equation of state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01838v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs), if captured by neutron stars (NSs), would emit a characteristic gravitational wave (GW) signal as they orbit inside the host star. We identify a specific and qualitatively new feature of these signals, namely quasi-periodic beats caused by the precession of noncircular PBH orbits. We demonstrate numerically and analytically that the beat frequency depends rather sensitively on the NS structure, so that hypothetical future observations with next-generation GW detectors would provide valuable constraints on the nuclear equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01838v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas W. Baumgarte, Stuart L. Shapiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Excitement Across the Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14908v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An Unruh-DeWitt (UDW) detector falling radially into a four-dimensional Schwarzschild black hole, coupled linearly to a massless scalar field that has been prepared in the Hartle-Hawking or Unruh state, has recently been shown to exhibit a local extremum in its transition probability near the black hole horizon [K.K. Ng et al., New J. Phys. 24 (2022) 103018]. We show that a similar phenomenon is present in the transition rate of a UDW detector falling radially into a spinless Ba\~nados-Teitelboim-Zanelli (BTZ) black hole, with the scalar field prepared in the Hartle-Hawking state. We give extensive numerical results as a function of the detector's energy gap, the black hole's mass, and the detector's drop-off radius. Our results suggest that the effect is robust, motivating a search for a similar effect in other black hole spacetimes, and calling for an explanation of the physical origin of the effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14908v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.025002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 025002 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mar\'ia R. Preciado-Rivas, Manar Naeem, Robert B. Mann, Jorma Louko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexadecapole at the heart of nonlinear electromagnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08909v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In classical Maxwell's electromagnetism, monopole term of the electric field is proportional to $r^{-2}$, while higher order multipole terms, sourced by anisotropic sources, fall-off faster. However, in nonlinear electromagnetism even a spherically symmetric field has multipole-like contributions. We prove that the leading subdominant term of the electric field, defined by nonlinear electromagnetic Lagrangian obeying Maxwellian weak field limit, in a static, spherically symmetric, asymptotically flat spacetime, is of the order $O(r^{-6})$ as $r \to \infty$. Moreover, using Lagrange inversion theorem and Fa\`a di Bruno's formula, we derive the series expansion of the electric field from the Taylor series of an analytic electromagnetic Lagrangian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08909v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad5c34</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quantum Grav. 41 (2024) 157002</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ana Bokuli\'c, Tajron Juri\'c, Ivica Smoli\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Degrees of Freedom in modified Teleparallel Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14184v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I discuss the issue of degrees of freedom in modified teleparallel gravity. These theories do have an extra structure on top of the usual (pseudo)Riemannian manifold, that of a flat parallel transport. This structure is absolutely abstract and unpredictable (pure gauge) in GR-equivalent models, however it becomes physical upon modifications. The problem is that, in the most popular models, this local symmetry is broken but not stably so, hence the infamous strong coupling issues. The Hamiltonian analyses become complicated and with contradictory results. A funny point is that what we see in available linear perturbation treatments of $f(T)$ gravity is much closer to the analysis with less dynamical degrees of freedom which has got a well-known mistake in it, while the more accurate work predicts much more of dynamics than what has ever been seen up to now. I discuss possible reasons behind this puzzle, and also argue in favour of studying the most general New GR models which are commonly ignored due to suspicion of ghosts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14184v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Golovnev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal modes and greybody factor of Schwarzschild Black Hole in the Cold Dark Matter Halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05272v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we firstly studied wave function in static spherically symmetric spacetime and obtained effective potential of perturbed fields with spin. Then we applied $6^{\rm{th}}$ order WKB approximation to analyze quasinormal modes of Schwarzschild black hole in the Cold Dark Matter halo in perturbed fields with different spins and derived quasinormal frequencies. Further, to study the relation between quasinormal frequencies and optics, we compare the results of WKB method with eikonal limit formula. At last, we discussed greybody factor in different perturbed fields under this spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05272v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Jie Ma, Rui-Bo Wang, Tian-Chi Ma, He-Xu Zhang, Jian-Bo Deng, Xian-Ru Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremal Kerr black holes as amplifiers of new physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.07358v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that extremal Kerr black holes are sensitive probes of new physics. Stringy or quantum corrections to general relativity are expected to generate higher-curvature terms in the gravitational action. We show that in the presence of these terms, asymptotically flat extremal rotating black holes have curvature singularities on their horizon. Furthermore, near-extremal black holes can have large yet finite tidal forces for infalling observers. In addition, we consider five-dimensional extremal charged black holes and show that higher-curvature terms can have a large effect on the horizon geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.07358v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.131.091402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 131, 091402 (2023), Editors' Suggestion</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gary T. Horowitz, Maciej Kolanowski, Grant N. Remmen, Jorge E. Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography and the Page curve of an evaporating black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16570v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Page curve exhibits a sharp peak at the Page time corresponding to a phase transition from an empty quantum extremal surface to a non-empty one. This study delves into the impact of this phase transition on the informational content of black hole radiation through constructing a smooth Page curve which represents a gradual transition instead. We utilize replica trick, apply holography in a specific form, and introduce mathematical identities inherent to the curve's smoothness. Our results suggest that a gradual transition could lead to a significant increase in the informational content of the radiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16570v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir A. Khodahami, Azizollah Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dephasing due to electromagnetic interactions in spatial qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05452v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Matter-wave interferometers with micro-particles will enable the next generation of quantum sensors to probe minute quantum phase information. Therefore, estimating the loss of coherence and the degree of entanglement degradation for such interferometers is essential. In this paper, we will provide a noise analysis in frequency-space focusing on electromagnetic sources of dephasing. We will assume that our matter-wave interferometer has a residual charge or dipole which can interact with a neighbouring particle in the ambience. We will investigate the dephasing due to the Coulomb, charge-induced dipole, charge-permanent dipole, and dipole-dipole interactions. All these interactions constitute electromagnetically driven dephasing channels that can affect single or multiple interferometers. As an example, we will apply the obtained formulae to situations with two adjacent micro-particles, which can provide insight for the noise analysis in the quantum gravity-induced entanglement of masses (QGEM) protocol and the C-NOT gate: we will compute the dephasing due to a gas of environmental particles interacting via dipole-dipole and charge-charge couplings, respectively. To obtain simple analytical dephasing formulae, we will employ uniform probability distributions for the impact parameter and for the angles characterizing the relative orientation with respect to the interferometer and a Gaussian distribution for the velocities of the environmental particles. In both cases, we will show that the dephasing rate grows with the number density of particles present in the vacuum chamber, as expected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05452v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martine Schut, Herre Bosma, MengZhi Wu, Marko Toro\v{s}, Sougato Bose, Anupam Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from cosmic superstrings and gauge strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10455v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform a phenomenological comparison of the gravitational wave (GW) spectrum expected from cosmic gauge string networks and superstring networks comprised of multiple string types. We show how violations of scaling behavior and the evolution of the number of relativistic degrees of freedom in the early Universe affect the GW spectrum. We derive simple analytical expressions for the GW spectrum from superstrings and gauge strings that are valid for all frequencies relevant to pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) and laser interferometers. We analyze the latest data from PTAs and show that superstring networks are consistent with 32 nHz data from NANOGrav, but are excluded by 3.2 nHz data at $3\sigma$ unless the string coupling $g_s&lt;0.2$ or the strings evolve in only about 10% of the volume of the higher-dimensional space. We also point out that while gauge string networks are excluded by NANOGrav-15 data at $3\sigma$, they are completely compatible with EPTA and PPTA data. Finally, we study correlations between GW signals at PTAs and laser interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10455v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danny Marfatia, Ye-Ling Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern-Simons gravity and PT Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14513v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper considers the possibility that, starting from a relativistic Hermitian quantum field theory in the ultraviolet (UV) regime, and applying a non-perturbative renormalization-group (RG) flow, we arrive at a situation where there are infrared (IR) singularities in the RG flow of couplings. The latter can be resolved by assuming that the theory can have a phase described by a related non-Hermitian PT-symmetric modification in the IR. The UV-to-IR (Hermitian-to-PT-symmetric) transition can occur in a single renormalization-group flow of the pertinent couplings, as demonstrated in concrete examples. When embedded in a gravitational setting such a transition can lead to a repulsive gravity phase. If there is a RG flow to a repulsive PT -symmetric gravity, then this would be an alternative to dark energy. The discussion here is presented in the context of a string-inspired Chern-Simons gravitational effective action, which involves a pseudoscalar (axion-like) field coupled to Abelian gauge fields and gravity; it may also hold more generally in gravity with torsion. The validity of such a scenario in realistic theories might alleviate the need for de Sitter phases in the current epoch of cosmological evolution, thus avoiding their associated conceptual and technical complications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14513v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick E. Mavromatos, Sarben Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic inflation and entropy bound in de Sitter spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the entropy behavior of the de Sitter spacetime during the inflationary phase. A cosmological horizon in de Sitter spacetime that constrains the causally accessible region of an observer exhibits thermal properties analogous to the event horizon of a black hole. According to the principles of holography, the entropy within a causally connected region for an observer is limited by its boundary. This entropy bound is violated during the late inflation stage. To address the issue of entropy bound violations from a quantum information perspective, we adopted a stochastic approach to cosmic inflation. We consider Shannon entropy of the probability distribution of the inflaton field, which shows the same behavior as the entanglement entropy of a Hubble-size region in stochastic inflation. Adopting the volume-weighted probability distribution for the inflaton field, we show a meaningful entropy behavior in the de Sitter spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10837v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiromasa Tajima, Yasusada Nambu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brane Profiles of Non-Supersymmetric Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16327v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We connect the indications of 2D CFT for branes in non-supersymmetric strings to actual spacetime profiles, taking the bulk tadpole potentials into account. We find exact solutions for the uncharged branes that spread in the internal intervals of Dudas-Mourad vacua for non-tachyonic orientifolds and heterotic strings. These solutions involve suitable dressings of the uncharged branes of the nine-dimensional tadpole-free theory. Similar exact results for uncharged branes that are transverse to the internal space, or for charged branes, appear more challenging. Nevertheless, we identify their large-distance behavior, which is determined by linearized equations, and show that it is compatible with the CFT analysis in all expected cases. We also draw some indications on the leading back-reaction of the form-fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16327v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Mourad (APC, U. Paris Cit\'e), S. Raucci (Scuola Normale Superiore,INFN, Pisa), A. Sagnotti (Scuola Normale Superiore,INFN, Pisa)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PixelPop: High Resolution Nonparameteric Inference of Gravitational-Wave Populations in Multiple Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16813v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The origins of merging compact binaries observed by gravitational-wave detectors remains highly uncertain. Several astrophysical channels may contribute to the overall merger rate, with distinct formation processes imprinted on the structure and correlations in the underlying distributions of binary source parameters. In the absence of confident theoretical models, the current understanding of this population mostly relies on simple parametric models that make strong assumptions and are prone to misspecification. Recent work has made progress using more flexible nonparametric models, but detailed measurement of the multidimensional population remains challenging. In pursuit of this, we present PixelPop-a high resolution Bayesian nonparametric model to infer joint distributions and parameter correlations with minimal assumptions. PixelPop densely bins the joint parameter space and directly infers the merger rate in each bin, assuming only that bins are coupled to their nearest neighbors. We demonstrate this method on mock populations with and without bivariate source correlations, employing several statistical metrics for information gain and correlation significance to quantify our nonparametric results. We show that PixelPop correctly recovers the true populations within posterior uncertainties and offers a conservative assessment of population-level features and parameter correlations. Its flexibility and tractability make it a useful data-driven tool to probe gravitational-wave populations in multiple dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16813v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Heinzel, Matthew Mould, Sof\'ia \'Alvarez-L\'opez, Salvatore Vitale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric analysis of correlations in the binary black hole population with LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16844v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Formation channels of merging compact binaries imprint themselves on the distributions and correlations of their source parameters, but current understanding of this population is hindered by simplified parametric models. We overcome such limitations using PixelPop [Heinzel et al. (2024)]-our Bayesian nonparametric multidimensional population model. We analyze data from the first three LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA observing runs and make high resolution, minimally modeled measurements of the pairwise distributions of binary black hole masses, redshifts, and spins. We find no evidence that the mass spectrum evolves over redshift and show that such measurements are fundamentally limited by the detector horizon. We find support for correlations of the spin distribution with binary mass ratio and redshift, but at reduced significance compared to overly constraining parametric models. Confident data-driven conclusions about population-level correlations with flexible models like PixelPop will require more informative gravitational-wave catalogs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16844v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Heinzel, Matthew Mould, Salvatore Vitale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the cosmic distance duality relation using Type Ia supernovae and radio quasars through model-independent methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05559v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we perform a cosmological-model-independent test on the cosmic distance duality relation (CDDR) by comparing the angular diameter distance (ADD) obtained from the compact radio quasars (QSOs) with the luminosity distance (LD) from the Pantheon Type Ia supernovae (SNIa) sample. The binning method and Artificial Neural Network (ANN) are employed to match ADD data with LD data at the same redshift, and three different parameterizations are adopted to quantify the possible deviations from the CDDR. We initially investigate the impacts of the specific prior values for the absolute magnitude $M_{\rm B}$ from SNIa and the linear size scaling factor $l$ from QSOs on the CDDR test, demonstrating that these prior values introduce significant biases in the CDDR test. To avoid the biases, we propose a method independent of $M_{\rm B}$ and $l$ to test CDDR, which treats the fiducial value of a new variable $\kappa\equiv10^{M_{\rm B} \over 5}\,l$ as a nuisance parameter and then marginalize its impact with a flat prior in the statistical analysis. The results show that the CDDR is consistent with the observational data, and QSOs can serve as a powerful tool for testing the CDDR independent of cosmological models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05559v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Yang, Xiangyun Fu, Bing Xu, Kaituo Zhang, Yang Huang, Ying Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
