<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 01:45:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Complete Treatment of Scalar-induced Gravitational Waves with Early Matter Domination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large curvature perturbations can source an observable amount of stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB). We consider several scenarios where small-scale curvature perturbations are naturally enhanced due to the presence of additional spectator fields during inflation. The same spectator fields can lead to a period of early matter domination (EMD) after inflation. We compute the inflationary spectrum of curvature perturbation and determine its evolution at later times, taking into account both the onset and the end of the EMD epoch, and also the impact of relative velocity perturbation between matter and radiation. The feature that the same field is responsible for both enhanced perturbations and the EMD era, leads to a predictive framework within which the full frequency dependence of SGWB can be computed. The SGWB can be observed in several detectors, including those focused on the nano-Hz regime. Our numerical framework can also be used to study other non-standard cosmological histories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17291v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soubhik Kumar, Hanwen Tai, Lian-Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing screened scalar-tensor theories of gravity with atomic clocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In any scalar-tensor theory of gravity exhibiting a screening mechanism, the fifth force mediated by the scalar field is dynamically suppressed at sub-Solar system scales, allowing it to pass existing tests of gravity. As a result, a major research effort has been carried out over the past decades to 'outsmart' screened scalars in this game of hide-and-seek. While most of such tests rely on fifth force effects, one should keep in mind that the latter are by no means the only physical feature of scalar-tensor gravity. In particular, this article investigates the possibility of testing screened scalar-tensor models by means of gravitational redshift measurements performed with atomic clocks. Upon deriving the expression for the redshift in this framework, we propose a thought experiment for testing the chameleon model by clock comparisons, which guides us towards more realistic experimental setups, in the laboratory and in space. We find that the current level of precision exhibited by leading-edge technology is still too low to yield competitive constraints on the chameleon model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17292v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo L\'evy, Jean-Philippe Uzan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shadow and observational images of the non-singular rotating black holes in loop quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By considering the celestial light source and the thin disk source, we employ the backward ray-tracing method to carefully study the shadow, inner shadow and observational images of the non-singular rotating black holes in loop quantum gravity. The results show that the increase of quantum parameter $\lambda$ causes the shadow to shrink, while increases the deviation from circularity. And, the shadow's angular diameter of M87* impose stronger constraints on the observed properties of the no-singulgar rotating black holes by comparing with SgrA*. For a celestial light source, the parameter $\lambda$ indeed influences the distortion of light around black hole shadow, but this effect is relatively small and only becomes noticeable when extremely close to the shadow. When a thin accretion disk around black hole, it turns out that for an observer at any position, the parameter $\lambda$ has little effect on the shape of the inner shadow. However, it decreases the size of the inner shadow, reduces the observed light intensity, and narrows the redshifted shadow images, regardless of whether the accretion disk is prograde or retrograde. Meanwhile, it is true that the thin disk images of black hole cannot effectively reflect the internal structure of black hole. Finally, we can conclude that a key observational feature of these non-singular rotating black holes is that the larger the black hole's spin parameter, the smaller the upper limit of $\lambda'$s effect. And, the parameter $\lambda$ decreases the gravitational field's strength, thereby weakens the observed images. This could provide a possible way to constraining black hole parameters, identifying quantum gravity effects, and distinguishing loop quantum gravity black holes, even if it cannot be used to distinguish the non-singular properties of black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17295v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Ping Li, He-Bin Zheng, Ke-Jian He, Qing-Quan Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of relativistic waveforms in LISA's science objectives with extreme-mass-ratio inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17310v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extreme-Mass-Ratio Inspirals (EMRIs) are one of the key targets for future space-based gravitational wave detectors, such as LISA. The scientific potential of these sources can only be fully realized with fast and accurate waveform models. In this work, we extend the \textsc{FastEMRIWaveform} (\texttt{FEW}) framework by providing fully relativistic waveforms at adiabatic order for circular, equatorial orbits in Kerr spacetime, for mass ratios up to $10^{-3}$. We study the importance of including relativistic corrections in the waveform for both vacuum and non-vacuum environments. For EMRIs in vacuum, we find that non-relativistic waveforms can result in $\sim 35\%$ error in the predicted source's horizon redshift. By developing relativistic non-vacuum EMRI waveforms, we demonstrate significant improvements in detecting environmental effects. Our analysis shows that incorporating relativistic corrections enhances constraints on accretion disks, modeled through power-law torques, and improves the constraints on disk parameters (error $\sim6\%$), representing a significant improvement from previous estimates. We also estimated the evidence for models in a scenario where ignoring the accretion disk causes bias in parameter estimation (PE) and report a $\log_{10}$ Bayes factor of $1.1$ in favor of the accretion disk model. Additionally, in a fully relativistic setup, we estimate the parameters of superradiant scalar clouds with high accuracy, achieving errors below $5\%$ for the scalar cloud's mass and below $0.5\%$ for the ultralight field's mass. These results demonstrate that incorporating relativistic effects greatly enhances the accuracy and reliability of waveform predictions, essential for PE and model selection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17310v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Khalvati, Alessandro Santini, Francisco Duque, Lorenzo Speri, Jonathan Gair, Huan Yang, Richard Brito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linking Edge Modes and Geometrical Clocks in Linearized Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reference frames are crucial for describing local observers in general relativity. In quantum gravity, different proposals exist for how to treat reference frames. There are models with either classical or quantum reference frames. Recently, different choices appeared for investigating these possibilities at the level of the classical and quantum algebra of observables. One choice is based on the covariant phase space approach, using gravitational edge modes. In the canonical approach, there is another choice, relational clocks, built from matter or geometry itself. In this work, we extend existing results and show how to relate edge modes and geometrical clocks in linearized gravity. We proceed in three steps. First, we introduce an extension of the ADM (Arnowitt-Deser-Misner) phase space to account for covariant gauge fixing conditions and the explicit time dependence they add to Hamilton's equations. Second, we show how these gauge fixing conditions recover a specific choice of geometrical clocks in terms of Ashtekar-Barbero connection variables. Third, we study the effect of the Barbero-Immirzi parameter on the generators of asymptotic symmetries and the corresponding charges. This parameter, which disappears from metric gravity, affects the generators for angle-dependent asymptotic symmetries and the corresponding super-translation charges, while it has no effect on the global charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17339v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristina Giesel, Viktoria Kabel, Wolfgang Wieland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kiselev-inspired Wormholes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we explore traversable wormholes inspired by the Kiselev framework, which generalizes classical black hole solutions by incorporating anisotropic fluids. These exotic fluids are essential in cosmology for describing phenomena like the accelerated expansion of the universe. We extend the Kiselev framework to static, spherically symmetric traversable wormholes, analyzing their properties under two distinct models of the redshift function: constant and varying with the inverse radial coordinate. The energy conditions, including the Null Energy Condition (NEC), Weak Energy Condition (WEC), and Strong Energy Condition (SEC), are evaluated for these models, showing that only specific exotic fluids can support the wormhole structure. Additionally, we calculate the amount of exotic matter required to sustain these wormholes using the volume integral quantifier and compare the results with other wormhole models. The impact of these configurations on weak gravitational lensing is also discussed. Our findings suggest that Kiselev-inspired wormholes could serve as promising candidates for exotic geometries, potentially offering novel avenues for future experimental verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17475v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piyachat Panyasiripan (Naresuan U.), Phongpichit Channuie (Walailak U.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar quasinormal modes in emergent modified gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Emergent modified gravity is a post-Einsteinian gravitational theory where spacetime geometry is not fundamental but rather emerges from the gravitational degrees of freedom in a non-trivial way. The specific relationship between geometry and these degrees of freedom is unique for each theory, but it is not predetermined. Instead, it is derived from constraints and equations of motion, relying on key aspects of the canonical formulation of gravity, such as structure functions in Poisson brackets of constraints and covariance conditions. As shown in previous work, these new theories allow for two types of scalar matter coupling: (1) minimal coupling, where the matter equations of motion mirror the Klein-Gordon equation on a curved emergent spacetime, and (2) nonminimal coupling, where the equations deviate from the Klein-Gordon form but still respect covariance. Observable features, such as the quasinormal mode spectrum, can help distinguish between different couplings based on how well their predictions match the data. In this work, the spectra of scalar quasinormal modes for both minimal and nonminimal couplings are derived using the third-order WKB approximation. Significant differences are found between the two cases. Notably, the nonminimal coupling allows for vanishing real and imaginary frequency components, and even opposite-sign values for the imaginary part at sufficiently small mass scales, pointing to potential new physical implications. Finally, the high-frequency QNM spectra in emergent modified gravity is identical to the classical result, up to an overall constant, suggesting that the horizon area spectrum remains equispaced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17501v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bojowald, Erick I. Duque, S. Shankaranarayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound-state solutions for the charged Dirac oscillator in a rotating frame in the Bonnor-Melvin-Lambda spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we determine the relativistic bound-state solutions for the charged (DO) Dirac oscillator in a rotating frame in the Bonnor-Melvin-Lambda spacetime in $(2+1)$-dimensions, where such solutions are given by the two-component Dirac spinor and by the relativistic energy spectrum. In this way, we work with the curved DO with minimal coupling in polar coordinates, where we use the tetrad formalism. To analytically solve our problem, we consider two approximations, where the first is that the cosmological constant is very small (conical approximation), and the second is that the linear velocity of the rotating frame is much less than the speed of light (slow rotation regime). So, after solving a second-order differential equation, we obtain a generalized Laguerre equation, whose solutions are the generalized Laguerre polynomials. Consequently, we obtain the energy spectrum, which is quantized in terms of the radial and total magnetic quantum numbers $n$ and $m_j$, and explicitly depends on the angular frequency $\omega$ (describes the DO), cyclotron frequency $\omega_c$ (describes the external magnetic field), angular velocity $\Omega$ (describes the rotating frame), spin parameter $s$ (describes the ``spin''), spinorial parameter $u$ (describes the components of the spinor), effective rest mass $m_{eff}$ (describes the rest mass modified by the spin-rotation coupling), and on a real parameter $\sigma$ and cosmological constant $\Lambda$ (describes the Bonnor-Melvin-Lambda spacetime). In particular, we note that this spectrum is asymmetrical (due to the presence of $\Omega$) and has its degeneracy broken (due to the presence of $\sigma$ and $\Lambda$) for $m_js&lt;0$. Besides, we also graphically analyze the behavior of the spectrum and of the probability density as a function of the parameters of the system for different values of $n$ and $m_j$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17535v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. R. S. Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherically symmetric collapse: Initial configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The initial state of the spherical gravitational collapse in general relativity has been studied with different methods, especially by using {\it a priori} given equations of state that describe the matter as a perfect fluid. We propose an alternative approach, in which the energy density of the perfect fluid is given as a polynomial function of the radial coordinate that is well-behaved everywhere inside the fluid. We then solve the corresponding differential equations, including the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff equilibrium condition, using a fourth-order Runge-Kutta method and obtain a consistent model with a central perfect-fluid core surrounded by dust. We analyze the Hamiltonian constraint, the mass-to-radius relation, the boundary and physical conditions, and the stability and convergence properties of the numerical solutions. The energy density and pressure of the resulting matter distribution satisfy the standard physical conditions. The model is also consistent with the Buchdahl limit and the speed of sound conditions, even by using realistic values of compact astrophysical objects such as neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17537v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elly Bayona, Hernando Quevedo, Miguel Alcubierre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from burdened primordial black holes dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs) are the natural candidate of dark matter (DM) as they only interact gravitationally and can evade any experiments on earth. In the standard semiclassical calculation of Hawking radiation, PBHs with mass below $10^{15}\rm g$ evaporated by now and therefore cannot be DM. However, the recently-discovered quantum memory burden effect can significantly suppress the evaporation of PBHs after the half-decay time. This quantum effect could open up a new mass window below $10^{10} \rm g$ where PBHs can still exist today and be DM. In this paper, we compute the gravitational wave (GW) signals associated with the formation of PBHs in this new mass window. We consider two formation scenarios: PBHs formed from inflationary perturbation and PBHs formed from collapse of Fermi-balls in a first-order phase transition (FOPT). GWs produced from these two scenarios have distinct features and, while the GW from inflation peaks at high frequency, the GW from FOPT peaks at lower frequency that can be within the reach of future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17544v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngo Phuc Duc Loc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light escape cones in the locally non-rotating reference frames of the Kerr-de Sitter superspinars and related superspinar shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The construction of local escape cones and their complementary cones, related to the locally non-rotating frames (LNRFs) orbiting superspinars with the external field described by the Kerr-de Sitter (KdS) naked singularity (NS) spacetimes, is described for all possible classes of the KdS NS spacetimes and all possible positions of the photon emitter. The notion of the local escape cones is then applied to construct the shadow of the KdS superspinars related to the distant static observers represented by the LNRFs located near the so-called static radius where the spacetime is close to the asymptotically flat region of the Kerr spacetimes. The shadow construction is focused on the KdS superpsinars limited by the cosmological and astrophysical restrictions on the spacetime parameters, namely the superspinar dimensionless spin and the dimensionless cosmological parameter relating the cosmological constant and the superspinar's mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17659v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Charbul\'ak, Zden\v{e}k Stuchl\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology of Quasi-Dilaton Massive Gravity with Non-minimal Kinetic Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the cosmological implications of the quasi-dilaton massive gravity theory with a non-minimal kinetic coupling. We investigate the resulting gravitational dynamics by introducing a nonzero mass for the graviton. We derive the complete set of background equations of motion and obtain self-accelerating background solutions to explain the late-time accelerated expansion of the Universe using the effective cosmological constant originating from massive gravity. Furthermore, we derive the dispersion relation of gravitational waves to obtain the stability condition of the system. This allows us to use the propagation of gravitational perturbations in a Friedman-Lemaitre-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) cosmology to constrain the quasi-dilaton massive gravity with a non-minimal kinetic coupling theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17915v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sobhan Kazempour, Amin Rezaei Akbarieh, Sichun Sun, Chengye Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge-invariant perturbations of relativistic non-perfect fluids in spherical spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Astrophysical compact objects are usually studied using a perfect fluid model. However, in astrophysical processes out-of-equilibrium, dissipative effects become important to describe the dynamics of the system. In this work, we obtain gauge-invariant non-spherical perturbations of a self-gravitating non-perfect fluid in spherical spacetime. We use the Gerlach-Sengupta formalism to work with gauge-invariant metric perturbations, and the Gundlach-Mart\'in-Garc\'ia approach to transform the equations of tensor perturbations into scalar equations. We calculate the dynamics of the dissipative contributions, e.g., viscosity and heat flux, using the M\"uller-Israel-Stewart equations in the gauge-invariant formalism. We obtain a set of field equations for the evolution of matter and metric perturbations in the polar and axial sectors. Specifically, in the former we find two wave equations sourced by the anisotropic contributions, and the evolution of all matter perturbations for radiative modes ($l\geq 2$). In the axial sector, we find one wave equation coupled to the evolution of matter perturbations. Finally, we comment on the contribution of dissipative effects in the lower-order multipoles ($l=0,1$) for both sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18081v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David D\'iaz-Guerra, Conrado Albertus, Prasanta Char, M. \'Angeles P\'erez-Garc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gas-induced perturbations on the gravitational wave in-spiral of live post-Newtonian LISA massive black hole binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of dynamically coupling gas torques with gravitational wave (GW) emission during the orbital evolution of an equal-mass massive black hole binary (MBHB). We perform hydrodynamical simulations of eccentric MBHBs with total mass $M=10^6~{\rm M}_\odot$ embedded in a prograde locally isothermal circumbinary disk (CBD). We evolve the binary from $53$ to $30$ Schwarzschild radii separations using up to 2.5 post-Newtonian (PN) corrections to the binary dynamics, which allow us to follow the GW-driven in-spiral. For the first time, we report the measurement of gas torques onto a live binary a few years before the merger, with and without concurrent GW radiation. We also identify and measure a novel GW-gas coupling term in the in-spiral rate that makes gas effects an order of magnitude stronger than the gas-only contribution. We show that the evolution rate ($\dot a$) of the MBHB can be neatly expressed as the sum of the GW rate ($\dot a_{\rm GW}$), the pure gas-driven rate ($\dot a_{\rm gas}$), and their cross-term $\propto\dot a_{\rm GW}\dot a_{\rm gas}$. The source-frame gas-induced dephasing in the GW waveform is equivalent to losing $\sim0.5$ GW cycles over the expected $\sim1700$ cycles in a vacuum, which LISA should detect at redshift $z=1$. We also propose a phenomenological model that captures the essence of simulations and can be used to perform Bayesian inference. Our results show how GWs alone can be used to probe the astrophysical properties of CBDs and have important implications on multi-messenger strategies aimed at studying the environments of MBHBs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17305v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mudit Garg, Alessia Franchini, Alessandro Lupi, Matteo Bonetti, Lucio Mayer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography of Information in a Ball of Finite Radius</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The principle of holography of information states that all information available in the bulk of asymptotically flat spacetime is also available near its boundary at spatial infinity. However, physical observers never have access to spatial infinity. Therefore, we ask the question: ``Is information contained in a ball of finite radius also holographic in nature?". Phrased differently, we ask whether correlation functions on the boundary of the ball capture all the information of all correlators in the bulk of the ball. In this work, we answer this question in the affirmative within the confines of linearised quantum gravity for generic low-energy (free Klein-Gordon) states in flat space created by the action of unitaries on the vacuum to leading order in a certain perturbative parameter. For an infinite sub-class of these states, our results are perturbatively exact and valid to all orders in this same parameter. Unlike at infinity, massive and massless fields can be captured within the same framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17316v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nava Gaddam, Ashik H</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting the population properties of merging black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Third-generation gravitational-wave detectors will observe up to millions of merging binary black holes. With such a vast dataset, stacking events into population analyses will arguably be more important than analyzing single sources. We present the first application of population-level Fisher-matrix forecasts tailored to third-generation gravitational-wave interferometers. We implement the formalism first derived by Gair et al. and explore how future experiments such as Einstein Telescope and Cosmic Explorer will constrain the distributions of black-hole masses, spins, and redshift. Third-generation detectors will be transformative, improving constraints on the population hyperparameters by several orders of magnitude compared to current data. At the same time, we highlight that a single third-generation observatory and a network of detectors will deliver qualitatively similar performances. Obtaining precise measurements of some population features (e.g. peaks in the mass spectrum) will require only a few months of observations while others (e.g. the fraction of binaries with aligned spins) will instead require years if not decades. We argue population forecasts of this kind should be featured in white papers and feasibility studies aimed at developing the science case of future gravitational-wave interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17325v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viola De Renzis, Francesco Iacovelli, Davide Gerosa, Michele Mancarella, Costantino Pacilio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric scattering for nonlinear wave equations on the Schwarzschild metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we establish a conformal scattering theory for the defocusing semilinear wave equations on the Schwarzschild spacetime. We combine the energy and pointwise decay results of solutions obtained in \cite{Yang} and a Sobolev embedding on spacelike hypersurfaces to establish the energy estimates in two sides between the energy flux of solution through the Cauchy initial hypersurface $\Sigma_0=\left\{ t=0 \right\}$ and the one through the null conformal boundaries $\mathfrak{H}^+\cup \scri^+$ (resp. $\mathfrak{H}^-\cup \scri^-$). Combining these estimates and the well-posedness of Cauchy and Goursat problems for nonlinear wave equations we provide a bounded linear and locally Lipschitz scattering operator which maps the past scattering data to the future scattering data. Our results extend also the previous works \cite{BaSeZho1990,Jo2012,Jo2019} to an asymptotically flat spacetime such as Schwarzschild spacetime which is static and spherically symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17745v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tran Thi Ngoc, Pham Truong Xuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the axion-photon coupling with space-based gravitational waves detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17763v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a simple modification of space-based gravitational wave (GW) detector optical benches which would enable the measurement of vacuum birefringence of light induced by axion dark matterthrough its coupling to electromagnetism. While marginally affecting the sensitivity to GW by a factor $\sqrt{2}$, we show that such an adjustment would make future detectors such as LISA, TianQin, Taiji and Big-Bang Observer the most sensitive experiments at low axion masses</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17763v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Gu\'e, Aur\'elien Hees, Peter Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of scalar non-Gaussianity on induced scalar-tensor gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17819v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If primordial scalar or tensor perturbations are enhanced on short scales, it may lead to the production of observable gravitational wave signals. These waves may be sourced by scalar-scalar, scalar-tensor or tensor-tensor interactions. Typically, models of inflation capable of producing large peaks in the scalar primordial power spectrum also generate sizeable scalar non-Gaussianity. Previous studies have investigated the possible effects of this on the scalar-scalar induced gravitational wave spectrum by assuming a local expansion in terms of the parameters $F_{\textrm{NL}}$, $G_{\textrm{NL}}$ and so on. We extend this approach to the case of scalar-tensor induced gravitational waves, introducing a local expansion for scalar non-Gaussianity into the scalar-tensor sector equations. We compute the contribution to the gravitational wave spectrum from the resulting new term and analyse its distinguishing features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17819v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Picard, Matthew W. Davies</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling PTA and JWST and preparing for LISA with \texttt{POMPOCO}: a Parametrisation Of the Massive black hole POpulation for Comparison to Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17916v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a parametrised model to describe the formation and evolution of massive black holes, designed for comparisons with both electromagnetic and gravitational wave observations. Using an extended Press-Schechter formalism, we generate dark matter halo merger trees. We then seed and evolve massive black holes through parameterised prescriptions. This approach, which avoids solving differential equations, is computationally efficient, enabling us to analyse observational data and infer the parameters of our model in a fully Bayesian framework. We find that observations of the black hole luminosity function are compatible with the nHz gravitational wave signal (likely) measured by PTAs, provided we allow for an increased luminosity function at high redshift ($4-7$), as recently suggested by JWST observations. Our model can simultaneously reproduce the bulk of the $M_*-M_{\rm BH}$ relation at $z-0$, as well as its outliers, something cosmological simulations struggle to do. The inferred model parameters are consistent with expectations from observations and more complex simulations: They favour heavier black hole seeds and short delays between halo and black hole mergers, while requiring supper-Edington accretion episodes lasting a few tens of million years, which in our model are linked to galaxy mergers. We find accretion to be suppressed in the most massive black holes below $z\simeq 2.5$, consistently with the anti-hierarchical growth hypothesis. Finally, our predictions for LISA, although fairly broad, are in agreement with previous models. Our model offers a new perspective on the apparent tensions between the black hole luminosity function and the latest JWST and PTA results. Its flexibility makes it ideal to fully exploit the potential of future gravitational wave observations of massive black hole binaries with LISA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17916v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Toubiana, L. Sberna, M. Volonteri, E. Barausse, S. Babak, R. Enficiaud, D. Izquierdo Villalba, J. R. Gair, J. E. Greene, H. Quelquejay Leclere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantizable Ghost-ridden theories using Kinetic Positivity Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel way to constrain the ghost field with respect to other physical fields present in a given theory such that the theory becomes quantizable. This is achieved by imposing positivity of the total kinetic energy of the system and performing Lorentz transformations in the field space manifold to arrive at an effective Lagrangian containing only physical degrees of freedom. Since models containing ghost fields such as quintom models are relevant in the cosmological context, this method can help ensure that such theories don't violate unitarity and can be treated as realistic candidates without the need to completely eliminate ghost(s).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17924v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sukanta Panda, Archit Vidyarthi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small noise expansion of stochastic inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By introducing the small noise expansion techniques, we show that the fully nonlinear (non-Markovian) stochastic inflationary system, may be re-cast in terms of an infinite set of Wiener processes (stochastic equations with white noises). As a byproduct, we show that the Starobinsky test field approximation might only provide information about the linear regime of cosmological perturbations and scalar-feld non-Gaussianities might only appear at next to leading order in slow-roll parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17987v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Cruces, Cristiano Germani, Amin Nassiri-Rad, Masahide Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic Flow for Cosmological Loop Integrands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17994v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, an interesting pattern was found in the differential equations satisfied by the Feynman integrals describing tree-level correlators of conformally coupled scalars in a power-law FRW cosmology [1,2]. It was proven that simple and universal graphical rules predict the equations for arbitrary graphs as a flow in kinematic space. In this note, we show that the same rules$\unicode{x2013}$with one small addition$\unicode{x2013}$also determine the differential equations for loop integrands. We explain that both the basis of master integrals and the singularities of the differential equations can be represented by tubings of marked graphs. An important novelty in the case of loops is that some basis functions can vanish, and we present a graphical rule to identify these vanishing functions. Taking this into account, we then demonstrate that the kinematic flow correctly predicts the differential equations for all loop integrands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17994v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Baumann, Harry Goodhew, Hayden Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing compact objects in extreme-mass-ratio inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.01110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.01110v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Extreme mass-ratio inspirals (EMRIs) are promising gravitational wave (GW) sources for space-based GW detectors. EMRI signals typically have long durations, ranging from several months to several years, necessitating highly accurate GW signal templates for detection. In most waveform models, compact objects in EMRIs are treated as test particles, without accounting for their spin, mass quadrupole, or tidal deformation. In this study, we simulate GW signals from EMRIs by incorporating the spin and mass quadrupole moments of the compact objects. We evaluate the accuracy of parameter estimation for these simulated waveforms using the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM) and find that the spin, tidal-induced quadruple, and spin-induced quadruple can all be measured with precision ranging from $10^{-2}$ to $10^{-1}$, particularly for a mass ratio of $\sim 10^{-4}$. Assuming the "true" GW signals originate from an extended body inspiraling into a supermassive black hole, we compute the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) and Bayes factors between a test-particle waveform template and our model, which includes the spin and quadrupole of the compact object. Our results show that the spin of compact objects can produce detectable deviations in the waveforms across all object types, while tidal-induced quadrupoles are only significant for white dwarfs, especially in cases approaching an intermediate mass ratio. Spin-induced quadrupoles, however, have negligible effects on the waveforms. Therefore, our findings suggest that it is possible to distinguish primordial black holes from white dwarfs, and, under certain conditions, neutron stars can also be differentiated from primordial black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.01110v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu-Jia Xu, Shu-Cheng Yang, Wen-Biao Han, Xing-Yu Zhong, Run-Dong Tang, Yuan-Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>f-mode oscillations of anisotropic neutron stars in full general relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00439v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate f-mode oscillations of static anisotropic stable neutron stars within the framework of full general relativity. We present equations governing unperturbed stellar structures and oscillations with an ansatz to account for the anisotropy. We solve those equations for two different equations of states. We see that, moderately anisotropic neutron stars with the tangential pressure larger than the radial pressure can give more massive neutron stars than the isotropic or very anisotropic ones. We find that the frequency of the f-mode exhibits a linear relationship with the square root of the average density of the stars and the slope of the fit depends on the anisotropic strength. For any given value of the anisotropic strength, the frequency increases with the increase of the mass of the neutron star, linearly for lower masses, and rapidly at higher masses. However, this non-linear rise in the frequency with the mass is not prominent when the radial pressure is larger than the tangential pressure. For a fixed value of a small mass, higher anisotropy leads to a larger value of the frequency, but when the fixed mass is above a threshold value, higher anisotropy leads to a smaller value of the frequency. The nature of the variation in the frequency with the change in the anisotropic strength is similar for the two equations of state, but for a fixed mass and the same amount of the anisotropy, the softer equations of state gives higher frequency. We also find that the damping time of the f-mode oscillation decreases as the mass of the neutron star increases for all values of the anisotropic strength. For a fixed mass of the neutron star and for the same amount of the anisotropy, the value of the damping time is lower for the softer equation of state, but the nature of the variation in the damping time with the change in the anisotropic strength is similar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00439v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sushovan Mondal, Manjari Bagchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing and Mitigating the Impact of Glitches on Gravitational-Wave Parameter Estimation: a Model Agnostic Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09159v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate the impact of transient noise artifacts, or {\it glitches}, on gravitational-wave inference from ground-based interferometer data, and test how modeling and subtracting these glitches affects the inferred parameters. Due to their time-frequency morphology, broadband glitches cause moderate to significant biasing of posterior distributions away from true values. In contrast, narrowband glitches induce negligible biasing effects, due to distinct signal and glitch morphologies. We inject simulated binary black hole signals into data containing three occurring glitch types from past LIGO-Virgo observing runs, and reconstruct both signal and glitch waveforms using \bw{}, a wavelet-based Bayesian analysis. We apply the standard LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA deglitching procedure to the detector data, which consists of subtracting from calibrated LIGO data the glitch waveform estimated by the joint \bw{} inference. {We produce posterior distributions on the parameters of the injected signal before and after subtracting the glitch,} and we {show that removing the transient noise} effectively mitigates bias from broadband glitches. This study provides a baseline validation of existing techniques, while demonstrating waveform reconstruction improvements to the Bayesian algorithm for robust astrophysical characterization in glitch-prone detector data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09159v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudarshan Ghonge, Joshua Brandt, J. M. Sullivan, Margaret Millhouse, Katerina Chatziioannou, James A. Clark, Tyson Littenberg, Neil Cornish, Sophie Hourihane, Laura Cadonati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel category of environmental effect in gravitational waves from binaries perturbed by periodic forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05698v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the gravitational wave (GW) emission of sources perturbed by periodic dynamical forces which do not cause secular evolution in the orbital elements. We construct a corresponding post-Newtonian waveform model and provide estimates for the detectability of the resulting GW phase perturbations, for both space-based and future ground-based detectors. We validate our results by performing a set of Bayesian parameter recovery experiments with post-Newtonian waveforms. We find that, in stark contrast to the more commonly studied secular dephasing, periodic phase perturbations do not suffer from degeneracies with any of the tested vacuum binary parameters. We discuss the applications of our findings to a range of possible astrophysical scenarios, finding that such periodic perturbations may be detectable for massive black hole binaries embedded in circum-binary discs, extreme mass-ratio inspirals in accretion discs, as well as stellar-mass compact objects perturbed by tidal fields. We argue that modelling conservative sub-orbital dynamics opens up a promising new avenue to detect environmental effects in binary sources of GWs that should be included in state-of-the-art waveform templates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05698v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenz Zwick, Christopher Tiede, Alessandro A. Trani, Andrea Derdzinski, Zoltan Haiman, Daniel J. D'Orazio, Johan Samsing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological inhomogeneities, primordial black holes, and a hypothesis on the death of the universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the impact of the expansion of the universe on a broad class of objects, including black holes, neutron stars, white dwarfs, and others. Using metrics that incorporate primordial inhomogeneities, the effects of a hypothetical "center of the universe" on inflation are calculated. Dynamic coordinates for black holes that account for expansions or contractions with arbitrary rates are provided. We consider the possibility that the universe may be bound to evolve into an ultimate state of "total dilution", wherein stable particles are so widely separated that physical communication among them will be impossible for eternity. This is also a scenario of "cosmic virtuality", as no wave-function collapse would occur again. We provide classical models evolving this way, based on the Majumdar-Papapetrou geometries. More realistic configurations, instead, indicate that gravitational forces locally counteract expansion, except in the universe's early stages. We comment on whether quantum phenomena may dictate that total dilution is indeed the cosmos' ultimate destiny.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12050v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym16111412</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry 2024, 16(11), 1412</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Damiano Anselmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spikes and spines in 4D Lorentzian simplicial quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simplicial approaches to quantum gravity such as quantum Regge calculus and spin foams include configurations where bulk edges can become arbitrarily large while the boundary edges are kept small. Spikes and spines are prime examples for such configurations. They pose a significant challenge for a desired continuum limit, for which the average lengths of edges ought to become very small. Here we investigate spike and spine configurations in four-dimensional Lorentzian quantum Regge calculus. We find that the expectation values of arbitrary powers of the bulk length are finite. To that end, we explore new types of asymptotic regimes for the Regge amplitudes, in which some of the edges are much larger than the remaining ones. The amplitudes simplify considerably in such asymptotic regimes and the geometric interpretation of the resulting expressions involves a dimensional reduction, which might have applications to holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13601v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2024)150</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2024) 150</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Borissova, Bianca Dittrich, Dongxue Qu, Marc Schiffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hawking radiation with pure states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18652v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hawking's seminal work on black hole radiation highlights a critical issue in our understanding of quantum field theory in curved spacetime (QFTCS), specifically the problem of unitarity loss (where pure states evolve into mixed states). In this paper, we examine a recent proposal for a direct-sum QFTCS, which maintains unitarity through a novel quantization method that employs geometric superselection rules based on discrete spacetime transformations. This approach describes a quantum state in terms of components that evolve within geometric superselection sectors of the complete Hilbert space, adhering to the discrete symmetries of a Schwarzschild black hole. Consequently, it represents a maximally entangled pure state as a direct-sum of two components in the interior and exterior regions of the black hole, thereby preserving the unitarity of Hawking radiation by keeping it in the form of pure states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18652v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Sravan Kumar, Jo\~ao Marto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-Normal Modes of Loop Quantum Black Holes Formed from Gravitational Collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19654v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the quasi-normal modes (QNMs) of a scalar field in the background of a large class of quantum black holes that can be formed from gravitational collapse of a dust fluid in the framework of effective loop quantum gravity. The loop quantum black holes (LQBHs) are characterized by three free parameters, one of which is the mass parameter, while the other two are purely due to quantum geometric effects. Among these two quantum parameters, one is completely fixed by black hole thermodynamics and its effects are negligible for macroscopic black holes, while the second parameter is completely free (in principle). In the studies of the QNMs of such LQBHs, we pay particular attention to the difference of the QNMs between LQBHs and classical ones, so that they can be observed for the current and forthcoming gravitational wave observations, whereby place the LQBH theory directly under the test of observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19654v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/10/070</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 10 (2024) 070</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chao Zhang, Anzhong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kerr Geodesics in horizon-penetrating Kerr coordinates: description in terms of Weierstrass functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03722v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the theory of timelike and null geodesics in the (extended) Kerr spacetime. This work is a sequel to a recent paper by Cie\'{s}lik, Hackmann, and Mach, who applied the so-called Biermann-Weierstrass formula to integrate Kerr geodesic equations expressed in Boyer-Lindquist coordinates. We show that a formulation based on the Biermann-Weierstrass theorem can also be applied in horizon-penetrating Kerr coordinates, resulting in solutions that are smooth across Kerr horizons. Horizon-penetrating Kerr coordinates allow for an explicit continuation of timelike and null geodesics between appropriate regions of the maximal analytic extension of the Kerr spacetime. A part of this work is devoted to a graphic visualisation of such geodesics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03722v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuzanna Bakun, Angelika {\L}ukanty, Anastasiia Untilova, Adam Cie\'slik, Patryk Mach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the warped vacuum geometry around a Kerr black hole by quasi-periodic oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08955v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs) in the context of a new rotating black hole solution that incorporates a cosmological constant. Recent work by the authors in \cite{Ovalle:2022eqb} interpreted the cosmological constant, denoted as $\Lambda$, as a form of vacuum energy and employed a gravitational decoupling approach to derive an extended Kerr-de Sitter black hole solution, which is geometrically richer than the classical case. In this study, we derive the expressions for timelike circular geodesics within this solution and, using a relativistic precision model, calculate the corresponding frequencies of the QPOs. To constrain our model, we apply Bayesian formalism, utilizing data from three well-known microquasars: GRO 1655-40, XTE 1550-564, and GRS 1915+105. Our analysis reveals that$\Lambda$ is degenerate and correlated with other parameters. Finally, we perform a Bayesian model comparison with the Kerr metric and find that the Kerr metric is favored among the models considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08955v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Hossein Hesamolhokama, Alireza Allahyari, Jafar Khodagholizadeh, Ali Vahedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a unitary formulation of quantum field theory in curved space-time: the case of Schwarzschild black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10345v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We argue that the origin of unitarity violation and information loss paradox in our understanding of black holes (BH) lies in the standard way of doing quantum field theory in curved space-time (QFTCS), which is heavily biased on intuition borrowed from classical General Relativity. In this paper, with the quantum first approach, we formulate a so-called direct-sum QFT (DQFT) in BH space-time based on a novel formulation of discrete space-time transformations in gravity that potentially restores unitarity. By invoking the quantum effects associated with the gravitational backreaction, we show that the Hawking quanta emerging outside of the Schwarzschild radius ($r_S=2GM$) cannot be independent of the quanta that continue to be inside $r_S$. This enables the information to be carried by Hawking quanta, but in the BH DQFT formalism, we do not get any firewalls. Furthermore, DQFT leads to the BH evaporation involving only pure states. This means the quantum mechanical effects at the BH horizon produce two components of a maximally entangled pure state in geometric superselection sector Hilbert spaces. This construction enables pure states to evolve into pure states, restoring unitarity and observer complementarity. Finally, we discuss how our framework leaves important clues for formulating a scattering matrix and probing the nature of quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10345v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Sravan Kumar, Jo\~ao Marto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The covariant Langevin equation of diffusion on Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17314v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The covariant form of the multivariable diffusion-drift process is described by the covariant Fokker--Planck equation using the standard toolbox of Riemann geometry. The covariant form of the equivalent Langevin stochastic differential equation is long sought after in both physics and mathematics. We show that the simplest covariant Stratonovich stochastic differential equation depending on the local orthogonal frame (cf. vielbein) becomes the desired covariant Langevin equation provided we impose an additional covariant constraint: the vectors of the frame must be divergence-free.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17314v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rep.Math.Phys. 94, 143 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lajos Di\'osi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanics on a background modulo observation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12493v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we will answer the following question: What remains of Quantum Mechanics when we transform the background space-time into a space modularized by observation or measurement regions ? This new moduli space is constructed by identifying regions of space-time where quantum phase comparison (observation, measurement) is implied. We call it Observation Modular space (OM-space). In addition we replace in QM statements the Plank constant (h) by the quantity $\zeta_0 4 \pi^2$ (where $\zeta_0$ is the Plank Length) or otherwise, replacing $P_0$ (the Planck Momentum) by $4 \pi^2$. This maps Quantum Mechanics into a very rich dual Number Theory which we call Observation Modular Quantum Mechanics (OM-QM). We find the OM-dual to the Dirac Equation, the quantum Wave Function and a free particle's mass. The OM-QM counterparts of the Energy turns out to be a simple function of the zeroes of the Riemann zeta function. We also find the OM-QM correspondents to the electron spin, the electron charge, the Electric Field and the Fine Structure Constant. We also find the OM-QM correspondents of the Heisemberg uncertainty relation and Einstein's General Relativity Field equation emerging as certain limits of a unique OM-QM equation. We also get the OM-QM correspondents of the Gravitational Constant and the Cosmological Constant. We find the analog of holography in the OM-QM side and we get an interpretation of spin as a high dimensional curvature. An interpretation of the OM-QM correspondence is proposed as giving the part of QM information which is not measurement or observation dependent. Some potential future applications of this correspondence are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12493v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. Pereira Frugone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Computation of Overlap Reduction Functions for Pulsar Timing Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14159v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Pulsar timing arrays seek and study gravitational waves (GWs) through the angular two-point correlation function of timing residuals they induce in pulsars. The two-point correlation function induced by the standard transverse-traceless GWs is the famous Hellings-Downs curve, a function only of the angle between the two pulsars. Additional polarization modes (vector/scalar) that may arise in alternative-gravity theories have different angular correlation functions. Furthermore, anisotropy, linear, or circular polarization in the stochastic GW background gives rise to additional structure in the two-point correlation function that cannot be written simply in terms of the angular separation of the two pulsars. In this paper, we provide a simple formula for the most general two-point correlation function--or overlap reduction function (ORF)--for a gravitational-wave background with an arbitrary polarization state, possibly containing anisotropies in its intensity and polarization (linear or circular). We provide specific expressions for the ORFs sourced by the general-relativistic transverse-traceless GW modes as well as vector (or spin-1) modes that may arise in alternative-gravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14159v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neha Anil Kumar, Marc Kamionkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlations and signaling in the Schr\"{o}dinger-Newton model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Schr\"odinger--Newton model is a semi-classical theory in which, in addition to mutual attraction, massive quantum particles interact with their own gravitational fields. While there are many studies on the phenomenology of single particles, correlation dynamics in multipartite systems is largely unexplored. Here, we show that the Schr\"odinger--Newton interactions preserve the product form of the initial state of a many-body system, yet on average agreeing with classical mechanics of continuous mass distributions. This leads to a simple test of the model, based on verifying bipartite gravitational evolution towards non-product states. We show using standard quantum mechanics that, with currently accessible single-particle parameters, two masses released from harmonic traps get correlated well before any observable entanglement is accumulated. Therefore, the Schr\"odinger--Newton model can be tested with setups aimed at observation of gravitational entanglement with significantly relaxed requirements on coherence time. We also present a mixed-state extension of the model that avoids superluminal signaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09230v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacek Aleksander Gruca, Ankit Kumar, Ray Ganardi, Paramasivan Arumugam, Karolina Kropielnicka, Tomasz Paterek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence of spin superposition state caused by a quantum electromagnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14581v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the decoherence of a spatially superposed electrically neutral spin-$\frac12$ particle in the presence of a relativistic quantum electromagnetic field in Minkowski spacetime. We demonstrate that decoherence due to the spin-magnetic field coupling can be categorized into two distinct factors: local decoherence, originating from the two-point correlation functions along each branch of the superposed trajectories, and nonlocal decoherence, which arises from the correlation functions between the two superposed trajectories. These effects are linked to phase damping and amplitude damping. We also show that if the quantum field is prepared in a thermal state, decoherence monotonically increases with the field temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14581v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kensuke Gallock-Yoshimura, Yuuki Sugiyama, Akira Matsumura, Kazuhiro Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Extended Uncertainty Principles, Liouville theorem and density of states: Snyder-de Sitter and Yang models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modifications in quantum mechanical phase space lead to changes in the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, which can result in the Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) or the Extended Uncertainty Principle (EUP), introducing quantum gravitational effects at small and large distances, respectively. A combination of GUP and EUP, the Generalized Extended Uncertainty Principle (GEUP or EGUP), further generalizes these modifications by incorporating noncommutativity in both coordinates and momenta. This paper examines the impact of GEUP on the Liouville theorem in statistical physics and density of states within non-relativistic quantum mechanics framework. We find a weighted phase space volume element, invariant under the infinitesimal time evolution, in the cases of Snyder-de Sitter and Yang models, presenting how GEUP alters the density of states, potentially affecting physical (thermodynamical) properties. Special cases, obtained in certain limits from the above models are also discussed. New higher order types of GEUP and EUP are also proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05110v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Pacho{\l}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the speed of light with cosmological observations: current constraints and forecasts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05838v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We measure the speed of light with current observations, such as Type Ia Supernova, galaxy ages, radial BAO mode, as well as simulations of forthcoming redshift surveys and gravitational waves as standard sirens. By means of a Gaussian Process reconstruction, we find that the precision of such measurements can be improved from roughly 6\% and to about $2-2.5\%$ when the gravitational wave simulations are considered, and to $1.5-2\%$ when redshift survey are included in the analysis as well. This result demonstrates that we will be able to perform a cosmological measurement of a fundamental physical constant with significantly improved precision, which will help us underpinning if its value is truly consistent with local measurements, as predicted by the standard model of Cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05838v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaiane Santos, Carlos Bengaly, Jonathan Morais, Rodrigo S. Gon\c{c}alves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching current observational constraints with nonminimally coupled dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17019v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that a universe with a nonminimally coupled scalar field can fit current measurements of the expansion rate of the Universe better than the standard $\Lambda$-Cold Dark Matter model or other minimally coupled dark energy models. While we find a clear improvement in the goodness of fit for this dark energy model with respect to others that have been considered in the recent literature, using various information theoretic criteria, we show that the evidence for it is still inconclusive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17019v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William J. Wolf, Pedro G. Ferreira, Carlos Garc\'ia-Garc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
