<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Pressure of the FRW Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the effective pressure of the $N$-dimensional FRW(Friedmann-Robertson-Walker) universe in Einstein gravity, Gauss-Bonnet gravity, and Lovelock gravity. The effective pressure is defined by $P_{eff}:=-dE/dV$, where $E=\rho V$ is the effective energy and $V$ is the volume of the FRW universe inside the apparent horizon. The effective pressure in Einstein gravity is always negative and its absolute value decreases with the horizon radius $R_A$. The effective pressure in Gauss-Bonnet gravity is different with the one in Einstein gravity only when $N\geq6$, and in this case, the effective pressure is not always negative and has a minimum. The effective pressure in Lovelock gravity can have multiple zero-points and extreme points. The effective pressure in different dimensions has interesting relations. We also find that under certain condition, the effective pressure is equivalent with the `ordinary' pressure $p$ of the perfect fluid, and this condition do not depend on the specific choice of gravitational theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17789v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Bei Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Expansion of the Universe in modified gravity with quadratic terms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chapter1 introduces cosmic acceleration and outlines key features and limitations of GR and its alternatives, including teleparallel and symmetric teleparallel gravity. In Chapter2, we analyze the cosmological implications of $f(T,\mathcal{T})$ theory by considering the squared-torsion model $f(T,\mathcal{T})= \alpha \mathcal{T}+ \beta T^2$, where $T$ represents torsion and $\mathcal{T}$ is the trace of the energy-momentum tensor. In Chapter3, we explore the inflationary scenario within the framework of torsion-trace coupling gravity, utilizing a Lagrangian density derived from a function denoted as $f(T,\mathcal{T})$. In Chapter4, we aim to investigate the dark sector of the Universe, which encompasses the enigmatic components of the Dark Matter (DM) and Dark Energy (DE). We consider an extended form of the Equation of State (EoS) for DM, widely known as the Extended Bose-Einstein Condensation (EBEC) EoS for DM. In Chapter5, we propose an extended formulation of symmetric teleparallel gravity by generalizing the gravitational Lagrangian through the inclusion of an arbitrary function of $f(Q,\mathcal{T_{\mu\nu}} \mathcal{T^{\mu\nu}})$. We derived the FRW equations for a flat, homogeneous, and isotropic spacetime. In Chapter6, we delved into the dark sector of the Universe, specifically focusing on DM and DE. We examine an extended version of the EoS for DM, commonly referred to EBEC EoS for DM, given as $p=\alpha \rho + \beta \rho^2$, alongside the modified $f(Q)$ Lagrangian given by $f(Q)= \gamma Q^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17794v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaqid Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Entropy Bounded by the Specific Heat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose new bounds on black hole entropy in terms of the specific heat at fixed charges. For special spherically-symmetric and static black holes ($g_{tt} g_{rr}=-1$), we prove the bounds with suitable sufficient energy conditions. For more general static and rotating black holes, we test the bounds with a variety of examples. This work extends the previously-known algebraic inequalities of the black hole thermodynamic variables such as the Penrose inequality, to include their derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17812v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Peng Lu, H. Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic Casimir-like wormhole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of exact solutions for traversable wormhole geometries in a static and hyperbolic symmetric spacetime. In the conventional form of studying wormhole geometry, traversability requires the presence of exotic matter, which also provides negative gravity effects to keep the wormhole throat open. Using hyperbolic symmetry we obtain a solution already provided with negative energy density that replaces this effect and allows us to derive wormhole geometries that effectively violate the null energy condition. To achieve this goal, we use a generalized complexity factor for hyperbolic symmetry adapted to study wormhole geometries and with a suitable redshift function in order to construct a Casimir-like traversable hyperbolic wormhole. A detailed study has been conducted on the behavior of the matter sector, the energy conditions, and the traversability conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17906v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14526-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C. (2025)85:793</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Avalos, Ernesto Contreras, Daniel Brito, Ernesto Fuenmayor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated constraints on modified gravity from binary pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Binary pulsars offer a unique natural laboratory to test General Relativity (GR) and probe for deviations from its paradigm, as predicted by alternative theories of gravity. In this paper, we study two such possible deviations: a time variation of Newton's constant $G$ and the emission of dipolar gravitational radiation. We use updated data for some well-known pulsars, namely PSR J1738+0333, PSR J1012+5307, and PSR J1713+0747, to extract the Keplerian and post-Keplerian parameters that characterize their orbital dynamics, using recent high-precision pulsar timing data and a Bayesian parameter estimation with Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) techniques. We do this via the TEMPO2 software, the MCMC4Tempo2 plugin, and a unified python pipeline to analyze the data. We then perform a combined analysis of different binary systems to constrain both the time evolution of Newton's constant and the dipolar emission parameter $\kappa_D$. For the best of our three pulsars (PSR J1713+0747), we obtain $\dot{G}/G = (0.32 \pm 0.31) \times 10^{-12}~\text{yr}^{-1}$ at 95\% confidence, along with a stringent constraint on the dipolar emission parameter, $\kappa_D = (-0.04 \pm 0.14) \times 10^{-4}$. Thanks to the recent high-precision timing data sets, we provide updated bounds on key parameters relevant to modified gravity theories, and we find that our results are consistent with GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18188v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bussieres, M. Caldarola, S. Nesseris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole formation in matter domination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Primordial Black Holes (PBHs) formed by the collapse of rare primordial fluctuations during an early period of Matter Domination. The collapse threshold strongly depends on the shape of the peaks, decreasing as they become flatter and hence rarer. In the extreme limit of a top-hat perturbation, Harada, Kohri, Sasaki, Terada, and Yoo have argued that the growth of velocity dispersion prevents the formation of black holes unless the initial peak is larger than $\zeta_{\rm th} \sim \zeta_{\rm rms}^{2/5}$. Including the shape distribution of the peaks, we find that for a realistic cosmic abundance of PBHs, the effective threshold is larger, $\zeta_{\rm th} \sim \zeta_{\rm rms }^{1/10}$. And this model requires $\zeta_{\rm rms}\sim 10^{-1}$, which is much larger than the observed value at the CMB scales. Hence, PBH formation during Matter Domination is barely more efficient than Radiation Domination. We estimate the dimensionless spin parameter to be $a_{\rm rms} \sim \zeta_{\rm rms}^{7/4}\ll 1$, slightly larger than PBHs formed in Radiation Domination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18312v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Ebrahimian, Ali Akbar Abolhasani, Mehrdad Mirbabayi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New models of nonsingular black hole dark matter from limiting curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider phenomenological models for nonsingular black hole that satisfy the limiting curvature condition (i.e., that have curvatures that are always sub-Planckian in size) while having a more general dependence on the black hole mass than the most studied examples. These models allow black holes to exist while having regulators that are larger than the horizon scale; it has been shown previously that this can lead to observable consequences in an astrophysical setting, for allowed choices for the regulator scale. Noting that substantial horizon-scale modifications of the metric will affect black hole thermodynamics and Hawking radiation, we study these metrics in the context of primordial black hole dark matter. Considering examples with de\,Sitter and Minkowski cores, respectively, we study the effect of the regulator in these metrics on the allowed black hole mass ranges (or ``bands"), the black hole temperature, specific heat and lifetime, and the bounds on the primordial black hole fraction of the total dark matter density from the observed extragalactic gamma ray background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18322v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Selin A\c{s}mano\u{g}lu, Jens Boos, Christopher D. Carone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Dynamics of Spherically Symmetric Static Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In general relativity, the Einstein equations provide spherically symmetric static spacetimes with dynamics defined as an evolution along the radial coordinate $r$. The geometrical sector becomes a one-dimensional mechanical system, with the Misner-Sharp mass and lapse as canonically conjugate variables, and a vanishing Hamiltonian for pure gravity. Coupling classical or quantum matter fields, or introducing (quantum) corrections to general relativity, then generate a non-vanishing effective Hamiltonian, leading to non-trivial evolutions of the mass and lapse. We illustrate this mechanism through various examples of classical matter fields and identify Hamiltonians describing the effective dynamics of gravity coupled to perfect fluids with linear barotropic equation of state. Finally, we derive effective Hamiltonians that reproduce the gravitational semi-classical dynamics coupled to renormalized quantum matter fields and discuss the conditions for which the singularity at $r=0$ is resolved. In particular, we find a singularity-free black-hole-like solution, stabilized by quantum matter, smoothly transitioning from a bulk with constant negative Ricci scalar to the standard outside Schwarzschild metric. This opens new possibilities for the modeling of both semi-classical corrections and deep quantum effects on the interior structure of self-gravitating compact objects and black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18345v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etera R. Livine, Yuki Yokokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological dark energy from spacetime foam: A challenge for $\Lambda$CDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using only the standard considerations of spacetime foam and the Euclidean Quantum Gravity techniques known long ago, we result to a model of Topological Dark Energy (TDE) that outperforms the standard $\Lambda$CDM paradigm with regard to data fitting efficiency. Specifically, it is known that at the foam level, topologically non-trivial solutions such as instantons appear. In the particular case of Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity, we obtain an effective dynamical dark energy term proportional to the instanton density, and the latter can be easily calculated through standard techniques. Hence, we can immediately extract the differential equation that determines the evolution of the topologically induced effective dark energy density. Significantly, this TDE scenario allows for changing sign of dark energy during the cosmic evolution and also exhibits Dark Energy interaction with Dark Matter. We confront the TDE scenario, in both flat and non-flat cases, with Pantheon+/SH0ES Supernovae Type Ia (SNIa), Baryonic Accoustic Oscillations (BAO), and Cosmic Chronometers (CC) datasets. By applying standard model selection methods (AIC and DevIC information criteria), we find a moderate but statistically significant preference over $\Lambda$CDM scenario. Finally, we show that the TDE scenario passes constraints from Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) and thus does not spoil the thermal history of the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18389v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fotios K. Anagnostopoulos, Stylianos A. Tsilioukas, Emmanuel N. Saridakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation and Redundancy of Time-Delay Interferometry Configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-Delay Interferometry (TDI) is essential for space-based gravitational wave (GW) missions, as it suppresses laser frequency noise and achieve the required sensitivity. Beyond the standard Michelson configuration, a variety of second-generation TDI schemes have been proposed, each utilizing different combinations of inter-spacecraft laser links. In this work, we conduct a comparative study of several representative TDI configurations with varying time spans and demonstrate that their (quasi-)orthogonal channels are highly correlated, indicating substantial redundancy among these schemes. In the low-frequency regime, the performance of different TDI configurations are nearly identical. Their distinctions emerge primarily at high frequencies, where the GW wavelength becomes comparable to the arm length. In this regime, shorter TDI time spans with minimal null frequencies facilitate more accurate waveform modeling and parameter recovery in frequency domain. In contrast, configurations with longer time spans and more null frequencies, such as the Michelson, are more susceptible to frequency aliasing and waveform modulation effects, which degrade inference accuracy. However, if signal modeling and analysis are performed in the time domain, all TDI configurations become effectively equivalent. Considering the usability in both frequency and time domain, the short-span PD4L scheme, which exhibits minimal nulls and superior performance in high frequencies, emerges as a promising candidate for future space-based GW mission designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18397v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Big Bang singularity for the Einstein-Maxwell-scalar field-Vlasov system in the full strong sub-critical regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In $3+1$ dimensions, we study the stability of Kasner solutions for the Einstein-Maxwell-scalar field-Vlasov system. This system incorporates gravity, electromagnetic, weak and strong interactions for the initial stage of our universe. Due to the presence of the Vlasov field, various new challenges arise. By observing detailed mathematical structures and designing new delicate arguments, we identify a new strong sub-critical regime and prove the nonlinear stability with Kasner exponents lying in this full regime. This extends the result of Fournodavlos-Rodnianski-Speck [8] from the Einstein-scalar field system to the physically more complex system with the Vlasov field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18585v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinliang An, Taoran He, Dawei Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Gravitational Waves with Gaia and its Cross-Correlation with PTA: Absolute vs Relative Astrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Astrometric missions like Gaia provide exceptionally precise measurements of stellar positions and proper motions. Gravitational waves traveling between the observer and distant stars can induce small, correlated shifts in these apparent positions, a phenomenon known as astrometric deflection. The precision and scale of astrometric datasets make them well-suited for searching for a stochastic gravitational wave background, whose signature appears in the two-point correlation function of the deflection field across the sky. Although Gaia achieves high accuracy in measuring angular separations in its focal plane, systematic uncertainties in the satellite's absolute orientation limit the precision of absolute position measurements. These orientation errors can be mitigated by focusing on relative angles between star pairs, which effectively cancel out common-mode orientation noise. In this work, we compute the astrometric response and the overlap reduction functions for this relative astrometry approach, correcting previous expressions presented in the literature. We use a Fisher matrix analysis to compare the sensitivity of relative astrometry to that of conventional absolute astrometry. Our analysis shows that while the relative method is theoretically sound, its sensitivity is limited for closely spaced star pairs within a single Gaia field of view. Pairs with large angular separations could provide competitive sensitivity, but are practically inaccessible due to Gaia's scanning law. Finally, we demonstrate that combining astrometric data with observations from pulsar timing arrays leads to slight improvements in sensitivity at frequencies greater than approximately 10^-7 Hz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18593v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo Vaglio, Mikel Falxa, Giorgio Mentasti, Arianna I. Renzini, Adrien Kuntz, Enrico Barausse, Carlo Contaldi, Alberto Sesana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not-quite-primordial black holes seeded by cosmic string loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cosmic strings appear in many well-motivated extensions to the standard model of particle physics. If they exist, an abundant population of compact objects known as cosmic string loops permeate the Universe at all times, providing a secondary source of density perturbations that are large amplitude and non-gaussian in nature. In general, these loops are not stationary in the rest frame of the dark matter, thus their relative velocities will typically seed both spherical and filamentary overdensities in the matter era. Building upon previous work, we provide an improved framework to compute the complete halo mass function for these string seeded overdensities, valid for any loop velocity distribution. Using this mass function, we also compute the subset of halos capable of undergoing a direct collapse, forming a population of black holes with initial mass $10^{4-5} \, M_{\odot}$ at high redshifts. Interestingly, for reasonable values of the string parameters, one can reproduce the abundance of ``Little Red Dots" as inferred by JWST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17833v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryce Cyr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapsar Disk Outflows III: Detectable Neutrino and Gravitational Wave Signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the neutrino and gravitational wave (GW) signals from accretion disks formed during the failed collapse of a rotating massive star (a collapsar). Following black hole formation, a neutrino-cooled, shocked accretion disk forms, which displays non-spherical oscillations for a period of seconds before becoming advective and exploding the star. We compute the neutrino and GW signals (matter quadrupole) from collapsar disks using global axisymmetric, viscous hydrodynamic simulations. The neutrino signal with typical energies of O$(10)$ MeV is maximal during the neutrino-cooled (NDAF) phase that follows shock formation. This phase lasts for a few seconds and is easily detectable within O$(10-100)$ kpc by the IceCube Neutrino Telescope. Additional neutrino signatures from a precursor equatorial shock and by stochastic accretion plumes during the advective phase are detectable within the galaxy. The GW signal during the NDAF phase is detectable in the galaxy by current and next-generation ground-based observatories. The explosion (memory) GW signal is similar to that of standard core-collapse supernovae and can be probed with a deci-Hertz space-based detector. Shock oscillations during the NDAF phase impart time variations with frequency O$(10-100)$ Hz to the neutrino and GW signals, encoding information about the shock dynamics and inner disk. These time variations can be detectable in neutrinos by IceCube within O$(1-10)$ kpc depending on progenitor model, flavor transformation scenario, and detailed properties of the angular momentum transport mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17836v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Fern\'andez, Silas Janke, Coleman Dean, Irene Tamborra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Page Curve for an Evaporating Schwarzschild Black Hole in Dimensionally-Reduced Model of Dilaton Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17855v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study entanglement entropy of quantum fields in a (1+1)-dimensional model of dilaton gravity derived from the four-dimensional Einstein-Hilbert action by dimensional reduction. Scalar matter is coupled to gravity, while the back-reaction is included via the Polyakov-Liouville action. This theory exhibits both eternal and evaporating Schwarzschild black hole solutions. The fine-grained entropy in a collapse scenario is investigated by applying the "island rule" via the quantum extremal surface approach. We demonstrate that the fine-grained entropy of the Hawking radiation follows the Page curve, and therefore the evolution of the Hawking radiation is unitary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17855v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan {\DJ}or{\dj}evi\'c, Voja Radovanovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Supersymmetric D-brane probes in 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ $\text{AdS}_2\times\mathbf{S}^2$ Attractors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the $\kappa$-symmetry analysis of supersymmetric D-brane probes in the $\mathrm{AdS}_2 \times \mathbf{S}^2$ attractor geometry, originally performed by Simons, Strominger, Thompson, and Yin, to also include stationary -- but non-static -- worldlines carrying angular momentum along the 2-sphere. We demonstrate that certain special trajectories, with fixed radius and orbital velocity, solve the equations of motion and moreover satisfy a supersymmetry preserving condition, thus defining new $\frac12$-BPS configurations. Furthermore, these classical paths are shown to saturate a lower bound for the Hamiltonian generating global time translations, with the corresponding minimal energy depending on a generalized angular momentum vector $\boldsymbol{J}$. The direction of the latter, in turn, determines exactly which supercharges remain unbroken. Our results reveal a richer spectrum of (multi-particle) supersymmetric states in $\mathrm{AdS}_2 \times \mathbf{S}^2$, which can be organized into distinct selection sectors labeled by the conserved $SU(2)$ charges. This construction has direct applications in black hole microstate counting, the analysis of probe dynamics and $\text{AdS}_2/\text{CFT}_1$ holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17857v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Castellano, Carmine Montella, Matteo Zatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matter Spectral Functions from Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17862v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate Lorentzian quantum gravity coupled to a template matter sector with gauge fields, scalars and fermions. In the absence of quantised gravity, the matter sector by itself is renormalisable, but UV-incomplete. Provided quantum gravity offers an asymptotically safe UV-completion, we determine the photon and scalar two-point functions in the presence of gravitational fluctuations, and show that both possess a K\"all\'en-Lehmann spectral representation. Our results are achieved using functional renormalisation adapted for theories in Lorentzian signature. We explain why and how interactions with gravity modify both the infrared as well as the ultraviolet behaviour of matter spectral functions. We further determine the corresponding form factors on the level of the quantum effective action. Limitations and extensions of our study are discussed alongside implications for particle physics and unitarity of quantum gravity with matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17862v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varun Kher, Brandon King, Daniel F. Litim, Manuel Reichert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom crossing or dark interaction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent results from DESI BAO measurements, together with Planck CMB and Pantheon+ data, suggest that there may be a `phantom' phase ($w_{\rm de}&lt;-1$) in the expansion of the Universe. This inference follows when the $w_0, w_a$ parametrization for the dark energy equation of state $w_{\rm de}$ is used to fit the data. Since phantom dark energy in general relativity is unphysical, we investigate the possibility that the phantom behaviour is not intrinsic, but effective -- due to a non-gravitational interaction between dark matter and non-phantom dark energy. To this end, we assume a physically motivated thawing quintessence-like form of the intrinsic dark energy equation of state $w_{\rm de}$. Then we use a $w_0, w_a$ model for the \emph{effective} equation of state of dark energy. We find that the data favours a phantom crossing for the effective dark energy, but only at low significance. The intrinsic equation of state of dark energy is non-phantom, without imposing any non-phantom priors. A nonzero interaction is favoured at more than $3\sigma$ at $z\sim0.3$. The energy flows from dark matter to dark energy at early times and reverses at later times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18274v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S\^ecloka L. Guedezounme, Bikash R. Dinda, Roy Maartens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark and lepton mixing in the asymptotically safe Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quark mixing (CKM) matrix is near-diagonal, whereas the lepton mixing (PMNS) matrix is not. We learn that both observations can generically be explained within an ultraviolet completion of the Standard Model with gravity. We find that certain relations between CKM matrix elements should hold approximately because of asymptotically safe regimes, including $|V_{ud}|^2+|V_{us}|^2 \approx 1$ and $|V_{cd}|^2+|V_{cs}|^2\approx 1$. Theoretically, the accuracies of these relations determine the length of the asymptotically safe regimes. Experimental data confirms these relations with an accuracy of $10^{-5}$ and $10^{-3}$, respectively. This difference in accuracies is also expected, because the ultraviolet completion consists in a fixed-point cascade during which one relation is established already much deeper in the ultraviolet. This results in $|V_{ub}|^2 &lt; |V_{cb}|^2$ and translates into measurable properties of $B$-mesons.
  Similar results would hold for the PMNS matrix, if neutrino Yukawa couplings were large. The ultraviolet complete theory therefore must -- and in fact can -- avoid such an outcome. It contains a mechanism that dynamically limits the size of neutrino Yukawa couplings. Below an upper bound on the sum of Dirac neutrino masses, this allows the PMNS matrix to avoid a near-diagonal structure like the CKM matrix. Thus, large neutrino mixing is intimately tied to small Dirac neutrino masses, $\sum m_{\nu} \lesssim {\mathcal{O}} (1)\, \rm eV$ and a mass gap in the Standard Model fermion masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18304v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Astrid Eichhorn, Zois Gyftopoulos, Aaron Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>\kappa-deformed spin-1/2 field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18336v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the $\kappa$-deformed theory of a spin-1/2 field. We construct an action that is Poincar\'e invariant and analyze its consequences within the deformed framework. Our results confirm the findings of our recent analysis of the $\kappa$-deformed scalar field, where we established that there is no action invariant under both Poincar\'e symmetry and charge conjugation in the $\kappa$-deformed case. Furthermore, we present an explicit calculation of the Noether charges associated with Poincar\'e symmetry and show that their algebra closes, demonstrating the internal consistency of the theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18336v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadeusz Adach, Andrea Bevilacqua, Jerzy Kowalski-Glikman, Giacomo Rosati, Wojciech Wi\'slicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface growth scheme for bulk reconstruction and $T\bar T$ deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18435v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the dynamical connection between the surface growth scheme and the conformal field theory with $T\bar{T}$ deformation. By utilizing the extended one-shot entanglement distillation tensor network, we find that the iterative growth, i.e. radial evolution of homogenous and isotropic bulk minimal surfaces in asymptotically anti-de Sitter (AdS) spacetime can be mapped to the $T\bar{T}$ operator flow driven by the deformation parameter. Our results show that the $T\bar{T}$ deformation can provide a dynamical mechanism for the surface growth in asymptotically AdS spacetime, which may shed light on reconstructing bulk gravitational dynamics from the surface growth scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18435v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Chun Liang, Jia-Rui Sun, Yuan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational pulsars: correlations between the electromagnetic and the continuous gravitational wave signal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18439v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars emitting continuous gravitational waves may be regarded as gravitational pulsars, in the sense that it could be possible to track the evolution of their rotational period with long-baseline observations of next-generation gravitational wave interferometers. Assuming that the pulsar's electromagnetic signal is tracked and allows us to monitor the pulsar's spin evolution, we provide a physical interpretation of the possible observed correlation between this timing solution and its gravitational counterpart, if the system is also detected in gravitational waves. In particular, we show that next-generation detectors, such as the Einstein Telescope, could have the sensitivity to discern different models for the coupling between the superfluid and normal components of the neutron star and constrain the origin of timing noise (whether due to magnetospheric or internal processes). Observational confirmation of one of the proposed scenarios would therefore provide valuable information on the physics of gravitational wave emission from pulsars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18439v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Antonelli, Avishek Basu, Brynmor Haskell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent-gravity Hall effect from quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18458v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We theoretically propose a Hall effect driven by effective gravitational fields arising from quantum geometry. We develop four mechanisms for this ''emergent-gravity Hall effect" : real-space gravity, momentum-space gravity, gravitional anomalous velocity, and gravitational Lorentz force which are described by the Christoffel symbols in real, momentum, and time spaces. We construct a unified theoretical framework to systematically investigate the effects of emergent gravity in these spaces on transport phenomena based on the semiclassical theory. We demonstrate these effects by model calculations and clarify the conditions under which a finite Hall response can arise. Our findings open a new avenue for exploring gravitational effects in quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18458v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Yoshida, Takehito Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo studies of the emergent spacetime in the polarized IKKT model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The IKKT matrix model has been investigated as a promising nonperturbative formulation of superstring theory. One of the recent developments concerning this model is the discovery of the dual supergravity solution corresponding to the model obtained after supersymmetry-preserving mass deformation, which is dubbed the polarized IKKT model. Here we perform Monte Carlo simulations of this model in the case of matrix size N = 2 for a wide range of the deformation parameter Omega. While we reproduce precisely the known result for the partition function obtained by the localization method developed for supersymmetric theories, we also calculate the observables, which were not accessible by previous work, in order to probe the spacetime structure emergent from the dominant matrix configurations. In particular, we find that the saddle point corresponding to the original IKKT model is smoothly connected to the saddle represented by the fuzzy sphere dominant at large Omega, whereas the dominant configurations become diverging commuting matrices at small Omega.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18472v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chien-Yu Chou, Jun Nishimura, Cheng-Tsung Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A continuity equation compatible basis for Effective Field Theory of Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Effective Field Theory (EFT) of Dark Energy (DE) is a model independent framework that allows for the description of a wide class of dark energy and modified gravity models. This is achieved by extending the Hilbert Einstein action through the introduction of time dependent functions. However, the choice of these functions and thus the operator basis is not unique. In this paper, we propose a physically motivated constraint based on the continuity equation, leading to a continuity equation compatible (CEC) basis that ensures a clear physical interpretation of the background EFT operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18526v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Armato, Edoardo Martinelli, Marco Raveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graviton scattering on self-dual black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18605v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The computation of gravitational wave scattering on black hole spacetimes is an extremely hard problem, typically requiring approximation schemes which either treat the black hole perturbatively or are only amenable to numerical techniques. In this paper, we consider linearised gravitational waves (or gravitons) scattering on the self-dual analogue of a black hole: namely, the self-dual Taub-NUT metric. Using the hidden integrability of the self-dual sector, we can solve the linearised Einstein equations on these self-dual black hole backgrounds exactly in terms of simple, explicit quasi-momentum eigenstates. Using a description of the self-dual Taub-NUT metric and its gravitons in terms of twistor theory, we obtain an explicit formula, exact in the background, for the tree-level maximal helicity violating graviton scattering amplitude at arbitrary multiplicity, with and without spin. This is obtained from the description of the MHV amplitudes in terms of the perturbation theory of a chiral sigma model whose target is the twistor space of the background. The incorporation of spin effects on these backgrounds is a straightforward application of the Newman-Janis shift. We also demonstrate that the holomorphic collinear splitting functions in the self-dual background are equal to those in flat space so that the celestial symmetry algebra is undeformed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18605v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Adamo, Giuseppe Bogna, Lionel Mason, Atul Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OGRePy: An Object-Oriented General Relativity Package for Python</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03803v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: OGRePy is a modern, open-source Python package designed to perform symbolic tensor calculations, with a particular focus on applications in general relativity. Built on an object-oriented architecture, OGRePy encapsulates tensors, metrics, and coordinate systems as self-contained objects, automatically handling raising and lowering of indices, coordinate transformations, contractions, partial or covariant derivatives, and all tensor operations. By leveraging the capabilities of SymPy and Jupyter Notebook, OGRePy provides a robust, user-friendly environment that facilitates both research and teaching in general relativity and differential geometry. This Python package reproduces the functionality of the popular Mathematica package OGRe, while greatly improving upon it by making use of Python's native object-oriented syntax. In this paper, we describe OGRePy's design and implementation, and discuss its potential for reuse across research and education in mathematics and physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03803v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5334/jors.558</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Open Research Software, 13: 9 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Barak Shoshany</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase consistency test to identify type II strongly lensed gravitational wave signals using a single event</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15148v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For gravitationally lensed type II signals, the phase of the dominant (2, 2) mode and the higher order (3, 3) mode is offset by $-\pi/12$, or roughly -0.26 radians. Using this, we develop a test for type II imagery by allowing the phases of the (2,2) and (3,3) modes to vary separately and introducing a new waveform parameter to represent the phase offset between the two. We use simulated, asymmetric mass ratio, precessing signals to show that the test can reproduce the $-\pi/12$ phase offset when detected by three detectors for H-L optimal SNR $\gtrsim$ 40 and $\mathcal{M} \leq 30$. We analyze GW190412 and GW190814 using this parameterization, measuring the offset to be $0.13^{+0.22}_{-0.17}$ for GW190412 and $-0.05^{+0.20}_{-0.22}$ for GW190814. We also measure the Bayes factor in support of zero phase offset, $\log_{10} \mathcal{B}_{\Delta \varphi = 0}$, to be $-0.14$ for GW190412 and $0.21$ for GW190814. This implies our results are not strong enough to confidently argue if either event is a type II image, and is consistent with our statistical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15148v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/m16d-hwkz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112 (2025), 024035</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kelsie Taylor, Derek Davis, Rico K. L. Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resumming Post-Minkowskian and Post-Newtonian gravitational waveform expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19257v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive formulae that resum, at a given order in the soft limit, the infinite series of Post-Minkowskian (small gravitational coupling) or Post-Newtonian (small velocities) corrections to the gravitational waveform produced by particles moving along a general (open or closed) trajectory in the Schwarzschild geometry in the probe limit. Specifying to the case of circular orbits, we compute the waveform and the energy flux to order 30PN, and compare it against the available results in the literature. Our results are based on a novel hypergeometric representation of the solutions of the Heun equation (and its confluence), that leads to a simple mathematical proof of the Heun connection formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19257v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cipriani, Giorgio Di Russo, Francesco Fucito, Jos\'e Francisco Morales, Hasmik Poghosyan, Rubik Poghossian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reformulation of Einstein equations in the Fully Constrained Formulation: local-uniqueness, post-Newtonian expansion and initial data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10323v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Einstein equations can be written in the so-called Fully Constrained Formulation (FCF). This formulation has two different sectors: the elliptic sector, formed by the Hamiltonian and Momentum constraints together with the equations derived from the gauge choice; and the hyperbolic sector, formed by the evolution of the rest of the spacetime metric variables, which encodes the gravitational radiation. In this work, we present a modification of both sectors that keeps local uniqueness properties of the elliptic system of equations and includes a hierarchical post-Newtonian structure of all the elliptic and hyperbolic equations. This reformulation can have potential applications in cosmology and relativistic astrophysics. Moreover, we show how initial stationary data can be computed numerically using this formulation without assuming a conformally flat spatial metric, with the illustrative example of a rotating neutron star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10323v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Santos-P\'erez, Isabel Cordero-Carri\'on, Pablo Cerd\'a-Dur\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five dimensional rotating and Quintessence black hole and their hypershadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11408v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new five-dimensional rotating quintessence black hole solution. To obtain this, we employ the $5D$ version of the Janis Newman algorithm, which incorporates the Hopf bifurcation. The variation of the quintessence parameter $w_q$ causes the geometry to transition from a regular rotating universe surrounded by a cosmological horizon to a singular rotating geometry, which can represent a naked singularity, a singular extremal black hole, or a singular black hole with both an inner and an outer (event) horizon. We have also determined the properties of the ergosphere. For the study of the shadow, we followed a novel approach in which the $2D$ shadow observed by humans corresponds to cross sections of the $3D$ shadow. We analyzed how quintessence affects both the size and shape of the black hole shadow, showing that increasing the quintessence strength reduces the shadow radius, contrary to the known results in $4D$. We also propose a speculative methodology to test the shadow behavior in five dimensional scenarios, in light of the constraints provided by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) concerning the shadow of the four-dimensional supermassive black hole M87. We identify scenarios in which the theoretical $5D$ results could be consistent with these observational constraints. We have also tested the circularity deviation of our shadows, finding that the results satisfy the bound $\Delta C \leq 0.1$ both in the case with quintessence and in the limiting case without quintessence. Finally, we determine the energy conditions required to support the solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11408v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milko Estrada, L. C. N. Santos, M. S. Cunha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of asymmetry: Gravitational wave memory and the parity violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09096v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Einstein's equivalence principle suggests a deep connection between matter and spacetime, prompting the question: if matter violates parity, must gravity? This letter explores the detection of parity violation in gravity using gravitational wave (GW) memory. Gravitational parity violation could be observable through GW amplitude birefringence and large-scale structure correlations. With improved sensitivity, next-generation GW detectors offer unprecedented opportunities to probe these effects. We propose that the integrated cosmological memory (ICM) of GWs, amplified over cosmological distances, can enhance faint parity-violating signatures. Specifically, if GWs from astrophysical events have differing polarization amplitudes, as in Chern-Simons gravity, ICM significantly amplifies this disparity. ICM uniquely and independently allows us to test fundamental symmetries, constrain gravity parameters, and gain insights into the interplay of particle physics, cosmology and gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09096v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/fb3l-16w6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Chakraborty (IIT Bombay), Susmita Jana (IIT Bombay), S. Shankaranarayanan (IIT Bombay)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending the micro-Hertz detection horizons via orbital resonance effect for geocentric gravitational wave antennas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19185v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $\mu$Hz gravitational wave band holds crucial insights into coalescing supermassive black hole binaries and stochastic backgrounds but remains inaccessible due to technical challenges. We demonstrate that geocentric space-based GW detectors (e.g., TianQin, gLISA, GADFLI) can bridge this gap by considering orbital resonance effects, circumventing the need for prohibitively long baselines. When GW frequencies match with integer multiples of a satellite's orbital frequency, sustained tidal forces induce cumulative orbital deviations through resonant effects, which, combined with orbital modulation, improve detector sensitivity by 1-2 orders of magnitude in the $\mu$Hz band. Consequently, geocentric missions can detect SMBHBs across significantly expanded mass-redshift parameter space and track their inspiral-merger-ringdown evolution. Crucially, such observations could synergize with pulsar timing array data of the same binaries at earlier inspiral stages, enabling unprecedented joint tests of strong-field gravity and binary evolution. Our findings establish geocentric antennas as a cost-effective, near-term precursor for unlocking the $\mu$Hz GW astronomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19185v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiong Deng, Minghui Du, Peng Xu, Liang Huang, Ziren Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of black and white holes in ensemble of Planckons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13145v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Tsallis-Cirto non-extensive statistics with $\delta=2$ describes the processes of splitting and merging of black holes and their thermodynamics. Here we consider a toy model, which matches this generalized statistics and extends it by providing the integer valued entropy of the black hole, $S_{\rm BH}(N)=N(N-1)/2$. In this model the black hole consists of $N$ the so-called Planckons -- objects with reduced Planck mass $m_{\rm P}=1/\sqrt{8\pi G}$ -- so that its mass is quantized, $M=Nm_{\rm P}$. The entropy of each Planckon is zero, but the entropy of black hole with $N$ Planckons is provided by the $N(N-1)/2$ degrees of freedom -- the correlations between the gravitationally attracted Planckons. This toy model can be extended to a charged Reissner-Nordstr\"om (RN) black hole, which consists of charged Planckons. Despite the charge, the statistical ensemble of Planckons remains the same, and the RN black hole with $N$ Planckons has the same entropy as the electrically neutral hole, $S_{\rm RNBH}(N)=N(N-1)/2$. This is supported by the adiabatic process of transformation from the RN to Schwarzschild black hole by varying the fine structure constant. The adiabaticity is violated in the extreme limit, when the gravitational interaction between two Planckons is compensated by the repulsion between their electric charges, and the RN black hole loses stability. The entropy of a white hole formed by the same $N$ Planckons has negative entropy, $S_{\rm WH}(N)=-N(N-1)/2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13145v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. E. Volovik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator Ordering in the Relativistic Quantization: Specific Heat in the Rindler Frame</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a covariant canonical quantization for a particle in curved spacetime that tracks operator-ordering ambiguities. Parameterizing spatial and temporal ordering, we derive a Hermitian Hamiltonian with leading quantum-relativistic corrections. In a uniformly accelerated frame, we show the semiclassical heat-capacity approximation misses these effects and then develop a perturbative quantum treatment using Airy-function modes to obtain analytical first- and second-order energy shifts. Including these shifts in the partition function yields nontrivial, ordering-dependent specific-heat corrections. Numerical studies for electrons in extreme electric fields and ultra-light particles in strong gravitational fields demonstrate that these corrections become significant at intermediate temperatures. Enforcing the Tolman-Ehrenfest relation for spatial temperature variation further modulates the heat-capacity profile. Our results suggest that precision calorimetry in laser-acceleration or analogue gravity setups could probe quantum-ordering effects in relativistic regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17362v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/q73g-l7wx</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Karol Sajnok, Kacper D\k{e}bski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-extensive and quasi-homogeneous black hole thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21342v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the thermodynamic properties of black holes, taking into account the non-extensive character of their entropy at the thermodynamic and statistical level. To this end, we assume that the R\'enyi entropy determines the fundamental thermodynamic equation of black holes and is represented by a quasi-homogeneous function. As a consequence, the R\'enyi parameter turns out to be an independent thermodynamic variable, which must be treated in the framework of extended thermodynamics. As a particular example, we use the formalism of geometrothermodynamics to show that the Schwarzschild black hole can become stable for certain values of the R\'enyi parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21342v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hernando Quevedo, Mar\'ia N. Quevedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraically special perturbations of the Kerr black hole: a metric formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10384v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Perturbations of the Kerr black hole are notoriously difficult to describe in the metric formalism and are usually studied in terms of perturbations of the Weyl scalars. In this work, we focus on the algebraically special linear perturbations (ASLP) of the Kerr geometry and show how one can describe this subsector of the perturbations solely using the metric formulation. To that end, we consider the most general twisting algebraically special solution space of vacuum General Relativity. By linearizing around the Kerr solution, we obtain two coupled partial differential wave equations describing the dynamics of the Kerr ASLP. We provide an algorithm to solve them analytically in the small spin approximation up to third order, providing the first exact solution of this kind in the metric formulation. Then, we use this framework to study the stationary zero modes of the Kerr geometry. We present the exact analytical form of the shifts in mass and spin together with the required change of coordinates needed to identify them. Finally, we also provide for the first time closed expressions for the solution-generating perturbations generating the NUT and acceleration charges, thus deforming the Kerr solution to the linearized Kerr-NUT and spinning C-metric. These results provide a first concrete and rare example of perturbations of the Kerr black hole which can be treated entirely in the metric formulation. They can serve as a useful testbed to search for hidden symmetries of the Kerr perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10384v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jibril Ben Achour, Clara Montagnon, Hugo Roussille</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Non-Commutative Kalb-Ramond Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17390v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work presents a new black hole solution within the framework of a non-commutative gauge theory applied to Kalb-Ramond gravity. Using the method recently proposed in the literature [Nucl.Phys.B 1017 (2025) 116950], we employ the Moyal twist $\partial_r \wedge \partial_\theta$ to implement non-commutativity, being encoded by parameter $\Theta$. We begin by verifying that the resulting black hole no longer possesses spherical symmetry, while the event horizon remains unaffected by non-commutative corrections. The Kretschmann scalar is computed to assess the corresponding regularity. It turns out that the solution is regular, provided that the Christoffel symbols and related quantities are not expanded to second order in $\Theta$. We derive the thermodynamic quantities, including the Hawking temperature $T^{(\Theta,\ell)}$, entropy $S^{(\Theta,\ell)}$, and heat capacity $C_V^{(\Theta,\ell)}$. The remnant mass $M_{\text{rem}}$ is estimated by imposing $T^{(\Theta,\ell)} \to 0$, although the absence of a physical remnant indicates complete evaporation. Quantum radiation for bosons and fermions is analyzed via the tunneling method, where divergent integrals are treated using the residue theorem. Notably, in the low-frequency regime, the particle number density for bosons surpasses that of fermions (at least within the scope of the methods considered here). The effective potential for a massless scalar field is obtained perturbatively, enabling the computation of quasinormal modes and the time-domain profiles. Finally, further bounds on $\Theta$ and $\ell$ (Lorentz-violating paramter) are derived from solar system tests, including the perihelion precession of Mercury, light deflection, and the Shapiro time delay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17390v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Ara\'ujo Filho, N. Heidari, Iarley P. Lobo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Geodesics Cannot Spiral</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.07978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.07978v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that conformal geodesics on a Riemannian manifold cannot spiral: there does not exist a conformal geodesic which becomes trapped in every neighbourhood of a point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.07978v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Cameron, Maciej Dunajski, Paul Tod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To be or not to be, but where?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.21031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.21031v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The identification of physical subsystems in quantum mechanics as compared to classical mechanics poses significant conceptual challenges, especially in the context of quantum gravity. Traditional approaches associate quantum systems with classical ones localized in spacetime, using either Hilbert space factors for finite-dimensional systems or local operator algebras in algebraic quantum field theory. These methods ensure statistical independence for state preparations and measurements. However, covariant linearized quantum gravity disrupts this framework by preventing the formation of gauge-invariant local algebras, thereby undermining statistical independence. This presents a major obstacle for modeling early universe cosmology and gravity-induced entanglement experiments, and poses a significant roadblock toward a comprehensive theory of quantum gravity. A pivotal shift is proposed: the identification between classical and quantum systems should be dynamically evolving rather than fixed, opening the possibility of a single-world unitary quantum mechanics. This perspective aligns with the broader aim of understanding how classical spatiotemporal existence emerges from quantum mechanics and connects the measurement problem with quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.21031v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guilherme Franzmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Gravitational Wave Probe to the Nature of Dark Energy from the Aging of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17041v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One of the most dominant energy budgets in the Universe is Dark Energy, which remains enigmatic since its existence was first claimed based on observations of late-time cosmic acceleration. We propose a new way of inferring the dark energy equation of state (EoS) by measuring the aging of the Universe using only gravitational wave (GW) signals from coalescing binary compact objects of any masses. We show that the behavior of dark energy as the Universe ages will lead to a change in the observed chirp mass of GW sources inferred from observations of different stages of their coalescence. This change can be studied by monitoring a coherent source over a few years, with two well-separated GW frequencies. With a coordinated network of GW detectors that can reach a sensitivity of Big Bang Observer, we can reach a $5\sigma$ detection of the dark energy EoS parameter $w_0=-1$ and its variation with cosmic time by using stellar origin binary black holes and binary neutron stars up to high redshift over 10 years of observation time without using any external calibrator. If the next generation of GW detectors can achieve this precision, then it can open a new window to discover the fundamental nature of dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17041v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvodip Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge fields induced by curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03647v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I found an extended duality (triality) between Dirac fermions in periodic spacetime metrics, nonrelativistic fermions in gauge fields (e.g., Harper-Hofstadter model), and in periodic scalar fields on a lattice (e.g., Aubry-Andr\'e model). This indicates an unexpected equivalence between spacetime metrics, gauge fields, and scalar fields on the lattice, which is understood as different physical representations of the same mathematical object, the quantum group $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{sl}_2)$. This quantum group is generated by the exponentiation of two canonical conjugate operators, namely a linear combination of position and momentum (periodic spacetime metrics), the two components of the gauge invariant momentum (gauge fields), position and momentum (periodic scalar fields). Hence, on a lattice, Dirac fermions in a periodic spacetime metric are equivalent to nonrelativistic fermions in a periodic scalar field after a proper canonical transformation. The three lattice Hamiltonians (periodic spacetime metric, Harper-Hofstadter, and Aubry-Andr\'e) share the same properties, namely fractal phase diagrams, self-similarity, $S$-duality, topological invariants, flat bands, and topologically quantized current in the incommensurate regimes. In essence, this work unveils an unexpected link between gravity and gauge fields, opens new avenues for studying analog gravity, e.g., the Unruh effect and universe expansions/contractions, suggests the existence of an $S$-duality of spacetime curvatures, and hints at novel pathways to quantized gravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03647v4</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Marra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear effects on the Cosmological Gravitational Wave Background anisotropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15654v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Cosmological Gravitational Wave Background (CGWB) anisotropies contain valuable information about the physics of the early universe. Given that General Relativity is intrinsically nonlinear, it is important to look beyond first-order contributions in cosmological perturbations. In this work, we present a non-perturbative approach for the computation of CGWB anisotropies at large scales, providing the extension of the initial conditions and the Sachs-Wolfe effect for the CGWB, which encodes the full non-linearity of the scalar metric perturbations. We also derive the non-perturbative expression for three-point correlation of the gravitational wave energy density perturbation in the case of an inflationary CGWB with a scale-invariant power spectrum and negligible primordial non-Gaussianity. We show that, under such conditions, the gravitational wave energy density perturbations are lognormally distributed, leading to an interesting effect such as intermittency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15654v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/07/068</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alina Mierna, Sabino Matarrese, Nicola Bartolo, Angelo Ricciardone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sky Remembers everything: Celestial amplitude, Shadow and OPE in quadratic EFT of gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02899v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we compute the celestial amplitude arising from higher curvature corrections to Einstein gravity, incorporating phase dressing. The inclusion of such corrections leads to effective modifications of the theory's ultraviolet (UV) behaviour. In the eikonal limit, we find that, in contrast to Einstein's gravity, where the $u$ and $s$-channel contributions cancel, these contributions remain non-vanishing in the presence of higher curvature terms. We examine the analytic structure of the resulting amplitude and derive a dispersion relation for the phase-dressed eikonal amplitude in quadratic gravity. Furthermore, we investigate the celestial conformal block expansion of the Mellin-transformed conformal shadow amplitude within the framework of celestial conformal field theory (CCFT). As a consequence, we compute the corresponding operator product expansion (OPE) coefficients using the Burchnall-Chaundy expansion. In addition, we evaluate the OPE via the Euclidean OPE inversion formula across various kinematic channels and comment on its applicability and implications. Finally, we briefly explore the Carrollian amplitude associated with the corresponding quadratic EFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02899v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Bhattacharyya, Saptaswa Ghosh, Sounak Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of a fraction of LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA events coming from active galactic nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02924v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The formation channels of the gravitational-wave (GW) sources detected by LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA (LVK) remain poorly constrained. Active galactic nucleus (AGN) has been proposed as one of the potential hosts, but the fraction of GW events originating from AGNs has not been quantified. Here, we constrain the AGN-origin fraction $f_{\rm agn}$ by analyzing the spatial correlation between GW source localizations ($O1\!-\!O4$a) and AGNs (SDSS DR16). We report preliminary evidence of an excess of lower-luminosity ($10^{44.5} \lesssim L_{\rm bol} \le 10^{45}~\!\mathrm{erg~s}^{-1}$) as well as lower-Eddington ratio ($0.01 \lesssim \lambda_{\rm Edd} \le 0.05$) AGNs around the LVK events, the explanation of which requires $f_{\rm agn} = 0.39^{+0.41}_{-0.32}$ and $0.29^{+0.40}_{-0.25}$ (90\% confidence level) of the LVK events originating from these respective AGN populations. Monte Carlo simulations confirm that this correlation is unlikely to arise from random coincidence, further supported by anomalous variation of the error of $f_{\rm agn}$ with GW event counts. These results support the theoretical speculation that some LVK events come from lower-luminosity or lower-accretion-rate AGNs, offering critical insights into the environmental dependencies of the formation of GW sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02924v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang-Gui Zhu, Xian Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In search of an interaction in the dark sector through Gaussian Process and ANN approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04336v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Whether the current observational data indicate any evidence of interaction between the dark sector is a matter of supreme interest at the present moment. This article searched for an interaction in the dark sector between a pressure-less dark matter and a dark energy fluid with constant equation of state, $w_{\rm DE}$. For this purpose, two non-parametric approaches, namely, the Gaussian Process (GP) and the Artificial Neural Networks (ANN) have been employed and using the Hubble data from Cosmic Chronometers (CC), Pantheon+ from Supernovae Type Ia and their combination we have reconstructed the interaction function. We find that for $w_{\rm DE} =-1$, the interaction in the dark sector is not prominent while for $w_{\rm DE} \neq -1$, evidence of interaction is found depending on the value of $w_{\rm DE}$. In particularly, we find that if we start deviating from $w_{\rm DE} = -1$ either in the quintessence ($w_{\rm DE} &gt; -1$) or phantom ($w_{\rm DE} &lt; -1$) direction, an emergence of dark interaction is observed from both GP and ANN reconstructions. We further note that ANN which is applied for the first time in this context seems to play a very efficient role compared to GP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04336v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf762</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS 540, 2253-2268 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mazaharul Abedin, Guo-Jian Wang, Yin-Zhe Ma, Supriya Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclidean wormholes stability analysis revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21118v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Previous studies of linearized stability of asymptotically flat Euclidean axion wormholes found that symmetric modes suffered from divergences. We show that such divergences were an artifact of a particular way of solving the constraints, and that a full treatment leads to finite actions for such modes. The modes must thus be included in a stability analysis. However, since the action for these modes turns out to be positive, this turns out not to affect previous statements about stability of axion wormholes. We also introduce a technique that allows us to show this positivity at a pseudo-analytic level that avoids heavy numerics. Our techniques should be useful to future studies of stabilities of other wormholes as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21118v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donald Marolf, Bruno Missoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whispers from the Early Universe: The Ringdown of Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07665v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) generated by the ringdown phase of primordial black holes (PBHs) formed in the early universe. As the ringdown signal is independent of the PBH formation mechanism, the resulting SGWB offers a model-independent probe of PBHs. We numerically compute the ringdown waveform and derive the corresponding SGWB. We show that such a signal could be detected by future pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) for PBHs heavier than the solar mass. Additionally, we evaluate the SGWB from binary PBH mergers and demonstrate that it lies within the sensitivity bands of next-generation ground-based interferometers such as Cosmic Explorer and Einstein Telescope, suggesting a multi-band observational strategy for probing the PBH dark matter scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07665v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yuan, Zhen Zhong, Qing-Guo Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alleviating the Hubble tension with Torsion Condensation (TorC)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09228v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Constraints on the cosmological parameters of Torsion Condensation (TorC) are investigated using Planck 2018 Cosmic Microwave Background data. TorC is a case of Poincar\'e gauge theory -- a formulation of gravity motivated by the gauge field theories underlying fundamental forces in the standard model of particle physics. Unlike general relativity, TorC incorporates intrinsic torsion degrees of freedom while maintaining second-order field equations. At specific parameter values, it reduces to the $\Lambda$CDM model, providing a natural extension to standard cosmology. The base model of TorC introduces two parameters beyond those in $\Lambda$CDM: the initial value of the torsion scalar field and its time derivative -- one can absorb the latter by allowing the dark energy density to float. To constrain these parameters, `PolyChord` nested sampling algorithm is employed, interfaced via `Cobaya` with a modified version of `CAMB`. Our results indicate that TorC allows for a larger inferred Hubble constant, offering a potential resolution to the Hubble tension. Tension analysis using the $R$-statistic shows that TorC alleviates the statistical tension between the Planck 2018 and SH0Es 2020 datasets, though this improvement is not sufficient to decisively favour TorC over $\Lambda$CDM in a Bayesian model comparison. This study highlights TorC as a compelling theory of gravity, demonstrating its potential to address cosmological tensions and motivating further investigations of extended theories of gravity within a cosmological context. As current and upcoming surveys -- including Euclid, Roman Space Telescope, Vera C. Rubin Observatory, LISA, and Simons Observatory -- deliver data on gravity across all scales, they will offer critical tests of gravity models like TorC, making the present a pivotal moment for exploring extended theories of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09228v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sinah Legner, Will Handley, Will Barker</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
