<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>gr-qc updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc</link>
    <description>gr-qc updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/gr-qc" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 05:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Gravastar Structure with the Finch-Skea Metric in Extended Modified Symmetric Teleparallel Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study analyzes the physical features of a gravastar within the $f(\mathcal{Q}, \mathbb{T})$ gravity framework, where $\mathcal{Q}$ is the non-metricity scalar and $\mathbb{T}$ is the trace of the energy-momentum tensor. Gravastars present a viable alternative to black holes, featuring a central de Sitter core, a surrounding thin shell and a dynamic layer in the Schwarzschild exterior that separates these two regions. Using the Finch-Skea metric, the necessary field equations for the core and shell are derived, while the Israel junction conditions maintain a seamless connection between the inner and outer regions. This work extensively explores crucial aspects such as energy distribution, proper length, energy conditions, entropy and the equation of state parameter. The model's stability is studied through the effective potential, redshift, causality conditions and adiabatic index. Our results highlight the essential role of modified gravity in maintaining the structural viability and stability of gravastars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09679v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Phys. B 1011(2025)116791</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Iqra Ibrar, M. Sharif</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simpler Embeddings of Causal Sets into Minkowski Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new method for embedding a causal set into Minkowski spacetime. The method is similar to a previously presented method, but is simpler and provides better embedding results. The method uses spacetime volumes to define causal set analogs of time coordinates for all elements, and spatial distances for pairs of causally related elements. The spatial distances for causally related pairs are then used to derive spatial distances for spaceliked separated pairs by applying the triangle inequality. The result is a matrix of spatial distances for all pairs of elements in the causal set. This distance matrix can be decomposed to give coordinates in Minkowski spacetime. Results are presented showing good quality embeddings into Minkowski spacetime for dimensions d=2,3,4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09701v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Johnston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from gauge fixing and polymerization of loop quantum black holes with a cosmological constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Loop quantization of Schwarzschild black holes with a cosmological constant for polymerization parameters which are constant is studied in the effective spacetime description. We show that for the positive cosmological constant there can be an appearance of large quantum effects at small spacetime curvatures. These effects can manifest as an additional black hole horizon. While the central singularity is resolved in all the cases, these limitations demonstrate incompatibility of the Kantowski-Sachs gauge and schemes with fixed polymerization parameters in the presence of a positive cosmological constant. In contrast, the case of a negative cosmological constant is free of such problematic features. Noted limitations are similar to those in the $\mu_o$ scheme for the loop quantization of cosmological models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09718v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geeth Ongole, Parampreet Singh, Anzhong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The information loss problem and Hawking radiation as tunneling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we review some methods that tried to solve the information loss problem. In particular, we revisit the solution based on Hawking radiation as tunneling, and provide a detailed statistical interpretation on the black hole entropy in terms of the quantum tunneling probability of Hawking radiation from the black hole. In addition, we show that black hole evaporation is governed by a time-dependent Schrodinger equation that sends pure states into pure states rather than into mixed states (Hawking had originally established that the final result would be mixed states). This is further confirmation of the fact that black hole evaporation is unitary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09924v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e27020167</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 27, 167 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Baocheng Zhang, Christian Corda, Qing-yu Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Uncertainty Principle mimicking dynamical Dark Energy: matter perturbations and gravitational wave data analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10043v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) stands out as a nearly ubiquitous feature in quantum gravity modeling, predicting the emergence of a minimum length at the Planck scale. Recently, it has been shown to modify the area-law scaling of the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy, giving rise to deformed Friedmann equations within Jacobson's approach. The ensuing model incorporates the GUP correction as a quintessence-like dark energy that supplements the cosmological constant, influencing the dynamics of the early Universe while aligning with the $\Lambda$CDM paradigm in the current epoch. In this extended scenario, we examine the growth of matter perturbations and structure formation employing the Top-Hat Spherical Collapse approach. Our analysis reveals that the profile of the density contrast is sensitive to the GUP parameter $\beta$, resulting in a slower gravitational evolution of primordial fluctuations in the matter density. We also discuss implications for the relic density of Primordial Gravitational Waves (PGWs), identifying the parameter space that enhances the PGW spectrum. Using the sensitivity of the next-generation GW observatories in the frequency range below $10^3\,\mathrm{Hz}$, we constrain $\beta\lesssim10^{39}$, which is more stringent than most other cosmological/astrophysical limits. This finding highlights the potential role of GWs in the pursuit of understanding quantum gravity phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10043v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139315</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Lett.B 862 (2025) 139315</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Gaetano Luciano, Yassine Sekhmani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex degenerate metrics in general relativity: a covariant extension of the Moore-Penrose algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Moore-Penrose algorithm provides a generalized notion of an inverse, applicable to degenerate matrices. In this paper, we introduce a covariant extension of the Moore-Penrose method that permits to deal with general relativity involving complex non-invertible metrics. Unlike the standard technique, this approach guarantees the uniqueness of the pseudoinverse metric through the fulfillment of a set of covariant relations, and it allows for the proper definition of a covariant derivative operator and curvature-related tensors. Remarkably, the degenerate nature of the metric can be given a geometrical representation in terms of a torsion tensor, which vanishes only in special cases. Applications of the new scheme to complex black hole geometries and cosmological models are also investigated, and a generalized concept of geodesics that exploits the notion of autoparallel and extremal curves is presented. Relevance of our findings to quantum gravity and quantum cosmology is finally discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10053v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Garnier, Emmanuele Battista</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The implications of stochastic gas torques for asymmetric binaries in the LISA band</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational waves from asymmetric mass-ratio black-hole binaries carry unique information about their astrophysical environment. For instance, the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) could potentially measure the amplitude and slope of gas torques in binaries embedded in the accretion disks of Active Galactic Nuclei, helping differentiate competing accretion disk models. However, this relies on simplified analytic models, which do not account for the stochastic variability of torques seen in hydrodynamic simulations. In this work, we use hydrodynamic simulations to create gravitational waveforms for extreme and intermediate mass-ratio inspirals in the LISA band. We then analyze these simulated waveforms using simpler templates that assume analytic torques, without stochastic time variability. By performing realistic Bayesian parameter estimation, we find no bias at 90% confidence in the binary parameters; however, estimates of accretion disk parameters, such as torque amplitude and slope, may be biased. Typically, the posterior distribution is centered around the average value of the torques, but when stochastic variability is large, the posterior can indicate no torques, even though they are present in the simulation. Our results suggest that while simplified analytic torque models work well for estimating binary parameters, caution is needed when using them to infer properties of the accretion disk. This work moves towards a more realistic assessment of one of the LISA science objectives, i.e., probing the properties of the astrophysical environments of black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10087v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Copparoni, Lorenzo Speri, Laura Sberna, Andrea Derdzinski, Enrico Barausse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of definitions of angular momentum at null infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The supertranslation ambiguity of angular momentum at null infinity creates a technical difficulty in choosing the proper definition for this conserved quantity. As a result, many different approaches are found in the literature. This article aims to review the most relevant of these notions and compare their most significant properties. A new definition of angular momentum at null infinity is also proposed, which is supertranslation invariant under certain assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10105v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Szymon Bagi\'nski, Jacek Jezierski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test fields and naked singularities: is the second law the cosmic censor?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been claimed that a Kerr-Newman black hole can generically be overspun by neutral test fields, and it has been argued that even when backreactions are taken into account, the black hole can still be destroyed. In this paper, we revisit the weak cosmic censorship conjecture for a Kerr-Newman black hole with a test scalar field and a neutrino field, and point out that the assumption in previous work regarding the energy and angular momentum of the test fields absorbed by the black hole violates the second law of black hole thermodynamics. By solving the test scalar field and neutrino field near the event horizon explicitly, we demonstrate that an extremal Kerr-Newman black hole cannot be overspun by a test scalar field but can be destroyed by a neutrino field. Our results indicate that the condition required to overspin an extremal Kerr-Newman black hole coincides with the condition needed to violate the second law of black hole thermodynamics. Furthermore, we observe that such a violation of the second law might inevitably result in a breakdown of the weak cosmic censorship conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10133v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Jiang Yang, Zheng-Quan Cui, Shao-Wen Wei, Yu-Xiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stimulated emission or absorption of gravitons by light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the exchange of energy between gravitational and electromagnetic waves in a Sagnac type geometry, in analogy to an ``optical Weber bar.'' In the presence of a gravitational wave (such as the ones measured by LIGO), we find that it should be possible to observe signatures of stimulated emission or absorption of gravitons with present day technology. Apart from marking the transition from passively observing to actively manipulating such a natural phenomenon, this could also be used as a complementary detection scheme. Non-classical photon states may improve the sensitivity and might even allow us to test certain quantum aspects of the gravitational field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10221v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ralf Sch\"utzhold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spacetime curvature corrections for the Yukawa potential and its application for the Reissner-Nordstr\"om Metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10247v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the influence of the spacetime curvature on the Yukawa potential, focusing on boson-boson interactions derived from the {\Phi^3} theory. Using the Bunch-Parker propagator expansion within Born's first approximation, we derive a Yukawa-like potential in a curved spacetime. We analyze the impact of the curvature on the propagator in momentum space, revealing modifications to the potential and showing that the corrections are determined by geometric quantities from Einstein's equations, like the Ricci scalar and tensor. We illustrate this using the Reissner-Nordstr\"om metric, highlighting the corrections' magnitude for specific parameters. Our results underscore the nuanced interplay between spacetime curvature and quantum interactions, providing insights into nucleon-nucleon systems in curved spacetimes or near strong gravitational fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10247v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. V. Zamperlini, C. C. Barros Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Null Torus Knotted Gravitational Waves from Gravitoelectromagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct a non-null torus-knotted gravitational monochromatic wave solution of the linearized Einstein equations in vacuum, employing the gravitoelectromagnetic (GEM) framework by analogy with classical electrodynamics. We derive the geometric objects, including the line element, the Riemann tensor, the Ricci tensor, the Ricci scalar, and the geodesic equation for this background. Also, we investigate two properties inherent to this solution due to its GEM origin: the dual GEM potential and GEM helicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10347v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. S. Facundo, I. V. Vancea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flipped Rotating Axion Non-minimally Coupled to Gravity: Baryogenesis and Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the co-genesis of baryon asymmetry and dark matter can be achieved through the rotation of an axion-like particle, driven by a flip in the vacuum manifold's direction at the end of inflation. This can occur if the axion has a periodic non-minimal coupling to gravity, while preserving the discrete shift symmetry. In non-oscillating inflation models, after inflation there is typically a period of kination (with $w = 1$). In this case, it is shown that the vacuum manifold of the axion is flipped and the axion begins rotating in field space, because it can slide across the decreasing potential barrier as in Ricci reheating. Such a rotating axion can generate the baryon asymmetry of the Universe through spontaneous baryogenesis, while at later epochs it can oscillate as dark matter. The period of kination makes the primordial gravitational waves (GW) generated during inflation sharply blue-tilted which constrains the parameter space due to GW overproduction, while being testable by next generation CMB experiments. As a concrete example, we show that such a cogenesis of baryon asymmetry and dark matter can be realized for the axion as the Majoron in the Type-I seesaw setup, predicting mass ranges for the Majoron below sub eVs, with right-handed neutrino mass above $\mathcal{O}(10^{8})$ GeV. We also show that in order to avoid fragmentation of the axion condensate during the rotation, we require the non-minimal coupling \mbox{$\xi \sim (f/m_P)^2 $} or somewhat larger, where $f$ is the axion decay constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08720v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Chen, Suruj Jyoti Das, Konstantinos Dimopoulos, Anish Ghoshal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Effects of a Small Primordial Black Hole Passing Through the Human Body</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The gravitational effects of a primordial black hole (PBH) passing through the human body are examined, with the goal of determining the minimum mass necessary to produce significant injury or death. Two effects are examined: the damage caused by a shock wave propagating outward from the black hole trajectory, and the dissociation of brain cells from tidal forces produced by the black hole on its passage through the human body. It is found that the former is the dominant effect, with a cutoff mass for serious injury or death of approximately $M_{PBH} &gt; 1.4 \times 10^{17} {\rm g}$. The number density of primordial black holes with a mass above this cutoff is far too small to produce any observable effects on the human population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09734v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J. Scherrer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the self-coherence of primordial quantum fluctuations with complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A smoking gun for our current paradigm of the early universe would be direct evidence for the quantum mechanical origin of density perturbations which are conjectured to seed the large scale structure of our universe. A recently-proposed novel phenomenon is that of \textit{recoherence}, wherein a specific interaction between the adiabatic and the entropic sector leads to the adiabatic mode retaining a coherent state after a transient increase in linear entropy. In this paper, we choose the most general Gaussian action and analyze the evolution of linear entropy, complexity of purification (COP), and complexity of formation (COF) to capture the interplay between decoherence and recoherence in this model. In the presence of two types of couplings that drive these two opposing characteristics, we highlight how COF is an efficient tool for diagnosing dynamics for such an open quantum system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09739v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Bhattacharya, Suddhasattwa Brahma, S. Shajidul Haque, Jacob S. Lund, Arpon Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimax surfaces and the holographic entropy cone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study and prove properties of the minimax formulation of the HRT holographic entanglement entropy formula, which involves finding the maximal-area surface on a timelike hypersurface, or time-sheet, and then minimizing over the choice of time-sheet. In this formulation, the homology condition is imposed at the level of the spacetime: the homology regions are spacetime volumes rather spatial regions. We show in particular that the smallest minimax homology region is the entanglement wedge. The minimax prescription suggests a way to construct a graph model for time-dependent states, a weighted graph on which min cuts compute HRT entropies. The existence of a graph model would imply that HRT entropies obey the same inequalities as RT entropies, in other words that the RT and HRT entropy cones coincide. Our construction of a graph model relies on the time-sheets obeying a certain ``cooperating'' property, which we show holds in some examples and for which we give a partial proof; however, we also find scenarios where it may fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09894v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brianna Grado-White, Guglielmo Grimaldi, Matthew Headrick, Veronika E. Hubeny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linking Analytic Light Curve Models to Physical Properties of Kilonovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10021v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In binary neutron star mergers, lanthanide-rich dynamical ejecta and lanthanide-poor post-merger ejecta have been often linked to the red and blue kilonova emission, respectively. However, analytic light curve modeling of kilonova often results in the ejecta parameters that are at odds with such expectations. To investigate the physical meaning of the derived parameters, we perform analytic modeling of the kilonova light curves calculated with realistic multi-dimensional radiative transfer based on the numerical relativity simulations. Our fiducial simulations adopt a faster-moving, less massive dynamical ejecta and slower-moving, more massive post-merger ejecta. The results of analytic modeling, however, show that the inferred ''red'' component is more massive and slower, while the ''blue'' component is less massive and faster, as also inferred for GW170817/AT2017gfo. This suggests that the parameters derived from light curve modeling with an analytic model do not represent the true configuration of the kilonova ejecta. We demonstrate that the post-merger ejecta contributes to both blue and red emissions: the emission from the post-merger ejecta is absorbed and reprocessed to red emission by the dynamical ejecta with a higher lanthanide fraction. Our results caution against separately discussing the origins of red and blue components derived from the analytic models. Despite of the challenges in the parameter estimation, we show that the estimate of the total ejecta mass is rather robust within a factor of a few, reflecting the total luminosity output. To derive the reliable total ejecta mass, multi-epoch observations in near-infrared wavelengths near their light curve peaks are important.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10021v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayari Kitamura, Kyohei Kawaguchi, Masaomi Tanaka, Sho Fujibayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Schwarzschild-(A)dS Black Holes: Unitarity and Singularity Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10104v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the canonical quantisation of spherically symmetric spacetimes within unimodular gravity, leaving sign choices in the metric general enough to include both the interior and exterior Schwarzschild-(Anti-)de Sitter spacetime. In unimodular gravity the cosmological constant appears as an integration constant analogous to a total energy, and the quantum Wheeler-DeWitt equation takes the form of a Schr\"odinger equation in unimodular time. We discuss self-adjoint extensions of the Schr\"odinger-like Hamiltonian arising from the requirement of unitarity in unimodular time, and identify a physically motivated one-parameter family of extensions. For semiclassical states we are able to derive analytical expressions for expectation values of the metric, representing a quantum-corrected, nonsingular extension of the classical Schwarzschild-(A)dS geometry which describes a quantum transition between asymptotic black hole and white hole states. The sign of the self-adjoint extension parameter corresponds to the allowed sign of the black hole/white hole mass, and so it can be chosen to ensure that this mass is always positive. We also discuss tunnelling states which allow for a change in the sign of the mass, but which are not semiclassical in high-curvature regions. Our mechanism for singularity resolution and the explicit form of the quantum-corrected metric can be compared to other proposals for black holes in quantum gravity, and in the asymptotically AdS case can be contrasted with holographic arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10104v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steffen Gielen, Sofie Ried</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning-based holography for T-linear resistivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10245v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We employ deep learning within holographic duality to investigate $T$-linear resistivity, a hallmark of strange metals. Utilizing Physics-Informed Neural Networks, we incorporate boundary data for $T$-linear resistivity and bulk differential equations into a loss function. This approach allows us to derive dilaton potentials in Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton-Axion theories, capturing essential features of strange metals, such as $T$-linear resistivity and linear specific heat scaling. We also explore the impact of the resistivity slope on dilaton potentials. Regardless of slope, dilaton potentials exhibit universal exponential growth at low temperatures, driving $T$-linear resistivity and matching infrared geometric analyses. At a specific slope, our method rediscovers the Gubser-Rocha model, a well-known holographic model of strange metals. Additionally, the robustness of $T$-linear resistivity at higher temperatures correlates with the asymptotic AdS behavior of the dilaton coupling to the Maxwell term. Our findings suggest that deep learning could help uncover mechanisms in holographic condensed matter systems and advance our understanding of strange metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10245v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byoungjoon Ahn, Hyun-Sik Jeong, Chang-Woo Ji, Keun-Young Kim, Kwan Yun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An overview of what current data can (and cannot yet) say about evolving dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent measurements of Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) and distance moduli from Type Ia supernovae suggest a preference for Dynamical Dark Energy (DDE) scenarios characterized by a time-varying equation of state (EoS). This focused review assesses its robustness across independent measurements and surveys. Using the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder (CPL) parameterization to describe the evolution of the DE EoS, we analyze over 35 dataset combinations, incorporating Planck Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) anisotropies, three independent Type Ia supernova (SN) catalogs (PantheonPlus, Union3, DESY5), BAO measurements from DESI and SDSS, and expansion rate measurements $H(z)$ inferred from the relative ages of massive, passively evolving galaxies at early cosmic times known as Cosmic Chronometers (CC). This review has two main objectives: first, to evaluate the statistical significance of the DDE preference across different dataset combinations, which incorporate varying sources of information. Specifically, we consider cases where only low-redshift probes are used in different combinations, others where individual low-redshift probes are analyzed together with CMB data, and finally, scenarios where high- and low-redshift probes are included in all possible independent combinations. Second, we provide a reader-friendly synthesis of what the latest cosmological and astrophysical probes can (and cannot yet) reveal about DDE. Overall, our findings highlight that combinations that \textit{simultaneously} include PantheonPlus SN and SDSS BAO significantly weaken the preference for DDE. However, intriguing hints supporting DDE emerge in combinations that do not include DESI-BAO measurements: SDSS-BAO combined with SN from Union3 and DESY5 (with and without CMB) support the preference for DDE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10264v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Giar\`e, Tariq Mahassen, Eleonora Di Valentino, Supriya Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonians to all Orders in Perturbation Theory and Higher Loop Corrections in Single Field Inflation with PBHs Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10287v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We calculate the action and the interaction Hamiltonians to all orders in perturbation theory in the model of single field inflation with a transient ultra slow-roll phase. Employing the formalism of EFT of inflation, we obtain a compact non-perturbative expression for the interaction Hamiltonian in terms of the Goldstone field $\pi$ in the decoupling limit. In addition, we also present a non-linear relation between $\pi$ and the curvature perturbations to all orders in perturbation theory. These are powerful results which enable us to calculate the cosmological correlators and loop corrections to any order in perturbation theory. As a non-trivial example, we calculate the $L$-loop corrections on long CMB scale perturbations in the USR models which are used for PBHs formation. We show that the loop corrections scale like $(\Delta N {\cal P}_e L) ^L$ in which ${\cal P}_e$ is the peak of the power spectrum and $\Delta N$ is the duration of the USR phase. This indicates that the loop corrections grow quickly out of perturbative control for large values of $L$. In the conventional USR setup for PBHs formation with $\Delta N \simeq 2.5$, this happens at $L=4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10287v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Firouzjahi, Bahar Nikbakht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Past stability of FLRW solutions to the Einstein-Euler-scalar field equations and their big bang singularites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07475v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish, in spacetime dimensions $n\geq 3$, the nonlinear stability in the contracting direction of Friedmann-Lema\^itre-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) solutions to the Einstein-Euler-scalar field equations with linear equations of state $P=c_s^2 \rho$ for sounds speeds $c_s$ satisfying $1/(n-1)&lt;c_s^2 &lt; 1$. We further show that nonlinear perturbations of the FLRW solutions are asymptotically pointwise Kasner and terminate in crushing, asymptotically velocity term dominated (AVTD) big bang singularities characterised by curvature blow-up.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07475v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4310/BPAM.2024.v1.n2.a4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Beijing J. of Pure and Appl. Math., Volume 1, Number 2, 515-637, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Florian Beyer, Todd A. Oliynyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary constraints: Gluing in a toy model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11880v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is possible to solve the Einstein constraint equations as an evolutionary rather than an elliptic system. Here we consider the Gauss constraint in electrodynamics as a toy model for thist. We use a combination of the evolutionary method with the gluing construction to produce initial data for an electromagnetic pulse surrounded by vacuum. It turns out that solving the evolutionary form of the constraint is straightforward, and explicitly yields the desired type of initial data. In contrast, proving the existence of a solution to the same problem within the elliptic setting requires sophisticated arguments based on functional analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11880v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Found. Phys. 55 (2025) 16</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ingemar Bengtsson, Istvan Racz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic Properties and Shadows of Black Holes in $f(R,T)$ Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00606v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore two $f(R,T)$ gravity models and derive black hole solutions within these models. We focus on investigating how the $f(R,T)$ model influences the thermodynamic characteristics of black holes by studying their thermodynamic topology and thermodynamic geometry. We consider five specific values of the thermodynamic parameter $\omega$, which signify five different classes of black hole solutions in general relativity (GR). We observe significant changes in the local topological properties of these black holes compared to GR, depending on the model parameters. Notably, we identify an additional topological class $W=0$ for some values of $\omega$ that is absent in the GR framework. We also study the thermodynamic geometry of the black hole using the Geometrothermodynamics (GTD) formalism. Our analysis demonstrates that the singular point, where the GTD scalar curvature diverges, corresponds exactly to the point where the heat capacity changes sign. Additionally, we constrain the model parameters of both models considered by utilizing black hole shadow data from the Sgr A* black hole, measured by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00606v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.15302/frontphys.2025.035201</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Front. Phys., 2025, 20(3): 035201</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bidyut Hazarika, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fiber optics in curved space-times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23048v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Single-mode fibers are used in fiber-optic gyroscopes to measure the Sagnac effect and are planned to be used in forthcoming experiments on the gravitationally induced phase shift in single photons. However, current theoretical models of such experiments are limited to ray-optics approximations or, if based on wave optics, to a restricted class of fiber alignments. To overcome these shortcomings, this paper develops a comprehensive perturbative scheme to solve for electromagnetic modes, i.e., monochromatic solutions to Maxwell's equations, of arbitrarily bent step-index fibers in general stationary space-times. This leads to transport equations for the electromagnetic phase and polarization that include the gravitational redshift, the Sagnac effect, a generalization of Rytov's law to curved space, a gravitational Faraday effect in the form of shift-induced gyrotropy, as well as inverse spin Hall effects caused by fiber bending, gravitational acceleration, and space-time curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23048v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013162</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013162 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas B. Mieling, Mario Hudelist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Einstein-Horndeski gravity and the ultra slowly evaporating black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03785v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study the evaporation behaviors of asymptotically flat charged black holes in the Einstein-Horndeski gravity theory. Based on the thermodynamics of the Horndeski black hole, we present a physical understanding of the scalar charge of the Horndeski black hole and also clarify its connection to the Einstein vector theory. As the presence of non-minimal coupling, the evaporating behaviors of the Horndeski black hole are vastly different from the Reissner-Nordstrom (RN) black hole case. Due to the different spacetime and electric field structures, the evaporation rate of the Horndeski black hole will slow down at the late stage of evaporation and thus gain a lifetime much longer than the RN black hole. These results illuminate the effect of non-minimally coupled matters on the black hole evaporation and provide clues to search for these matter fields in future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03785v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139303</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics Letters B Volume 862, March 2025, 139303</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Liang, Yu-Sen An, Chen-Hao Wu, Ya-Peng Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal Love numbers of analogue black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tidal Love numbers quantify the conservative static response of compact objects to external tidal fields, and are found to vanish exactly for asymptotically flat black holes in four-dimensional general relativity. Many aspects of the physics of black holes have an analogue in the theory of supersonic acoustic flows, including the existence of an event horizon and associated phenomena, such as quasinormal modes and superradiance. In this paper, we investigate the tidal Love numbers of acoustic black holes in different number of dimensions. We find that they exhibit a number of similar properties as higher-dimensional general relativistic black holes, such as logarithmic running with radial distance, and vanishing tidal response for special multipole moments. We show that the latter is a consequence of ladder symmetries, analogous to those identified for black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08728v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio De Luca, Brandon Khek, Justin Khoury, Mark Trodden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic inflation and holographic dark energy from entropy of the anti-de Sitter black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02759v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Based on the entropy of anti-de Sitter black hole, a new holographic dark energy model has been proposed. When the Hubble horizon and particle horizon are chosen as the IR cutoff, the late-time accelerated expansion of universe is realized. In this paper, we consider the Hubble horizon as the IR cutoff to investigate holographic inflation and slow-roll inflation in this model. We find that slow-roll inflation with the chaotic potential $V_{0}\phi^{n}$ is favored by Planck results for some special cases, such as $n=1/3$ and $n=1/2$, while holographic inflation is not supported by Planck results. Then, we analyze the reheating temperature and the number of reheating e-folds in this model, and we find that the results favor the cases $n=1/3$ and $n=1/2$. Finally, we use the dynamical analysis method, statefinder diagnostic pairs, and the Hubble diagram to analyze this model. Our results indicate that when $b^{2}$ takes a small value, this model cannot be distinguished from the standard $\Lambda$CDM model and can serve as an alternative to it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02759v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qihong Huang, He Huang, Bing Xu, Kaituo Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resumming Post-Minkowskian and Post-Newtonian gravitational waveform expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The gravitational waveform emitted by a particle moving in a Schwarzschild geometry can be computed, in perturbation theory, as a double series expansion in the limit where distances are large with respect to the size of the horizon, $z=2M/r\ll 1$ (Post-Minkowskian approximation), but small with respect to the gravitational wavelength, $y=2{\rm i} \omega r\ll 1$ (Post-Newtonian approximation). While in the case of bounded systems the two expansions are linked, for scattering processes they describe complementary regions of spacetime. In this paper, we derive all order formulae for those two expansions of the waveform, where the entire dependence on the $y$ or $z$ variables is resummed under the assumption $\omega M\ll 1$. The results are based on a novel hypergeometric representation of the confluent Heun functions and provide a new derivation of the recently discovered Heun connection formulae. Similar results are found for the non-confluent Heun case. Finally, in the case of circular orbits we compute our formulae at order 30PN and show excellent agreement against solutions obtained via numerical integrations and the MST method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19257v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cipriani, Giorgio Di Russo, Francesco Fucito, Jos\'e Francisco Morales, Hasmik Poghosyan, Rubik Poghossian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic perfect fluids near Kasner singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.03435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.03435v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish the existence of a stable family of solutions to the Euler equations on Kasner backgrounds near the singularity with the full expected asymptotic data degrees of freedom and no symmetry or isotropy restrictions. Existence is achieved through transforming the Euler equations into the form of a symmetric hyperbolic Fuchsian system followed by an application of a new existence theory for the singular initial value problem. Stability is shown to follow from the existence theory for the (regular) global initial value problem for Fuchsian systems that was developed in arXiv:1907.04071. In fact, for each solution in the family, we prove the existence of an open set of nearby solutions with the same qualitative asymptotics and show that any such perturbed solution agrees again with another solution of the singular initial value problem. All our results hold in the regime where the speed of sound of the fluid is large in comparison to all Kasner exponents. This is interpreted as the regime of stable fluid asymptotics near Kasner big bang singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.03435v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4310/CAG.241204004223</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Analysis and Geometry, Volume 32, Number 6, 1701-1794, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Florian Beyer, Todd A. Oliynyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Action, entropy and pair creation rate of charged black holes in de Sitter space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.12713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.12713v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute and clarify the interpretation of the on-shell Euclidean action for Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m black holes in de Sitter space. We show the on-shell action is minus the sum of the black hole and cosmological horizon entropy for arbitrary mass and charge in any number of dimensions. This unifying expression helps to clear up a confusion about the Euclidean actions of extremal and ultracold black holes in de Sitter, as they can be understood as special cases of the general expression. We then use this result to estimate the probability for the pair creation of black holes with arbitrary mass and charge in an empty de Sitter background, by employing the formalism of constrained instantons. Finally, we suggest that the decay of charged de Sitter black holes is governed by the gradient flow of the entropy function and that, as a consequence, the regime of light, superradiant, rapid charge emission should describe the potential decay of extreme charged Nariai black holes to singular geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.12713v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward K. Morvan, Jan Pieter van der Schaar, Manus R. Visser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes as Fermion Factories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00741v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultralight bosons near rotating black holes can undergo significant growth through superradiant energy extraction, potentially reaching field values close to the Planck scale and transforming black holes into effective transducers for these fields. The interaction between boson fields and fermions may lead to parametric production or Schwinger pair production of fermions, with efficiencies significantly exceeding those of perturbative decay processes. Additionally, the spatial gradients of scalar clouds and the electric components of vector clouds can accelerate fermions, resulting in observable fluxes. This study considers both Standard Model neutrinos and dark sector fermions, which could contribute to boosted dark matter. Energy loss due to fermion emissions can potentially quench the exponential growth of the cloud, leading to a saturated state. This dynamic provides a framework for establishing limits on boson-neutrino interactions, previously constrained by neutrino self-interaction considerations. In the saturation phase, boson clouds have the capacity to accelerate fermions to TeV energies, producing fluxes that surpass those from atmospheric neutrinos near black holes. These fluxes open new avenues for observations through high-energy neutrino detectors like IceCube, as well as through dark matter direct detection efforts focused on targeted black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00741v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/02/035</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP02(2025)035</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Chen, Xiao Xue, Vitor Cardoso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the equation of state in neutron-star cores via the long-ringdown signal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03246v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multimessenger signals from binary neutron star (BNS) mergers are promising tools to infer the largely unknown properties of nuclear matter at densities that are presently inaccessible to laboratory experiments. The gravitational waves (GWs) emitted by BNS merger remnants, in particular, have the potential of setting tight constraints on the neutron-star equation of state (EOS) that would complement those coming from the late inspiral, direct mass-radius measurements, or ab-initio dense-matter calculations. To explore this possibility, we perform a representative series of general-relativistic simulations of BNS systems with EOSs carefully constructed so as to cover comprehensively the high-density regime of the EOS space. From these simulations, we identify a novel and tight correlation between the ratio of the energy and angular-momentum losses in the late-time portion of the post-merger signal, i.e., the ``long ringdown'', and the properties of the EOS at the highest pressures and densities in neutron-star cores. When applying this correlation to post-merger GW signals, we find a significant reduction of the EOS uncertainty at densities several times the nuclear saturation density, where no direct constraints are currently available. Hence, the long ringdown has the potential of providing new and stringent constraints on the state of matter in neutron stars in general and, in particular, in their cores.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03246v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-56500-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Commun. 16 (2025) 1, 1320</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ecker, Tyler Gorda, Aleksi Kurkela, Luciano Rezzolla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed universes, factorization, and ensemble averaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13047v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study closed universes in holographic theories of quantum gravity. We argue that within any fixed theory, factorization implies there is one unique closed universe state. The wave function of any state that can be prepared by the path integral is proportional to the Hartle-Hawking wave function. This unique wave function depends on the properties of the underlying holographic theory such as the energy spectrum. We show these properties explicitly in JT gravity, which is known to be dual to an ensemble of random Hamiltonians. For each member of the ensemble, the corresponding wave function is erratic as a result of the spectrum being chaotic. After ensemble averaging, we obtain smooth semi-classical wave functions as well as different closed universe states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13047v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mykhaylo Usatyuk, Ying Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting thermodynamic topology of Hawking-Page and Davies type phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02526v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a common vector field to study the thermodynamic topology of the Davies type and Hawking-Page phase transitions. Existing literature has shown that studying these two types of phase transitions typically requires defining two separate vector fields . In our approach, we adopt Duan's $\phi$-mapping topological current theory to define a novel vector field, denoted as $\phi$, whose critical points exactly correspond to the Davies point and the Hawking-Page phase transition point. More importantly, we can differentiate between these two points by their topological charge. While, the topological charge for the critical point corresponding to the Davies-type phase transition is found to be $-1$, the same for the Hawking-Page phase transition point, it is $+1$. Although our analysis is applicable to all black hole systems where both types of phase transitions are found, we illustrate it using three simple systems as examples: the Schwarzschild AdS black hole, the Reissner-Nordstr\"om AdS black hole in the grand canonical ensemble, and finally the Kerr AdS black holes in the grand canonical ensemble. It is wellknown that these black holes exhibit both Davies and Hawking-Page phase transitions. With our proposed vector $\phi$, the critical points obtained for these three systems exactly match the Davies-type and Hawking-Page phase transition points, and the associated topological charges are found to be $-1$ for the Davies point and $+1$ for the Hawking-Page phase transition point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02526v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jheap.2024.11.013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Astrophysics,45,2025,87-95</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bidyut Hazarika, Naba Jyoti Gogoi, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of restricted phase space thermodynamics in Kerr-Sen-Ads black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02328v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the thermodynamic topology of the Kerr-Sen-Ads black hole in restricted phase space. In the restricted phase space, a new parameter, central charge $C$, and its conjugate parameter $\mu$ are introduced, omitting the well-known $PdV$ term in the first law of black hole thermodynamics. We study the local and global topology of the black hole by considering the black hole solution as topological defects in the free energy landscape. We compute the winding number and the total topological number at the thermodynamic defects. For our analysis, we have considered five ensembles of Kerr-Sen-Ads black holes in restricted phase space: fixed $(Q, J, C)$, fixed $(\phi, J, C)$, fixed $(Q,\Omega, C)$, fixed $(Q, J, \mu)$, and fixed $(\phi,\Omega, C)$, where $Q$ is the electric charge, $J$ is the angular momentum, $C$ is the central charge, $\phi$ is the electric potential conjugate to charge, $\Omega$ is the angular frequency conjugate to $J$, and finally, $\mu$ is the chemical potential. In the fixed $(Q, J, C)$, fixed $(\phi, J, C)$, and fixed $(Q, J, \mu)$ ensembles, we find a topological charge of $+1$. In the fixed $(Q,\Omega, C)$ and fixed $(\phi, \Omega, C)$ ensembles, depending on the values of the thermodynamic parameters, we find topological charges of $-1$, $0$, and $+1$. Interestingly, in ensembles where we find the topological charge to be $0$, we observe both Hawking-Page and Davies type phase transitions. We show that both types of these phase transitions can be studied using a common vector field, and the topological charges associated with Davies type and Hawking-Page phase transitions are $-1$ and $+1$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02328v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.116837</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Physics B,1012,116837(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bidyut Hazarika, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weyl double copy in type D spacetime in four and five dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04774v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a second realization of the Weyl double copy (WDC) in four-dimensional algebraic type D spacetime. We show that any type D vacuum solution admits an algebraically general Maxwell scalar on the curved background that squares to give the Weyl scalar. The WDC relation defines a scalar field that satisfies the Klein-Gordon equation sourced by the Weyl scalar on the curved background. We then extend the type D WDC to five dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04774v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weicheng Zhao, Pu-Jian Mao, Jun-Bao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The origin channels of hierarchical binary black hole mergers in the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA O1, O2, and O3 runs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09195v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We infer the origin channels of hierarchical mergers observed in the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) O1, O2, and O3 runs using a hierarchical Bayesian analysis under a parametric population model. By assuming the active galactic nucleus (AGN) disk and nuclear star cluster (NSC) channels, we find that NSCs likely dominate the hierarchical merger rate in the Universe, corresponding to a fraction of $f_{\rm NSC}=0.87_{-0.29}^{+0.10}$ at 90\% credible intervals in our fiducial model; AGN disks may contribute up to nearly half of hierarchical mergers detectable with LVK, specifically $f_{\rm det,AGN}=0.34_{-0.26}^{+0.38}$. We investigate the impact of the escape speed, along with other population parameters on the branching fraction, suggesting that the mass, mass ratio, and spin of the sources play significant roles in population analysis. We show that hierarchical mergers constitute at least $\sim$$10\%$ of the gravitational wave events detected by LVK during the O1-O3 runs. Furthermore, we demonstrate that it is challenging to effectively infer detailed information about the host environment based solely on the distribution of black hole merger parameters if multiple formation channels are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09195v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Peng Li, Xi-Long Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yang-Mills Field in the $\kappa$-space-time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11501v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct Yang-Mills theory in the $\kappa$-space-time. We derive Yang-Mills equations in the $\kappa$-deformed space-time, valid up to first order in the deformation parameter $a$, using the generalisation of Feynman's approach. We first derive the $\kappa$-deformed Wong's equation and using it, in the Jacobi identity involving velocities and coordinates of $\kappa$-deformed space-time, we derive the $\kappa$-deformed homogeneous Yang-Mills equations. We then construct the Lagrangian for Yang-Mills theory in $\kappa$-deformed space-time and show that it is invariant under SU(N) transformation. We also derive the expression for the force experienced by an isospin-carrying particle in the presence of Yang-Mills field in the $\kappa$-space-time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11501v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhagya. R, E. Harikumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fuzzball Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09495v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe the puzzles that arise in the quantum theory of black holes, and explain how they are resolved in string theory. We review how the Bekenstein entropy is obtained through the count of brane bound states. We describe the fuzzball construction of black hole microstates. These states have no horizon and radiate from their surface like a normal body, so there is no information puzzle. We explain how the semiclassical approximation is violated in gravitational collapse even though curvatures are low at the classical horizon. This violation happens because the collapse leads to a stretching of space that is {\it fast}: light does not have time to travel across the collapsing region to establish the `vecro' correlations needed in the quantum gravitational vacuum. These vecro correlations arise from the existence of virtual fuzzball fluctuations in the gravitational vacuum, and are significant because of the large degeneracy of fuzzball states implied by the Bekenstein entropy. It is plausible that similar effects of fast expansion may be responsible for effects like dark energy and the Early Dark Energy postulated to explain the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09495v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samir D. Mathur, Madhur Mehta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
