<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 04:02:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Note on a Theoretical Justification for Approximations of Arithmetic Forwards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This brief note explores the theoretical justification for some approximations of arithmetic forwards ($F_a$) with weighted averages of overnight (ON) forwards ($F_k$). The central equation presented in this analysis is: \begin{equation*} F_a(0;T_s,T_e)=\frac{1}{\tau(T_s,T_e)}\sum_{k=1}^K \tau_k \mathcal{A}_k F_k\,, \end{equation*} with $\mathcal{A}_k$ being explicit model-dependent quantities that, under certain market scenarios, are close to one. We will present computationally cheaper methods that approximate $F_a$, i.e., we will define some $\{\tilde{\mathcal{A}}_k\}_{k=1}^K$ such that \begin{equation*} F_a(0;T_s,T_e)\approx \frac{1}{\tau(T_s,T_e)}\sum_{k=1}^K \tilde{\mathcal{A}}_k \tau_k F_k\,. \end{equation*} We also demonstrate that one of these forms can be closely aligned with an approximation suggested by Katsumi Takada in his work on the valuation of arithmetic averages of Fed Funds rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09488v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Alvaro Romaniega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation of Robust Option Prices via Structured Multi-Marginal Martingale Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce an efficient computational framework for solving a class of multi-marginal martingale optimal transport problems, which includes many robust pricing problems of large financial interest. Such problems are typically computationally challenging due to the martingale constraint, however, by extending the state space we can identify them with problems that exhibit a certain sequential martingale structure. Our method exploits such structures in combination with entropic regularisation, enabling fast computation of optimal solutions and allowing us to solve problems with a large number of marginals. We demonstrate the method by using it for computing robust price bounds for different options, such as lookback options and Asian options.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09959v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linn Engstr\"om, Sigrid K\"allblad, Johan Karlsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal randomised signatures for generative time series modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10214v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Randomised signature has been proposed as a flexible and easily implementable alternative to the well-established path signature. In this article, we employ randomised signature to introduce a generative model for financial time series data in the spirit of reservoir computing. Specifically, we propose a novel Wasserstein-type distance based on discrete-time randomised signatures. This metric on the space of probability measures captures the distance between (conditional) distributions. Its use is justified by our novel universal approximation results for randomised signatures on the space of continuous functions taking the underlying path as an input. We then use our metric as the loss function in a non-adversarial generator model for synthetic time series data based on a reservoir neural stochastic differential equation. We compare the results of our model to benchmarks from the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10214v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Biagini, Lukas Gonon, Niklas Walter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Options Pricing under Bayesian MS-VAR Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.05998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.05998v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we have studied option pricing methods that are based on a Bayesian Markov-Switching Vector Autoregressive (MS--BVAR) process using a risk-neutral valuation approach. A BVAR process, which is a special case of the Bayesian MS--VAR process is widely used to model interdependencies of economic variables and forecast economic variables. Here we assumed that a regime-switching process is generated by a homogeneous Markov process and a residual process follows a conditional heteroscedastic model. With a direct calculation and change of probability measure, for some frequently used options, we derived pricing formulas. An advantage of our model is it depends on economic variables and is easy to use compared to previous option pricing papers, which depend on regime-switching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.05998v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Battulga Gankhuu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equity--Linked Life Insurances on Maximum of Several Assets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.04038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.04038v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Economic variables play important roles in any economic model, and sudden and dramatic changes exist in the financial market and economy. For this reason, to price and hedge equity-linked life insurance products, including segregated funds and unit-linked life insurance products on maximum price of several assets, this paper introduces Bayesian Markov-Switching Vector Autoregressive (MS-VAR) process. By assuming that a regime-switching process is generated by a homogeneous Markov process and a residual process follows a heteroscedastic model, we obtain joint distribution of endogenous variables and insured's future lifetime random variable under risk-neutral probability probability measure. Using the distribution function, we obtain net single premiums and hedging formulas of the equity-linked life insurance products. An advantage of our model is it depends on economic variables and is not complicated as compared to previous papers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.04038v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Battulga Gankhuu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal investment and consumption under logarithmic utility and uncertainty model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05367v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a robust utility maximization problem in the case of an incomplete market and logarithmic utility with general stochastic constraints, not necessarily convex. Our problem is equivalent to maximizing of nonlinear expected logarithmic utility. We characterize the optimal solution using quadratic BSDE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05367v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wahid Faidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
