<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 05:05:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Design of Automated Market Makers on Decentralized Exchanges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13291v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Automated market makers are a popular mechanism used on decentralized exchange, through which users trade assets with each other directly and automatically through a liquidity pool and a fixed pricing function. The liquidity provider contributes to the liquidity pool by supplying assets to the pool, and in return, they earn trading fees from investors who trade in the pool. We propose a model of optimal liquidity provision in which a risk-averse liquidity provider decides the amount of wealth she would invest in the decentralized market to provide liquidity in a two-asset pool, trade in a centralized market, and consume in multiple periods. We derive the liquidity provider's optimal strategy and the optimal design of the automated market maker that maximizes the liquidity provider's utility. We find that the optimal unit trading fee increases in the volatility of the fundamental exchange rate of the two assets. We also find that the optimal pricing function is chosen to make the asset allocation in the liquidity pool efficient for the liquidity provider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13291v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue Dong He, Chen Yang, Yutian Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomization of Short-Rate Models, Analytic Pricing and Flexibility in Controlling Implied Volatilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05014v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We focus on extending existing short-rate models, enabling control of the generated implied volatility while preserving analyticity. We achieve this goal by applying the Randomized Affine Diffusion (RAnD) method to the class of short-rate processes under the Heath-Jarrow-Morton framework. Under arbitrage-free conditions, the model parameters can be exogenously stochastic, thus facilitating additional degrees of freedom that enhance the calibration procedure. We show that with the randomized short-rate models, the shapes of implied volatility can be controlled and significantly improve the quality of the model calibration, even for standard 1D variants. In particular, we illustrate that randomization applied to the Hull-White model leads to dynamics of the local volatility type, with the prices for standard volatility-sensitive derivatives explicitly available. The randomized Hull-White (rHW) model offers an almost perfect calibration fit to the swaption implied volatilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05014v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lech A. Grzelak</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
