<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 04:04:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Max-stability under first-order stochastic dominance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Max-stability is the property that taking a maximum between two inputs results in a maximum between two outputs. We investigate max-stability with respect to first-order stochastic dominance, the most fundamental notion of stochastic dominance in decision theory. Under two additional standard axioms of monotonicity and lower semicontinuity, we establish a representation theorem for functionals satisfying max-stability, which turns out to be represented by the supremum of a bivariate function. Our characterized functionals encompass special classes of functionals in the literature of risk measures, such as benchmark-loss Value at Risk (VaR) and $\Lambda$-quantile.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13138v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Chambers, Alan Miller, Ruodu Wang, Qinyu Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractal wavelet dynamic mode decomposition modeling for marketing time series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Marketing is the way we ensure our sales are the best in the market, our prices the most accessible, and our clients satisfied, thus ensuring our brand has the widest distribution. This requires sophisticated and advanced understanding of the whole related network. Indeed, marketing data may exist in different forms such as qualitative and quantitative data. However, in the literature, it is easily noted that large bibliographies may be collected about qualitative studies, while only a few studies adopt a quantitative point of view. This is a major drawback that results in marketing science still focusing on design, although the market is strongly dependent on quantities such as money and time. Indeed, marketing data may form time series such as brand sales in specified periods, brand-related prices over specified periods, market shares, etc. The purpose of the present work is to investigate some marketing models based on time series for various brands. This paper aims to combine the dynamic mode decomposition and wavelet decomposition to study marketing series due to both prices, and volume sales in order to explore the effect of the time scale on the persistence of brand sales in the market and on the forecasting of such persistence, according to the characteristics of the brand and the related market competition or competitors. Our study is based on a sample of Saudi brands during the period 22 November 2017 to 30 December 2021.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13361v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Elshazli A. Zidan, Anouar Ben Mabrouk, Nidhal Ben Abdallah, Tawfeeq M. Alanazi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Stochastic Fubini Theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The classic stochastic Fubini theorem says that if one stochastically integrates with respect to a semimartingale $S$ an $\eta(dz)$-mixture of $z$-parametrized integrands $\psi^z$, the result is just the $\eta(dz)$-mixture of the individual $z$-parametrized stochastic integrals $\int\psi^z{d}S.$ But if one wants to use such a result for the study of Volterra semimartingales of the form $ X_t =\int_0^t \Psi_{t,s}dS_s, t \geq0,$ the classic assumption that one has a fixed measure $\eta$ is too restrictive; the mixture over the integrands needs to be taken instead with respect to a stochastic kernel on the parameter space. To handle that situation and prove a corresponding new stochastic Fubini theorem, we introduce a new notion of measure-valued stochastic integration with respect to a general multidimensional semimartingale. As an application, we show how this allows to handle a class of quite general stochastic Volterra semimartingales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13791v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tahir Choulli, Martin Schweizer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium with Heterogeneous Information Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01272v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a continuous time economy where throughout time, insiders receive private signals regarding the risky assets' terminal payoff. We prove existence of a partial communication equilibrium where, at each private signal time, the public receives a signal of the same form as the associated insider, but of lower quality. This causes a jump in both the public information flow and equilibrium asset price. The resultant markets, while complete between each jump time, are incomplete over each jump. After establishing equilibrium for a finite number of private signal times, we consider the limit as the private signals become more and more frequent. Under appropriate scaling we prove convergence of the public filtration to the natural filtration generated by both the fundamental factor process $X$ and a continuous time process $J$ taking the form $J_t = X_1 + Y_t$ where $X_1$ is the terminal payoff and $Y$ an independent Gaussian process. This coincides with the filtration considered in 'Additional Utility of Insiders with Imperfect Dynamical Information' (Corcuera, et al. Finance &amp; Stochastics 2004). However, while therein the filtration was exogenously assumed to be that of an insider who observes a private signal flow, here it arises endogenously as the public filtration when there are a large number of insiders receiving signals throughout time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01272v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott Robertson</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
