<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 02:44:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Empirical Implementation of the Shadow Riskless Rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of asset pricing in a market where there is no risky asset. Previous work developed a theoretical model for a shadow riskless rate (SRR) for such a market in terms of the drift component of the state-price deflator for that asset universe. Assuming asset prices are modeled by correlated geometric Brownian motion, in this work we develop a computational approach to estimate the SRR from empirical datasets. The approach employs: principal component analysis to model the effects of the individual Brownian motions; singular value decomposition to capture the abrupt changes in condition number of the linear system whose solution provides the SRR values; and a regularization to control the rate of change of the condition number. Among other uses (e.g., for option pricing, developing a term structure of interest rate), the SRR can be employed as an investment discriminator between asset classes. We apply the computational procedure to markets consisting of groups of stocks, varying asset type and number. The theoretical and computational analysis provides not only the drift, but also the total volatility of the state-price deflator. We investigate the time trajectory of these two descriptive components of the state-price deflator for the empirical datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07421v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Lauria, JiHo Park, Yuan Hu, W. Brent Lindquist, Svetlozar T. Rachev, Frank J. Fabozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Dynamic Pricing Across Multiple Pricing Groups in Real Estate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article presents a mathematical model of dynamic pricing for real estate (RE) that incorporates multiple pricing groups, thereby expanding the capabilities of existing models. The developed model solves the problem of maximizing aggregate cumulative revenue at the end of the sales period while meeting the revenue and sales goals. A method is proposed for distributing aggregate cumulative revenue goals across different RE pricing groups. The model is further modified to account for the time value of money and the real estate value increase as construction progresses. The algorithm for constructing a pricing policy for multiple pricing groups is described, and numerical simulations are performed to demonstrate how the algorithm operates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07732v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lev Razumovskiy, Mariya Gerasimova, Nikolay Karenin, Mikhail Safro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean field equilibrium asset pricing model with habit formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02155v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents an asset pricing model in an incomplete market involving a large number of heterogeneous agents based on the mean field game theory. In the model, we incorporate habit formation in consumption preferences, which has been widely used to explain various phenomena in financial economics. In order to characterize the market-clearing equilibrium, we derive a quadratic-growth mean field backward stochastic differential equation (BSDE) and study its well-posedness and asymptotic behavior in the large population limit. Additionally, we introduce an exponential quadratic Gaussian reformulation of the asset pricing model, in which the solution is obtained in a semi-analytic form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02155v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaaki Fujii, Masashi Sekine</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
