<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 05:00:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed-Income Pricing and the Replication of Liabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14662v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a model-free framework for static fixed-income pricing and the replication of liability cash flows. We show that the absence of static arbitrage across a universe of fixed-income instruments is equivalent to the existence of a strictly positive discount curve that reproduces all observed market prices. We then study the replication and super-replication of liabilities and establish conditions ensuring the existence of least-cost super-replicating portfolios, including a rigorous interpretation of swap--repo replication within this static framework. The results provide a unified foundation for discount-curve construction and liability-driven investment, with direct relevance for economic capital assessment and regulatory practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14662v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damir Filipovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-run survival in limited stock market participation models with power utilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14680v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the limited participation model in Basak and Cuoco (1998) to allow for traders with different time-preference coefficients but identical constant relative risk-aversion coefficients. Our main result gives parameter restrictions which ensure the existence of a Radner equilibrium. As an application, we give further parameter restrictions which ensure all traders survive in the long run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14680v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heeyoung Kwon, Kasper Larsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic volatility approximation for a tick-by-tick price model with mean-field interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a tick-by-tick model of price formation, in which buy and sell orders are modeled as self-exciting point processes (Hawkes process), similar to the one in [Hoffmann, Bacry, Delattre, Muzy, Modelling microstructure noise with mutually exciting point processes, Quantitative Finance, 2013] and [El Euch, Fukasawa, Rosenbaum, The microstructural foundations of leverage effect and rough volatility, Finance and Stochastics, 2018]. We adopt an agent based approach by studying the aggregation of a large number of these point processes, mutually interacting in a mean-field sense.
  The financial interpretation is that of an asset on which several labeled agents place buy and sell orders following these point processes, influencing the price. The mean-field interaction introduces positive correlations between order volumes coming from different agents that reflect features of real markets such as herd behavior and contagion. When the large scale limit of the aggregated asset price is computed, if parameters are set to a critical value, a singular phenomenon occurs: the aggregated model converges to a stochastic volatility model with leverage effect and faster-than-linear mean reversion of the volatility process.
  The faster-than-linear mean reversion of the volatility process is supported by econometric evidence, and we have linked it in [Dai Pra, Pigato, Multi-scaling of moments in stochastic volatility models, Stochastic Processes and their Applications, 2015] to the observed multifractal behavior of assets prices and market indices. This seems connected to the Statistical Physics perspective that expects anomalous scaling properties to arise in the critical regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03445v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Dai Pra, Paolo Pigato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fair Volatility: A Framework for Reconceptualizing Financial Risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18837v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Volatility is the canonical measure of financial risk, a role largely inherited from Modern Portfolio Theory. Yet, its universality rests on restrictive efficiency assumptions that render volatility, at best, an incomplete proxy for true risk. This paper identifies three fundamental inconsistencies: (i) volatility is path-independent and blind to temporal dependence and non-stationarity; (ii) its relevance collapses in derivative-intensive strategies, where volatility often represents opportunity rather than risk; and (iii) it lacks an absolute benchmark, providing no guidance on what level of volatility is economically ``fair'' in efficient markets. To address these limitations, we propose a new paradigm that reconceptualizes risk in terms of predictability rather than variability. Building on a general class of stochastic processes, we derive an analytical link between volatility and the Hurst-Holder exponent within the Multifractional Process with Random Exponent (MPRE) framework. This relationship yields a formal definition of ``fair volatility'', namely the volatility implied under market efficiency, where prices follow semi-martingale dynamics. Extensive empirical analysis on global equity indices supports this framework, showing that deviations from fair volatility provide a tractable measure of market inefficiency, distinguishing between momentum-driven and mean-reverting regimes. Our results advance both the theoretical foundations and empirical assessment of financial risk, offering a definition of volatility that is efficiency-consistent and economically interpretable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18837v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Bianchi, Daniele Angelini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
