<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 04:05:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Analysis of the Model-Free Valuation Approach: Hedging Gaps, Conservatism, and Trading Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16595v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study the quality of model-free valuation approaches for financial derivatives by systematically evaluating the difference between model-free super-hedging strategies and the realized payoff of financial derivatives using historical option prices from several constituents of the S&amp;P 500 between 2018 and 2022.
  Our study allows in particular to describe the realized gap between payoff and model-free hedging strategy empirically so that we can quantify to which degree model-free approaches are overly conservative. Our results imply that the model-free hedging approach is only marginally more conservative than industry-standard models such as the Heston-model while being model-free at the same time.
  This finding, its statistical description and the model-independence of the hedging approach enable us to construct an explicit trading strategy which, as we demonstrate, can be profitably applied in financial markets, and additionally possesses the desirable feature with an explicit control of its downside risk due to its model-free construction preventing losses pathwise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16595v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixing Chen, Yihan Qi, Shanlan Que, Julian Sester, Xiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning for Jump-Diffusions, with Financial Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16449v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study continuous-time reinforcement learning (RL) for stochastic control in which system dynamics are governed by jump-diffusion processes. We formulate an entropy-regularized exploratory control problem with stochastic policies to capture the exploration--exploitation balance essential for RL. Unlike the pure diffusion case initially studied by Wang et al. (2020), the derivation of the exploratory dynamics under jump-diffusions calls for a careful formulation of the jump part. Through a theoretical analysis, we find that one can simply use the same policy evaluation and $q$-learning algorithms in Jia and Zhou (2022a, 2023), originally developed for controlled diffusions, without needing to check a priori whether the underlying data come from a pure diffusion or a jump-diffusion. However, we show that the presence of jumps ought to affect parameterizations of actors and critics in general. We investigate as an application the mean--variance portfolio selection problem with stock price modelled as a jump-diffusion, and show that both RL algorithms and parameterizations are invariant with respect to jumps. Finally, we present a detailed study on applying the general theory to option hedging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16449v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuefeng Gao, Lingfei Li, Xun Yu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit local volatility formula for Cheyette-type interest rate models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23876v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the approximation of the local volatility function in the Cheyette interest rate model. Its main contribution is an explicit analytical formula for approximating local volatility, derived by extending the classical Dupire framework to interest rate models. In particular, an implicit Dupire-like expression for local volatility is first derived for options written on the short rate. This expression is then approximated using a combination of perturbation methods and probabilistic techniques, resulting in a formula expressed in terms of time and strike derivatives of the Bachelier implied variance. The final formula naturally extends to multi-factor Cheyette models and provides a practical tool for model calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23876v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Gairat, Vyacheslav Gorovoy, Vadim Shcherbakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
