<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 01:40:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Asian Basket Spread Options: A New Approximation Based on Stochastic Taylor Expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16011v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present closed analytical approximations for the pricing of Asian basket spread options under the Black-Scholes model. The formulae are obtained by using a stochastic Taylor expansion around a log-normal proxy model and are found to be highly accurate for Asian and spread options in practice. Unlike other approaches, they do not require any numerical integration or root solving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16011v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabien Le Floc'h</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pitman's Theorem, Black-Scholes Equation, and Derivative Pricing for Fundraisers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13956v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a financial market model that comprises a savings account and a stock. The stock price process is modeled as a one-dimensional diffusion, in which two types of agents exist: an ordinary investor and a fundraiser who buys or sells stocks as funding activities. Although the investor information is the natural filtration of the diffusion, the fundraiser possesses additional information regarding the funding, as well as additional cash flows as a result of the funding. This concept is modeled using Pitman's theorem for the three-dimensional Bessel process. Two contributions are presented: First, the prices of European options for the fundraiser are derived. Second, a numerical scheme for call option prices in a market with a bubble is proposed, where multiple solutions exist for the Black--Scholes equation and the derivative prices are characterized as the smallest nonnegative supersolution. More precisely, the call option price in such a market is approximated from below by the prices for the fundraiser. This scheme overcomes the difficulty that stems from the discrepancy that the payoff shows linear growth, whereas the price function shows strictly sublinear growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13956v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukihiro Tsuzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary conditions at infinity for Black-Scholes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05549v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a numerical procedure for computing the prices of European options, in which the underlying asset price is a Markovian strict local martingale. If the underlying process is a strict local martingale and the payoff is of linear growth, multiple solutions exist for the corresponding Black-Scholes equations. When numerical schemes such as finite difference methods are applied, a boundary condition at infinity must be specified, which determines a solution among the candidates. The minimal solution, which is considered as the derivative price, is obtained by our boundary condition. The stability of our procedure is supported by the fact that our numerical solution satisfies a discrete maximum principle. In addition, its accuracy is demonstrated through numerical experiments in comparison with the methods proposed in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05549v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukihiro Tsuzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quadratic Local Variance Gamma Model: an arbitrage-free interpolation of class C3 for option prices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13791v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper generalizes the local variance gamma model of Carr and Nadtochiy, to a piecewise quadratic local variance function. The formulation encompasses the piecewise linear Bachelier and piecewise linear Black local variance gamma models. The quadratic local variance function results in an arbitrage-free interpolation of class C3. The increased smoothness over the piecewise-constant and piecewise-linear representation allows to reduce the number of knots when interpolating raw market quotes, thus providing an interesting alternative to regularization while reducing the computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13791v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabien Le Floc'h</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
