<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 04:00:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Trading under Instantaneous and Persistent Price Impact, Predictable Returns and Multiscale Stochastic Volatility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a dynamic portfolio optimization problem that incorporates predictable returns, instantaneous transaction costs, price impact, and stochastic volatility, extending the classical results of Garleanu and Pedersen (2013), which assume constant volatility. Constructing the optimal portfolio strategy in this general setting is challenging due to the nonlinear nature of the resulting Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equations. To address this, we propose a multi-scale volatility expansion that captures stochastic volatility dynamics across different time scales. Specifically, the analysis involves a singular perturbation for the fast mean-reverting volatility factor and a regular perturbation for the slow-moving factor. We also introduce an approximation for small price impact and demonstrate its numerical accuracy. We formally derive asymptotic approximations up to second order and use Monte Carlo simulations to show how incorporating these corrections improves the Profit and Loss (PnL) of the resulting portfolio strategy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17162v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Chan, Ronnie Sircar, Iosif Zimbidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Deep Gradient Flow Method for pricing American options</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17606v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this research, we explore neural network-based methods for pricing multidimensional American put options under the BlackScholes and Heston model, extending up to five dimensions. We focus on two approaches: the Time Deep Gradient Flow (TDGF) method and the Deep Galerkin Method (DGM). We extend the TDGF method to handle the free-boundary partial differential equation inherent in American options. We carefully design the sampling strategy during training to enhance performance. Both TDGF and DGM achieve high accuracy while outperforming conventional Monte Carlo methods in terms of computational speed. In particular, TDGF tends to be faster during training than DGM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17606v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasper Rou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Market Making and Arbitrage Profits in the Presence of Fees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.14604v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the impact of trading fees on the profits of arbitrageurs trading against an automated market maker (AMM) or, equivalently, on the adverse selection incurred by liquidity providers (LPs) due to arbitrage. We extend the model of Milionis et al. [2022] for a general class of two asset AMMs to introduce both fees and discrete Poisson block generation times. In our setting, we are able to compute the expected instantaneous rate of arbitrage profit in closed form. When the fees are low, in the fast block asymptotic regime, the impact of fees takes a particularly simple form: fees simply scale down arbitrage profits by the fraction of blocks which present profitable trading opportunities to arbitrageurs. This fraction decreases with an increasing block rate, hence our model yields an important practical insight: faster blockchains will result in reduced LP losses. Further introducing gas fees (fixed costs) in our model, we show that, in the fast block asymptotic regime, lower gas fees lead to smaller losses for LPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.14604v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Milionis, Ciamac C. Moallemi, Tim Roughgarden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical CEV Option Pricing Model: an Analytical Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18154v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to obtain closed form solutions for the semiclassical (or WKB) approximation of the heat kernel propagator of the diffusion equation defined by the constant elasticity variance (CEV) option pricing model. One of the key points is that our calculations are based on the Van Vleck-Morette determinant instead of the Van Vleck determinant used by other authors. In fact, we compute this determinant in two different ways: by means of the solution of the classical Hamiltonian equations, and by solving the variational equations. Furthermore, the calculation reveals an exponential factor in the prefactor of the kernel not considered in previous works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18154v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. Capit\'an, Jose Lope-Alba, Juan J. Morales-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Factor Models: Generating High-Dimensional Returns with Factor Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06566v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Financial scenario simulation is essential for risk management and portfolio optimization, yet it remains challenging especially in high-dimensional and small data settings common in finance. We propose a diffusion factor model that integrates latent factor structure into generative diffusion processes, bridging econometrics with modern generative AI to address the challenges of the curse of dimensionality and data scarcity in financial simulation. By exploiting the low-dimensional factor structure inherent in asset returns, we decompose the score function--a key component in diffusion models--using time-varying orthogonal projections, and this decomposition is incorporated into the design of neural network architectures. We derive rigorous statistical guarantees, establishing nonasymptotic error bounds for both score estimation at O(d^{5/2} n^{-2/(k+5)}) and generated distribution at O(d^{5/4} n^{-1/2(k+5)}), primarily driven by the intrinsic factor dimension k rather than the number of assets d, surpassing the dimension-dependent limits in the classical nonparametric statistics literature and making the framework viable for markets with thousands of assets. Numerical studies confirm superior performance in latent subspace recovery under small data regimes. Empirical analysis demonstrates the economic significance of our framework in constructing mean-variance optimal portfolios and factor portfolios. This work presents the first theoretical integration of factor structure with diffusion models, offering a principled approach for high-dimensional financial simulation with limited data. Our code is available at https://github.com/xymmmm00/diffusion_factor_model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06566v4</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minshuo Chen, Renyuan Xu, Yumin Xu, Ruixun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
