<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.MF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF</link>
    <description>q-fin.MF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.MF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:01:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension Reduction in Martingale Optimal Transport: Geometry and Robust Option Pricing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.04947v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of robust option pricing within the framework of Vectorial Martingale Optimal Transport (VMOT). We investigate the geometry of VMOT solutions for $N$-period market models and demonstrate that, when the number of underlying assets is $d=2$ and the payoff is sub- or supermodular, the extremal model reduces to a single-factor structure in the first period. This structural result allows for a significant dimension reduction, transforming the problem into a more tractable format. We prove that this reduction is specific to the two-asset case and provide counterexamples showing it generally fails for $d \geq 3$. Finally, we exploit this monotonicity to develop a reduced-dimension Sinkhorn algorithm. Numerical experiments demonstrate that this structure-preserving approach reduces computational time by approximately 99\% compared to standard methods while improving accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.04947v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Zoen-Git Hiew, Tongseok Lim, Brendan Pass, Marcelo Cruz de Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-Dimensional LQ Mean Field Games with Common Noise: Small and Arbitrary Finite Time Horizons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13493v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend the results of (Liu and Firoozi, 2025), which develops the theory of linear-quadratic (LQ) mean field games (MFGs) in Hilbert spaces, by incorporating a common noise. This common noise is modeled as an infinite-dimensional Wiener process affecting the dynamics of all agents. In the presence of common noise, the mean-field consistency condition is characterized by a system of coupled forward-backward stochastic evolution equations (FBSEEs) in Hilbert spaces, whereas, in its absence it is represented by coupled forward-backward deterministic evolution equations. We establish the existence and uniqueness of solutions to the coupled linear FBSEEs associated with the LQ MFG framework for small time horizons and prove the $\epsilon$-Nash property of the resulting equilibrium strategy. Furthermore, we establish the well-posedness of these coupled linear FBSEEs for arbitrary finite time horizons. Beyond the specific context of MFGs, our analysis also yields a broader contribution by providing, to the best of our knowledge, the first well-posedness result for a class of infinite-dimensional linear FBSEEs, for which only mild solutions exist, over arbitrary finite time horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13493v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanchao Liu, Dena Firoozi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
