<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 04:01:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison Theorems for the Mixing Times of Systematic and Random Scan Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A popular method for sampling from high-dimensional distributions is the Gibbs sampler, which iteratively resamples sites from the conditional distribution of the desired measure given the values of the other coordinates. But to what extent does the order of site updates matter in the mixing time? Two natural choices are (i) standard, or random scan, Glauber dynamics where the updated variable is chosen uniformly at random, and (ii) the systematic scan dynamics where variables are updated in a fixed, cyclic order. We first show that for systems of dimension $n$, one round of the systematic scan dynamics has spectral gap at most a factor of order $n$ worse than the corresponding spectral gap of a single step of Glauber dynamics, tightening existing bounds in the literature by He, et al. [NeurIPS '16] and Chlebicka, {\L}atuszy\'nski, and Miasodejow [Ann. Appl. Probab. '24]. This result is sharp even for simple spin systems by an example of Roberts and Rosenthal [Int. J. Statist. Prob. '15]. We complement this with a converse statement: if all, or even just one scan order rapidly mixes, the Glauber dynamics has a polynomially related mixing time, resolving a question of Chlebicka, {\L}atuszy\'nski, and Miasodejow. Our arguments are simple and only use elementary linear algebra and probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11136v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Gaitonde, Elchanan Mossel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting particle systems on sparse $W$-random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11240v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a general interacting particle system with interactions on a random graph, and study the large population limit of this system. When the sequence of underlying graphs converges to a graphon, we show convergence of the interacting particle system to a so called graphon stochastic differential equation. This is a system of uncountable many SDEs of McKean-Vlasov type driven by a continuum of Brownian motions. We make sense of this equation in a way that retains joint measurability and essentially pairwise independence of the driving Brownian motions of the system by using the framework of Fubini extension. The convergence results are general enough to cover nonlinear interactions, as well as various examples of sparse graphs. A crucial idea is to work with unbounded graphons and use the $L^p$ theory of sparse graph convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11240v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carla Crucianelli, Ludovic Tangpi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inequalities for independent random vectors under sublinear expectations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, by using the representation theorem for sublinear expectations, we give a simple proof to obtain two inequalities about the sample mean for independent random vectors under sublinear expectations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11349v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojuan Li, Mingshang Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtering coupled Wright-Fisher diffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coupled Wright-Fisher diffusions have been recently introduced to model the temporal evolution of finitely-many allele frequencies at several loci. These are vectors of multidimensional diffusions whose dynamics are weakly coupled among loci through interaction coefficients, which make the reproductive rates for each allele depend on its frequencies at several loci. Here we consider the problem of filtering a coupled Wright-Fisher diffusion with parent-independent mutation, when this is seen as an unobserved signal in a hidden Markov model. We assume individuals are sampled multinomially at discrete times from the underlying population, whose type configuration at the loci is described by the diffusion states, and adapt recently introduced duality methods to derive the filtering and smoothing distributions. These respectively provide the conditional distribution of the diffusion states given past data, and that conditional on the entire dataset, and are key to be able to perform parameter inference on models of this type. We show that for this model these distributions are countable mixtures of tilted products of Dirichlet kernels, and describe their mixing weights and how these can be updated sequentially. The evaluation of the weights involves the transition probabilities of the dual process, which are not available in closed form. We lay out pseudo codes for the implementation of the algorithms, discuss how to handle the unavailable quantities, and briefly illustrate the procedure with synthetic data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11429v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Boetti, Matteo Ruggiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stationary distributions of state-dependent diffusions reflected at one and two sides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider a one-dimensional diffusion process which has state-dependent drift and deviation and is reflected at the origin, which is called a one-side reflected diffusion or simply reflected diffusion. We are particularly interested in the case that its drift and deviation are discontinuous. The aim of this paper is to define this reflected diffusion as the solution of a stochastic integral equation, and simply derive their stationary distribution and conditions for its existence. As related results, we also consider the case that it is reflected at two sides, which is called a two-sides reflected diffusion, and derive its stationary distribution and conditions for its existence.
  In the literature, these problems are studied through a state-dependent diffusion on the whole line particularly when the drift and deviation are discontinuous. However, the reflected process itself is not defined in such a study. Thus, the stationary distribution has not been fully studied for a general state-dependent reflected diffusion. We aim to fills this insufficiency and to make the stationary distributions of reflected diffusions widely available in application.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11496v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masakiyo Miyazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riemann-Liouville fractional Brownian motion with random Hurst exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine two stochastic processes with random parameters, which in their basic versions (i.e., when the parameters are fixed) are Gaussian and display long range dependence and anomalous diffusion behavior, characterized by the Hurst exponent. Our motivation comes from biological experiments, which show that the basic models are inadequate for accurate description of the data, leading to modifications of these models in the literature through introduction of the random parameters. The first process, fractional Brownian motion with random Hurst exponent (referred to as FBMRE below) has been recently studied, while the second one, Riemann-Liouville fractional Brownian motion with random exponent (RL FBMRE) has not been explored. To advance the theory of such doubly stochastic anomalous diffusion models, we investigate the probabilistic properties of RL FBMRE and compare them to those of FBMRE. Our main focus is on the autocovariance function and the time-averaged mean squared displacement (TAMSD) of the processes. Furthermore, we analyze the second moment of the increment processes for both models, as well as their ergodicity properties. As a specific case, we consider the mixture of two point distributions of the Hurst exponent, emphasizing key differences in the characteristics of RL FBMRE and FBMRE, particularly in their asymptotic behavior. The theoretical findings presented here lay the groundwork for developing new methods to distinguish these processes and estimate their parameters from experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11546v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hubert Woszczek, Agnieszka Wylomanska, Aleksei Chechkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness of subcritical non-linear heat equations with Gaussian initial data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that any non-linear heat equation with scaling critical dimension $-1$ is locally well-posed when its initial condition is taken as the Gaussian free field in fractional dimension $d &lt; 4$. Our results in particular extend the well-posedness results of arXiv:2111.10652, arXiv:2201.03487 from $d=3$ to the entire subcritical regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11638v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Chevyrev, Hora Mirsajjadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability that $n$ points are in convex position in a general convex polygon: Asymptotic results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{P}_K(n)$ be the probability that $n$ points $z_1,\ldots,z_n$ picked uniformly and independently in $K$, a non-flat compact convex polygon in $\mathbb{R}^2$, are in convex position, that is, form the vertex set of a convex polygon. In this paper, we give an equivalent of $\mathbb{P}_K(n)$ when $n\to\infty$. This improves on a famous result of B\'ar\'any (yet valid for a general convex domain $K$) and a result we initiated in the case where $K$ is a regular convex polygon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11706v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovic Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Paquette-Zeitouni law of fractional logarithms for the GUE minor process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The scaled and centered largest eigenvalue of the $n\times n$ principal minor of an infinite GUE matrix, denoted by $\widetilde{\lambda}_n$, converges to the GUE Tracy-Widom distribution. We show that $\liminf\limits_{n\to \infty}(\log n)^{-1/3}\widetilde{\lambda}_n= -4^{1/3}$ almost surely, confirming a conjecture of Paquette and Zeitouni (Ann. Probab., 2017). Our arguments rely on the recently established sharp lower tail estimate for the largest eigenvalue of GUE from (Baslingker et al., 2024) and a correspondence between the GUE minor process and Brownian last passage percolation, due to Baryshnikov (Probab. Theory Related Fields, 2001). The latter result is used in a geometric argument to show the decorrelation of the largest eigenvalues at the appropriate scale. Our arguments also give a new proof of the corresponding law of fractional logarithms for the limsup, established by Paquette and Zeitouni (Ann. Probab., 2017).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11836v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jnaneshwar Baslingker, Riddhipratim Basu, Sudeshna Bhattacharjee, Manjunath Krishnapur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two waves of adaptation: speciation induced by dormancy in a model with changing environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10890v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a population model in which the season alternates between winter and summer, and individuals can acquire mutations either that are advantageous in the summer and disadvantageous in the winter, or vice versa. Also, we assume that individuals in the population can either be active or dormant, and that individuals can move between these two states. Dormant individuals do not reproduce but do not experience selective pressures. We show that, under certain conditions, over time we see two waves of adaptation. Some individuals repeatedly acquire mutations that are beneficial in the summer, while others repeatedly acquire mutations that are beneficial in the winter. Individuals can survive the season during which they are less fit by entering a dormant state. This result demonstrates that, for populations in fluctuating environments, dormancy has the potential to induce speciation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10890v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Cordero, Adri\'an Gonz\'alez Casanova, Jason Schweinsberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical field theory of random graphs with prescribed degrees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Statistical field theory methods have been very successful with a number of random graph and random matrix problems, but it is challenging to apply these methods to graphs with prescribed degree sequences due to the extensive number of constraints that enforce the desired degree at each vertex. Building on top of recent results where similar methods are applied to random regular graph counting, we develop an accurate statistical field theory description for the adjacency matrix spectra of graphs with prescribed degrees. For large graphs, the expectation values are dominated by functional saddle points satisfying explicit equations. For the case of regular graphs, this immediately leads to the known McKay distribution. We then consider mixed-regular graphs with N1 vertices of degree d1, N2 vertices of degree d2, etc, such that the ratios N_i/N are kept fixed as N goes to infinity. For such graphs, the eigenvalue densities are governed by nonlinear integral equations of the Hammerstein type. Solving these equations numerically reproduces with an excellent accuracy the empirical eigenvalue distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11191v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawat Akara-pipattana, Oleg Evnin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unbiased estimation of second-order parameter sensitivities for stochastic reaction networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11471v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stochastic models for chemical reaction networks are increasingly popular in systems and synthetic biology. These models formulate the reaction dynamics as Continuous-Time Markov Chains (CTMCs) whose propensities are parameterized by a vector $\theta$ and parameter sensitivities are introduced as derivatives of their expected outputs with respect to components of the parameter vector. Sensitivities characterise key properties of the output like robustness and are also at the heart of numerically efficient optimisation routines like Newton-type algorithms used in parameter inference and the design of of control mechanisms. Currently the only unbiased estimator for second-order sensitivities is based on the Girsanov transform and it often suffers from high estimator variance. We develop a novel estimator for second-order sensitivities by first rigorously deriving an integral representation of these sensitivities. We call the resulting method the Double Bernoulli Path Algorithm and illustrate its efficiency through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11471v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Badolle, Ankit Gupta, Mustafa Khammash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of long-range order in random-field Ising model on Dyson hierarchical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the random-field Ising model on a Dyson hierarchical lattice, where the interactions decay in a power-law-like form, $J(r)\sim r^{-\alpha}$, with respect to the distance. Without a random field, the Ising model on the Dyson hierarchical lattice has a long-range order at finite low temperatures when $1&lt;\alpha&lt;2$. In this study, for $1&lt;\alpha&lt;3/2$, we rigorously prove that there is a long-range order in the random-field Ising model on the Dyson hierarchical lattice at finite low temperatures, including zero temperature, when the strength of the random field is sufficiently small but nonzero. Our proof is based on Dyson's method for the case without a random field, and the concentration inequalities in probability theory enable us to evaluate the effect of a random field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11515v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manaka Okuyama, Masayuki Ohzeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments of random multiplicative functions, III: A short review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11523v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a short review of recent progress on determining the order of magnitude of moments $\mathbb{E}|\sum_{n \leq x} f(n)|^{2q}$ of random multiplicative functions, and of closely related issues.
  We hope this can serve as a concise introduction to some of the ideas involved, for those who may not have too much background in the area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11523v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam J. Harper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov-Nash equilibria in mean-field games under model uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose and analyze a framework for mean-field Markov games under model uncertainty. In this framework, a state-measure flow describing the collective behavior of a population affects the given reward function as well as the unknown transition kernel of the representative agent. The agent's objective is to choose an optimal Markov policy in order to maximize her worst-case expected reward, where worst-case refers to the most adverse scenario among all transition kernels considered to be feasible to describe the unknown true law of the environment. We prove the existence of a mean-field equilibrium under model uncertainty, where the agent chooses the optimal policy that maximizes the worst-case expected reward, and the state-measure flow aligns with the agent's state distribution under the optimal policy and the worst-case transition kernel. Moreover, we prove that for suitable multi-agent Markov games under model uncertainty the optimal policy from the mean-field equilibrium forms an approximate Markov-Nash equilibrium whenever the number of agents is large enough.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11652v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Langner, Ariel Neufeld, Kyunghyun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian upper heat kernel bounds and Faber-Krahn inequalities on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11715v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the equivalence of relative Faber-Krahn inequalities and the conjunction of Gaussian upper heat kernel bounds and volume doubling on large scales on graphs. For the normalizing measure, we obtain their equivalence up to constants by imposing comparability of small balls and the vertex degree at their centers. Removing this comparability assumption on the cost of a local regularity condition entering the equivalence and allowing for a variable dimension lead to a further generalization. The variable dimension converges to the doubling dimension for increasing ball radius. If the counting measure or arbitrary measures are considered, the local regularity condition contains the vertex degree. Furthermore, correction functions for the Gaussian, doubling, and Faber-Krahn dimension depending on the vertex degree are introduced. For the Gaussian and doubling, the variable correction functions always tend to one at infinity. Moreover, the variable Faber-Krahn dimension can be related to the doubling dimension and the vertex degree growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11715v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Rose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measure estimation on a manifold explored by a diffusion process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11777v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: From the observation of a diffusion path $(X_t)_{t\in [0,T]}$ on a compact connected $d$-dimensional manifold $M$ without boundary, we consider the problem of estimating the stationary measure $\mu$ of the process. Wang and Zhu (2023) showed that for the Wasserstein metric $W_2$ and for $d\ge 5$, the convergence rate of $T^{-1/(d-2)}$ is attained by the occupation measure of the path $(X_t)_{t\in [0,T]}$ when $(X_t)_{t\in [0,T]}$ is a Langevin diffusion. We extend their result in several directions. First, we show that the rate of convergence holds for a large class of diffusion paths, whose generators are uniformly elliptic. Second, the regularity of the density $p$ of the stationary measure $\mu$ with respect to the volume measure of $M$ can be leveraged to obtain faster estimators: when $p$ belongs to a Sobolev space of order $\ell&gt;0$, smoothing the occupation measure by convolution with a kernel yields an estimator whose rate of convergence is of order $T^{-(\ell+1)/(2\ell+d-2)}$. We further show that this rate is the minimax rate of estimation for this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11777v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Divol, H\'el\`ene Gu\'erin, Dinh-Toan Nguyen, Viet Chi Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving The Dynamic Volatility Fitting Problem: A Deep Reinforcement Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11789v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The volatility fitting is one of the core problems in the equity derivatives business. Through a set of deterministic rules, the degrees of freedom in the implied volatility surface encoding (parametrization, density, diffusion) are defined. Whilst very effective, this approach widespread in the industry is not natively tailored to learn from shifts in market regimes and discover unsuspected optimal behaviors. In this paper, we change the classical paradigm and apply the latest advances in Deep Reinforcement Learning(DRL) to solve the fitting problem. In particular, we show that variants of Deep Deterministic Policy Gradient (DDPG) and Soft Actor Critic (SAC) can achieve at least as good as standard fitting algorithms. Furthermore, we explain why the reinforcement learning framework is appropriate to handle complex objective functions and is natively adapted for online learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11789v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel Gnabeyeu, Omar Karkar, Imad Idboufous</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utility maximization in constrained and unbounded financial markets: Applications to indifference valuation, regime switching, consumption and Epstein-Zin recursive utility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.00199</link>
      <description>arXiv:1707.00199v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This memoir presents a systematic study of the utility maximization problem of an investor in a constrained and unbounded financial market. Building upon the work of Hu et al. (2005) [Ann. Appl. Probab., 15, 1691--1712] in a bounded framework, we extend our analysis to the more challenging unbounded case. Our methodology combines both methods of quadratic backward stochastic differential equations with unbounded solutions and convex duality. Central to our approach is the verification of the finite entropy condition, which plays a pivotal role in solving the underlying utility maximization problem and establishing the martingale property and the convex duality representation of the conditional value process. Through four distinct applications, we first study the utility indifference valuation of financial derivatives with unbounded payoffs, uncovering novel asymptotic behaviors as the risk aversion parameter approaches zero or infinity. Furthermore, we study the regime switching market model with unbounded random endowments and consumption-investment problems with unbounded random endowments, both constrained to portfolios chosen from a convex and closed set. Finally, we investigate the investment-consumption problem of an investor with the Epstein-Zin recursive utility in an unbounded financial market.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1707.00199v5</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Hu, Gechun Liang, Shanjian Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit local density bounds for It\^o-processes with irregular drift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02241v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find explicit upper bounds for the density of marginals of continuous diffusions where we assume that the diffusion coefficient is constant and the drift is solely assumed to be progressively measurable and locally bounded. In one dimension we extend our result to the case that the diffusion coefficient is a locally Lipschitz-continuous function of the state. Our approach is based on a comparison to a suitable doubly reflected Brownian motion whose density is known in a series representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02241v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Kr\"uhner, Shijie Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variance Bounds: Some Old and Some New</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For functions of independent random variables, various upper and lower variance bounds are revisited in diverse settings. These are then specialized to the Bernoulli, Gaussian, infinitely divisible cases and to Banach space valued random variables. Frameworks and techniques vary from jackknives through semigroups and beyond. Some new applications are presented, recovering, in particular, all the known estimates on the variance of the length of the longest common subsequences of two random words.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03063v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Deslandes, Christian Houdr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability that $n$ points are in convex position in a regular $\kappa$-gon : Asymptotic results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{P}_{\kappa}(n)$ be the probability that $n$ points $z_1,\ldots,z_n$ picked uniformly and independently in $\mathfrak{C}_\kappa$, a regular $\kappa$-gon with area $1$, are in convex position, that is, form the vertex set of a convex polygon. In this paper, we give an equivalent of $\mathbb{P}_{\kappa}(n)$ for all $\kappa\geq 3$, which improves on a famous result of B\'ar\'any. A second aim of the paper is to establish a limit theorem which describes the fluctuations around the limit shape of a $n$-tuple of points in convex position when $n\to+\infty$. Finally, we give an algorithm asymptotically exact for the random generation of $z_1,\ldots,z_n$, conditioned to be in convex position in $\mathfrak{C}_\kappa$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16207v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovic Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condensation in zero-range processes with a fast rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a simple zero-range process with constant rates and one fast rate for a particular occupation number, which diverges with the system size. Surprisingly, this minor modification induces a condensation transition in the thermodynamic limit, where the structure of the condensed phase depends on the scaling of the fast rate. We study this transition and its dependence on system parameters in detail on a rigorous level using size-biased sampling. This approach generalizes to any particle system with stationary product measures, and the techniques used in this paper provide a foundation for a more systematic understanding of condensing models with a non-trivial condensed phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02590v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Watthanan Jatuviriyapornchai, Stefan Grosskinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exchangeable arrays and integrable systems for characteristic polynomials of random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19233v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The joint moments of the derivatives of the characteristic polynomial of a random unitary matrix, and also a variant of the characteristic polynomial that is real on the unit circle, in the large matrix size limit, have been studied intensively in the past twenty five years, partly in relation to conjectural connections to the Riemann zeta-function and Hardy's function. We completely settle the most general version of the problem of convergence of these joint moments, after they are suitably rescaled, for an arbitrary number of derivatives and with arbitrary positive real exponents. Our approach relies on a hidden, higher-order exchangeable structure, that of an exchangeable array. Using these probabilistic techniques, we then give a combinatorial formula for the leading order coefficient in the asymptotics of the joint moments, when the power on the characteristic polynomial itself is a positive real number and the exponents of the derivatives are integers, in terms of a finite number of finite-dimensional integrals which are explicitly computable. Finally, we develop a method, based on a class of Hankel determinants shifted by partitions, that allows us to give an exact representation of all these joint moments, for finite matrix size, in terms of derivatives of Painlev\'e V transcendents, and then for the leading order coefficient in the large-matrix limit in terms of derivatives of solutions of the $\sigma$-Painlev\'e III' equation. Equivalently, we can represent all the joint moments of power sum linear statistics of a certain determinantal point process behind this problem in terms of derivatives of $\sigma$-Painlev\'e III' transcendents. This gives an efficient way to compute all these quantities explicitly. Our methods can be used to obtain analogous results for a number of other models sharing the same features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19233v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodoros Assiotis, Mustafa Alper Gunes, Jonathan P. Keating, Fei Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The macroscopic shape of Gelfand-Tsetlin patterns and free probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10754v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A Gelfand-Tsetlin function is a real-valued function $\phi:C \to \mathbb{R}$ defined on a finite subset $C$ of the lattice $\mathbb{Z}^2$ with the property that $\phi(x) \leq \phi(y)$ for every edge $\langle x,y \rangle$ directed north or east between two elements of $C$. We study the statistical physics properties of random Gelfand-Tsetlin functions from the perspective of random surfaces, showing in particular that the surface tension of Gelfand-Tsetlin functions at gradient $u = (u_1,u_2) \in \mathbb{R}_{&gt;0}^2$ is given by \begin{align*} \sigma(u_1,u_2) = - \log (u_1 + u_2 ) - \log \sin (\pi u_1/(u_1+u_2)) -1 + \log \pi. \end{align*} A Gelfand-Tsetlin pattern is a Gelfand-Tsetlin function defined on the triangle $T_n = \{(x_1,x_2) \in \mathbb{Z}^2 : 1 \leq x_2 \leq x_1 \leq n \}$. We show that after rescaling, a sequence of random Gelfand-Tsetlin patterns with fixed diagonal heights approximating a probability measure $\mu$ satisfies a large deviation principle with speed $n^2$ and rate functional of the form \begin{align*} \mathcal{E}[\psi] := \int_{\blacktriangle} \sigma(\nabla \psi)\, \mathrm{d}s \,\mathrm{d}t - \chi[\mu] \end{align*} where $\chi[\mu]$ is Voiculescu's free entropy. We show that the Euler-Lagrange equations satisfied by the minimiser of the rate functional agree with those governing the free compression operation in free probability, thereby resolving a recent conjecture of Shlyakhtenko and Tao.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10754v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel G. G. Johnston, Joscha Prochno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environmental management and restoration under unified risk and uncertainty using robustified dynamic Orlicz risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.01998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.01998v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Environmental management and restoration should be designed such that the risk and uncertainty owing to nonlinear stochastic systems can be successfully addressed. We apply the robustified dynamic Orlicz risk to the modeling and analysis of environmental management and restoration to consider both the risk and uncertainty within a unified theory. We focus on the control of a jump-driven hybrid stochastic system that represents macrophyte dynamics. The dynamic programming equation based on the Orlicz risk is first obtained heuristically, from which the associated Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equation is derived. In the proposed Orlicz risk, the risk aversion of the decision-maker is represented by a power coefficient that resembles a certainty equivalence, whereas the uncertainty aversion is represented by the Kullback-Leibler divergence, in which the risk and uncertainty are handled consistently and separately. The HJB equation includes a new state-dependent discount factor that arises from the uncertainty aversion, which leads to a unique, nonlinear, and nonlocal term. The link between the proposed and classical stochastic control problems is discussed with a focus on control-dependent discount rates. We propose a finite difference method for computing the HJB equation. Finally, the proposed model is applied to an optimal harvesting problem for macrophytes in a brackish lake that contains both growing and drifting populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.01998v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidekazu Yoshioka, Motoh Tsujimura, Futoshi Aranishi, Tomomi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Dimension of the Brownian Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Conformal dimension of a metric space $X$, denoted by $\dim_C X$, is the infimum of the Hausdorff dimension among all its quasisymmetric images. If conformal dimension of $X$ is equal to its Hausdorff dimension, $X$ is said to be minimal for conformal dimension. In this paper we show that the graph of the one dimensional Brownian motion is almost surely minimal for conformal dimension. We also give many other examples of minimal sets for conformal dimension, which we call Bedford-McMullen type sets. In particular we show that Bedford-McMullen self-affine sets with uniform fibers are minimal for conformal dimension. The main technique in the proofs is the construction of ``rich families of minimal sets of conformal dimension one''. The latter concept is quantified using Fuglede's modulus of measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02350v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilia Binder, Hrant Hakobyan, Wen-Bo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of viscosity solutions for a class of second order PDEs on the Wasserstein space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05040v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a comparison result for viscosity solutions of second order parabolic partial differential equations in the Wasserstein space. The comparison is valid for semisolutions that are Lipschitz continuous in the measure in a Fourier-Wasserstein metric and uniformly continuous in time. The class of equations we consider is motivated by Mckean-Vlasov control problems with common noise and filtering problems. The proof of comparison relies on a novel version of Ishii's lemma, which is tailor-made for the class of equations we consider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05040v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhan Bayraktar, Ibrahim Ekren, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous random flights and time-fractional run-and-tumble equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15941v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Random flights (also called run-and-tumble walks or transport processes) represent finite velocity random motions changing direction at any Poissonian time. These models in d-dimension, can be studied giving a general formulation of the problem valid at any spatial dimension. The aim of this paper is to extend this general analysis to time-fractional processes arising from a non-local generalization of the kinetic equations. The probabilistic interpretation of the solution of the time-fractional equations leads to a time-changed version of the original transport processes. The obtained results provides a clear picture of the role played by the time-fractional derivatives in this kind of random motions. They display an anomalous behavior and are useful to describe several complex systems arising in statistical physics and biology. In particular, we focus on the one-dimensional random flight, called telegraph process, studying the time-fractional version of the classical telegraph equation and providing a suitable interpretation of its stochastic solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15941v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10955-024-03344-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Stat. Phys. 191, 129 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Angelani, Alessandro De Gregorio, Roberto Garra, Francesco Iafrate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Malliavin Calculus for the stochastic heat equation and results on the density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the one-dimensional stochastic heat equation with nonlinear Lipschitz coefficients and Dirichlet boundary conditions. We apply Malliavin calculus to this equation; we show that the solution $u \in L_{1,2}$ and provide a different proof for the existence of a density for $u$ that relies on a localization argument. This type of localization has been used before for other SPDE. However, our proof for the existence of a density for the solution to the stochastic heat equation follows a different strategy and is more involved due to new difficulties arising with the heat kernel. We also prove the existence of a density for the supremum of $u$ and that it belongs in $D_{1,2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10115v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Farazakis, G. Karali, A. Stavrianidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
