<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-intransitive Systems of Independent Random Variables and Fractals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct meta-intransitive systems of independent random variables of any finite order from basic tuple of random variables which generalize intransitive dice. Under this construction, the equality of some linear functional is preserved, provided this equality hold for the basic variables. This scheme is also extended to infinite-order systems, which are shown to be fractals, and for which the similarity dimension can be evaluated. The problem of the upper bound for this dimension is posed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02424v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey V. Lebedev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brownian Motion in a Vector Space over a Local Field is a Scaling Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For any natural number $d$, the Vladimirov-Taibleson operator is a natural analogue of the Laplace operator for complex-valued functions on a $d$-dimensional vector space $V$ over a local field $K$. Just as the Laplace operator on $L^2(\mathbb R^d)$ is the infinitesimal generator of Brownian motion with state space $\mathbb R^d$, the Vladimirov-Taibleson operator on $L^2(V)$ is the infinitesimal generator of real-time Brownian motion with state space $V$. This study deepens the formal analogy between the two types of diffusion processes by demonstrating that both are scaling limits of discrete-time random walks on a discrete group. It generalizes the earlier works, which restricted $V$ to be the $p$-adic numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02502v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Pierce, Rahul Rajkumar, Andrea Stine, David Weisbart, Adam M. Yassine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of a Poisson process in weakly interacting particle systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Gibbs measure of a general interacting particle system for a certain class of ``weakly interacting" kernels. In particular, we show that the local point process converges to a Poisson point process as long as the inverse temperature $\beta$ satisfies $N^{-1} \ll \beta \ll N^{-\frac{1}{2}}$, where $N$ is the number of particles. This expands the temperature regime for which convergence to a Poisson point process has been proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02625v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Padilla-Garza, Luke Peilen, Eric Thoma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviation Principles of Invariant Measures of Stochastic Reaction-Diffusion Lattice Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the large deviation principle of invariant measures of stochastic reaction-diffusion lattice systems driven by multiplicative noise. We first show that any limit of a sequence of invariant measures of the stochastic system must be an invariant measure of the deterministic limiting system as noise intensity approaches zero. We then prove the uniform Freidlin-Wentzell large deviations of solution paths over all initial data and the uniform Dembo-Zeitouni large deviations of solution paths over a compact set of initial data. We finally establish the large deviations of invariant measures by combining the idea of tail-ends estimates and the argument of weighted spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02720v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bixiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heyde theorem for locally compact Abelian groups containing no subgroups topologically isomorphic to the 2-dimensional torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the following group analogue of the well-known Heyde theorem on a characterization of the Gaussian distribution on the real line. Let $X$ be a second countable locally compact Abelian group containing no subgroups topologically isomorphic to the 2-dimensional torus. Let $G$ be the subgroup of $X$ generated by all elements of $X$ of order $2$ and let $\alpha$ be a topological automorphism of the group $X$ such that ${\rm Ker}(I+\alpha)=\{0\}$. Let $\xi_1$ and $\xi_2$ be independent random variables with values in $X$ and distributions $\mu_1$ and $\mu_2$ with nonvanishing characteristic functions. If the conditional distribution of the linear form $L_2 = \xi_1 + \alpha\xi_2$ given $L_1 = \xi_1 +\xi_2$ is symmetric, then $\mu_j$ are convolutions of Gaussian distributions on $X$ and distributions supported in $G$. We also prove that this theorem is false if $X$ is the 2-dimensional torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02789v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gennadiy Feldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Behavior of Maxima under Dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak convergence of maxima of dependent sequences of identically distributed continuous random variables is studied under normalizing sequences arising as subsequences of the normalizing sequences from an associated iid sequence. This general framework allows one to derive several generalizations of the well-known Fisher-Tippett-Gnedenko theorem under conditions on the univariate marginal distribution and the dependence structure of the sequence. The limiting distributions are shown to be compositions of a generalized extreme value distribution and a distortion function which reflects the limiting behavior of the diagonal of the underlying copula. Uniform convergence rates for the weak convergence to the limiting distribution are also derived. Examples covering well-known dependence structures are provided. Several existing results, e.g. for exchangeable sequences or stationary time series, are embedded in the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02833v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Herrmann, Marius Hofert, Johanna G. Neslehova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic cellular automata with local transition matrices: synchronization, ergodicity, and inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new class of probabilistic cellular automata that are capable of exhibiting rich dynamics such as synchronization and ergodicity and can be easily inferred from data. The system is a finite-state locally interacting Markov chain on a circular graph. Each site's subsequent state is random, with a distribution determined by its neighborhood's empirical distribution multiplied by a local transition matrix. We establish sufficient and necessary conditions on the local transition matrix for synchronization and ergodicity. Also, we introduce novel least squares estimators for inferring the local transition matrix from various types of data, which may consist of either multiple trajectories, a long trajectory, or ensemble sequences without trajectory information. Under suitable identifiability conditions, we show the asymptotic normality of these estimators and provide non-asymptotic bounds for their accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02928v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhan Bayrakta, Fei Lu, Mauro Maggioni, Ruoyu Wu, Sichen Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Background risk model in presence of heavy tails under dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the background risk model under a various forms of dependence and some distribution classes of heavy tails. First, we study the asymptotic behavior of tail expectation of a portfolios with unequal heavytailedness, of non-random sums and randomly stopped sums, under some dependence structure which contains the independence as a special case. Further we investigate the asymptotic behavior of a pair of randomly weighted sums, generalizing the dependence structure among random vector components, our results contains the finite ruin probability in bi-dimensional discrete time risk model with unequal heavytailedness. Next, we carry out asymptotic analysis of the tail distortion risk measures in background risk model under various forms of dependence, with multivariate regularly varying risk distributions in each portfolio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03014v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios G. Konstantinides, Charalampos D. Passalidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial lower bound on the effective resistance for the one-dimensional critical long-range percolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we study the critical long-range percolation on $\mathbb{Z}$, where an edge connects $i$ and $j$ independently with probability $1-\exp\{-\beta |i-j|^{-2}\}$ for some fixed $\beta&gt;0$. Viewing this as a random electric network where each edge has a unit conductance, we show that with high probability the effective resistances from the origin 0 to $[-N, N]^c$ and from the interval $[-N,N]$ to $[-2N,2N]^c$ (conditioned on no edge joining $[-N,N]$ and $[-2N,2N]^c$) both have a polynomial lower bound in $N$. Our bound holds for all $\beta&gt;0$ and thus rules out a potential phase transition (around $\beta = 1$) which seemed to be a reasonable possibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03460v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Ding, Zherui Fan, Lu-Jing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From 1 to infinity: The log-correction for the maximum of variable-speed branching Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the extremes of variable speed branching Brownian motion (BBM) where the time-dependent "speed functions", which describe the time-inhomogeneous variance, converge to the identity function.
  We consider general speed functions lying strictly below their concave hull and piecewise linear, concave speed functions.
  In the first case, the log-correction for the order of the maximum depends only on the rate of convergence of the speed function near 0 and 1 and exhibits a smooth interpolation between the correction in the i.i.d. case, $\frac{1}{2\sqrt{2}} \ln t$, and that of standard BBM, $\frac{3}{2\sqrt{2}} \ln t$.
  In the second case, we describe the order of the maximum in dependence of the form of speed function and show that any log-correction larger than $\frac{3}{2\sqrt{2}} \ln t$ can be obtained.
  In both cases, we prove that the limiting law of the maximum and the extremal process essentially coincide with those of standard BBM, using a first and second moment method which relies on the localisation of extremal particles.
  This extends the results of Bovier and Hartung for two-speed BBM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03580v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Alban, Anton Bovier, Annabell Gros, Lisa Hartung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling the Stochastic Importation Dynamics and Establishment of Novel Pathogenic Strains using a General Branching Processes Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02379v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The importation and subsequent establishment of novel pathogenic strains in a population is subject to a large degree of uncertainty due to the stochastic nature of the disease dynamics. Mathematical models need to take this stochasticity in the early phase of an outbreak in order to adequately capture the uncertainty in disease forecasts. We propose a general branching process model of disease spread that includes host-level heterogeneity, and that can be straightforwardly tailored to capture the salient aspects of a particular disease outbreak. We combine this with a model of case importation that occurs via an independent marked Poisson process. We use this framework to investigate the impact of different control strategies, particularly on the time to establishment of an invading, exogenous strain, using parameters taken from the literature for COVID-19 as an example. We also demonstrate how to combine our model with a deterministic approximation, such that longer term projections can be generated that still incorporate the uncertainty from the early growth phase of the epidemic. Our approach produces meaningful short- and medium-term projections of the course of a disease outbreak when model parameters are still uncertain and when stochasticity still has a large effect on the population dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02379v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Curran-Sebastian, Frederik M{\o}lkj{\ae}r Andersen, Samir Bhatt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Sample Analysis and Bounds of Generalization Error of Gradient Descent in In-Context Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent studies show that transformer-based architectures emulate gradient descent during a forward pass, contributing to in-context learning capabilities - an ability where the model adapts to new tasks based on a sequence of prompt examples without being explicitly trained or fine tuned to do so. This work investigates the generalization properties of a single step of gradient descent in the context of linear regression with well-specified models. A random design setting is considered and analytical expressions are derived for the statistical properties of generalization error in a non-asymptotic (finite sample) setting. These expressions are notable for avoiding arbitrary constants, and thus offer robust quantitative information and scaling relationships. These results are contrasted with those from classical least squares regression (for which analogous finite sample bounds are also derived), shedding light on systematic and noise components, as well as optimal step sizes. Additionally, identities involving high-order products of Gaussian random matrices are presented as a byproduct of the analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02462v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karthik Duraisamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A combinatorial problem related to the classical probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the classical probability model, let $f(n)$ be the maximum number of pairwise independent events for the sample space with $n$ sample points. The determination of $f(n)$ is equivalent to the problem of determining the maximum cardinality of specific intersecting families on the set $\{1,2,\ldots,n\}$ . We show that $f(n)\leq n+1$, and $f(n)=n+1$ if there exists a Hadamard matrix of order $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02577v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.disc.2024.114067</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete Mathematics 347 (2024) 114067</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling frequency distribution above a priority in presence of IBNR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In reinsurance, Poisson and Negative binomial distributions are employed for modeling frequency. However, the incomplete data regarding reported incurred claims above a priority level presents challenges in estimation. This paper focuses on frequency estimation using Schnieper's framework for claim numbering. We demonstrate that Schnieper's model is consistent with a Poisson distribution for the total number of claims above a priority at each year of development, providing a robust basis for parameter estimation. Additionally, we explain how to build an alternative assumption based on a Negative binomial distribution, which yields similar results. The study includes a bootstrap procedure to manage uncertainty in parameter estimation and a case study comparing assumptions and evaluating the impact of the bootstrap approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02871v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Baradel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General harmonic measures for distance-expanding dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Partially motivated by the study of I. Binder, N. Makarov, and S. Smirnov [BMS03] on dimension spectra of polynomial Cantor sets, we initiate the investigation on some general harmonic measures, inspired by Sullivan's dictionary, for distance-expanding dynamical systems. Let $f\colon X\to X$ be an open distance-expanding map on a compact metric space $(X,\rho)$. A Gromov hyperbolic tile graph $\Gamma$ associated to the dynamical system $(X,f)$ is constructed following the ideas from M. Bonk, D. Meyer [BM17] and P. Ha\"issinsky, K. M. Pilgrim [HP09]. We consider a class of one-sided random walks associated with $(X,f)$ on $\Gamma$. They induce a Martin boundary of the tile graph, which may be different from the hyperbolic boundary. We show that the Martin boundary of such a random walk admits a surjection to $X$. We provide a class of examples to show that the surjection may not be a homeomorphism. Such random walks also induce measures on $X$ called harmonic measures. When $\rho$ is a visual metric, we establish an equality between the fractal dimension of the harmonic measure and the asymptotic quantities of the random walk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02987v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiqiang Li, Ruicen Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saturation in Random Hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $K^r_n$ be the complete $r$-uniform hypergraph on $n$ vertices, that is, the hypergraph whose vertex set is $[n]:=\{1,2,...,n\}$ and whose edge set is $\binom{[n]}{r}$. We form $G^r(n,p)$ by retaining each edge of $K^r_n$ independently with probability $p$.
  An $r$-uniform hypergraph $H\subseteq G$ is $F$-saturated if $H$ does not contain any copy of $F$, but any missing edge of $H$ in $G$ creates a copy of $F$. Furthermore, we say that $H$ is weakly $F$-saturated in $G$ if $H$ does not contain any copy of $F$, but the missing edges of $H$ in $G$ can be added back one-by-one, in some order, such that every edge creates a new copy of $F$. The smallest number of edges in an $F$-saturated hypergraph in $G$ is denoted by $sat(G,F)$, and in a weakly $F$-saturated hypergraph in $G$ by $wsat(G,F)$.
  In 2017, Kor\'andi and Sudakov initiated the study of saturation in random graphs, showing that for constant $p$, with high probability $sat(G(n,p),K_s)=(1+o(1))n\log_{\frac{1}{1-p}}n$, and $wsat(G(n,p),K_s)=wsat(K_n,K_s)$. Generalising their results, in this paper, we solve the suturation problem for random hypergraphs for every $2\le r &lt; s$ and constant $p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03061v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahar Diskin, Ilay Hoshen, D\'aniel Kor\'andi, Benny Sudakov, Maksim Zhukovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Null controllability for stochastic fourth order semi-discrete parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to studying null controllability for a class of stochastic fourth order semi-discrete parabolic equations, where the spatial variable is discretized with finite difference scheme and the time is kept as a continuous variable. For this purpose, we establish a new global Carleman estimate for a backward stochastic fourth order semi-discrete parabolic operators, in which the large parameter is connected to the mesh size. A relaxed observability estimate is established for backward stochastic fourth order semi-discrete parabolic equations by this new Carleman estimate, with an explicit observability constant that depends on the discretization parameter and coefficients of lower order terms. Then, the $\phi$-null controllability of the stochastic fourth order semi-discrete parabolic equations is proved using the standard duality technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03257v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Qingmei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of random 2-SAT solutions is asymptotically log-normal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that throughout the satisfiable phase, the logarithm of the number of satisfying assignments of a random 2-SAT formula satisfies a central limit theorem. This implies that the log of the number of satisfying assignments exhibits fluctuations of order $\sqrt n$, with $n$ the number of variables. The formula for the variance can be evaluated effectively. By contrast, for numerous other random constraint satisfaction problems the typical fluctuations of the logarithm of the number of solutions are {\em bounded} throughout all or most of the satisfiable regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03302v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Chatterjee, Amin Coja-Oghlan, Noela M\"uller, Connor Riddlesden, Maurice Rolvien, Pavel Zakharov, Haodong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-side Liouville theorems under an exponential growth condition for Kolmogorov operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is known that for a possibly degenerate hypoelliptic Ornstein-Uhlenbeck operator $$ L= \frac{1}{2}\text{ tr} (QD^2 ) + \langle Ax, D \rangle = \frac{1}{2}\text{ div} (Q D ) + \langle Ax, D \rangle,\;\; x \in R^N, $$ all (globally) bounded solutions of $Lu=0$ on $R^N$ are constant if and only if all the eigenvalues of $A$ have non-positive real parts (i.e., $s(A) \le 0)$. We show that if $Q$ is positive definite and $s(A) \le 0$, then any non-negative solution $v$ of $Lv=0$ on $R^N$ which has at most an exponential growth is indeed constant. Thus under a non-degeneracy condition we relax the boundedness assumption on the harmonic functions and maintain the sharp condition on the eigenvalues of $A$. We also prove a related one-side Liouville theorem in the case of hypoelliptic Ornstein-Uhlenbeck operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03410v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Priola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A central limit theorem associated with a sequence of positive line bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03479v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a central limit theorem for random currents of integration along the zero divisors of standard Gaussian holomorphic sections in a sequence of holomorphic line bundles with Hermitian metrics of class $\mathscr{C}^{3}$ over a compact K\"{a}hler manifold. In the course of our analysis, we derive first-order asymptotics and upper decay estimates for near and off-diagonal Bergman kernels, respectively. These results are essential for determining the statistical properties of the zeros of random holomorphic sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03479v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Afrim Bojnik, Ozan G\"uny\"uz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On anomalous dissipation induced by transport noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03525v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that suitable transport noises produce anomalous dissipation of energy of solutions to the 2D Navier-Stokes equations and diffusion equations in all dimensions. The key ingredients are Meyers' type estimates for SPDEs with transport noise which are combined with recent scaling limits for such SPDEs. The former allow us to obtain, for the first time for such type of scaling limits, convergence in a space of positive smoothness uniformly in time. Compared to known results, one of the main novelties is that anomalous dissipation might take place even in presence of a transport noise of arbitrarily small intensity. Further, we discuss physical interpretations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03525v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Agresti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging discrete and continuous state spaces: Exploring the Ehrenfest process in time-continuous diffusion models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generative modeling via stochastic processes has led to remarkable empirical results as well as to recent advances in their theoretical understanding. In principle, both space and time of the processes can be discrete or continuous. In this work, we study time-continuous Markov jump processes on discrete state spaces and investigate their correspondence to state-continuous diffusion processes given by SDEs. In particular, we revisit the $\textit{Ehrenfest process}$, which converges to an Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process in the infinite state space limit. Likewise, we can show that the time-reversal of the Ehrenfest process converges to the time-reversed Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process. This observation bridges discrete and continuous state spaces and allows to carry over methods from one to the respective other setting. Additionally, we suggest an algorithm for training the time-reversal of Markov jump processes which relies on conditional expectations and can thus be directly related to denoising score matching. We demonstrate our methods in multiple convincing numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03549v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludwig Winkler, Lorenz Richter, Manfred Opper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examples of measures with trivial left and non-trivial right random walk tail boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.11359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.11359v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In early 80's Vadim Kaimanovich presented a construction of a non-degenerate measure, on the standard lamplighter group, that has a trivial left and non-trivial right random walk tail boundary. We show that examples of such kind are possible precisely for amenable groups that have non-trivial factors with infinite conjugacy classes property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.11359v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Alpeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Co-spectral radius for countable equivalence relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.06692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.06692v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define the co-spectral radius of inclusions $\mathcal{S}\leq \mathcal{R}$ of discrete, probability measure-preserving equivalence relations, as the sampling exponent of a generating random walk on the ambient relation. The co-spectral radius is analogous to the spectral radius for random walks on $G/H$ for inclusion $H\leq G$ of groups. For the proof, we develop a more general version of the 2-3 method we used in another work on the growth of unimodular random rooted trees. We use this method to show that the walk growth exists for an arbitrary unimodular random rooted graph of bounded degree. We also investigate how the co-spectral radius behaves for hyperfinite relations, and discuss new critical exponents for percolation that can be defined using the co-spectral radius.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.06692v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikl\'os Abert, Mikolaj Fraczyk, Ben Hayes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Small-Noise Limit of the Most Likely Element is the Most Likely Element in the Small-Noise Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.04523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.04523v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Onsager-Machlup function and its relationship to the Freidlin-Wentzell function for measures equivalent to arbitrary infinite dimensional Gaussian measures. The Onsager-Machlup function can serve as a density on infinite dimensional spaces, where a uniform measure does not exist, and has been seen as the Lagrangian for the ``most likely element". The Freidlin-Wentzell rate function is the large deviations rate function for small-noise limits and has also been identified as a Lagrangian for the ``most likely element". This leads to a conundrum - what is the relationship between these two functions?
  We show both pointwise and $\Gamma$-convergence (which is essentially the convergence of minimizers) of the Onsager-Machlup function under the small-noise limit to the Freidlin-Wentzell function - and give an expression for both. That is, we show that the small-noise limit of the most likely element is the most likely element in the small noise limit for infinite dimensional measures that are equivalent to a Gaussian. Examples of measures include the law of solutions to path-dependent stochastic differential equations and the law of an infinite system of random algebraic equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.04523v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Selk, Harsha Honnappa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic results for compound sums in separable Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.08788v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove large and moderate deviation results for sequences of compound sums, where the summands are i.i.d. random variables taking values in a separable Banach space. We establish that the results hold by proving that we are dealing with exponentially tight sequences. We present two moderate deviation results: in the first one the summands are centered, in the second one the compound sums are centered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.08788v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Macci, Barbara Pacchiarotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H\"older regularity and roughness: construction and examples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13794v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study how to construct a stochastic process on a finite interval with given `roughness' and finite joint moments of marginal distributions. We first extend Ciesielski's isomorphism along a general sequence of partitions, and provide a characterization of H\"older regularity of a function in terms of its Schauder coefficients. Using this characterization we provide a better (pathwise) estimator of H\"older exponent. As an additional application, we construct fake (fractional) Brownian motions with some path properties and finite moments of marginal distributions same as (fractional) Brownian motions. These belong to non-Gaussian families of stochastic processes which are statistically difficult to distinguish from real (fractional) Brownian motions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13794v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhan Bayraktar, Purba Das, Donghan Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$1/f$ noise in electrical conductors arising from the heterogeneous detrapping process of individual charge carriers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a model of $1/f$ noise in electrical conductors based on the drift of individual charge carriers and their interaction with the trapping centers. We assume that the trapping centers are distributed uniformly across the material. The trapping centers are assumed to be heterogeneous and have unique detrapping rates, which are sampled from a uniform distribution. We show that under these assumptions, and if the trapping rate is low in comparison to the maximum detrapping rate, $1/f$ noise in the form of Hooge's relation is recovered. Hooge's parameter is shown to be a ratio between the characteristic trapping rate and the maximum detrapping rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07009v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksejus Kononovicius, Bronislovas Kaulakys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic selection problem for a Stratonovich SDE with power non-linearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06646v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In our paper [Bernoulli 26(2), 2020, 1381-1409], we found all strong Markov solutions that spend zero time at $0$ of the Stratonovich stochastic differential equation $d X=|X|^{\alpha}\circ dB$, $\alpha\in (0,1)$. These solutions have the form $X_t^\theta=F(B^\theta_t)$, where $F(x)=\frac{1}{1-\alpha}|x|^{1/(1-\alpha)}\text{sign}\, x$ and $B^\theta$ is the skew Brownian motion with skewness parameter $\theta\in [-1,1]$ starting at $F^{-1}(X_0)$. In this paper we show how an addition of small external additive noise $\varepsilon W$ restores uniqueness. In the limit as $\varepsilon\to 0$, we recover heterogeneous diffusion corresponding to the physically symmetric case $\theta=0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06646v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Pavlyukevich, Georgiy Shevchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Sharp Deconfinement Transition for Potts Lattice Gauge Theory in Codimension Two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07534v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 1983, Aizenman, Chayes, Chayes, Fr\"ohlich, and Russo proved that $2$-dimensional Bernoulli plaquette percolation in $\mathbb{Z}^3$ exhibits a sharp phase transition for the event that a large rectangular loop is "bounded by a surface of plaquettes.'' We extend this result both to $(d-1)$-dimensional plaquette percolation in $\mathbb{Z}^d,$ and to a dependent model of plaquette percolation called the plaquette random-cluster model. As a consequence, we obtain a sharp phase transition for Wilson loop expectations in $(d-2)$-dimensional $q$-state Potts hyperlattice gauge theory on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ dual to that of the Potts model. Our proof is unconditional for Ising lattice gauge theory, but relies on a regularity conjecture for the random-cluster model in slabs when $q&gt;2.$ We also further develop the general theory of the $i$-plaquette random cluster model and its relationship with $(i-1)$-dimensional Potts lattice gauge</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07534v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Duncan, Benjamin Schweinhart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost sure approximations and laws of iterated logarithm for signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02665v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We obtain strong invariance principles for normalized multiple iterated sums and integrals of the form $\bbS_N^{(\nu)}(t)=N^{-\nu/2}\sum_{0\leq k_1&lt;...&lt;k_\nu\leq Nt}\xi(k_1)\otimes\cdots\otimes\xi(k_\nu)$, $t\in[0,T]$ and $\bbS_N^{(\nu)}(t)=N^{-\nu/2}\int_{0\leq s_1\leq...\leq s_\nu\leq Nt}\xi(s_1)\otimes\cdots\otimes\xi(s_\nu)ds_1\cdots ds_\nu$, where $\{\xi(k)\}_{-\infty&lt;k&lt;\infty}$ and $\{\xi(s)\}_{-\infty&lt;s&lt;\infty}$ are centered stationary vector processes with some weak dependence properties. These imply also laws of iterated logarithm for such objects. In the continuous time we work both under direct weak dependence assumptions and also within the suspension setup which is more appropriate for applications in dynamical systems. Similar results under substantially more restricted conditions were obtained in \cite{FK} relying heavily on rough paths theory and notations while here we obtain these results in a more direct way which makes them accessible to a wider readership. This is a companion paper of our paper "Limit theorems for signatures" and we consider a similar setup and rely on many result from there.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02665v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Kifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New proofs to measurable, predictable and optional section theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13086v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we present new, short and elementary proofs of the famous projection and section theorems that are used in Stochastic Calculus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13086v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefanos Theodorakopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic partial differential equations associated with Feller processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.18726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.18726v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For the stochastic partial differential equation $\frac{\partial u}{\partial t}=\mathcal L u +u\dot W$ where $\dot W$ is Gaussian noise colored in time and $\mathcal L$ is the infinitesimal generator of a Feller process $X$, we obtain Feynman-Kac type of representations for the Stratonovich and Skorohod solutions as well as for their moments. The regularity of the law and the H\"older continuity of the solutions are also studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.18726v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Song, Meng Wang, Wangjun Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the probability of a Pareto record</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17220v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a sequence of independent random vectors taking values in ${\mathbb R}^d$ and having common continuous distribution function $F$, say that the $n^{\rm \scriptsize th}$ observation sets a (Pareto) record if it is not dominated (in every coordinate) by any preceding observation. Let $p_n(F) \equiv p_{n, d}(F)$ denote the probability that the $n^{\rm \scriptsize th}$ observation sets a record. There are many interesting questions to address concerning $p_n$ and multivariate records more generally, but this short paper focuses on how $p_n$ varies with $F$, particularly if, under $F$, the coordinates exhibit negative dependence or positive dependence (rather than independence, a more-studied case). We introduce new notions of negative and positive dependence ideally suited for such a study, called negative record-setting probability dependence (NRPD) and positive record-setting probability dependence (PRPD), relate these notions to existing notions of dependence, and for fixed $d \geq 2$ and $n \geq 1$ prove that the image of the mapping $p_n$ on the domain of NRPD (respectively, PRPD) distributions is $[p^*_n, 1]$ (resp., $[n^{-1}, p^*_n]$), where $p^*_n$ is the record-setting probability for any continuous $F$ governing independent coordinates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17220v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Allen Fill (The Johns Hopkins University), Ao Sun (The Johns Hopkins University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics of the confluent hypergeometric process with a varying external potential in the super-exponential region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16475v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a determinantal point process on the interval $(-s,s)$, associated with the confluent hypergeometric kernel. Let $\mathcal{K}^{(\alpha,\beta)}_s$ denote the trace class integral operator acting on $L^2(-s, s)$ with the confluent hypergeometric kernel. Our focus is on deriving the asymptotics of the Fredholm determinant $\det(I-\gamma \mathcal{K}^{(\alpha,\beta)}_s)$ as $s \to +\infty$, while simultaneously $\gamma \to 1^-$ in a super-exponential region. In this regime of double scaling limit, our asymptotic result also gives us asymptotics of the eigenvalues $\lambda^{(\alpha, \beta)}_k(s)$ of the integral operator $\mathcal{K}^{(\alpha,\beta)}_s$ as $s \to +\infty$. Based on the integrable structure of the confluent hypergeometric kernel, we derive our asymptotic results by applying the Deift-Zhou nonlinear steepest descent method to analyze the related Riemann-Hilbert problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16475v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Dai, Luming Yao, Yu Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uniqueness of the infinite cluster and the cluster density in the Poisson driven random connection model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a random connection model (RCM) on a general space driven by a Poisson process whose intensity measure is scaled by a parameter $t\ge 0$. We say that the infinite clusters are deletion stable if the removal of a Poisson point cannot split a cluster in two or more infinite clusters. We prove that this stability together with a natural irreducibility assumption implies uniqueness of the infinite cluster. Conversely, if the infinite cluster is unique then this stability property holds. Several criteria for irreducibility will be established. We also study the analytic properties of expectations of functions of clusters as a function of $t$. In particular we show that the position dependent cluster density is differentiable. A significant part of this paper is devoted to the important case of a stationary marked RCM (in Euclidean space), containing the Boolean model with general compact grains and the so-called weighted RCM as special cases. In this case we establish differentiability and a convexity property of the cluster density $\kappa(t)$. These properties are crucial for our proof of deletion stability of the infinite clusters but are also of interest in their own right. It then follows that an irreducible stationary marked RCM can have at most one infinite cluster. This extends and unifies several results in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17762v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Chebunin, G\"unter Last</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectral edge of non-Hermitian random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17512v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For general non-Hermitian random matrices $X$ and deterministic deformation matrices $A$, we prove that the local eigenvalue statistics of $A+X$ close to the typical edge points of its spectrum are universal. Furthermore, we show that under natural assumptions on $A$ the spectrum of $A+X$ does not have outliers at a distance larger than the natural fluctuation scale of the eigenvalues. As a consequence, the number of eigenvalues in each component of $\mathrm{Spec}(A+X)$ is deterministic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17512v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Campbell, Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Hong Chang Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing bootstrap processes on the random graph $G(n,p)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00363v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a generalization of classic bootstrap percolation in which two competing processes concurrently evolve on the same graph $G(n,p)$. Nodes can be in one of three states, conveniently represented by different colors: red, black and white. Initially, a given number $a_R$ of active red nodes (red seeds) are selected uniformly at random among the $n$ nodes. Similarly, a given number $a_B$ of active black nodes (black seeds) are selected uniformly at random among the other $n-a_R$ nodes. All remaining nodes are initially white (inactive). White nodes wake up at times dictated by independent Poisson clocks of rate 1. When a white node wakes up, it checks the state of its neighbors: if the number of red (black) neighbors exceeds the number of black (red) neighbors by a fixed amount $r \geq 2$, the node becomes an active red (black) node, and remains so forever. The parameters of the model are, besides $r$ (fixed) and $n$ (tending to $\infty$), the numbers $a_R$ ($a_B$) of initial red (black) seeds, and the edge existence probability $p=p(n)$. We study the size $A^*_R$ ($A^*_B$) of the final set of active red (black) nodes, identifying different regimes which are analyzed under suitable time-scales, allowing us to obtain detailed (asymptotic) temporal dynamics of the two concurrent activation processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00363v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Garetto, Emilio Leonardi, Giovanni Luca Torrisi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The limiting distribution of Legendre paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13025v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime number and $\left(\frac{\cdot}{p}\right)$ be the Legendre symbol modulo $p$. The \emph{Legendre path} attached to $p$ is the polygonal path whose vertices are the normalized character sums $\frac{1}{\sqrt{p}} \sum_{n\leq j} \left(\frac{n}{p}\right)$ for $0\leq j\leq p-1$. In this paper, we investigate the distribution of Legendre paths as we vary over the primes $Q\leq p\leq 2Q$, when $Q$ is large. Our main result shows that as $Q \to \infty$, these paths converge in law, in the space of real-valued continuous functions on $[0, 1]$, to a certain random Fourier series constructed using Rademacher random completely multiplicative functions. This was previously proved by the first author under the assumption of the Generalized Riemann Hypothesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13025v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayesha Hussain, Youness Lamzouri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounding the Difference between the Values of Robust and Non-Robust Markov Decision Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05520v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this note we provide an upper bound for the difference between the value function of a distributionally robust Markov decision problem and the value function of a non-robust Markov decision problem, where the ambiguity set of probability kernels of the distributionally robust Markov decision process is described by a Wasserstein-ball around some reference kernel whereas the non-robust Markov decision process behaves according to a fixed probability kernel contained in the ambiguity set. Our derived upper bound for the difference between the value functions is dimension-free and depends linearly on the radius of the Wasserstein-ball.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05520v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Neufeld, Julian Sester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit Formula for Partial Information Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03554v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mutual information between two random variables is a well-studied notion, whose understanding is fairly complete. Mutual information between one random variable and a pair of other random variables, however, is a far more involved notion. Specifically, Shannon's mutual information does not capture fine-grained interactions between those three variables, resulting in limited insights in complex systems. To capture these fine-grained interactions, in 2010 Williams and Beer proposed to decompose this mutual information to information atoms, called unique, redundant, and synergistic, and proposed several operational axioms that these atoms must satisfy. In spite of numerous efforts, a general formula which satisfies these axioms has yet to be found. Inspired by Judea Pearl's do-calculus, we resolve this open problem by introducing the do-operation, an operation over the variable system which sets a certain marginal to a desired value, which is distinct from any existing approaches. Using this operation, we provide the first explicit formula for calculating the information atoms so that Williams and Beer's axioms are satisfied, as well as additional properties from subsequent studies in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03554v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aobo Lyu, Andrew Clark, Netanel Raviv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An SEIR network epidemic model with manual and digital contact tracing allowing delays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13392v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider an SEIR epidemic model on a network also allowing random contacts, where recovered individuals could either recover naturally or be diagnosed. Upon diagnosis, manual contact tracing is triggered such that each infected network contact is reported, tested and isolated with some probability and after a random delay. Additionally, digital tracing (based on a tracing app) is triggered if the diagnosed individual is an app-user, and then all of its app-using infectees are immediately notified and isolated. The early phase of the epidemic with manual and/or digital tracing is approximated by different multi-type branching processes, and three respective reproduction numbers are derived. The effectiveness of both contact tracing mechanisms is numerically quantified through the reduction of the reproduction number. This shows that app-using fraction plays an essential role in the overall effectiveness of contact tracing. The relative effectiveness of manual tracing compared to digital tracing increases if: more of the transmission occurs on the network, when the tracing delay is shortened, and when the network degree distribution is heavy-tailed. For realistic values, the combined tracing case can reduce $R_0$ by $20-30\%$, so other preventive measures are needed to reduce the reproduction number down to $1.2-1.4$ for contact tracing to make it successful in avoiding big outbreaks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13392v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongni Zhang, Tom Britton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Super-spreaders in Network Cascades</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03205v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Suppose that a cascade (e.g., an epidemic) spreads on an unknown graph, and only the infection times of vertices are observed. What can be learned about the graph from the infection times caused by multiple distinct cascades? Most of the literature on this topic focuses on the task of recovering the entire graph, which requires $\Omega ( \log n)$ cascades for an $n$-vertex bounded degree graph. Here we ask a different question: can the important parts of the graph be estimated from just a few (i.e., constant number) of cascades, even as $n$ grows large?
  In this work, we focus on identifying super-spreaders (i.e., high-degree vertices) from infection times caused by a Susceptible-Infected process on a graph. Our first main result shows that vertices of degree greater than $n^{3/4}$ can indeed be estimated from a constant number of cascades. Our algorithm for doing so leverages a novel connection between vertex degrees and the second derivative of the cumulative infection curve. Conversely, we show that estimating vertices of degree smaller than $n^{1/2}$ requires at least $\log(n) / \log \log (n)$ cascades. Surprisingly, this matches (up to $\log \log n$ factors) the number of cascades needed to learn the \emph{entire} graph if it is a tree.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03205v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elchanan Mossel, Anirudh Sridhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unique stationary boundary property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18140v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a locally compact group and $\mu$ an admissible probability measure on $G$. Let $(B,\nu)$ be the universal topological Poisson $\mu$-boundary of $(G,\mu)$ and $\Pi_s(G)$ the universal minimal strongly proximal $G$-flow. This note is inspired by a recent result of Hartman and Kalantar. We show that for a locally compact second countable group $G$ the following conditions are equivalent: (i) the measure $\nu$ is the unique $\mu$-stationary measure on $B$, (ii) $(B,G) \cong (\Pi_s(G),G)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18140v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eli Glasner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
