<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 05:00:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Refining Concentration for Gaussian Quadratic Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We visit and slightly modify the proof of Hanson-Wright inequality (HW inequality) for concentration of Gaussian quadratic chaos where we are able to tighten the bound by increasing the absolute constant in its formulation from its largest currently known value of 0.125 to at least 0.145 in the symmetric case. We also present a sharper version of the so-called Laurent-Massart inequality (LM inequality) through which we are able to increase the absolute constant in HW inequality from its largest currently available value of 0.134 due to LM inequality itself to at least 0.152 in the positive-semidefinite case. Generalizing HW inequality in the symmetric case, we derive a sequence of concentration bounds for Gaussian quadratic chaos indexed over m = 1, 2, 3,... that involves the Schatten norms of the underlying matrix. The case m = 1 reduces to HW inequality. These bounds exhibit a phase transition in behaviour in the sense that m = 1 results in the tightest bound if the deviation is smaller than a critical threshold and the bounds keep getting tighter as the index m increases when the deviation is larger than the aforementioned threshold. Finally, we derive a concentration bound that is asymptotically tighter than HW inequality both in the small and large deviation regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03774v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamyar Moshksar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLE$_{\kappa}(\rho)$ processes in the light cone regime on Liouville quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the relationship between certain SLE$_\kappa(\rho)$ processes, which are variants of the Schramm-Loewner evolution with parameter $\kappa$ in which one keeps track of an extra marked point, and Liouville quantum gravity (LQG). These processes are defined whenever $\rho &gt; -2-\kappa/2$ and in this work we will focus on the light cone regime, meaning that $\kappa \in (0,4)$ and $\max(\kappa/2-4,-2-\kappa/2) &lt; \rho &lt; -2$. Such processes are self-intersecting even though ordinary SLE$_\kappa$ curves are simple for $\kappa \in (0,4)$. We show that such a process drawn on top of an independent $\sqrt{\kappa}$-LQG surface called a weight $(\rho+4)$-quantum wedge can be represented as a gluing of a pair of trees which are described by the two coordinate functions of a correlated $\alpha$-stable L\'evy process with $\alpha = 1-2(\rho+2)/\kappa$. Combined with another work, this shows that bipolar oriented random planar maps with large faces can be identified in the scaling limit with an SLE$_\kappa(\kappa-4)$ curve on an independent $\sqrt{\kappa}$-LQG surface for $\kappa \in (4/3,2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04005v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Kavvadias, Jason Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rate estimates for total variation distance with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a Fourier-analytic method for estimating convergence rates in total variation distance in terms of various metrics related to weak convergence. Applications are provided in the areas of Malliavin calculus, normal approximation and stochastic dynamical systems with memory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04013v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miklos Rasonyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear fluctuation of interfaces in Glauber-Kawasaki dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we find a scaling limit of the space-time mass fluctuation field of Glauber + Kawasaki particle dynamics around its hydrodynamic mean curvature interface limit. Here, the Glauber rates are scaled by $K=K_N$, the Kawasaki rates by $N^2$ and space by $1/N$. We start the process so that the interface $\Gamma_t$ formed is stationary that is, $\Gamma_t$ is `flat'. When the Glauber rates are balanced on $T^d$, $\Gamma_t=\Gamma=\{x: x_1=0\}$ is immobile and the hydrodynamic limit is given by $\rho(t,v) = \rho_+$ for $v_1\in (0,1/2)$ and $\rho(t,v)= \rho_-$ for $v_1\in (-1/2,0)$ for all $t\ge 0$, where $v=(v_1,\ldots,v_d)\in T^d$ identified with $[-1/2,1/2)^d$. Since in the formation the boundary region about the interface has width $O(1/\sqrt{K_N})$, we will scale the $v_1$ coordinate in the fluctuation field by $\sqrt{K_N}$ so that the scaling limit will capture information `near' the interface.
  We identify the fluctuation limit as a Gaussian field when $K_N\uparrow \infty$ and $K_N= O(\sqrt{\log(N)})$ in $d\leq 2$. In the one dimensional case, the field limit is given by ${\bf e}(v_1) B_t$ where $B_t$ is a Brownian motion and ${\bf e}$ is the normalized derivative of a decreasing `standing wave' solution $\phi$ of $\partial^2_{v_1} \phi - V'(\phi)=0$ on $R$, where $V'$ is the homogenization of the Glauber rates. In two dimensions, the limit is ${\bf e}(v_1)Z_t(v_2)$ where $Z_t$ is the solution of a one dimensional stochastic heat equation. The appearance of the function ${\bf e}(\cdot)$ in the limit field indicates that the interface fluctuation retains the shape of the transition layer $\phi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04015v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahisa Funaki, Claudio Landim, Sunder Sethuraman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cutoff for the mixing time of the Facilitated Exclusion Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the mixing time of the Facilitated Exclusion Process (FEP) and obtain cutoff and pre-cutoff in different regimes. The main tool to obtain this result is a new bijective, deterministic mapping between the joint law of an ergodic FEP and its current through the origin, and the joint law of a SSEP and its current through the origin. This mapping is interesting in itself, as it remains valid in the non-ergodic regime where it gives a coupling between the position of a tagged particle in the FEP and the current through the origin in a SSEP with traps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04032v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brune Massouli\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rectangular Gilbert Tessellation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A random planar quadrangulation process is introduced as an approximation for certain cellular automata describing neuronal dynamics. This model turns out to be a particular (rectangular) case of a well-known Gilbert tessellation. The central and still open question is the distribution of the line segments. We derive exponential bounds for the tail of this distribution. The correlations in the model are also investigated for some instructive examples. In particular, the exponential decay of correlations is established. If the initial configuration of points is confined in a box $[0,N]^2$ it is proved that the average number of rays escaping the box has a linear order in $N$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04212v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Ewers, Tatyana Turova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximately Jumping Towards the Origin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given an initial point $x_0 \in \mathbb{R}^d$ and a sequence of vectors $v_1, v_2, \dots$ in $\mathbb{R}^d$, we define a greedy sequence by setting $x_{n} = x_{n-1} \pm v_n$ where the sign is chosen so as to minimize $\|x_n\|$. We prove that if the vectors $v_i$ are chosen uniformly at random from $\mathbb{S}^{d-1}$ then elements of the sequence are, on average, approximately at distance $\|x_n\| \sim \sqrt{\pi d/8}$ from the origin. We show that the sequence $(\|x_n\|)_{n=1}^{\infty}$ has an invariant measure $\pi_d$ depending only on $d$ and we determine its mean and study its decay for all $d$. We also investigate a completely deterministic example in $d=2$ where the $v_n$ are derived from the van der Corput sequence. Several additional examples are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04284v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Albors, Fran\c{c}ois Cl\'ement, Shosuke Kiami, Braeden Sodt, Ding Yifan, Tony Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The critical Karp--Sipser core of Erd\H{o}s--R\'enyi random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Karp--Sipser algorithm consists in removing recursively the leaves as well their unique neighbours and all isolated vertices of a given graph. The remaining graph obtained when there is no leaf left is called the Karp--Sipser core. When the underlying graph is the classical sparse Erd\H{o}s--R\'enyi random graph $ \mathrm{G}[n, \lambda/n]$, it is known to exhibit a phase transition at $\lambda = \mathrm{e}$. We show that at criticality, the Karp--Sipser core has size of order $n^{3/5}$, which proves a conjecture of Bauer and Golinelli. We provide the asymptotic law of this renormalized size as well as a description of the distribution of the core as a graph. Our approach relies on the differential equation method, and builds up on a previous work on a configuration model with bounded degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04328v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Budzinski, Alice Contat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional counting process at L\'evy times and its applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditionally, fractional counting processes, such as the fractional Poisson process, etc. have been defined using fractional differential and integral operators. Recently, Laskin (2024) introduced a generalized fractional counting process (FCP) by changing the probability mass function (pmf) of the time fractional Poisson process using the generalized three-parameter Mittag-Leffler function. Here, we study some additional properties for the FCP and introduce a time-changed fractional counting process (TCFCP), defined by time-changing the FCP with an independent L\'evy subordinator. We derive distributional properties such as the Laplace transform, probability generating function, the moments generating function, mean, and variance for the TCFCP. Some results related to waiting time distribution and the first passage time distribution are also discussed. We define the multiplicative and additive compound variants for the FCP and the TCFCP and examine their distributional characteristics with some typical examples. We explore some interesting connections of the TCFCP with Bell polynomials by introducing subordinated generalized fractional Bell polynomials. It is shown that the moments of the TCFCP can be represented in terms of the subordinated generalized fractional Bell polynomials. Finally, we present the application of the FCP in a shock deterioration model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04334v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilpa Garg, Ashok Kumar Pathak, Aditya Maheshwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Replica Symmetry of a Variant of the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Spin Glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04336v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider $N$ i.i.d. Ising spins with mean $m\in (-1,1)$ whose interactions are described by a Sherrington-Kirkpatrick Hamiltonian with a quartic correction. This model was recently introduced by Bolthausen in \cite{Bolt2} as a toy model to understand whether a second moment argument can be used to derive the replica symmetric formula in the full high temperature regime if $m\neq 0$. In \cite{Bolt2}, Bolthausen suggested that a natural analogue of the de Almeida-Thouless condition for the toy model is
  \begin{equation}\label{eq:conj} \beta^2(1-m^2)^2\leq 1. \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, \, (1)\end{equation} Here, $\beta \geq 0$ corresponds to the inverse temperature. While the second moment method implies replica symmetry for $\beta $ sufficiently small, Bolthausen showed that the method fails to prove replica symmetry in the full region described by (1). A natural question that was left open in \cite{Bolt2} is whether (1) correctly characterizes the high temperature phase of the toy model. In this note, we show that this is indeed not the case. We prove that if $|m| \geq m_*$, for some $m_* \in (0,1)$, the limiting free energy of the toy model is negative for suitable $\beta $ that satisfy (1).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04336v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Brennecke, Adrien Schertzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superdiffusive Scaling Limits for the Symmetric Exclusion Process with Slow Bonds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In \cite{fgn1}, the hydrodynamic limit in the diffusive scaling of the symmetric simple exclusion process with a finite number of slow bonds of strength $n^{-\beta}$ has been studied. Here $n$ is the scaling parameter and $\beta&gt;0$ is fixed. As shown in \cite{fgn1}, when $\beta&gt;1$, such a limit is given by the heat equation with Neumann boundary conditions. In this work, we find more non-trivial super-diffusive scaling limits for this dynamics. Assume that there are $k$ equally spaced slow bonds in the system.
  If $k$ is fixed and the time scale is $k^2n^\theta$, with $\theta\in (2,1+\beta)$, the density is asymptotically constant in each of the $k$ boxes, and equal to the initial expected mass in that box, i.e., there is no time evolution. If $k$ is fixed and the time scale is $k^2n^{1+\beta}$, then the density is also spatially constant in each box, but evolves in time according to the discrete heat equation. Finally, if the time scale is $k^2n^{1+\beta}$ and, additionally, the number of boxes $k$ increases to infinity, then the system converges to the continuous heat equation on the torus, with no boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04396v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dirk Erhard, Tertuliano Franco, Tiecheng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions of composition schemes: Mittag-Leffler and mixed Poisson distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.03751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.03751v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multitudinous probabilistic and combinatorial objects are associated with generating functions satisfying a composition scheme $F(z)=G(H(z))$. The analysis becomes challenging when this scheme is critical (i.e., $G$ and $H$ are simultaneously singular). Motivated by many examples (random mappings, planar maps, directed lattice paths), we consider a natural extension of this scheme, namely $F(z,u)=G(u H(z))M(z)$. We also consider a variant of this scheme, which allows us to analyse the number of $H$-components of a given size in $F$.
  We prove that these two models lead to a rich world of limit laws, where we identify the key role played by a new universal law introduced in this article: the three-parameter Mittag-Leffler distribution, which is essentially the product of a beta and a Mittag-Leffler distribution. We also prove (double) phase transitions, additionally involving Boltzmann and mixed Poisson distributions, bringing a unified explanation of the associated thresholds. In all cases we obtain moment convergence and local limit theorems. We end with extensions of the critical composition scheme to a cycle scheme and to the multivariate case, leading to product distributions. Applications are presented for random walks, trees (supertrees of trees, increasingly labelled trees, preferential attachment trees), triangular P\'olya urns, and the Chinese restaurant process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.03751v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/24-AAP2076</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. Appl. Probab. 34(5): 4635-4693 (October 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cyril Banderier, Markus Kuba, Michael Wallner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot-down stable processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.12290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.12290v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The shot-down process is a strong Markov process which is annihilated, or shot down, when jumping over or to the complement of a given open subset of a vector space. Due to specific features of the shot-down time, such processes suggest new type of boundary conditions for nonlocal differential equations. In this work we construct the shot-down process for the fractional Laplacian in Euclidean space. For smooth bounded sets $D$, we study its transition density and characterize Dirichlet form. We show that the corresponding Green function is comparable to that of the fractional Laplacian with Dirichlet conditions on $D$. However, for nonconvex $D$, the transition density of the shot-down stable process is incomparable with the Dirichlet heat kernel of the fractional Laplacian for $D$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.12290v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Bogdan, Kajetan Jastrz\c{e}bski, Moritz Kassmann, Micha{\l} Kijaczko, Pawe{\l} Pop{\l}awski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rough analysis of two scale systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.15781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.15781v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address a slow-fast system of coupled three dimensional Navier--Stokes equations where the fast component is perturbed by an additive Brownian noise. By means of the rough path theory, we establish the convergence in law of the slow component towards a Navier--Stokes system with an It{\^o}--Stokes drift and a rough path driven transport noise. This gives an alternative, more general and direct proof to \cite{DP22}. Notably, the limiting rough path is identified as a geometric rough path, which does not necessarily coincide with the Stratonovich lift of the Brownian motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.15781v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnaud Debussche, Martina Hofmanov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviations and Metastability Analysis for Heavy-Tailed Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03479v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces novel frameworks for large deviations and metastability analysis in heavy-tailed stochastic dynamical systems. Employing these frameworks in the context of stochastic difference equation $ X^\eta_{j+1}(x) = X^\eta_{j}(x) + \eta a\big( X^\eta_{j}(x)\big) + \eta \sigma\big( X^\eta_{j}(x)\big)Z_{j+1} $ and its variation with truncated dynamics $X^{\eta|b}_{j+1}( x) = X^{\eta|b}_{j}( x) + \varphi_b\big(\eta a\big( X^{\eta|b}_{j}( x)\big) + \eta \sigma\big( X^{\eta|b}_{j}( x)\big) Z_{j+1}\big)$, where $\varphi_b(x) = (x/\|x\|)\max\{\|x\|, b\}$, we first establish locally uniform sample-path large deviations and then translate the asymptotics into a precise characterization of the joint distribution of the first exit time and exit location. As a result, we obtain the heavy-tailed counterparts of the classical Freidlin-Wentzell theory. Our large deviations asymptotics are sharp enough to identify how rare events arise in heavy-tailed dynamical systems and characterize \emph{the catastrophe principle}. Furthermore, we unveil a discrete hierarchy of phase transitions in the asymptotics. Since truncated dynamics are often introduced by modulation mechanisms in heavy-tailed systems, these findings demonstrate that analyzing $X^\eta_{j+1}(x)$ alone is insufficient and that it is essential to study the truncated dynamics of $X^{\eta|b}_{j+1}(x)$. In particular, they enable a systematic analysis of the global dynamics of heavy-tailed stochastic processes in deep learning. We present our results in the context of discrete time processes, as these are more directly relevant to the stochastic algorithms in deep learning that motivated this work. However, the same approach applies straightforwardly to continuous-time processes, and we include the corresponding results for the L\'evy-driven SDEs in the appendix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03479v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Wang, Chang-Han Rhee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near optimal bounds for weak and strong spatial mixing for the anti-ferromagnetic Potts model on trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the anti-ferromagnetic Potts model on trees exhibits strong spatial mixing for a near-optimal range of parameters. Our work complements recent results of Chen, Liu, Mani, and Moitra [arXiv.2304.01954] who showed this to be true in the infinite temperature setting, corresponding to uniform proper colorings. We furthermore prove weak spatial mixing results complementing results in [arXiv.2304.01954].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04338v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferenc Bencs, Khallil Berrekkal, Guus Regts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A scaling limit of $\mathrm{SU}(2)$ lattice Yang-Mills-Higgs theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The construction of non-Abelian Euclidean Yang-Mills theories in dimension four, as scaling limits of lattice Yang-Mills theories or otherwise, is a central open question of mathematical physics. This paper takes the following small step towards this goal. In any dimension $d\ge 2$, we construct a scaling limit of $\mathrm{SU}(2)$ lattice Yang-Mills theory coupled to a Higgs field transforming in the fundamental representation of $\mathrm{SU}(2)$. After unitary gauge fixing and taking the lattice spacing $\varepsilon\to 0$, and simultaneously taking the gauge coupling constant $g\to 0$ and the Higgs length $\alpha\to \infty$ in such a manner that $\alpha g$ is always equal to $c\varepsilon$ for some fixed $c$ and $g= O(\varepsilon^{50d})$, a stereographic projection of the gauge field is shown to converge to a scale-invariant massive Gaussian field. This gives the first construction of a scaling limit of a non-Abelian lattice Yang-Mills theory in a dimension higher than two, as well as the first rigorous proof of mass generation by the Higgs mechanism in such a theory. Analogous results are proved for $\mathrm{U}(1)$ theory as well. The question of constructing a non-Gaussian scaling limit remains open.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10507v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Moran model with random resampling rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01333v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the two-type Moran model with $N$ individuals. Each individual is assigned a resampling rate, drawn independently from a probability distribution ${\mathbb P}$ on ${\mathbb R}_+$, and a type, either $1$ or $0$. Each individual resamples its type at its assigned rate, by adopting the type of an individual drawn uniformly at random. Let $Y^N(t)$ denote the empirical distribution of the resampling rates of the individuals with type $1$ at time $Nt$. We show that if ${\mathbb P}$ has countable support and satisfies certain tail and moment conditions, then in the limit as $N\to\infty$ the process $(Y^N(t))_{t \geq 0}$ converges in law to the process $(S(t)\,\P)_{t \geq 0}$, in the so-called Meyer-Zheng topology, where $(S(t))_{t \geq 0}$ is the Fisher-Wright diffusion with diffusion constant $D$ given by $1/D = \int_{{\mathbb R}_+} (1/r)\,{\mathbb P}(\mathrm{d} r)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01333v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siva Athreya, Frank den Hollander, Adrian R\"ollin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic analysis of Mandelbrot cascades -- in the context of vector-valued martingales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13164v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We solve a long-standing open problem of determining the Fourier dimension of the Mandelbrot canonical cascade measure (MCCM). This problem of significant interest was raised by Mandelbrot in 1976 and reiterated by Kahane in 1993. Specifically, we derive the exact formula for the Fourier dimension of the MCCM for random weights $W$ satisfying the condition $\mathbb{E}[W^t]&lt;\infty$ for all $t&gt;0$. As a corollary, we prove that the MCCM is Salem if and only if the random weight has a specific two-point distribution. In addition, we show that the MCCM is Rajchman with polynomial Fourier decay whenever the random weight satisfies $\mathbb{E}[W^{1+\delta}]&lt;\infty$ for some $\delta&gt;0$. As a consequence, we discover that, in the Biggins-Kyprianou's boundary case, the Fourier dimension of the MCCM exhibits a second order phase transition at the inverse temperature $\beta = 1/2$; we establish the upper Frostman regularity for MCCM; and we obtain a Fourier restriction estimate for MCCM.
  While the precise Fourier dimension formula seems to be a little magical in the realm of cascade theory, it turns out to be fairly natural in the context of vector-valued martingales. Indeed, the vector-valued martingales will play key roles in our new formalism of actions by multiplicative cascades on finitely additive vector measures, which is the major novelty of this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13164v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinxin Chen, Yong Han, Yanqi Qiu, Zipeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mean-field limit of diffusive games through the master equation: extreme value analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18869v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider an $N$-player game where the players control the drifts of their diffusive states which have no interaction in the noise terms. The aim of each player is to minimize the expected value of her cost, which is a function of the player's state and the empirical measure of the states of all the players. Our aim is to determine the $N \to \infty$ asymptotic behavior of the upper order statistics of the player's states under Nash equilibrium (the Nash states). For this purpose, we consider also a system of interacting diffusions which is constructed by using the Master PDE of the game and approximates the system of the Nash states, and we improve an $L^2$ estimate for the distance between the drifts of the two systems which has been used for establishing Central Limit Theorems and Large Deviations Principles for the Nash states in the past. By differentiating the Master PDE, we obtain that estimate also in $L^{\infty}$, which allows us to control the Radon-Nikodym derivative of a Girsanov transformation that connects the two systems. The latter allows us to reduce the problem to the case of $N$ uncontrolled diffusions with standard mean-field interaction in the drifts, which has been treated in a previous work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18869v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhan Bayraktar, Nikolaos Kolliopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal decay of eigenvector overlap for non-Hermitian random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the standard overlap $\mathcal{O}_{ij}: =\langle \mathbf{r}_j, \mathbf{r}_i\rangle\langle \mathbf{l}_j, \mathbf{l}_i\rangle$ of any bi-orthogonal family of left and right eigenvectors of a large random matrix $X$ with centred i.i.d. entries and we prove that it decays as an inverse second power of the distance between the corresponding eigenvalues. This extends similar results for the complex Gaussian ensemble from Bourgade and Dubach [arXiv:1801.01219], as well as Benaych-Georges and Zeitouni [arXiv:1806.06806], to any i.i.d. matrix ensemble in both symmetry classes. As a main tool, we prove a two-resolvent local law for the Hermitisation of $X$ uniformly in the spectrum with optimal decay rate and optimal dependence on the density near the spectral edge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16572v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Yuanyuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feller property and convergence for semigroups of time-changed processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19543v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a substitute to Feller property for semigroups of time-changed processes; under some conditions this leads to establish sufficient (new) conditions for the semigroups to be Feller. Moreover, given a standard process and a sequence of measures converging vaguely to a final measure, under some assumptions, we establish convergence of the sequence of the semigroups and the resolvents of the corresponding time changed-processes. Some applications are given: convergence of solutions of evolution equations and convergence of finite time distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19543v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali BenAmor, Kazuhiro Kuwae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal transport on path space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02948v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study properties of causal couplings for probability measures on the space of continuous functions. We first provide a characterization of bicausal couplings between weak solutions of stochastic differential equations. We then provide a complete description of all such bicausal Monge couplings. In particular, we show that bicausal Monge couplings of $d$-dimensional Wiener measures are induced by stochastic integrals of rotation-valued integrands. As an application, we give necessary and sufficient conditions for bicausal couplings to be induced by Monge maps and show that such bicausal Monge transports are dense in the set of bicausal couplings between laws of SDEs with regular coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02948v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rama Cont, Fang Rui Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fisher-Rao gradient flow for entropy-regularised Markov decision processes in Polish spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02951v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the global convergence of a Fisher-Rao policy gradient flow for infinite-horizon entropy-regularised Markov decision processes with Polish state and action space. The flow is a continuous-time analogue of a policy mirror descent method. We establish the global well-posedness of the gradient flow and demonstrate its exponential convergence to the optimal policy. Moreover, we prove the flow is stable with respect to gradient evaluation, offering insights into the performance of a natural policy gradient flow with log-linear policy parameterisation. To overcome challenges stemming from the lack of the convexity of the objective function and the discontinuity arising from the entropy regulariser, we leverage the performance difference lemma and the duality relationship between the gradient and mirror descent flows. Our analysis provides a theoretical foundation for developing various discrete policy gradient algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02951v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bekzhan Kerimkulov, James-Michael Leahy, David Siska, Lukasz Szpruch, Yufei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Networks for Causal Analysis in Socioecological Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Causal and counterfactual reasoning are emerging directions in data science that allow us to reason about hypothetical scenarios. This is particularly useful in fields like environmental and ecological sciences, where interventional data are usually not available. Structural causal models are probabilistic models for causal analysis that simplify this kind of reasoning due to their graphical representation. They can be regarded as extensions of the so-called Bayesian networks, a well known modeling tool commonly used in environmental and ecological problems. The main contribution of this paper is to analyze the relations of necessity and sufficiency between the variables of a socioecological system using counterfactual reasoning with Bayesian networks. In particular, we consider a case study involving socioeconomic factors and land-uses in southern Spain. In addition, this paper aims to be a coherent overview of the fundamental concepts for applying counterfactual reasoning, so that environmental researchers with a background in Bayesian networks can easily take advantage of the structural causal model formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10101v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Caba\~nas, Ana D. Maldonado, Mar\'ia Morales, Pedro A. Aguilera, Antonio Salmer\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence properties of Markov models for image generation with applications to spin-flip dynamics and to diffusion processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10255v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the field of Markov models for image generation, the main idea is to learn how non-trivial images are gradually destroyed by a trivial forward Markov dynamics over the large time window $[0,t]$ converging towards pure noise for $t \to + \infty$, and to implement the non-trivial backward time-dependent Markov dynamics over the same time window $[0,t]$ starting from pure noise at $t$ in order to generate new images at time $0$. The goal of the present paper is to analyze the convergence properties of this reconstructive backward dynamics as a function of the time $t$ using the spectral properties of the trivial continuous-time forward dynamics for the $N$ pixels $n=1,..,N$. The general framework is applied to two cases : (i) when each pixel $n$ has only two states $S_n=\pm 1$ with Markov jumps between them; (ii) when each pixel $n$ is characterized by a continuous variable $x_n$ that diffuses on an interval $]x_-,x_+[$ that can be either finite or infinite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10255v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cecile Monthus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit Theorems for Stochastic Gradient Descent with Infinite Variance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16340v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Stochastic gradient descent is a classic algorithm that has gained great popularity especially in the last decades as the most common approach for training models in machine learning. While the algorithm has been well-studied when stochastic gradients are assumed to have a finite variance, there is significantly less research addressing its theoretical properties in the case of infinite variance gradients. In this paper, we establish the asymptotic behavior of stochastic gradient descent in the context of infinite variance stochastic gradients, assuming that the stochastic gradient is regular varying with index $\alpha\in(1,2)$. The closest result in this context was established in 1969 , in the one-dimensional case and assuming that stochastic gradients belong to a more restrictive class of distributions. We extend it to the multidimensional case, covering a broader class of infinite variance distributions. As we show, the asymptotic distribution of the stochastic gradient descent algorithm can be characterized as the stationary distribution of a suitably defined Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process driven by an appropriate stable L\'evy process. Additionally, we explore the applications of these results in linear regression and logistic regression models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16340v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Blanchet, Aleksandar Mijatovi\'c, Wenhao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Impossibility of Equating the Youden Index with Tjur's $R^2$-like metrics in $2\times2$ Tables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05391v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 2017, Hughes claimed an equivalence between Tjurs $R^2$ coefficient of discrimination and the Youden index for assessing diagnostic test performance on $2\times 2$ contingency tables. We prove an impossibility result when averaging over binary outcomes (0s and 1s) under any continuous real-valued scoring rule. Our finding clarifies the limitations of such a possible equivalence and highlights the distinct roles these metrics play in diagnostic test assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05391v2</guid>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linard Hoessly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the thresholds of degenerate hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18596v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An $n$-vertex $k$-uniform hypergraph $G$ is $(d,\alpha)$-degenerate if $m_1(G)\le{d}$ and there exists a constant $\varepsilon &gt;0$ such that for every subset $U\subseteq{V(G)}$ with size $2\le|U|\le{\varepsilon n}$, we have $e\left(G[U]\right)\le{d\left(|U|-1\right)-\alpha}$. These hypergraphs include many natural graph classes, such as the degenerate hypergraphs, the planar graphs, and the power of cycles. In this paper, we consider the threshold of the emergence of a $(d,\alpha)$-degenerate hypergraph with bounded maximum degree in the Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi model. We show that its threshold is at most $n^{-1/d}$, improving previous results of Riordan and Kelly-M\"uyesser-Pokrovskiy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18596v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Chen, Jie Han, Haoran Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
