<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 04:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Random Walk in Random Environment: A short introduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a report of a scientific project carried out at Ecole Centrale Casablanca in 2019. This work is an entry into the world of Random Walk in a Random Environment (RWRE). We will discuss some intuitive concepts such as recurrence, location, and random potential. We will thereafter focus on providing an "electrical" understanding of this type of walk and finally explore an application of RWRE to graphene conduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04758v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mouad El Bouchattaoui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Time Explosion of Stochastic Differential Equations: A survey into Khasminskii's Lyapunov Method and its Consistency with the Osgood Criterion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solutions of Stochastic Differential Equations can have three types of explosive behaviors: almost-sure non-explosive, explosion with positive probability, and almost sure explosion. In this paper, we will provide a survey of Khasminskii's Lyapunov method for classifying explosive behaviors of solutions of stochastic differential equations. We will embark our expedition by examining the renowned Feller's test for explosion and observing its shortfalls. Afterwards, we will present Khasminskii's Lyapunov method for almost-sure non-explosion, explosion with positive probability, and almost-sure explosion. Ample examples will be provided to illuminate the power of Khasminskii's Lyapunov methods. Furthermore, quick layovers will be made to extend Khasminskii's Lyapunov method for almost-sure non-explosion and explosion with positive probability for jump processes with constant Poisson intensities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04834v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seungsoo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharpening the gap between $L^{1}$ and $L^{2}$ norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We refine the classical Cauchy--Schwartz inequality $\|X\|_{1} \leq \|X\|_{2}$ by demonstrating that for any $p$ and $q$ with $q&gt;p&gt;2$, there exists a constant $C=C(p,q)$ such that $\|X\|_1 \leq 1 - C \Big{(}\|X\|_p^p - 1\Big{)}^{\frac{q-2}{q-p}}\Big{(}\|X\|_q^q - 1\Big{)}^{\frac{2-p}{q-p}}$ holds true for all Borel measurable random variables $X$ with $\|X\|_{2}=1$ and $\|X\|_{p}&lt;\infty$. We illustrate two applications of this result: one for biased Rademacher sums and another for exponential sums.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04835v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paata Ivanisvili, Yonathan Stone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curie--Weiss Model under $\ell^{p}$ constraint and a Generalized Hubbard--Stratonovich Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Ising Curie--Weiss model on the complete graph constrained under a given $\ell_{p}$ norm for some $p&gt;0$. For $p=\infty$, it reduces to the classical Ising Curie--Weiss model. We prove that for all $p&gt;2$, there exists $\beta_{c}(p):=\frac{3}{p^{2/p}}\cdot\tfrac{\Gamma(1+1/p)}{\Gamma(1+3/p)}$ such that for $\beta&lt;\beta_{c}(p)$, the magnetization is concentrated at zero and satisfies an appropriate Gaussian CLT; whereas for $\beta&gt;\beta_{c}(p)$ the magnetization is not concentrated at zero similar to the classical case. Though $\beta_{c}(2)=1$, we have $\beta_{c}(p)&gt;1$ for $p&gt;2$ and $\lim_{p\to\infty}\beta_{c}(p)=3$. We further generalize the model for general symmetric spin distributions and prove a similar phase transition. For $0&lt;p&lt;1$, the log-partition function scales at the order of $n^{2/p-1}$. The proofs are mainly based on the generalized Hubbard--Stratonovich (GHS) transform, which is of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04875v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha S. Dey, Daesung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The averaging principle of stochastic functional partial differential equations with H\"older coefficients and infinite delay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the averaging principle for stochastic functional partial differential equations (SFPDEs) characterized by H\"older coefficients and infinite delay. Firstly, we rigorously establish the existence and uniqueness of strong solutions for a specific class of finite-dimensional systems characterized by H\"older continuous coefficients and infinite delay. We extend these results to their infinite-dimensional counterparts using the variational approach and Galerkin projection technique. Subsequently, we establish the averaging principle (the first Bogolyubov theorem) for SFPDEs with infinite delay, subject to conditions of linear growth and H\"older continuity. This is achieved through classical Khasminskii time discretization and reductio ad absurdum, illustrating the convergence of solutions from the original Cauchy problem to those of the averaged equation across the finite interval [0, T]. To illustrate our findings, we present two applications: stochastic generalized porous media equations and stochastic reaction-diffusion equations with H\"older coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04909v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaishuai Lu, Xue Yang, Yong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path-dependent processes from signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide explicit series expansions to certain stochastic path-dependent integral equations in terms of the path signature of the time augmented driving Brownian motion. Our framework encompasses a large class of stochastic linear Volterra and delay equations and in particular the fractional Brownian motion with a Hurst index $H \in (0, 1)$. Our expressions allow to disentangle an infinite dimensional Markovian structure and open the door to straightforward and simple approximation schemes, that we illustrate numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04956v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Abi Jaber, Louis-Amand G\'erard, Yuxing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness for the Skorokhod problem in an orthant: critical cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the Skorokhod problem in the closed non-negative orthant: find a solution $(g(t),m(t))$ to \[ g(t)= f(t)+ Rm(t),\] where $f$ is a given continuous vector-valued function with $f(0)$ in the orthant, $R$ is a given $d\times d$ matrix with 1's along the diagonal, $g$ takes values in the orthant, and $m$ is a vector-valued function that starts at 0, each component of $m$ is non-decreasing and continuous, and for each $i$ the $i^{th}$ coordinate of $m$ increases only when the $i^{th}$ coordinate of $g$ is 0. The stochastic version of the Skorokhod problem replaces $f$ by the paths of Brownian motion. It is known that there exists a unique solution to the Skorokhod problem if the spectral radius of $|Q|$ is less than 1, where $Q=I-R$ and $|Q|$ is the matrix whose entries are the absolute values of the corresponding entries of $Q$. The first result of this paper shows pathwise uniqueness for the stochastic version of the Skorokhod problem holds if the spectral radius of $|Q|$ is equal to 1. The second result of this paper settles the remaining open cases for uniqueness for the deterministic version when the dimension $d$ is two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05140v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard F. Bass, Krzysztof Burdzy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending the noise of splitting to its completion and stability of Brownian maxima</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The stochastic noise of splitting, defined initially on the (basic) algebra of unions of intervals, is extended to a maximal class of domains. The $\sigma$-fields of this largest extension constitute the completion, in the sense of noise-type Boolean algebras, of the range of the unextended (basic) splitting noise. A Lebesgue measurable domain to which the extension is possible is characterized by a certain stability property: under independent perturbation of Brownian increments off the domain, of the times of Brownian local maxima belonging to the domain; together with the same property for the complement of the domain. A set that is equal to an open set modulo a Lebesgue negligible one, with the same being true of its complement, has this stability property, but others have it too: the extension is non-trivial. Some domains are totally unstable with respect to the indicated perturbation, and to them the extension cannot be made.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05144v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matija Vidmar, Jon Warren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multiple birth properties of multi-type Markov branching processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main purpose of this paper is to consider the multiple birth properties for multi-type Markov branching processes. We first construct a new multi-dimensional Markov process based on the multi-type Markov branching process, which can reveal the multiple birth characteristics. Then the joint probability distribution of multiple birth of multi-type Markov branching process until any time $t$ is obtained by using the new process. Furthermore, the probability distribution of multiple birth until the extinction of the process is also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05252v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junping Li, Wanting Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry-Ess\'een bound for complex Wiener-It\^{o} integral</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For complex multiple Wiener-It\^{o} integral, we present Berry-Ess\'een upper and lower bounds in terms of moments and kernel contractions under the Wasserstein distance. As a corollary, we simplify the previously known contraction condition of the complex Fourth Moment Theorem. Additionally, as an application, we explore the optimal Berry-Ess\'een bound for a statistic associated with the complex-valued Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05353v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiping Chen, Yong Chen, Yong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of (sub)critical non-local spatial branching processes with and without immigration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the setting of either a general non-local branching particle process or a general non-local superprocess, in both cases, with and without immigration. Under the assumption that the mean semigroup has a Perron-Frobenious type behaviour for the immigrated mass, as well as the existence of second moments, we consider necessary and sufficient conditions that ensure limiting distributional stability. More precisely, our first main contribution pertains to proving the asymptotic Kolmogorov survival probability and Yaglom limit for critical non-local branching particle systems and superprocesses under a second moment assumption on the offspring distribution. Our results improve on existing literature by removing the requirement of bounded offspring in the particle setting [21] and generalising [43] to allow for non-local branching mechanisms. Our second main contribution pertains to the stability of both critical and sub-critical non-local branching particle systems and superprocesses with immigration. At criticality, we show that the scaled process converges to a Gamma distribution under a necessary and sufficient integral test. At subcriticality we show stability of the process, also subject to an integral test. In these cases, our results complement classical results for (continuous-time) Galton-Watson processes with immigration and continuous-state branching processes with immigration; see [22,40,42,48,51], among others. In the setting of superprocesses, the only work we know of at this level of generality is summarised in [34]. The proofs of our results, both with and without immigration, appeal to similar technical approaches and accordingly, we include the results together in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05472v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Horton, Andreas E. Kyprianou, Pedro Mart\'in-Ch\'avez, Ellen Powell, Victor Rivero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact convergence rates to derivatives of local time for some self-similar Gaussian processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, for some $d-$dimensional Gaussian processes
  \[X=\big\{X_t=(X^1_t,\cdots,X^d_t):t\ge0\big\},\]
  whose components are i.i.d. $1-$dimensional self-similar Gaussian process with Hurst index $H\in(0,1)$, we consider the asymptotic behavior of approximation of its $\boldsymbol{k}-$th derivatives of local time under certain mild conditions, where
  $\boldsymbol{k}=(k_1,\cdots,k_d)$ and $k_\ell$'s are non-negative real numbers. We will give a derivative version of the limit theorems for functional of Gaussian processes and use this result to get the asymptotic behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05514v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minhao Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brownian Motion in the $p$-Adic Integers is a Limit of Discrete Time Random Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05561v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vladimirov defined an operator on balls in $\mathbb Q_p$, the $p$-adic numbers, that is analogous to the Laplace operator in the real setting. Kochubei later provided a probabilistic interpretation of the operator. This Vladimirov-Kochubei operator generates a real-time diffusion process in the ring of $p$-adic integers, a Brownian motion in $\mathbb Z_p$. The current work shows that this process is a limit of discrete time random walks. It motivates the construction of the Vladimirov-Kochubei operator, provides further intuition about the properties of ultrametric diffusion, and gives an example of the weak convergence of stochastic processes in a profinite group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05561v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Pierce, David Weisbart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Large Deviations for the Number of Descents and the Major Index in a Random Permutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to improve the large deviation principle for the number of descents in a random permutation by establishing a sharp large deviation principle of any order. We shall also prove a sharp large deviation principle of any order for the major index in a random permutation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05708v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Bercu (IMB), Michel Bonnefont (IMB), Luis Fredes (IMB), Adrien Richou (IMB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selection principle for the $N$-BBM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $N$-branching Brownian motion with selection ($N$-BBM) is a particle system consisting of $N$ independent particles that diffuse as Brownian motions in $\mathbb{R}$, branch at rate one, and whose size is kept constant by removing the leftmost particle at each branching event. We establish the following selection principle: as $N \rightarrow \infty$ the stationary empirical measure of the $N$-particle system converges to the minimal travelling wave of the associated free boundary PDE. This resolves an open question going back at least to \cite[p.19]{Maillard2012} and \cite{GroismanJonckheer}, and follows a recent related result by the second author establishing a similar selection principle for the so-called Fleming-Viot particle system \cite{Tough23}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05792v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Berestycki, Oliver Tough</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability graphons: the right convergence point of view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the theory of probability graphons, continuum representations of edge-decorated graphs arising in graph limits theory, to the 'right convergence' point of view. First of all, we generalise the notions of overlay functionals and quotient sets to the case of probability graphons. Furthermore, we characterise the convergence of probability graphons in terms of these global quantities. In particular, we show the equivalence of these two notions of convergence with the unlabelled cut-metric convergence (and thus also with the homomorphism densities convergence and the subgraph sampling convergence). In other words, we prove the equivalence of the 'left convergence' and the 'right convergence' views on probability graphons convergence, generalising the corresponding result for (real-valued) graphons (the classical continuum representation for simple graphs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05998v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Zucal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loewner traces driven by Levy processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Loewner chains with Levy drivers have been proposed in the physics literature as models related to random dendritic growth in off-critical systems (and even for diffusion-limited aggregation), and in mathematics as candidates for finding extremal multifractal spectra (towards Brennan's conjecture and related problems in classical function theory). These processes are not scale-invariant in general, but they do enjoy a natural domain Markov property thanks to the stationary independent increments of Levy processes. The associated Loewner hulls feature remarkably intricate topological properties and possibly complicated multifractal phenomena, of which very little is known rigorously.
  We prove that a chordal Loewner chain driven by a Levy process $W$ satisfying mild regularity conditions (including stable processes) is a.s. generated by a cadlag curve. Specifically, if the diffusivity parameter of the driving process $W$ is $\kappa \in [0,8)$, then the jump measure of $W$ is required to be locally (upper) Ahlfors regular near the origin, while if $\kappa &gt; 8$, no constraints are imposed. In particular, we show that the associated Loewner hulls are a.s. locally connected and path-connected. We also show that, the complements of the hulls are a.s. Holder domains when $\kappa \neq 4$ (which is not expected to hold when $\kappa=4$), without any regularity assumptions. The proofs of these results mainly rely on careful derivative estimates for both the forward and backward Loewner maps obtained using delicate but robust enough supermartingale domination arguments. As one cannot control the jump accumulation of general Levy processes, we must circumvent all reasoning that would use continuity. To prove the local connectedness, we use an extension of part of the Hahn-Mazurkiewicz theorem: hulls generated by cadlag curves are locally connected even when jumps would occur at infinite intensity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06144v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eveliina Peltola, Anne Schreuder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Multivariate Generalized Counting Process and its Time-Changed Variants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a multivariate version of the generalized counting process (GCP) and discuss its various time-changed variants. The time is changed using random processes such as the stable subordinator, inverse stable subordinator, and their composition, tempered stable subordinator, gamma subordinator etc. Several distributional properties that includes the probability generating function, probability mass function and their governing differential equations are obtained for these variants. It is shown that some of these time-changed processes are L\'evy and for such processes we have derived the associated L\'evy measure. The explicit expressions for the covariance and codifference of the component processes for some of these time-changed variants are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06156v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. K. Kataria, M. Dhillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit theorems for the neutron transport equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04820v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Over the last decade, ingenuous developments in Monte Carlo methods have enabled the unbiased estimation of adjoint-weighted reactor parameters expressed as bilinear forms, such as kinetics parameters and sensitivity coefficients. A prominent example is the Iterated Fission Probability method, which relies on the simulation of the fission chains descending from an ancestor neutron: the neutron population at an asymptotic fission generation yields an estimate of the importance function (and hence of the adjoint fundamental eigenmode) at the phase-space coordinates of the ancestor neutron. In this paper we first establish rigorous results concerning the moments of the asymptotic neutron population stemming from a single initial particle, with special focus on the average and the variance. Then, we propose a simple benchmark configuration where exact solutions are derived for these moments, which can be used for the verification of new functionalities of production Monte Carlo codes involving the Iterated Fission Probability method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04820v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Dumonteil, Emma Horton, Andreas E. Kyprianou, Andrea Zola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kullback-Leibler Barycentre of Stochastic Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04860v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem where an agent aims to combine the views and insights of different experts' models. Specifically, each expert proposes a diffusion process over a finite time horizon. The agent then combines the experts' models by minimising the weighted Kullback-Leibler divergence to each of the experts' models. We show existence and uniqueness of the barycentre model and proof an explicit representation of the Radon-Nikodym derivative relative to the average drift model. We further allow the agent to include their own constraints, which results in an optimal model that can be seen as a distortion of the experts' barycentre model to incorporate the agent's constraints.
  Two deep learning algorithms are proposed to find the optimal drift of the combined model, allowing for efficient simulations. The first algorithm aims at learning the optimal drift by matching the change of measure, whereas the second algorithm leverages the notion of elicitability to directly estimate the value function. The paper concludes with a extended application to combine implied volatility smiles models that were estimated on different datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04860v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Jaimungal, Silvana M. Pesenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Perfect Samplers for Incremental Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04931v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If $G : \mathbb{R}_+ \to \mathbb{R}_+$, the $G$-moment of a vector $\mathbf{x}\in\mathbb{R}_+^n$ is $G(\mathbf{x}) = \sum_{v\in[n]} G(\mathbf{x}(v))$ and the $G$-sampling problem is to select an index $v_*\in [n]$ according to its contribution to the $G$-moment, i.e., such that $\Pr(v_*=v) = G(\mathbf{x}(v))/G(\mathbf{x})$. Approximate $G$-samplers may introduce multiplicative and/or additive errors to this probability, and some have a non-trivial probability of failure.
  In this paper we focus on the exact $G$-sampling problem, where $G$ is selected from the class $\mathcal{G}$ of Laplace exponents of non-negative, one-dimensional L\'evy processes, which includes several well studied classes such as $p$th moments $G(z)=z^p$, $p\in[0,1]$, logarithms $G(z)=\log(1+z)$, Cohen and Geri's soft concave sublinear functions, which are used to approximate concave sublinear functions, including cap statistics. We develop $G$-samplers for a vector $\mathbf{x} \in \mathbb{R}_+^n$ that is presented as an incremental stream of positive updates. In particular:
  * For any $G\in\mathcal{G}$, we give a very simple $G$-sampler that uses 2 words of memory and stores at all times a $v_*\in [n]$, such that $\Pr(v_*=v)$ is exactly $G(\mathbf{x}(v))/G(\mathbf{x})$.
  * We give a ``universal'' $\mathcal{G}$-sampler that uses $O(\log n)$ words of memory w.h.p., and given any $G\in \mathcal{G}$ at query time, produces an exact $G$-sample.
  With an overhead of a factor of $k$, both samplers can be used to $G$-sample a sequence of $k$ indices with or without replacement. Our sampling framework is simple and versatile, and can easily be generalized to sampling from more complex objects like graphs and hypergraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04931v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seth Pettie, Dingyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface waves in randomly perturbed discrete models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the propagation of surface waves across structured surfaces with random, localized inhomogeneities. A discrete analogue of Gurtin-Murdoch model is employed and surface elasticity, in contrast to bulk elasticity, is captured by distinct point masses and elastic constants for nearest-neighbour interactions parallel to the surface. Expressions for the surface wave reflectance and transmittance, as well as the radiative loss, are provided for every localized patch of point mass perturbation on the surface. As the main result in the article, we provide the statistics of surface wave reflectance and transmittance and the radiative loss for an ensemble of random mass perturbations, independent and identically distributed with mean zero, on the surface. In the weakly scattering regime, the mean radiative loss is found to be proportional to the size of the perturbed patch, to the variance of the mass perturbations, and to an effective parameter that depends on the continuous spectrum of the unperturbed system. In the strongly scattering regime, the mean radiative loss is found to depend on another effective parameter that depends on the continuous spectrum, but not on the variance of the mass perturbations. Numerical simulations are found in quantitative agreement with the theoretical predictions for several illustrative values of the surface structure parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05056v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josselin Garnier, Basant Lal Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What's the Best Seat in the Game Left, Center, Right?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05069v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Left, Center, Right is a popular dice game. We analyze the game using Markov chain and Monte Carlo methods. We compute the expected game length for two to eight players and determine the probability of winning for each player in the game. We discuss the surprising conclusions of which players have the highest and lowest chance of winning, and we propose a small rule change that makes the game a little more fair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05069v1</guid>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Richeson, David Richeson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subleading correction to the Asian options volatility in the Black-Scholes model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05142v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The short maturity limit $T\to 0$ for the implied volatility of an Asian option in the Black-Scholes model is determined by the large deviations property for the time-average of the geometric Brownian motion. In this note we derive the subleading $O(T)$ correction to this implied volatility, using an asymptotic expansion for the Hartman-Watson distribution. The result is used to compute subleading corrections to Asian options prices in a small maturity expansion, sharpening the leading order result obtained using large deviations theory. We demonstrate good numerical agreement with precise benchmarks for Asian options pricing in the Black-Scholes model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05142v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S021902492350005X</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IJTAF vol 26, no. 2-3, 2350005, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dan Pirjol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended mean-field control problems with Poissonian common noise: Stochastic maximum principle and Hamiltonian-Jacobi-Bellman equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the extended mean-field control problems with state-control joint law dependence and Poissonian common noise. We develop the stochastic maximum principle (SMP) and establish the connection to the Hamiltonian-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equation on the Wasserstein space. The presence of the conditional joint law in the McKean-Vlasov dynamics and its discontinuity caused by the Poissonian common noise bring us new technical challenges. To develop the SMP when the control domain is not necessarily convex, we first consider a strong relaxed control formulation that allows us to perform the first-order variation. We also propose the technique of extension transformation to overcome the compatibility issues arising from the joint law in the relaxed control formulation. By further establishing the equivalence between the relaxed control formulation and the strict control formulation, we obtain the SMP for the original problem in the strict control formulation. In the part to investigate the HJB equation, we formulate an auxiliary control problem subjecting to a controlled measure-valued dynamics with Poisson jumps, which allows us to derive the HJB equation of the original problem through an equivalence argument. We also show the connection between the SMP and HJB equation and give an illustrative example of linear quadratic extended mean-field control with Poissonian common noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05356v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lijun Bo, Jingfei Wang, Xiaoli Wei, Xiang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudorandomness of primes at large scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Assuming a variant of the Hardy--Littlewood prime $k$-tuple conjecture, we compute mixed moments of the number of primes in disjoint short intervals and short progressions respectively. This involves estimating the mean of singular series over any product of lattices, which is of independent interest. As a consequence, we establish the convergence of both sequences of suitably normalized primes to a standard Poisson point process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05380v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sun-Kai Leung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basins of Attraction in Two-Player Random Ordinal Potential Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the class of two-person ordinal potential games where each player has the same number of actions $K$. Each game in this class admits at least one pure Nash equilibrium and the best-response dynamics converges to one of these pure Nash equilibria; which one depends on the starting point. So, each pure Nash equilibrium has a basin of attraction.
  We pick uniformly at random one game from this class and we study the joint distribution of the sizes of the basins of attraction. We provide an asymptotic exact value for the expected basin of attraction of each pure Nash equilibrium, when the number of actions $K$ goes to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05460v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Collevecchio, Hlafo Alfie Mimun, Matteo Quattropani, Marco Scarsini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Installation of renewable capacities to meet emission targets and demand under uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper focuses on minimizing the costs related to renewable energy installations under emission constraints. We tackle the problem in three different cases. Assuming intervening once, we determine the optimal time to install and the optimal capacity expansions under uncertainty. By assuming the possibility of two or multiple interventions, we find that the optimal strategy is to intervene only once. We also prove that there are instances where capacity expansions should be delayed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05774v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nacira Agram, Fred Espen Benth, Giulia Pucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of Zamolodchikov conjecture for semi-classical conformal blocks on torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1986, Zamolodchikov conjectured an exponential structure for the semi-classical limit of conformal blocks on a sphere. This paper provides a rigorous proof of the analog of Zamolodchikov conjecture for Liouville conformal blocks on a one-punctured torus, using their probabilistic construction and show the existence of a positive radius of convergence of the semi-classical limit. As a consequence, we obtain a closed form expression for the solution of the Lam\'e equation, and show a relation between its accessory parameter and the classical action of the non-autonomous elliptic Calogero-Moser model evaluated at specific values of the solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05839v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harini Desiraju, Promit Ghosal, Andrei Prokhorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volatility modeling in a Markovian environment: Two Ornstein-Uhlenbeck-related approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce generalizations of the COGARCH model of Kl\"uppelberg et al. from 2004 and the volatility and price model of Barndorff-Nielsen and Shephard from 2001 to a Markov-switching environment. These generalizations allow for exogeneous jumps of the volatility at times of a regime switch. Both models are studied within the framework of Markov-modulated generalized Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes which allows to derive conditions for stationarity, formulas for moments, as well as the autocovariance structure of volatility and price process. It turns out that both models inherit various properties of the original models and therefore are able to capture basic stylized facts of financial time-series such as uncorrelated log-returns, correlated squared log-returns and non-existence of higher moments in the COGARCH case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05866v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anita Behme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Bellman equations for continuous-time policy evaluation I: discretization and approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05966v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of computing the value function from a discretely-observed trajectory of a continuous-time diffusion process. We develop a new class of algorithms based on easily implementable numerical schemes that are compatible with discrete-time reinforcement learning (RL) with function approximation. We establish high-order numerical accuracy as well as the approximation error guarantees for the proposed approach. In contrast to discrete-time RL problems where the approximation factor depends on the effective horizon, we obtain a bounded approximation factor using the underlying elliptic structures, even if the effective horizon diverges to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05966v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenlong Mou, Yuhua Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition in one-dimensional excitable media with variable interaction range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1701.00319</link>
      <description>arXiv:1701.00319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate two discrete models of excitable media on a one-dimensional integer lattice $\mathbb{Z}$: the $\kappa$-color Cyclic Cellular Automaton (CCA) and the $\kappa$-color Firefly Cellular Automaton (FCA). In both models, sites are assigned uniformly random colors from $\mathbb{Z}/\kappa\mathbb{Z}$. Neighboring sites with colors within a specified interaction range $r$ tend to synchronize their colors upon a particular local event of 'excitation'. We establish that there are three phases of CCA/FCA on $\mathbb{Z}$ as we vary the interaction range $r$. First, if $r$ is too small (undercoupled), there are too many non-interacting pairs of colors, and the whole graph $\mathbb{Z}$ will be partitioned into non-interacting intervals of sites with no excitation within each interval. If $r$ is within a sweet spot (critical), then we show the system clusters into ever-growing monochromatic intervals. For the critical interaction range $r=\lfloor \kappa/2 \rfloor$, we show the density of edges of differing colors at time $t$ is $\Theta(t^{-1/2})$ and each site excites $\Theta(t^{1/2})$ times up to time $t$. Lastly, if $r$ is too large (overcoupled), then neighboring sites can excite each other and such 'defects' will generate waves of excitation at a constant rate so that each site will get excited at least at a linear rate. For the special case of FCA with $r=\lfloor 2/\kappa \rfloor+1$, we show that every site will become $(\kappa+1)$-periodic eventually.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1701.00319v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ander Aguirre, Hanbaek Lyu, David Sivakoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Laplace transform of the integrated Volterra Wishart process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.07719</link>
      <description>arXiv:1911.07719v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish an explicit expression for the conditional Laplace transform of the integrated Volterra Wishart process in terms of a certain resolvent of the covariance function. The core ingredient is the derivation of the conditional Laplace transform of general Gaussian processes in terms of Fredholm's determinant and resolvent. Furthermore , we link the characteristic exponents to a system of non-standard infinite dimensional matrix Riccati equations. This leads to a second representation of the Laplace transform for a special case of convolution kernel. In practice, we show that both representations can be approximated by either closed form solutions of conventional Wishart distributions or finite dimensional matrix Riccati equations stemming from conventional linear-quadratic models. This allows fast pricing in a variety of highly flexible models, ranging from bond pricing in quadratic short rate models with rich autocorrelation structures, long range dependence and possible default risk, to pricing basket options with covariance risk in multivariate rough volatility models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1911.07719v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1111/mafi.12334</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mathematical Finance, 2022, 32 (1), pp.309-348</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Abi Jaber (CES, UP1 UFR27)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremal Invariant Distributions of Infinite Brownian Particle Systems with Rank Dependent Drifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.08331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.08331v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: \noindent Consider an infinite collection of particles on the real line moving according to independent Brownian motions and such that the $i$-th particle from the left gets the drift $g_{i-1}$. The case where $g_0=1$ and $g_{i}=0$ for all $i \in \mathbb{N}$ corresponds to the well studied infinite Atlas model. Under conditions on the drift vector $\boldsymbol{g} = (g_0, g_1, \ldots)'$ it is known that the Markov process corresponding to the gap sequence of the associated ranked particles has a continuum of product form stationary distributions $\{\pi_a^{\boldsymbol{g}}, a \in S^{\boldsymbol{g}}\}$ where $S^{\boldsymbol{g}}$ is a semi-infinite interval of the real line. In this work we show that all of these stationary distributions are extremal and ergodic. We also prove that any product form stationary distribution of this Markov process that satisfies a mild integrability condition must be $\pi_a^{\boldsymbol{g}}$ for some $a \in S^{\boldsymbol{g}}$. These results are new even for the infinite Atlas model. The work makes progress on the open problem of characterizing all the invariant distributions of general competing Brownian particle systems interacting through their relative ranks. Proofs rely on synchronous and mirror coupling of Brownian particles and properties of the intersection local times of the various particles in the infinite system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.08331v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Banerjee, Amarjit Budhiraja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Critical Beta-splitting Random Tree II: Overview and Open Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.02529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.02529v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the critical beta-splitting model of a random $n$-leaf rooted tree, clades are recursively (from the root) split into sub-clades, and a clade of $m$ leaves is split into sub-clades containing $i$ and $m-i$ leaves with probabilities $\propto 1/(i(m-i))$. Study of structure theory and explicit quantitative aspects of the model is an active research topic, and this article provides an extensive overview what is currently known. For many results there are different proofs, probabilistic or analytic, so the model provides a testbed for a ``compare and contrast" discussion of techniques. We give some proofs that are not currently available elsewhere, and also give heuristics for some proven results and for some open problems. Our discussion is centered around three ``foundational" results.
  (i) There is a canonical embedding into a continuous-time model, that is a random tree $\mbox{CTCS}(n)$ on $n$ leaves with real-valued edge lengths, and this model turns out more convenient to study. The family $(\mbox{CTCS}(n), n \ge 2)$ is consistent under a ``delete random leaf and prune" operation. That leads to an explicit inductive construction of $(\mbox{CTCS}(n), n \ge 2)$ as $n$ increases, and then to a limit structure $\mbox{CTCS}(\infty)$ formalized via exchangeable partitions, in some ways analogous to the Brownian continuum random tree.
  (ii) There is a CLT for leaf heights, and the analytic proof can be extended to provide surprisingly precise analysis of other height-related aspects.
  (iii) There is an explicit description of the limit {\em fringe distribution} relative to a random leaf, whose graphical representation is essentially the format of the cladogram representation of biological phylogenies.
  Many open problems remain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.02529v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David J. Aldous, Svante Janson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of population processes with small and frequent mutations to the canonical equation of adaptive dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.09936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.09936v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, a stochastic individual-based model describing Darwinian evolution of asexual, phenotypic trait-structured population, is studied. We consider a large population with constant population size characterised by a resampling rate modeling competition pressure driving selection and a mutation rate where mutations occur during life. In this model, the population state at fixed time is given as a measure on the space of phenotypes and the evolution of the population is described by a continuous time, measure-valued Markov process. We investigate the asymptotic behavior of the system, where mutations are frequent, in the double simultaneous limit of large population $(K \to +\infty)$ and small mutational effects $(\sigma_{K} \to 0)$ proving convergence to an ODE known as the canonical equation of adaptive dynamics. This result holds only for a certain range of $\sigma_{K}$ parameters (as a function of $K$) which must be small enough but not too small either. The canonical equation describes the evolution in time of the dominant trait in the population driven by a fitness gradient. This result is based on an slow-fast asymptotic analysis. We use an averaging method, inspired by (Kurtz, 1992), which exploits a martingale approach and compactness-uniqueness arguments. The contribution of the fast component, which converges to the centered Fleming-Viot process, is obtained by averaging according to its invariant measure, recently characterised in (Champagnat-Hass, 2022).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.09936v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Champagnat, Vincent Hass</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$1/f$ noise in semiconductors arising from the heterogeneous detrapping process of individual charge carriers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07009v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a model of $1/f$ noise in semiconductors based on the drift of individual charge carriers and their interaction with the trapping centers. We assume that the trapping centers are homogeneously distributed in the material. The trapping centers are assumed to be heterogeneous and have unique detrapping rates. We show that uniform detrapping rate distribution emerges as a natural consequence of the vacant trap depths following the Boltzmann distribution, and the detrapping process obeying Arrhenius law. When these laws apply, and if the trapping rate is low in comparison to the maximum detrapping rate, $1/f$ noise in the form of Hooge's relation is recovered. Hooge's parameter, $\alpha_{H}$, is shown to be a ratio between the characteristic trapping rate and the maximum detrapping rate. The proposed model implies that $1/f$ noise arises from the temporal charge carrier number fluctuations, not from the spatial mobility fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07009v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksejus Kononovicius, Bronislovas Kaulakys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition of singular Gibbs measures for three-dimensional Schr\"odinger-wave system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.17013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.17013v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study singular Gibbs measures for the three-dimensional Schr\"odinger-wave system, also known as the Yukawa system. Our primary result is the phase transition between weak and strong coupling cases, a phenomenon absent in one- and two-dimensional cases. Therefore, the three-dimensional model turns out to be critical, exhibiting the phase transition. In the weak coupling case, the Gibbs measure can be normalized as a probability measure and is shown to be singular with respect to the Gaussian free field. Conversely, in the strong coupling case, the Gibbs measure cannot be constructed as a probability measure. In particular, the finite-dimensional truncated Gibbs measures have no weak limit in an appropriate space, even up to a subsequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.17013v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kihoon Seong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Superposition and Thinning of Generalized Counting Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06638v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the merging and splitting of generalized counting processes (GCPs). First, we study the merging of a finite number of independent GCPs and then extend it to the case of countably infinite. The merged process is observed to be a GCP with increased arrival rates. It is shown that a packet of jumps arrives in the merged process according to the Poisson process. Also, we study two different types of splitting of a GCP. In the first type, we study the splitting of jumps of a GCP where the probability of simultaneous jumps in the split components is negligible. In the second type, we consider the splitting of jumps in which there is a possibility of simultaneous jumps in the split components. It is shown that the split components are GCPs with certain decreased jump rates. Moreover, the independence of split components is established. Later, we discuss applications of the obtained results to industrial fishing problem and hotel booking management system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06638v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Dhillon, K. K. Kataria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local times of deterministic paths and self-similar processes with stationary increments as normalized numbers of interval crossings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05570v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a general result on a relationship between a limit of normalized numbers of interval crossings by a c\`adl\`ag path and an occupation measure associated with this path.
  Using this result we define local times of fractional Brownian motions (classically defined as densities of relevant occupation measure) as weak limits of properly normalized numbers of interval crossings.
  We also discuss a similar result for c\`adl\`ag semimartingales, in particular for alpha-stable processes, and for Rosenblatt processes, and provide natural examples of deterministic paths which possess quadratic or higher order variation but no local times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05570v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Witold Bednorz, Purba Das, Rafa{\l} {\L}ochowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Scaling, Ergodicity and Covariance Decay of Interacting Particle Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06935v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main focus of this article is the study of ergodicity of Interacting Particle Systems (IPS). We present a simple lemma showing that scaling time is equivalent to taking the convex combination of the transition matrix of the IPS with the identity. As a consequence, the ergodic properties of IPS are invariant under this transformation. Surprisingly, this simple observation has non-trivial implications: It allows to extend any result that does not respect this invariance, which we demonstrate with examples. Additionally, we develop a recursive method to deduce decay of correlations for IPS with alphabets of arbitrary (finite) size, and apply the Time-Scaling Lemma to that as well. As an application of this new criterion we show that certain one-dimensional IPS are ergodic answering an open question of Toom et al..</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06935v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej G{\l}uchowski, Georg Menz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deviation of top eigenvalue for some tridiagonal matrices under various moment assumptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetric tridiagonal matrices appear ubiquitously in mathematical physics, serving as the matrix representation of discrete random Schr\"odinger operators. In this work we investigate the top eigenvalue of these matrices in the large deviation regime, assuming the random potentials are on the diagonal with a certain decaying factor $N^{-\alpha}$, and the probability law $\mu$ of the potentials satisfy specific decay assumptions. We investigate two different models, one of which has random matrix behavior at the spectral edge but the other does not. Both the light-tailed regime, i.e. when $\mu$ has all moments, and the heavy-tailed regime are covered. Precise right tail estimates and a crude left tail estimate are derived. In particular we show that when the tail $\mu$ has a certain decay rate, then the top eigenvalue is distributed as the Frechet law composed with some deterministic functions. The proof relies on computing one point perturbations of fixed tridiagonal matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12146v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00023-024-01467-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yi Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the monotonicity of discrete entropy for log-concave random vectors on $\mathbb{Z}^d$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15462v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the following type of discrete entropy monotonicity for sums of isotropic, log-concave, independent and identically distributed random vectors $X_1,\dots,X_{n+1}$ on $\mathbb{Z}^d$: $$ H(X_1+\cdots+X_{n+1}) \geq H(X_1+\cdots+X_{n}) + \frac{d}{2}\log{\Bigl(\frac{n+1}{n}\Bigr)} +o(1), $$ where $o(1)$ vanishes as $H(X_1) \to \infty$. Moreover, for the $o(1)$-term, we obtain a rate of convergence $ O\Bigl({H(X_1)}{e^{-\frac{1}{d}H(X_1)}}\Bigr)$, where the implied constants depend on $d$ and $n$. This generalizes to $\mathbb{Z}^d$ the one-dimensional result of the second named author (2023). As in dimension one, our strategy is to establish that the discrete entropy $H(X_1+\cdots+X_{n})$ is close to the differential (continuous) entropy $h(X_1+U_1+\cdots+X_{n}+U_{n})$, where $U_1,\dots, U_n$ are independent and identically distributed uniform random vectors on $[0,1]^d$ and to apply the theorem of Artstein, Ball, Barthe and Naor (2004) on the monotonicity of differential entropy. In fact, we show this result under more general assumptions than log-concavity, which are preserved up to constants under convolution. In order to show that log-concave distributions satisfy our assumptions in dimension $d\ge2$, more involved tools from convex geometry are needed because a suitable position is required. We show that, for a log-concave function on $\mathbb{R}^d$ in isotropic position, its integral, barycenter and covariance matrix are close to their discrete counterparts. Moreover, in the log-concave case, we weaken the isotropicity assumption to what we call almost isotropicity. One of our technical tools is a discrete analogue to the upper bound on the isotropic constant of a log-concave function, which extends to dimensions $d\ge1$ a result of Bobkov, Marsiglietti and Melbourne (2022).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15462v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Fradelizi, Lampros Gavalakis, Martin Rapaport</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability of entering an orthant by correlated fractional Brownian motion with drift: Exact asymptotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03217v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $\{B_H(t)= (B_{H,1}(t), \ldots, B_{H,d}(t))^\top,t\ge0\}$, where $\{B_{H,i}(t),t\ge 0\}, 1\le i\le d$ are mutually independent fractional Brownian motions, we obtain the exact asymptotics of $$ \mathbb P (\exists t\ge 0: A B_{H}(t) - \mu t &gt;\nu u), \ \ \ \ u\to\infty, $$ where $A$ is a non-singular $d\times d$ matrix and $\mu=(\mu_1,\ldots, \mu_d)^\top\in R^d$, $\nu=(\nu_1, \ldots, \nu_d)^\top \in R^d$ are such that there exists some $1\le i\le d$ such that $\mu_i&gt;0, \nu_i&gt;0.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03217v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Debicki, Lanpeng Ji, Svyatoslav Novikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-concentration applied to roots of randomized derivatives of polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12472v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $(Z^{(n)}_k)_{1 \leq k \leq n}$ be a random set of points and let $\mu_n$ be its \emph{empirical measure}:
  $$\mu_n = \frac{1}{n} \sum_{k=1}^n \delta_{Z^{(n)}_k}. $$
  Let $$P_n(z) := (z - Z^{(n)}_1)\cdots (z - Z^{(n)}_n)\quad \text{and}\quad Q_n (z) := \sum_{k=1}^n \gamma^{(n)}_k \prod_{1 \leq j \leq n, j \neq k} (z- Z^{(n)}_j), $$ where $(\gamma^{(n)}_k)_{1 \leq k \leq n}$ are independent, i.i.d. random variables with Gamma distribution of parameter $\beta/2$, for some fixed $\beta &gt; 0$. We prove that in the case where $\mu_n$ almost surely tends to $\mu$ when $n \rightarrow \infty$, the empirical measure of the complex zeros of the \emph{randomized derivative} $Q_n$ also converges almost surely to $\mu$ when $n$ tends to infinity. Furthermore, for $k = o(n / \log n)$, we obtain that the zeros of the $k-$th \emph{randomized derivative} of $P_n$ converge to the limiting measure $\mu$ in the same sense. We also derive the same conclusion for a variant of the randomized derivative related to the unit circle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12472v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e Galligo, Joseph Najnudel, Truong Vu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A critical drift-diffusion equation: intermittent behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13641v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a drift-diffusion process with a time-independent and divergence-free random drift that is of white-noise character. We are interested in the critical case of two space dimensions, where one has to impose a small-scale cut-off for well-posedness, and is interested in the marginally super-diffusive behavior on large scales.
  In the presence of an (artificial) large-scale cut-off at scale L, as a consequence of standard stochastic homogenization theory, there exist harmonic coordinates with a stationary gradient $F_L$; the merit of these coordinates being that under their lens, the drift-diffusion process turns into a martingale.
  It has recently been established that the second moments diverge as $\mathbb{E}|F_L|^2\sim\sqrt{\ln L}$ for $L\uparrow\infty$. We quantitatively show that in this limit, and in the regime of small P\'eclet number, $|F_L|^2/\mathbb{E}|F_L|^2$ is not equi-integrable, and that $\mathbb{E}|{\rm det}F_L|/\mathbb{E}|F_L|^2 $ is small. Hence the Jacobian matrix of the harmonic coordinates is very peaked and non-conformal.
  We establish this asymptotic behavior by characterizing a proxy $\tilde F_L$ introduced in previous work as the solution of an It\^{o} SDE w. r. t. the variable $\ln L$, and which implements the concept of a scale-by-scale homogenization based on a variance decomposition and admits an efficient calculus. For this proxy, we establish $\mathbb{E}|\tilde F_L|^4\gg(\mathbb{E}|\tilde F_L|^2)^2$ and $\mathbb{E}({\rm det}\tilde F_L-1)^2\ll 1$. In view of the former property, we assimilate this phenomenon to intermittency. In fact, $\tilde F_L$ behaves like a tensorial stochastic exponential, and as a field can be assimilated to multiplicative Gaussian chaos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13641v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Otto, Christian Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic algorithm approach for the elephant random walk with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12495v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The randomized play-the-winner rule (RPW) is a response-adaptive design proposed by Wei and Durham (1978) for sequentially randomizing patients to treatments in a two-treatment clinical trial so that more patients are assigned to the better treatment as the clinical trial goes on. The elephant random walk (ERW) proposed by Schutz and Trimper (2004) is a non-Markovian discrete-time random walk on $\mathbb Z$ which has a link to a famous saying that elephants can always remember where they have been. The asymptotic behaviors of RPW rule and ERW have been studied in litterateurs independently, and their asymptotic behaviors are very similar. In this paper, we show that the RPW rule is a biased ERW and link them with the recursive stochastic algorithm. With the help of a recursive stochastic algorithm, we obtain the strong invariance principle of the ERW as well as multi-dimensional varying-memory ERW with random step sizes. By the strong invariance principle, the central limit theorem, precise law of the iterated logarithm, and almost sure central limit theorem are obtained for both the multi-dimensional ERW, the multi-dimensional ERW with random step sizes and their centers of mass for all the diffusive, critical and superdifficult regime. The Chung type law of the iterated logarithm of the multi-dimensional ERW is also obtained for both the diffusive regime and superdifficult regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12495v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meeting times of Markov chains via singular value decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04958v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We suggest a non-asymptotic matrix perturbation-theoretic approach to get sharp bounds on the expected meeting time of random walks on large (possibly random) graphs. We provide a formula for the expected meeting time in terms of the singular value decomposition of the diagonally killed generator of a pair of independent random walks, which we view as a perturbation of the generator. Employing a rank-one approximation of the diagonally killed generator as the proof of concept, we work out sharp bounds on the expected meeting time of simple random walks on sufficiently dense Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi random graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04958v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas van Belle, Anton Klimovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Linear Sofic Approximations Of Countable Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.10111v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A countable group G is called k-linear sofic (for some 0 &lt;k \le 1) if finite subsets of G admit "approximate representations" by complex invertible matrices in the normalized rank metric, so that non-identity elements are k-away from the identity. This class of groups was systematically studied by Arzhantseva and Paunescu [AP17], where it is shown that such a group is always 1/4-linear sofic. In this paper, we will study the optimality of this result for general countable groups and show that every linear sofic group is 1/2-linear sofic, and 1/2 cannot be improved. However, if G is assumed to be torsion-free, then it is 1-linear sofic. These results answer a question posed by G. Arzhantseva in her talk in the IAS Stability and Testability lecture series. We also study the optimal linear sofic constant of finite groups over C and fields of positive characteristic. For the proof, we establish effective non-concentration estimates for random walks on finitely generated abelian groups, which may be of independent interest. Another ingredient of the proof involves bounding integrals of certain trigonometric sums.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.10111v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keivan Mallahi-Karai, Maryam Mohammadi Yekta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multilevel Stochastic Approximation Algorithm for Value-at-Risk and Expected Shortfall Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01207v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a multilevel stochastic approximation (MLSA) scheme for the computation of the value-at-risk (VaR) and expected shortfall (ES) of a financial loss, which can only be computed via simulations conditional on the realization of future risk factors. Thus, the problem of estimating its VaR and ES is nested in nature and can be viewed as an instance of stochastic approximation problems with biased innovations. In this framework, for a prescribed accuracy $\epsilon$, the optimal complexity of a nested stochastic approximation algorithm is shown to be of order $\epsilon$--3. To estimate the VaR, our MLSA algorithm attains an optimal complexity of order $\epsilon$--2--$\delta$ , where $\delta$ \&lt; 1 is some parameter depending on the integrability degree of the loss, while to estimate the ES, it achieves an optimal complexity of order $\epsilon$--2 |ln $\epsilon$|2. Numerical studies of the joint evolution of the error rate and the execution time demonstrate how our MLSA algorithm regains a significant amount of the performance lost due to the nested nature of the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01207v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>St\'ephane Cr\'epey (LPSM), Noufel Frikha (CES), Azar Louzi (LPSM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization of a 1d quadratic Schr{\"o}dinger model with additive noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.03114v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The study is devoted to the interpretation and wellposedness of a stochastic NLS model with a quadratic nonlinearity and a space-time fractional noise. We focus on a rough regime corresponding to the case where the Hurst indexes of the fractional noise are small. In this specific case, we exhibit an explicit renormalization procedure allowing to restore the (local) convergence of the approximated solutions. We follow a pathwise-type approach emphasizing the distinction between the stochastic objects at the core of the dynamics and the general deterministic machinery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.03114v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aur\'elien Deya (IECL), Reika Fukuizumi (IECL), Laurent Thomann (IECL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-passage time of a Brownian motion: two unexpected journeys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.17656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.17656v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The distribution of the first-passage time (FPT)$T_a$ for a Brownian particle with drift $\mu$ subject to hitting an absorber at a level $a&gt;0$ is well-known and given by its density $\gamma(t) = \frac{a}{\sqrt{2 \pi t^3} } e^{-\frac{(a-\mu t)^2}{2 t}}, t&gt;0$, which is normalized only if $\mu \geq 0$. This article demonstrates the existence of two additional diffusion process categories (one with one parameter and the other with two) that have the same first passage-time distributions when $\mu &lt;0$. For both, we identify the transition densities and thoroughly investigate the processes. A substantial implication is that the first-passage time distribution does not indicate whether the process originates from a drifted Brownian motion or from one of the new processes presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.17656v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alain Mazzolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk Aversion and Insurance Propensity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09173v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a new foundation of risk aversion by showing that the propension to exploit insurance opportunities fully describes this attitude. Our foundation, which applies to any probabilistically sophisticated preference, well accords with the commonly held prudential interpretation of risk aversion that dates back to the seminal works of Arrow (1963) and Pratt (1964).
  In our main results, we first characterize the Arrow-Pratt risk aversion in terms of propension to full insurance and the stronger notion of risk aversion of Rothschild and Stiglitz (1970) in terms of propension to partial insurance. We then extend the analysis to comparative risk aversion by showing that the notion of Yaari (1969) corresponds to comparative propension to full insurance, while the stronger notion of Ross (1981) corresponds to comparative propension to partial insurance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09173v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Maccheroni, Massimo Marinacci, Ruodu Wang, Qinyu Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inter-city infections and the role of size heterogeneity in containment strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03100v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the effectiveness of regional lockdown strategies to mitigate the spread of a pathogen across regional units, in the following called cities, within a country or region for a single infection wave. The heterogeneity in the epidemically relevant connectivity is defined via a random network model with cities as nodes, where the city's sizes determine their connectivity via a gravity type kernel function. Isolation of a whole city is initiated when infection numbers surpass defined thresholds. We consider two basic strategies for the lockdowns. Strategy~$(P)$ isolates cities based on a proportional threshold of infections, while stra\-tegy~\((U)\) uses a uniform infection threshold for all cities. Given the heavy-tailed distribution of city sizes, strategy \((P)\) can potentially result in more secondary infections from larger cities than strategy \((U)\). As an efficiency measure we use the ratio of individuals under lockdown and the number of infected individuals. Additionally, we analytically derive formulas for the basic reproduction numbers and prevalences. Our model is fitted to mobility data from France, Japan, and Poland, and validated through simulations. The findings indicate that while the model aligns well with data from France and Poland, it deviates in Japan, highlighting the importance of geographical nuances in pathogen spread modeling. Furthermore, it suggests that for France (and Japan) both strategies perform equally well, while for Poland strategy \((U)\) outperforms strategy \((P)\).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03100v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Bezborodov, Tyll Krueger, Cornelia Pokalyuk, Piotr Szyma\'nski, Aur\'elien Velleret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pricing of geometric Asian options in the Volterra-Heston model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15828v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Geometric Asian options are a type of options where the payoff depends on the geometric mean of the underlying asset over a certain period of time. This paper is concerned with the pricing of such options for the class of Volterra-Heston models, covering the rough Heston model. We are able to derive semi-closed formulas for the prices of geometric Asian options with fixed and floating strikes for this class of stochastic volatility models. These formulas require the explicit calculation of the conditional joint Fourier transform of the logarithm of the stock price and the logarithm of the geometric mean of the stock price over time. Linking our problem to the theory of affine Volterra processes, we find a representation of this Fourier transform as a suitably constructed stochastic exponential, which depends on the solution of a Riccati-Volterra equation. Finally we provide a numerical study for our results in the rough Heston model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15828v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Aichinger, Sascha Desmettre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hilbert Space-Valued LQ Mean Field Games: An Infinite-Dimensional Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01012v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive study of linear-quadratic (LQ) mean field games (MFGs) in Hilbert spaces, generalizing the classic LQ MFG theory to scenarios involving $N$ agents with dynamics governed by infinite-dimensional stochastic equations. In this framework, both state and control processes of each agent take values in separable Hilbert spaces. All agents are coupled through the average state of the population which appears in their linear dynamics and quadratic cost functional. Specifically, the dynamics of each agent incorporates an infinite-dimensional noise, namely a $Q$-Wiener process, and an unbounded operator. The diffusion coefficient of each agent is stochastic involving the state, control, and average state processes. We first study the well-posedness of a system of $N$ coupled semilinear infinite-dimensional stochastic evolution equations establishing the foundation of MFGs in Hilbert spaces. We then specialize to $N$-player LQ games described above and study the asymptotic behaviour as the number of agents, $N$, approaches infinity. We develop an infinite-dimensional variant of the Nash Certainty Equivalence principle and characterize a unique Nash equilibrium for the limiting MFG. Finally, we study the connections between the $N$-player game and the limiting MFG, demonstrating that the empirical average state converges to the mean field and that the resulting limiting best-response strategies form an $\epsilon$-Nash equilibrium for the $N$-player game in Hilbert spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01012v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanchao Liu, Dena Firoozi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Low-Degree Hardness of Finding Large Independent Sets in Sparse Random Hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03842v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the algorithmic task of finding large independent sets in Erdos-Renyi $r$-uniform hypergraphs on $n$ vertices having average degree $d$. Krivelevich and Sudakov showed that the maximum independent set has density $\left(\frac{r\log d}{(r-1)d}\right)^{1/(r-1)}$. We show that the class of low-degree polynomial algorithms can find independent sets of density $\left(\frac{\log d}{(r-1)d}\right)^{1/(r-1)}$ but no larger. This extends and generalizes earlier results of Gamarnik and Sudan, Rahman and Virag, and Wein on graphs, and answers a question of Bal and Bennett. We conjecture that this statistical-computational gap holds for this problem.
  Additionally, we explore the universality of this gap by examining $r$-partite hypergraphs. A hypergraph $H=(V,E)$ is $r$-partite if there is a partition $V=V_1\cup\cdots\cup V_r$ such that each edge contains exactly one vertex from each set $V_i$. We consider the problem of finding large balanced independent sets (independent sets containing the same number of vertices in each partition) in random $r$-partite hypergraphs with $n$ vertices in each partition and average degree $d$. We prove that the maximum balanced independent set has density $\left(\frac{r\log d}{(r-1)d}\right)^{1/(r-1)}$ asymptotically. Furthermore, we prove an analogous low-degree computational threshold of $\left(\frac{\log d}{(r-1)d}\right)^{1/(r-1)}$. Our results recover and generalize recent work of Perkins and the second author on bipartite graphs.
  While the graph case has been extensively studied, this work is the first to consider statistical-computational gaps of optimization problems on random hypergraphs. Our results suggest that these gaps persist for larger uniformities as well as across many models. A somewhat surprising aspect of the gap for balanced independent sets is that the algorithm achieving the lower bound is a simple degree-1 polynomial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03842v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Dhawan, Yuzhou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current fluctuations of a self-interacting diffusion on a ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15561v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate fluctuations in the average speed or current of a self-interacting diffusion (SID) on a ring, mimicking the non-Markovian behaviour of an agent influenced by its own path. We derive the SID's phase diagram, showing a delocalisation-localisation phase transition from self-repelling to self-attracting. Current fluctuations are analysed using: (i) an adiabatic approximation, where the system reaches its stationary distribution before developing current fluctuations, and (ii) an original extension of level 2.5 large deviations for Markov processes. The latter, combined with perturbation theory, provides an upper bound to current fluctuations, which is tight in the self-repelling region, while the former approximates current fluctuations well in all regimes. Both methods accurately estimate the asymptotic variance and suggests a phase transition at the onset of the localised regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15561v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Coghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation of the heat kernel and the Brownian motion from the perspective of the Ben Sa\"id--Kobayashi--{\O}rsted $(k,a)$-generalized Laguerre semigroup theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03664v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We deform the heat kernel and the Brownian motion on $\mathbb{R}^{N}$ from the perspective of "$(k,a)$-generalized Fourier analysis" with $k=0$. This is a new type of harmonic analysis proposed by S.Ben Sa\"id--T.Kobayashi--B.{\O}rsted from the representation theoretic viewpoint. In this paper, we construct the $a$-deformed heat kernel and $a$-deformed Brownian motion, and explore their some basic properties. We also prove that the $(k,a)$-generalized Fourier integral kernels are polynomial growth when $k=0$, for a justification of some discussions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03664v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Temma Aoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
