<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Markov chains and mappings of distributions on compact spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider a compact metric space $S$ and a pair $(j,k)$ with $k \ge 2$ and $1 \le j \le k$. For any probability distribution $\theta \in P(S)$, define a Markov chain on $S$ by: from state $s$, take $k$ i.i.d. ($\theta$) samples, and jump to the $j$'th closest. Such a chain converges in distribution to a unique stationary distribution, say $\pi_{j,k}(\theta)$. So this defines a mapping $\pi_{j,k}: P(S) \to P(S)$. What happens when we iterate this mapping? In particular, what are the fixed points of this mapping? We present a few rigorous results, to complement our extensive simulation study elsewhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01348v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David J. Aldous, Shi Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normal approximation for exponential random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The question of whether the central limit theorem (CLT) holds for the total number of edges in exponential random graph models (ERGMs) in the subcritical region of parameters has remained an open problem. In this paper, we establish the CLT in a subset of the subcritical region known as Dobrushin's uniqueness region. As a result of our proof, we also derive a convergence rate for the CLT and an explicit formula for the asymptotic variance. To establish our main result, we develop Stein's method for the normal approximation for general functionals of nonlinear exponential families of random variables, which is of independent interest. In addition to ERGM, our general theorem can also be applied to other models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01666v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Fang, Song-Hao Liu, Qi-Man Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditionings to avoid points with various clocks for L\'{e}vy processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss conditionings to avoid two points and one-point local time penalizations with conditioning to avoid another point, for which we adopt various clocks. We also give corrections to some of the previous results of Takeda--Yano for one-point local time penalizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01762v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohki Iba, Kouji Yano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long Time Propagation of Chaos in Total Variation Distance for Mean Field Interacting Particle System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, a general result on the long time quantitative propagation of chaos in total variation distance for mean field interacting particle system driven by general L\'{e}vy noise is derived, where the non-interacting drift is assumed to be dissipative in long distance and the initial distribution of interacting particle system converges to that of the limit equation in $L^1$-Wasserstein distance. Moreover, by using the method of coupling, the results are applied to mean field interacting particle system driven by Brownian motion and $\alpha(\alpha&gt;1)$-stable noise respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01795v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing Huang, Fen-Fen Yang, Chenggui Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle systems for mean reflected BSDEs with jumps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the mean reflected backward stochastic differential equations with jump (BSDEJs) where the generator only depends on $Y$. We extend the work of Briand and Hibon on the propagation of chaos for mean reflected BSDEs \cite{briand2021particles} to the jump framework. Besides, we study the reflections for the particle system and obtain the rate of of convergence of the particle system towards the deterministic flat solution to the mean reflected BSDEJ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01916v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqing Lin, Kun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green Measures for a Class of non-Markov Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the Green measure for a class of non-Gaussian processes in $\mathbb{R}^{d}$. These measures are associated with the family of generalized grey Brownian motions $B_{\beta,\alpha}$, $0&lt;\beta\le1$, $0&lt;\alpha\le2$. This family includes both fractional Brownian motion, Brownian motion, and other non-Gaussian processes. We show that the perpetual integral exists with probability $1$ for $d\alpha&gt;2$ and $1&lt;\alpha\le2$. The Green measure then generalizes those measures of all these classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02076v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herry Pribawanto Suryawan, Jos\'e Lu\'is da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Burning Random Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01545v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{T}$ be a Galton-Watson tree with a given offspring distribution $\xi$, where $\xi$ is a $Z_{\geq 0}$-valued random variable with $E[\xi] = 1$ and $0 &lt; \sigma^{2}:=Var[\xi] &lt; \infty$. For $n \geq 1$, let $T_{n}$ be the tree $\mathcal{T}$ conditioned to have $n$ vertices. In this paper we investigate $b(T_n)$, the burning number of $T_n$. Our main result shows that asymptotically almost surely $b(T_n)$ is of the order of $n^{1/3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01545v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Devroye, Austin Eide, Pawel Pralat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liouville Theory: An Introduction to Rigorous Approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, a surprisingly direct and simple rigorous understanding of quantum Liouville theory has developed. We aim here to make this material more accessible to physicists working on quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02001v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Chatterjee, Edward Witten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Deviator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.03744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.03744v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A group of players are supposed to follow a prescribed profile of strategies. If they follow this profile, they will reach a given target. We show that if the target is not reached because some player deviates, then an outside observer can identify the deviator. We also construct identification methods in two nontrivial cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.03744v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noga Alon, Benjamin Gunby, Xiaoyu He, Eran Shmaya, Eilon Solan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On strong solutions of time inhomogeneous It\^o's equations with Morrey diffusion gradient and drift. A supercritical case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.03719v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the existence of strong solutions of It\^o's stochastic time dependent equations with irregular diffusion and drift terms of Morrey spaces. Strong uniqueness is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.03719v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. V. Krylov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atypical stars on a directed landscape geodesic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05734v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In random geometry, a recurring theme is that any two geodesics emanating from a typical point part ways at a strictly positive distance from the above point, and we call such points as $1$-stars. However, the measure zero set of atypical stars, the points where such coalescence fails, is typically uncountable and the corresponding Hausdorff dimensions of these sets have been heavily investigated for a variety of models including the directed landscape, Liouville quantum gravity and the Brownian map. In this paper, we consider the directed landscape-- the scaling limit of last passage percolation as constructed in the work Dauvergne-Ortmann-Vir\'ag '18-- and look into the Hausdorff dimension of the set of atypical stars lying on a geodesic. We show that the above dimension is almost surely equal to $1/3$. This is in contrast to Ganguly-Zhang '22, where it was shown that set of atypical stars on the line $\{x=0\}$ has dimension $2/3$. This reduction of the dimension from $2/3$ to $1/3$ yields a quantitative manifestation of the smoothing of the environment around a geodesic with regard to exceptional behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05734v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manan Bhatia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality in the directed landscape and its applications to fractal geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.07704v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Geodesic coalescence, or the tendency of geodesics to merge together, is a hallmark phenomenon observed in a variety of planar random geometries involving a random distortion of the Euclidean metric. As a result of this, the union of interiors of all geodesics going to a fixed point tends to form a tree-like structure which is supported on a vanishing fraction of the space. Such geodesic trees exhibit intricate fractal behaviour; for instance, while almost every point in the space has only one geodesic going to the fixed point, there exist atypical points which admit two such geodesics. In this paper, we consider the directed landscape, the recently constructed scaling limit of exponential last passage percolation (LPP), with the aim of developing tools to analyse the fractal aspects of the tree of semi-infinite geodesics in a given direction. We use the duality (Pimentel '16) between the geodesic tree and the interleaving competition interfaces in exponential LPP to obtain a duality between the geodesic tree and the corresponding dual tree in the landscape. Using this, we show that problems concerning the fractal behaviour of sets of atypical points for the geodesic tree can be transformed into corresponding problems for the dual tree, which might turn out to be easier. In particular, we use this method to show that the set of points admitting two semi-infinite geodesics in a fixed direction a.s. has Hausdorff dimension $4/3$, thereby answering a question posed in Busani-Sepp\"{a}l\"{a}inen-Sorensen '22. We also show that the set of points admitting three semi-infinite geodesics in a fixed direction is a.s. countable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.07704v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manan Bhatia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Couplings of Brownian motions on $SU(2,\mathbb{C})$ and $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.10017v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Lie groups $SU(2)$ and $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$ can be viewed as model spaces in subRiemannian geometry. Coupling two subelliptic Brownian motions on $SU(2)$ (resp. $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$) consists in coupling two Brownian motions on the sphere (resp. the hyperbolic plane) and simultaneously their swept areas. Using this approach we propose an explicit construction of a co-adapted successful coupling on $SU(2)$. The strategy is to alternate between reflection and synchronous (with noise) coupling on the sphere. We also describe some more general constructions of co-adapted couplings on $SU(2)$ and also on $SL(2,\mathbb{R})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.10017v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magalie B\'en\'efice (IMB, UB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central Limit Theorem of Overlap for the Mean Field Ghatak-Sherrington model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15774v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Ghatak-Sherrington (GS) spin glass model is a random probability measure defined on the configuration space $\{0,\pm1,\pm2,\ldots, \pm \mathcal{S} \}^N$ with system size $N$ and $\mathcal{S}\ge1$ finite. This generalizes the classical Sherrington-Kirkpatrick (SK) model on the boolean cube $\{-1,+1\}^N$ in order to capture more complex behaviors, including the spontaneous inverse freezing phenomenon. Although many results on the physics side have been established to understand the GS model, mathematical exploration of the model remains scarce. Overlap, the normalized inner product of two configurations, acts as the system order parameter to understand the phase transition of mean-field spin glass models. In this paper, we use moment method combined with the cavity approach to rigorously establish a quantitative joint central limit theorem for the overlap and self-overlap array. The results hold at high temperatures under arbitrary crystal and external fields. Compared to the SK model, the main challenge comes from the non-trivial self-overlap terms which also correlated with the standard overlap terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15774v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueqi Sheng, Qiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quick probability-oriented introduction to operator splitting methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00123v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is an extended and reworked version of a short course given by the author at ''Uzbekistan-Ukrainian readings in stochastic processes'', Tashkent-Kyiv, 2022, and was prepared for a special issue of ''Theory of stochastic processes'', devoted to publishing lecture notes from the aforementioned workshop.
  The survey is devoted to operator splitting methods in the abstract formulation and their applications in probability. While the survey is focused on multiplicative methods, the BCH formula is used to discuss exponential splitting methods and a short informal introduction to additive splitting is presented. We introduce frameworks and available deterministic and probabilistic results and concentrate on constructing a wide picture of the field of operator splitting methods, providing a rigorous description in the setting of abstract Cauchy problems and an informal discussion for further and parallel advances. Some limitations and common difficulties are listed, as well as examples of works that provide solutions or hints. No new results are given. The bibliography contains illustrative deterministic examples and a selection of probability-related works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00123v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. B. Vovchanskyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp bounds for max-sliced Wasserstein distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00666v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We obtain essentially matching upper and lower bounds for the expected max-sliced 1-Wasserstein distance between a probability measure on a separable Hilbert space and its empirical distribution from $n$ samples. By proving a Banach space version of this result, we also obtain an upper bound, that is sharp up to a log factor, for the expected max-sliced 2-Wasserstein distance between a symmetric probability measure $\mu$ on a Euclidean space and its symmetrized empirical distribution in terms of the operator norm of the covariance matrix of $\mu$ and the diameter of the support of $\mu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00666v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>March T. Boedihardjo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory on new fractional operators using normalization and probability tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06198v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show how a rescaling of fractional operators with bounded kernels may help circumvent their documented deficiencies, for example, the inconsistency at zero or the lack of inverse integral operator. On the other hand, we build a novel class of linear operators with memory effects to extend the L-fractional and the ordinary derivatives, using probability tools. A Mittag-Leffler-type function is introduced to solve linear problems, and nonlinear equations are solved with power series, illustrating the methods for the SIR model. The inverse operator is constructed, and a fundamental theorem of calculus and an existence-and-uniqueness result for differential equations are proved. A conjecture on deconvolution is raised, that would permit completing the proposed theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06198v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Jornet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The top eigenvalue of uniformly random trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let ${\mathbf T}_n$ be a uniformly random tree with vertex set $[n]=\{1,\ldots,n\}$, let $\Delta_{{\mathbf T}_n}$ be the largest vertex degree in ${\mathbf T}_n$, and let $\lambda_1({\mathbf T}_n),\ldots,\lambda_n({\mathbf T}_n)$ be the eigenvalues of its adjacency matrix, arranged in decreasing order. We prove that $|\lambda_1({\mathbf T}_n)-\sqrt{\Delta_{{\mathbf T}_n}}| \to 0$ in expectation as $n \to \infty$, and additionally prove probability tail bounds for $|\lambda_1({\mathbf T}_n)-\sqrt{\Delta_{{\mathbf T}_n}}|$. Writing $a_n$ for any median of $\Delta_{{\mathbf T}_n}$, we also prove that $|\lambda_k({\mathbf T}_n)-\sqrt{a_n}| \to 0$ in expectation, uniformly over $1 \le k \le e^{\log^\beta(n)}$, for any fixed $\beta \in (0,1/2)$.
  The proof is based on the trace method and thus on counting closed walks in a random tree. To this end, we develop novel combinatorial tools for encoding walks in trees that we expect will find other applications. In order to apply these tools, we show that uniformly random trees -- after appropriate "surgery" -- satisfy, with high probability, the properties required for the combinatorial bounds to be effective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08443v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louigi Addario-Berry, G\'abor Lugosi, Roberto Imbuzeiro Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling limit of heavy tailed nearly unstable cumulative INAR($\infty$) processes and rough fractional diffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11773v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigated the scaling limit of heavy-tailed unstable cumulative INAR($\infty$) processes. These processes exhibit a power law tail of the form $n^{-(1+\alpha)}$, with $\alpha \in (\frac{1}{2}, 1)$, where the $\ell^1$ norm of the kernel vector is close to $1$. The result is in contrast to scaling limit of the continuous-time heavy tailed unstable Hawkes processes and the one of INAR($p$) processes. We show that the discrete-time scaling limit also has long-memory property and can also be seen as an integrated fractional Cox-Ingersoll-Ross process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11773v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingli Wang, Chunhao Cai, Ping He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomisation in the Josephus Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18110v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Josephus problem is a well--studied elimination problem consisting in determining the position of the survivor after repeated applications of a deterministic rule removing one person at a time from a given group.
  A natural probabilistic variant of this process is introduced in this paper. More precisely, in this variant, the survivor is determined after performing a succession of Bernouilli trials with parameter $p$ designating each time the person to remove. When the number of participants tends to infinity, the main result characterises the limit distribution of the position of the survivor with an increasing degree of precision as the parameter approaches the unbiaised case $p=1/2$. Then, the convergence rate to the position of the survivor is obtained in the form of a Central-Limit Theorem.
  A number of other variants of the suggested probabilistic elimination process are also considered. They each admit a specific limit behavior which, in most cases, is stated in the form of an open problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18110v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faustin Adiceam, Steven Robertson, Victor Shirandami, Ioannis Tsokanos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modularity and partially observed graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.13190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.13190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Suppose that there is an unknown underlying graph $G$ on a large vertex set, and we can test only a proportion of the possible edges to check whether they are present in $G$. If $G$ has high modularity, is the observed graph $G'$ likely to have high modularity? We see that this is indeed the case under a mild condition, in a natural model where we test edges at random. We find that $q^*(G') \geq q^*(G)-\varepsilon$ with probability at least $1-\varepsilon$, as long as the expected number edges in $G'$ is large enough. Similarly, $q^*(G') \leq q^*(G)+\varepsilon$ with probability at least $1-\varepsilon$, under the stronger condition that the expected average degree in $G'$ is large enough. Further, under this stronger condition, finding a good partition for $G'$ helps us to find a good partition for $G$.
  We also consider the vertex sampling model for partially observing the underlying graph: we find that for dense underlying graphs we may estimate the modularity by sampling constantly many vertices and observing the corresponding induced subgraph, but this does not hold for underlying graphs with a subquadratic number of edges. Finally we deduce some related results, for example showing that under-sampling tends to lead to overestimation of modularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.13190v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin McDiarmid, Fiona Skerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Elementary Proof of the Inequality $\chi \leq \chi^*$ for Conditional Free Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02574v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Through the study of large deviations theory for matrix Brownian motion, Biane-Capitaine-Guionnet proved the inequality $\chi(X) \leq \chi^*(X)$ that relates two analogs of entropy in free probability defined by Voiculescu. We give a new proof of $\chi \leq \chi^*$ that is elementary in the sense that it does not rely on stochastic differential equations and large deviation theory. Moreover, we generalize the result to conditional microstates and non-microstates free entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02574v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Jekel, Jennifer Pi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loop Vertex Representation for Cumulants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.08399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.08399v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we construct cumulants for stable random matrix models with single trace interactions of arbitrarily high even order. We obtain explicit and convergent expansions for the cumulants. We show that any cumulant is an analytic function inside a cardioid domain in the complex plane and we prove their Borel-LeRoy summability at the origin of the coupling constant. Our proof is uniform in the external variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.08399v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Rivasseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smoothing in linear multicompartment biological processes subject to stochastic input</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09004v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many physical and biological systems rely on the progression of material through multiple independent stages. In viral replication, for example, virions enter a cell to undergo a complex process comprising several disparate stages before the eventual accumulation and release of replicated virions. While such systems may have some control over the internal dynamics that make up this progression, a challenge for many is to regulate behaviour under what are often highly variable external environments acting as system inputs. In this work, we study a simple analogue of this problem through a linear multicompartment model subject to a stochastic input in the form of a mean-reverting Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process, a type of Gaussian process. By expressing the system as a multidimensional Gaussian process, we derive several closed-form analytical results relating to the covariances and autocorrelations of the system, quantifying the smoothing effect discrete compartments afford multicompartment systems. Semi-analytical results demonstrate that feedback and feedforward loops can enhance system robustness, and simulation results probe the intractable problem of the first passage time distribution, which has specific relevance to eventual cell lysis in the viral replication cycle. Finally, we demonstrate that the smoothing seen in the process is a consequence of the discreteness of the system, and does not manifest in system with continuous transport. While we make progress through analysis of a simple linear problem, many of our insights are applicable more generally, and our work enables future analysis into multicompartment processes subject to stochastic inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09004v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander P Browning, Adrianne L Jenner, Ruth E Baker, Philip K Maini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generalized Pell's equation for a class of multivariate orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10668v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend the polynomial Pell's equation satisfied by univariate Chebyshev polynomials on [--1, 1] from one variable to several variables, using orthogonal polynomials on regular domains that include cubes, balls, and simplexes of arbitrary dimension. Moreover, we show that such an equation is strongly connected (i) to a certificate of positivity (from real algebraic geometry) on the domain, as well as (ii) to the Christoffel functions of the equilibrium measure on the domain. In addition, the solution to Pell's equation reflects an extremal property of orthonormal polynomials associated with an entropy-like criterion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10668v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Bernard Lasserre (LAAS-POP, TSE-R), Yuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative Proof for the Expected Number of Distinct Consecutive Patterns in a Random Permutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14071v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\pi_n$ be a uniformly chosen random permutation on $[n]$. Using an analysis of the probability that two overlapping consecutive $k$-permutations are order isomorphic, the authors of a recent paper showed that the expected number of distinct consecutive patterns of all lengths $k\in\{1,2,\ldots,n\}$ in $\pi_n$ is $\frac{n^2}{2}(1-o(1))$ as $n\to\infty$. This exhibited the fact that random permutations pack consecutive patterns near-perfectly. We use entirely different methods, namely the Stein-Chen method of Poisson approximation, to reprove and slightly improve their result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14071v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anant Godbole, Hannah Swickheimer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Local False Discovery Rate Control: A Resource Allocation Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11425v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of sequentially conducting multiple experiments where each experiment corresponds to a hypothesis testing task. At each time point, the experimenter must make an irrevocable decision of whether to reject the null hypothesis (or equivalently claim a discovery) before the next experimental result arrives. The goal is to maximize the number of discoveries while maintaining a low error rate at all time points measured by local False Discovery Rate (FDR). We formulate the problem as an online knapsack problem with exogenous random budget replenishment. We start with general arrival distributions and show that a simple policy achieves a $O(\sqrt{T})$ regret. We complement the result by showing that such regret rate is in general not improvable. We then shift our focus to discrete arrival distributions. We find that many existing re-solving heuristics in the online resource allocation literature, albeit achieve bounded loss in canonical settings, may incur a $\Omega(\sqrt{T})$ or even a $\Omega(T)$ regret. With the observation that canonical policies tend to be too optimistic and over claim discoveries, we propose a novel policy that incorporates budget safety buffers. It turns out that a little more safety can greatly enhance efficiency -- small additional logarithmic buffers suffice to reduce the regret from $\Omega(\sqrt{T})$ or even $\Omega(T)$ to $O(\ln^2 T)$. From a practical perspective, we extend the policy to the scenario with continuous arrival distributions as well as time-dependent information structures. We conduct both synthetic experiments and empirical applications on a time series data from New York City taxi passengers to validate the performance of our proposed policies. Our results emphasize how effective policies should be designed in online resource allocation problems with exogenous budget replenishment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11425v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruicheng Ao, Hongyu Chen, David Simchi-Levi, Feng Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multivariate Berry--Esseen theorem for time-dependent expanding dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16349v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We adapt Stein's method to obtain Berry--Esseen type error bounds in the multivariate central limit theorem for non-stationary processes generated by time-dependent compositions of uniformly expanding dynamical systems. In a particular case of random dynamical systems with a strongly mixing base transformation, we derive an error estimate of order $O(N^{-1/2})$ in the quenched multivariate CLT, provided that the covariance matrix "grows linearly" with the number of summands $N$. The error in the normal approximation is estimated for the class of all convex sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16349v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juho Lepp\"anen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An $\alpha$-potential game framework for $N$-player games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16962v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes and studies a general form of dynamic $N$-player non-cooperative games called $\alpha$-potential games, where the change of a player's value function upon her unilateral deviation from her strategy is equal to the change of an $\alpha$-potential function up to an error $\alpha$. Analogous to the static potential game (which corresponds to $\alpha=0$), the $\alpha$-potential game framework is shown to reduce the challenging task of finding approximate Nash equilibria for a dynamic game to minimizing the $\alpha$-potential function. Moreover, an analytical characterization of $\alpha$-potential functions is established, with $\alpha$ represented in terms of the magnitude of the asymmetry of value functions' second-order derivatives. For stochastic differential games in which the state dynamic is a controlled diffusion, $\alpha$ is explicitly identified in terms of the number of players, the choice of admissible strategies, and the intensity of interactions and the level of heterogeneity among players. This is achieved by introducing a suitable linear derivative of the value functions with respect to unilateral deviations of strategies and via analyzing the sensitivity processes of state dynamics with respect to controls.
  For games with mean-field type interactions, $\alpha$ is shown to decay to zero as the number of players goes to infinity, even with heterogeneity in state dynamics, cost functions, and admissible strategy classes. For distributed games, if a static potential function can be derived from the cost functions, then $\alpha=0$. For crowd aversion games, $\alpha$ is capable of capturing the subtle difference between the choice of admissible strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16962v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Guo, Xinyu Li, Yufei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
