<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 05:01:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-negative Martingale Solutions to the Stochastic Porous Medium Equation with Sticky Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct non-negative martingale solutions to the stochastic porous medium equation in one dimension with homogeneous Dirichlet boundary conditions which exhibit a type of sticky behavior at zero. The construction uses the stochastic Faedo--Galerkin method via spatial semidiscretization, so that the pre-limiting system is given by a finite-dimensional diffusion with Wentzell boundary condition. We derive uniform moment estimates for the discrete systems by an Aubin-Lions-type interpolation argument, which enables us to implement a general weak convergence approach for the construction of martingale solutions of an SPDE using a Skorokhod representation-type result for non-metrizable spaces. We rely on a stochastic argument based on the occupation time formula for continuous semimartingales for the identification of the diffusion coefficient in the presence of an indicator function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05924v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Hambly, D\"orte Kreher, Konstantins Starovoitovs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing time of the torus shuffle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a theorem that reduces bounding the mixing time of a card shuffle to verifying a condition that involves only triplets of cards. Then we use it to analyze a classic model of card shuffling.
  In 1988, Diaconis introduced the following Markov chain. Cards are arranged in an $n$ by $n$ grid. Each step, choose a row or column, uniformly at random, and cyclically rotate it by one unit in a random direction. He conjectured that the mixing time is ${\rm O}(n^3 \log n)$. We obtain a bound that is within a poly log factor of the conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06006v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olena Blumberg, Ben Morris, Alto Senda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Averaging principle for semilinear slow-fast rough PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the averaging principle for a class of semilinear slow-fast stochastic partial differential equations driven by finite-dimensional rough multiplicative noise. Specifically, the slow component is driven by a general random rough path, while the fast component is driven by a Brownian rough path. Using controlled rough path theory and the classical Khasminskii's time discretization scheme, we demonstrate that the slow component converges strongly to the solution of the corresponding averaged equation under the H\"{o}lder topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06089v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miaomiao Li, Yunzhang Li, Bin Pei, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian dynamics: the governing equations of probability density functions for nonlinear dynamical systems with combined fractional Gaussian and Gaussian white noises</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper aims to investigate the non-Markovian dynamics. The governing equations are derived for probability density functions (PDFs) of non-Markovian stochastic responses to nonlinear dynamical systems (NDSs) excited by combined fractional Gaussian noises (FGNs) and Gaussian white noises (GWNs). The main difficulty here, is that, NDSs excited by FGNs cannot be augmented by filters excited by GWNs, leading to the inapplicability of It\^o stochastic calculus theory. Thus, in the present work, based on fractional Wick It\^o Skorohod integral and rough path theory, new non-Markovian probability density evolution methods (PDEMs) are established to derive theoretically the fractional-power time varying term-dependent governing equations (FPTV-GEs) for PDFs of non-Markovian stochastic responses to NDSs excited by FGNs and GWNs, which is a breakthrough to stochastic dynamics. Then, we extend an efficient algorithm, the local discontinuous Galerkin method, to numerically solve the FPTV-GEs. Remarkably, this proposed method attains a higher accuracy compared to the prevalent methods such as finite difference, path integral and Monte Carlo methods, and boasts a broader applicability than the path integral method, which fails to solve the FPTV-GEs for PDFs of non-Markovian stochastic responses. Finally, several numerical examples are illustrated to verify the proposed scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06131v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Pei, Lifang Feng, Yunzhang Li, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictions of some reinforced processes to subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that the restriction of the vertex-reinforced jump process to a subset of the vertex set is a mixture of vertex-reinforced jump processes. A similar statement holds for the non-linear hyperbolic supersymmetric sigma model. This is then applied to vertex-reinforced jump processes on subdivided versions of graphs of bounded degree, where every edge is replaced by a finite sequence of edges. We prove that discrete-time processes associated to suitable corresponding restrictions are mixtures of positive recurrent Markov chains. We also deduce a similar statement for edge-reinforced random walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06195v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margherita Disertori, Franz Merkl, Silke W. W. Rolles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the longest/shortest negative excursion of a L\'evy risk process and related quantities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze some distributions involving the longest and shortest negative excursions of spectrally negative L\'evy processes using the binomial expansion approach. More specifically, we study the distributions of such excursions and related quantities such as the joint distribution of the shortest and longest negative excursion and their difference (also known as the range) over a random and infinite horizon time. Our results are applied to address new Parisian ruin problems, stochastic ordering and the number near-maximum distress periods showing the superiority of the binomial expansion approach for such cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06245v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Lkabous, Z. Palmowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverting the operation of conditioning a branching process on extinction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well-known that conditioning a supercritical (multi-type) branching process on the event that it eventually becomes extinct yields a subcritical branching process. We study the corresponding inverse problem: given a subcritical branching process, does there exist a supercritical branching process with the property that when we condition it on extinction, we get back the original subcritical branching process? We show that such a supercritical branching process (which we call a conjugate branching process) exists under mild hypotheses on the original subcritical branching process. We also show by example that if there are at least two types, then the conjugate branching process is not necessarily unique. Our results are relevant to the problem of constructing natural random planar maps whose scaling limit is given by supercritical Liouville quantum gravity. Moreover, conjugate branching processes can also be used to give alternative evolutionary hypotheses in cancer modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06301v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ewain Gwynne, Jiaqi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment-based approach for two erratic KPZ scaling limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A recent paper of Tsai shows that the first few moments of a stochastic flow in the space of measures completely determine its law. Here we give another proof of this result for the particular case of the one-dimensional multiplicative stochastic heat equation (mSHE), and then we investigate two corollaries. The first one recovers a recent result of Hairer on a ``variance blowup" problem related to the KPZ equation , albeit in a much weaker topology. The second one recovers a KPZ scaling limit result related to random walks in random environments, but in a weaker topology. In these two problems, we furthermore explain why it is hard to directly use the martingale characterization of the mSHE, the chaos expansion, or other known methods. Using the moment-based approach avoids technicalities, leading to a short proof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06571v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalin Parekh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Exponential Lie Series and a Chen-Strichartz Formula for Levy Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we derive a Chen-Strichartz formula for stochastic differential equations driven by Levy processes, that is, we derive a series expansion of the logarithm of the flowmap of the stochastic differential equation in terms of commutators of vector fields with stochastic coefficients, and we provide an explicit formula for the components in this series. The stochastic components are generated by the Levy processes that drive the stochastic differential equation and their quadratic variation and power jumps; the vector fields are given as linear combinations of commutators of elements in the pre-Lie Magnus expansion generated by the original vector fields governing our stochastic differential equation. In particular, we show the logarithm of the flowmap is a Lie series. These results extend previous results for deterministic differential equations and continuous stochastic differential equations. For these, the Chen-Strichartz series has shown to play a pivotal role in the design of numerical integration schemes that preserve qualitative properties of the solution such as the construction of geometric numerical schemes and in the context of efficient numerical schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06827v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kurusch Ebrahimi-Fard, Frederic Patras, Anke Wiese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Wasserstein Barycenters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a generalization, where negative weights are allowed, of the Wasserstein barycenter of $n$ probability measures. The barycenter is found, as usual, as a minimum of a functional. In this paper, we prove existence of a minimizer for probability measures on a separable Hilbert space and uniqueness in the case of one positive coefficient and $n-1$ negative ones. In the one-dimensional case, we characterize the quantile function of the unique minimum as the orthogonal projection of the $L^2$-barycenter of the quantiles on the cone of nonincreasing functions in $L^2(0,1)$. Further, we provide a stability estimate in dimension one and a counterexample to uniqueness in $\mathbb{R}^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06838v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Tornabene, Marco Veneroni, Giuseppe Savar\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quenched invariance principle for random walks in random environments admitting a cycle decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a class of non-reversible, continuous-time random walks in random environments on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ that admit a cycle representation with finite cycle length. The law of the transition rates, taking values in $[0, \infty)$, is assumed to be stationary and ergodic with respect to space shifts. Moreover, the transition rate from $x$ to $y$, denoted by $c^\omega(x,y)$, is a superposition of non-negative random weights on oriented cycles that contain the edge $(x,y)$. We prove a quenched invariance principle under moment conditions that are comparable to the well-known p-q moment condition of Andres, Deuschel, and Slowik [2] for the random conductance model. A key ingredient in proving the sublinearity is an energy estimate for the non-symmetric generator. Our result extends that of Deuschel and K\"osters [12] beyond strong ellipticity and bounded cycle lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06861v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Dominique Deuschel, Martin Slowik, Weile Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correction to: Multivariate CARMA processes, continuous-time state space models and complete regularity of the innovations of the sampled processes, Bernoulli 18, pp. 46-63, 2012</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A serious flaw in the proof of the equivalence of continuous time state space models and MCARMA processes spotted in Fasen and Schenk (2024) is corrected. We point out that likewise an issue in the proof of Theorem 3.2 in Brockwell and Schlemm (2013) can be resolved and, hence, any MCARMA process and linear state space model has both a controller and an observer canonical representation. Equivalently, the transfer function has both a left and right matrix fraction representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06935v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Stelzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distribution dependent SDEs with by multiplicative fractional noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The well-posedness is investigated for distribution dependent stochastic differential equations driven by fractional Brownian motion with Hurst parameter $H\in (\ff {\sq 5-1} 2,1)$ and distribution dependent multiplicative noise. To this aim, we introduce a H\"older space of probability measure paths which is a complete metric space under a new metric. Our arguments rely on a mix of contraction mapping principle on the H\"older space and fractional calculus tools. We also establish the large and moderate deviation principles for this type of equations via the weak convergence criteria in the factional Brownian motion setting, which extend previously known results in the additive setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06974v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiliang Fan, Shao-Qin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a connection between total positivity and last-success stopping problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the optimal stopping problem of maximising the expected payoff from selecting the last success in a sequence of independent Bernoulli trials. The total positivity of the Markov chain embedded in the success epochs of the trials is exploited to prove the optimality of the myopic strategy for both unimodal stopping and continuation payoffs. In contrast, the problem is shown to be nonmonotone for oscillating payoffs, alternating between two values. The myopic strategy is demonstrated not to be a threshold rule. Lastly, the optimality of the myopic policy is established for the $\ell$th-to-$m$th last-success problem based on a total positivity argument. An illustrative example is given to compute the asymptotic threshold and winning probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07103v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zakaria Derbazi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On differentiability and mass distributions of topologically typical multivariate Archimedean copulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Copulas, in particular Archimedean copulas are commonly viewed as analytically nice and regular objects. Motivated by a recently established result sta\-ting that the first partial derivatives of bivariate copulas can exhibit surprisingly pathological behavior, we focus on the class of $d$-dimensional Archimedean copulas denoted by $\mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$ and show that partial derivatives of order $(d-1)$ can be sur\-pri\-singly irregular as well. In fact, we prove the existence of Archimedean copulas $C \in \mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$ whose $(d-1)$-st order partial derivatives are pathological in the sense that for almost every $\mathbf{x} \in [0,1]^{d-1}$ the derivative $\partial_1...\partial_{d-1}C(\mathbf{x},y)$ does not exist on a dense set of $y \in (0,1)$. \\ Since the existence of mixed partial derivatives of order $(d-1)$ of a copula $C$ is closely related to the existence of a discrete component, we also study mass distributions of Archimedean copulas. Building upon the interplay between Archimedean copulas and so-called Williamson measures we show that absolute continuity, discreteness and singularity of the Williamson measure propagates to the associated Archimedean copula and vice versa. Moreover, we prove the fact that the sub-family of $\mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$ consisting of copulas whose absolutely continuous, discrete and singular component have full support is dense in $\mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$. \\ Finally, viewing $\mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$ in the light of Baire categories, we show that, in contrast to the space of bivariate copulas, a topologically typical $d$-dimensional Archimedean copula $C$ is not absolutely continuous but has degenerated discrete component, implying that pathological elements are rare in $\mathcal{C}_{ar}^d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07113v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Dietrich, Wolfgang Trutschnig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing on the cycle with constant size perturbation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Considering a Markov chain defined on a cycle, near-quadratic improvement of mixing is shown when only a subtle perturbation is introduced to the structure and non-reversible transition probabilities are used. More precisely, a mixing time of $O(n^{\frac{k+2}{k+1}})$ can be achieved by adding $k$ random edges to the cycle, keeping $k$ fixed while $n\to\infty$. The construction builds upon a biased random walk along the cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07125v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Feng, Bal\'azs Gerencs\'er</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rough differential equations in the flow approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07157v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show how the flow approach of Duch, with elementary differentials as coordinates, can be used to prove local well-posedness for rough stochastic differential equations driven by fractional Brownian motion with Hurst index $H &gt; \frac{1}{4}$. A novelty appearing here is that we use coordinates for the flow that are indexed by trees rather than multi-indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07157v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Chandra, L\'eonard Ferdinand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov chains on trees: almost lower and upper directed cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition matrix of a Markov chain $(X_k,k\geq 0)$ on a finite or infinite rooted tree is said to be almost upper-directed if, given $X_k$, the node $X_{k+1}$ is either a descendant of $X_k$ or the parent of $X_k$. It is said to be almost lower-directed if given $X_k$, $X_{k+1}$ is either an ancestor of $X_k$ or a child of $X_k$.
  These models include nearest neighbor Markov chains on trees.
  Under an irreducibility assumption, we show that every almost upper-directed transition matrix on infinite (locally finite) trees has some invariant measures. An invariant measure $\pi$ is expressed thanks to a determinantal formula. We give general explicit criteria for recurrence and positive recurrence. An efficient algorithm (the leaf addition algorithm) of independent interest allows $\pi$ to be computed on many trees, without resorting to linear algebra considerations.
  Flajolet, in a series of papers, provided some relations between continuous fractions, generating functions of weighted M\"otzkin paths, and used them in connection with the analysis of birth and death processes. These fruitful representations made it possible to establish many formulae for continuous fractions. Analogous considerations appear here: this type of study can be extended to weighted paths on trees, whose generating functions can also be expressed, this time in terms of multicontinuous fractions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07158v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Fredes, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Marckert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layered Hill esimator for extreme data in clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new estimator is proposed for estimating the tail exponent of a heavy-tailed distribution. This estimator, referred to as the layered Hill estimator, is a generalization of the traditional Hill estimator, building upon a layered structure formed by clusters of extreme values. We argue that the layered Hill estimator provides a robust alternative to the traditional approach, exhibiting desirable asymptotic properties such as consistency and asymptotic normality for the tail exponent. Both theoretical analysis and simulation studies demonstrate that the layered Hill estimator shows significantly better and more robust performance, particularly when a portion of the extreme data is missing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05808v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taegyu Kang, Takashi Owada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive Online Smoother with Closed-Form Solutions and Information-Theoretic Lag Selection for Conditional Gaussian Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05870v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data assimilation (DA) combines partial observations with a dynamical model to improve state estimation. Filter-based DA uses only past and present data and is the prerequisite for real-time forecasts. Smoother-based DA exploits both past and future observations. It aims to fill in missing data, provide more accurate estimations, and develop high-quality datasets. However, the standard smoothing procedure requires using all historical state estimations, which is storage-demanding, especially for high-dimensional systems. This paper develops an adaptive-lag online smoother for a large class of complex dynamical systems with strong nonlinear and non-Gaussian features, which has important applications to many real-world problems. The adaptive lag allows the DA to utilize only observations within a nearby window, significantly reducing computational storage. Online lag adjustment is essential for tackling turbulent systems, where temporal autocorrelation varies significantly over time due to intermittency, extreme events, and nonlinearity. Based on the uncertainty reduction in the estimated state, an information criterion is developed to systematically determine the adaptive lag. Notably, the mathematical structure of these systems facilitates the use of closed analytic formulae to calculate the online smoother and the adaptive lag, avoiding empirical tunings as in ensemble-based DA methods. The adaptive online smoother is applied to studying three important scientific problems. First, it helps detect online causal relationships between state variables. Second, its advantage of computational storage is illustrated via Lagrangian DA, a high-dimensional nonlinear problem. Finally, the adaptive smoother advances online parameter estimation with partial observations, emphasizing the role of the observed extreme events in accelerating convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05870v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marios Andreou, Nan Chen, Yingda Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal drug application on stochastic cancer growth: an approach through path integral control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide an overview of an optimal control problem within a stochastic model of tumor growth, which includes drug application. The model comprises two stochastic differential equations (SDE) representing the diffusion of nutrient and drug concentrations. To account for various uncertainties, stochastic terms are incorporated into the deterministic framework, capturing random disturbances. Control variables, informed by medical principles, are used to regulate drug and nutrient concentrations. In defining the optimal control problem, a stochastic cost function can be established, and a Feynman-type path integral control approach would lead to an optimal drug treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05968v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noelymar Farinacci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Exact Mixing Time for Trees of Fixed Order and Diameter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize the extremal structure for the exact mixing time for random walks on trees $\mathcal{T}_{n,d}$ of order $n$ with diameter $d$. Given a graph $G=(V,E)$, let $H(v,\pi)$ denote the expected length of an optimal stopping rule from vertex $v$ to the stationary distributon $\pi$. We show that the quantity $\max_{G \in \mathcal{T}_{n,d} } T_{\mbox{mix}}(G) = \max_{G \in \mathcal{T}_{n,d} } \max_{v \in V} H(v,\pi)$ is achieved uniquely by the balanced double broom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06247v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Beveridge, Kristin Heysse, Rhys O'Higgins, Lola Vescovo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Resolving Non-Preemptivity in Multitask Scheduling: An Optimal Algorithm in Deterministic and Stochastic Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The efficient scheduling of multi-task jobs across multiprocessor systems has become increasingly critical with the rapid expansion of computational systems. This challenge, known as Multiprocessor Multitask Scheduling (MPMS), is essential for optimizing the performance and scalability of applications in fields such as cloud computing and deep learning. In this paper, we study the MPMS problem under both deterministic and stochastic models, where each job is composed of multiple tasks and can only be completed when all its tasks are finished. We introduce $\mathsf{NP}$-$\mathsf{SRPT}$, a non-preemptive variant of the Shortest Remaining Processing Time (SRPT) algorithm, designed to accommodate scenarios with non-preemptive tasks. Our algorithm achieves a competitive ratio of $\ln \alpha + \beta + 1$ for minimizing response time, where $\alpha$ represents the ratio of the largest to the smallest job workload, and $\beta$ captures the ratio of the largest non-preemptive task workload to the smallest job workload. We further establish that this competitive ratio is order-optimal when the number of processors is fixed. For stochastic systems modeled as M/G/N queues, where job arrivals follow a Poisson process and task workloads are drawn from a general distribution, we prove that $\mathsf{NP}$-$\mathsf{SRPT}$ achieves asymptotically optimal mean response time as the traffic intensity $\rho$ approaches $1$, assuming the task size distribution has finite support. Moreover, the asymptotic optimality extends to cases with infinite task size distributions under mild probabilistic assumptions, including the standard M/M/N model. Experimental results validate the effectiveness of $\mathsf{NP}$-$\mathsf{SRPT}$, demonstrating its asymptotic optimality in both theoretical and practical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06348v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of weights on a connected finite graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06393v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On a connected finite graph, we propose an evolution of weights including Ollivier's Ricci flow as a special case. During the evolution process, on each edge, the speed of change of weight is exactly the difference between the Wasserstein distance related to two probability measures and certain graph distance. Here the probability measure may be chosen as an $\alpha$-lazy one-step random walk, an $\alpha$-lazy two-step random walk, or a general probability measure. Based on the ODE theory, we show that the initial value problem has a unique global solution.
  A discrete version of the above evolution is applied to the problem of community detection. Our algorithm is based on such a discrete evolution, where probability measures are chosen as $\alpha$-lazy one-step random walk and $\alpha$-lazy two-step random walk respectively. Note that the later measure has not been used in previous works [2, 16, 20, 23]. Here, as in [20], only one surgery needs to be performed after the last iteration. Moreover, our algorithm is much easier than those of [2, 16, 20], which were all based on Lin-Lu-Yau's Ricci curvature. The code is available at https://github.com/mjc191812/Evolution-of-weights-on-a-connected-finite-graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06393v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jicheng Ma, Yunyan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Eigenspaces and Pseudospectra of Nonnormal and Defective Matrix-Valued Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider nonnormal matrix-valued dynamical systems with discrete time. For an eigenvalue of matrix, the number of times it appears as a root of the characteristic polynomial is called the algebraic multiplicity. On the other hand, the geometric multiplicity is the dimension of the linear space of eigenvectors associated with that eigenvalue. If the former exceeds the latter, then the eigenvalue is said to be defective and the matrix becomes nondiagonalizable by any similarity transformation. The discrete-time of our dynamics is identified with the geometric multiplicity of the zero eigenvalue $\lambda_0=0$. Its algebraic multiplicity takes about half of the matrix size at $t=1$ and increases stepwise in time, which keeps excess to the geometric multiplicity until their coincidence at the final time. Our model exhibits relaxation processes from far-from-normal to near-normal matrices, in which the defectivity of $\lambda_0$ is recovering in time. We show that such processes are realized as size reductions of pseudospectrum including $\lambda_0$. Here the pseudospectra are the domains on the complex plane which are not necessarily exact spectra but in which the resolvent of matrix takes extremely large values. The defective eigenvalue $\lambda_0$ is sensitive to perturbation and the eigenvalues of the perturbed systems are distributed densely in the pseudospectrum including $\lambda_0$. By constructing generalized eigenspace for $\lambda_0$, we give the Jordan block decomposition for the resolvent of matrix and characterize the pseudospectrum dynamics. Numerical study of the systems perturbed by Gaussian random matrices supports the validity of the present analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06472v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saori Morimoto, Makoto Katori, Tomoyuki Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counterexamples to a Weitz-Style Reduction for Multispin Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06541v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a seminal paper, Weitz showed that for two-state spin systems, such as the Ising and hardcore models from statistical physics, correlation decay on trees implies correlation decay on arbitrary graphs. The key gadget in Weitz's reduction has been instrumental in recent advances in approximate counting and sampling, from analysis of local Markov chains like Glauber dynamics to the design of deterministic algorithms for estimating the partition function. A longstanding open problem in the field has been to find such a reduction for more general multispin systems like the uniform distribution over proper colorings of a graph.
  In this paper, we show that for a rich class of multispin systems, including the ferromagnetic Potts model, there are fundamental obstacles to extending Weitz's reduction to the multispin setting. A central component of our investigation is establishing nonconvexity of the image of the belief propagation functional, the standard tool for analyzing spin systems on trees. On the other hand, we provide evidence of convexity for the antiferromagnetic Potts model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06541v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuikui Liu, Nitya Mani, Francisco Pernice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kaczmarz Kac Walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06614v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kaczmarz method is a way to iteratively solve a linear system of equations $Ax = b$. One interprets the solution $x$ as the point where hyperplanes intersect and then iteratively projects an approximate solution onto these hyperplanes to get better and better approximations. We note a somewhat related idea: one could take two random hyperplanes and project one into the orthogonal complement of the other. This leads to a sequence of linear systems $A^{(k)} x = b^{(k)}$ which is fast to compute, preserves the original solution and whose small singular values grow like $\sigma_{\ell}(A^{(k)}) \sim \exp(k/n^2) \cdot \sigma_{\ell}(A)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06614v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Steinerberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average signature of geodesic paths in compact Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06760v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For any compact Lie group $G$, we introduce a novel notion of average signature $\mathbb A(G)$ valued in its tensor Lie algebra, by taking the average value of the signature of the unique length-minimizing geodesics between all pairs of generic points in $G$. We prove that the trace spectrum of $\mathbb A(G)$ recovers certain geometric quantities of $G$, including the dimension, the diameter, the volume and the scalar curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06760v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Liu, Shi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Transitions via Complex Extensions of Markov Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study algebraic properties of partition functions, particularly the location of zeros, through the lens of rapidly mixing Markov chains. The classical Lee-Yang program initiated the study of phase transitions via locating complex zeros of partition functions. Markov chains, besides serving as algorithms, have also been used to model physical processes tending to equilibrium. In many scenarios, rapid mixing of Markov chains coincides with the absence of phase transitions (complex zeros). Prior works have shown that the absence of phase transitions implies rapid mixing of Markov chains. We reveal a converse connection by lifting probabilistic tools for the analysis of Markov chains to study complex zeros of partition functions.
  Our motivating example is the independence polynomial on $k$-uniform hypergraphs, where the best-known zero-free regime has been significantly lagging behind the regime where we have rapidly mixing Markov chains for the underlying hypergraph independent sets. Specifically, the Glauber dynamics is known to mix rapidly on independent sets in a $k$-uniform hypergraph of maximum degree $\Delta$ provided that $\Delta \lesssim 2^{k/2}$. On the other hand, the best-known zero-freeness around the point $1$ of the independence polynomial on $k$-uniform hypergraphs requires $\Delta \le 5$, the same bound as on a graph.
  By introducing a complex extension of Markov chains, we lift an existing percolation argument to the complex plane, and show that if $\Delta \lesssim 2^{k/2}$, the Markov chain converges in a complex neighborhood, and the independence polynomial itself does not vanish in the same neighborhood. In the same regime, our result also implies central limit theorems for the size of a uniformly random independent set, and deterministic approximation algorithms for the number of hypergraph independent sets of size $k \le \alpha n$ for some constant $\alpha$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06857v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingcheng Liu, Chunyang Wang, Yitong Yin, Yixiao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric estimation of trend for stochastic differential equations driven by multiplicative stochastic volatility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06865v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss nonparametric estimation of the trend coefficient in models governed by a stochastic differential equation driven by a multiplicative stochastic volatility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06865v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. L. S. Prakasa Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigorous enclosure of Lyapunov exponents of stochastic flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07064v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a powerful and general method to provide arbitrarily accurate rigorous upper and lower bounds for Lyapunov exponents of stochastic flows. Our approach is based on computer-assisted tools, the adjoint method and established results on the ergodicity of diffusion processes. We do not require any structural assumptions on the stochastic system and work under mild hypoellipticity conditions outside of perturbative regimes. Therefore, our method allows for the treatment of systems that were so far inaccessible from existing mathematical tools. We demonstrate our method to exhibit the chaotic nature of three non-Hamiltonian systems. Finally, we show that our approach is robust to continuation methods to produce bounds on Lyapunov exponents for large parameter regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07064v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Breden, Hugo Chu, Jeroen S. W. Lamb, Martin Rasmussen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-sum Dynkin games under common and independent Poisson constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07134v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Zero-sum Dynkin games under the Poisson constraint have been studied widely in the recent literature. In such a game the players are only allowed to stop at the event times of a Poisson process. The constraint can be modelled in two different ways: either both players share the same Poisson process (the common constraint) or each player has her own Poisson process (the independent constraint). In the Markovian case where the payoff is given by a pair of functions of an underlying diffusion, we give sufficient conditions under which the solution of the game (the value function, and the optimal stopping sets for each player) under the common (respectively, independent) constraint is also the solution of the game under the independent (respectively, common) constraint. Roughly speaking, if the stopping sets of the maximiser and minimiser in the game under the common constraint are disjoint, then the solution to the game is the same under both the common and the independent constraint. However, the fact that the stopping sets are disjoint in the game under the independent constraint, is not sufficient to guarantee that the solution of the game under the independent constraint is also the solution under the common constraint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07134v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Hobson, Gechun Liang, Edward Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on hyperbolic sphere packings: On a conjecture by Cohn and Zhao</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove sphere packing density bounds in hyperbolic space (and more generally irreducible symmetric spaces of noncompact type), which were conjectured by Cohn and Zhao and generalize Euclidean bounds by Cohn and Elkies. We work within the Bowen-Radin framework of packing density and replace the use of the Poisson summation formula in the proof of the Euclidean bound by Cohn and Elkies with an analogous formula arising from methods used in the theory of mathematical quasicrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07139v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Wackenhuth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-frequency analysis of parabolic stochastic PDEs with multiplicative noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.04145</link>
      <description>arXiv:1908.04145v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the stochastic heat equation driven by a multiplicative Gaussian noise that is white in time and spatially homogeneous in space. Assuming that the spatial correlation function is given by a Riesz kernel of order $\alpha \in (0,1)$, we prove a central limit theorem for power variations and other related functionals of the solution. To our surprise, there is no asymptotic bias despite the low regularity of the noise coefficient in the multiplicative case. We trace this circumstance back to cancellation effects between error terms arising naturally in second-order limit theorems for power variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1908.04145v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carsten Chong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The cut norm and Sampling Lemmas for unbounded kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.07581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.07581v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generalizing the bounded kernel results of Borgs, Chayes, Lov\'asz, S\'os and Vesztergombi (2008), we prove two Sampling Lemmas for unbounded kernels with respect to the cut norm. On the one hand, we show that given a (symmetric) kernel $U\in L^p([0,1]^2)$ for some $3&lt;p&lt;\infty$, the cut norm of a random $k$-sample of $U$ is with high probability within $O(k^{-\frac14+\frac{1}{4p}})$ of the cut norm of $U$. The cut norm of the sample has a strong bias to being larger than the original, allowing us to actually obtain a stronger high probability bound of order $O(k^{-\frac 12+\frac1p+\varepsilon})$ for how much smaller it can be (for any $p&gt;2$ here). These results are then partially extended to the case of vector valued kernels. On the other hand, we show that with high probability, the $k$-samples are also close to $U$ in the cut metric, albeit with a weaker bound of order $O((\ln k)^{-\frac12+\frac1{2p}})$ (for any appropriate $p&gt;2$). As a corollary, we obtain that whenever $U\in L^p$ with $p&gt;4$, the $k$-samples converge almost surely to $U$ in the cut metric as $k\to\infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.07581v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panna T\'imea Fekete, D\'avid Kunszenti-Kov\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLT for real beta-ensembles at high temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.05516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.05516v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a central limit theorem for the fluctuations of the linear statistics in the $\beta$-ensemble of dimension $N$ at a temperature proportional to $N$ and with confining smooth potential. In this regime, the particles do not accumulate in a compact set as in the fixed $\beta&gt;0$ case which results in an equilibrium measure supported on the whole real line. The space of test functions for which the CLT holds includes bounded $C^2$ functions. The method that we use is based on a change of variables in the partition function introduced in Johansson [1998] and allows to deduce the convergence of the Laplace transform of the recentred linear statistics towards the Laplace transform of the normal distribution. It is obtained by the inversion of the master operator, which is the main contribution of the present paper, by following the scheme developed in Hardy, Lambert [2019] in the compact case. In the high-temperature regime, the master operator contains an additional differential term due to entropic effects which makes it an unbounded operator. The techniques used in this article involve Schr\"odinger operators theory as well as concentration of measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.05516v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/24-EJP1233</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electronic Journal of Probability 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Charlie Dworaczek Guera, Ronan Memin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Inequalities for Sums of Markov Dependent Random Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.02150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.02150v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give Hoeffding and Bernstein-type concentration inequalities for the largest eigenvalue of sums of random matrices arising from a Markov chain. We consider time-dependent matrix-valued functions on a general state space, generalizing previous results that had only considered Hoeffding-type inequalities, and only for time-independent functions on a finite state space. In particular, we study a kind of noncommutative moment generating function, provide tight bounds on this object, and use a method of Garg et al. to turn this into tail bounds. Our proof proceeds spectrally, bounding the norm of a certain perturbed operator. In the process we make an interesting connection to dynamical systems and Banach space theory to prove a crucial result on the limiting behavior of our moment generating function that may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.02150v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joe Neeman, Bobby Shi, Rachel Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLE partition functions via conformal welding of random surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05177v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: SLE curves describe the scaling limit of interfaces from many 2D lattice models. Heuristically speaking, the SLE partition function is the continuum counterpart of the partition function of the corresponding discrete model. It is well known that conformally welding of Liouville quantum gravity (LQG) surfaces gives SLE curves as the interfaces. In this paper, we demonstrate in several settings how the SLE partition function arises from conformal welding of LQG surfaces. The common theme is that we conformally weld a collection of canonical LQG surfaces which produces a topological configuration with more than one conformal structure. Conditioning on the conformal moduli, the surface after welding is described by Liouville conformal field theory (LCFT), and the density of the random moduli contains the SLE partition function for the interfaces as a multiplicative factor. The settings we treat includes the multiple SLE for $\kappa\in (0,4)$, the flow lines of imaginary geometry on the disk with boundary marked points, and the boundary Green function. These results demonstrate an alternative approach to construct and study the SLE partition function, which complements the traditional method based on stochastic calculus and differential equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05177v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Sun, Pu Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained quantization for a uniform distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Constrained quantization for a Borel probability measure refers to the idea of estimating a given probability by a discrete probability with a finite number of supporting points lying on a specific set. The specific set is known as the constraint of the constrained quantization. A quantization without a constraint is known as an unconstrained quantization, which traditionally in the literature is known as quantization. Constrained quantization has recently been introduced by Pandey and Roychowdhury. In this paper, for a uniform distribution with support lying on a side of an equilateral triangle, and the constraint as the union of the other two sides, we obtain the optimal sets of $n$-points and the $n$th constrained quantization errors for all positive integers $n$. We also calculate the constrained quantization dimension and the constrained quantization coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16615v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pigar Biteng, Mathieu Caguiat, Dipok Deb, Mrinal Kanti Roychowdhury, Beatriz Vela Villanueva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchy of KPZ limits arising from directed random walk models in random media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06073v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a generalized model of random walk in dynamical random environment, and we show that the multiplicative-noise stochastic heat equation (SHE) describes the fluctuations of the quenched density at a certain precise location in the tail. The distribution of transition kernels is fixed rather than changing under the diffusive rescaling of space-time, i.e., there is no critical tuning of the model parameters when scaling to the stochastic PDE limit. The proof is done by pushing the methods developed in [arxiv 2304.14279, arXiv 2311.09151] to their maximum, substantially weakening the assumptions and obtaining fairly sharp conditions under which one expects to see the SHE arise in a wide variety of random walk models in random media. In particular we are able to get rid of conditions such as nearest-neighbor interaction as well as spatial independence of quenched transition kernels. Moreover, we observe an entire hierarchy of moderate deviation exponents at which the SHE can be found, confirming a physics prediction of J. Hass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06073v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalin Parekh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strichartz estimates for orthonormal functions and probabilistic convergence of density functions of compact operators on manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13764v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish some Strichartz estimates for orthonormal functions and probabilistic convergence of density functions related to compact operators on manifolds. Firstly, we present the suitable bound of $\int_{a\leq|s|\leq b}e^{isx}s^{-1+i\gamma}ds$ for the cases $\gamma \in \mathbb{R},a\geq0,b&gt;0,$ $\gamma \in \mathbb{R},\gamma\neq0,a,b\in \mathbb{R}$ and $\gamma \in \mathbb{R}$, which extends the result of Page 204 of Vega (199-211,IMA Vol. Math. Appl., 42, 1992.) Secondly, we prove that $\left|\gamma\int_{a}^{b}e^{isx}s^{-1+i\gamma}ds\right|\leq C(1+|\gamma|)^{2}(\gamma \in \mathbb{R},a,b\in \mathbb{R}),$ where $C$ is independent of $\gamma,a, b$, which extends Lemma 1 of Bez et al. (Forum of Mathematics, Sigma, 9(2021), 1-52). Thirdly, we extend the result of Theorems 8, 9 of R. Frank, J. Sabin (Amer. J. Math. 139(2017), 1649-1691.) with the aid of the suitable bound of the above complex integrals established in this paper. Fourthly, we establish the Strichartz estimates for orthonormal functions related to Boussinesq operator on the real line for both small time interval and large time interval and on the torus with small time interval; we also establish the convergence result of some compact operators in Schatten norm. Fifthly, we establish the convergence result related to nonlinear part of the solution to some operator equations in Schatten spaces. Finally, inspired by the work of Hadama and Yamamoto (Probabilistic Strichartz estimates in Schatten classes and their applications to Hartree equation, arxiv:2311.02713v1.), for $\gamma_{0}\in \mathfrak{S}^{2}$, we establish the probabilistic convergence of density functions of compact operator on manifolds with full randomization, which improves the result of Corollary 1.2 of Bez et al. (Selecta Math. 26(2020), 24 pp) in the probabilistic sense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13764v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Yan, Jinqiao Duan, Jianhua Huang, Haoyuan Xu, Meihua Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong solutions to degenerate SDEs and uniqueness for degenerate Fokker-Planck equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17135v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the existence of probabilistically strong solutions for large classes of possibly degenerate stochastic differential equations with locally Sobolev-regular coefficients, using the restricted Yamada-Watanabe theorem. Our approach relies on existence results for the corresponding Fokker-Planck equation, combined with both novel and existing restricted pathwise uniqueness results for SDEs. Here, restricted pathwise uniqueness means pathwise uniqueness among a subclass of weak solutions to the SDE. Furthermore, we derive new uniqueness results for the Fokker-Planck equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17135v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Grube</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random spanning trees in random environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16830v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new spanning tree model called the random spanning tree in random environment (RSTRE), which interpolates between the uniform spanning tree and the minimum spanning tree as the inverse temperature (disorder strength) $\beta$ varies. On the complete graph with $n$ vertices and i.i.d.\ uniform disorder variables on the edges, we identify: (1) a low disorder regime with $\beta \leq C n/\log n$, where the diameter of the random spanning tree is typically of order $n^{1/2}$, the same as for the uniform spanning tree; (2) a high disorder regime with $\beta \geq n^{4/3} \log n$, where the diameter is typically of order $n^{1/3}$, the same as for the minimum spanning tree. We conjecture that for $\beta=n^{\alpha}$ with $\alpha \in (1, 4/3)$, the diameter is of order $n^{\gamma+o(1)}$ for some $\gamma=\gamma(\alpha)$ strictly between $1/2$ and $1/3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16830v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Makowiec, Michele Salvi, Rongfeng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Limit of the Tridiagonal Model for $\beta$-Dyson Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01633v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In previous work, a description of the result of applying the Householder tridiagonalization algorithm to a G$\beta$E random matrix is provided by Edelman and Dumitriu. The resulting tridiagonal ensemble makes sense for all $\beta&gt;0$, and has spectrum given by the $\beta$-ensemble for all $\beta&gt;0$. Moreover, the tridiagonal model has useful stochastic operator limits which was introduced and analyzed in subsequent studies.
  In this work, we analogously study the result of applying the Householder tridiagonalization algorithm to a G$\beta$E process which has eigenvalues governed by $\beta$-Dyson Brownian motion. We propose an explicit limit of the upper left $k \times k$ minor of the $n \times n$ tridiagonal process as $n \to \infty$ and $k$ remains fixed. We prove the result for $\beta=1$, and also provide numerical evidence for $\beta=1,2,4$. This leads us to conjecture the form of a dynamical $\beta$-stochastic Airy operator with smallest $k$ eigenvalues evolving according to the $n \to \infty$ limit of the largest, centered and re-scaled, $k$ eigenvalues of $\beta$-Dyson Brownian motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01633v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan Edelman, Sungwoo Jeong, Ron Nissim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Frictions are Fractional: Rough Noise in High-Frequency Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.16149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.16149v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The analysis of high-frequency financial data is often impeded by the presence of noise. This article is motivated by intraday return data in which market microstructure noise appears to be rough, that is, best captured by a continuous-time stochastic process that locally behaves as fractional Brownian motion. Assuming that the underlying efficient price process follows a continuous It\^o semimartingale, we derive consistent estimators and asymptotic confidence intervals for the roughness parameter of the noise and the integrated price and noise volatilities, in all cases where these quantities are identifiable. In addition to desirable features such as serial dependence of increments, compatibility between different sampling frequencies and diurnal effects, the rough noise model can further explain divergence rates in volatility signature plots that vary considerably over time and between assets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.16149v4</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carsten H. Chong, Thomas Delerue, Guoying Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-time expansion of characteristic functions in a rough volatility setting with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.00830v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive a higher-order asymptotic expansion of the conditional characteristic function of the increment of an It\^o semimartingale over a shrinking time interval. The spot characteristics of the It\^o semimartingale are allowed to have dynamics of general form. In particular, their paths can be rough, that is, exhibit local behavior like that of a fractional Brownian motion, while at the same time have jumps with arbitrary degree of activity. The expansion result shows the distinct roles played by the different features of the spot characteristics dynamics. As an application of our result, we construct a nonparametric estimator of the Hurst parameter of the diffusive volatility process from portfolios of short-dated options written on an underlying asset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.00830v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carsten H. Chong, Viktor Todorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and convergence of the Euler scheme for stochastic linear evolution equations in Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.08375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.08375v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For the Euler scheme of the stochastic linear evolution equations, discrete stochastic maximal $ L^p $-regularity estimate is established, and a sharp error estimate in the norm $ \|\cdot\|_{L^p((0,T)\times\Omega;L^q(\mathcal O))} $, $ p,q \in [2,\infty) $, is derived via a duality argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.08375v5</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binjie Li, Xiaoping Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A matrix model of a non-Hermitian $\beta$-ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.13184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.13184v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the first random matrix model of a complex $\beta$-ensemble. The matrices are tridiagonal and can be thought of as the non-Hermitian analogue of the Hermite $\beta$-ensembles discovered by Dumitriu and Edelman (J. Math. Phys., Vol. 43, 5830 (2002)). The main feature of the model is that the exponent $\beta$ of the Vandermonde determinant in the joint probability density function (j.p.d.f.) of the eigenvalues can take any value in $\mathbb{R}_+$. However, when $\beta=2$, the j.p.d.f. does not reduce to that of the Ginibre ensemble, but it contains an extra factor expressed as a multidimensional integral over the space of the eigenvectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.13184v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Mezzadri, Henry Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Noise for $f$-Differential Privacy via Anti-Concentration and Stochastic Dominance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08343v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish anti-concentration inequalities for additive noise mechanisms which achieve $f$-differential privacy ($f$-DP), a notion of privacy phrased in terms of a tradeoff function $f$ which limits the ability of an adversary to determine which individuals were in the database. We show that canonical noise distributions (CNDs), proposed by Awan and Vadhan (2023), match the anti-concentration bounds at half-integer values, indicating that their tail behavior is near-optimal. We also show that all CNDs are sub-exponential, regardless of the $f$-DP guarantee. In the case of log-concave CNDs, we show that they are the stochastically smallest noise compared to any other noise distributions with the same privacy guarantee. In terms of integer-valued noise, we propose a new notion of discrete CND and prove that a discrete CND always exists, can be constructed by rounding a continuous CND, and that the discrete CND is unique when designed for a statistic with sensitivity 1. We further show that the discrete CND at sensitivity 1 is stochastically smallest compared to other integer-valued noises. Our theoretical results shed light on the different types of privacy guarantees possible in the $f$-DP framework and can be incorporated in more complex mechanisms to optimize performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08343v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Awan, Aishwarya Ramasethu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Heavy-Tailed Hawkes Processes and the Microstructure of Rough Volatility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08784v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish the weak convergence of the intensity of a nearly-unstable Hawkes process with heavy-tailed kernel. Our result is used to derive a scaling limit for a financial market model where orders to buy or sell an asset arrive according to a Hawkes process with power-law kernel. After suitable rescaling the price-volatility process converges weakly to a rough Heston model. Our convergence result is much stronger than previously established ones that have either focused on light-tailed kernels or the convergence of integrated volatility process. The key is to establish the tightness of the family of rescaled volatility processes. This is achieved by introducing a new methods to establish the $C$-tightness of c\`adl\`ag processes based on the classical Kolmogorov-Chentsov tightness criterion for continuous processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08784v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Horst, Wei Xu, Rouyi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving correlations: A statistical method for generating synthetic data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01471v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a method to generate statistically representative synthetic data from a given dataset. The main goal of our method is for the created data set to mimic the between feature correlations present in the original data, while also offering a tunable parameter to influence the privacy level. In particular, our method constructs a statistical map by using the empirical conditional distributions between the features of the original dataset.
  We describe in detail our algorithms used both in the construction of a statistical map and how to use this map to generate synthetic observations.
  This approach is tested in three different ways: with a hand calculated example; a manufactured dataset; and a real world energy-related dataset of consumption/production of households in Madeira Island. We test our method's performance by comparing the datasets using the on Pearson correlation matrix.
  The proposed methodology is general in the sense that it does not rely on the used test dataset. We expect it to be applicable in a much broader context than indicated here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01471v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicklas J\"averg{\aa}rd, Rainey Lyons, Adrian Muntean, Jonas Forsman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision making in stochastic extensive form I: Stochastic decision forests</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12332v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A general theory of stochastic decision forests is developed to bridge two concepts of information flow: decision trees and refined partitions on the one side, filtrations from probability theory on the other. Instead of the traditional "nature" agent, this framework uses a single lottery draw to select a tree of a given decision forest. Each "personal" agent receives dynamic updates from an own oracle on the lottery outcome and makes partition-refining choices adapted to this information. This theory addresses a key limitation of existing approaches in extensive form theory, which struggle to model continuous-time stochastic processes, such as Brownian motion, as outcomes of "nature" decision making. Additionally, a class of stochastic decision forests based on time-indexed action paths is constructed, encompassing a wide range of models from the literature and laying the groundwork for an approximation theory for stochastic differential games in extensive form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12332v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Emanuel Rapsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
