<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>H\"offding's Kernels and Periodic Covariance Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We start with a brief survey on H\"offding's kernels, its properties, related spectral decompositions, and discuss marginal distributions of H\"offding measures. In the second part of this note, one-dimensional covariance representations are considered over compactly supported probability distributions in the class of periodic smooth functions. H\"offding's kernels are used in the construction of mixing measures whose marginals are multiples of given probability distributions, leading to optimal kernels in periodic covariance representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19719v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey G. Bobkov, Devraj Duggal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free Zero Bias and Infinite Divisibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The (classical) zero bias is a transformation of centered, finite variance probability distributions, often expressed in terms of random variables $X\mapsto X^\ast$, characterized by the functional equation \[ E[Xf(X)] = \sigma^2 E[f'(X^\ast)] \quad \text{for all }\; f\in C_c^\infty(\mathbb{R}) \] where $\sigma^2$ is the variance of $X$. The zero bias distribution is always absolutely continuous, and supported on the convex hull of the support of $X$. It is related to Stein's method, and has many applications throughout probability and statistics, most recently finding new characterization of infinite divisiblity and relation to the L\'evy--Khintchine formula.
  In this paper, we define a free probability analogue, the {\em free zero bias} transform $X\mapsto X^\circ$ acting on centered $L^2$ random variables, characterized by the functional equation \[ E[Xf(X)] = \sigma^2 E[\partial f(X^\circ)] \quad \text{for all }\; f\in C_c^\infty(\mathbb{R}) \] where $\partial f$ denotes the free difference quotient. We prove existence of this transform, and show that it has comparable smoothness and support properties to the classical zero bias. Our main theorem is an analogous characterization of free infinite divisibility in terms of the free zero bias, and a new understanding of free L\'evy measures. To achieve this, we develop several new operations on Cauchy transforms of probability distributions that are of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19860v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Larry Goldstein, Todd Kemp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong stochastic stability of cellular automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the notion of stochastic stability, already present in the literature in the context of smooth dynamical systems, for invariant measures of cellular automata perturbed by a random noise, and the notion of strongly stochastically stable cellular automaton. We study these notions on basic examples (nilpotent cellular automata, spreading symbols) using different methods inspired by those presented in \cite{MST19}. We then show that this notion of stability is not trivial by proving that a Turing machine cannot decide if a given invariant measure of a cellular automaton is stable under a uniform perturbation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19932v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Marsan, Mathieu Sablik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cutoff for the transience and mixing time of a SSEP with traps and consequences on the FEP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new particle system that we call the SSEP with traps, which is non reversible, attractive, and has a transient regime. We study its \emph{transience time} $\theta_K$, meaning the time after which the system is no longer in a transient state with high probability, on the ring with $K$ sites. We first show that $\theta_K$ is of order $K^2 \log K$ for a system of size $K$, and more precisely that it exhibits a cutoff at time $\frac{1}{\pi^2} K^2 \log K$. We then show that its \emph{mixing time} also undergoes cutoff at the same time.
  We further define a new mapping between the SSEP with traps and the Facilitated Exclusion Process (FEP) which has attracted significant scrutiny in recent years. We expect that this mapping will be a very useful tool to study the FEP's microscopic and macroscopic behaviour. In particular, using this mapping, we show that the FEP's transience time also undergoes a cutoff at time $\frac{1}{4 \pi^2} N^2 \log N$. Notably, our results show that for a FEP with particle density strictly greater than $\frac12$, the transient component is exited in a diffusive time. This allows to extend the upper-bound from [Ayre Chleboun 2024] for the mixing time of the FEP with particle density $\rho &gt; 1/2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20010v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Erignoux, Brune Massouli\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Negation of a Probability Distribution and Jensen Inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Yager[5] proposed a transformation for opposing(negating) the occurence of an event that is not certain using the idea that one can oppose the occurence of any uncertain event by allocating its probability among the other outcomes in the sample space without preference to any particular outcome \textit{i.e.} the probability of every event in the sample space is redistributed equally among the other outcomes in the sample space. However this redistribution increases the uncertainty associated with the occurence of events. In the present work, we have established bounds on the uncertainty associated with negation of a probability distribution using well known Jensen inequality. The obtained results are validated with the help of various numerical examples. Finally a dissimilarity function between a probability distribution and its negation has been developed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20027v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random friend trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20185v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a random recursive tree model featuring complete redirection called the random friend tree and introduced by Saram\"aki and Kaski. Vertices are attached in a sequential manner one by one by selecting an existing target vertex and connecting to one of its neighbours (or friends), chosen uniformly at random. This model has interesting emergent properties, such as a highly skewed degree sequence. In contrast to the preferential attachment model, these emergent phenomena stem from a local rather than a global attachment mechanism. The structure of the resulting tree is also strikingly different from both the preferential attachment tree and the uniform random recursive tree: every edge is incident to a macro-hub of asymptotically linear degree, and with high probability all but at most $n^{9/10}$ vertices in a tree of size $n$ are leaves. We prove various results on the neighbourhood of fixed vertices and edges, and we study macroscopic properties such as the diameter and the degree distribution, providing insights into the overall structure of the tree. We also present a number of open questions on this model and related models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20185v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louigi Addario Berry, Simon Briend, Luc Devroye, Serte Donderwinkel, C\'eline Kerriou, G\'abor Lugosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Ball Probabilities for Simple Random Tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the small ball probability of an order-$\ell$ simple random tensor $X=X^{(1)}\otimes\cdots\otimes X^{(\ell)}$ where $X^{(i)}, 1\leq i\leq\ell$ are independent random vectors in $\mathbb{R}^n$ that are log-concave or have independent coordinates with bounded densities. We show that the probability that the projection of $X$ onto an $m$-dimensional subspace $F$ falls within an Euclidean ball of length $\varepsilon$ is upper bounded by $\frac{\varepsilon}{(\ell-1)!}\left(C\log\left(\frac{e}{\varepsilon}\right)\right)^{\ell}$ and also this upper bound is sharp when $m$ is small. We also established that a much better estimate holds true for a random subspace.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20192v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuehan Hu, Grigoris Paouris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaled Brownian motion with random anomalous diffusion exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The scaled Brownian motion (SBM) is regarded as one of the paradigmatic random processes, featuring the anomalous diffusion property characterized by the diffusion exponent. It is a Gaussian, self-similar process with independent increments, which has found applications across various fields, from turbulence and stochastic hydrology to biophysics. In our paper, inspired by recent single particle tracking biological experiments, we introduce a process termed the scaled Brownian motion with random exponent (SBMRE), which preserves SBM characteristics at the level of individual trajectories, albeit with randomly varying anomalous diffusion exponents across the trajectories. We discuss the main probabilistic properties of SBMRE, including its probability density function (pdf), and the q-th absolute moment. Additionally, we present the expected value of the time-averaged mean squared displacement (TAMSD) and the ergodicity breaking parameter. Furthermore, we analyze the pdf of the first hitting time in a semi-infinite domain, the martingale property of SBMRE, and its stochastic exponential. As special cases, we consider two distributions of the anomalous diffusion exponent, namely the two-point and beta distributions, and discuss the asymptotics of the presented characteristics in such cases. Theoretical results for SBMRE are validated through numerical simulations and compared with the corresponding characteristics for SBM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20206v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hubert Woszczek, Aleksei Chechkin, Agnieszka Wylomanska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nodal Volumes as Differentiable Functionals of Gaussian fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the absolute continuity of the law and the Malliavin-Sobolev regularity of random nodal volumes associated with smooth Gaussian fields on generic $\mathcal{C}^2$ manifolds with arbitrary dimension. Our results extend and generalize the seminal contribution by Angst and Poly (2020) about stationary fields on Euclidean spaces and cover, in particular, the case of two-dimensional manifolds, possibly with boundary and corners. The main tools exploited in the proofs include the use of Gaussian measures on Banach spaces, Morse theory, and the characterization of Malliavin-Sobolev spaces in terms of ray absolute continuity. Several examples are analyzed in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20243v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Peccati, Michele Stecconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lower Bounds for the Large Deviations of Selberg's Central Limit Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19803v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\delta&gt;0$ and $\sigma=\frac{1}{2}+\tfrac{\delta}{\log T}$. We prove that, for any $\alpha&gt;0$ and $V\sim \alpha\log \log T$ as $T\to\infty$, $\frac{1}{T}\text{meas}\big\{t\in [T,2T]: \log|\zeta(\sigma+\rm{i} \tau)|&gt;V\big\}\geq C_\alpha(\delta)\int_V^\infty \frac{e^{-y^2/\log\log T}}{\sqrt{\pi\log\log T}} \rm{d} y,$ where $\delta$ is large enough depending on $\alpha$. The result is unconditional on the Riemann hypothesis. As a consequence, we recover the sharp lower bound for the moments on the critical line proved by Heap &amp; Soundararajan and Radziwi{\l}{\l} &amp; Soundararajan. The constant $C_\alpha(\delta)$ is explicit and is compared to the one conjectured by Keating &amp; Snaith for the moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19803v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis-Pierre Arguin, Emma Bailey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Harris theorem for enhanced dissipation, and an example of Pierrehumbert</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19858v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many situations, the combined effect of advection and diffusion greatly increases the rate of convergence to equilibrium -- a phenomenon known as enhanced dissipation. Here we study the situation where the advecting velocity field generates a random dynamical system satisfying certain Harris conditions. If $\kappa$ denotes the strength of the diffusion, then we show that with probability at least $1 - o(\kappa^N)$ enhanced dissipation occurs on time scales of order $|\ln \kappa|$, a bound which is known to be optimal. Moreover, on long time scales, we show that the rate of convergence to equilibrium is almost surely independent of diffusivity. As a consequence we obtain enhanced dissipation for the randomly shifted alternating shears introduced by Pierrehumbert '94.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19858v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Cooperman, Gautam Iyer, Seungjae Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Randomness, Effective Disintegrations, and Rates of Convergence to the Truth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: L\'evy's Upward Theorem says that the conditional expectation of an integrable random variable converges with probability one to its true value with increasing information. In this paper, we use methods from effective probability theory to characterise the probability one set along which convergence to the truth occurs, and the rate at which the convergence occurs. We work within the setting of computable probability measures defined on computable Polish spaces and introduce a new general theory of effective disintegrations. We use this machinery to prove our main results, which (1) identify the points along which certain classes of effective random variables converge to the truth in terms of certain classes of algorithmically random points, and which further (2) identify when computable rates of convergence exist. Our convergence results significantly generalize earlier results within a unifying novel abstract framework, and there are no precursors of our results on computable rates of convergence. Finally, we make a case for the importance of our work for the foundations of Bayesian probability theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19978v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon M. Huttegger, Sean Walsh, Francesca Zaffora Blando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on Sarnak processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20054v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Basic properties of stationary processes called Sarnak processes are studied. As an application, a combinatorial reformulation of Sarnak's conjecture on M{\"o}bius orthogonality is provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20054v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariusz Lema\'nczyk (LMRS), Michal D. Lema\'nczyk (LMRS), Thierry de La Rue (LMRS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum trajectory of the one atom maser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20094v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The evolution of a quantum system undergoing repeated indirect measurements naturally leads to a Markov chain on the set of states which is called a quantum trajectory. In this paper we consider a specific model of such a quantum trajectory associated to the one-atom maser model. It describes the evolution of one mode of the quantized electromagnetic field in a cavity interacting with two-level atoms. When the system is non-resonant we prove that this Markov chain admits a unique invariant probability measure. We moreover prove convergence in the Wasserstein metric towards this invariant measure. These results rely on a purification theorem: almost surely the state of the system approaches the set of pure states. Compared to similar results in the literature, the system considered here is infinite dimensional. While existence of an invariant measure is a consequence of the compactness of the set of states in finite dimension, in infinite dimension existence of an invariant measure is not free. Furthermore usual purification criterions in finite dimension have no straightforward equivalent in infinite dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20094v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tristan Benoist, Laurent Bruneau, Cl\'ement Pellegrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional analysis of ridge regression for non-identically distributed data with a variance profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20200v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-dimensional linear regression has been thoroughly studied in the context of independent and identically distributed data. We propose to investigate high-dimensional regression models for independent but non-identically distributed data. To this end, we suppose that the set of observed predictors (or features) is a random matrix with a variance profile and with dimensions growing at a proportional rate. Assuming a random effect model, we study the predictive risk of the ridge estimator for linear regression with such a variance profile. In this setting, we provide deterministic equivalents of this risk and of the degree of freedom of the ridge estimator. For certain class of variance profile, our work highlights the emergence of the well-known double descent phenomenon in high-dimensional regression for the minimum norm least-squares estimator when the ridge regularization parameter goes to zero. We also exhibit variance profiles for which the shape of this predictive risk differs from double descent. The proofs of our results are based on tools from random matrix theory in the presence of a variance profile that have not been considered so far to study regression models. Numerical experiments are provided to show the accuracy of the aforementioned deterministic equivalents on the computation of the predictive risk of ridge regression. We also investigate the similarities and differences that exist with the standard setting of independent and identically distributed data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20200v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emie Bigot, Issa-Mbenard Dabo, Camille Male</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An ordinary differential equation for entropic optimal transport and its linearly constrained variants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20238v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize the solution to the entropically regularized optimal transport problem by a well-posed ordinary differential equation (ODE). Our approach works for discrete marginals and general cost functions, and in addition to two marginal problems, applies to multi-marginal problems and those with additional linear constraints. Solving the ODE gives a new numerical method to solve the optimal transport problem, which has the advantage of yielding the solution for all intermediate values of the ODE parameter (which is equivalent to the usual regularization parameter). We illustrate this method with several numerical simulations. The formulation of the ODE also allows one to compute derivatives of the optimal cost when the ODE parameter is $0$, corresponding to the fully regularized limit problem in which only the entropy is minimized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20238v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Zoen-Git Hiew, Luca Nenna, Brendan Pass</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immediate recapture in the trapping-detrapping process of a single charge carrier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previously we have shown that pure 1/f noise arises from the trapping-detrapping process when traps are heterogeneous. Namely, the trapping-detrapping process relies on the assumption that detrapping rates of individual trapping centers in the condensed matter are random and uniformly distributed. Another assumption underlying the trapping-detrapping process was that both trapping and detrapping times need to have non-zero duration. Here we violate the latter assumption by introducing immediate recapture of the charge carrier. We show that 1/f noise will still be observed, though the range of frequencies over which it will be observed shifts to the lower frequency range as the immediate recapture probability increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20257v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICNF57520.2023.10472770</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2023 International Conference on Noise and Fluctuations (ICNF), Grenoble, France, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksejus Kononovicius, Bronislovas Kaulakys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling of variability measures in hierarchical demographic data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Demographic heterogeneity is often studied through the geographical lens. Therefore it is considered at a predetermined spatial resolution, which is a suitable choice to understand scalefull phenomena. Spatial autocorrelation indices are well established for this purpose. Yet complex systems are often scale-free, and thus studying the scaling behavior of demographic heterogeneity may provide valuable insights. Furthermore, migration processes are not necessarily influenced by the physical landscape, which is accounted for by the spatial autocorrelation indices. The migration process may be more influenced by the socio-economic landscape, which is better reflected by the hierarchical demographic data. Here we explore the scaling behavior of variability measures in the United Kingdom 2011 census data set. As expected, all of the considered variability measures decrease as the hierarchical scale becomes coarser. Though the non-monotonicity is observed, it can be explained by accounting for the imperfect hierarchical relationships. We show that the scaling behavior of variability measures can be qualitatively understood in terms of Schelling's segregation model and Kawasaki-Ising</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20259v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/icnf57520.2023.10472763</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2023 International Conference on Noise and Fluctuations (ICNF), Grenoble, France, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksejus Kononovicius, Justas Kvedaravicius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Further remarks on absorbing Markov decision processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, based on the recent remarkable results of Dufour and Prieto-Rumeau, we deduce that for an absorbing MDP with a given initial state, under a standard compactness-continuity condition, the space of occupation measures has the same convergent sequences, when it is endowed with the weak topology and with the weak-strong topology. We provided two examples demonstrating that imposed condition cannot be replaced with its popular alternative, and the above assertion does not hold for the space of marginals of occupation measures on the state space. Moreover, the examples also clarify some results in the previous literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20292v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhang, Xinran Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-Field Limits for Stochastic Interacting Particles on Digraph Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many natural phenomena are effectively described by interacting particle systems, which can be modeled using either deterministic or stochastic differential equations (SDEs). In this study, we specifically investigate particle systems modeled by SDEs, wherein the mean field limit converges to a Vlasov-Fokker-Planck-type equation. Departing from conventional approaches in stochastic analysis, we explore the network connectivity between particles using diagraph measures (DGMs). DGMs are one possible tool to capture sparse, intermediate and dense network/graph interactions in the mean-field thereby going beyond more classical approaches such as graphons. Since the main goal is to capture large classes of mean-field limits, we set up our approach using measure-theoretic arguments and combine them with suitable moment estimates to ensure approximation results for the mean-field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20325v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Kuehn, Carlos Pulido</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity of harmonic functions on the supercritical percolation cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.04736v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use ideas from quantitative homogenization to show that nonconstant harmonic functions on the percolation cluster cannot satisfy certain structural constraints, for example, a Lipschitz bound. These unique-continuation-type results are false on the full lattice and hence the disorder is utilized in an essential way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.04736v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Bou-Rabee, William Cooperman, Paul Dario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smallest gaps between eigenvalues of real Gaussian matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider an $n\times n$ matrix of independent real Gaussian random variables and determine the asymptotic distribution of the smallest gaps between complex eigenvalues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09521v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Lopatto, Matthew Meeker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lipschitz-type estimate for the frog model with Bernoulli initial configuration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the frog model with Bernoulli initial configuration, which is an interacting particle system on the multidimensional lattice consisting of two states of particles: active and sleeping. Active particles perform independent simple random walks. On the other hand, although sleeping particles do not move at first, they become active and can move around when touched by active particles. Initially, only the origin has one active particle, and the other sites have sleeping particles according to a Bernoulli distribution. Then, starting from the original active particle, active ones are gradually generated and propagate across the lattice, with time. It is of interest to know how the propagation of active particles behaves as the parameter of the Bernoulli distribution varies. In this paper, we treat the so-called time constant describing the speed of propagation, and prove that the absolute difference between the time constants for parameters $p,q \in (0,1]$ is bounded from above and below by multiples of $|p-q|$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18665v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Van Hao Can, Naoki Kubota, Shuta Nakajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of random noises on pathwise solutions to the high-dimensional modified Euler-Poincar\'{e} system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.09603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2107.09603v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Cauchy problem for the stochastically perturbed high-dimensional modified Euler-Poincar\'{e} system (MEP2) on the torus $\mathbb{T}^d$, $d\geq 1$. We first establish a local well-posedness framework in the sense of Hadamard for the MEP2 driven by general nonlinear multiplicative noises. Then two kinds of global existence and uniqueness results are demonstrated: One indicates that the MEP2 perturbed by nonlocal-type random noises with proper intensity admits a unique large global strong solution; The other one infers that, if the initial data is sufficiently small, then the MEP2 perturbed by linear multiplicative noise has a unique global solution with high probability. In the case of one dimension, we find that the stochastic MEP2 will break down in finite time when the initial data meets appropriate shape condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2107.09603v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
