<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 01:39:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Central limit theorem of Multilevel Monte Carlo Euler estimators for Stochastic Volterra equations with fractional kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to proving a (Lindeberg-Feller type ) central limit theorem for the multilevel Monte Carlo estimator associated with the Euler discretization scheme for the stochastic Volterra equations with fractional kernels $K(u)=u^{H-\frac{1}{2}}/\Gamma(H+1/2), H\in (0,1/2]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03421v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shanqi Liu, Yaozhong Hu, Hongjun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of backward propagation of chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of the present paper is to introduce and establish a notion of stability for the backward propagation of chaos, with respect to (initial) data sets. Consider, for example, a sequence of discrete-time martingales converging to a continuous-time limit, and a system of mean-field BSDEs that satisfies the backward propagation of chaos, i.e. converges to a sequence of i.i.d. McKean-Vlasov BSDEs. Then, we say that the backward propagation of chaos is stable if the system of mean-field BSDEs driven by the discrete-time martingales converges to the sequence of McKean-Vlasov BSDEs driven by the continuous-time limit. We consider the convergence scheme of the backward propagation of chaos as the image of the corresponding data set under which this scheme is established. Then, using an appropriate notion of convergence for data sets, we are able to show a variety of continuity properties for this functional point of view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03562v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonis Papapantoleon, Alexandros Saplaouras, Stefanos Theodorakopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large deviation probabilities for sums of censored random variables with regularly varying distribution tails</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\xi_1, \xi_2,\ldots$ be a sequence of independent and identically distributed random variables with zero mean, finite second moment and regularly varying right distribution tail. Motivated by a stop-loss insurance model, we consider a threshold sequence $M_n\gg (n\ln n)^{1/2},$ $n\to \infty,$ and establish the asymptotics of the probabilities of the large deviations of the form $ \sum_{j=1}^n(\xi_j \wedge M_n)&gt;x$ in the whole spectrum of $x$-values in the region $O(M_n).$ The asymptotic representations for these probabilities obey the "multiple large jumps principle" and have different forms in the vicinities of the multiples $kM_n$ of the censoring threshold values, on the one hand, and inside intervals of the form $((k-1)M_n, kM_n),$ on the other. We show that there is a "smooth transition" of these representations from one to the other when the deviation $x$ increases to a multiple of $M_n$, "crosses" it and then moves away from it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03727v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Chong, Konstantin Borovkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete left-tail asymptotic for branching processes with immigration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a complete left-tail asymptotic series for the density of the {\it martingale limit} of a Galton-Watson process with immigration. We show that the series converges everywhere, not only for small arguments. This is the first complete result regarding the left tails of branching processes with immigration. A good, quickly computed approximation for the density will also be derived from the series.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03823v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton A Kutsenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moderate deviation principles for the current and the tagged particle in the WASEP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the weakly asymmetric simple exclusion process in one dimension. We prove sample path moderate deviation principles for the current and the tagged particle when the process starts from one of its stationary measures. We simplify the proof in our previous works [Xue and Zhao, Electronic Journal of Probability, 2024] and [Xue and Zhao, Stochastic Processes and their Applications, 2023], where the same problem was investigated in the symmetric simple exclusion process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03924v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaofeng Xue, Linjie Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large deviations for scaled families of Schr\"odinger bridges with reflection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we show a large deviation principle for certain sequences of static Schr\"{o}dinger bridges, typically motivated by a scale-parameter decreasing towards zero, extending existing large deviation results to cover a wider range of reference processes. Our results provide a theoretical foundation for studying convergence of such Schr\"{o}dinger bridges to their limiting optimal transport plans. Within generative modeling, Schr\"{o}dinger bridges, or entropic optimal transport problems, constitute a prominent class of methods, in part because of their computational feasibility in high-dimensional settings. Recently, Bernton et al. established a large deviation principle, in the small-noise limit, for fixed-cost entropic optimal transport problems. In this paper, we address an open problem posed by Bernton et al. and extend their results to hold for Schr\"{o}dinger bridges associated with certain sequences of more general reference measures with enough regularity in a similar small-noise limit. These can be viewed as sequences of entropic optimal transport plans with non-fixed cost functions. Using a detailed analysis of the associated Skorokhod maps and transition densities, we show that the new large deviation results cover Schr\"{o}dinger bridges where the reference process is a reflected diffusion on bounded convex domains, corresponding to recently introduced model choices in the generative modeling literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03999v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Nilsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new proof of finitary isomorphism for Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a new proof of a result of Rudolph stating that a countable-state mixing Markov chain with exponential return times is finitarily isomorphic to an IID process. Besides being short and direct, our proof has the added benefit of working for processes of finite or infinite entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04069v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinon Spinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring birth versus death dynamics for ecological interactions in stochastic heterogeneous populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09041v3 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the significance of ecological interactions and separation of birth and death dynamics in stochastic heterogeneous populations via general birth-death processes. Interactions can manifest through the birth dynamics, the death dynamics, or some combination of the two. The underlying microscopic mechanisms are important but often implicit in population-level data. We propose an inference method for disambiguating the types of interaction and the birth and death processes from population size time series data of a stochastic $n$-type heterogeneous population. The interspecies interactions considered can be competitive, antagonistic, or mutualistic. We show that different pairs of birth and death rates with the same net growth rate result in different time series statistics. Then, the inference method is validated in the example of a birth-death process inspired by the two-type Lotka-Volterra interaction dynamics. Utilizing stochastic fluctuations enables us to estimate additional parameters in this stochastic Lotka-Volterra model, which are not identifiable in a deterministic model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09041v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin Beckman, Heyrim Cho, Linh Huynh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Marcinkiewicz-Zygmund inequality and the Kadec Pe{\l}czyn\'ski theorem in Orlicz spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the Marcinkiewicz--Zygmund inequality to the setting of Orlicz and Lorentz spaces. Furthermore, we generalize a Kadec--Pe{\l}czy\'nski-type result -- originally established by the first and third authors for $L^p$ spaces with $1 \le p &lt; 2$ -- to a broader class of Orlicz spaces defined via Young functions $\psi$ satisfying $x \le \psi(x) \le x^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04025v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Istvan Berkes, Eduard Stefanescu, Robert Tichy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature bound of Dyson Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00262v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a strongly local symmetric Dirichlet form on the configuration space $\Upsilon$ whose symmetrising (thus also invariant) measure is $\mathsf{sine}_\beta$, which is the law of the sine $\beta$ ensemble for every $\beta&gt;0$. For every $\beta&gt;0$, this Dirichlet form satisfies the Bakry-\'Emery gradient estimate $\mathsf{BE}(K, \infty)$ with $K=0$. This implies various functional inequalities, including the local Poincar\'e inequality, the local log-Sobolev inequality and the local hyper-contractivity. We then introduce an $L^2$-transportation-type extended distance $\bar{\sf d}_{\Upsilon}$ on $\Upsilon$, and prove the dimension-free Harnack inequality and several Lipschitz regularisation estimates of the $L^2$-semigroup associated with the Dirichlet form in terms of $\bar{\sf d}_{\Upsilon}$. As a result of $\mathsf{BE}(0,\infty)$, we obtain that the dual semigroup on the space of probability measures over $\Upsilon$, endowed with a Benamou--Brenier-like extended distance $\mathsf{W}_{\mathcal E}$, satisfies the evolutional variation inequality with respect to the Bolzmann--Shannon entropy $\mathsf{Ent}_{\mathsf{sine}_\beta}$ associated with $\mathsf{sine}_\beta$. Furthermore, the dual semigroup is characterised as the unique $\mathsf{W}_{\mathcal E}$-gradient flow in the space of probability measures with respect to $\mathsf{Ent}_{\mathsf{sine}_\beta}$. Finally, we provide a sufficient condition for $\mathsf{BE}(K, \infty)$ beyond $\mathsf{sine}_\beta$ and apply it to the infinite particle diffusion whose symmetrising measure is the law of the $1$-dimensional $(\beta,s)$-circular Riesz gas with $\beta&gt;0$ and $0&lt;s&lt;1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00262v5</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-025-05323-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Math. Phys. 406, 154 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hausdorff dimensions of irreducible Markov hom tree-shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05320v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper features a Cram\'er's theorem for finite-state Markov chains indexed by rooted $d$-trees, obtained via the method of types in the classical analysis of large deviations. Along with the theorem comes two applications: an almost-sure type convergence of sample means and a formula for the Hausdorff dimension of the symbolic space associated with the irreducible Markov chain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05320v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jung-Chao Ban, Guan-Yu Lai, Yu-Liang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic motions of the two-dimensional many-body delta-Bose gas, IV: Transformations of relative motions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17243v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is the last in a series devoted to constructing stochastic motions representing the two-dimensional $N$-body delta-Bose gas for all integers $N\geq 3$ via Feynman-Kac-type formulas. The main result here supplements [1,2] of the series by proving a bijective transformation between two general classes of Langevin-type SDEs such that the SDEs of one class describe precisely the stochastic relative motions of the SDEs of the other class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17243v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Ting Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Domination of Exit Times for Random Walks and Brownian Motion with Drift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00277v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, by an elementary use of Girsanov's transform we show that the exit time for either a biased random walk or a drifted Brownian motion on a symmetric interval is stochastically monotone with respect to the drift parameter. In the random walk case, this gives an alternative proof of a recent result of E. Pek\"oz and R. Righter in 2024. Our arguments in both discrete and continuous cases are parallel to each other. We also outline a simple SDE proof for the Brownian case based on a standard comparison theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00277v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Geng, Greg Markowsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Temporal Variation for Fractional Stochastic Heat Equation Driven by Space-Time White Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20426v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the exact fractional variation for the temporal process of the solution to the fractional stochastic heat equation on $\mathbb{R}$ driven by a space-time white noise, and as an application we give the estimate of drift parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20426v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongkang Li, Huisheng Shu, Litan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sticky diffusions on star graphs : characterization and It{\^o} formula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05441v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate continuous diffusions on star graphs with sticky behavior at the vertex. These are Markov processes with continuous paths having a positive occupation time at the vertex. We characterize sticky diffusions as time-changed nonsticky diffusions by adapting the classical technique of It{\^o} and McKean. We prove a form of It{\^o} formula, also known as Freidlin-Sheu formula, for this type of process. As an intermediate step, we also obtain a stochastic differential equation satisfied by the radial component of the process. These results generalize those already known for sticky diffusions on a half-line and skew sticky diffusions on the real line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05441v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jules Berry (IRMAR, INSA Rennes, UR), Fausto Colantoni (UNIROMA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cutoff via rigidity for high dimensional curved diffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15969v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider overdamped Lanvegin diffusions in Euclidean space, with curvature equal to the spectral gap. This includes the Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process as well as non Gaussian and non product extensions with convex interaction, such as the Dyson process from random matrix theory. We show that a cutoff phenomenon or abrupt convergence to equilibrium occurs in high-dimension, at a critical time equal to the logarithm of the dimension divided by twice the spectral gap. This cutoff holds for Wasserstein distance, total variation, relative entropy, and Fisher information. A key observation is a relation to a spectral rigidity, linked to the presence of a Gaussian factor. A novelty is the extensive usage of functional inequalities, even for short-time regularization, and the reduction to Wasserstein. The proofs are short and conceptual. Since the product condition is satisfied, an Lp cutoff hold for all p. We moreover discuss a natural extension to Riemannian manifolds, a link with logarithmic gradient estimates in short-time for the heat kernel, and ask about stability by perturbation. Finally, beyond rigidity but still for diffusions, a discussion around the recent progresses on the product condition for nonnegatively curved diffusions leads us to introduce a new curvature product condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15969v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Djalil Chafa\"i, Max Fathi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Proof of The Changepoint Detection Threshold Conjecture in Preferential Attachment Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00514v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the problem of detecting and estimating a changepoint in the attachment function of a network evolving according to a preferential attachment model on $n$ vertices, using only a single final snapshot of the network. Bet et al.~\cite{bet2023detecting} show that a simple test based on thresholding the number of vertices with minimum degrees can detect the changepoint when the change occurs at time $n-\Omega(\sqrt{n})$. They further make the striking conjecture that detection becomes impossible for any test if the change occurs at time $n-o(\sqrt{n}).$ Kaddouri et al.~\cite{kaddouri2024impossibility} make a step forward by proving the detection is impossible if the change occurs at time $n-o(n^{1/3}).$ In this paper, we resolve the conjecture affirmatively, proving that detection is indeed impossible if the change occurs at time $n-o(\sqrt{n}).$ Furthermore, we establish that estimating the changepoint with an error smaller than $o(\sqrt{n})$ is also impossible, thereby confirming that the estimator proposed in Bhamidi et al.~\cite{bhamidi2018change} is order-optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00514v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Du, Shuyang Gong, Jiaming Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong and weak convergence rates for fully coupled multiscale stochastic differential equations driven by $\alpha$-stable processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10229v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We first establish strong convergence rates for multiscale systems driven by $\alpha$-stable processes, with analyses constructed in two distinct scaling regimes. When addressing weak convergence rates of this system, we derive four averaged equations with respect to four scaling regimes. Notably, under sufficient H\"{o}lder regularity conditions on the time-dependent drifts of slow process, the strong convergence orders are related to the known optimal strong convergence order $1-\frac{1}{\alpha}$, and the weak convergence orders are 1. Our primary approach involves employing nonlocal Poisson equations to construct ``corrector equations" that effectively eliminate inhomogeneous terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10229v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kun Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the rate of convergence in the CLT for LSS of large-dimensional sample covariance matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02880v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the rate of convergence for the central limit theorem of linear spectral statistic (LSS) associated with large-dimensional sample covariance matrices. We consider matrices of the form ${\mathbf B}_n=\frac{1}{n}{\mathbf T}_p^{1/2}{\mathbf X}_n{\mathbf X}_n^*{\mathbf T}_p^{1/2},$ where ${\mathbf X}_n= (x_{i j} ) $ is a $p \times n$ matrix whose entries are independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) real or complex variables, and ${\mathbf T} _p$ is a $p\times p$ nonrandom Hermitian nonnegative definite matrix with its spectral norm uniformly bounded in $p$. Employing Stein's method, we establish that if the entries $x_{ij}$ satisfy $\mathbb{E}|x_{ij}|^{10}&lt;\infty$ and the ratio of the dimension to sample size $p/n\to y&gt;0$ as $n\to\infty$, then the convergence rate of the normalized LSS of ${\mathbf B}_n$ to the standard normal distribution, measured in the Kolmogorov-Smirnov distance, is $O(n^{-1/2+\kappa})$ for any fixed $\kappa&gt;0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02880v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Cui, Jiang Hu, Zhidong Bai, Guorong Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BV Functions and Sets of Finite Perimeter on Configuration Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.06078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.06078v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper contributes to foundations of the geometric measure theory in the infinite dimensional setting of the configuration space over the Euclidean space $\mathbb R^n$ equipped with the Poisson measure $\pi$. We first provide a rigorous meaning and construction of the $m$-codimensional Poisson measure -- formally written as "$(\infty-m)$-dimensional Poisson measure" -- on the configuration space. We then show that our construction is consistent with potential analysis by establishing the absolute continuity with respect to Bessel capacities. Secondly, we introduce three different definitions of BV functions based on the variational, relaxation and the semigroup approaches, and prove the equivalence of them. Thirdly, we construct perimeter measures and introduce the notion of the reduced boundary. We then prove that the perimeter measure can be expressed by the $1$-codimensional Poisson measure restricted on the reduced boundary, which is a generalisation of De Giorgi's identity to the configuration space. Finally, we construct the total variation measures for BV functions, and prove the Gau{\ss}--Green formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.06078v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00526-025-03015-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Calc. Var. 64, 177 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Elia Bru\`e, Kohei Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic error in the eigenfunction expansion for the Green's function of a Sturm-Liouville problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.10887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.10887v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic error arising when approximating the Green's function of a Sturm-Liouville problem through a truncation of its eigenfunction expansion, both for the Green's function of a regular Sturm-Liouville problem and for the Green's function associated with the Hermite polynomials, the associated Laguerre polynomials, and the Jacobi polynomials, respectively. We prove that the asymptotic error obtained on the diagonal can be expressed in terms of the coefficients of the related second-order Sturm-Liouville differential equation, and that the suitable scaling exponent which yields a non-degenerate limit on the diagonal depends on the asymptotic behaviour of the corresponding eigenvalues. We further consider the asymptotic error away from the diagonal and analyse which scaling exponents ensure that it remains at zero. For the Hermite polynomials, the associated Laguerre polynomials, and the Jacobi polynomials, a Christoffel-Darboux type formula, which we establish for all classical orthogonal polynomial systems, allows us to obtain a better control away from the diagonal than what a sole application of known asymptotic formulae gives. As a consequence of our study for regular Sturm-Liouville problems, we identify the fluctuations for the Karhunen-Lo\`eve expansion of Brownian motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.10887v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00365-025-09711-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Karen Habermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrarily small spectral gaps for random hyperbolic surfaces with many cusps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.15681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.15681v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{M}_{g,n(g)}$ be the moduli space of hyperbolic surfaces of genus $g$ with $n(g)$ punctures endowed with the Weil-Petersson metric. In this paper we study the asymptotic behavior of the Cheeger constants and spectral gaps of random hyperbolic surfaces in $\mathcal{M}_{g,n(g)}$, when $n(g)$ grows slower than $g$ as $g\to \infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.15681v4</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Shen, Yunhui Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit theorems of Chatterjee's rank correlation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.08031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.08031v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Establishing the limiting distribution of Chatterjee's rank correlation for a general, possibly non-independent, pair of random variables has been eagerly awaited by many. This paper shows that (a) Chatterjee's rank correlation is asymptotically normal as long as one variable is not a measurable function of the other, (b) the corresponding asymptotic variance is uniformly bounded by 36, and (c) a consistent variance estimator exists. Similar results also hold for Azadkia-Chatterjee's graph-based correlation coefficient, a multivariate analogue of Chatterjee's original proposal. The proof is given by appealing to H\'ajek representation and Chatterjee's nearest-neighbor CLT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.08031v4</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhexiao Lin, Fang Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient scheduling in redundancy systems with general service times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.10164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.10164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We characterize the impact of scheduling policies on the mean response time in nested systems with cancel-on-complete redundancy. We consider not only redundancy-oblivious policies, such as FCFS and ROS, but also redundancy-aware policies of the form $\Pi$ 1 -- $\Pi$ 2 , where $\Pi$ 1 discriminates among job classes (e.g., least-redundant-first (LRF), most-redundantfirst (MRF)) and $\Pi$ 2 discriminates among jobs of the same class. Assuming that jobs have independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) copies, we prove the following: (i) When jobs have exponential service times, LRF policies outperform any other policy. (ii) When service times are New-Worse-than-Used, MRF-FCFS outperforms LRF-FCFS as the variability of the service time grows infinitely large. (iii) When service times are New-Better-than-Used, LRF-ROS (resp. MRF-ROS) outperforms LRF-FCFS (resp. MRF-FCFS) in a two-server system. Statement (iii) also holds when job sizes follow a general distribution and have identical copies (all the copies of a job have the same size). Moreover, we show via simulation that, for a large class of redundancy systems, redundancy-aware policies can considerably improve the mean response time compared to redundancy-oblivious policies. We also explore the effect of redundancy on the stability region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.10164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Queueing Systems, 2024, 106, pp.333-372</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Elene Anton (UPPA), Rhonda Righter (UC Berkeley), Ina Maria Maaike Verloop (IRIT-RMESS, Toulouse INP, CNRS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundaries and equivariant maps for ergodic groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15355v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a notion of boundary pair $(\mathcal{B}_-,\mathcal{B}_+)$ for measured groupoids which generalizes the one introduced by Bader and Furman \cite{BF14} for locally compact groups. In the case of a semidirect groupoid $\mathcal{G}=\Gamma \ltimes X$ obtained by a probability measure preserving action $\Gamma \curvearrowright X$ of a locally compact group, we show that a boundary pair is exactly $(B_- \times X, B_+ \times X)$, where $(B_-,B_+)$ is a boundary pair for $\Gamma$. For any measured groupoid $(\mathcal{G},\nu)$, we prove that the Poisson boundaries associated to the Markov operators generated by a probability measure equivalent to $\nu$ provide other examples of our definition.
  Following Bader and Furman \cite{BF:Unpub}, we define algebraic representability for an ergodic groupoid $(\mathcal{G},\nu)$. In this way, given any measurable representation $\rho:\mathcal{G} \rightarrow H$ into the $\kappa$-points of an algebraic $\kappa$-group $\mathbf{H}$, we obtain $\rho$-equivariant maps $\mathcal{B}_\pm \rightarrow H/L_\pm$, where $L_\pm=\mathbf{L}_\pm(\kappa)$ for some $\kappa$-subgroups $\mathbf{L}_\pm&lt;\mathbf{H}$. In the particular case when $\kappa=\mathbb{R}$ and $\rho$ is Zariski dense, we show that $L_\pm$ must be minimal parabolic subgroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15355v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Sarti, Alessio Savini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary solution to Stochastically Forced Euler-Poisson Equations in Bounded Domain: Part 2. 1-D Ohmic Contact Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the asymptotic stability of the steady-state for a 1-D stochastic Euler-Poisson equations with Ohmic contact boundary conditions forced by the Wiener process. We utilize Banach's fixed point theorem and the a priori energy estimates uniformly in time to ensure the global existence of solutions around the steady state. In contrast to the deterministic case, the presence of stochastic forces lead to the lack of temporal derivatives of momentum, posing challenges for energy estimates. Furthermore, Ohmic contact boundary conditions pose greater challenges for energy estimates compared to systems with insulating boundary conditions. To address this issue, we establish asymptotic stability concerning the spatial derivatives through weighted energy estimates for the estimates of stochastic integrals, employing a technique distinct from that of the deterministic case. Furthermore, we demonstrate the existence of an invariant measure based on the a priori energy estimates. This invariant measure precisely corresponds to the Dirac measure generated by the steady state, due to the exponential decay of perturbed solutions around the steady state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20104v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yachun Li, Ming Mei, Lizhen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Learning for Entropy-Regularized Markov Decision Processes via Multilevel Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21224v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Designing efficient learning algorithms with complexity guarantees for Markov decision processes (MDPs) with large or continuous state and action spaces remains a fundamental challenge. We address this challenge for entropy-regularized MDPs with Polish state and action spaces, assuming access to a generative model of the environment. We propose a novel family of multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC) algorithms that integrate fixed-point iteration with MLMC techniques and a generic stochastic approximation of the Bellman operator. We quantify the precise impact of the chosen approximate Bellman operator on the accuracy of the resulting MLMC estimator. Leveraging this error analysis, we show that using a biased plain MC estimate for the Bellman operator results in quasi-polynomial sample complexity, whereas an unbiased randomized multilevel approximation of the Bellman operator achieves polynomial sample complexity in expectation. Notably, these complexity bounds are independent of the dimensions or cardinalities of the state and action spaces, distinguishing our approach from existing algorithms whose complexities scale with the sizes of these spaces. We validate these theoretical performance guarantees through numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21224v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Meunier, Christoph Reisinger, Yufei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-exchangeable evolutionary and mean field games and their applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02644v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A replicator dynamic for non-exchangeable agents in a continuous action space is formulated and its well-posedness is proven in a space of probability measures. The non-exchangeability allows for the analysis of evolutionary games involving agents with distinct (and possibly infinitely many) types. We also explicitly connect this replicator dynamic to a stationary mean field game, which determines the pairwise actions of the heterogeneous agents. Moreover, as a byproduct of our theoretical results, we show that a class of nonlinear voter models, recently the subject of increasing interest, called q-voter models, can be viewed as a replicator dynamic driven by a utility that is a power of the probability density. This implies that non-exchangeable and/or mean-field game formulations of these models can also be constructed. We also present computational examples of evolutionary and mean field game models using a finite difference method, focusing on tragedy of the commons and the q-voter model with non-exchangeable agents, of which are interesting cases from theoretical and computational perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02644v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Yoshioka, M. Tsujimura, T. Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
