<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 05:00:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The effects of individual versus community-influenced isolation on SIS epidemic persistence on finite random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The contact process, or SIS epidemic, is a continuous-time Markov process used to model the spread of infection on a graph. Each vertex is either healthy or infected, and each infected vertex independently infects each of its healthy neighbors at rate $\lambda$ and recovers at rate $1$. We study the contact process in the presence of additional intervention measures by introducing a third possible state for vertices, which we call isolated. Vertices may enter the isolated state either because of individual decisions or due to community-influenced decisions, which leads to two distinct models that we call the isolation model and the vigilance model, respectively. In the isolation model, infected vertices self-isolate at rate $\alpha$. In the vigilance model, each healthy vertex causes each of its infected neighbors to isolate at rate $\alpha$. Unlike the usual contact process, these models lack the key features of attractiveness and existence of a dual, which makes analyzing them more challenging. We study the persistence times of the infection on large, finite, degree-heterogeneous random graphs. We show that the infection in the isolation model persists for at least stretched exponential time in the size of the graph for all values of $\alpha$ and $\lambda$. By contrast, in the vigilance model, for every fixed $\alpha$ the persistence time of the infection exhibits a phase transition in $\lambda$: for small $\lambda$ the infection persists for at most a linear time in the size of the graph, while for large $\lambda$ the infection persists exponentially long. This contrast demonstrates that individual versus community-influenced isolation can substantially affect the persistence of an epidemic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06175v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shirshendu Chatterjee, David Sivakoff, Matthew Wascher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion bridge with misspecification: theory construction and application to high-resolution fish count data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06216v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stochastic processes of bridge types having pinned initial and terminal conditions have been widely used in applied research areas, but they all have a common drawback in that the model at hand is possibly misspecified owing to its stochastic nature; namely, parameter values and coefficients are distorted compared to the ground truth. We consider a pair of novel exactly-solvable optimization problems that provide both the lower and upper bounds of the performance index of a diffusion bridge. Our formulation is based on the Girsanov transformation, in which the model uncertainty is measured through relative entropy. We provide a sufficient condition under which these optimization problems are well-posed, and hence admit the corresponding maximizer/minimizer that achieves the worst-case lower and upper bounds given the ambiguity aversion or uncertainty size. We apply the proposed method to the latest 10-min, high-resolution fish count data of a migratory fish in a river and discuss the influence of model uncertainty on the estimation of the total fish count, which is an important problem in resource and environmental management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06216v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidekazu Yoshioka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak exponential metrics for high-dimensional log-correlated Gaussian fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For log-correlated Gaussian fields on $\mathbb{R}^d$ with $d \geq 2$, Ding-Gwynne-Zhuang (2023) established the existence of subsequential limits of exponential metrics obtained from appropriate approximations. For $\gamma \in (0,\sqrt{2d})$, we define a \textit{weak $\gamma$-exponential metric} to be a map $h \mapsto D_h$ that assigns to a sample of a log-correlated Gaussian field $h$ a continuous metric on $\mathbb{R}^d$ satisfying a list of axioms. We prove that every subsequential limit of exponential metrics built from appropriate approximations of $h$ is a weak $\gamma$-exponential metric in this sense. Moreover, we establish general properties that hold for any weak exponential metric: (1). sharp moment bounds for several natural distances; (2). optimal H\"older exponents when comparing $D_h$ and the Euclidean metric; and (3). Hausdorff dimension and a KPZ relation. These results extend the two-dimensional Liouville quantum gravity metric theory to higher dimensions. Along the way we derive several useful properties for log-correlated Gaussian fields including the equivalence between white-noise decomposition and convolution, and a shell independence lemma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06292v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andres A. Contreras Hip, Zijie Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit theorems for the Wiener process with resetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a large deviation principle for the trajectories of Wiener processes subject to random resets to the origin occurring according to a Poisson process. In addition to the pathwise large deviation principle, we identify the rate function and establish a large deviation principle for the supremum of the process over long time intervals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06325v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Logachov, O. M. Logachova, A. A. Yambartsev, K. A. Zaykov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Argmin-Theorems for multiple nets of multivariate c\`adl\`ag stochastic processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06375v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider finitely many nets of multivariate c\`adl\`ag stochastic processes. We show that the vectors consisting of the respective minimizing points converge in distribution to a random closed set. This set is given as a cartesian product with factors which are equal to the set of all minimizing points of stochastic processes occurring as functional limits of the respective nets. If these limit processes have almost surely exactly one minimizer, then the vectors converge classically in distribution to the vector of these minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06375v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dietmar Ferger, Niklas Rosar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and sharpness of the phase transition for the Frog Model on transitive graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a slight modification of the frog model. For a given graph, each vertex has $\mathrm{Poisson}(\lambda)$ particles (or frogs). At time zero, only the particles at the origin are active, and all the other particles are sleeping. Each active particle performs an independent, continuous-time simple random walk, becoming inactive after time $t$. Once an active frog jumps to a vertex, it activates all of its particles. The survival of active particles can be studied as a dependent percolation model with two parameters $\lambda$ and $t$. In the present work, we establish the existence of a phase transition with respect to each parameter for non-amenable graphs of bounded degrees and quasi-transitive graphs of superlinear polynomial growth, as well as prove the sharpness of the phase transition for transitive graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06640v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omer Angel, Daniel de la Riva, Jonathan Hermon, Yuliang Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrical representation and dependence structure of three-dimensional Bernoulli distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper fully characterizes the geometrical structure of the class of distributions of three-dimensional Bernoulli random variables with equal means, $p$. We find all the geometrical generators in closed form as functions of $p$. This result stems from an algebraic representation of the class that encodes the statistical properties of Bernoulli distributions. We study extremal negative dependence within the class and provide an application example by finding the impact of negative dependence to minimal aggregate risk. The application relies on a game theory approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06786v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Fontana, Patrizia Semeraro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Multi-set Allocation Occupancy function and inequality (MAO function and MAO inequality): the foundation of Generalized hypergeometric distribution theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our previous work, we studied the Generalized Hypergeometric Distribution (GHGD), which we refer to as the Multi-set Allocation Occupancy (MAO) distribution. We derived formulas for its expectation and variance for any number of subsets $T$ and overlap count $t$ ($1 \le t \le T$), and established an asymptotic property. However, these formulas were complex, and higher moments were not derived. Through further study, we have established a novel function that describes all higher moments of the MAO distribution with a unified, elegant formula. The core definitions are the MAO function $g(A_1, A_2, \dots, A_r) = \prod_{i=1}^{T} (m_i)_{k_i} \cdot (n-m_i)_{r-k_i}$ and the MAO norm $\|(p_1, \dots, p_r)\|_T = \frac{\sum_{A_1, \dots, A_r \subseteq [T] \; : \; |A_j|=p_j} g(A_1, \dots, A_r)}{((n)_r)^{T-1}}$, where $p_i$ is the size of subset $A_i$, $m_i &lt; n$, and $(x)_r$ is the falling factorial. Using these definitions, the intricate moment relations simplify into a unified form: the $\nu$-th raw moment of $p(x_{=t})$ and $p(x_{\ge t})$ can be calculated as $E(x_{=t}^\nu) = \sum_{1 \le i \le \nu} s_{\nu,i} \|t^i\|$ and $E(x_{\ge t}^\nu) = \sum_{1 \le i \le \nu} s_{\nu,i} \|[t, T]^i\|$, where $s_{\nu,i}$ are Stirling numbers of the second kind and $[t,T] = \{t, t+1, \dots, T\}$. Furthermore, based on the MAO norm, we formulate a novel MAO inequality under the proximity condition $\max(p_i) - \min(p_i) \le 1$: $\prod_{1\le i \le r} \|(p_i)\|_T \ge \|(p_1, \dots, p_r)\|_T$. A direct corollary is the asymptotic property of the MAO distribution: $E(X) &gt; \text{Var}(X)$ and $E(X) - \text{Var}(X) = o(E(X))$ as $E(X) \to 0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06880v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-gang Mao, Xiao-yan Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic integral representations for the Ray-Knight theorem of the Levy forest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a simple stochastic integral representation for the local times of the height process of a spectrally positive Levy process stopped at a hitting time. From the representation we derive a strong stochastic equation for the local time process of the type of Bertoin and Le Gall (Illinois J. Math., 2006) and Dawson and Li (Ann. Probab., 2012). This leads to a representation of the Ray-Knight theorem of Le Gall and Le Jan (Ann. Probab., 1998) and Duquesne and Le Gall (Asterisque, 2002), which codes the genealogical forest of a continuous-state branching process. The results extend those in the recent work of Aidekon et al. (Sci. China Math., 2024) for a Brownian motion with a local time drift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06884v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Sen Li, Zenghu Li, Wenjing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite Dimensional Multifractal Analysis of the Wiener measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a multifractal formalism for measures on infinite dimensional metric spaces, in terms of scales instead of dimensions in the classical multifractal analysis. We prove a multifractal formalism with a suitable scaling, called order, for the Wiener measure, which is the probability law of the standard Brownian motion. We also prove the fundamental Frostman Lemma on a large class of Polish spaces, for which the increasing sets lemma holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06984v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aihua Fan, Mathieu Helfter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme Values in Closed Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a widely used hub-and-spoke closed product-form network consisting of an infinite-server node and several single-server queues, we characterize the maximum queue-length distribution in various operational regimes by leveraging a novel probabilistic representation of the joint queue-length distribution and scaling where the number of customers grows. In these limiting regimes, we derive explicit characterizations of the maximum that are asymptotically equivalent to the maximum of independent random variables with the same geometric marginal distribution as queue lengths. In particular, when both the number of customers and queues grow, the parameters of the marginal distribution depend on the global characteristics of the network and are explicitly computed from a quadratic equation that arises from the corresponding large-deviation rate functions. Explicit computation of global characteristics of product-form distribution beyond the marginals, e.g., the maximum, appears novel, and our methodology may apply to other global measures of interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07003v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Predrag Jelenkovic, Petar Momcilovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorenz ordering of parasite loads across hosts in Isham's model of Host-Macroparasite Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In Isham's model of host-macroparasite interaction, parasite-induced host mortality increases parasite aggregation in the sense of the Lorenz order and related measures when the distribution of the number of parasites entering the host at infectious contacts is log-concave. Furthermore, in the presence of parasite-induce host mortality, the rate of parasite mortality may no longer have a monotone effect on aggregation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07156v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. McVinish</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hitting Probabilities for Hypoelliptic Differential Equations Driven by Fractional Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main goal of this article is to derive a two-sided estimate for hitting probabilities of a hypoelliptic stochastic differential equation (SDE) driven by fractional Brownian motion (fBM) with Hurst parameter $H\in(1/4,1)$ in terms of Newtonian-type capacities that are defined with respect to the (sub-Riemannian) control distance associated with the vector fields. As a starting point, we first establish the existence and smoothness of joint densities for the finite-dimensional distributions of the solution in the general context of hypoellitpic SDEs driven by Gaussian rough paths. We then turn to the fBM setting and derive a local upper bound for the joint density in terms of the control distance. As an application of these results, we establish our main estimate on hitting probabilities which generalises a well-known elliptic result of \cite{BNOT} to the hypoelliptic case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07202v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Geng, Sheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation and Development of the Methodologies for Simulating Self-similar Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to the study of simulating a large class of self-similar processes. Since most current simulation approaches are limited to case-by-case studies, every existing approach has its constraints and flaws; hence a general and efficient simulation approach is in demand. Our study sheds some light in this direction. The paper's contributions are bi-fold. First, reviews and improvements are made to some existing methods for simulating specific self-similar processes. Second, we propose a novel method to simulate a general self-similar process, where we use a modified inverse Lamperti transformation to transform self-similarity to stationarity. Successful applications are made to simulate fractional Brownian motion and sub-fractional Brownian motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07296v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qidi Peng, William Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-asymptotic convergence bounds of modified EM schemes for non-dissipative SDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we address the issue on non-asymptotic convergence bounds of Euler-type schemes associated with non-dissipative SDEs. On the one hand, for non-degenerate SDEs with super-linear drifts, we propose a novel modified Euler scheme and establish the corresponding non-asymptotic convergence bound under the multiplicative type quasi-Wasserstein distance
  by the aid of the asymptotic reflection by coupling. As a direct application of the theory derived, we explore the non-asymptotic convergence bound of the modified tamed/truncated Euler scheme
  and, as a byproduct, furnish the associated non-asymptotic convergence rate under the $L^1$-Wasserstein distance although the
  dissipativity at infinity is not in force. On the other hand, we tackle the non-asymptotic convergence analysis of the Euler scheme corresponding to a kind of degenerate SDEs, where the underdamped Langevin SDE is a typical candidate. To handle such setting, we also appeal to a carefully tailored coupling approach, where the ingredient in the coupling construction lies in that a proper metric and a suitable substitute in the cut-off function and the reflection matrix need to be chosen appropriately. In addition, as a consequent application, the non-asymptotic convergence bound and the $L^1$-Wasserstein convergence rate are revealed for the kinetic Langevin sampler.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07298v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhai Bao, Jiaqing Hao, Panpan Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaotic and Predictable Representations for Markov Additive Processes with Levy Modulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our main result is the martingale representations for Markov additive processes where the modulator is a Levy process. These processes have three parts: the modulator, the jumps of the ordinate triggered by the modulator, and the semimartingale part of the ordinate with parameters depending on the modulator. We orthogonalize Teugels martingales constructed from these parts to give a chaotic representation of square-integrable random variables as a sum of stochastic integrals with respect to the orthogonal sequence obtained. Consequently, a predictable representation of square-integrable martingales is derived in terms of the ordinate and the Teugels martingales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07534v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Celal Umut Yaran, Mine \c{C}a\u{g}lar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple proof of exponential decay for the near-critical planar Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the Ising model defined on $a\mathbb{Z}^2$ at critical temperature with external field $a^{15/8}h$, we give a simple and elementary proof that its truncated two-point function decays exponentially. The proof combines the high temperature expansion, random-cluster and random current representations. A new input in the proof is that, in the near-critical sourceless single current measure, there are many loops formed by a path on $a\mathbb{Z}^2$ with diameter of order $1$, together with two external edges that connect the path's endpoints to the ghost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07554v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianping Jiang, Frederik Ravn Klausen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renewal Hawkes Processes: Expectations and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07563v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hawkes processes are point processes with self-exciting and clustering properties that are popular in applications. In recent years, renewal Hawkes processes have gained attention, due to their versatility such as the capability of capturing dependence between clusters. In this paper, three classes of novel renewal Hawkes processes are introduced after incorporating exogenous and endogenous renewal factors. The relationship among five related Hawkes processes is studied. The expectations of the three classes of renewal Hawkes processes are derived by establishing a set of integral equations. A general common renewal equation for these expectations is derived and further discussions are provided. The special case of constant exogenous factor is discussed as well for the three proposed Hawkes processes. Finally, we apply our proposed models to study the optimization problems that arise in a periodic replacement policy for systems with cascading failures and provide numerical illustrations. The numerical solutions rely on computing the expectations of the proposed renewal Hawkes processes that can be efficiently obtained by using the direct Riemann integration method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07563v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lirong Cui, Yongji Zhang, Lingjiong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of weighted branching processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the long-term behavior of weighted multi-type branching processes, focusing on extending classical laws of large numbers and martingale convergence to settings with infinitely many weighted particles, arbitrary type spaces and non-geometric rescaling. We demonstrate applications to Galton-Watson trees indexed by random weights and by random kernels, convergence in Wasserstein distance of the underlying mean semi-group, and convergence of ergodic averages along lineages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07653v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Villemonais, Nicolas Zalduendo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative indistinguishability and sparse and dense clusters in factor of IID percolations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chifan-Ioana (2010) implies that, for any factor of IID percolation on any nonamenable Cayley graph $G$, there is a countable set of (strong) indistinguishability classes for non-hyperfinite clusters. We introduce quantitative strengthenings, called (qI) and (qSI): for $\eta$-non-hyperfinite clusters, there are at most $M(G,\eta)&lt;\infty$ (strong) indistinguishability classes, for any FIID percolation.
  We first show that (qI) and (qSI) for any $G$ are equivalent to the ``sparse implies thin'' property (SiT): any FIID percolation with $\eta$-non-hyperfinite clusters has density at least $c(G,\eta)&gt;0$. Also, (SiT) is independent of the finite generating set of a group. We prove, using entropy inequalities, that (SiT) holds for free groups, even for weak FIIDs. On the other hand, recent work of Jard\'on-S\'anchez, Mellick, Poulin, and Wr\'obel implies that (SiT) fails for weak FIIDs on non-exact, i.e., not property (A) groups.
  Furthermore, (SiT) implies that the Bernoulli graphing over any non-hyperfinite FIID cluster is strongly ergodic, and that indistinguishability for non-hyperfinite FIID clusters is equivalent to strong indistinguishability. These results follow from the work of Chifan-Ioana for every nonamenable Cayley graph, but with non-probabilistic proofs.
  We also prove, again using entropy inequalities, this time for all nonamenable Cayley graphs, that any FIID percolation with high enough expected degree must have a density close to 1, and there must be a single indistinguishability class of such clusters. On Kazhdan groups, there must be a single such cluster.
  Our results have finite counterparts: in any large girth $d$-regular graph sequence, any FIID subgraph of average degree at least $2+\delta$ must have density at least $c(d,\delta)&gt;0$. In the uniform random d-regular graph $G_{n,d}$, this holds for every subgraph of average degree at least $2+\delta$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07740v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Endre Cs\'oka, P\'eter Mester, G\'abor Pete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How many coin tosses would you need until you get $n$ Heads or $m$ Tails?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We harness both human ingenuity and the power of symbolic computation to study the number of coin tosses until reaching $n$ Heads or $m$ Tails. We also talk about the closely related problem of reaching $n$ Heads and $m$ Tails. This paper is accompanied by a Maple package that enables fast computation of expectations, variances, and higher moments of these quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07803v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svante Janson, Lucy Martinez, Doron Zeilberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality of AMP via Tree Pairings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove universality for Approximate Message Passing (AMP) with polynomial nonlinearities applied to symmetric sub-Gaussian matrices $A\in\mathbb R^{N\times N}$. Our approach is combinatorial: we represent AMP iterates as sums over trees and define a Wick pairing algebra that counts the number of valid row-wise pairings of edges. The number of such pairings coincides with the trees contribution to the state evolution formulas. This algebra works for non-Gaussian entries. For polynomial nonlinearities of degree at most $D$, we show that the moments of AMP iterates match their state evolution predictions for $t \lesssim \frac{\log N}{D\log D}$ iterations. The proof controls all "excess" trees via explicit enumeration bounds, showing non "Wick-paired" contributions vanish in the large-$N$ limit. The same framework should apply, with some modifications, to spiked AMP and tensor AMP models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07816v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Kogan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic Regularization in the Deep Linear Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study regularization for the deep linear network (DLN) using the entropy formula introduced in arXiv:2509.09088. The equilibria and gradient flow of the free energy on the Riemannian manifold of end-to-end maps of the DLN are characterized for energies that depend symmetrically on the singular values of the end-to-end matrix.
  The only equilibria are minimizers and the set of minimizers is an orbit of the orthogonal group. In contrast with random matrix theory there is no singular value repulsion. The corresponding gradient flow reduces to a one-dimensional ordinary differential equation whose solution gives explicit relaxation rates toward the minimizers. We also study the concavity of the entropy in the chamber of singular values. The entropy is shown to be strictly concave in the Euclidean geometry on the chamber but not in the Riemannian geometry defined by the DLN metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06137v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan Chen, Tejas Kotwal, Govind Menon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>gp2Scale: A Class of Compactly-Supported Non-Stationary Kernels and Distributed Computing for Exact Gaussian Processes on 10 Million Data Points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06143v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite a large corpus of recent work on scaling up Gaussian processes, a stubborn trade-off between computational speed, prediction and uncertainty quantification accuracy, and customizability persists. This is because the vast majority of existing methodologies exploit various levels of approximations that lower accuracy and limit the flexibility of kernel and noise-model designs -- an unacceptable drawback at a time when expressive non-stationary kernels are on the rise in many fields. Here, we propose a methodology we term \emph{gp2Scale} that scales exact Gaussian processes to more than 10 million data points without relying on inducing points, kernel interpolation, or neighborhood-based approximations, and instead leveraging the existing capabilities of a GP: its kernel design. Highly flexible, compactly supported, and non-stationary kernels lead to the identification of naturally occurring sparse structure in the covariance matrix, which is then exploited for the calculations of the linear system solution and the log-determinant for training. We demonstrate our method's functionality on several real-world datasets and compare it with state-of-the-art approximation algorithms. Although we show superior approximation performance in many cases, the method's real power lies in its agnosticism toward arbitrary GP customizations -- core kernel design, noise, and mean functions -- and the type of input space, making it optimally suited for modern Gaussian process applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06143v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcus M. Noack, Mark D. Risser, Hengrui Luo, Vardaan Tekriwal, Ronald J. Pandolfi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable Neural Approximation of Stochastic Reaction Dynamics with Guaranteed Reliability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stochastic Reaction Networks (SRNs) are a fundamental modeling framework for systems ranging from chemical kinetics and epidemiology to ecological and synthetic biological processes. A central computational challenge is the estimation of expected outputs across initial conditions and times, a task that is rarely solvable analytically and becomes computationally prohibitive with current methods such as Finite State Projection or the Stochastic Simulation Algorithm. Existing deep learning approaches offer empirical scalability, but provide neither interpretability nor reliability guarantees, limiting their use in scientific analysis and in applications where model outputs inform real-world decisions. Here we introduce DeepSKA, a neural framework that jointly achieves interpretability, guaranteed reliability, and substantial computational gains. DeepSKA yields mathematically transparent representations that generalise across states, times, and output functions, and it integrates this structure with a small number of stochastic simulations to produce unbiased, provably convergent, and dramatically lower-variance estimates than classical Monte Carlo. We demonstrate these capabilities across nine SRNs, including nonlinear and non-mass-action models with up to ten species, where DeepSKA delivers accurate predictions and orders-of-magnitude efficiency improvements. This interpretable and reliable neural framework offers a principled foundation for developing analogous methods for other Markovian systems, including stochastic differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06294v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Badolle, Arthur Theuer, Zhou Fang, Ankit Gupta, Mustafa Khammash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lipschitz Liouville Property, Affine Rigidity, and Coarse Harmonic Coordinates on Groups of Polynomial Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06753v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a quantitative theory of Lipschitz harmonic functions (LHF) on finitely generated groups, with emphasis on the Lipschitz Liouville property, affine rigidity, and quasi-isometric invariance for groups of polynomial growth. On finitely generated nilpotent groups we prove an affine rigidity theorem: for any adapted, smooth, Abelian-centered probability measure $\mu$, every Lipschitz $\mu$-harmonic function is affine, $f(x)=c+\varphi([x])$. For any finite generating set $S$ this yields a canonical isometric identification $$
  \mathrm{LHF}(G,\mu)/\mathbb{C} \cong \mathrm{Hom}(G_{\mathrm{ab}},\mathbb{C}),\qquad
  \|\nabla_S f\|_\infty=\max_{s\in S}|\varphi([s])|, $$ independent of the choice of centered measure. Next, for any finite-index subgroup $H\le G$ and adapted smooth $\mu$ we prove a quantitative induction-restriction principle: restriction along $H$ and an explicit averaging operator give a linear isomorphism $\mathrm{LHF}(G,\mu)\cong\mathrm{LHF}(H,\mu_H)$, where $\mu_H$ is the hitting measure, with two-sided control of the Lipschitz seminorms. For groups of polynomial growth equipped with SAS measures we then show that $\mathrm{LHF}$ is a quasi-isometry invariant, and use this to construct coarse harmonic coordinates that straighten quasi-isometries up to bounded error. Finally, within the Lyons-Sullivan / Ballmann-Polymerakis discretization framework, we prove a quantitative discrete-to-continuous extension theorem: Lipschitz harmonic data on an orbit extend to globally Lipschitz $L$-harmonic functions on the ambient manifold, with gradient bounds controlled by the background geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06753v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mayukh Mukherjee, Soumyadeb Samanta, Soumyadip Thandar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free energy dissipation and a decomposition of general jump diffusions on $\mathbb{R}^n$ without detailed balance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the thermodynamic structure of jump diffusions combining Brownian and Poisson noise, a class of stochastic dynamics relevant to nonequilibrium statistical physics. For such nonlocal dynamics, the free energy admits a full dissipation formula that decomposes into entropy production and housekeeping heat. A central result is a decomposition of the generator into symmetric and anti-symmetric parts with respect to the invariant measure $\rho_{ss}$. The symmetric sector corresponds to a reversible dynamics and yields a nonlocal Fisher information governing free-energy decay, whereas the anti-symmetric sector generates a canonical conservative flow that produces circulation but no dissipation. Several numerical examples demonstrate how this decomposition clarifies the structure of nonequilibrium stationary states in jump-driven systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06839v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuyuan Fan, Qi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Paths to Multi-Sector Equilibrium: Belief Dynamics Under Uncertain Returns to Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores the dynamics of learning in a multi-sector general equilibrium model where firms operate under incomplete information about their production returns to scale. Firms iteratively update their beliefs using maximum a-posteriori estimation, derived from observed production outcomes, to refine their knowledge of their returns to scale. The implications of these learning dynamics for market equilibrium and the conditions under which firms can effectively learn their true returns to scale are the key objects of this study. Our results shed light on how idiosyncratic shocks influence the learning process and demonstrate that input decisions encode all pertinent information for belief updates. Additionally, we show that a long-memory (path-dependent) learning which keeps track of all past estimations ends up having a worse performance than a short-memory (path-independent) approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07013v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Nasini, Rabia Nessah, Bertrand Wigniolle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic theory and statistical inference for the samples problems with heavy-tailed data using the functional empirical process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07088v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the Trimmed Functional Empirical Process (TFEP) as a robust framework for statistical inference when dealing with heavy-tailed or skewed distributions, where classical moments such as the mean or variance may be infinite or undefined. Standard approaches including the classical Functional Empirical Process (FEP), break down under such conditions, especially for distributions like Pareto, Cauchy, low degree of freedom Student-t, due to their reliance on finite-variance assumptions to guarantee asymptotic convergence. The TFEP approach addresses these limitations by trimming a controlled proportion of extreme order statistics, thereby stabilizing the empirical process and restoring asymptotic Gaussian behavior. We establish the weak convergence of the TFEP under mild regularity conditions and derive new asymptotic distributions for one-sample and twosample problems. These theoretical developments lead to robust confidence intervals for truncated means, variances, and their differences or ratios. The efficiency and reliability of the TFEP are supported by extensive Monte Carlo experiments and an empirical application to Senegalese income data. In all scenarios, the TFEP provides accurate inference where both Gaussian-based methods and the classical FEP break down. The methodology thus offers a powerful and flexible tool for statistical analysis in heavy-tailed and non-standard environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07088v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdoulaye Camara, Saliou Diouf, Moumouni Diallo, Gane Samb Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Results On The Modulated Cubic Nonlinear Schr\"odinger Equation On $\mathbb{T}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07147v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: New Strichartz estimates for the modulated cubic nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation are proved. These Strichartz estimates allow us to show that this equation is pathwise locally well-posed. We also show that improved Strichartz estimates are available in the case where the modulation is white noise. Additionally, we comment on a few basic properties of the modulated cubic nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation such as conservation of mass and convergence of its linear flow as time tends to zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07147v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Messing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of increasing profits in a 1D general diffusion market with interest rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07555v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a financial market model consisting of a risky asset, modeled as a general diffusion parameterized by a scale function and a speed measure, and a bank account process with a constant interest rate. This flexible class of financial market models allows for features such as reflecting boundaries, skewness effects, sticky points, and slowdowns on fractal sets. For this market model, we study the structure of a strong form of arbitrage opportunity called increasing profits. Our main contributions are threefold. First, we characterize the existence of increasing profits in terms of an auxiliary deterministic signed measure $\nu$ and a canonical trading strategy $\theta$, both of which depend only on the deterministic parametric characteristics of our model, namely the scale function, the speed measure, and the interest rate. More precisely, we show that an increasing profit exists if and only if $\nu$ is nontrivial, and that this is equivalent to $\theta$ itself generating an increasing profit. Second, we provide a precise characterization of the entire set of increasing profits in terms of $\nu$ and $\theta$, and moreover characterize the value processes associated with increasing profits. Finally, we establish novel connections between no-arbitrage theory and the general theory of stochastic processes. Specifically, we relate the failure of the representation property for general diffusions to the existence of certain types of increasing profits whose value processes are dominated by the quadratic variation measure of a space-transformed version of the asset price process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07555v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Anagnostakis, David Criens, Mikhail Urusov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumeration of maps with the Dumitriu-Edelman model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07753v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give an expansion in $1/N$ and $\beta$ of the cumulants of power sums of the particles of the $\beta$-ensemble. This new expansion is obtained using the tridiagonal model of Dumitriu and Edelman. The coefficients of the expansion are expressed in terms of suitably labelled maps introduced by Bouttier, Fusy, and Guitter. Our expansion is of a different nature than the one obtained by LaCroix in is study of the $b$-conjecture of Goulden and Jackson, and involves only orientable maps. We are able to relate bijectively the first two orders of our expansion to the one of LaCroix using a novel many-to-one mapping that relates suitably labelled planar maps with two minima and maps on the projective plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07753v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Buc-d'Alch\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large deviations principle for the cubic NLS equation with slowly decaying data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we prove a sharp large derivation principle (LDP) for the cubic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with Gaussian random initial data in Fourier Lebesgue spaces. As a consequence, we improve the exponential decay condition in [M.A. Garrido, R. Grande, K.M. Kurianski, G. Staffilani. Commun. Pure Appl. Math. 76 (2023), 4087--4136] to $\ell^1$ decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07773v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Liang, Yuzhao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VaR at Its Extremes: Impossibilities and Conditions for One-Sided Random Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07787v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the extremal aggregation behavior of Value-at-Risk (VaR) -- that is, its additivity properties across all probability levels -- for sums of one-sided random variables. For risks supported on \([0,\infty)\), we show that VaR sub-additivity is impossible except in the degenerate case of exact additivity, which holds only under co-monotonicity. To characterize when VaR is instead fully super-additive, we introduce two structural conditions: negative simplex dependence (NSD) for the joint distribution and simplex dominance (SD) for a margin-dependent functional. Together, these conditions provide a unified and easily verifiable framework that accommodates non-identical margins, heavy-tailed laws, and a wide spectrum of negative dependence structures. All results extend to random variables with arbitrary finite lower or upper endpoints, yielding sharp constraints on when strict sub- or super-additivity can occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07787v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nawaf Mohammed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Up-down ordered Chinese restaurant processes with two-sided immigration, emigration and diffusion limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.15758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.15758v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish scaling limit theorems for the up-down ordered Chinese restaurant processes (oCRPs) of Rogers and Winkel as processes in a space of interval partitions. As previously conjectured, the limits are self-similar diffusions previously constructed directly in the continuum. We extend the oCRP model and the results to a three-parameter family ${\rm oCRP}^{(\alpha)}(\theta_1,\theta_2)$, $\alpha\in(0,1)$, $\theta_1,\theta_2\ge 0$. We use the scaling limit approach to extend existing stationarity results to the full three-parameter family, identifying an extended family of Poisson--Dirichlet interval partitions. Their ranked sequence of interval lengths has Poisson--Dirichlet distribution with parameters $\alpha\in(0,1)$ and $\theta:=\theta_1+\theta_2-\alpha\ge-\alpha$, including for the first time the usual range of $\theta&gt;-\alpha$ rather than being restricted to $\theta\ge 0$. This has applications to Fleming--Viot processes, nested interval partition evolutions and tree-valued Markov processes, notably relying on the extended parameter range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.15758v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Shi, Matthias Winkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Martingale solution, invariant measure and ergodicity for stochastic convective Brinkman-Forchheimer equations on general domains in $\mathbb{R}^d$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.05510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.05510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The convective Brinkman-Forchheimer equations (CBFEs) \[ \frac{\partial \boldsymbol{X}}{\partial t} - \mu \Delta\boldsymbol{X} + (\boldsymbol{X}\cdot\nabla)\boldsymbol{X} + \alpha\boldsymbol{X} + \beta|\boldsymbol{X}|^{r-1}\boldsymbol{X} + \nabla p = \mathbf{F}, \qquad \nabla\cdot\boldsymbol{X}=0, \] with parameters $\mu,\alpha,\beta&gt;0$ and $r\in[1,\infty)$ describe incompressible fluid motion in saturated porous media. In the stochastic setting, for $d=2,3$ and $r\in[3,\infty)$ (with $2\beta\mu\geq 1$ when $r=3$), strong pathwise solutions on general domains are already known, hence weak martingale solutions exist as well. In the same parameter regime, invariant probability measures on bounded domains have also been obtained. The present work complements and significantly extends these results. More precisely, on general domains in $\mathbb{R}^d$ (bounded or unbounded), for all $d\in\{2,3\}$, we prove the existence of a weak martingale solution to the stochastic CBFEs for every exponent $r\in[1,\infty)$, which includes the regimes where no strong solution theory is available. For $d=2$, $r\in[1,\infty)$, and for $d=3$, $r\in[3,\infty)$, we further show that the martingale solutions satisfy the energy equality (It\^o's formula) and possess $\mathbb{H}$-valued continuous trajectories almost surely. In this regularity regime (excluding $2\beta\mu &lt; 1$ when $r=3$), we establish pathwise uniqueness and thereby, via the Yamada-Watanabe argument, obtain the existence of strong solutions and uniqueness in law, thereby recovering, in particular, the known results. Finally, for $d=2$, $r\in[1,\infty)$, and for $d=3$, $r\in[3,\infty)$ (with $2\beta\mu\geq 1$ when $r=3$), we prove the existence of an invariant probability measure for the associated Markov semigroup, while for $d=2,3$ with $r\in[3,\infty)$ (and with $2\beta\mu\geq 1$ for $r=3$), we show that at most one invariant measure can exist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.05510v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kush Kinra, Fernanda Cipriano, Manil T. Mohan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic wave equation with additive fractional noise: solvability and global H\"older continuity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We determine the range of Hurst parameters that provide the necessary and sufficient conditions for the solvability, in $L^2(\Omega)$, of the stochastic wave equation: $ \frac{\partial^2 }{\partial t^2}u(t,x) =\Delta u(t,x)+\dot{W}(t,x)$, where $\{ W(t,x),\ t\geq 0, x\in \mathbb{R}^d\} $ is a fractional Brownian field with temporal Hurst parameter $H_0\in[\tfrac12,1]$ and spatial Hurst parameters $H_i\in(0,1)$ for $i=1,\cdots,d$. {In particular, the solvability condition exhibits a phase transition at $H_0 = 1$.} We also obtain the sharp growth rate and the sharp H\"older continuity of the solution on the real line in the case $H_0=1/2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02425v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhui Liu, Yaozhong Hu, Xiong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roots of polynomials under repeated differentiation and repeated applications of fractional differential operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14883v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We start with a random polynomial $P^{N}(z)$ of degree $N$ with independent coefficients. We then consider a new polynomial $P_{t}^{N}$ obtained by $\lceil Nt\rceil$ applications of a fractional differential operator of the form $z^{a} (d/dz)^{b},$ where $a$ and $b$ are real numbers. When $b&gt;0,$ we compute the limiting root distribution $\mu_{t}$ of $P_{t}^{N}$ as $N\rightarrow\infty.$ We show that $\mu_{t}$ is the push-forward of the limiting root distribution of $P^{N}$ under a transport map $T_{t}$. The map $T_{t}$ is defined by flowing along the characteristic curves of a PDE satisfied by the log potential of $\mu_{t}.$
  In the special case of repeated differentiation, our results may be interpreted as saying that the roots evolve radially \textit{with constant speed} until they hit the origin, at which point, they cease to exist. For general $a$ and $b,$ the transport map $T_{t}$ has a free probability interpretation as multiplication of an $R$-diagonal operator by an $R$-diagonal \textquotedblleft transport operator.\textquotedblright As an application, we obtain a push-forward characterization of the free self-convolution semigroup $\oplus$ of radial measures on $\mathbb{C}$.
  We also consider the case $b&lt;0,$ which includes the case of repeated integration. More complicated behavior of the roots can occur in this case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14883v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian C. Hall, Ching-Wei Ho, Jonas Jalowy, Zakhar Kabluchko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaskets of $O(2)$ loop-decorated random planar maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05541v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that for $n = 2$ the gaskets of critical rigid $O(n)$ loop-decorated random planar maps are $3/2$-stable maps. The case $n = 2$ thus corresponds to the critical case in random planar maps. The proof relies on the Wiener-Hopf factorisation for random walks. Our techniques also provide a characterisation of weight sequences of critical $O(2)$ loop-decorated maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05541v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel Kammerer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the number of crossings and bouncings of a diffusion at a sticky threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08846v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the asymptotic behavior of the number of crossings by a one-dimensional diffusion of a threshold where the process exhibits stickiness. We distinguish three types of crossings and show that to each type corresponds a distinct asymptotic regime for the respective number of crossings statistic. We introduce notions of bouncing as the symmetric counterparts to crossings and show that the corresponding number of bouncings statistics share the same asymptotic properties as their crossings counterparts. We first prove the results for sticky Brownian motion, then extend them to sticky-reflected Brownian motion (where only bouncing is possible) and to sticky diffusions. As an application, we propose consistent estimators for the stickiness parameter of sticky diffusions and sticky-reflected Brownian motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08846v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Anagnostakis, Sara Mazzonetto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-dimensional long-range statistical mechanical models have random walk correlation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12104v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider long-range percolation, Ising model, and self-avoiding walk on $\mathbb{Z}^d$, with couplings decaying like $|x|^{-(d+\alpha)}$ where $0 &lt; \alpha \le 2$, above the upper critical dimensions. In the spread-out setting where the lace expansion applies, we show that the two-point function for each of these models exactly coincides with a random walk two-point function, up to a constant prefactor. Using this, for $0&lt;\alpha &lt; 2$, we prove upper and lower bounds of the form $|x|^{-(d-\alpha)} \min\{ 1, (p_c - p)^{-2} |x|^{-2\alpha} \}$ for the two-point function near the critical point $p_c$. For $\alpha=2$, we obtain a similar upper bound with logarithmic corrections. We also give a simple proof of the convergence of the lace expansion, assuming diagrammatic estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12104v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucheng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long memory score-driven models as approximations for rough Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09105v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the continuous-time limit of score-driven models with long memory. By extending score-driven models to incorporate infinite-lag structures with coefficients exhibiting heavy-tailed decay, we establish their weak convergence, under appropriate scaling, to fractional Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes with Hurst parameter $H &lt; 1/2$. When score-driven models are used to characterize the dynamics of volatility, they serve as discrete-time approximations for rough volatility. We present several examples, including EGARCH($\infty$) whose limits give rise to a new class of rough volatility models. Building on this framework, we carry out numerical simulations and option pricing analyses, offering new tools for rough volatility modeling and simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09105v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinhao Wu, Ping He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brownian motion on the Fubini extension space and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12096v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a family of essentially pairwise independent Brownian motions indexed by a continuum of labels and show how the Fubini extension framework provides a rigorous way to represent such families as a single jointly measurable process. Within this framework, we address two main objectives: first, we show how a system of graphon stochastic differential equations can be reformulated as a single McKean-Vlasov type equation driven by a standard Brownian motion, which significantly facilitates its analysis. Second, we establish a Girsanov theorem for a continuum of essentially pairwise independent Brownian motions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12096v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Amini, Nina H. Amini, Sofiane Chalal, Gaoyue Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenization of non-divergence form operators in i.i.d. random environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04410v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study random walks in a balanced, i.i.d. random environment in $\mathbb Z^d$ for $d\geq 3$. We establish improved convergence rates for the homogenization of the Dirichlet problem associated with the corresponding non-divergence form difference operators, surpassing the $O(R^{-1})$ rate, which is expected to be optimal for environments with a finite range of dependence. In particular, the improved rates are $O(R^{-3/2})$ when $d=3$, and $O(R^{-2}\log R)$ when $d\geq 4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04410v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoqin Guo, Timo Sprekeler, Hung V. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Optimal Approximation Factor in Density Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.05876</link>
      <description>arXiv:1902.05876v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consider the following problem: given two arbitrary densities $q_1,q_2$ and a sample-access to an unknown target density $p$, find which of the $q_i$'s is closer to $p$ in total variation.
  A remarkable result due to Yatracos shows that this problem is tractable in the following sense: there exists an algorithm that uses $O(\epsilon^{-2})$ samples from $p$ and outputs~$q_i$ such that with high probability, $TV(q_i,p) \leq 3\cdot\mathsf{opt} + \epsilon$, where $\mathsf{opt}= \min\{TV(q_1,p),TV(q_2,p)\}$. Moreover, this result extends to any finite class of densities $\mathcal{Q}$: there exists an algorithm that outputs the best density in $\mathcal{Q}$ up to a multiplicative approximation factor of 3.
  We complement and extend this result by showing that: (i) the factor 3 can not be improved if one restricts the algorithm to output a density from $\mathcal{Q}$, and (ii) if one allows the algorithm to output arbitrary densities (e.g.\ a mixture of densities from $\mathcal{Q}$), then the approximation factor can be reduced to 2, which is optimal. In particular this demonstrates an advantage of improper learning over proper in this setup.
  We develop two approaches to achieve the optimal approximation factor of 2: an adaptive one and a static one. Both approaches are based on a geometric point of view of the problem and rely on estimating surrogate metrics to the total variation. Our sample complexity bounds exploit techniques from {\it Adaptive Data Analysis}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1902.05876v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Bousquet, Daniel Kane, Shay Moran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper-bishops, Hyper-rooks, and Hyper-queens: Percentage of Safe Squares on Higher Dimensional Chess Boards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04423v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $n$ queens problem considers the maximum number of safe squares on an $n \times n$ chess board when placing $n$ queens; the answer is only known for small $n$. Miller, Sheng and Turek considered instead $n$ randomly placed rooks, proving the proportion of safe squares converges to $1/e^2$. We generalize and solve when randomly placing $n$ hyper-rooks and $n^{k-1}$ line-rooks on a $k$-dimensional board, using combinatorial and probabilistic methods, with the proportion of safe squares converging to $1/e^k$. We prove that the proportion of safe squares on an $n \times n$ board with bishops in 2 dimensions converges to $2/e^2$. This problem is significantly more interesting and difficult; while a rook attacks the same number of squares wherever it's placed, this is not so for bishops. We expand to the $k$-dimensional chessboard, defining line-bishops to attack along $2$-dimensional diagonals and hyper-bishops to attack in the $k-1$ dimensional subspace defined by its diagonals in the $k-2$ dimensional subspace. We then combine the movement of rooks and bishops to consider the movement of queens in 2 dimensions, as well as line-queens and hyper-queens in $k$ dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04423v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caroline Cashman, Joseph Cooper, Raul Marquez, Steven J. Miller, Jenna Shuffelton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two waves of adaptation: speciation induced by dormancy in a model with changing environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10890v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a population model in which the season alternates between winter and summer, and individuals can acquire mutations either that are advantageous in the summer and disadvantageous in the winter, or vice versa. Also, we assume that individuals in the population can either be active or dormant, and that individuals can move between these two states. Dormant individuals do not reproduce but do not experience selective pressures. We show that, under certain conditions, over time we see two waves of adaptation. Some individuals repeatedly acquire mutations that are beneficial in the summer, while others repeatedly acquire mutations that are beneficial in the winter. Individuals can survive the season during which they are less fit by entering a dormant state. This result demonstrates that, for populations in fluctuating environments, dormancy has the potential to induce speciation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10890v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Cordero, Adri\'an Gonz\'alez Casanova, Jason Schweinsberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-sum Dynkin games under common and independent Poisson constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07134v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Zero-sum Dynkin games under Poisson constraints, where players can only stop at the event times of a Poisson process, have been studied widely in the recent literature. The constraint can be modelled in two ways: either both players share the same Poisson process (the common constraint) or each player has their own Poisson process (the independent constraint). In a Markovian framework, where payoffs are functions of an underlying diffusion, we establish necessary and sufficient conditions for the equivalence of the game's solution--comprising the value function and optimal stopping sets--under the common and independent constraints. Specifically, if the stopping sets of the maximiser and minimiser in the game under the common constraint are disjoint, then the solution to the game is the same under both the common and the independent constraint. However, the fact that the stopping sets are disjoint in the game under the independent constraint is not sufficient to guarantee that the solution of the game under the independent constraint is also the solution under the common constraint. To demonstrate the broad applicability of our results, we solve infinite-horizon Dynkin games satisfying the assumptions of our main theorems, using backward stochastic differential equation (BSDE) techniques. This requires extending standard BSDE results from the finite-horizon setting to the infinite-horizon case, allowing for unbounded solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07134v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Hobson, Gechun Liang, Edward Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to simulate L\'evy flights in a steep potential: An explicit splitting numerical scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07339v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an effective explicit numerical scheme for simulating solutions of stochastic differential equations with confining superlinear drift terms, driven by multiplicative heavy-tailed L\'evy noise. The scheme is designed to prevent explosion and accurately capture all finite moments of the solutions.
  In the purely Gaussian case, it correctly reproduces moments of sub-Gaussian tails of the solutions.
  This method is particularly well-suited for approximating statistical moments and other probabilistic characteristics of L\'evy flights in steep potential landscapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07339v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Pavlyukevich, Olga Aryasova, Alexei Chechkin, Oleksii Kulyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing POMDPs: Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis for Parity Objectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13134v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Partially observable Markov decision processes (POMDPs) are a central model for uncertainty in sequential decision making. The most basic objective is the reachability objective, where a target set must be eventually visited, and the more general parity objectives can model all omega-regular specifications. For such objectives, the computational analysis problems are the following: (a) qualitative analysis that asks whether the objective can be satisfied with probability 1 (almost-sure winning) or probability arbitrarily close to 1 (limit-sure winning); and (b) quantitative analysis that asks for the approximation of the optimal probability of satisfying the objective. For general POMDPs, almost-sure analysis for reachability objectives is EXPTIME-complete, but limit-sure and quantitative analyses for reachability objectives are undecidable; almost-sure, limit-sure, and quantitative analyses for parity objectives are all undecidable. A special class of POMDPs, called revealing POMDPs, has been studied recently in several works, and for this subclass the almost-sure analysis for parity objectives was shown to be EXPTIME-complete. In this work, we show that for revealing POMDPs the limit-sure analysis for parity objectives is EXPTIME-complete, and even the quantitative analysis for parity objectives can be achieved in EXPTIME.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13134v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Asadi, Krishnendu Chatterjee, David Lurie, Raimundo Saona</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-square exponential stability of exact and numerical solutions for neutral stochastic delay differential equations with Markovian switching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21620v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the mean-square exponential stability of neutral stochastic differential delay equations (NSDDEs) with Markovian switching. The analysis addresses the complexities arising from the interaction between the neutral term, time-varying delays, and structural changes governed by a continuous-time Markov chain. We establish novel and practical criteria for the mean-square exponential stability of both the underlying system and its numerical approximations via the Euler-Maruyama method. Furthermore, we prove that the numerical scheme can reproduce the exponential decay rate of the true solution with arbitrary accuracy, provided the step size is sufficiently small. The theoretical results are supported by a numerical example that illustrates their effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21620v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jina Yang, Ky Quan Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central limit theorems for random multiplicative functions over function fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22905v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a sufficient characterization for subsets $\mathcal{A}$ of the polynomial ring $\mathbb{F}_q[t]$ for which partial sums of Steinhaus random multiplicative functions approach a complex standard normal distribution. This extends recent work of Soundararajan and Xu to the function field setting. We apply this characterization to deduce central limit theorems in four cases: polynomials in short intervals, polynomials with few prime factors, shifted primes, and rough polynomials. In doing so, we also establish an explicit Hildebrand inequality for smooth polynomials in short intervals, a function field form of Shiu's theorem for multiplicative functions, and an explicit Chebyshev bound for rough polynomials in short intervals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22905v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Declan Hoban, Jibran Iqbal Shah, Nadya-Catherine Ismail, William Verreault, Asif Zaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation-Weighted Communicability Curvature as a Structural Driver of Dengue Spread: A Bayesian Spatial Analysis of Recife (2015-2024)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate whether the structural connectivity of urban road networks helps explain dengue incidence in Recife, Brazil (2015--2024). For each neighborhood, we compute the average \emph{communicability curvature}, a graph-theoretic measure capturing the ability of a locality to influence others through multiple network paths. We integrate this metric into Negative Binomial models, fixed-effects regressions, SAR/SAC spatial models, and a hierarchical INLA/BYM2 specification. Across all frameworks, curvature is the strongest and most stable predictor of dengue risk. In the BYM2 model, the structured spatial component collapses ($\phi \approx 0$), indicating that functional network connectivity explains nearly all spatial dependence typically attributed to adjacency-based CAR terms. The results show that dengue spread in Recife is driven less by geographic contiguity and more by network-mediated structural flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00315v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc\'ilio Ferreira dos Santos, Cleiton de Lima Ricardo, Andreza dos Santos Rodrigues de Melo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
