<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 01:47:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The generalized Alice HH vs Bob HT problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2024, Daniel Litt posed a simple coinflip game pitting Alice's "Heads-Heads" vs Bob's "Heads-Tails": who is more likely to win if they score 1 point per occurrence of their substring in a sequence of n fair coinflips? This attracted over 1 million views on X and quickly spawned several articles explaining the counterintuitive solution. We study the generalized game, where the set of coin outcomes, {Heads, Tails}, is generalized to an arbitrary finite alphabet A, and where Alice's and Bob's substrings are any finite A-strings of the same length. We find that the winner of Litt's game can be determined by a single quantity which measures the amount of prefix/suffix self-overlaps in each string; whoever's string has more overlaps loses. For example, "Heads-Tails" beats "Heads-Heads" in the original problem because "Heads-Heads" has a prefix/suffix overlap of length 1 while "Heads-Tails" has none. The method of proof is to develop a precise Edgeworth expansion for discreteMarkov chains, and apply this to calculate Alice's and Bob's probability to win the game correct to order O(1/n).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19035v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svante Janson, Mihai Nica, Simon Segert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Langevin Monte Carlo Sampling: A Large Deviations Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Langevin algorithms are popular Markov chain Monte Carlo methods that are often used to solve high-dimensional large-scale sampling problems in machine learning. The most classical Langevin Monte Carlo algorithm is based on the overdamped Langevin dynamics. There are many variants of Langevin dynamics that often show superior performance in practice. In this paper, we provide a unified approach to study the acceleration of the variants of the overdamped Langevin dynamics through the lens of large deviations theory. Numerical experiments using both synthetic and real data are provided to illustrate the efficiency of these variants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19066v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nian Yao, Pervez Ali, Xihua Tao, Lingjiong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Number variance for homogeneous determinantal processes on hyperbolic spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19197v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an abstract determinantal point process on a general non--elementary Gromov hyperbolic metric space governed by an orthogonal projection in the case when the space is homogeneous and the point process is invariant under isometries. We give a lower bound of the variance of the number of points inside a ball that is proportional to the volume of the ball. In particular, such point processes are never hyperuniform. Our result applies to the known examples of radial determinantal point processes on Cayley trees and on the standard hyperbolic spaces governed by Bergman projection kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19197v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Lazag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random skeletons in high-dimensional lattice trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the behaviour of the rescaled minimal subtree containing the origin and K random vertices selected from a random critical (sufficiently spread-out, and in dimensions d &gt; 8) lattice tree conditioned to survive until time ns, in the limit as n goes to infinity. We prove joint weak convergence of various quantities associated with these subtrees under this sequence of conditional measures to their counterparts for historical Brownian motion. We also show that when K is sufficiently large the entire rescaled tree is close to this rescaled skeleton with high probability, uniformly in n. These two results are the key conditions used in [5] to prove that the simple random walk on sufficiently spread-out lattice trees (conditioned to survive for a long time) converges to Brownian motion on a super-Brownian motion (conditioned to survive). The main convergence result is established more generally for a sequence of historical processes converging to historical Brownian motion in the sense of finite dimensional distri- butions and satisfying a pair of technical conditions. The conditions are readily verified for the lattice trees mentioned above and also for critical branching random walk. We expect that it will also apply with suitable changes to other lattice models in sufficiently high dimensions such as oriented percolation and the voter model. In addition some forms of the second skeleton density result are already established in this generality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19230v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Cabezas, Alexander Fribergh, Mark Holmes, Edwin Perkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faber-Krahn functions on glued graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Faber-Krahn functions provide lower bounds on the first Dirichlet eigenvalue of the Laplacian and are useful because they imply heat kernel upper bounds. In this paper, we are interested in Faber-Krahn functions and heat kernel estimates for a certain class of graphs consisting of "sufficiently nice pages" (satisfying a Harnack inequality) glued together via a "sufficiently nice spine." For such graphs, we obtain a relative Faber-Krahn function in terms of the Faber-Krahn functions on the pages. The corresponding heat kernel upper bound involves the volumes on the various pages. In the case our graphs satisfy a property we call "book-like" and the spine is appropriately transient, we provide a matching lower bound for the heat kernel between two points on the gluing spine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19256v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Dautenhahn, Laurent Saloff-Coste</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorizations of relative entropy using stochastic localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive entropy factorization estimates for spin systems using the stochastic localization approach proposed by Eldan and Chen-Eldan, which, in this context, is equivalent to the renormalization group approach developed independently by Bauerschmidt, Bodineau, and Dagallier. The method provides approximate Shearer-type inequalities for the corresponding Gibbs measure at sufficiently high temperature, without restrictions on the degree of the underlying graph. For Ising systems, these are shown to hold up to the critical tree-uniqueness threshold, including polynomial bounds at the critical point, with optimal $O(\sqrt n)$ constants for the Curie-Weiss model at criticality. In turn, these estimates imply tight mixing time bounds for arbitrary block dynamics or Gibbs samplers, improving over existing results. Moreover, we establish new tensorization statements for the Shearer inequality asserting that if a system consists of weakly interacting but otherwise arbitrary components, each of which satisfies an approximate Shearer inequality, then the whole system also satisfies such an estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19419v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Caputo, Zongchen Chen, Daniel Parisi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hereditary Hsu-Robbins-Erd\"os Law of Large Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19484v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that every sequence $f_1, f_2, \cdots$ of real-valued random variables with $\sup_{n \in \N} \E (f_n^2) &lt; \infty$ contains a subsequence $f_{k_1}, f_{k_2}, \cdots$ converging in \textsc{Ces\`aro} mean to some $\,f_\infty \in \mathbb{L}^2$ {\it completely,} to wit, $ \sum_{N \in \N} \, \P \left( \bigg| \frac{1}{N} \sum_{n=1}^N f_{k_n} - f_\infty \bigg| &gt; \eps \right)&lt; \infty\,, \quad \forall ~ \eps &gt; 0\,; $ and {\it hereditarily,} i.e., along all further subsequences as well. We also identify a condition, slightly weaker than boundedness in $ \mathbb{L}^2,$ which turns out to be not only sufficient for the above hereditary complete convergence in \textsc{Ces\`aro} mean, but necessary as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19484v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Istvan Berkes, Ioannis Karatzas, Walter Schachermayer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Support of the Brown measure of a family of free multiplicative Brownian motions with non-negative initial condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a family $b_{s,\tau}$ of free multiplicative Brownian motions labeled by a real variance parameter $s$ and a complex covariance parameter $\tau$. We then consider the element $xb_{s,\tau}$, where $x$ is non-negative and freely independent of $b_{s,\tau}$. Our goal is to identify the support of the Brown measure of $xb_{s,\tau}$. In the case $\tau =s$, we identify a region $\Sigma_s$ such that the Brown measure is vanishing outside of $\overline{\Sigma}_s$ except possibly at the origin. For general values of $\tau$, we construct a map $f_{s-\tau}$ and define $D_{s,\tau}$ as the complement of $f_{s-\tau}(\overline{\Sigma}_s^c)$. Then the Brown measure is zero outside $D_{s,\tau}$ except possibly at the origin. The proof of these results is based on a two-stage PDE analysis, using one PDE (following the work of Driver, Hall, and Kemp) for the case $\tau=s$ and a different PDE (following the work of Hall and Ho) to deform the $\tau=s$ case to general values of $\tau$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19682v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian C. Hall, Sorawit Eaknipitsari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The scaling limit of random 2-connected series-parallel maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A finite graph embedded in the plane is called a series-parallel map if it can be obtained from a finite tree by repeatedly subdividing and doubling edges. We study the scaling limit of weighted random two-connected series-parallel maps with $n$ edges and show that under some integrability conditions on these weights, the maps with distances rescaled by a factor $n^{-1/2}$ converge to a constant multiple of Aldous' continuum random tree (CRT) in the Gromov--Hausdorff sense. The proof relies on a bijection between a set of trees with $n$ leaves and a set of series-parallel maps with $n$ edges, which enables one to compare geodesics in the maps and in the corresponding trees via a Markov chain argument introduced by Curien, Haas and Kortchemski (2015).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19705v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Amankwah, Jakob Bj\"ornberg, Sigurdur \"Orn Stef\'ansson, Benedikt Stufler, Joonas Turunen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Product-form Steady-state Distribution for Semimartingale Reflecting Brownian Motion in Multi-scaling Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by Dai et al. [2023], we develop a novel multi-scaling asymptotic regime for semimartingale reflecting Brownian motion (SRBM). In this regime, we establish the steady-state convergence of SRBM to a product-form limit with exponentially distributed components by assuming the P-reflection matrix and a uniform moment bound condition. We further demonstrate that the uniform moment bound condition holds in several subclasses of P-matrices. Our proof approach is rooted in the basic adjoint relationship (BAR) for SRBM proposed by Harrison and Williams [1987a].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19710v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Guang, Xinyun Chen, J. G. Dai, Peter W. Glynn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamic limit for repeated averages on the complete graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a hydrodynamical limit for the averaging process on the complete graph with N vertices, showing that, after a timescale of order N, the empirical distribution of opinions converges to a unique measure. Moreover, if the initial distribution is absolutely continuous concerning the Lebesgue measure, the limiting measure remains absolutely continuous and its density satisfies a non-diffusive differential equation, that resembles the Smoluchowski coagulation equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19743v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto M. Campos, Tertuliano Franco, Markus Heydenreich, Marcel Schrocke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossing a fitness valley in a changing environment: With and without pit stop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a stochastic individual-based model of adaptive dynamics for an asexually reproducing population with mutation. Biologically motivated by the influence of seasons or the variation of drug concentration during medical treatment, the model parameters vary over time as piecewise constant and periodic functions. We study the typical evolutionary behavior of the population by looking at limits of large populations and rare mutations. An analysis of the crossing of valleys in the fitness landscape in a changing environment leads to various interesting phenomena on different time scales, which depend on the length of the valley. By carefully examining the influence of the changing environment on each time scale, we are able to determine the crossing rates of fit mutants and their ability to invade the resident population. In addition, we investigate the special scenario of pit stops, where single intermediate mutants within the valley have phases of positive fitness and can thus grow to a diverging size before going extinct again. This significantly accelerates the traversal of the valley and leads to an interesting new time scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19766v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Esser, Anna Kraut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Martingale Approach to Large-$\theta$ Ewens-Pitman Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the asymptotic behavior of the number of parts $K_n$ in the Ewens--Pitman partition model under the regime where the diversity parameter is scaled linearly with the sample size, that is, $\theta = \lambda n$ for some~$\lambda &gt; 0$. While recent work has established a law of large numbers (LLN) and a central limit theorem (CLT) for $K_n$ in this regime, we revisit these results through a martingale-based approach. Our method yields significantly shorter proofs, and leads to sharper convergence rates in the CLT, including improved Berry--Esseen bounds in the case $\alpha = 0$, and a new result for the regime $\alpha \in (0,1)$, filling a gap in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19892v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Deep Learning through Probability Engineering: A Pragmatic Paradigm for Modern AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent years have witnessed the rapid progression of deep learning, pushing us closer to the realization of AGI (Artificial General Intelligence). Probabilistic modeling is critical to many of these advancements, which provides a foundational framework for capturing data distributions. However, as the scale and complexity of AI applications grow, traditional probabilistic modeling faces escalating challenges, such as high-dimensional parameter spaces, heterogeneous data sources, and evolving real-world requirements often render classical approaches insufficiently flexible.
  This paper proposes a novel concept, Probability Engineering, which treats the already-learned probability distributions within deep learning as engineering artifacts. Rather than merely fitting or inferring distributions, we actively modify and reinforce them to better address the diverse and evolving demands of modern AI. Specifically, Probability Engineering introduces novel techniques and constraints to refine existing probability distributions, improving their robustness, efficiency, adaptability, or trustworthiness.
  We showcase this paradigm through a series of applications spanning Bayesian deep learning, Edge AI (including federated learning and knowledge distillation), and Generative AI (such as text-to-image generation with diffusion models and high-quality text generation with large language models). These case studies demonstrate how probability distributions once treated as static objects can be engineered to meet the diverse and evolving requirements of large-scale, data-intensive, and trustworthy AI systems. By systematically expanding and strengthening the role of probabilistic modeling, Probability Engineering paves the way for more robust, adaptive, efficient, and trustworthy deep learning solutions in today's fast-growing AI era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18958v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mathematics of Questions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18992v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I report the existence of exactly one non-trivial solution to the equation $i(A,B)+i(A,\neg B)+i(\neg A,B)+i(\neg A,\neg B)= 0$, where $i(A,B)=\log\frac{P(A\text{ and }B)}{P(A)P(B)}$, and $P(A)$ is the probability of the proposition $A$. The equation specifies an information balance condition between two logical propositions, which is satisfied only by independence and by this new solution. The solution is a new elementary informational relationship between logical propositions, which we denote as $A \sim B$.
  The $\sim$ relation cannot be expressed as a relationship between probabilities without the use of complex numbers. It can, however, be greatly simplified by expressing each proposition as a combination of a question and an answer, for example, writing, ``All men are mortal'', as (Are all men mortal?, Yes).
  We will study the mathematics of questions and find out what role the $\sim$ relationship plays inside the algebra. We will find that, like propositions, questions can act on probability distributions. A proposition, $X$, can be given, setting $P(X)$ to 1. The question of $X$ can be raised, setting $P(X)$ to $1/2$. Giving the proposition adds information to the probability distribution, but raising the question takes information away. Introducing questions into probability theory makes it possible to represent subtraction of information as well as addition.
  We will examine how questions can be related to each other geometrically. Remarkably, the simplest way of orienting questions in space has the same structure as the simplest quantum system -- the two-state system. We will find that the essential mathematical structure of the two-state quantum system can be derived from the mathematics of questions, including non-commutativity, complementarity, wavefunction collapse, the Hilbert space representation and the Born rule, as well as quantum entanglement and non-locality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18992v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. O'Flanagan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Arbitrary Planted Subgraphs in Random Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19069v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The problems of detecting and recovering planted structures/subgraphs in Erd\H{o}s-R\'{e}nyi random graphs, have received significant attention over the past three decades, leading to many exciting results and mathematical techniques. However, prior work has largely focused on specific ad hoc planted structures and inferential settings, while a general theory has remained elusive. In this paper, we bridge this gap by investigating the detection of an \emph{arbitrary} planted subgraph $\Gamma = \Gamma_n$ in an Erd\H{o}s-R\'{e}nyi random graph $\mathcal{G}(n, q_n)$, where the edge probability within $\Gamma$ is $p_n$. We examine both the statistical and computational aspects of this problem and establish the following results. In the dense regime, where the edge probabilities $p_n$ and $q_n$ are fixed, we tightly characterize the information-theoretic and computational thresholds for detecting $\Gamma$, and provide conditions under which a computational-statistical gap arises. Most notably, these thresholds depend on $\Gamma$ only through its number of edges, maximum degree, and maximum subgraph density. Our lower and upper bounds are general and apply to any value of $p_n$ and $q_n$ as functions of $n$. Accordingly, we also analyze the sparse regime where $q_n = \Theta(n^{-\alpha})$ and $p_n-q_n =\Theta(q_n)$, with $\alpha\in[0,2]$, as well as the critical regime where $p_n=1-o(1)$ and $q_n = \Theta(n^{-\alpha})$, both of which have been widely studied, for specific choices of $\Gamma$. For these regimes, we show that our bounds are tight for all planted subgraphs investigated in the literature thus far\textemdash{}and many more. Finally, we identify conditions under which detection undergoes sharp phase transition, where the boundaries at which algorithms succeed or fail shift abruptly as a function of $q_n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19069v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dor Elimelech, Wasim Huleihel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-Seeking Decision Strategies Mitigate Risk in Dynamic, Uncertain Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19107v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To survive in dynamic and uncertain environments, individuals must develop effective decision strategies that balance information gathering and decision commitment. Models of such strategies often prioritize either optimizing tangible payoffs, like reward rate, or gathering information to support a diversity of (possibly unknown) objectives. However, our understanding of the relative merits of these two approaches remains incomplete, in part because direct comparisons have been limited to idealized, static environments that lack the dynamic complexity of the real world. Here we compared the performance of normative reward- and information-seeking strategies in a dynamic foraging task. Both strategies show similar transitions between exploratory and exploitative behaviors as environmental uncertainty changes. However, we find subtle disparities in the actions they take, resulting in meaningful performance differences: whereas reward-seeking strategies generate slightly more reward on average, information-seeking strategies provide more consistent and predictable outcomes. Our findings support the adaptive value of information-seeking behaviors that can mitigate risk with minimal reward loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19107v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas W. Barendregt, Joshua I. Gold, Kre\v{s}imir Josi\'c, Zachary P. Kilpatrick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization of interacting random particles with power-law long-range hopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the interacting random particles with power-law long-rang hopping. Via the multi-scale analysis arguments for the Green's function, we establish the power-law localization for all energy with strong disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19432v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenwen Jian, Yingte Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of Lambert W function in the simulation of Weibull and non-Weibull distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19524v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we have taken up some distributions, mostly Weibull family, whose quantile functions could not be obtained using the traditional inversion method. We have solved the same quantile functions by using the inversion method only, with the additional help of transcendental functions like the Lambert W function. The usage of the Lambert W function has helped derive closed-form solutions for mathematical models in many fields, for which explicit or exact solutions were not available and approximation was the only known way of approaching it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19524v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhashree Patra, Subarna Bhattacharjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments of the Cram\'er transform of log-concave probability measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mu$ be a centered log-concave probability measure on ${\mathbb R}^n$ and let $\Lambda_{\mu}^{\ast}$ denote the Cram\'{e}r transform of $\mu$, i.e. $\Lambda_{\mu}^{\ast}(x)=\sup\{\langle x,\xi\rangle-\Lambda_{\mu}(\xi):\xi\in\mathbb{R}^n\}$ where $\Lambda_{\mu}$ is the logarithmic Laplace transform of $\mu$. We show that $\mathbb{E}_{\mu}\left[\exp\left(\frac{c_1}{n}\Lambda_{\mu}^{\ast }\right)\right]&lt;\infty $ where $c_1&gt;0$ is an absolute constant. In, particular, $\Lambda_{\mu}^{\ast}$ has finite moments of all orders. The proof, which is based on the comparison of certain families of convex bodies associated with $\mu$, implies that $\|\Lambda_{\mu}^{\ast}\|_{L^2(\mu)}\leqslant c_2n\ln n$. The example of the uniform measure on the Euclidean ball shows that this estimate is optimal with respect to $n$ as the dimension $n$ grows to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19528v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apostolos Giannopoulos, Natalia Tziotziou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subleading-order theory for condensation transitions in large deviations of sums of independent and identically distributed random variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the full distribution $P_{N}\left(A\right)$ of sums $A = \sum_{i=1}^N$ where $x_1, \dots, x_N$ are $N \gg 1$ independent and identically distributed random variables each sampled from a given distribution $p(x)$ with a subexponential $x \to \infty$ tail. We consider two particular cases: (I) the one-sided stretched exponential distribution $p(x) \propto e^{-x^\alpha}$ where $0 &lt; x &lt; \infty$, (II) the two-sided stretched exponential distribution $p(x) \propto e^{-|x|^\alpha}$ where $-\infty &lt; x &lt; \infty$. We assume $0 &lt; \alpha &lt; 1$ (in both cases). As follows immediately from known theorems, for both cases (i) typical fluctuations of $\Delta A = A - \left\langle A\right\rangle $ are described by the central-limit theorem, (ii) the tail $A \to \infty$ is described by the big-jump principle $P_{N}\left(A\right) \simeq N p\left(A\right)$, and (iii) in between these two regimes there is a nontrivial intermediate regime which displays anomalous scaling $P_{N}\left(A\right) \sim e^{-N^\beta f(\Delta A/N^\gamma)}$ with anomalous exponents $\beta,\gamma \in (0,1)$ and large-deviation function $f(y)$ that are all exactly known. In practice, although these theoretical predictions of $P_{N}\left(A\right)$ work very well in regimes (i) and (ii), they often perform quite poorly in the intermediate regime (ii), with errors of several orders of magnitude for $N$ as large as $10^4$. We calculate subleading order corrections to the theoretical predictions in the intermediate regime. We find that for $0 &lt; \alpha &lt; \alpha_c$, these corrections scale as power laws in $N$, while for $\alpha_c &lt; \alpha &lt; 1$ they scale as stretched exponentials, where the threshold value is $\alpha_c = 1/2$ in case (I) and $\alpha_c = 2/3$ in case (II). This difference between the two cases is a result of the mirror symmetry $p(x) = p(-x)$ which holds only in the latter case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19581v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naftali R. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic exit-time control on the half-line over a finite horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19648v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a finite-time stochastic drift control problem with the assumption that the control is bounded and the system is controlled until the state process leaves the half-line. Assuming general conditions, it is proved that the resulting parabolic Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation has a classical solution. In fact, we consider an even more general family of semilinear equations, which might be helpful in solving other control or game problems. Not only is the existence result proved, but also a recursive procedure for finding a solution resulting from a fixed-point argument is provided. An application to the dividend optimization problem is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19648v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dariusz Zawisza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No-prior Bayesian inference reIMagined: probabilistic approximations of inferential models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When prior information is lacking, the go-to strategy for probabilistic inference is to combine a "default prior" and the likelihood via Bayes's theorem. Objective Bayes, (generalized) fiducial inference, etc. fall under this umbrella. This construction is natural, but the corresponding posterior distributions generally only offer limited, approximately valid uncertainty quantification. The present paper takes a reimagined approach offering posterior distributions with stronger reliability properties. The proposed construction starts with an inferential model (IM), one that takes the mathematical form of a data-driven possibility measure and features exactly valid uncertainty quantification, and then returns a so-called inner probabilistic approximation thereof. This inner probabilistic approximation inherits many of the original IM's desirable properties, including credible sets with exact coverage and asymptotic efficiency. The approximation also agrees with the familiar Bayes/fiducial solution obtained in applications where the model has a group transformation structure. A Monte Carlo method for evaluating the probabilistic approximation is presented, along with numerical illustrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19748v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Skorohod measurable universal functional representation of solutions to semimartingale SDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.06278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.06278v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we show the existence of a universal Skorohod measurable functional representation for a large class of semimartingale-driven stochastic differential equations. For this we prove that paths of the strong solutions of stochastic differential equations can be written as measurable functions of the paths of their driving processes into the space of all c\`adl\`ag functions equipped with the Borel sigma-field generated by all open sets with respect to the Skorohod metric. This result can be applied to calculate Malliavin derivatives for SDEs driven by pure-jump L\'evy processes with drift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.06278v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawe{\l} Przyby{\l}owicz, Verena Schwarz, Alexander Steinicke, Michaela Sz\"olgyenyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Permutons, meanders, and SLE-decorated Liouville quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.02319v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a class of random permutons which can be constructed from a pair of space-filling Schramm-Loewner evolution (SLE) curves on a Liouville quantum gravity (LQG) surface. This class includes the skew Brownian permutons introduced by Borga (2021), which describe the scaling limit of various types of random pattern-avoiding permutations. Another interesting permuton in our class is the meandric permuton, which corresponds to two independent SLE$_8$ curves on a $\gamma$-LQG surface with $\gamma = \sqrt{\frac13 \left( 17 - \sqrt{145} \right)}$. Building on work by Di Francesco, Golinelli, and Guitter (2000), we conjecture that the meandric permuton describes the scaling limit of uniform meandric permutations, i.e., the permutations induced by a simple loop in the plane which crosses a line a specified number of times.
  We show that for any sequence of random permutations which converges to one of the above random permutons, the length of the longest increasing subsequence is sublinear. This proves that the length of the longest increasing subsequence is sublinear for Baxter, strong-Baxter, and semi-Baxter permutations and leads to the conjecture that the same is true for meandric permutations. We also prove that the closed support of each of the random permutons in our class has Hausdorff dimension one. Finally, we prove a re-rooting invariance property for the meandric permuton and write down a formula for its expected pattern densities in terms of LQG correlation functions (which are known explicitly) and the probability that an SLE$_8$ hits a given set of points in numerical order (which is not known explicitly). We conclude with a list of open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.02319v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Borga, Ewain Gwynne, Xin Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-of-$d$ Choices Load Balancing in the Sub-Halfin Whitt Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.07539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.07539v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the load balancing system under Poisson arrivals, exponential services, and homogeneous servers. Upon arrival, a job is to be routed to one of the servers, where it is queued until service. We consider the Power-of-$d$ choices routing algorithm, which chooses the queue with minimum length among $d$ randomly sampled queues. We study this system in the many-server heavy-traffic regime where the number of servers goes to infinity simultaneously when the load approaches the capacity. In particular, we consider a sequence of systems with $n$ servers and the arrival rate is given by $\lambda=n-n^{1-\gamma}$ for some $\gamma \in (0, 0.5)$, known as the sub-Halfin-Whitt regime. It was shown by [Liu Ying (2020)] that under Power-of-$d$ choices routing with $d \geq n^\gamma \log n$, the queue length behaves similarly to that of JSQ and that there are asymptotically zero queueing delays.
  The focus of this paper is to characterize the behavior when $d$ is below this threshold. We obtain high probability bounds on the queue lengths for various values of $d$ and large enough $n$. In particular, we show that when $d$ grows polynomially in $n$ but slower than in [Liu Ying (2020)], i.e., if $d$ is $\Theta\left((n^\gamma\log n)^{1/m})\right)$ for some integer $m&gt;1$, then the asymptotic queue length is $m$ with high probability. Moreover, if $d$ grows polylog in $n$, i.e., slower than any polynomial, but is at least $\Omega(\log (n)^3)$, the queue length blows up to infinity asymptotically. We obtain these results by using an iterative state space collapse approach. We first establish a weak state-space collapse (SSC) on the queue lengths. Then, we bootstrap on weak SSC to iteratively narrow down the region of the collapse. After enough steps, this inductive refinement provides the bounds we seek. We establish these sequences of collapse using Lyapunov drift arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.07539v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sushil Mahavir Varma, Francisco Castro, Siva Theja Maguluri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the exact simulation of a random eigenvalue of a GUE matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.03741v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a simple algorithm to generate random variables described by densities equaling squared Hermite functions. As an application, we show how to generate a randomly chosen eigenvalue of a matrix from the Gaussian Unitary Ensemble ({\textsc{gue}}) in sub-linear expected time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.03741v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Devroye, Jad Hamdan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of small-ball modes and maximum a posteriori estimators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16278v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A mode, or `most likely point', for a probability measure $\mu$ can be defined in various ways via the asymptotic behaviour of the $\mu$-mass of balls as their radius tends to zero. Such points are of intrinsic interest in the local theory of measures on metric spaces and also arise naturally in the study of Bayesian inverse problems and diffusion processes. Building upon special cases already proposed in the literature, this paper develops a systematic framework for defining modes through small-ball probabilities. We propose `common-sense' axioms that such definitions should obey, including appropriate treatment of discrete and absolutely continuous measures, as well as symmetry and invariance properties. We show that there are exactly ten such definitions consistent with these axioms, and that they are partially but not totally ordered in strength, forming a complete, distributive lattice. We also show how this classification simplifies for well-behaved $\mu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16278v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilja Klebanov, Hefin Lambley, T. J. Sullivan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-spin symmetry in the $\mathfrak{sl}_3$ boundary Toda conformal field theory I: Ward identities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13874v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article is the first of a two-part series dedicated to studying the symmetries enjoyed by the probabilistic construction of the $\mathfrak{sl}_3$ boundary Toda Conformal Field Theory. Namely in the present document we show that this model enjoys higher-spin symmetry in the form of Ward identities, both local and global. To do so we consider the $\mathfrak{sl}_3$ Toda theory on the upper-half plane and rigorously define the descendant fields associated to the Vertex Operators. We then show that we can express local as well as global Ward identities based on them, for both the stress-energy tensor and the higher-spin current that encodes this enhanced level of symmetry. This answers a question raised in the physics literature as to whether Toda theory still enjoys higher-spin symmetry in the boundary case. The second part of this series will be dedicated to computing the singular vectors of the theory and showing that they give rise to higher equations of motion as well as, under additional assumptions, BPZ-type differential equations for the correlation functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13874v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Cercl\'e, Nathan Huguenin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decorrelation transition in the Wigner minor process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06549v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the Wigner minor process, i.e. the eigenvalues of an $N\times N$ Wigner matrix $H^{(N)}$ together with the eigenvalues of all its $n\times n$ minors, $H^{(n)}$, $n\le N$. The top eigenvalues of $H^{(N)}$ and those of its immediate minor $H^{(N-1)}$ are very strongly correlated, but this correlation becomes weaker for smaller minors $H^{(N-k)}$ as $k$ increases. For the GUE minor process the critical transition regime around $k\sim N^{2/3}$ was analyzed by Forrester and Nagao (J. Stat. Mech.: Theory and Experiment, 2011) providing an explicit formula for the nontrivial joint correlation function. We prove that this formula is universal, i.e. it holds for the Wigner minor process. Moreover, we give a complete analysis of the sub- and supercritical regimes both for eigenvalues and for the corresponding eigenvector overlaps, thus we prove the decorrelation transition in full generality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06549v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Bao, Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Joscha Henheik, Oleksii Kolupaiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Clustering Algorithms on Poisson and Cox Point Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18555v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Clustering is a widely used technique in unsupervised learning to identify groups within a dataset based on the similarities between its elements. This paper introduces three new hierarchical clustering models, Clustroid Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{CHN}^2$), Single Linkage Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{SHN}^2$), and Hausdorff (Complete Linkage) Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{H}^2\mathrm{N}^2$), all designed for datasets with a countably infinite number of points. These algorithms proceed through multiple levels of clustering and construct clusters by connecting nearest-neighbor points or clusters, but differ in the distance metrics they employ (clustroid, single linkage, or Hausdorff, respectively). Each method is first applied to the homogeneous Poisson point process on the Euclidean space, where it defines a phylogenetic forest, which is a factor of the point process and therefore unimodular. The results established for the $\mathrm{CHN}^2$ algorithm include the almost-sure finiteness of the clusters and bounds on the mean cluster size at each level of the algorithm. The mean size of the typical cluster is shown to be infinite. Moreover, the limiting structure of all three algorithms is examined as the number of levels tends to infinity, and properties such as the one-endedness of the limiting connected components are derived. In the specific case of $\mathrm{SHN}^2$ on the Poisson point process, the limiting graph is shown to be a subgraph of the Minimal Spanning Forest. The $\mathrm{CHN}^2$ algorithm is also extended beyond the Poisson setting, to certain stationary Cox point processes. Similar finite-cluster properties are shown to hold in these cases. It is also shown that efficient detection of Cox-triggered aggregation can be achieved through this clustering algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18555v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayeh Khaniha, Fran\c{c}ois Baccelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law for Kendall's tau</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18645v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bandeira et al. (2017) show that the eigenvalues of the Kendall correlation matrix of $n$ i.i.d. random vectors in $\mathbb{R}^p$ are asymptotically distributed like $1/3 + (2/3)Y_q$, where $Y_q$ has a Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law with parameter $q=\lim(p/n)$ if $p, n\to\infty$ proportionately to one another. Here we show that another Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law emerges in the "ultra-high dimensional" scaling limit where $p\sim q'\, n^2/2$ for some $q'&gt;0$: in this quadratic scaling regime, Kendall correlation eigenvalues converge weakly almost surely to $(1/3)Y_{q'}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18645v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Bousseyroux, Tomas Espana, Matteo Smerlak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insight from the Kullback--Leibler divergence into adaptive importance sampling schemes for rare event analysis in high dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16828v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study two adaptive importance sampling schemes for estimating the probability of a rare event in the high-dimensional regime $d \to \infty$ with $d$ the dimension. The first scheme is the prominent cross-entropy (CE) method, and the second scheme, motivated by recent results, uses as auxiliary distribution a projection of the optimal auxiliary distribution on a lower dimensional subspace. In these schemes, two samples are used: the first one to learn the auxiliary distribution and the second one, drawn according to the learned distribution, to perform the final probability estimation. Contrary to the common belief that the sample size needs to grow exponentially in the dimension to make the estimator consistent and avoid the weight degeneracy phenomenon, we find that a polynomial sample size in the first learning step is enough. We prove this result assuming that the sought probability is bounded away from 0. For CE, insight is provided on the polynomial growth rate which remains implicit. In contrast, we study the second scheme in a simple computational framework assuming that samples from the conditional distribution are available. This makes it possible to show that the sample size only needs to grow like $rd$ with $r$ the effective dimension of the projection, which highlights the potential benefits of these projection methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16828v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Beh, Yonatan Shadmi, Florian Simatos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hilbert Space-Valued LQ Mean Field Games: An Infinite-Dimensional Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01012v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive study of linear-quadratic (LQ) mean field games (MFGs) in Hilbert spaces, generalizing the classic LQ MFG theory to scenarios involving $N$ agents with dynamics governed by infinite-dimensional stochastic equations. In this framework, both state and control processes of each agent take values in separable Hilbert spaces. All agents are coupled through the average state of the population which appears in their linear dynamics and quadratic cost functional. Specifically, the dynamics of each agent incorporates an infinite-dimensional noise, namely a $Q$-Wiener process, and an unbounded operator. The diffusion coefficient of each agent is stochastic involving the state, control, and average state processes. We first study the well-posedness of a system of $N$ coupled semilinear infinite-dimensional stochastic evolution equations establishing the foundation of MFGs in Hilbert spaces. We then specialize to $N$-player LQ games described above and study the asymptotic behaviour as the number of agents, $N$, approaches infinity. We develop an infinite-dimensional variant of the Nash Certainty Equivalence principle and characterize a unique Nash equilibrium for the limiting MFG. Finally, we study the connections between the $N$-player game and the limiting MFG, demonstrating that the empirical average state converges to the mean field and that the resulting limiting best-response strategies form an $\epsilon$-Nash equilibrium for the $N$-player game in Hilbert spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01012v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanchao Liu, Dena Firoozi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical multi-fidelity machine learning: fusion of deterministic and Bayesian models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multi-fidelity machine learning methods address the accuracy-efficiency trade-off by integrating scarce, resource-intensive high-fidelity data with abundant but less accurate low-fidelity data. We propose a practical multi-fidelity strategy for problems spanning low- and high-dimensional domains, integrating a non-probabilistic regression model for the low-fidelity with a Bayesian model for the high-fidelity. The models are trained in a staggered scheme, where the low-fidelity model is transfer-learned to the high-fidelity data and a Bayesian model is trained to learn the residual between the data and the transfer-learned model. This three-model strategy -- deterministic low-fidelity, transfer-learning, and Bayesian residual -- leads to a prediction that includes uncertainty quantification for noisy and noiseless multi-fidelity data. The strategy is general and unifies the topic, highlighting the expressivity trade-off between the transfer-learning and Bayesian models (a complex transfer-learning model leads to a simpler Bayesian model, and vice versa). We propose modeling choices for two scenarios, and argue in favor of using a linear transfer-learning model that fuses 1) kernel ridge regression for low-fidelity with Gaussian processes for high-fidelity; or 2) deep neural network for low-fidelity with a Bayesian neural network for high-fidelity. We demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of the proposed strategies and contrast them with the state-of-the-art based on various numerical examples and two engineering problems. The results indicate that the proposed approach achieves comparable performance in both mean and uncertainty estimation while significantly reducing training time for machine learning modeling in data-scarce scenarios. Moreover, in data-rich settings, it outperforms other multi-fidelity architectures by effectively mitigating overfitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15110v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxiang Yi, Ji Cheng, Miguel A. Bessa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic neighborhood embedding and the gradient flow of relative entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16963v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dimension reduction, widely used in science, maps high-dimensional data into low-dimensional space. We investigate a basic mathematical model underlying the techniques of stochastic neighborhood embedding (SNE) and its popular variant t-SNE. Distances between points in high dimensions are used to define a probability distribution on pairs of points, measuring how similar the points are. The aim is to map these points to low dimensions in an optimal way so that similar points are closer together. This is carried out by minimizing the relative entropy between two probability distributions.
  We consider the gradient flow of the relative entropy and analyze its long-time behavior. This is a self-contained mathematical problem about the behavior of a system of nonlinear ordinary differential equations. We find optimal bounds for the diameter of the evolving sets as time tends to infinity. In particular, the diameter may blow up for the t-SNE version, but remains bounded for SNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16963v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Weinkove</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tractable fish growth models considering individual differences with an application to the fish Plecoglossus altivelis altivelis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20076v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modeling fish growth is an important research topic in ecological and fishery sciences because body weight statistics directly affect the total biomass of fish in a habitat, which in turn affects their population dynamics. Many models of fish growth assume that the fish population in a habitat is homogenous, meaning that there is no physiological spectrum and, therefore, no size spectrum. Moreover, models that account for the size spectrum are not always analytically tractable. We present novel mathematical models of fish growth in which the body weight of each fish is assumed to follow a von Bertalanffy-type model whose proportionality coefficient, representing the maximum body weight, may differ among individual fish. This probabilistic description introduces the size spectrum into the model, owing to which the time-dependent probability density of this model is obtained explicitly. We also consider a misspecified version and a stochastic version of the model as advanced cases. We apply the first model to the real growth data of Plecoglossus altivelis altivelis as a keystone fish species in Japan. The model successfully reproduces the skewed size spectrum of this fish species over multiple years. We further use the stochastic model to investigate how fish growth dynamics are affected by environmental fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20076v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Yoshioka, Y. Yoshioka, M. Tsujimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A control variate method for threshold crossing probabilities of plastic deformation driven by transient coloured noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a hybrid method combining partial differential equation (PDE) and Monte Carlo (MC) techniques to obtain efficient estimates of statistics for plastic deformation related to kinematic hardening models driven by transient coloured noise. Our approach employs a control variate strategy inspired by [CPAM, 75 (3), 455-492, 2022] and relies on a class of PDEs with non-standard boundary conditions, which we derive here. The solutions of those PDEs represent the statistics of models driven by transient white noise and are significantly easier to solve than the coloured noise version. We apply our method to threshold-crossing probabilities, which are used as failure criteria known as ultimate and serviceability limit states under non-stationary excitation. Our contribution provides solid grounds for such calculations and is significantly more computationally efficient in terms of variance reduction compared to standard MC simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry L. F. Ip, Charlie Mathey, Laurent Mertz, Jonathan Wylie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse-Grained Games: A Framework for Bounded Perception in Game Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17598v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In everyday life, we frequently make coarse-grained judgments. When we say that Olivia and Noah excel in mathematics, we disregard the specific differences in their mathematical abilities. Similarly, when we claim that a particular automobile manufacturer produces high-quality cars, we overlook the minor variations among individual vehicles. These coarse-grained assessments are distinct from erroneous or deceptive judgments, such as those resulting from student cheating or false advertising by corporations. Despite the prevalence of such judgments, little attention has been given to their underlying mathematical structure. In this paper, we introduce the concept of coarse-graining into game theory, analyzing games where players may perceive different payoffs as identical while preserving the underlying order structure. We call it a Coarse-Grained Game (CGG). This framework allows us to examine the rational inference processes that arise when players equate distinct micro-level payoffs at a macro level, and to explore how Nash equilibria are preserved or altered as a result. Our key findings suggest that CGGs possess several desirable properties that make them suitable for modeling phenomena in the social sciences. This paper demonstrates two such applications: first, in cases of overly minor product updates, consumers may encounter an equilibrium selection problem, resulting in market behavior that is not driven by objective quality differences; second, the lemon market can be analyzed not only through objective information asymmetry but also through asymmetries in perceptual resolution or recognition ability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17598v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Izumo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
