<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 02:15:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the long time behavior of the elephant random walk with stops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the long time behavior of the elephant random walk with stops, introduced by Kumar, Harbola and Lindenberg (2010), and establish the phase transition of the number of visited points up to time $n$, and the correlation between the position at time $n$ and the number of moves up to time $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17586v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuya Akimoto, Masato Takei, Keisuke Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new tail bound for the sum of bounded independent random variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a new tail bound for the sum of independent random variables for situations in which the expected value of the sum is known and each random variable lies within a specified interval, which may be different for each variable. This new bound can be computed by solving a two-dimensional convex optimization problem. Simulations demonstrate that the new bound is often substantially tighter than Hoeffding's inequality for cases in which both bounds are applicable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17594v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson Loper, Jeffrey Regier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random cluster models on random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17636v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On locally tree-like random graphs, we relate the random cluster model with external magnetic fields and $q\geq 2$ to Ising models with vertex-dependent external fields. The fact that one can formulate general random cluster models in terms of two-spin ferromagnetic Ising models is quite interesting in its own right. However, in the general setting, the external fields are both positive and negative, which is mathematically unexplored territory. Interestingly, due to the reformulation as a two-spin model, we can show that the Bethe partition function, which is believed to have the same pressure per particle, is always a {\em lower bound} on the graph pressure per particle. We further investigate special cases in which the external fields do always have the same sign.
  The first example is the Potts model with general external fields on random $d$-regular graphs. In this case, we show that the pressure per particle in the quenched setting agrees with that of the annealed setting, and verify \cite[Assumption 1.4]{BasDemSly23}. We show that there is a line of values for the external fields where the model displays a first-order phase transition. This completes the identification of the phase diagram of the Potts model on the random $d$-regular graph. As a second example, we consider the high external field and low temperature phases of the system on locally tree-like graphs with general degree distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17636v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Van Hao Can, Remco van der Hofstad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the state occupancy distribution for Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent paper, Shah [arXiv:2502.03073] derived an explicit expression for the distribution of occupancy times for a two-state Markov chain, using a method based on enumerating sample paths. We consider here the more general problem of finding the distribution of occupancy times for countable-state Markov chains in discrete time. Our approach, which employs generating functions, leads to arguably simpler formulae for the occupancy distribution for the two-state chain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17647v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phil Pollett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple orthogonal polynomial ensembles of derivative type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the biorthogonal ensembles that are both a multiple orthogonal polynomial ensemble and a polynomial ensemble of derivative type (also called a P\'olya ensemble). We focus on the two notions of derivative type that typically appear in connection with the squared singular values of products of invertible random matrices and the eigenvalues of sums of Hermitian random matrices. Essential in the characterization is the use of the Mellin and Laplace transform: we show that the derivative type structure, which is a priori analytic in nature, becomes algebraic after applying the appropriate transform. Afterwards, we explain how these notions of derivative type can be used to provide a partial solution to an open problem related to orthogonality of the finite finite free multiplicative and additive convolution from finite free probability. In particular, we obtain families of multiple orthogonal polynomials that (de)compose naturally using these convolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17832v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Wolfs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermediate disorder for directed polymers with space-time correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit a result of Hairer-Shen on polymer-type approximations for the stochastic heat equation with a multiplicative noise (SHE) in $d=1$. We consider a general class of polymer models with strongly mixing environment in space and time, and we prove convergence to the It\^o solution of the SHE (modulo shear). The environment is not assumed to be Gaussian, nor is it assumed to be white-in-time. Instead of using regularity structures or paracontrolled products, we rely on simpler moment-based characterizations of the SHE to prove the convergence. However, the price to pay is that our topology of convergence is weak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17888v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalin Parekh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuations of the linear functionals for supercritical non-local branching superprocesses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Suppose $\{X_{t}:t\ge 0\}$ is a supercritical superprocess on a Luzin space $E$, with a non-local branching mechanism and probabilities $\mathbb{P}_{\delta_{x}}$, when initiated from a unit mass at $x\in E$. By ``supercritical", we mean that the first moment semigroup of $X_{t}$ exhibits a Perron-Frobenius type behaviour characterized by an eigentriple $(\lambda_{1},\varphi,\widetilde{\varphi})$, where the principal eigenvalue $\lambda_{1}$ is greater than $0$. Under a second moment condition, we prove that $X_{t}$ satisfies a law of large numbers. The main purpose of this paper is to further investigate the fluctuations of the linear functional $\mathrm{e}^{-\lambda_{1}t}\langle f,X_{t}\rangle$ around the limit given by the law of large numbers. To this end, we introduce a parameter $\epsilon(f)$ for a bounded measurable function $f$, which determines the exponent term of the decay rate for the first moment of the fluctuation. Qualitatively, the second-order behaviour of $\langle f,X_{t}\rangle$ depends on the sign of $\epsilon(f)-\lambda_{1}/2$. We prove that, for a suitable test function $f$, the fluctuation of the associated linear functional exhibits distinct asymptotic behaviours depending on the magnitude of $\epsilon(f)$: If $\epsilon(f)\ge \lambda_{1}/2$, the fluctuation converges in distribution to a Gaussian limit under appropriate normalization; If $\epsilon(f)&lt;\lambda_{1}/2$, the fluctuation converges to an $L^{2}$ limit with a larger normalization factor. In particular, when the test function is chosen as the right eigenfunction $\varphi$, we establish a functional central limit theorem. As an application, we consider a multitype superdiffusion in a bounded domain. For this model, we derive limit theorems for the fluctuations of arbitrary linear functionals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17929v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-uniqueness of Leray-Hopf Solutions to Forced Stochastic Hyperdissipative Navier-Stokes Equations up to Lions Index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show non-uniqueness of local strong solutions to stochastic fractional Navier-Stokes equations with linear multiplicative noise and some certain deterministic force. Such non-uniqueness holds true even if we perturb such deterministic force in appropriate sense.This is closely related to a critical condition on force under which Leray-Hopf solution to the stochastic equations is locally unique. Meanwhile, by a new idea, we show that for some stochastic force the system admits two different global Leray-Hopf solutions smooth on any compact subset of $(0,\infty) \times \mathbb{R}^d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18041v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiquan Chen, Zhao Dong, Yang Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodicity for stochastic 2D Boussinesq equations with a highly degenerate pure jump Levy noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study aims to analyze the ergodicity for stochastic 2D Boussinesq equations and explore the impact of a highly degenerate pure jump Levy noise acting only in the temperature equation, this noise could appear on a few Fourier modes. By leveraging the equi-continuity of the semigroup-established through Malliavin calculus and an analysis of stochastic calculus-together with the weak irreducibility of the solution process, we prove the existence and uniqueness of the invariant measure. Moreover, we overcome the main challenge of establishing time asymptotic smoothing properties of the Markovian dynamics corresponding to this system by conducting spectral analysis of the Malliavin covariance matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18045v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhua Huang, Xuhui Peng, Xue Wang, Jiangwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-(strong) ergodicity criteria for discrete time Markov chains on general state spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For discrete time Markov chains on general state spaces, we provide criteria for non-ergodicity and non-strong ergodicity. By taking advantage of minimal non-negative solution theory, our criteria are in terms of the existence of solutions to inequalities involving the one step transition semigroup of the chain. Based on Dynkin's formula, Lyapunov-type conditions for non-strong ergodicity are also obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18046v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling-Di Wang, Yu Chen, Yu-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rough Heston model as the scaling limit of bivariate heavy-tailed INAR($\infty$) processes and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18259v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper establishes a novel link between nearly unstable heavy-tailed integer-valued autoregressive (INAR) processes and the rough Heston model via discrete scaling limits. We prove that a sequence of bivariate cumulative INAR($\infty$) processes converge in law to the rough Heston model under appropriate scaling conditions, providing a rigorous mathematical foundation for understanding how microstructural order flow drives rough volatility dynamics. Our theoretical framework extends the scaling limit techniques from Hawkes processes to the INAR($\infty$) setting. Thus we can carry out Monte Carlo simulation of the rough Heston model through simulating the corresponding approximating INAR($\infty$) processes. Extensive numerical experiments illustrate the improved accuracy and efficiency of the proposed simulation method as compared to the literature, in the pricing of not only European options, but also path-dependent options such as arithmetic Asian options, lookback options and barrier options.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18259v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingli Wang, Zhenyu Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The probability of almost all eigenvalues being real for the elliptic real Ginibre ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18310v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate real eigenvalues of real elliptic Ginibre matrices of size $n$, indexed by the asymmetric parameter $\tau \in [0,1]$. In both the strongly and weakly non-Hermitian regimes, where $\tau \in [0,1)$ is fixed or $1-\tau=O(1/n)$, respectively, we derive the asymptotic expansion of the probability $p_{n,n-2l}$ that all but a finite number $2l$ of eigenvalues are real. In particular, we show that the expansion is of the form $$\begin{align*} \log p_{n, n-2l} = \begin{cases} a_1 n^2 +a_2 n + a_3 \log n +O(1) &amp;\text{at strong non-Hermiticity}, \\ b_1 n +b_2 \log n + b_3 +o(1) &amp;\text{at weak non-Hermiticity}, \end{cases} \end{align*}$$ and we determine all coefficients explicitly. Furthermore, in the special case where $l=1$, we derive the full-order expansions. For the proofs, we employ distinct methods for the strongly and weakly non-Hermitian regimes. In the former case, we utilise potential-theoretic techniques to analyse the free energy of elliptic Ginibre matrices conditioned to have $n-2l$ real eigenvalues, together with strong Szeg\H{o} limit theorems. In the latter case, we utilise the skew-orthogonal polynomial formalism and the asymptotic behaviour of the Hermite polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18310v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gernot Akemann, Sung-Soo Byun, Yong-Woo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the maximal displacement of some critical branching L{\'e}vy processes with stable offspring distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let X be a critical branching L{\'e}vy process whose offspring distribution is in the domain of attraction of a stable random variable. We study the tail probability of the maximum location ever reached by a particle in two different situations: first when the underlying L{\'e}vy process L admits moments of order at least two and is not centered, and then when the distribution of L has a regularly varying tail. This work complements some earlier results in which either L was centered or the offspring distribution was assumed to have moments of order three.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18451v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Profeta (LaMME)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weingarten calculus for centered random permutation matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and study the Weingarten calculus for centered random permutation matrices in the symmetric group S_N. After presenting a formulation of the Weingarten calculus on the symmetric group, we derive a formula in the centered case, as well as a sign-respecting formula. Our investigations uncover the fact that a building block of this Weingarten calculus is Kummer's confluent hypergeometric function. It allows us to derive multiple algebraic properties of the Weingarten function and uniform estimate. These results shed a conceptual light on phenomena that take place regarding the algebraic and asymptotic behavior of moments of random permutations in the resolution of Bordenave and Bordenave-Collins of strong convergence. We obtain multiple new non-trivial estimates for moments of coefficients in centered moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18453v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beno\^it Collins, Manasa Nagatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the sampling entropy of permutons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a permuton $\mu$ let $H_n(\mu)$ denote the Shannon entropy of the sampling distribution of $\mu$ on $n$ points. We investigate the asymptotic growth of $H_n(\mu)$ for a wide class of permutons.
  We prove that if $\mu$ has a non-vanishing absolutely continuous part, then $H_n(\mu)$ has a growth rate $\Theta(n \log n)$. We show that if $\mu$ is the graph of a piecewise continuously differentiable, measure-preserving function $f$, then $H_n(\mu)/n$ tends to the Kolmogorov--Sinai entropy of $f$. Using genericity arguments, we also prove the existence of function permutons for which $H_n(\mu)$ does not converge either after normalizing by $n$ or by $n\log n$.
  We study the sampling entropy of a natural family of random fractal-like permutons determined by a sequence of i.i.d. choices. It turns out that for every $n$, $H_n(\mu)/n$ is heavily concentrated. We prove that the sequence $H_n(\mu)/n$ either converges or has deterministic log-periodic oscillations almost surely, and argue towards the conjecture that in nondegenerate case, oscillation holds. On the other hand, for a straightforward random perturbation of the model $\tilde{\mu}$ of $\mu$, we prove the almost sure convergence of $H_n(\tilde{\mu})/n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18518v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bal\'azs Maga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Clustering Algorithms on Poisson and Cox Point Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18555v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Clustering is a widely used technique in unsupervised learning to identify groups within a dataset based on the similarities between its elements. This paper introduces three new hierarchical clustering models, Clustroid Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{CHN}^2$), Single Linkage Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{SHN}^2$), and Hausdorff (Complete Linkage) Hierarchical Nearest Neighbor ($\mathrm{H}^2\mathrm{N}^2$), all designed for datasets with a countably infinite number of points. These algorithms proceed through multiple levels of clustering and construct clusters by connecting nearest-neighbor points or clusters, but differ in the distance metrics they employ (clustroid, single linkage, or Hausdorff, respectively). Each method is first applied to the homogeneous Poisson point process on the Euclidean space, where it defines a phylogenetic forest, which is a factor of the point process and therefore unimodular. The results established for the $\mathrm{CHN}^2$ algorithm include the almost-sure finiteness of the clusters and bounds on the mean cluster size at each level of the algorithm. The mean size of the typical cluster is shown to be infinite. Moreover, the limiting structure of all three algorithms is examined as the number of levels tends to infinity, and properties such as the one-endedness of the limiting connected components are derived. In the specific case of $\mathrm{SHN}^2$ on the Poisson point process, the limiting graph is shown to be a subgraph of the Minimal Spanning Forest. The $\mathrm{CHN}^2$ algorithm is also extended beyond the Poisson setting, to certain stationary Cox point processes. Similar finite-cluster properties are shown to hold in these cases. It is also shown that efficient detection of Cox-triggered aggregation can be achieved through this clustering algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18555v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayeh Khaniha, Fran\c{c}ois Baccelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-fractional distributions and branching processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18563v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In branching process theory, linear-fractional distributions are commonly used to model individual reproduction, especially when the goal is to obtain more explicit formulas than those derived under general model assumptions. In this article, we explore a generalization of these distributions, first introduced by Sagitov and Lindo, which offers similar advantages. We refer to these as power-fractional distributions, primarily because, as we demonstrate, they exhibit power-law behavior. Along with a discussion of their additional properties, we present several results related to the Galton-Watson branching process in both constant and randomly varying environments, illustrating these advantages. The use of power-fractional distributions in continuous time, particularly within the framework of Markov branching processes, is also briefly addressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18563v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerold Alsmeyer, Viet Hung Hoang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemical distance in the Poisson Boolean model with regularly varying diameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Poisson Boolean model with convex bodies which are rotation-invariant distributed. We assume that the convex bodies have regularly varying diameters with indices $-\alpha_1\geq \dots\geq-\alpha_d$ where $\alpha_k &gt;0$ for all $k\in\{1,\dots,d\}.$ It is known that a sufficient condition for the robustness of the model, i.e. the union of the convex bodies has an unbounded connected component no matter what the intensity of the underlying Poisson process is, is that there exists some $k\in\{1,\dots,d\}$ such that $\alpha_k&lt;\min\{2k,d\}$. To avoid that this connected component covers all of $\mathbb{R}^d$ almost surely we also require $\alpha_k&gt; k$ for all $k\in\{1,\dots,d\}$. We show that under these assumptions, the chemical distance of two far apart vertices $\mathbf{x}$ and $\mathbf{y}$ behaves like $c\log\log|x-y|$ as $|x-y|\rightarrow \infty$, with an explicit and very surprising constant $c$ that depends only on the model parameters. We furthermore show that if there exists $k$ such that $\alpha_k\leq k$, the chemical distance is smaller than $c\log\log|x-y|$ for all $c&gt;0$ and that if $\alpha_k\geq\min\{2k,d\}$ for all $k$, it is bigger than $c\log\log|x-y|$ for all $c&gt;0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18577v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Gracar, Marilyn Korfhage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law for Kendall's tau</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18645v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bandeira et al. (2017) show that the eigenvalues of the Kendall correlation matrix of $n$ i.i.d. random vectors in $\mathbb{R}^p$ are asymptotically distributed like $1/3 + (2/3)Y_q$, where $Y_q$ has a Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law with parameter $q=\lim(p/n)$ if $p, n\to\infty$ proportionately to one another. Here we show that another Mar\v{c}enko-Pastur law emerges in the "ultra-high dimensional" scaling limit where $p\sim q'\, n^2/2$ for some $q'&gt;0$: in this quadratic scaling regime, Kendall correlation eigenvalues converge weakly almost surely to $(1/3)Y_{q'}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18645v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Bousseyroux, Tomas Espana, Matteo Smerlak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perpetuities with light tails and the local dependence measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work investigates the tail behavior of solutions to the affine stochastic fixed-point equation of the form $X\stackrel{d}{=}AX+B$, where $X$ and $(A,B)$ are independent. Focusing on the light-tail regime, following [Burdzy et al. (2022), Ann. Appl. Probab.] we introduce a local dependence measure along with an associated Legendre-type transform. These tools allow us to effectively describe the logarithmic right-tail asymptotics of the solution $X$.
  Moreover, we extend our analysis to a related recursive sequence $X_n=A_n X_{n-1}+B_n$, where $(A_n,B_n)_{n}$ are i.i.d. copies of $(A,B)$. For this sequence, we construct deterministic scaling $(f_n)_{n}$ such that $\limsup_{n\to\infty} X_n/ f_n$ is a.s. positive and finite, with its non-random explicit value provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18697v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Le Bihan, Bartosz Ko{\l}odziejek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation equations with stretched non-local operators and renewal processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and study renewal processes defined by means of extensions of the standard relaxation equation through ``stretched" non-local operators (of order $\alpha$ and with parameter $\gamma$). In a first case we obtain a generalization of the fractional Poisson process, which displays either infinite or finite expected waiting times between arrivals, depending on the parameter $\gamma$. In the long run, the latter is proved to control also the memory property of the process, which, in some cases, is long-range dependent. We then consider a second-order relaxation-type equation involving the same operator, under different sets of conditions on the constants involved, and prove that the corresponding renewal processes are linked to the previous one either by convolution or by convex combination of the distributions. We discuss also time-change representations of these models, in terms of the inverse of a non-decreasing process which generalizes the $\alpha$-stable L\'{e}vy subordinator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18863v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luisa Beghin, Nikolai Leonenko, Jayme Vaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Law of fractional logarithm for random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the Paquette-Zeitouni law of fractional logarithm (LFL) for the extreme eigenvalues [arXiv:1505.05627] in full generality, and thereby verify a conjecture from [arXiv:1505.05627]. Our result holds for any Wigner minor process and both symmetry classes, in particular for the GOE minor process, while [arXiv:1505.05627] and the recent full resolution of LFL by Baslingker et.~al.~[arXiv:2410.11836] cover only the GUE case which is determinantal. Lacking the possibility for a direct comparison with the Gaussian case, we develop a robust and natural method for both key parts of the proof. On one hand, we rely on a powerful martingale technique to describe precisely the strong correlation between the largest eigenvalue of an $N\times N$ Wigner matrix and its $(N-k)\times (N-k)$ minor if $k\ll N^{2/3}$. On the other hand, we use dynamical methods to show that this correlation is weak if $k\gg N^{2/3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18922v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Bao, Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Joscha Henheik, Oleksii Kolupaiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inequality and Mobility in a Minimal Model for Evolving Income Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17375v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we explore the dynamic relationship between income inequality and economic mobility through a pairing of a population-scale partial differential equation (PDE) model and an associated individual-based stochastic differential equation (SDE) model. We focus on two fundamental mechanisms of income growth: (1) that annual growth is percentile-dependent, and (2) that there is intrinsic variability from one individual to the next. Under these two assumptions, we show that increased economic mobility does not necessarily imply decreased income inequality. In fact, we show that the mechanism that directly enhances mobility, intrinsic variability, simultaneously increases inequality.
  Using Growth Incidence Curves, and other summary statistics like mean income and the Gini coefficient, we calibrate our model to US Census data (1968-2021) and show that there are multiple parameter settings that produce the same growth in inequality over time. Strikingly, these parameter settings produce dramatically different mobility outcomes. Naturally, the greater disparity there is between annual percentage growth in the upper and lower income levels, the less ability there is for individuals to climb the percentile ranks over a fixed period of time. However, more than this, the model shows that whatever mobility does exist, it decreases substantially over time. In other words, while it may remain true that opportunity to reach the upper ranks mathematically persists in the long run, that long run gets longer and longer every year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17375v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott A. McKinley, Gary A. Hoover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Group Means and Into the World of Individuals: A Distributional Spotlight for Experimental Effects on Individuals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17390v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditionally, experimental effects on humans are investigated at the group level. In this work, we present a distributional "spotlight" to investigate experimental effects at the individual level. Specifically, we estimate the effects on individuals through the changes in the probability distributions of their experimental data across conditions. We test this approach on Reaction Time (RT) data from 10 individuals in a visual search task, examining the effects of (1) information set sizes and (2) the presence or absence of a target on their processing speed. The changes in individuals' RT distributions are measured using three approaches: (i) direct measurements of distributional changes are compared against the changes captured by two established models of RT: (ii) the ex-Gaussian distribution and (iii) the Drift-Diffusion model. We find that direct measurement of distributional changes provides the clearest view of the effects on individuals and highlights the presence of two sub-groups based on the effects experienced: one that shows neither effect and the other showing only the target-presence effect. Moreover, the intra-individual changes across conditions (i.e., the experimental effects) appear much smaller than the intra-individual differences (i.e., the random effects). Generally, these results highlight the merits of going beyond group means and examining the effects on individuals, as well as the effectiveness of the distributional spotlight in such pursuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17390v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roussel Rahman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stereological 3D modeling of nano-scale catalyst particles using TEM projections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17437v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Catalysis, particularly heterogeneous catalysis, is crucial in the chemical industry and energy storage. Approximately 80% of all chemical products produced by heterogeneous catalysis are produced by solid catalysts, which are essential for the synthesizing of ammonia, methanol, and hydrocarbons. Despite extensive use, challenges in catalyst development remain, including enhancing selectivity, stability, and activity. These effective properties are influenced by the nanoscale morphology of the catalysts, whereby the size of the nanoparticles is only one key descriptor. To investigate the relationship between nanoparticle morphology and catalytic performance, a comprehensive 3D analysis of nano-scale catalyst particles is necessary. However, traditional imaging techniques for a representative recording of this size range, such as transmission electron microscopy (TEM), are mostly limited to 2D. Thus, in the present paper, a stochastic 3D model is developed for a data-driven analysis of the nanostructure of catalyst particles. The calibration of this model is achieved using 2D TEM data from two different length scales, allowing for a statistically representative 3D modeling of catalyst particles. Furthermore, digital twins of catalyst particles can be drawn for the stochastic 3D model for virtual materials testing, enhancing the understanding of the relationship between catalyst nanostructure and performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17437v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Fuchs, Kerstin Wein, Jens Friedland, Orkun Furat, Robert G\"uttel, Volker Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments of permutation statistics by cycle type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Beginning with work of Zeilberger on classical pattern counts, there are a variety of structural results for moments of permutation statistics applied to random permutations. Using tools from representation theory, Gaetz and Ryba generalized Zeilberger's results to uniformly random permutations of a given cycle type. We introduce regular statistics and characterize their moments for all cycle types, generalizing all results in this literature that we are aware of. Our approach splits into two steps: first characterize such statistics as linear combinations of indicator functions for partial permutations, then identifying the moments of such indicators. As an application, we show that many regular statistics exhibit a law of large numbers depending only on fixed point counts and a similar variance property that depends also on two--cycle counts.
  These results first appeared in arXiv:2206.06567, which is no longer intended for publication. Our original proof of the moment result for indicators of partial permutations relied on representation theory and symmetric functions. A referee generously shared a combinatorial argument, allowing us to give a self-contained treatment of these results that does not rely on representation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17556v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Hamaker, Brendon Rhoades</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistence and extinction dynamics in a stochastic predator-prey model with emergent Allee effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17583v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Allee effect describes a decline in population fitness at low densities, potentially leading to extinction. In predator-prey systems, an emergent Allee effect can arise due to interactions such as density-dependent maturation rates and predation constraints. This work studies a stochastic predator-prey model where the prey population is structured into juvenile and adult stages, with maturation following a nonlinear function. We introduce Ito-type stochastic perturbations in mortality rates to account for environmental variability. We first establish the positivity of solutions and derive sufficient conditions for the stability of the trivial equilibrium, prey extinction, and conditional predator extinction. We then analyze prey persistence under specific maturation rate functions. Finally, numerical simulations illustrate the theoretical results and their ecological implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17583v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Granados, Leon A. Valencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Block Gradient Ascent for Entropically Regularised Quantum Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17590v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a block gradient ascent method for solving the quantum optimal transport problem with entropic regularisation similar to the algorithm proposed in [D. Feliciangeli, A. Gerolin, L. Portinale: J. Funct. Anal. 285 (2023), no. 4, 109963] and [E. Caputo, A. Gerolin, N. Monina, L. Portinale: arXiv:2409.03698]. We prove a linear convergence rate based on strong concavity of the dual functional and present some results of numerical experiments of an implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17590v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marvin Randig, Max von Renesse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse-Grained Games: A Framework for Bounded Perception in Game Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17598v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In everyday life, we frequently make coarse-grained judgments. When we say that Olivia and Noah excel in mathematics, we disregard the specific differences in their mathematical abilities. Similarly, when we claim that a particular automobile manufacturer produces high-quality cars, we overlook the minor variations among individual vehicles. These coarse-grained assessments are distinct from erroneous or deceptive judgments, such as those resulting from student cheating or false advertising by corporations. Despite the prevalence of such judgments, little attention has been given to their underlying mathematical structure. In this paper, we introduce the concept of coarse-graining into game theory, analyzing games where players may perceive different payoffs as identical while preserving the underlying order structure. We call it a Coarse-Grained Game (CGG). This framework allows us to examine the rational inference processes that arise when players equate distinct micro-level payoffs at a macro level, and to explore how Nash equilibria are preserved or altered as a result. Our key findings suggest that CGGs possess several desirable properties that make them suitable for modeling phenomena in the social sciences. This paper demonstrates two such applications: first, in cases of overly minor product updates, consumers may encounter an equilibrium selection problem, resulting in market behavior that is not driven by objective quality differences; second, the lemon market can be analyzed not only through objective information asymmetry but also through asymmetries in perceptual resolution or recognition ability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17598v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Izumo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Sample Tests for Optimal Lifts, Manifold Stability and Reverse Labeling Reflection Shap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a quotient of a complete Riemannian manifold modulo an isometrically and properly acting Lie group and lifts of the quotient to the manifolds in optimal position to a reference point on the manifold. With respect to the pushed forward Riemannian volume onto the quotient we derive continuity and uniqueness a.e. and smoothness to large extents also with respect to the reference point. In consequence we derive a general manifold stability theorem: the Fr\'echet mean lies in the highest dimensional stratum assumed with positive probability, and a strong law for optimal lifts. This allows to define new two-sample tests utilizing individual optimal lifts which outperform existing two-sample tests on simulated data. They also outperform existing tests on a newly derived reverse labeling reflection shape space, that is used to model filament data of microtubules within cells in a biological application.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17879v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do Tran Van, Susovan Pal, Benjamin Eltzner, Stephan F. Huckemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Betting: Beyond the Long-Term Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While the Kelly portfolio has many desirable properties, including optimal long-term growth rate, the resulting investment strategy is rather aggressive. In this paper, we suggest a unified approach to the risk assessment of the Kelly criterion in both discrete and continuous time by introducing and analyzing the asymptotic variance that describes fluctuations of the portfolio growth, and use the results to propose two new measures for quantifying risk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17927v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Levon Hakobyan, Sergey Lototsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak Convergence Analysis for the Finite Element Approximation to Stochastic Allen-Cahn Equation Driven by Multiplicative White Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17981v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we aim to study the optimal weak convergence order for the finite element approximation to a stochastic Allen-Cahn equation driven by multiplicative white noise. We first construct an auxiliary equation based on the splitting-up technique and derive prior estimates for the corresponding Kolmogorov equation and obtain the strong convergence order of 1 in time between the auxiliary and exact solutions. Then, we prove the optimal weak convergence order of the finite element approximation to the stochastic Allen-Cahn equation by deriving the weak convergence order between the finite element approximation and the auxiliary solution via the theory of Kolmogorov equation and Malliavin calculus. Finally, we present a numerical experiment to illustrate the theoretical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17981v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minxing Zhang, Yongkui Zou, Ran Zhang, Yanzhao Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtering of Stochastic Nonlinear Wave Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we will develop linear and nonlinear filtering methods for a large class of nonlinear wave equations that arise in applications such as quantum dynamics and laser generation and propagation in a unified framework. We consider both stochastic calculus and white noise filtering methods and derive measure-valued evolution equations for the nonlinear filter and prove existence and uniqueness theorems for the solutions. We will also study first order approximations to these measure-valued evolutions by linearizing the wave equations and characterize the filter dynamics in terms of infinite dimensional operator Riccati equations and establish solvability theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18222v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sivaguru S. Sritharan, Saba Mudaliar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chernoff solutions of the heat and the Schr\"odinger equation in the Heisenberg group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the application of the classical Chernoff's theorem to construct explicit solutions for the heat and Schr\"odinger equations on the Heisenberg group $\mathbb{H}^d$. Using semigroup approximation techniques, we obtain analytically tractable and numerically implementable representations of fundamental solutions. In particular, we establish a new connection between the heat equation and Brownian motion on $\mathbb{H}^d$ and provide a rigorous realization of the Feynman path integral for the Schr\"odinger equation. The study highlights the challenges posed by the noncommutative structure of the Heisenberg group and opens new directions for PDEs on sub-Riemannian manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18481v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\`o Drago, Sonia Mazzucchi, Andrea Pinamonti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear statistics at the microscopic scale for the 2D Coulomb gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18586v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the classical Coulomb gas in two dimensions at the inverse temperature $\beta=2$, confined within a droplet of radius $R$ by a rotationally invariant potential $U(r)$. For $U(r)\sim r^2$ this describes the eigenvalues of the complex Ginibre ensemble of random matrices. We study linear statistics of the form ${\cal L}_N = \sum_{i=1}^N f(|{\bf x}_i|)$, where ${\bf x}_i$'s are the positions of the $N$ particles, in the large $N$ limit with $R=O(1)$. It is known that for smooth functions $f(r)$ the variance ${\rm Var} \,{\cal L}_N= O(1)$, while for an indicator function relevant for the disk counting statistics, all cumulants of ${\cal L}_N$ of order $q \geq 2$ behave as $\sim \sqrt{N}$. In addition, for smooth functions, it was shown that the cumulants of ${\cal L}_N$ of order $q \geq 3$ scale as $\sim N^{2-q}$. Surprisingly it was found that they depend only on $f'(|\bf x|)$ and its derivatives evaluated exactly at the boundary of the droplet. To understand this property, and interpolate between the two behaviors (smooth versus step-like), we study the microscopic linear statistics given by $f(r) \to f_N(r) = \phi((r-\hat r) \sqrt{N}/\xi)$, which probes the fluctuations at the scale of the inter-particle distance. We compute the cumulants of ${\cal L}_N$ at large $N$ for a fixed $\phi(u)$ at arbitrary $\xi$. For large $\xi$ they match the predictions for smooth functions which shows that the leading contribution in that case comes from a boundary layer of size $1/\sqrt{N}$ near the boundary of the droplet. Finally we show that the full probability distribution of ${\cal L}_N$ take two distinct large deviation forms, in the regime ${\cal L}_N \sim \sqrt{N}$ and ${\cal L}_N \sim N$ respectively. We also discuss applications of our results to fermions in a rotating harmonic trap and to the Ginibre symplectic ensemble.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18586v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Le Doussal, Gregory Schehr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the application of a high order symplectic method in Shardlow's method for dissipative particle dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the efficiency and reliability of the modified Shardlow's (M-Shardlow) method for dissipative particle dynamics (DPD). We show that the M-Shardlow method in which for its construction, the second order velocity Verlet method in the Shardlows method to integrate the Hamiltonian part has been replaced by a symplectic fourth order method, improperly uses some parameters. %In other words, in this paper, it is shown that the initial M-Shardlow method employed some parameters improperly in the fourth order symplectic method that was used for the M-Shardlow method. By numerical experiments and computing, some important configurational quantities such as configurational temperature and radial distribution function (RDF), the M-Shardlow's method is compared with the Shardlow and ABOBA methods. These results indicate that the new method obtained in this way, even with the proper parameters is too costly in the sense of the CPU-time that is required per each step which makes it an inefficient DPD integrator. Besides, by a comparison of the radial distribution function of this method with Shardlow and ABOBA for large time increments, we can observe no considerable improvement in preserving the structure of the system by this new DPD solver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18633v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdolreza Amiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the number of infected vertices in two symmetric sets for Bernoulli percolation (and other random partitions)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.12183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For Bernoulli percolation on a given graph $G = (V,E)$ we consider the cluster of some fixed vertex $o \in V$. We aim at comparing the number of vertices of this cluster in the set $V_+$ and in the set $V_-$, where $V_+,V_- \subset V$ have the same size. Intuitively, if $V_-$ is further away from $o$ than $V_+$, it should contain fewer vertices of the cluster. We prove such a result in terms of stochastic domination, provided that $o \in V_+$, and $V_+,V_-$ satisfy some strong symmetry conditions, and we give applications of this result in case $G$ is a bunkbed graph, a layered graph, the 2D square lattice or a hypercube graph. Our result only relies on general probabilistic techniques and a combinatorial result on group actions, and thus extends to fairly general random partitions, e.g. as induced by Bernoulli site percolation or the random cluster model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.12183v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Richthammer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bunkbed conjecture for complete bipartite graphs and related classes of graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.12931v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G = (V,E)$ be a simple finite graph. The corresponding bunkbed graph $G^\pm$ consists of two copies $G^+ = (V^+,E^+),G^- = (V^-,E^-)$ of $G$ and additional edges connecting any two vertices $v_+ \in V_+,v_- \in V_-$ that are the copies of a vertex $v \in V$. The bunkbed conjecture states that for independent bond percolation on $G^\pm$, for all $v,w \in V$, it is more likely for $v_-,w_-$ to be connected than for $v_-,w_+$ to be connected. While this seems very plausible, so far surprisingly little is known rigorously. Recently the conjecture has been proved for complete graphs. Here we give a proof for complete bipartite graphs, complete graphs minus the edges of a complete subgraph, and symmetric complete $k$-partite graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.12931v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Richthammer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonicity of Markov chain transition probabilities via quasi-stationarity -- an application to Bernoulli percolation on $C_k \times Z$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.13314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.13314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $X_n, n \ge 0$ be a Markov chain with finite state space $M$. If $x,y \in M$ such that $x$ is transient we have $P^y(X_n = x) \to 0$ for $n \to \infty$, and under mild aperiodicity conditions this convergence is monotone in that for some $N$ we have $\forall n \ge N: P^y(X_n = x)$ $\ge P^y(X_{n+1} = x)$. We use bounds on the rate of convergence of the Markov chain to its quasi-stationary distribution to obtain explicit bounds on $N$. We then apply this result to Bernoulli percolation with parameter $p$ on the cylinder graph $C_k \times Z$. Utilizing a Markov chain describing infection patterns layer per layer, we thus show the following uniform result on the monotonicity of connection probabilities: $\forall k \ge 3\, \forall n \ge 500k^6 2^k \,\forall p \in (0,1) \, \forall m \in C_k\!\!:$ $P_p((0,0) \leftrightarrow (m,n)) \ge P_p((0,0) \leftrightarrow (m,n+1))$. In general these kind of monotonicity properties of connection probabilities are difficult to establish and there are only few pertaining results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.13314v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp K\"onig, Thomas Richthammer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Triangle Condition for the Marked Random Connection Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.07727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.07727v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a spatial random graph model whose vertices are given as a marked Poisson process on $\mathbb{R}^d$. Edges are inserted between any pair of points independently with probability depending on the spatial displacement of the two endpoints and on their marks. Upon variation of the Poisson density, a percolation phase transition occurs under mild conditions: for low density there are finite connected components only, whilst for large density there is an infinite component almost surely. Our focus is on the transition between the low- and high-density phase, where the system is critical. We prove that if the dimension is high enough and the edge probability function satisfies certain conditions, then an infrared bound for the critical connection function is valid. This implies the triangle condition, and thus mean-field behaviour. We achieve this result through combining the recently established lace expansion for Poisson processes with spectral estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.07727v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Dickson, Markus Heydenreich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random tangled currents for $\varphi^4$: translation invariant Gibbs measures and continuity of the phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.00319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the set of automorphism invariant Gibbs measures for the $\varphi^4$ model on graphs of polynomial growth has at most two extremal measures at all values of $\beta$. We also give a sufficient condition to ensure that the set of all Gibbs measures is a singleton. As an application, we show that the spontaneous magnetisation of the nearest-neighbour $\varphi^4$ model on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ vanishes at criticality for $d\geq 3$. The analogous results were established for the Ising model in the seminal works of Aizenman, Duminil-Copin, and Sidoravicius (Comm. Math. Phys., 2015), and Raoufi (Ann. Prob., 2020) using the so-called random current representation introduced by Aizenman (Comm. Math. Phys., 1982). One of the main contributions of this paper is the development of a corresponding geometric representation for the $\varphi^4$ model called the random tangled current representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.00319v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trishen S. Gunaratnam, Christoforos Panagiotis, Romain Panis, Franco Severo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Porous Medium Equation: Large Deviations and Gradient Flow with Degenerate and Unbounded Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11289v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The problem of deriving a gradient flow structure for the porous medium equation which is {\em thermodynamic}, in that it arises from the large deviations of some microscopic particle system, is studied. To this end, a rescaled zero-range process with jump rate $g(k)=k^\alpha, \alpha&gt;1$ is considered, and its hydrodynamic limit and dynamical large deviations are shown in the presence of both degenerate and unbounded diffusion. The key superexponential estimate is obtained using pathwise discretised regularity estimates in the spirit of the Aubin-Lions-Simons lemma. This allows to exhibit the porous medium equation as the gradient flow of the entropy in a thermodynamic metric via the energy-dissipation inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11289v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Gess, Daniel Heydecker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic Sobolev inequalities for non-equilibrium steady states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider two methods to establish log-Sobolev inequalities for the invariant measure of a diffusion process when its density is not explicit and the curvature is not positive everywhere. In the first approach, based on the Holley-Stroock and Aida-Shigekawa perturbation arguments [J. Stat. Phys., 46(5-6):1159-1194, 1987, J. Funct. Anal., 126(2):448-475, 1994], the control on the (non-explicit) perturbation is obtained by stochastic control methods, following the comparison technique introduced by Conforti [Ann. Appl. Probab., 33(6A):4608-4644, 2023]. The second method combines the Wasserstein-2 contraction method, used in [Ann. Henri Lebesgue, 6:941-973, 2023] to prove a Poincar\'e inequality in some non-equilibrium cases, with Wang's hypercontractivity results [Potential Anal., 53(3):1123-1144, 2020].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07858v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11118-025-10211-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Potential Anal., 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Monmarch\'e, Songbo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the One-Dimensional Contact Process with Enhancements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02059v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a one-dimensional contact process with two infection parameters, one giving the infection rates at the boundaries of a finite infected region and the other one the rates within that region. We prove that the critical value of each of these parameters is a strictly monotone continuous function of the other parameter. We also show that if one of these parameters is equal to the critical value of the standard contact process and the other parameter is strictly larger, then the infection starting from a single point has positive probability of surviving. This is in contrast with another result also obtained here, that the critical contact process on the half line with enhanced infection rate at finitely many sites also dies out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02059v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Andjel, Leonardo T. Rolla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Trajectories. Spectral Gap, Quasi-compactness &amp; Limit Theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03879v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum trajectories are Markov processes modeling the evolution of a quantum system subjected to repeated independent measurements. Inspired by the theory of random products of matrices, it has been shown that these Markov processes admit a unique invariant measure under a purification and an irreducibility assumptions. This paper is devoted to the spectral study of the underlying Markov operator. Using Quasi-compactness, it is shown that this operator admits a spectral gap and the peripheral spectrum is described in a precise manner. Next two perturbations of this operator are studied. This allows to derive limit theorems (Central Limit Theorem, Berry-Esseen bounds and Large Deviation Principle) for the empirical mean of functions of the Markov chain as well as the Lyapounov exponent of the underlying random dynamical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03879v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tristan Benoist, Arnaud Hautecoeur, Cl\'ement Pellegrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical site percolation and cutsets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22152v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 2003, Kahn conjectured a characterization of the critical percolation probability $p_c$
  in terms of vertex cut sets (\cite{JK03}). Later, Lyons and Peres (2016) conjectured a similar characterization of $p_c$
  , but in terms of edge cut sets (\cite{LP16}). Both conjectures were subsequently proven by Tang (\cite{pt23}) for bond percolation and site percolation on bounded-degree graphs. Tang further conjectured that Kahn's vertex-cut characterization for $p_c^{site}$
  and the Lyons-Peres edge-cut characterization for $p_c^{site}$ would hold for site percolation on any infinite, connected, locally finite graph.
  In this paper, we establish Kahn's vertex-cut characterization for $p_c^{site}$ by adapting arguments from \cite{jmh57a, DCT15}. Additionally, we disprove the Lyons-Peres edge-cut characterization for $p_c^{site}$ by constructing a counterexample.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22152v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongyang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal quartic variation for non-linear stochastic heat equations with piecewise constant coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22750v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a stochastic partial differential equation with piecewise constant coefficients driven by a multiplicative space-time white noise. The existence and uniqueness of the mild solution in Walsh sense is established. We mainly study the limit behavior of the temporal quartic variation of the mild solution. As an application, we deduce a consistent estimator based on corresponding results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22750v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongkang Li, Huisheng Shu, Litan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness of McKean-Vlasov equations under the weak H\"ormander condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10987v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the McKean-Vlasov equation $dX_t = b(t, X_t, [X_t])dt + \sigma(t, X_t, [X_t])dW_t$ where $[X_t]$ is the law of $X_t$. We focus specifically on the "kinetic" case, where the equation is degenerate in the sense that the dimension of the Brownian motion $W$ can be strictly less than the dimension of the solution $X$. Assuming H\"older continuous coefficients and a hypoellipticity condition, we prove the well-posedness of the equation. This result complements the existing literature by addressing the case where the diffusion coefficient $\sigma$ depends on the law $[X_t]$, which have been previously unexplored. Our proof employs a novel technique that offers a simplified and direct argument, eliminating the need for PDEs involving derivatives with respect to the measure argument and exploiting the sub-Riemannian metric structure induced by the corresponding Fokker-Planck operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10987v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Pascucci, Alessio Rondelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of rescaled "true" self-avoiding walks to the T\'oth-Werner "true" self-repelling motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10960v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the rescaled ``true'' self-avoiding walk $(n^{-2/3}X_{\lfloor nt \rfloor})_{t\in\mathbb{R}_+}$ converges weakly as $n$ goes to infinity to the ``true'' self-repelling motion constructed by T\'oth and Werner. The proof features a joint generalized Ray-Knight theorem for the rescaled local times processes and their merge and absorption points as the main tool for showing both the tightness and convergence of the finite dimensional distributions. Thus, our result can be seen as an example of establishing a functional limit theorem for a family of processes by inverting the joint generalized Ray-Knight theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10960v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Kosygina, Jonathon Peterson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Milstein Approximation for Free Stochastic Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11233v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper derives a new numerical method for approximating Free Stochastic Differential Equations with strong convergence order one. Previously, the authors derived a free variant of the Euler-Maruyama method, which obeys strong convergence order of 0.5. In this paper these results are extended using multiple operator integrals and Taylor expansion of Operator Functions. The new method can be viewed as the free variant of the Milstein-Method for Stochastic Differential Equations. In addition, we generalize the results of the free Euler-Maruyama method to Lp({\phi}), 1 \leq p \leq \infty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11233v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Wibmer, Georg Schl\"uchtermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The largest subcritical component in inhomogeneous random graphs of preferential attachment type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05469v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We identify the size of the largest connected component in a subcritical inhomogeneous random graph with a kernel of preferential attachment type. The component is polynomial in the graph size with an explicitly given exponent, which is strictly larger than the exponent for the largest degree in the graph. This is in stark contrast to the behaviour of inhomogeneous random graphs with a kernel of rank one. Our proof uses local approximation by branching random walks going well beyond the weak local limit and novel results on subcritical killed branching random walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05469v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter M\"orters, Nick Schleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cheeger-type inequality for the drift Laplacian with Wentzell-type boundary condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove lower bounds for the first non-trivial eigenvalue of the drift Laplacian on manifolds with Wentzell-type boundary condition in terms of some Cheeger-type constants for bulk-boundary interactions. Our results are in the spirit of Cheeger's classical inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16093v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marie Bormann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling from $p$-adic algebraic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.05911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.05911v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a method for sampling points from an algebraic manifold, either affine or projective, defined over a local field, with a prescribed probability distribution. Inspired by the work of Breiding and Marigliano on sampling real algebraic manifolds, our approach leverages slicing the given variety with random linear spaces of complementary dimension. We also provide an implementation of this sampling technique and demonstrate its applicability to various contexts, including sampling from linear $p$-adic algebraic groups, abelian varieties, and modular curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.05911v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yassine El Maazouz, Enis Kaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathrm{GL}(n,\mathbb{Z}_p)$-invariant Gaussian measures on the space of $p$-adic polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.13634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.13634v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that if $p&gt;d$ there is a unique gaussian distribution (in the sense of Evans) on the space $\mathbb{Q}_p[x_1, \ldots, x_n]_{(d)}$ which is invariant under the action of $\mathrm{GL}(n, \mathbb{Z}_p)$ by change of variables. This gives the nonarchimedean counterpart of Kostlan's Theorem on the classification of orthogonally (respectively unitarily) invariant gaussian measures on the space $\mathbb{R}[x_1, \ldots, x_n]_{(d)}$ (respectively $\mathbb{C}[x_1, \ldots, x_n]_{(d)}$). More generally, if $V$ is an $n$--dimensional vector space over a nonarchimedean local field $K$ with ring of integers $R$, and if $\lambda$ is a partition of an integer $d$, we study the problem of determining the invariant lattices in the Schur module $S_\lambda(V)$ under the action of the group $\mathrm{GL}(n,R)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.13634v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yassine EL Maazouz, Antonio Lerario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admission Control for A Single Server Waiting Time Process in Heavy Traffic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.05674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.05674v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We address a single server queue control problem (QCP) in heavy traffic originating from Lee and Weerasinghe (2011). The state process represents the offered waiting time, the customer arrival has a state-dependent intensity, and the customers' service and patience times are i.i.d with general distributions. We introduce an infinite-horizon discounted cost functional consisting of a control cost generated from the use of control and a penalty for idleness cost. Our primary goal is to tackle the QCP, taking into account a non-trivial control cost and a non-increasing cost function resulting from the control mechanisms in the waiting time. Under mild assumptions, the heavy traffic limit of the QCP yields a stochastic control problem described by a diffusion process, which we call a diffusion control problem (DCP). We find the optimal control of the associated DCP by incorporating the Legendre-Fenchel transform and a formal Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equation. Then, we ``translate'' this optimal strategy to the QCP, of which we obtain an asymptotically optimal policy. Apart from theoretical results, we also examine the REINFORCE algorithm, a Reinforcement learning (RL) approach, for solving stochastic controls motivated by recent literature. We highlight the advantages and limitations of simulation from theoretical results and data-driven algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.05674v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Xie, Haoyu Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Nash Equilibria of Finite-State Ergodic Markovian Mean Field Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11695v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mean field games (MFGs) model equilibria in games with a continuum of weakly interacting players as limiting systems of symmetric $n$-player games. We consider the finite-state, infinite-horizon problem with ergodic cost. Assuming Markovian strategies, we first prove that any solution to the MFG system gives rise to a $(C/\sqrt{n})$-Nash equilibrium in the $n$-player game. We follow this result by proving the same is true for the strategy profile derived from the master equation. We conclude the main theoretical portion of the paper by establishing a large deviation principle for empirical measures associated with the asymptotic Nash equilibria. Then, we contrast the asymptotic Nash equilibria using an example. We solve the MFG system directly and numerically solve the ergodic master equation by adapting the deep Galerkin method of Sirignano and Spiliopoulos. We use these results to derive the strategies of the asymptotic Nash equilibria and compare them. Finally, we derive an explicit form for the rate functions in dimension two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11695v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asaf Cohen, Ethan Zell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy annealing for policy mirror descent in continuous time and space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20250v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Entropy regularization has been widely used in policy optimization algorithms to enhance exploration and the robustness of the optimal control; however it also introduces an additional regularization bias. This work quantifies the impact of entropy regularization on the convergence of policy gradient methods for stochastic exit time control problems. We analyze a continuous-time policy mirror descent dynamics, which updates the policy based on the gradient of an entropy-regularized value function and adjusts the strength of entropy regularization as the algorithm progresses. We prove that with a fixed entropy level, the mirror descent dynamics converges exponentially to the optimal solution of the regularized problem. We further show that when the entropy level decays at suitable polynomial rates, the annealed flow converges to the solution of the unregularized problem at a rate of $\mathcal O(1/S)$ for discrete action spaces and, under suitable conditions, at a rate of $\mathcal O(1/\sqrt{S})$ for general action spaces, with $S$ being the gradient flow running time. The technical challenge lies in analyzing the gradient flow in the infinite-dimensional space of Markov kernels for nonconvex objectives. This paper explains how entropy regularization improves policy optimization, even with the true gradient, from the perspective of convergence rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20250v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deven Sethi, David \v{S}i\v{s}ka, Yufei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularized e-processes: anytime valid inference with knowledge-based efficiency gains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01427v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical statistical methods have theoretical justification when the sample size is predetermined. In applications, however, it's often the case that sample sizes are data-dependent rather than predetermined. The aforementioned methods aren't reliable in this latter case, hence the recent interest in e-processes and methods that are anytime valid, i.e., reliable for any dynamic data-collection plan. But if the investigator has relevant-yet-incomplete prior information about the quantity of interest, then there's an opportunity for efficiency gain. This paper proposes a regularized e-process framework featuring a knowledge-based, imprecise-probabilistic regularization with improved efficiency. A generalized version of Ville's inequality is established, ensuring that inference based on the regularized e-process are anytime valid in a novel, knowledge-dependent sense. Regularized e-processes also facilitate possibility-theoretic uncertainty quantification with strong frequentist-like calibration properties and other Bayesian-like properties: satisfies the likelihood principle, avoids sure-loss, and offers formal decision-making with reliability guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01427v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviation Upper Bounds and Improved MSE Rates of Nonlinear SGD: Heavy-tailed Noise and Power of Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15637v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study large deviation upper bounds and mean-squared error (MSE) guarantees of a general framework of nonlinear stochastic gradient methods in the online setting, in the presence of heavy-tailed noise. Unlike existing works that rely on the closed form of a nonlinearity (typically clipping), our framework treats the nonlinearity in a black-box manner, allowing us to provide unified guarantees for a broad class of bounded nonlinearities, including many popular ones, like sign, quantization, normalization, as well as component-wise and joint clipping. We provide several strong results for a broad range of step-sizes in the presence of heavy-tailed noise with symmetric probability density function, positive in a neighbourhood of zero and potentially unbounded moments. In particular, for non-convex costs we provide a large deviation upper bound for the minimum norm-squared of gradients, showing an asymptotic tail decay on an exponential scale, at a rate $\sqrt{t} / \log(t)$. We establish the accompanying rate function, showing an explicit dependence on the choice of step-size, nonlinearity, noise and problem parameters. Next, for non-convex costs and the minimum norm-squared of gradients, we derive the optimal MSE rate $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(t^{-1/2})$. Moreover, for strongly convex costs and the last iterate, we provide an MSE rate that can be made arbitrarily close to the optimal rate $\mathcal{O}(t^{-1})$, improving on the state-of-the-art results in the presence of heavy-tailed noise. Finally, we establish almost sure convergence of the minimum norm-squared of gradients, providing an explicit rate, which can be made arbitrarily close to $o(t^{-1/4})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15637v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandar Armacki, Shuhua Yu, Dragana Bajovic, Dusan Jakovetic, Soummya Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean Estimation in Banach Spaces Under Infinite Variance and Martingale Dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11271v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider estimating the shared mean of a sequence of heavy-tailed random variables taking values in a Banach space. In particular, we revisit and extend a simple truncation-based mean estimator first proposed by Catoni and Giulini. While existing truncation-based approaches require a bound on the raw (non-central) second moment of observations, our results hold under a bound on either the central or non-central $p$th moment for some $p \in (1,2]$. Our analysis thus handles distributions with infinite variance. The main contributions of the paper follow from exploiting connections between truncation-based mean estimation and the concentration of martingales in smooth Banach spaces. We prove two types of time-uniform bounds on the distance between the estimator and unknown mean: line-crossing inequalities, which can be optimized for a fixed sample size $n$, and iterated logarithm inequalities, which match the tightness of line-crossing inequalities at all points in time up to a doubly logarithmic factor in $n$. Our results do not depend on the dimension of the Banach space, hold under martingale dependence, and all constants in the inequalities are known and small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11271v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Whitehouse, Ben Chugg, Diego Martinez-Taboada, Aaditya Ramdas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling and Tensorization of Kinetic Theory and Graph Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14512v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a non-exchangeable multi-agent system and rigorously derive a strong form of the mean-field limit. The convergence of the connection weights and the initial data implies convergence of large-scale dynamics toward a deterministic limit given by the corresponding extended Vlasov PDE, at any later time and any realization of randomness. This is established on what we call a bi-coupling distance defined through a convex optimization problem, which is an interpolation of the optimal transport between measures and the fractional overlay between graphs. The proof relies on a quantitative stability estimate of the so-called observables, which are tensorizations of agent laws and graph homomorphism densities. This reveals a profound relationship between mean-field theory and graph limiting theory, intersecting in the study of non-exchangeable systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14512v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Datong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A uniform rate of convergence for the entropic potentials in the quadratic Euclidean setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00084v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We bound the rate of uniform convergence in compact sets for both entropic potentials and their gradients towards the Brenier potential and its gradient, respectively. Both results hold in the quadratic Euclidean setting for absolutely continuous measures satisfying some convexity assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00084v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo L\'opez-Rivera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse Set Theory for AI Ethics and Decision-Making: A Mathematical Framework for Granular Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07347v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As artificial intelligence (AI) systems become increasingly embedded in ethically sensitive domains such as education, healthcare, and transportation, the need to balance accuracy and interpretability in decision-making has become a central concern. Coarse Ethics (CE) is a theoretical framework that justifies coarse-grained evaluations, such as letter grades or warning labels, as ethically appropriate under cognitive and contextual constraints. However, CE has lacked mathematical formalization. This paper introduces Coarse Set Theory (CST), a novel mathematical framework that models coarse-grained decision-making using totally ordered structures and coarse partitions. CST defines hierarchical relations among sets and uses information-theoretic tools, such as Kullback-Leibler Divergence, to quantify the trade-off between simplification and information loss. We demonstrate CST through applications in educational grading and explainable AI (XAI), showing how it enables more transparent and context-sensitive evaluations. By grounding coarse evaluations in set theory and probabilistic reasoning, CST contributes to the ethical design of interpretable AI systems. This work bridges formal methods and human-centered ethics, offering a principled approach to balancing comprehensibility, fairness, and informational integrity in AI-driven decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07347v5</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Izumo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multispecies inhomogeneous $t$-PushTASEP from antisymmetric fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00829v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the recently introduced inhomogeneous $n$-species $t$-PushTASEP, a long-range stochastic process on a periodic lattice. A Baxter-type formula is established, expressing the Markov matrix as an alternating sum of commuting transfer matrices over all the fundamental representations of $U_t(\widehat{sl}_{n+1})$. This superposition acts as an inclusion-exclusion principle, selectively extracting the sequential particle transitions characteristic of the PushTASEP, while canceling forbidden channels. The homogeneous specialization connects the PushTASEP to ASEP, showing that the two models share eigenstates and a common integrability structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00829v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arvind Ayyer, Atsuo Kuniba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrap percolation on a generalized Hamming cube \MakeUppercase{\romannumeral 2}</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12607v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate the critical probability $p_c(Q_n,r)$ for bootstrap percolation with the infection threshold $r$ on the $n$-dimensional hypercube $Q_n$ with vertex set $V(Q_n)=\{0,1\}^n$ and edges connecting the pairs at Hamming distance $1$. More precisely, by utilizing the techniques developed by Balogh, Bollob{\'a}s, and Morris (2009), we determine the first-order term of $p_c(Q_n,n^a)$ where $\frac{2}{3}&lt;a&lt; 1$. Additionally, we obtain the critical probability $p_c(Q_{k,n},r)$ for bootstrap percolation with the infection threshold $r=\frac{N}{2}$ on the generalized $n$-dimensional hypercube $Q_{k,n}$ with vertex set $V(Q_{k,n})=\{0,1\}^n$ and edges connecting the pairs at Hamming distance $1,2,\dots,k$, where $k\ge 2$ and $N=\sum_{i=1}^k\binom{n}{i}$. More precisely, we obtain the first-order term of $p_c(Q_{k,n},\frac{N}{2})$ and some bounds on the second-order term by extending the main theorem from Balogh, Bollob{\'a}s, and Morris (2009).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12607v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengxing Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Schr\"odinger bridges and Sinkhorn semigroups for log-concave models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15963v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article we obtain several new results and developments in the study of entropic optimal transport problems (a.k.a. Schr\"odinger problems) with general reference distributions and log-concave target marginal measures. Our approach combines transportation cost inequalities
  with the theory of Riccati matrix difference equations arising in filtering and optimal control theory. This methodology is partly based on a novel entropic stability of Schr\"odinger bridges and closed form expressions of a class of discrete time algebraic Riccati equations. In the context of regularized entropic transport these techniques provide new sharp entropic map estimates. When applied to the stability of Sinkhorn semigroups, they also yield
  a series of novel contraction estimates in terms of the fixed point of Riccati equations.
  The strength of our approach is that it is applicable to a large class of models arising in machine learning and artificial intelligence algorithms. We illustrate the impact of our results in the context of regularized entropic transport, proximal samplers and diffusion generative models as well as diffusion flow matching models</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15963v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Del Moral</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
