<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 05:01:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extremes of Brownian Decision Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a Brownian motion with linear drift that splits at fixed time points into a fixed number of branches, which may depend on the branching point. For this process, which we shall refer to as the Brownian decision tree, we investigate the exact asymptotics of high exceedance probabilities in finite time horizon, including: the probability that at least one branch exceeds some high threshold, the probability that the largest distance between branches gets large and the probability that all branches simultaneously exceed some high barrier. Additionally, we find the asymptotics for the probability that all branches of at least one of $M$ independent Brownian decision trees exceed a high threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05248v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof D\c{e}bicki, Pavel Ievlev, Nikolai Kriukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rate of convergence of the critical mean-field O(N) magnetization via multivariate nonnormal Stein's method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the distribution of the magnetization of the critical mean-field O(N) model with N &gt; 1. Specifically, we bound the Wasserstein distance between the finite-volume and limiting distributions, in terms of the number of spins. To achieve this, we extend a recent multivariate nonnormal approximation theorem. This generalizes known results for the Curie-Weiss magnetization to the multivariate O(N) setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05340v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy M. Garoni, Aram Perez, Zongzheng Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence rate of $\ell^p$-relaxation on a graph to a $p$-harmonic function with given boundary values</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the following dynamics on a connected graph $(V,E)$ with $n$ vertices. Let $V = I \bigcup B$, where the set of interior vertices $I \ne \emptyset$ is disjoint from the set of boundary vertices $B \neq \emptyset$. Given $p &gt; 1$ and an initial opinion profile $f_0: V \to [0,1]$, at each integer step $t \ge 1$ a uniformly random vertex $v_t \in I$ is selected, and the opinion there is updated to the value $f_{t}(v_t)$ that minimizes the sum $\sum_{w \sim v_t} \lvert f_t(v_t)-f_{t-1}(w) \rvert^p$ over neighbours $w$ of $v_t$.
  The case $p=2$ yields linear averaging dynamics, but for all $p \ne 2$ the dynamics are nonlinear.
  It is well known that almost surely, $f_t$ converges to the $p$-harmonic extension $h$ of $f_0 \vert_{B}$. Denote the number of steps needed to obtain $\lVert f_t - h \rVert_{\infty} \le \epsilon$ by $\tau_p(\epsilon).$ Recently, Amir, Nazarov, and Peres~\cite{noboundarycase} analyzed the same dynamics without boundary. For individual graphs, adding boundary values can slow down the convergence considerably; indeed, when $p = 2$ the approximation time is controlled by the hitting time of the boundary by random walk, and hitting times can be much larger than mixing times, which control the convergence when $B=\emptyset$.
  Nevertheless, we show that for all graphs with $n$ vertices, the mean approximation time $\E[\tau_p(\epsilon)]$ is at most $n^{\beta_p}$ (up to logarithmic factors in $\frac{n}{\epsilon}$ for $p \in [2, \infty)$, and polynomial factors in $\epsilon^{-1}$ for $p \in (1, 2)$), where $\beta_p=\max\big(\frac{2p}{p-1},3\big)$. This matches the definition of $\beta_p$ given in \cite{noboundarycase} and answers Question 6.2 in that paper. The exponent $\beta_p$ is optimal in both settings.
  We also prove sharp bounds for $n$-vertex graphs with given average degree, that are technically more challenging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05424v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu Gan, Yuval Peres, Junchi Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Flows and Marked Stable Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a random partition of the space-time plane $\mathbb{R}_+\times \mathbb{R}$ using two coupled stochastic squared Bessel flows, whose parameters differ by $\delta\in (0,2)$. We show that the cells of this partition correspond to squared Bessel excursions with a negative parameter $-\delta$ which are embedded within the jumps of a spectrally positive $(1+\frac\delta 2)$ stable process. In particular, we demonstrate that interval partition evolutions [Forman et. al. 2020] and stable shredded disks [Bj\"ornberg, Curien and Stef\'ansson 2022] arise naturally in this framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05466v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elie A\"id\'ekon, Quan Shi, Chengshi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic PDEs driven by G-Brownian motion and the associated Backward Doubly Stochastic Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our aim is to study the well-posedness of quasilinear stochastic partial differential equations driven by G-Brownian motion (GSPDEs for short) and the associated backward doubly stochastic differential equations (GBDSDEs for short). We first prove the existence and uniqueness of weak solution to GSPDEs by analytical approach, and then solve the corresponding GBDSDEs. Finally, the relation between GSPDEs and GBDSDEs is established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05572v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent Denis (LMM), Jing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L^p$-Boltzmann-Gibbs principle via Littlewood-Paley-Stein inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the Boltzmann-Gibbs principle in the $L^p$ sense by applying the Littlewood-Paley-Stein inequality. Our model is an asymmetric Ginzburg-Landau interface model on a one-dimensional periodic lattice. Assuming convexity of the potential,we derive detailed error estimates, particularly their dependence on the size of the system and the size of the region on which the sample average is taken. Notably, the estimates are uniform in the strength of the asymmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05687v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahisa Funaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-passage percolation, non-positive curvature, and radial maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given an infinite connected graph $G$, a way to randomly perturb its metric is to assign random i.i.d. lengths to the edges of the graph, a process called first-passage percolation. Assume that the graph is infinite and of bounded degree. Assume the edge length distribution, $\nu$, has a finite expectation and is supported on $[0, \infty)$. We prove in this paper that non-positive curvature almost surely is not preserved by the associated percolation. In particular, Gromov hyperbolicity and coarse CAT(0) property of graphs are almost surely not preserved. We also show that if a graph contains a Morse geodesic ray, then the resulting image of the ray under first-passage percolation is no longer Morse. Lastly, we show that first-passage percolation almost surely is a radial map on $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05720v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic Bair, Sagnik Jana, Yulan Qing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A phase transition in Erd\H{o}s-Barak random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study monotone paths in Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi random graphs on numbered vertices. Benjamini &amp; Tzalik established a phase transition at $p = \frac{\log n}{n}$ for this model. We refine the critical value to $p = \frac{\log n - \log \log n }{n}$ and identify the critical window of order $\Theta(1/n)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05756v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gilles Blanchard, Nicolas Curien, Klara Krause, Alexander Reisach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Quantum Groups and Yang-Baxter Equation For Probabilists</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05782v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These are a set of lecture notes for a mini-course I gave at The University of Warwick from October 30th to November 1st, 2024. Recordings of the lectures are available on Oleg Zaboronski's webpage at https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/maths/people/staff/oleg_zaboronski/jeffrey_kuan_visit/ . The main body of the notes covers the content of the lectures, and provides an introduction to Drinfel'd-Jimbo quantum groups and the Yang-Baxter equation, with a probabilist as the target audience. The appendix contains several topics, requested by colleagues during my visit to the United Kingdom, which all depend on the main set of notes.
  The notes begin by defining what it means for the asymmetric simple exclusion process (ASEP) to be integrable, in the sense of satisfying the Yang-Baxter equation. It then provides the algebraic background for the Yang-Baxter equation, by defining Drinfel'd-Jimbo groups as a quasi-triangular Hopf algebra. The algebraic background motivates generalizations of ASEP to stochastic vertex models and "fused" models. Each section corresponds to approximately an hour of lecture time.
  The appendix covers the F.R.T. construction, Hecke algebras, the matrix product ansatz, and orthogonal polynomial vertex weights. The topics in the appendix can be read independently of each other.
  Accessibility Statement: This PDF meets the technical standards of WCAG2.1AA, which complies with Ohio Administrative Policy IT-09 , Texas Administrative Code 206.70 and Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act (effective April 24, 2026) . A webpage version of this PDF, typeset in MathML, is also available at https://go.osu.edu/QuantumKuan . To block web crawlers, the webpage is password protected. The password is TaySwift13. As an additional benefit, the webpage will have space for public comments and a list of updated errata, without the need to update the arXiv version.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05782v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Kuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical behaviour of the fully packed loop-$O(n)$ model on planar triangulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the fully packed loop-$O(n)$ model on planar triangulations. This model is also bijectively equivalent to the Fortuin--Kasteleyn model of planar maps with parameter $q\in (0,4)$ at its self-dual point. These have been traditionally studied using either techniques from analytic combinatorics (based in particular on the gasket decomposition of Borot, Bouttier and Guitter arXiv:1106.0153) or probabilistic arguments (based on Sheffield's hamburger-cheeseburger bijection arXiv:1108.2241). In this paper we establish a dictionary relating quantities of interest in both approaches. This has several consequences. First, we derive an exact expression for the partition function of the fully packed loop-$O(n)$ model on triangulations, as a function of the outer boundary length. This confirms predictions by Gaudin and Kostov. In particular, this model exhibits critical behaviour, in the sense that the partition function exhibits a power-law decay characteristic of the critical regime at this self-dual point. This can be thought of as the planar map analogue of Nienhuis' predictions for the critical point of the loop-$O(n)$ model on the hexagonal lattice. Finally, we derive precise asymptotics for geometric features of the FK model of planar maps when $0 &lt; q &lt;4$, such as the exact tail behaviour of the perimeters of clusters and loops. This sharpens previous results of arXiv:1502.00450 and arXiv:1502.00546. A key step is to use the above dictionary and the probabilistic results to justify rigorously an ansatz commonly assumed in the analytic combinatorics literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05867v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathana\"el Berestycki, William Da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T\'oth's buses and the "detachment process''</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces the \textbf{detachment process}, a novel, time-inhomogeneous Markov process inspired by I. P. T\'oth's problem \cite{Toth} concerning the number of ``lonely passengers'' (those without companions) when $n$ passengers are seated independently and uniformly in $k$ initially empty buses. T\'oth showed that this number is stochastically non-decreasing in $k$ for fixed $n$ (see also Haslegrave's work \cite{Haslegrave}).
  We extend T\'oth's model by treating the number of buses $k$ as a time parameter. Specifically, for a fixed number of passengers $n$, the state of our Markov process at time $k \ge 1$ is exactly T\'oth's configuration $(n, k)$. (We formally extend the process definition for all $t \in [1, \infty)$.) These processes can be coupled for all $n \ge 1$, and this larger coupled process is what we dub the \textbf{detachment process}.
  Our investigation focuses on properties related to detachment, clumping, the number of lonely passengers and of non-empty buses. The central notion is \textbf{detachment}, which occurs at time $k$ if every passenger occupies a distinct bus; we say the process is \textbf{in a state of detachment} at $k$. A \textbf{detachment time} $k$ is when the process transitions from a non-detached state at $k-1$ to a detached state at $k$.
  \textbf{Four critical time scales} are idetified -- linear, quadratic, and log-corrected linear or quadratic in the number of passengers, $n$ -- that govern the process's properties.
  We investigate (relative) clumping. We also explore why modeling the number of passengers with a Poisson distribution simplifies the analysis of T\'oth's original model. To aid this derivation, we introduce a comparison theorem for binomial distributions, originally obtained by J. Najnudel \cite{Najnudel}, along with a novel proof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05896v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'anos Engl\"ander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A model of discrete interacting updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider $N$ counters taking integer values which are subject to the following dynamics. At every time, a pair of distinct counters is chosen uniformly at random and their states are updated according to the following rule. If the states are different, then the smaller one is increased by $1$, while if the states are the same, both of them are increased by $1$. We show that, for a fixed $N$, the distances between consecutive ordered counters form a positive recurrent Markov chain and there exists the speed $V(N)$ defined as the average number of counters updated per time step in the stationary regime. We provide non-trivial upper and lower bounds for $V(N)$ as $N\to \infty$. Despite the simple formulation of the problem, its analysis seems to be highly complicated. We also provide a list of open problems and discuss various methods one may want to use, and obstacles one encounters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05913v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Denisov, Seva Shneer, Vitali Wachtel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cable-graph percolation between dimensions 2 and 3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Gaussian free field on two-dimensional slabs with a thickness described by a height $h$ at spatial scale $N$. We investigate the radius of critical clusters for the associated cable-graph percolation problem, which depends sensitively on the parameter $h$. Our results unveil a whole family of new "fixed points", which interpolate between recent results from arXiv:2303.03782 in two dimensions and from arXiv:2405.17417 and arXiv:2406.02397 in three dimensions, and describe critical behaviour beyond those regimes. In the delocalised phase, the one-arm decay exhibits a "plateau", i.e. it doesn't depend on the speed at which the variance of the field diverges in the large-$N$ limit. Our methods rely on a careful analysis of the interplay between two- and three-dimensional effects for the underlying random walk, which manifest themselves in a corresponding decomposition of the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05947v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois Rodriguez, Wen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Tame Your LLM: Semantic Collapse in Continuous Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a general theory of semantic dynamics for large language models by formalizing them as Continuous State Machines (CSMs): smooth dynamical systems whose latent manifolds evolve under probabilistic transition operators. The associated transfer operator $P: L^2(M,\mu) \to L^2(M,\mu)$ encodes the propagation of semantic mass. Under mild regularity assumptions (compactness, ergodicity, bounded Jacobian), $P$ is compact with discrete spectrum. Within this setting, we prove the Semantic Characterization Theorem (SCT): the leading eigenfunctions of $P$ induce finitely many spectral basins of invariant meaning, each definable in an o-minimal structure over $\mathbb{R}$. Thus spectral lumpability and logical tameness coincide. This explains how discrete symbolic semantics can emerge from continuous computation: the continuous activation manifold collapses into a finite, logically interpretable ontology. We further extend the SCT to stochastic and adiabatic (time-inhomogeneous) settings, showing that slowly drifting kernels preserve compactness, spectral coherence, and basin structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05162v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. M. Wyss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exactly Solvable Population Model with Square-Root Growth Noise and Cell-Size Regulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze a size-structured branching process in which individual cells grow exponentially according to a Feller square-root process and divide under general size-control mechanisms. We obtain exact expressions for the asymptotic population growth rate, the steady-state snapshot distribution of cell sizes, and the fluctuations of the total cell number. Our first result is that the population growth rate is exactly equal to the mean single-cell growth rate, for all noise strengths and for all division and size-regulation schemes that maintain size homeostasis. Thus square-root growth noise is neutral with respect to long-term fitness, in sharp contrast to models with size-independent stochastic growth rates. Second, we show that the steady-state population cell-size distribution is obtained from the deterministic inverse-square-law solution by a one-sided exponential convolution with kernel width set by the strength of growth fluctuations. Third, the mean-rescaled population size $N_t/\left\langle N_t\right\rangle$ converges to a stationary compound Poisson-exponential distribution that depends only on growth noise. This distribution, and hence the long-time shape of population-size fluctuations, is unchanged by division-size noise or asymmetric partitioning. These results identify Feller-type exponential growth with square-root noise as an exactly solvable benchmark for stochastic growth in size-controlled populations and provide concrete signatures that distinguish it from models with size-independent growth-rate noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05190v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farshid Jafarpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundations of information theory for coding theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Information theory is introduced in this lecture note with a particular emphasis on its relevance to algebraic coding theory. The document develops the mathematical foundations for quantifying uncertainty and information transmission by building upon Shannon's pioneering formulation of information, entropy, and channel capacity. Examples, including the binary symmetric channel, illustrate key concepts such as entropy, conditional entropy, mutual information, and the noisy channel model. Furthermore, the note describes the principles of maximum likelihood decoding and Shannon's noisy channel coding theorem, which characterizes the theoretical limits of reliable communication over noisy channels. Students and researchers seeking a connection between probabilistic frameworks of information theory and structural and algebraic techniques used in modern coding theory will find this work helpful.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05316v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>El Mahdi Mouloua, Essaid Mohamed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convolution-FFT for option pricing in the Heston model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05326v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a convolution-FFT method for pricing European options under the Heston model that leverages a continuously differentiable representation of the joint characteristic function. Unlike existing Fourier-based methods that rely on branch-cut adjustments or empirically tuned damping parameters, our approach yields a stable integrand even under large frequency oscillations. Crucially, we derive fully analytical error bounds that quantify both truncation error and discretization error in terms of model parameters and grid settings. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to provide such explicit, closed-form error estimates for an FFT-based convolution method specialized to the Heston model. Numerical experiments confirm the theoretical rates and illustrate robust, high-accuracy option pricing at modest computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05326v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Gao, Cody Hyndman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Decision Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Analyzing decision problems under uncertainty commonly relies on idealizing assumptions about the describability of the world, with the most prominent examples being the closed world and the small world assumption. Most assumptions are operationalized by introducing states of the world, conditional on which the decision situation can be analyzed without any remaining uncertainty. Conversely, most classical decision-theoretic approaches are not applicable if the states of the world are inaccessible. We propose a decision model that retains the appeal and simplicity of the original theory, but completely overcomes the need to specify the states of the world explicitly. The main idea of our approach is to address decision problems in a radically empirical way: instead of specifying states and consequences prior to the decision analysis, we only assume a protocol of observed act--consequence pairs as model primitives. We show how optimality in such empirical decision problems can be addressed by using protocol-based empirical choice functions and discuss three approaches for deriving inferential guarantees: (I) consistent statistical estimation of choice sets, (II) consistent statistical testing of choice functions with robustness guarantees, and (III) direct inference for empirical choice functions using credal sets. We illustrate our theory with a proof-of-concept application comparing different prompting strategies in generative AI models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05677v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Jansen (Lancaster University Leipzig), Georg Schollmeyer (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen), Thomas Augustin (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen), Julian Rodemann (CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security Saarbr\"ucken)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic stability and ergodic properties of quantum trajectories under imperfect measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05770v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the asymptotic stability and ergodic properties of quantum trajectories under imperfect measurement, extending previous results established for the ideal case of perfect measurement. We establish a necessary and sufficient condition ensuring the convergence of the estimated trajectory, initialized from an estimated state, to the true trajectory. This result is obtained assuming that the associated quantum channel is irreducible. Building on this, we prove the uniqueness of the invariant measure and demonstrate convergence toward this measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05770v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nina H. Amini, Tristan Benoist, Ma\"el Bompais, Cl\'ement Pellegrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Passivity in Stochastic Differential Equations: A Port-Hamiltonian Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend deterministic port-Hamiltonian systems (PHS) to a stochastic framework by means of stochastic differential equations. As the dissipation inequality plays a crucial role for deterministic PHS, we develop several passivity concepts for stochastic input-state-output systems and characterize these in terms of the parameters of the system. Afterwards, we examine properties of a certain class of linear stochastic systems that can be regarded as an extension of linear deterministic PHS to a stochastic passivity framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05838v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Ackermann, Thomas Kruse, Stefan Tappe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous approximations for the fixation probability of the Moran processes on star graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.04572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.04572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a generalized version of the birth-death (BD) and death-birth (DB) processes introduced by Kaveh, Komarova, and Kohandel (2015), in which two constant fitnesses, one for birth and the other for death, describe the selection mechanism of the population. Rather than constant fitnesses, in this paper we consider more general frequency-dependent fitness functions (allowing any smooth functions) under the weak-selection regime. A particular case arises in evolutionary games on graphs, where the fitness functions are linear combinations of the frequencies of types. For a large population structured as a star graph, we provide approximations for the fixation probability which are solutions of certain ODEs (or systems of ODEs). For the DB case, we prove that our approximation has an error of order $1/N$, where $N$ is the size of the population.
  The general BD and DB processes contain, as special cases, the BD-* and DB-* (where * can be either B or D) processes described in Hadjichrysanthou, Broom, and Rycht\'a\v{r} (2011) -- this class includes many examples of update rules used in the literature. Our analysis shows how the star graph may act as an amplifier, suppressor, or remains isothermal depending on the scaling of the initial mutant placement. We identify an analytical threshold for this transition and illustrate it through applications to evolutionary games, which further highlight asymmetric structural effects across different game types. Numerical examples show that our fixation probability approximations remain accurate even for moderate population sizes and across a wide range of frequency-dependent fitness functions, extending well beyond previously studied linear cases derived from evolutionary games, or constant fitness scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.04572v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Poly H. da Silva, Max O. Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general correlation inequality for level sets of sums of independent random variables using the Bernoulli part with applications to the almost sure local limit theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.19372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $X=\{X_j , j\ge 1\}$ be a sequence of independent, square integrable variables taking values in a common lattice $\mathcal L(v_{ 0},D )= \{v_{ k}=v_{ 0}+D k , k\in \Z\}$.
  Let $S_n=X_1+\ldots +X_n$, $a_n= {\mathbb E\,} S_n$, and $\s_n^2={\rm Var}(S_n)\to \infty$ with $n$. Assume that for each $j$, $\t_{X_j} =\sum_{k\in \Z}{\mathbb P}\{X_j=v_k\}\wedge{\mathbb P}\{X_j=v_{k+1}\}&gt;0$. Using the Bernoulli part, we prove a general sharp correlation inequality extending the one we obtained in the i.i.d.\,case in \cite{W3}: Let $0&lt;\t_j\le \t_{X_j}$ and assume that $ \nu_n =\sum_{j=1}^n \t_j \, \uparrow \infty$, $n\to \infty$.
  Let $\k_j\in \mathcal L(jv_0,D)$, $j=1,2,\ldots$ be a sequence of integers such that
  \begin{equation*} {\rm(1)}\qquad\frac{\kappa_j-a_j}{\s_j}=\mathcal O(1 ), \qq\quad {\rm(2)}\qquad \s_j \,{\mathbb P}\{S_j=\kappa_j\} ={\mathcal O}(1).
  \end{equation*}
  Then there exists a constant $C $
  such that for all $1\le m&lt;n$, \begin{align*}
  \s_n&amp;\s_m \, \Big|{\mathbb P}\{S_n=\k_n, S_m=\k_m\}- {\mathbb P}\{S_n=\k_n \}{\mathbb P}\{ S_m=\k_m\} \Big|
  \cr &amp; \,\le \, \frac{C}{D^2}\, \max \Big(\frac{\s_n }{\sqrt{\nu_n}},\frac{\s_m }{\sqrt {\nu_m}} \Big)^3 \,\bigg\{ \nu_n^{1/2} \prod_{j=m+1}^n\vartheta_j + {\nu_n^{1/2} \over
  (\nu_n-\nu_m) ^{3/2}}+{ 1\over \sqrt{{\nu_n\over \nu_m}}-1} \bigg\}.
  \end{align*} We derive a sharp almost sure local limit theorem</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.19372v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michel J. G. Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Evaluation of Small Call Centres in a Transient Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16399v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses a fundamental and practically significant problem in call centre operations -- determining optimal call allocation policies that meet client service targets while minimising staffing costs. Motivated by a problem presented by an industry partner, we examine a real-world setting involving a relatively small call centre with hierarchical structure among agents. It is natural to model the operation of such a centre as a continuous-time Markov chain. To gain insight into the structure of optimal policies, we first (i) apply backward induction based on Bellman's equation to a finite-horizon discrete-time model, and (ii) derive stationary policies for an infinite-horizon continuous-time model with discounting. Subsequently, we evaluate the performance of these policies in the original finite-horizon continuous-time setting by computing the expected number of abandonments and the waiting time distributions of customers. This is achieved using first-step analysis combined with Laplace transform methods. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is illustrated through numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16399v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Fackrell, Hritika Gupta, Peter G. Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit theorems for Non-Markovian rumor models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07170v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a non-Markovian rumor model in the complete graph on $n$ vertices inspired by Daley and Kendall's ideas (1964). For this model, we prove a functional law of large numbers (FLLN) and a functional central limit theorem (FCLT). We apply these results to a non-Markovian version of the model introduced by Lebensztayn, Machado and Rodr\'{i}guez (2011).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07170v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian F. Coletti, Denis A. Luiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A random recursive tree model with doubling events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18466v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new model of random tree that grows like a random recursive tree, except at some exceptional "doubling events" when the tree is replaced by two copies of itself attached to a new root. We prove asymptotic results for the size of this tree at large times, its degree distribution, and its height profile. We also prove a lower bound for its height. Because of the doubling events that affect the tree globally, the proofs are all much more intricate than in the case of the random recursive tree in which the growing operation is always local.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18466v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.spa.2025.104790</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jakob E. Bj\"ornberg, C\'ecile Mailler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to quantum exclusion processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01570v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The QSSEP, short for quantum symmetric simple exclusion process, is a paradigm model for stochastic quantum dynamics. Averaging over the noise, the quantum dynamics reduce to the well-studied SSEP (symmetric simple exclusion process). These notes provide an introduction to quantum exclusion processes, focusing on the example of QSSEP and its connection to free probability, with an emphasis on mathematical aspects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01570v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Barraquand, Denis Bernard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal diameter bounds for random graphs with given degrees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10759v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a graph $G$, let $\mathrm{diam}(G)$ be the greatest distance between any two vertices of $G$ which lie in the same connected component, and let $\mathrm{diam}^+(G)$ be the greatest distance between any two vertices of $G$; so $\mathrm{diam}^+(G)=\infty$ if $G$ is not connected.
  Fix a sequence $(d_1,\ldots,d_n)$ of positive integers, and let $\mathbf{G}$ be a uniformly random connected simple graph with $V(\mathbf{G})=[n]:=\{1,\ldots,n\}$ such that $\mathrm{deg}_{\mathbf{G}}(v)=d_v$ for all $v \in [n]$. We show that, unless a $1-o(1)$ proportion of vertices have degree $2$, then $\mathbb{E}[\mathrm{diam}(\mathbf{G})]=O(\sqrt{n})$. It is not hard to see that this bound is best possible for general degree sequences (and in particular in the case of trees, in which $\sum_{v=1}^n d_v = 2(n-1)$). We also prove that this bound holds without the connectivity constraint. As a key input to the proofs, we show that graphs with minimum degree $3$ are with high probability connected and have logarithmic diameter: if $\min(d_1,\ldots,d_n) \ge 3$ and $\mathbf{G}$ is a uniformly random simple graph with $V(\mathbf{G})=[n]$ such that $\mathrm{deg}_{\mathbf{G}}(v)=d_v$ for all $v \in [n]$, then $\mathrm{diam}^+(\mathbf{G})=$ $O_{\mathbb{P}}(\log n)$; this bound is also best possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10759v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louigi Addario-Berry, Gabriel Crudele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ranges of Extremal Processes and Heavy-Tailed Random Walks in Spaces of Growing Dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18780v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider extremal processes and random walks generated by heavy-tailed random vectors. We assume that these vectors take values in $\mathbb{R}^d$, and establish limit theorems for their paths in the triangular array setting when both the number of steps $n$ and the dimension $d$ grow to infinity. It is shown that it is possible to map the paths using isometries of $\ell_p$ such that the images converge and to identify the limit as derived from a Poisson cluster process. This also implies the convergence in distribution in distribution of the paths interpreted as finite metric spaces on the family of metric spaces equipped with the Gromov-Hausdorff distance. We also show that the images of the paths converge in distribution in the space of counting measures on the line equipped with the Hausdorff metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18780v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bochen Jin, Ilya Molchanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slit-slide-sew bijections for constellations and quasiconstellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12141v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend so-called slit-slide-sew bijections to constellations and quasiconstellations. We present an involution on the set of hypermaps given with an orientation, one distinguished corner, and one distinguished edge leading away from the corner while oriented in the given orientation. This involution reverts the orientation, exchanges the distinguished corner with the distinguished edge in some sense, slightly modifying the degrees of the incident faces in passing, while keeping all the other faces intact.
  The construction consists in building a canonical path from the distinguished elements, slitting the map along it, and sewing back after sliding by one unit along the path. The involution specializes into a bijection interpreting combinatorial identities linking the numbers of constellations or quasiconstellations with a given face degree distribution, where the degree distributions differ by one $+1$ and one $-1$. In particular, this allows to recover the counting formula for constellations or quasiconstellations with a given face degree distribution.
  Our bijections furthermore provide an algorithm for sampling a hypermap uniformly distributed among constellations or quasiconstellations with prescribed face degrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12141v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emie Bettinelli, Dimitri Korkotashvili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Maximum of a Gaussian Random Field and Exact (t-)Spacing test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18397v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we introduce the novel concept of the second maximum of a Gaussian random field on a Riemannian submanifold. This second maximum serves as a powerful tool for characterizing the distribution of the maximum. By utilizing an ad-hoc Kac Rice formula, we derive the explicit form of the maximum's distribution, conditioned on the second maximum and some regressed component of the Riemannian Hessian. This approach results in an exact test, based on the evaluation of spacing between these maxima, which we refer to as the spacing test.
  We investigate the applicability of this test in detecting sparse alternatives within Gaussian symmetric tensors, continuous sparse deconvolution, and two-layered neural networks with smooth rectifiers. Our theoretical results are supported by numerical experiments, which illustrate the calibration and power of the proposed tests. More generally, this test can be applied to any Gaussian random field on a Riemannian manifold, and we provide a general framework for the application of the spacing test in continuous sparse kernel regression.
  Furthermore, when the variance-covariance function of the Gaussian random field is known up to a scaling factor, we derive an exact Studentized version of our test, coined the $t$-spacing test. This test is perfectly calibrated under the null hypothesis and has high power for detecting sparse alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18397v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Marc Aza\"is, Federico Dalmao, Yohann De Castro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Proof of Talagrand's Creating Large Sets Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17336v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Talagrand conjectured that if a family of sets $\mathcal{F}$ over $X = \{ 1,2,\cdots, N \}$ is of large measure, then constant times of unions of sets in $\mathcal{F}$ will cover a large portion of the power set of $X$. This conjecture is a central open problem at the intersection of combinatorics and probability theory, and was described by Talagrand as a personal favorite. This paper provides a proof confirming this conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17336v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Fang, Tianyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of a Sequential Monte Carlo algorithm towards multimodal distributions on Rd</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22564v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In an earlier joint work, we studied a sequential Monte Carlo algorithm to sample from the Gibbs measure supported on torus with a non-convex energy function at a low temperature, where we proved that the time complexity of the algorithm is polynomial in the inverse temperature. However, the analysis in that torus setting relied crucially on compactness and does not directly extend to unbounded domains. This work introduces a new approach that resolves this issue and establishes a similar result for sampling from Gibbs measures supported on Rd. In particular, our main result shows that for double-well energy with equal well depths, the time complexity scales as seventh power of the inverse temperature, and quadratically in both the inverse allowed absolute error and probability error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22564v3</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
