<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 04:01:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The near critical random bond ising model via embedding deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the formalism of differential equations, we introduce a new method to continuously deform the $s$-embeddings associated with a family of Ising models as their coupling constants vary. This provides a geometric interpretation of the critical scaling window $\asymp n^{-1}$ for the model on the $n \times n$ box. We then drive this deterministic deformation process by i.i.d.\ Brownian motions on each edge, centered at the critical model, thereby generating random $s$-embeddings as solutions to stochastic differential equations attached to near-critical random bond Ising models. In this setting, with high probability with respect to the random environment, the Ising model remains conformally invariant in the scaling limit, even when the standard deviation of the random variables (up to logarithmic corrections) is $n^{-\frac{1}{3}} \gg n^{-1}$, far exceeding the deterministic critical window. We also construct an Ising model with slightly correlated (in space) random coupling constants, whose critical window is $ \asymp \log(n)^{-1}$ on the $n \times n$ box. Our method, which can also be applied to the dimer context, naturally extends to a much broader class of graphs and opens a new approach to understanding the critical Ising model in random environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08928v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Remy Mahfouf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The near-critical random bond FK-percolation model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study FK-percolation where the edge parameters are chosen as independent random variables in the near-critical regime. We show that if these parameters satisfy a natural centering condition around the critical point, then the quenched model typically exhibits critical behaviour at scales much larger than the deterministic characteristic length. More precisely, in a box of size $N$, if the homogeneous model with deterministic edge parameter $p$ looks critical in the regime $|p-p_c|\le \textrm W$, then the quenched model with random edge parameters $\mathbf p$ that typically satisfy $|\mathbf p-p_c|\le \textrm W^{1/3}$ looks critical, assuming some conjectured inequality on critical exponents, and up to logarithmic corrections. We also treat the special case of Bernoulli percolation, where we show that if one first samples non-degenerate independent random edge parameters centered around $\frac12$, and then a percolation configuration on these edges, the quenched model almost surely looks critical at large scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08938v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emile Av\'erous, R\'emy Mahfouf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long memory score-driven models as approximations for rough Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the continuous-time limit of score-driven models with long memory. By extending score-driven models to incorporate infinite-lag structures with coefficients exhibiting heavy-tailed decay, we establish their weak convergence, under appropriate scaling, to fractional Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes with Hurst parameter $H &lt; 1/2$. When score-driven models are used to characterize the dynamics of volatility, they serve as discrete-time approximations for rough volatility. We present several examples, including EGARCH($\infty$) whose limits give rise to a new class of rough volatility models. Building on this framework, we carry out numerical simulations and option pricing analyses, offering new tools for rough volatility modeling and simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09105v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinhao Wu, Ping He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments of additive martingales of branching L\'evy processes and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $W_t(\theta)$ be the Biggins martingale of a supercritical branching L\'evy process with non-local branching mechanism, and denote by $W_\infty(\theta)$ its limit. In this paper, we first study moment properties of $W_t(\theta)$ and $W_\infty(\theta)$, and the tail behavior of $W_\infty(\theta)$. We then apply these results to establish central limit theorems for $W_t(\theta)-W_\infty(\theta)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09188v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Xia Ren, Renming Song, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry of critical discrete structures: percolation on the hierarchical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider balls $\Lambda_n$ of growing volumes in the $d$-dimensional hierarchical lattice, and place edges independently between each pair of vertices $x\neq y\in\Lambda_n$ with probability $1-\exp(-\beta J(x, y) )$ where $J(x, y) \asymp \| x-y \|^{-\alpha}$ for some $0&lt;\alpha&lt;5d/6$. We identify the critical window for this model and establish the metric scaling limit within the critical window. More precisely, we show that the metric scaling limit of the maximal components is Brownian, and that this model belongs to the Erdos-Renyi universality class when $0&lt;\alpha&lt;5d/6$. It was recently conjectured by Hutchcroft [43, Section~7.1] that this model is a member of the Erdos-Renyi universality class when $\alpha\in(d, 4d/3]$, and we believe that this is also true for all $\alpha\in (0, d]$. This paper proves a first result in that direction. We further show that when $0&lt;\alpha&lt;2d/3$, the girth of each maximal component in the critical window is $\Omega_P(|\Lambda_n|^{1/3})$, contrary to the situation when $d&lt;\alpha\leq 4d/3$ where the girth equals $3$ .
  Our key tool is a universality principle proven in [10, 13]. Our proof technique can be adapted for the analogous problem on long-range percolation on the discrete torus provided an upper bound on the barely subcritical two-point function is obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09589v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanchayan Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Behavior of Random Time-Inhomogeneous Markovian Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of continuous-time, time-inhomogeneous Markovian quantum dynamics in a stationary random environment. Under mild faithfulness and eventually positivity-improving assumptions, the normalized evolution converges almost surely to a stationary family of full-rank states, and the normalized propagators converge almost surely to a rank-one family determined by these states. Beyond a disorder-dependent threshold, these convergences occur at exponential rates that may depend on the disorder; when the environment is ergodic, the rate itself is deterministic. When the dynamical propagators display vanishing maximal temporal stochastic correlation, convergence in stochastic expectations for the above limits is faster than any power of the time separation, and improves to exponential rates when the dynamical propagators display stochastically independent increments. These expectation bounds yield disorder-uniform high-probability estimates. The framework does not require complete positivity or trace preservation and encompasses random Lindbladian evolutions and collision-model dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08924v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lubashan Pathirana, Jeffrey Schenker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Activity-driven clustering of jamming run-and-tumble particles: Exact three-body steady state by dynamical symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We exactly resolve the three-particle steady state of run-and-tumble particles with jamming interactions, providing the first microscopic description beyond two bodies. The invariant measure, derived via a piecewise-deterministic Markov process description and symmetry principles, reveals persistent, separated, and diffusive regimes. A cascade of scales in the activity parameter organizes the structural weights, showing the separated phase dominates at finite activity, while non-uniformity plays only a minor role. This approach lays the groundwork for tackling the $N$-body problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08945v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leo Hahn, Arnaud Guillin, Manon Michel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Blaschke--Santal\'o-type inequalities, without symmetry restrictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08998v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nakamura and Tsuji (2024) recently investigated a many-function generalization of the functional Blaschke--Santal\'o inequality, which they refer to as a generalized Legendre duality relation. They showed that, among the class of all even test functions, centered Gaussian functions saturate this general family of functional inequalities. Leveraging a certain entropic duality, we give a short alternate proof of Nakamura and Tsuji's result, and, in the process, eliminate all symmetry assumptions. As an application, we establish a Talagrand-type inequality for the Wasserstein barycenter problem (without symmetry restrictions) originally conjectured by Kolesnikov and Werner (\textit{Adv.~Math.}, 2022). An analogous geometric Blaschke--Santal\'o-type inequality is established for many convex bodies, again without symmetry assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08998v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas A. Courtade, Edric Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Probability Distribution of mRNA and Protein Molecules in a Stochastic Gene Expression Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stochastic modeling of gene expression is a classic problem in theoretical biophysics. However, models formulated via chemical master equation have long been considered analytically intractable unless burst approximation is applied. This article shows that general stochastic gene expression models with an arbitrary number of gene states admit direct analysis. Based on chemical master equation and high-dimensional binomial moment method, we derive recurrence relations for binomial moments in steady state, yielding analytical expressions to arbitrary order in a hierarchical manner. Subsequently, the joint probability mass function of mRNA and protein copy number can be reconstructed. An algorithm is developed for numerical computation. Particularly, explicit expressions for low-order cumulants are presented. Compared with models under burst approximation, the first-order cumulant remains exact, whereas the second-order cumulant typically differs. We estimate the difference between two second-order binomial moments using functional analysis, therefore evaluating the validity of burst approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09122v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuntao Lu, Yunxin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divide, Interact, Sample: The Two-System Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mean-field, ensemble-chain, and adaptive samplers have historically been viewed as distinct approaches to Monte Carlo sampling. In this paper, we present a unifying {two-system} framework that brings all three under one roof. In our approach, an ensemble of particles is split into two interacting subsystems that propose updates for each other in a symmetric, alternating fashion. This cross-system interaction ensures that the overall ensemble has $\rho(x)$ as its invariant distribution in both the finite-particle setting and the mean-field limit. The two-system construction reveals that ensemble-chain samplers can be interpreted as finite-$N$ approximations of an ideal mean-field sampler; conversely, it provides a principled recipe to discretize mean-field Langevin dynamics into tractable parallel MCMC algorithms. The framework also connects naturally to adaptive single-chain methods: by replacing particle-based statistics with time-averaged statistics from a single chain, one recovers analogous adaptive dynamics in the long-time limit without requiring a large ensemble. We derive novel two-system versions of both overdamped and underdamped Langevin MCMC samplers within this paradigm. Across synthetic benchmarks and real-world posterior inference tasks, these two-system samplers exhibit significant performance gains over the popular No-U-Turn Sampler, achieving an order of magnitude higher effective sample sizes per gradient evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09162v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Chok, Myung Won Lee, Daniel Paulin, Geoffrey M. Vasil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipole and Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless Transitions in the Two-component Plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the two-dimensional two-component Coulomb gas in the canonical ensemble and at inverse temperature $\beta&gt;2$. In that regime, the partition function diverges and the interaction needs to be cut off at a length scale $\lambda&gt;0$. Particles of opposite charges tend to pair into dipoles of length scale comparable to $\lambda$, which themselves can aggregate into multipoles. Despite the slow decay of dipole--dipole interactions, we construct a convergent cluster expansion around a hierarchical reference model that retains only intra-multipole interactions. This yields a large deviation result for the number of $2p$-poles as well as a sharp free energy expansion as $N\to\infty$ and $\lambda\to0$ with three contributions: (i) the free energy of $N$ independent dipoles, (ii) a perturbative correction, and (iii) the contribution of a non-dilute subsystem.
  The perturbative term has two equivalent characterizations: (a) a convergent Mayer series obtained by expanding around an i.i.d.\ dipole model; and (b) a variational formula as the minimum of a large-deviation rate function for the empirical counts of $2p$-poles. The Mayer coefficients exhibit transitions at $\beta_p=4-\tfrac{2}{p}$, that accumulate at $\beta=4$, which corresponds to the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition in the low-dipole-density limit. At $\beta=\beta_p$ the $p$-dipole cluster integrals switch from non-integrable to integrable tails.
  The non-dilute system corresponds to the contribution of large dipoles: we exhibit a new critical length scale $R_{\beta, \lambda}$ which transitions from $\lambda^{-(\beta-2)/(4-\beta)}$ to $+\infty$ as $\beta$ crosses the critical inverse temperature $\beta=4$, and which can be interpreted as the maximal scale such that the dipoles of that scale form a dilute set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09449v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeanne Boursier, Sylvia Serfaty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric formulation of GENERIC stochastic differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a coordinate-invariant geometric formulation of the GENERIC stochastic differential equation, unifying reversible Hamiltonian and irreversible dissipative dynamics within a differential-geometric framework. Our construction builds on the classical GENERIC formalism, extending it to manifolds by introducing a degenerate Poisson structure, a degenerate co-metric, and a volume form satisfying a unimodularity condition. The resulting equation preserves a particular Boltzmann-type measure, ensures almost-sure conservation of energy, and reduces to the deterministic metriplectic formulation in the zero-noise limit. This geometrization separates system-specific quantities from the ambient space, clarifies the roles of the underlying structures, and provides a foundation for analytic and numerical methods, as well as future extensions to quantum and coarse-grained systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09566v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark A. Peletier, Marcello Seri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Random Walk Approach to Broadcasting on Random Recursive Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the broadcasting problem on trees, a $\{-1,1\}$-message originating in an unknown node is passed along the tree with a certain error probability $q$. The goal is to estimate the original message without knowing the order in which the nodes were informed. We show a connection to random walks with memory effects and use this to develop a novel approach to analyse the majority estimator on random recursive trees. With this powerful approach, we study the entire group of very simple increasing trees as well as shape exchangeable trees together. This also extends Addario-Berry et al. (2022) who investigated this estimator for uniform and linear preferential attachment random recursive trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04385v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ernst Althaus, Lisa Hartung, Rebecca Steiner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization dimensions of negative order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13387v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the possibility of defining meaningful upper and lower quantization dimensions for a compactly supported Borel probability measure of order $r$, including negative values of $r$. To this end, we use the concept of partition functions, which generalizes the idea of the $L^{q}$-spectrum and in this way naturally extends the work in [M. Kesseb\"ohmer, A. Niemann, and S. Zhu. Quantization dimensions of probability measures via R\'enyi dimensions. Trans. Amer. Math. Soc. 376.7 (2023)]. In particular, we provide natural fractal geometric bounds as well as easily verifiable necessary conditions for the existence of the quantization dimensions. The exact asymptotics of the quantization error of negative order for absolutely continuous measures are stated, whereby an open question from [S. Graf, H. Luschgy. Math. Proc. Cambridge Philos. Soc. 136, 3 (2004)] regarding the geometric mean error is also answered in the affirmative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13387v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Kesseb\"ohmer, Aljoscha Niemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint parameter estimations for spin glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10760v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin glass models with quadratic-type Hamiltonians are disordered statistical physics systems with competing ferromagnetic and anti-ferromagnetic spin interactions. The corresponding Gibbs measures belong to the exponential family parametrized by (inverse) temperature $\beta&gt;0$ and external field $h\in\mathbb{R}$. Given a sample from these Gibbs measures, a statistically fundamental question is to infer the temperature and external field parameters. In 2007, Chatterjee (Ann. Statist. 35 (2007), no.5, 1931-1946) first proved that in the absence of external field $h=0$, the maximum pseudolikelihood estimator for $\beta$ is $\sqrt{N}$-consistent under some mild assumptions on the disorder matrices. It was left open whether the same method can be used to estimate the temperature and external field simultaneously. In this paper, under some easily verifiable conditions, we prove that the bivariate maximum pseudolikelihood estimator is indeed jointly $\sqrt{N}$-consistent for the temperature and external field parameters. The examples cover the classical Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model and its diluted variants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10760v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Kuo Chen, Arnab Sen, Qiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-reversible bullet models: colliding bullet model with creations and a new(?) loop model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00750v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a large class of bullet models that contains, in particular, the colliding bullet model with creations and a new loop model. For this large class of bullet models, we give sufficient conditions on their parameter to be $\text{rot}(\pi)$-quasi-reversible and to be $\text{rot}(\pi/2)$-quasi-reversible. Moreover, those conditions assure them that one of their stationary measures is described by a Poisson point process. These results, applied to the colliding bullet model with creations, are the first steps to study its non-empty stationary measure, and, applied to the loop model, prove its invariance according to all the symmetries of the square.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00750v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\^ome Casse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sampling inverse subordinators and subdiffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15815v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, a method to exactly sample the trajectories of inverse subordinators (in the sense of the finite-dimensional distributions), jointly with the undershooting or overshooting process, is provided. The method applies to general {strictly increasing} subordinators. The (random) running times of these algorithms have finite moments and explicit bounds for the expectations are provided. Additionally, the Monte Carlo approximation of functionals of subdiffusive processes (in the form of time-changed Feller processes) is considered where a central limit theorem and the Berry-Esseen bounds are proved. The approximation of time-changed It\^o diffusions is also studied. The strong error, as a function of the time step, is explicitly evaluated demonstrating the strong convergence, and the algorithm's complexity is provided. The Monte Carlo approximation of functionals and its properties for the approximate method is studied as well. An application of our algorithms in the context of weak ergodicity breaking of subdiffusion is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15815v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Bio\v{c}i\'c, Daniel E. Cede\~no-Gir\'on, Bruno Toaldo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An approximate solution of a case of perturbed Fokker-Planck equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18131v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper focuses on finding an approximate solution of a kind of Fokker-Planck equation with time-dependent perturbations. A formulation of the approximate solution of the equation is constructed, and then the existence of the formulation is proved. The related Hamiltonian dynamical system explains the estimations. Our work provides a more comprehensive understanding of the behaviour of systems described by this Fokker-Planck equation and the corresponding stochastic differential equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18131v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Luo, Kaicheng Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided filtering and smoothing for infinite-dimensional diffusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06786v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the filtering and smoothing problems for an infinite-dimensional diffusion process X, observed through a finite-dimensional representation at discrete points in time. At the heart of our proposed methodology lies the construction of a path measure, termed the guided distribution of X, that is absolutely continuous with respect to the law of X, conditioned on the observations. We show that this distribution can be incorporated as a potent proposal measure for both sequential Monte Carlo as well as Markov Chain Monte Carlo schemes to tackle the filtering and smoothing problems respectively. In the offline setting, we extend our approach to incorporate parameter estimation of unknown model parameters. The proposed methodology is numerically illustrated in a case study for the stochastic Amari equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06786v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thorben Pieper-Sethmacher, Daniele Avitabile, Frank van der Meulen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global fluctuations for standard Young tableaux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of a Young generating function for a probability measure on integer partitions. We use this object to characterize probability distributions over integer partitions satisfying a law of large numbers and those that satisfy a central limit theorem. We further establish a multilevel central limit theorem, which enables the study of random standard Young tableaux. As applications of these results, we describe the fluctuations of height functions associated with (i) the Plancherel growth process, (ii) random standard Young tableaux of fixed shape, and (iii) probability distributions induced by extreme characters of the infinite symmetric group $S_\infty$. In all cases, we identify the limiting fluctuations as a conditioned Gaussian Free Field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18601v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Raposo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A threshold for online balancing of sparse i.i.d. vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02432v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consider the task of \textit{online} vector balancing for stochastic arrivals $(X_i)_{i \in [T]}$, where the time horizon satisfies $T = \Theta(n)$, and the $X_i$ are i.i.d uniform $d$--sparse $n$--dimensional binary vectors, with $2\leq d \le (\log\log n)^2/\log\log\log n$. We show that for this range of parameters, every online algorithm incurs discrepancy at least $\Omega(\log \log n)$, and there is an efficient algorithm which achieves a matching discrepancy bound of $O(\log\log n)$ w.h.p. This establishes an asymptotic gap, both existential and algorithmic, between the online and offline versions of the average--case Beck--Fiala problem. Strikingly, the optimal online discrepancy in the considered setting is order $\log \log n$, independent of $d$ and the norms of the vectors $(X_i)_i$. Our assumptions on $d$ are nearly optimal, as this independence ceases when $d=\omega((\log\log n)^2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02432v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan J. Altschuler, Konstantin Tikhomirov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal investment with insider information using Skorokhod &amp; Russo-Vallois integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07471v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the maximization of the logarithmic utility for an insider with different anticipating techniques. Our aim is to compare the utilization of Russo-Vallois forward and Skorokhod integrals in this context. Theoretical analysis and illustrative numerical examples showcase that the Skorokhod insider outperforms the forward insider. This remarkable observation stands in contrast to the scenario involving risk-neutral traders. Furthermore, an ordinary trader could surpass both insiders if a significant negative fluctuation in the driving stochastic process leads to a sufficiently negative final value. These findings underline the intricate interplay between anticipating stochastic calculus and nonlinear utilities, which may yield non-intuitive results from the financial viewpoint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07471v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10957-025-02789-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J Optim Theory Appl 207, 48 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Elizalde, Carlos Escudero, Tomoyuki Ichiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonamenable subforests of multi-ended quasi-pmp graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07908v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the a.e. nonamenability of locally finite quasi-pmp Borel graphs whose every component admits at least three nonvanishing ends with respect to the underlying Radon--Nikodym cocycle. We witness their nonamenability by constructing Borel subforests with at least three nonvanishing ends per component, and then applying Tserunyan and Tucker-Drob's recent characterization of amenability for acyclic quasi-pmp Borel graphs. Our main technique is a weighted cycle-cutting algorithm, which yields a weight-maximal spanning forest. We also introduce a random version of this forest, which generalizes the Free Minimal Spanning Forest, to capture nonunimodularity in the context of percolation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07908v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyuan Chen, Grigory Terlov, Anush Tserunyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic maximum principle for weighted mean-field system with jump</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16000v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we consider a weighted mean-field control problem with jump-diffusion as its state process. The main difficulty is from the non-Lipschitz property of the coefficients. We overcome this difficulty by an $L_{p,q}$-estimate of the solution processes with a suitably chosen $p$ and $q$. Convex pertubation method combining with the aforementioned $L_{p,q}$-estimation method is utilized to derive the stochastic maximum principle for this control problem. A sufficient condition for the optimality is also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16000v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanyan Tang, Jie Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative chaos measure for multiplicative functions: the $L^1$-regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10555v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\alpha$ be a Steinhaus random multiplicative function. For a wide class of multiplicative functions $f$ we construct a multiplicative chaos measure arising from the Dirichlet series of $\alpha f$, in the whole $L^1$-regime. Our method does not rely on the thick point approach or Gaussian approximation, and uses a modified second moment method with the help of an approximate Girsanov theorem. We also employ the idea of weak convergence in $L^r$ to show that the limiting measure is independent of the choice of the approximation schemes, and this may be seen as a non-Gaussian analogue of Shamov's characterisation of multiplicative chaos.
  Our class of $f$-s consists of those for which the mean value of $|f(p)|^2$ lies in $(0,1)$. In particular, it includes the indicator of sums of two squares. As an application of our construction, we establish a generalised central limit theorem for the (normalised) sums of $\alpha f$, with random variance determined by the total mass of our measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10555v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofir Gorodetsky, Mo Dick Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond separability: convergence rate of vanishing viscosity approximations to mean field games via FBSDE stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the vanishing viscosity approximation to mean field games (MFGs) in $\mathbb{R}^d$ with a nonlocal and possibly non-separable Hamiltonian. We prove that the value function converges at a rate of $\mathcal{O}(\beta)$, where $\beta^2$ is the diffusivity constant, which matches the classical convergence rate of vanishing viscosity for Hamilton-Jacobi (HJ) equations. The same rate is also obtained for the approximation of the distribution of players as well as for the gradient of the value function. The proof is a combination of probabilistic and analytical arguments by first analyzing the forward-backward stochastic differential equation associated with the MFG, and then applying a general stability result for HJ equations. Applications of our result to $N$-player games, mean field control, and policy iteration for solving MFGs are also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18529v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.48550/arXiv.2505.18529</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Winston Yu, Qiang Du, Wenpin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A potential-theoretic approach to optimal stopping in a spectrally L\'evy Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10538v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a systematic solution method for optimal stopping problems of one-dimensional spectrally negative \lev processes. Our approach relies essentially on the potential theory, in particular the Riesz decomposition and the maximum principle. Using these mathematical results, we not only identify and prove the necessary and sufficient conditions of optimality for a broad class of reward functions, but also present a method to tackle general problems in a direct and constructive way (without pre-specifying the solution form). To reinforce the latter point, we provide a step-by-step solution procedure, which is applicable to complex solution structures including multiple double-sided continuation regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10538v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiko Egami, Tomohiro Koike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the limiting distribution of sums of random multiplicative functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12956v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish the limiting distribution of $\frac{{(\log \log x)}^{1/4}}{\sqrt{x}} \sum_{n\le x}\alpha(n)$ where $\alpha$ is a Steinhaus random multiplicative function, answering a question of Harper. The distributional convergence is proved by applying the martingale central limit theorem to a suitably truncated sum. This truncation is inspired by work of Najnudel, Paquette, Simm and Vu on subcritical holomorphic multiplicative chaos setting, but analysed with a different conditioning argument generalised from Harper's work on fractional moments to circumvent integrability issues at criticality.
  A significant part of the proof is devoted to the convergence in probability of the associated partial Euler product to a critical multiplicative chaos measure, independent of the mild shift away from the critical line. Our approach to the universality of critical non-Gaussian multiplicative chaos bypasses the barrier analysis with the help of a modified second moment method, and employs a novel argument based on coupling and homogenisation by change of measure, which could be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12956v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofir Gorodetsky, Mo Dick Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Online Hardness for Large Balanced Independent Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20785v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the algorithmic problem of finding large $\gamma$-balanced independent sets in dense random bipartite graphs; an independent set is $\gamma$-balanced if a $\gamma$ proportion of its vertices lie on one side of the bipartition. In the sparse regime, Perkins and Wang established tight bounds within the low-degree polynomial (LDP) framework, showing a factor-$1/(1-\gamma)$ statistical-computational gap via the Overlap Gap Property (OGP) framework tailored for stable algorithms. However, these techniques do not appear to extend to the dense setting. For the related large independent set problem in dense random graph, the best known algorithm is an online greedy procedure that is inherently unstable, and LDP algorithms are conjectured to fail even in the "easy" regime where greedy succeeds. We show that the largest $\gamma$-balanced independent set in dense random bipartite graphs has size $\alpha:=\frac{\log_b n}{\gamma(1-\gamma)}$ whp, where $n$ is the size of each bipartition, $p$ is the edge probability, and $b=1/(1-p)$. We design an online algorithm that achieves $(1-\epsilon)(1-\gamma)\alpha$ whp for any $\epsilon&gt;0$. We complement this with a sharp lower bound, showing that no online algorithm can achieve $(1+\epsilon)(1-\gamma)\alpha$ with nonnegligible probability. Our results suggest that the same factor-$1/(1-\gamma)$ gap is also present in the dense setting, supporting its conjectured universality. While the classical greedy procedure on $G(n,p)$ is straightforward, our algorithm is more intricate: it proceeds in two stages, incorporating a stopping time and suitable truncation to ensure that $\gamma$-balancedness-a global constraint-is met despite operating with limited information. Our lower bound utilizes the OGP framework; we build on a recent refinement of this framework for online models and extend it to the bipartite setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20785v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Dhawan, Eren C. K{\i}z{\i}lda\u{g}, Neeladri Maitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
