<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 04:01:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Conditional Probability formula as a consequence of the Insufficient Reason Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The standard conditional probability definition formula is derived as a consequence of the Insufficient Reason Principle expressed as the Maximum Relative Divergence Principle for grading (order-comonotonic) functions on a totally ordered set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08040v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Dukhovny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Statistics for Coulomb Gases at Intermediate Temperature Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the microscopic statistics of a Coulomb gas in $\mathbb{R}^2$ at intermediate temperatures. In particular, we show that the microscopic point process associated to the Coulomb gas converges to a homogeneous Poisson point process at intermediate temperature regimes $\beta N \rightarrow \infty$ and $\beta N \log N \rightarrow 0$, extending previous results. Our approach relies on a novel quantitative asymptotic description of correlation functions, which is of its own interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08198v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Padilla-Garza, Luke Peilen, Eric Thoma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal transport, determinantal point processes and the Bergman kernel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Bergman determinantal point process from a theoretical point of view motivated by its simulation. We construct restricted and restricted-truncated variants of the Bergman kernel and show optimal transport inequalities involving the Kantorovitch-Rubinstein Wasserstein distance to show to what extent it is fair to truncate the restriction of this point process to a compact ball of radius $1 - \varepsilon $. We also investigate the deviation of the number of points of the restricted Bergman determinantal point process, indicate which number of points looks like an optimal choice, and provide upper bounds on its deviation, providing an answer to an open question asked in [5]. We also consider restrictions to other regions and investigate the choice of such regions for restriction. Finally, we provide general results as to the deviation of the number of points of any determinantal point process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08204v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Driot, Laurent Decreusefond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp and Exact Tail Estimates for Multitype Poissonian Galton Watson Processes and Inhomogeneous Cluster Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove exponential moments for linear combinations of the number of individuals of each type of a whole multitype Poissonian Galton Watson process. We give sharp estimates for such quantities, which depend on the expectation of the Poissonian offspring distribution and the linear combination. We apply this result to derive type specific exponential moments for multitype Hawkes processes, improving existing results when the dimension is large. We also prove exponential estimates for tails of inhomogeneous Poissonian clusters. These estimates depend on the decay of the interaction functions defining the clusters and are starting points to derive probabilistic properties on branching processes such as Hawkes processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08462v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Leblanc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Level area of spin random fields: a chaos decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study real left-invariant spin Gaussian fields on $SO(3)$, a special class of non-isotropic random fields used to model the polarization of the Cosmic Microwave Background. Leveraging recent results from "New chaos decomposition of Gaussian nodal volumes" (arXiv:2505.22350), we provide an explicit formula for the Wiener-It\^o chaos decomposition of the area measure of level sets of such random fields. Our analysis represents a step forward in the study of second-order asymptotic properties of the Lipschitz-Killing curvatures of excursion sets of spin random fields. Remarkably, our formulas reveal a clear difference between the high frequency regime and the zero spin case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08550v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Pistolato, Michele Stecconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domino Tilings of the Aztec Diamond in Random Environment and Schur Generating Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of random domino tilings of the Aztec diamond of size $M$ in a random environment, where the environment is a one-periodic sequence of i.i.d. random weights attached to domino positions (i.e., to the edges of the underlying portion of the square grid). We consider two cases: either the variance of the weights decreases at a critical scale $1/M$, or the distribution of the weights is fixed. In the former case, the unrescaled fluctuations of the domino height function are governed by the sum of a Gaussian Free Field and an independent Brownian motion. In the latter case, we establish fluctuations on the much larger scale $\sqrt M$, given by the Brownian motion alone.
  To access asymptotic fluctuations in random environment, we employ the method of Schur generating functions. Moreover, we substantially extend the known Law of Large Numbers and Central Limit Theorems for particle systems via Schur generating functions in order to apply them to our setting. These results might be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08560v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Bufetov, Leonid Petrov, Panagiotis Zografos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pointwise explicit estimates for derivatives of solutions to linear parabolic PDEs with Neumann boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a pointwise bound on the spatial derivative $\left| \frac{\partial V}{\partial x} \right|$ of the solution to a parabolic PDE with Neumann boundary conditions.
  The bound is fully explicit in the sense that it depends only on the coefficients of the PDE and the domain, including closed-form expression for all constants. The proof is purely probabilistic. We first extend to time inhomogeneous diffusions a result concerning the derivative of the solution of a reflected SDE. Then, we combine it with the spectral expansion of the law of the first hitting time to a boundary for a reflected diffusion. The motivation for this work arises from optimal control theory where, when the Hamilton Jacobi Bellman (HJB) equation does not admit a closed-form solution, precise estimates of its derivatives are often required to apply a verification theorem. This result will be used in a forthcoming paper to rigorously prove that the conjectured optimal strategy for the sailboat trajectory optimization problem, formulated in a previous paper by the author, is indeed optimal far from the buoy. We also state a sufficient condition for $\left| \frac{\partial V}{\partial x}(t,x) \right|$ to be bounded as $t\rightarrow \infty$ which only involves the coefficients of the problem and the first eigenvalue of the spectral expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08622v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C Ciccarella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some notes on higher order concentration of measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This survey-type paper provides a common framework for a larger number of higher order concentration results (i.\,e., concentration results for non-Lipschitz functions which have bounded derivatives of higher order) in the spirit of Bobkov--G\"otze--Sambale (2019). Situations inlude measures satisfying various functional inequalities (log-Sobolev, Poincar\'{e}, $\mathrm{LS}_q$), uniform and cone measures on spheres with respect to the Euclidean as well as $\ell_p^n$-norms, Stiefel and Grassmann manifolds as well as discrete situations. In particular in the latter case, some open questions and remarks are stated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08692v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Sambale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong existence and uniqueness of the tilt-indexed Busemann process in the planar corner growth model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Busemann process indexed by tilts in the super-differential of the limit shape exists and is unique in the strong sense in the i.i.d.\ planar corner growth model. This means that every probability space that supports the field of i.i.d.~weights supports a copy of the process and any two realizations of the process are equal almost surely.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08757v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Janjigian, Firas Rassoul-Agha, Timo Sepp\"al\"ainen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relative importance of being Gaussian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08059v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The remarkable results for denoising in computer vision using diffusion models given in \cite{SDWMG,HJA,HHG} yield a robust mathematical justification for algorithms based on crucial properties of a sequence of Gaussian independent $N(0,1)$ random variables. In particular the derivations use the fact that a Gaussian distribution is determined by its mean and variance and that the sum of two Gaussians is another Gaussian.
  \bigskip
  The issue raised in this short note is the following: suppose we use the algorithm without any changes but replace the nature of the noise and use, for instance, uniformly distributed noise or noise with a Beta distribution, or noise which is a random superposition of two Gaussians with very different variances. One could, of course, try to modify the algorithm keeping in mind the nature of the noise, but this is not what we do. Instead we study the performance of the algorithm when used with noise that is very far in nature from the Gaussian case, where it is designed to work well.
  Usually these algorithms are implemented on very powerful computers. Our experiments are all carried out on a small laptop and for the smallest possible image size. Exploring how our observations are confirmed or changed when dealing in different situations remains an interesting challenge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08059v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Alberto Gr\"unbaum, Tondgi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-level qualitative classification of financial risks under varying conditions through first passage times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work focuses on financial risks from a probabilistic point of view. The value of a firm is described as a geometric Brownian motion and default emerges as a first passage time event. On the technical side, the critical threshold that the value process has to cross to trigger the default is assumed to be an arbitrary continuous function, what constitutes a generalization of the classical Black-Cox model. Such a generality favors modeling a wide range of risk scenarios, including those characterized by strongly time-varying conditions; but at the same time limits the possibility of obtaining closed-form formulae. To avoid this limitation, we implement a qualitative classification of risk into three categories: high, medium, and low. They correspond, respectively, to a finite mean first passage time, to an almost surely finite first passage time with infinite mean, and to a positive probability of survival for all times. This allows for an extensive classification of risk based only on the asymptotic behavior of the default function, which generalizes previously known results that assumed this function to be an exponential. However, even within these mathematical conditions, such a classification is not exhaustive, as a consequence of the behavioral freedom that continuous functions enjoy. Overall, our results contribute to the design of credit risk classifications from analytical principles and, at the same time, constitute a call of attention on potential models of risk assessment in situations largely affected by time evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08101v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Bouthelier-Madre, Carlos Escudero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mallows Model with Learned Distance Metrics: Sampling and Maximum Likelihood Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08108v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: \textit{Mallows model} is a widely-used probabilistic framework for learning from ranking data, with applications ranging from recommendation systems and voting to aligning language models with human preferences~\cite{chen2024mallows, kleinberg2021algorithmic, rafailov2024direct}. Under this model, observed rankings are noisy perturbations of a central ranking $\sigma$, with likelihood decaying exponentially in distance from $\sigma$, i.e, $P (\pi) \propto \exp\big(-\beta \cdot d(\pi, \sigma)\big),$ where $\beta &gt; 0$ controls dispersion and $d$ is a distance function.
  Existing methods mainly focus on fixed distances (such as Kendall's $\tau$ distance), with no principled approach to learning the distance metric directly from data. In practice, however, rankings naturally vary by context; for instance, in some sports we regularly see long-range swaps (a low-rank team beating a high-rank one), while in others such events are rare. Motivated by this, we propose a generalization of Mallows model that learns the distance metric directly from data. Specifically, we focus on $L_\alpha$ distances: $d_\alpha(\pi,\sigma):=\sum_{i=1} |\pi(i)-\sigma(i)|^\alpha$.
  For any $\alpha\geq 1$ and $\beta&gt;0$, we develop a Fully Polynomial-Time Approximation Scheme (FPTAS) to efficiently generate samples that are $\epsilon$- close (in total variation distance) to the true distribution. Even in the special cases of $L_1$ and $L_2$, this generalizes prior results that required vanishing dispersion ($\beta\to0$). Using this sampling algorithm, we propose an efficient Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE) algorithm that jointly estimates the central ranking, the dispersion parameter, and the optimal distance metric. We prove strong consistency results for our estimators (for any values of $\alpha$ and $\beta$), and we validate our approach empirically using datasets from sports rankings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08108v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yeganeh Alimohammadi, Kiana Asgari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ratio limits and pressure function for group extensions of Gibbs Markov maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ratio limit theorems for random walks on (various) groups are known. We obtain a generalization of this type of ratio limit for deterministic walks on certain groups driven by Gibbs Markov maps. In terms of proofs, the main difficulty comes down to the absence of a convolution structure. Also, for (finitely generated) group extensions of Gibbs Markov maps we obtain a characterization of the pressure function without a symmetry assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08186v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaime Gomez, Dalia Terhesiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic scaling of growing interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a brief overview of the seminal paper which introduced the Kardar-Parisi-Zhang equation as a paradigmatic model for random growth in 1986. We describe some of the developments to which it gave rise in mathematics and physics over the years, and some examples of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08341v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Le Doussal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genericity of Polyak-Lojasiewicz Inequalities for Entropic Mean-Field Neural ODEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08486v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address the behavior of idealized deep residual neural networks (ResNets), modeled via an optimal control problem set over continuity (or adjoint transport) equations. The continuity equations describe the statistical evolution of the features in the asymptotic regime where the layers of the network form a continuum. The velocity field is expressed through the network activation function, which is itself viewed as a function of the statistical distribution of the network parameters (weights and biases). From a mathematical standpoint, the control is interpreted in a relaxed sense, taking values in the space of probability measures over the set of parameters. We investigate the optimal behavior of the network when the cost functional arises from a regression problem and includes an additional entropic regularization term on the distribution of the parameters. In this framework, we focus in particular on the existence of stable optimizers --that is, optimizers at which the Hessian of the cost is non-degenerate. We show that, for an open and dense set of initial data, understood here as probability distributions over features and associated labels, there exists a unique stable global minimizer of the control problem. Moreover, we show that such minimizers satisfy a local Polyak--Lojasiewicz inequality, which can lead to exponential convergence of the corresponding gradient descent when the initialization lies sufficiently close to the optimal parameters. This result thus demonstrates the genericity (with respect to the distribution of features and labels) of the Polyak--Lojasiewicz condition in ResNets with a continuum of layers and under entropic penalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08486v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Daudin, Fran\c{c}ois Delarue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hermite trace polynomials and chaos decompositions for the Hermitian Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.13180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.13180v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a non-zero parameter $q$, we define Hermite trace polynomials, which are multivariate polynomials indexed by permutations. We prove several combinatorial properties for them, such as expansions and product formulas. The linear functional determined by these trace polynomials is a state for $q = \frac{1}{N}$ for $N$ a non-zero integer. For such $q$, Hermite trace polynomials of different degrees are orthogonal. The product formulas extend to the closure with respect to the state. The state can be identified with the expectation induced by the $N \times N$ Hermitian Brownian motion. Hermite trace polynomials are martingales for this Brownian motion, while the elements in the closure can be interpreted as stochastic integrals with respect to it. Using the grading on the algebra, we prove several chaos decompositions for such integrals, as well as analyze corresponding creation and annihilation operators. In the univariate, pure trace polynomial case, trace Hermite polynomials can be identified with the Hermite polynomials of matrix argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.13180v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Anshelevich, David Buzinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determinantal random subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.06819v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define two families of determinantal random spanning subgraphs of a finite connected graph, one supported by acyclic spanning subgraphs (spanning forests) with fixed number of connected components, the other by connected spanning subgraphs with fixed number of independent cycles. Each family generalizes the uniform spanning tree and the generating functions of these probability measures generalize the classical Kirchhoff and Symanzik polynomials.
  We call Symanzik spanning forests the elements of the acyclic spanning subgraphs family, and single out a particular determinantal mixture of these, having as kernel a normalized Laplacian on $1$-forms, which we call the Laplacian spanning forest.
  Our proofs rely on a set of integral and real or complex (which we call geometric) multilinear identies involving cycles, coboundaries, and forests on graphs. We prove these identities using classical pieces of the algebraic topology of graphs and the exterior calculus applied to finite determinantal point processes, both of which we treat in a self-contained way.
  We emphasize the matroidal nature of our constructions, thereby showing how the above two families of random spanning subgraphs are dual to one another, as well as possible generalisations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.06819v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Kassel, Thierry L\'evy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectral edge of non-Hermitian random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17512v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For general non-Hermitian random matrices $X$ and deterministic deformation matrices $A$, we prove that the local eigenvalue statistics of $A+X$ close to the typical edge points of its spectrum are universal. Furthermore, we show that under natural assumptions on $A$ the spectrum of $A+X$ does not have outliers at a distance larger than the natural fluctuation scale of the eigenvalues. As a consequence, the number of eigenvalues in each component of $\mathrm{Spec}(A+X)$ is deterministic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17512v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Campbell, Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Hong Chang Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some FKG inequalities for stochastic processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13871v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is interested in proving correlation inequalities of the FKG-type for various stochastic processes in continuous time. The pivotal tool which yields these correlation inequalities is an approximation with (possibly conditioned) Markov chains and random walks. In particular, we prove FKG inequalities for L\'evy processes, Bessel processes and several conditioned Brownian processes. As a side result, we also provide a necessary and sufficient condition for a random walk distribution in $\bbZ$ to satisfy the well-known ``FKG lattice condition''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13871v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Legrand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rough Functional It\^o Formula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02532v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a rough It\^o formula for path-dependent functionals of $\alpha$-H\"older continuous paths for $\alpha\in(0,1)$. Our approach combines the sewing lemma and a Taylor approximation in terms of path-dependent derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02532v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franziska Bielert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian spectral universality at critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17030v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For general large non-Hermitian random matrices $X$ and deterministic normal deformations $A$, we prove that the local eigenvalue statistics of $A+X$ close to the critical edge points of its spectrum are universal. This concludes the proof of the third and last remaining typical universality class for non-Hermitian random matrices, after bulk and sharp edge universalities have been established in recent years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17030v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00440-025-01384-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Cipolloni, L\'aszl\'o Erd\H{o}s, Hong Chang Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodic and foliated kernel-differentiation method for linear responses of random systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10138v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend the kernel-differentiation method for the linear response (parameter-derivative of averaged observables) of random dynamical systems. First, for the linear response of physical (or stationary) measures, we extend the method to an ergodic version, which is sampled by an infinitely long sample path, so it is more efficient than previous results. This is achieved by combining the likelihood ratio trick, decay of correlations, and ergodic theorem. Second, when the noise and perturbation are along a given foliation, we show that the method is still valid for both finite and infinite time. These results are derived using basic calculus via a microscopic view of transfer operators.
  We use the ergodic formula to numerically compute the linear response of a tent map with additive noise. We use the foliated formula to compute the linear response of an unstable neural network with 51 layers $\times$ 9 neurons, with respect to the bias parameter. We show that adding foliated noise incurs a smaller error than adding noise in all directions, in terms of approximating the trend between the averaged observable and the parameter. We give a rough error analysis of the kernel-differentiation method and show that it can be expensive for small noise.
  Finally, we derive the three basic linear response methods (path-perturbation, divergence, and kernel-differentiation methods) in simplified settings, and propose a potential future program unifying them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10138v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angxiu Ni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization-delocalization transition for a random block matrix model at the edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00512v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consider a random block matrix model consisting of $D$ random systems arranged along a circle, where each system is modeled by an independent $N\times N$ complex Hermitian Wigner matrix. Neighboring systems interact via an arbitrary deterministic $N\times N$ matrix $A$. In this paper, we extend the localization-delocalization transition previously established in arxiv:2312.07297 for the bulk eigenvalue spectrum to the entire spectrum, including the spectral edges. Let $[E^-,E^+]$ denote the support of the limiting spectral density, and define $\kappa_E:=|E-E^+|\wedge |E-E^-|$ as the distance from a given energy $E \in [E^-, E^+]$ to the spectral edges. We show that for eigenvalues near $E$, the corresponding eigenvectors undergo a localization-delocalization transition when $\|A\|_{\mathrm{HS}}$ crosses the critical threshold $(\kappa_E + N^{-2/3})^{-1/2}$. In the delocalized phase, the extreme eigenvalues asymptotically follow the Tracy-Widom distribution, while in the localized phase, the edge eigenvalue statistics asymptotically match those of $D$ independent GUE ensembles, up to a deterministic shift. Our results recover those of arxiv:2312.07297 in the bulk regime, where $\kappa_E \asymp 1$, and further reveal the presence of mobility edges near $E^\pm$ when $1 \ll \|A\|_{\mathrm{HS}} \ll N^{1/3}$. Specifically, bulk eigenvectors corresponding to energies $E$ with $\kappa_E \gg \|A\|_{\mathrm{HS}}^{-2}$ are delocalized, while those with $\kappa_E \ll \|A\|_{\mathrm{HS}}^{-2}$ are localized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00512v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Fan, Bertrand Stone, Fan Yang, Jun Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On conditions for Dobrushin's Central limit theorem for non-homogeneous Markov chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07287v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new sufficient condition is proposed in the problem of Central Limit Theorem in the array scheme for non-homogeneous Markov Chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07287v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Veretennikov, Aisha Nurieva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cokernel statistics for walk matrices of directed and weighted random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12655v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The walk matrix associated to an $n\times n$ integer matrix $X$ and an integer vector $b$ is defined by $W := (b,X b, . . . ,X^{n-1} b)$. We study limiting laws for the cokernel of $W$ in the scenario where $X$ is a random matrix with independent entries and $b$ is deterministic. Our first main result provides a formula for the distribution of the $p^{m}$-torsion part of the cokernel, as a group, when $X$ has independent entries from a specific distribution. The second main result relaxes the distributional assumption and concerns the $\mathbb{Z}[x]$-module structure.
  The motivation for this work arises from an open problem in spectral graph theory which asks to show that random graphs are often determined up to isomorphism by their (generalized) spectrum. Sufficient conditions for generalized spectral determinacy can namely be stated in terms of the cokernel of a walk matrix. Extensions of our results could potentially be used to determine how often those conditions are satisfied. Some remaining challenges for such extensions are outlined in the paper</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12655v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S0963548324000312</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Combinator. Probab. Comp. 34 (2025) 131-150</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Van Werde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sibson $\alpha$-Mutual Information and Its Variational Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08352v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Information measures can be constructed from R\'enyi divergences much like mutual information from Kullback-Leibler divergence. One such information measure is known as Sibson $\alpha$-mutual information and has received renewed attention recently in several contexts: concentration of measure under dependence, statistical learning, hypothesis testing, and estimation theory. In this paper, we survey and extend the state of the art. In particular, we introduce variational representations for Sibson $\alpha$-mutual information and employ them in each described context to derive novel results. Namely, we produce generalized Transportation-Cost inequalities and Fano-type inequalities. We also present an overview of known applications, spanning from learning theory and Bayesian risk to universal prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08352v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amedeo Roberto Esposito, Michael Gastpar, Ibrahim Issa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Construction of Kakeya-Type Sets in $\mathbb{R}^2$ associated to separated sets of directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17674v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a condition on a set of directions $\Omega \subset \mathbb{S}^1$ ensuring that the associated directional maximal operator $M_\Omega$ is unbounded on $L^p(\mathbb{R}^2)$ for every $1 \leq p &lt; \infty$. The techniques of proof extend ideas of Bateman and Katz involving probabilistic construction of Kakeya-type sets involving sticky maps and Bernoulli percolation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17674v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Hagelstein, Blanca Radillo-Murguia, Alexander Stokolos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic contiguity from low-degree conjecture and applications in correlated random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09832v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, assuming a natural strengthening of the low-degree conjecture, we provide evidence of computational hardness for two problems: (1) the (partial) matching recovery problem in the sparse correlated Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi graphs $\mathcal G(n,q;\rho)$ when the edge-density $q=n^{-1+o(1)}$ and the correlation $\rho&lt;\sqrt{\alpha}$ lies below the Otter's threshold, solving a remaining problem in \cite{DDL23+}; (2) the detection problem between the correlated sparse stochastic block model $\mathcal S(n,\tfrac{\lambda}{n};k,\epsilon;s)$ and a pair of independent stochastic block models $\mathcal S(n,\tfrac{\lambda s}{n};k,\epsilon)$ when $\epsilon^2 \lambda s&lt;1$ lies below the Kesten-Stigum (KS) threshold and $s&lt;\sqrt{\alpha}$ lies below the Otter's threshold, solving a remaining problem in \cite{CDGL24+}.
  One of the main ingredient in our proof is to derive certain forms of \emph{algorithmic contiguity} between two probability measures based on bounds on their low-degree advantage. To be more precise, consider the high-dimensional hypothesis testing problem between two probability measures $\mathbb{P}$ and $\mathbb{Q}$ based on the sample $\mathsf Y$. We show that if the low-degree advantage $\mathsf{Adv}_{\leq D} \big( \frac{\mathrm{d}\mathbb{P}}{\mathrm{d}\mathbb{Q}} \big)=O(1)$, then (assuming the low-degree conjecture) there is no efficient algorithm $\mathcal A$ such that $\mathbb{Q}(\mathcal A(\mathsf Y)=0)=1-o(1)$ and $\mathbb{P}(\mathcal A(\mathsf Y)=1)=\Omega(1)$. This framework provides a useful tool for performing reductions between different inference tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09832v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhangsong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Phase Transitions in Estimation with Low-Degree Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14407v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: High-dimensional planted problems, such as finding a hidden dense subgraph within a random graph, often exhibit a gap between statistical and computational feasibility. While recovering the hidden structure may be statistically possible, it is conjectured to be computationally intractable in certain parameter regimes. A powerful approach to understanding this hardness involves proving lower bounds on the efficacy of low-degree polynomial algorithms. We introduce new techniques for establishing such lower bounds, leading to novel results across diverse settings: planted submatrix, planted dense subgraph, the spiked Wigner model, and the stochastic block model. Notably, our results address the estimation task -- whereas most prior work is limited to hypothesis testing -- and capture sharp phase transitions such as the "BBP" transition in the spiked Wigner model (named for Baik, Ben Arous, and P\'{e}ch\'{e}) and the Kesten-Stigum threshold in the stochastic block model. Existing work on estimation either falls short of achieving these sharp thresholds or is limited to polynomials of very low (constant or logarithmic) degree. In contrast, our results rule out estimation with polynomials of degree $n^{\delta}$ where $n$ is the dimension and $\delta &gt; 0$ is a constant, and in some cases we pin down the optimal constant $\delta$. Our work resolves open problems posed by Hopkins &amp; Steurer (2017) and Schramm &amp; Wein (2022), and provides rigorous support within the low-degree framework for conjectures by Abbe &amp; Sandon (2018) and Lelarge &amp; Miolane (2019).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14407v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngtak Sohn, Alexander S. Wein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Malliavin calculus approach to score functions in diffusion generative models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05550v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Score-based diffusion generative models have recently emerged as a powerful tool for modelling complex data distributions. These models aim at learning the score function, which defines a map from a known probability distribution to the target data distribution via deterministic or stochastic differential equations (SDEs). The score function is typically estimated from data using a variety of approximation techniques, such as denoising or sliced score matching, Hyv\"arien's method, or Schr\"odinger bridges. In this paper, we derive an exact, closed form, expression for the score function for a broad class of nonlinear diffusion generative models. Our approach combines modern stochastic analysis tools such as Malliavin derivatives and their adjoint operators (Skorokhod integrals or Malliavin Divergence) with a new Bismut-type formula. The resulting expression for the score function can be written entirely in terms of the first and second variation processes, with all Malliavin derivatives systematically eliminated, thereby enhancing its practical applicability. The theoretical framework presented in this work offers a principled foundation for advancing score estimation methods in generative modelling, enabling the design of new sampling algorithms for complex probability distributions. Our results can be extended to broader classes of stochastic differential equations, opening new directions for the development of score-based diffusion generative models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05550v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Mirafzali, Frank Proske, Utkarsh Gupta, Daniele Venturi, Razvan Marinescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
