<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Critical branching processes with immigration: scaling limits of local extinction sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the joint scaling limit of a critical Bienaym\'e-Galton-Watson process with immigration (BGWI) and its (counting) local time at zero to the corresponding self-similar continuous-state branching process with immigration (CBI) and its (Markovian) local time at zero for balanced offspring and immigration laws in stable domains of attraction. Using a general framework for invariance principles of local times~\cite{MR4463082}, the problem reduces to the analysis of the structure of excursions from zero and positive levels, together with the weak convergence of the hitting times of points of the BGWI to those of the CBI. A key step in the proof of our main limit theorem is a novel Yaglom limit for the law at time $t$ of an excursion with lifetime exceeding $t$ of a scaled infinite-variance critical BGWI.
  Our main result implies a joint septuple scaling limit of BGWI $Z_1$, its local time at $0$, the random walks $X_1$ and $Y_1$ associated to the reproduction and immigration mechanisms, respectively, the counting local time at $0$ of $X_1$, an additive functional of $Z_1$ and $X_1$ evaluated at this functional. In the septuple limit, four different scaling sequences are identified and given explicitly in terms of the offspring generating function (modulo asymptotic inversion), the local extinction probabilities of the BGWI and the tails of return times to zero of $X_1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20923v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandar Mijatovi\'c, Benjamin Povar, Ger\'onimo Uribe Bravo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Percolation of both signs in a triangular-type 3D Ising model above $T_c$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{T}$ be the two-dimensional triangular lattice, and $\mathbb{Z}$ the one-dimensional integer lattice. Let $\mathbb{T}\times \mathbb{Z}$ denote the Cartesian product graph. Consider the Ising model defined on this graph with inverse temperature $\beta$ and external field $h$, and let $\beta_c$ be the critical inverse temperature when $h=0$. We prove that for each $\beta\in[0,\beta_c)$, there exists $h_c(\beta)&gt;0$ such that both a unique infinite $+$cluster and a unique infinite $-$cluster coexist whenever $|h|&lt;h_c(\beta)$. The same coexistence result also holds for the three-dimensional triangular lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21147v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianping Jiang, Sike Lang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuations in random field Ising models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper establishes a CLT for linear statistics of the form $\langle \mathbf{q},\boldsymbol{\sigma} \rangle$ with quantitative Berry-Esseen bounds, where $\boldsymbol{\sigma}$ is an observation from an exponential family with a quadratic form as its sufficient statistic, in the \enquote{high-temperature} regime. We apply our general result to random field Ising models with both discrete and continuous spins. To demonstrate the generality of our techniques, we apply our results to derive both quenched and annealed CLTs in various examples, which include Ising models on some graph ensembles of common interest (Erd\H{o}s-R\'{e}nyi, regular, dense bipartite), and the Hopfield spin glass model. Our proofs rely on a combination of Stein's method of exchangeable pairs and Chevet type concentration inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21152v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seunghyun Lee, Nabarun Deb, Sumit Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantification of limit theorems for Hawkes processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we fill a gap in the literature regarding quantitative functional central limit theorems (qfCLT) for Hawkes processes by providing an upper bound for the convergence of a nearly unstable Hawkes process toward a Cox-Ingersoll-Ross (CIR) process. Note that in this case no speed of convergence has been established even for one-dimensional marginals; we provide in this paper a control in terms of a supremum norm in $2$-Wasserstein distance. To do so, we make use of the so-called Poisson imbedding representation and provide a qfCLT formulation in terms of a Brownian sheet. Incidentally, we construct an optimal coupling between a rescaled bi-dimensional Poisson random measure and a Brownian sheet with respect to the $2$-Wasserstein distance and analyze the asymptotic quality of this coupling in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21273v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laure Coutin (IMT, UT), Benjamin Massat (IMT, UT), Anthony R\'eveillac (INSA Toulouse, IMT, UT)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence in $\chi^2$ Distance to the Normal Distribution for Sums of Independent Random Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Suppose $n$ independent random variables $X_1, X_2, \dots, X_n$ have zero mean and equal variance. We prove that if the average of $\chi^2$ distances between these variables and the normal distribution is bounded by a sufficiently small constant, then the $\chi^2$ distance between their normalized sum and the normal distribution is $O(1/n)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21320v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vytas Zacharovas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition probabilities for stochastic differential equations using the Laplace approximation: Analysis of the continuous-time limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We recently proposed a method for estimation of states and parameters in stochastic differential equations, which included intermediate time points between observations and used the Laplace approximation to integrate out these intermediate states. In this paper, we establish a Laplace approximation for the transition probabilities in the continuous-time limit where the computational time step between intermediate states vanishes. Our technique views the driving Brownian motion as a control, casts the problem as one of minimum effort control between two states, and employs a Girsanov shift of probability measure as well as a weak noise approximation to obtain the Laplace approximation. We demonstrate the technique with examples; one where the approximation is exact due to a property of coordinate transforms, and one where contributions from non-near paths impair the approximation. We assess the order of discrete-time scheme, and demonstrate the Strang splitting leads to higher order and accuracy than Euler-type discretization. Finally, we investigate numerically how the accuracy of the approximation depends on the noise intensity and the length of the time interval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21399v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uffe H{\o}gsbro Thygesen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds for survival probabilities in supercritical Galton-Watson processes and applications to population genetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Population genetic processes, such as the adaptation of a quantitative trait to directional selection, may occur on longer time scales than the sweep of a single advantageous mutation. To study such processes in finite populations, approximations for the time course of the distribution of a beneficial mutation were derived previously by branching process methods. The application to the evolution of a quantitative trait requires bounds for the probability of survival $\Sn$ up to generation $n$ of a single beneficial mutation. Here, we present a method to obtain a simple, analytically explicit, either upper or lower, bound for $\Sn$ in a supercritical Galton-Watson process. We prove the existence of an upper bound for offspring distributions including Poisson and binomial. They are constructed by bounding the given generating function, $\varphi$, by a fractional linear one that has the same survival probability $\Sinf$ and yields the same rate of convergence of $\Sn$ to $\Sinf$ as $\varphi$. For distributions with at most three offspring, we characterize when this method yields an upper bound, a lower bound, or only an approximation. Because for many distributions it is difficult to get a handle on $\Sinf$, we derive an approximation by series expansion in $s$, where $s$ is the selective advantage of the mutant. We briefly review well-known asymptotic results that generalize Haldane's approximation $2s$ for $\Sinf$, as well as less well-known results on sharp bounds for $\Sinf$. We apply them to explore when bounds for $\Sn$ exist for a family of generalized Poisson distributions. Numerical results demonstrate the accuracy of our and of previously derived bounds for $\Sinf$ and $\Sn$. Finally, we treat an application of these results to determine the response of a quantitative trait to prolonged directional selection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21403v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reinhard B\"urger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral independence of almost fully correlated random matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the joint spectral properties of two coupled random matrices $H^{(1)}$ and $H^{(2)}$, which are either real symmetric or complex Hermitian. The entries of these matrices exhibit polynomially decaying correlations, both within each matrix and between them. Surprisingly, we find that under extremely weak decorrelation condition, permitting $H^{(1)}$ and $H^{(2)}$ to be almost fully correlated, the fluctuations of their individual eigenvalues in the bulk of the spectrum are still asymptotically independent. Furthermore, we demonstrate that this decorrelation condition is optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21472v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksii Kolupaiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean field stochastic differential equations with a diffusion coefficient with irregular distributional dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study mean field stochastic differential equations with a diffusion coefficient that depends on the distribution function of the unknown process in a discontinuous manner, which is a type of distribution dependent regime switching. To determine the distribution function we show that under certain conditions these equations can be transformed into SDEs with deterministic coefficients using a Lamperti-type transformation. We prove an existence and uniqueness result and consider cases when the uniqueness may fail or a solution exists only for a finite time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21475v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jani Nyk\"anen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of a Stochastic Particle System to the Continuous Generalized Exchange-Driven Growth Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The continuous generalized exchange-driven growth model (CGEDG) is a system of integro-differential equations describing the evolution of cluster mass under mass exchange. The rate of exchange depends on the masses of the clusters involved and the mass being exchanged. This can be viewed as both a continuous generalization of the exchange-driven growth model and a coagulation-fragmentation equation that generalizes the continuous Smoluchowski equation.
  Starting from a Markov jump process that describes a finite stochastic interacting particle system with exchange dynamics, we prove the weak law of large numbers for this process for sublinearly growing kernels in the mean-field limit. We establish the tightness of the stochastic process on a measure-valued Skorokhod space induced by the $1$-Wasserstein metric, from which we deduce the existence of solutions to the (CGEDG) system. The solution is shown to have a Lebesgue density under suitable assumptions on the initial data. Moreover, within the class of solutions with density, we establish the uniqueness under slightly more restrictive conditions on the kernel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21572v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Yin Lam, Andr\'e Schlichting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Measures and Strong Laws of Large Numbers in Categorical Probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Glivenko-Cantelli theorem is a uniform version of the strong law of large numbers. It states that for every IID sequence of random variables, the empirical measure converges to the underlying distribution (in the sense of uniform convergence of the CDF). In this work, we provide tools to study such limits of empirical measures in categorical probability.
  We propose two axioms, permutation invariance and empirical adequacy, that a morphism of type $X^\mathbb{N} \to X$ should satisfy to be interpretable as taking an infinite sequence as input and producing a sample from its empirical measure as output. Since not all sequences have a well-defined empirical measure, ``such empirical sampling morphisms'' live in quasi-Markov categories, which, unlike Markov categories, allow partial morphisms. Given an empirical sampling morphism and a few other properties, we prove representability as well as abstract versions of the de Finetti theorem, the Glivenko-Cantelli theorem and the strong law of large numbers.
  We provide several concrete constructions of empirical sampling morphisms as partially defined Markov kernels on standard Borel spaces. Instantiating our abstract results then recovers the standard Glivenko-Cantelli theorem and the strong law of large numbers for random variables with finite first moment. Our work thus provides a joint proof of these two theorems in conjunction with the de Finetti theorem from first principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21576v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Fritz, Tom\'a\v{s} Gonda, Antonio Lorenzin, Paolo Perrone, Areeb Shah Mohammed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong convergence and stability of stochastic theta method for time-changed stochastic differential equations with local Lipschitz coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, the stochastic theta (ST) method is investigated for a class of stochastic differential equations driven by a time-changed Brownian motion, whose coefficients are time-space-dependent and satisfy the local Lipschitz condition. It is proved that under the local Lipschitz and some additional assumptions, the ST method with $\theta\in[1/2,1]$ is strongly convergent. It is also obtained that, for all positive stepsizes, the ST method with $\theta\in[1/2,1]$ is asymptotically mean square stable under a coercivity condition. With some restrictions on the stepsize, the ST method with $\theta\in[0,1/2)$ is asymptotically mean square stable under a stronger assumption. Some numerical simulations are presented to illustrate the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21653v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingwei Chen, Jun Ye, Jinwen Chen, Zhidong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-intensity Voronoi percolation on manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Voronoi percolation on a large class of $d$-dimensional Riemannian manifolds, which includes hyperbolic space $\mathbb{H}^d$ for $d\geq 2$. We prove that as the intensity $\lambda$ of the underlying Poisson point process tends to infinity, both critical parameters $p_c(M,\lambda)$ and $p_u(M,\lambda)$ converge to the Euclidean critical parameter $p_c(\mathbb{R}^d)$. This extends a recent result of Hansen &amp; M\"uller in the special case $M=\mathbb{H}^2$ to a general class of manifolds of arbitrary dimension. A crucial step in our proof, which may be of independent interest, is to show that if $M$ is simply connected and one-ended, then embedded graphs induced by a general class of tessellations on $M$ have connected minimal cutsets. In particular, this result applies to $\varepsilon$-nets, allowing us to implement a "fine-graining" argument. We also develop an annealed way of exploring the Voronoi cells that we use to characterize the uniqueness phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21737v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tillmann B\"uhler, Barbara Dembin, Ritvik Ramanan Radhakrishnan, Franco Severo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Results on branching random walks and rumor processes via germ order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Germ order is a non-standard stochastic order defined through the comparison of the generating functions of the processes. This order was first introduced for branching random walks with a constant breeding law and independent dispersal of offspring, which are characterized by a one-dimensional generating function. In this work, we investigate the properties of the extension of this concept to processes characterized by a multidimensional generating function, such as general branching random walks and rumor processes. In particular, we use germ ordering to characterize the behavior of certain branching random walks and rumor processes with inhomogeneous breeding/transmitting laws.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21768v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniela Bertacchi, Fabio Zucca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Errico Presutti 1942-2024</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20795v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Errico Presutti was a leading figure in mathematical physics and an important contributor to rigorous results in statistical mechanics. Due to his strong scientific personality and human qualities, there are many who remember Errico Presutti as colleague, mentor, and friend.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20795v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Bertini, Joel L. Lebowitz, Mario Pulvirenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Behaviors of Besov Seminorms for Dunkl Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As $s\rightarrow0^+$, we establish limiting formulas of Besov seminorms and nonlocal perimeters associated with the Dunkl operator, a (nonlocal) differential-difference operator parameterized by multiplicity functions and finite reflection groups. Our results are further developments of both the Maz'ya--Shaposhnikova limiting formula for the Gagliardo seminorm and the asymptotic behavior of the (relative) fractional $s$-perimeter. The main contribution is twofold. On the one hand, to establish our dimension-free Maz'ya--Shaposhnikova limiting formula, we develop a simplified approach which do not depend on the density property of the corresponding Besov space and turns out to be quite robust. On the other hand, to derive the limiting formula of our nonlocal perimeter, we do not demand additional regularity on the (topological) boundary of the domain, and to obtain the converse assertion, our assumption on the boundary regularity of the domain, which allows for fractals, is much weaker than those in existing literatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20809v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaiqian Li, Bingyao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teachable normal approximations to binomial and related probabilities or confidence bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This document is an extended version of an abstract for a talk, with approximately the same title, to be held at the 7th Joint Statistical Meeting of the Deutsche Arbeitsgemeinschaft Statistik, from 24 to 28 March 2025 in Berlin.
  Here ``teachable'' is meant to apply to people ranging from sufficiently advanced high school pupils to university students in mathematics or statistics: For understanding most of the proposed approximation results, it should suffice to know binomial laws, their means and variances, and the standard normal distribution function (but not necessarily the concept of a corresponding normal random variable).
  Of the proposed approximations, some are well-known (at least to experts), and some are based on teaching experience and research at Trier University.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20852v1</guid>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lutz Mattner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Least Squares as Random Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear least squares (LLS) is perhaps the most common method of data analysis, dating back to Legendre, Gauss and Laplace. Framed as linear regression, LLS is also a backbone of mathematical statistics. Here we report on an unexpected new connection between LLS and random walks. To that end, we introduce the notion of a random walk based on a discrete sequence of data samples (data walk). We show that the slope of a straight line which annuls the net area under a residual data walk equals the one found by LLS. For equidistant data samples this result is exact and holds for an arbitrary distribution of steps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20965v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kostinski, Glenn Ierley, Sarah Kostinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Learning for Entropy-regularized Markov Decision Processes via Multilevel Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Designing efficient learning algorithms with complexity guarantees for Markov decision processes (MDPs) with large or continuous state and action spaces remains a fundamental challenge. We address this challenge for entropy-regularized MDPs with Polish state and action spaces, assuming access to a generative model of the environment. We propose a novel family of multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC) algorithms that integrate fixed-point iteration with MLMC techniques and a generic stochastic approximation of the Bellman operator. We quantify the precise impact of the chosen approximate Bellman operator on the accuracy of the resulting MLMC estimator. Leveraging this error analysis, we show that using a biased plain MC estimate for the Bellman operator results in quasi-polynomial sample complexity, whereas an unbiased randomized multilevel approximation of the Bellman operator achieves polynomial sample complexity in expectation. Notably, these complexity bounds are independent of the dimensions or cardinalities of the state and action spaces, distinguishing our approach from existing algorithms whose complexities scale with the sizes of these spaces. We validate these theoretical performance guarantees through numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21224v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Meunier, Christoph Reisinger, Yufei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Asset Pricing Theory for Life Contingent Risks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21256v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Although the valuation of life contingent assets has been thoroughly investigated under the framework of mathematical statistics, little financial economics research pays attention to the pricing of these assets in a non-arbitrage, complete market. In this paper, we first revisit the Fundamental Theorem of Asset Pricing (FTAP) and the short proof of it. Then we point out that discounted asset price is a martingale only when dividends are zero under all random states of the world, using a simple proof based on pricing kernel. Next, we apply Fundamental Theorem of Asset Pricing (FTAP) to find valuation formula for life contingent assets including life insurance policies and life contingent annuities. Last but not least, we state the assumption of static portfolio in a dynamic economy, and clarify the FTAP that accommodates the valuation of a portfolio of life contingent policies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21256v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Ling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of stochastic orders and statistical dependence in error analysis for multi-component system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21275v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze the relative errors that crop up in the various reliability measures due to the tacit assumption that the components are independently working associated with a $n$-component series system or a parallel system where the components are dependent and follow a well-defined multivariate Weibull or exponential distribution. We also list some important observations which the previous authors have not noted in their earlier works. In this paper, we focus on the incurred error in multi-component series and parallel systems having multivariate Weibull distributions. In the upcoming sections, we establish that the present study has relevance with stochastic orders and statistical dependence which were not previously pointed out by previous authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21275v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subarna Bhattacharjee, Aninda Kumar Nanda, Subhashree Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of copula functions in error assessment due to deviation from dependence assumption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze the relative errors in various reliability measures due to the tacit assumption that the components associated with a $n$-component series system or a parallel system are independently working where the components are dependent. We use Copula functions in said error analysis. This technique generalizes the existing work on error assessment for many wide class of distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21286v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subarna Bhattacharjee, Aninda Kumar Nanda, Subhashree Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference in stochastic differential equations using the Laplace approximation: Demonstration and examples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21358v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of estimating states and parameters in a model based on a system of coupled stochastic differential equations, based on noisy discrete-time data. Special attention is given to nonlinear dynamics and state-dependent diffusivity, where transition densities are not available in closed form. Our technique adds states between times of observations, approximates transition densities using, e.g., the Euler-Maruyama method and eliminates unobserved states using the Laplace approximation. Using case studies, we demonstrate that transition probabilities are well approximated, and that inference is computationally feasible. We discuss limitations and potential extensions of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21358v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uffe H{\o}gsbro Thygesen, Kasper Kristensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Mean Estimation for Optimization: The Impact of Heavy Tails</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of constructing a least conservative estimator of the expected value $\mu$ of a non-negative heavy-tailed random variable. We require that the probability of overestimating the expected value $\mu$ is kept appropriately small; a natural requirement if its subsequent use in a decision process is anticipated. In this setting, we show it is optimal to estimate $\mu$ by solving a distributionally robust optimization (DRO) problem using the Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence. We further show that the statistical properties of KL-DRO compare favorably with other estimators based on truncation, variance regularization, or Wasserstein DRO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21421v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bart P. G. van Parys, Bert Zwart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Bayesian Learning for Label Efficiency in Cardiac Real-Time MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cardiac real-time magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is an emerging technology that images the heart at up to 50 frames per second, offering insight into the respiratory effects on the heartbeat. However, this method significantly increases the number of images that must be segmented to derive critical health indicators. Although neural networks perform well on inner slices, predictions on outer slices are often unreliable.
  This work proposes sparse Bayesian learning (SBL) to predict the ventricular volume on outer slices with minimal manual labeling to address this challenge. The ventricular volume over time is assumed to be dominated by sparse frequencies corresponding to the heart and respiratory rates. Moreover, SBL identifies these sparse frequencies on well-segmented inner slices by optimizing hyperparameters via type -II likelihood, automatically pruning irrelevant components. The identified sparse frequencies guide the selection of outer slice images for labeling, minimizing posterior variance.
  This work provides performance guarantees for the greedy algorithm. Testing on patient data demonstrates that only a few labeled images are necessary for accurate volume prediction. The labeling procedure effectively avoids selecting inefficient images. Furthermore, the Bayesian approach provides uncertainty estimates, highlighting unreliable predictions (e.g., when choosing suboptimal labels).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21443v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Terhag, Philipp Knechtges, Achim Basermann, Anja Bach, Darius Gerlach, Jens Tank, Ra\'ul Tempone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasserstein bounds for non-linear Gaussian filters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21643v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Most Kalman filters for non-linear systems, such as the unscented Kalman filter, are based on Gaussian approximations. We use Poincar\'e inequalities to bound the Wasserstein distance between the true joint distribution of the prediction and measurement and its Gaussian approximation. The bounds can be used to assess the performance of non-linear Gaussian filters and determine those filtering approximations that are most likely to induce error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21643v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toni Karvonen, Simo S\"arkk\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-point correlation functions in the $\mathfrak{sl}_3$ Toda theory I: Reflection coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.06902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.06902v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Toda Conformal Field Theories (CFTs) form a family of 2d CFTs indexed by semisimple and complex Lie algebras. They are natural generalizations of the Liouville CFT in that they enjoy an enhanced level of symmetry encoded by W-algebras. These theories can be rigorously defined using a probabilistic framework that involves the consideration of correlated Gaussian Multiplicative Chaos measures.
  This document provides a first step towards the computation of a class of three-point correlation functions, that generalize the celebrated DOZZ formula and whose expressions were predicted in the physics literature by Fateev-Litvinov, within the probabilistic framework associated to the $\mathfrak{sl}_3$ Toda CFT. Namely this first article of a two-parts series is dedicated to the probabilistic derivation of the reflection coefficients of general Toda CFTs, which are essential building blocks in the understanding of Toda correlation functions.
  Along the computations of these reflection coefficients a new path decomposition for diffusion processes in Euclidean spaces, based on a suitable notion of minimum and that generalizes the celebrated one-dimensional result of Williams, will be unveiled. As a byproduct we describe the joint tail expansion of correlated Gaussian Multiplicative Chaos measures together with an asymptotic expansion of class one Whittaker functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.06902v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Cercl\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic epidemic models with varying infectivity and waning immunity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.04667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.04667v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study an individual-based stochastic epidemic model in which infected individuals become susceptible again following each infection. In contrast to classical compartment models, after each infection, the infectivity is a random function of the time elapsed since one's infection. Similarly, recovered individuals become gradually susceptible after some time according to a random susceptibility function. We study the large population asymptotic behaviour of the model, by proving a functional law of large numbers (FLLN) and investigating the endemic equilibria properties of the limit. The limit depends on the law of the susceptibility random functions but only on the mean infectivity functions. The FLLN is proved by constructing a sequence of i.i.d. auxiliary processes and adapting the approach from the theory of propagation of chaos. The limit is a generalisation of a PDE model introduced by Kermack and McKendrick, and we show how this PDE model can be obtained as a special case of our FLLN limit.% for a particular set of infectivity and susceptibility random functions and initial conditions. For the endemic equilibria, if $ R_0 $ is lower than (or equal to) some threshold, the epidemic does not last forever and eventually disappears from the population, while if $ R_0 $ is larger than this threshold, the epidemic will not disappear and there exists an endemic equilibrium. The value of this threshold turns out to depend on the harmonic mean of the susceptibility a long time after an infection, a fact which was not previously known.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.04667v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rapha\"el Forien, Guodong Pang, \'Etienne Pardoux, Arsene Brice Zotsa--Ngoufack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemic models with digital and manual contact tracing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12869v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze a Markovian SIR epidemic model where individuals either recover naturally or are diagnosed, leading to isolation and potential contact tracing. Our focus is on digital contact tracing via a tracing app, considering both its standalone use and combination with manual tracing. We prove that as the population size $n$ grows large, the epidemic process converges to a limiting process, which, unlike typical epidemic models, is not a branching process due to dependencies created by contact tracing. However, by grouping to-be-traced individuals into macro-individuals, we derive a multi-type branching process interpretation, allowing computation of the reproduction number $R$. This is then converted to an individual reproduction number $R^{(ind)}$, which, contrary to $R$, decays monotonically with the fraction of app-users while both share the same threshold at 1. Finally, we compare digital (only) contact tracing and manual (only) contact tracing, proving that the critical fraction app-users $\pi_c$ required for $R=1$ is higher than the critical fraction manually contact traced $p_c$ for manual tracing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12869v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Britton, Dongni Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher equations of motion for boundary Liouville Conformal Field Theory from the Ward identities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13271v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this document we prove higher equations of motion at the level 2 for boundary Liouville Conformal Field Theory. As a corollary we present a new derivation of the Belavin-Polyakov-Zamolodchikov differential equations. Our method of proof does not rely on the mating of trees machinery but rather exploits the symmetries of the model through the Ward identities it satisfies.
  To do so we provide a definition of derivatives of the correlation functions with respect to a boundary insertion which was lacking in the existing literature, and introduce a new notion of descendant fields related to these Ward identities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13271v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Cercl\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularization by rough Kraichnan noise for the generalised SQG equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12181v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the generalised Surface Quasi-Geostrophic (gSQG) equations in $\mathbb R^2$ with parameter $\beta\in (0,1)$, an active scalar model interpolating between SQG ($\beta=1$) and the 2D Euler equations ($\beta=0$) in vorticity form. Existence of weak $(L^1\cap L^p)$-valued solutions in the deterministic setting is known, but their uniqueness is open. We show that the addition of a rough Stratonovich transport noise of Kraichnan type regularizes the PDE, providing strong existence and pathwise uniqueness of solutions for initial data $\theta_0\in L^1\cap L^p$, for suitable values $p\in[2,\infty]$ related to the regularity degree $\alpha$ of the noise and the singularity degree $\beta$ of the velocity field; in particular, we can cover any $\beta\in (0,1)$ for suitable $\alpha$ and $p$ and we can reach a suitable ("critical") threshold. The result also holds in the presence of external forcing $f\in L^1_t (L^1\cap L^p)$ and solutions are shown to depend continuously on the data of the problem; furthermore, they are well approximated by vanishing viscosity and regular approximations. With similar techniques, we also show well-posedness for two-dimensional linear transport equation with random drift, with the same noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12181v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Bagnara, Lucio Galeati, Mario Maurelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average-case matrix discrepancy: satisfiability bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17887v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a sequence of $d \times d$ symmetric matrices $\{\mathbf{W}_i\}_{i=1}^n$, and a margin $\Delta &gt; 0$, we investigate whether it is possible to find signs $(\epsilon_1, \dots, \epsilon_n) \in \{\pm 1\}^n$ such that the operator norm of the signed sum satisfies $\|\sum_{i=1}^n \epsilon_i \mathbf{W}_i\|_{\rm op} \leq \Delta$. Kunisky and Zhang (2023) recently introduced a random version of this problem, where the matrices $\{\mathbf{W}_i\}_{i=1}^n$ are drawn from the Gaussian orthogonal ensemble. This model can be seen as a random variant of the celebrated Matrix Spencer conjecture and as a matrix-valued analog of the symmetric binary perceptron in statistical physics. In this work, we establish a satisfiability transition in this problem as $n, d \to \infty$ with $n / d^2 \to \tau &gt; 0$. First, we prove that the expected number of solutions with margin $\Delta=\kappa \sqrt{n}$ has a sharp threshold at a critical $\tau_1(\kappa)$: for $\tau &lt; \tau_1(\kappa)$ the problem is typically unsatisfiable, while for $\tau &gt; \tau_1(\kappa)$ the average number of solutions is exponentially large. Second, combining a second-moment method with recent results from Altschuler (2023) on margin concentration in perceptron-type problems, we identify a second threshold $\tau_2(\kappa)$, such that for $\tau&gt;\tau_2(\kappa)$ the problem admits solutions with high probability. In particular, we establish that a system of $n = \Theta(d^2)$ Gaussian random matrices can be balanced so that the spectrum of the resulting matrix macroscopically shrinks compared to the semicircle law. Finally, under a technical assumption, we show that there exists values of $(\tau,\kappa)$ for which the number of solutions has large variance, implying the failure of the second moment method. Our proofs rely on establishing concentration and large deviation properties of correlated Gaussian matrices under spectral norm constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17887v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Maillard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral distribution of the free Jacobi process with equal rank projections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07552v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The free Jacobi process is the radial part of the compression of the free unitary Brownian motion by two free orthogonal projections in a non commutative probability space. In this paper, we derive spectral properties of the free Jacobi process associated with projections having the same rank $\alpha \in (0,1)$. To start with, we determine the characteristic curves of the partial differential equation satisfied by the moment generating function of its spectral distribution. Doing so leads for any fixed time $t &gt;0$ to an expression of this function in a neighborhood of the origin, therefore extends our previous results valid for $\alpha = 1/2$. Moreover, the obtained characteristic curves are encoded by an $\alpha$-deformation of the compositional inverse of the $\chi$-transform of the spectral distribution of the free unitary Brownian motion. In this respect, we study mapping properties of this deformation and use the saddle point method to prove that the compositional inverse of a $\alpha$-deformation of the $\chi$-transform of the free unitary Brownian motion is analytic in the open unit disc (for large enough time $t$). The last part of the paper is devoted to a dynamical version of a recent identity pointed out by T. Kunisky in \cite{Kun}. Actually, this identity relates the stationary distributions of the free Jacobi processes corresponding to the sets of parameters $(\alpha, \alpha)$ and $(1/2,\alpha)$ respectively and we explain how it follows from the Nica-Speicher semi-group. Our dynamical version then relates the partial differential equations of the Cauchy-Stieltjes transforms of the densities of the finite-time spectral distributions. It also raises the problem of whether a dynamical analogue of the Nica-Speicher semi-group exists when the compressing projection has rank $1/2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07552v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nizar Demni, Tarek Hamdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy of Random Geometric Graphs in High and Low Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11418v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use a multivariate central limit theorem (CLT) to study the distribution of random geometric graphs (RGGs) on the cube and torus in the high-dimensional limit with general node distributions. We find that the distribution of RGGs on the torus converges to the Erd\H os-Reny\' i (ER) ensemble when the nodes are uniformly distributed, but that the distribution for RGGs with non-uniformly distributed nodes on the torus, and for RGGs with any distribution of nodes with kurtosis greater than 1 on the cube is different. In these cases, the distribution has a lower maximum entropy, but is still symmetric. Soft RGGs in either geometry converge to the ER ensemble. An Edgeworth correction to the CLT is then developed to derive the $\bigO{d^{-\frac{1}{2}}}$ scaling of Shannon entropy of RGGs in dimension for both geometries. We also provide numerical approximations of maximum entropy in low-dimensional hard and soft RGGs, and calculate exactly the entropy of hard RGGs with 3 nodes in the one-dimensional cube and torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11418v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Baker, Carl P. Dettmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LQG Risk-Sensitive Single-Agent and Major-Minor Mean-Field Game Systems: A Variational Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.15364v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a variational approach to address risk-sensitive optimal control problems with an exponential-of-integral cost functional in a general linear-quadratic-Gaussian (LQG) single-agent setup, offering new insights into such problems. Our analysis leads to the derivation of a nonlinear necessary and sufficient condition of optimality, expressed in terms of martingale processes. Subject to specific conditions, we find an equivalent risk-neutral measure, under which a linear state feedback form can be obtained for the optimal control. It is then shown that the obtained feedback control is consistent with the imposed condition and remains optimal under the original measure. Building upon this development, we (i) propose a variational framework for general LQG risk-sensitive mean-field games (MFGs) and (ii) advance the LQG risk-sensitive MFG theory by incorporating a major agent in the framework. The major agent interacts with a large number of minor agents, and unlike the minor agents, its influence on the system remains significant even with an increasing number of minor agents. We derive the Markovian closed-loop best-response strategies of agents in the limiting case where the number of agents goes to infinity. We establish that the set of obtained best-response strategies yields a Nash equilibrium in the limiting case and an $\varepsilon$-Nash equilibrium in the finite-player case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.15364v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanchao Liu, Dena Firoozi, Mich\`ele Breton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic curvature not comparable to other curvatures -- or is it?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04581v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we consider global $\theta$-curvatures of finite Markov chains with associated means $\theta$ in the spirit of the entropic curvature (based on the logarithmic mean) by Erbar-Maas and Mielke. As in the case of Bakry-\'Emery curvature, we also allow for a finite dimension parameter by making use of an adapted $\Gamma$ calculus for $\theta$-curvatures. We prove explicit positive lower curvature bounds (both finite- and infinite-dimensional) for finite abelian Cayley graphs. In the case of cycles, we provide also an upper curvature bound which shows that our lower bounds are asymptotically sharp (up to a logarithmic factor). Moreover, we prove new universal lower curvature bounds for finite Markov chains as well as curvature perturbation results (allowing, in particular, to compare entropic and Bakry-\'Emery curvatures). Finally, we present examples where entropic curvature differs significantly from other curvature notions like Bakry-\'Emery curvature or Ollivier Ricci and sectional curvatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04581v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Supanat Kamtue, Shiping Liu, Florentin M\"unch, Norbert Peyerimhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed radix numeration bases: Horner's rule, Yang-Baxter equation and Furstenberg's conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19798v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mixed radix bases in numeration is a very old notion but it is rarely studied on its own or in relation with concrete problems related to number theory. Starting from the natural question of the conversion of a basis to another for integers as well as polynomials, we use mixed radix bases to introduce two-dimensional arrays with suitable filling rules. These arrays provide algorithms of conversion which uses only a finite number of euclidean division to convert from one basis to another; it is interesting to note that these algorithms are generalizations of the well-known Horner's rule of quick evaluation of polynomials. The two-dimensional arrays with local transformations are reminiscent from statistical mechanics models: we show that changes between three numeration basis are related to the set-theoretical Yang-Baxter equation and this is, up to our knowledge, the first time that such a structure is described in number theory. As an illustration, we reinterpret well-known results around Furstenberg's conjecture in terms of Yang-Baxter transformations between mixed radix bases, hence opening the way to alternative approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19798v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damien Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditional uncorrelation equals independence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01849v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We express the independence of real-valued random variables in terms of the conditional uncorrelation, where the conditioning takes place over the cartesian products of intervals. Next, we express the mutual independence in terms of the conditional correlation matrix. While the previous studies on the subject are based on the copula functions, our approach uses the Radon-Nikodym derivative to reduce the general problem to the simple one-dimensional conditioning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01849v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dawid Tar{\l}owski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sideward contact tracing in an epidemic model with mixing groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11622v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a stochastic epidemic model with sideward contact tracing. We assume that infection is driven by interactions within mixing events (gatherings of two or more individuals). Once an infective is diagnosed, each individual who was infected at the same event as the diagnosed individual is contact traced with some given probability. Assuming few initial infectives in a large population, the early phase of the epidemic is approximated by a branching process with sibling dependencies. To address the challenges given by the dependencies, we consider sibling groups (individuals who become infected at the same event) as macro-individuals and define a macro-branching process. This allows us to derive an expression for the effective macro-reproduction number which corresponds to the effective individual reproduction number and represents a threshold for the behaviour of the epidemic. Through numerical examples, we show how the reproduction number varies with the distribution of the mixing event size, the mean size, the rate of diagnosis and the tracing probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11622v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongni Zhang, Martina Favero</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
