<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.PR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR</link>
    <description>math.PR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.PR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 01:39:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On a spherically lifted spin model at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate an \(n\)-vector model over \(k\) sites with generic pairwise interactions and spherical constraints. The model is a lifting of the Ising model whereby the support of the spin is lifted to a hypersphere. We show that the \(n\)-vector model converges to a limiting distribution at a rate of \(n^{-1/2 + o(1)}\). We show that the limiting distribution for \(n \to \infty\) is determined by the solution of an equality-constrained maximization task over positive definite matrices. We prove that the obtained maximal value and maximizer, respectively, give rise to the free energy and correlation function of the limiting distribution. In the finite temperature regime, the maximization task is a log-determinant regularization of the semidefinite program (SDP) in the Goemans-Williamson algorithm. Moreover, the inverse temperature determines the regularization strength, with the zero temperature limit converging to the SDP in Goemans-Williamson. Our derivation draws a curious connection between the semidefinite relaxation of integer programming and the spherical lifting of sampling on a hypercube. To the authors' best knowledge, this work is the first to solve the setting of fixed \(k\) and infinite \(n\) under unstructured pairwise interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02220v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xun Tang, Yuehaw Khoo, Lexing Ying</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Discontinuous Breaking of Replica Symmetry and Shattering in Mean-Field Spin Glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that in mean-field spin glasses, a discontinuous breaking of replica symmetry at the critical inverse temperature $\beta_c$ implies the existence of an intermediate shattered phase. This confirms a prediction from physics regarding the nature of random first order phase transitions. On the other hand, we give an example of a spherical spin glass which exhibits shattering, yet the transition is continuous at $\beta_c$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02238v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Auffinger, Ahmed El Alaoui, Mark Sellke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the shape of the typical Poisson-Voronoi cell in high dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the typical cell of the Poisson-Voronoi tessellation. We show that when divided by the $d$-th root of the intensity parameter $\lambda$ of the Poisson process times the volume of the unit ball, the inradius, outradius, diameter and mean width of the typical cell converge in probability to the constants $1/2, 1, 2, 2$ respectively, as the dimension $d\to\infty$. We also show that the width of the typical cell, when rescaled in the same way, is bounded between $2\sqrt{5}/(2+\sqrt{5})-o_d(1)$ and $3/2+o_d(1)$, with probability $1-o_d(1)$. These results in particular imply that, with probability $1-o_d(1)$, the Hausdorff distance between the typical cell and any ball is at least of the order of the diameter of the typical cell.
  In addition, we show that for all $k$ with $d-k\to\infty$, with probability $1-o_d(1)$, all faces of dimension $k$ have a diameter that is of a much smaller order than the diameter, inradius, etc., of the full typical cell. The same is true for ''almost all'' faces of dimension $d-k$ with $k$ fixed. And, we show that the number of such faces is $\left( (k+1)^{(k+1)/2} / k^{k/2} \pm o_d(1) \right)^d$ with probability $1-o_d(1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02607v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Irlbeck, Zakhar Kabluchko, Tobias M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The tight length spectrum of large-genus random hyperbolic surfaces with many cusps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Since the work of Mirzakhani \&amp; Petri \cite{Mirzakhani_petri_2019} on random hyperbolic surfaces of large genus, length statistics of closed geodesics have been studied extensively. We focus on the case of random hyperbolic surfaces with cusps, the number $n_g$ of which grows with the genus $g$. We prove that if $n_g$ grows fast enough and we restrict attention to special geodesics that are \emph{tight}, we recover upon proper normalization the same Poisson point process in the large-$g$ limit for the length statistics. The proof relies on a recursion formula for tight Weil-Petersson volumes obtained in \cite{budd2023topological} and on a generalization of Mirzakhani's integration formula to the tight setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02611v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy Budd, Tanguy Lions</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A central limit theorem for the stochastic cable equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider one-dimensional nonlinear stochastic cable equations driven by a multiplicative space-time white noise. Using the Malliavin--Stein's method, we prove the Gaussian fluctuation for the spatial average of the solution under the total variation distance with mild conditions. We also establish functional central limit theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02755v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soma Nishino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the rate of convergence in the CLT for LSS of large-dimensional sample covariance matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02880v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the rate of convergence for the central limit theorem of linear spectral statistic (LSS) associated with large-dimensional sample covariance matrices. We consider matrices of the form ${\mathbf B}_n=\frac{1}{n}{\mathbf T}_p^{1/2}{\mathbf X}_n{\mathbf X}_n^*{\mathbf T}_p^{1/2},$ where ${\mathbf X}_n= (x_{i j} ) $ is a $p \times n$ matrix whose entries are independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) real or complex variables, and ${\mathbf T} _p$ is a $p\times p$ nonrandom Hermitian nonnegative definite matrix with its spectral norm uniformly bounded in $p$. Employing Stein's method, we establish that if the entries $x_{ij}$ satisfy $\mathbb{E}|x_{ij}|^{10}&lt;\infty$ and the ratio of the dimension to sample size $p/n\to y&gt;0$ as $n\to\infty$, then the convergence rate of the normalized LSS of ${\mathbf B}_n$ to the standard normal distribution, measured in the Kolmogorov-Smirnov distance, is $O(n^{-1/2+\kappa})$ for any fixed $\kappa&gt;0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02880v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Cui, Jiang Hu, Zhidong Bai, Guorong Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Merryfield's inequality for multiparameter martingales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend an inequality of Merryfield, valid in the continuous setting, to discrete multiparameter martingales.
  As a consequence, we obtain the $L^p$ comparison of the maximal function with the square function:
  \begin{align*}
  E[(Sf)^p] \lesssim E[(f^*)^p]
  \end{align*}
  for regular multiparameter filtrations and $0 &lt; p &lt; \infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02974v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Rey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded Discrete Bridges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2010 Banderier and Nicodeme consider the height of bounded discrete bridges and conclude to a limiting Rayleigh distribution. This result is correct although their proof is partly erroneous. They make asymptotic simplifications based upon dominance properties of the roots of the kernel of the walk within a disk centered at the origin, but these dominance properties apply only upon a positive real segment. However the very good agreement of simulations with their asymptotic expansion of the probability distribution in case of {\L}ukasiewicz bridges let us think that their proof could be corrected. This is the scope of the present article which provides
  a proof using the dominance property only in its domain of validity. We also consider the case of periodic walks, a topic not considered in Banderier-Nicodeme2010. We limit ourselves to walks whose characteristic polynomial decomposes over $\bC$ without repeated factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02982v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Nicodeme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Probabilistic Learning on Manifolds through Double Diffusion Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a generative learning framework for probabilistic sampling based on an extension of the Probabilistic Learning on Manifolds (PLoM) approach, which is designed to generate statistically consistent realizations of a random vector in a finite-dimensional Euclidean space, informed by a limited (yet representative) set of observations. In its original form, PLoM constructs a reduced-order probabilistic model by combining three main components: (a) kernel density estimation to approximate the underlying probability measure, (b) Diffusion Maps to uncover the intrinsic low-dimensional manifold structure, and (c) a reduced-order Ito Stochastic Differential Equation (ISDE) to sample from the learned distribution. A key challenge arises, however, when the number of available data points N is small and the dimensionality of the diffusion-map basis approaches N, resulting in overfitting and loss of generalization. To overcome this limitation, we propose an enabling extension that implements a synthesis of Double Diffusion Maps -- a technique capable of capturing multiscale geometric features of the data -- with Geometric Harmonics (GH), a nonparametric reconstruction method that allows smooth nonlinear interpolation in high-dimensional ambient spaces. This approach enables us to solve a full-order ISDE directly in the latent space, preserving the full dynamical complexity of the system, while leveraging its reduced geometric representation. The effectiveness and robustness of the proposed method are illustrated through two numerical studies: one based on data generated from two-dimensional Hermite polynomial functions and another based on high-fidelity simulations of a detonation wave in a reactive flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02254v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitris G Giovanis, Nikolaos Evangelou, Ioannis G Kevrekidis, Roger G Ghanem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A General Approach to the Shape Transition of Run-and-Tumble Particles: The 1D PDMP Framework for Invariant Measure Regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Run-and-tumble particles (RTPs) have emerged as a paradigmatic example for studying nonequilibrium phenomena in statistical mechanics. The invariant measure of a wide class of RTPs subjected to a potential possesses a density, which is continuous when tumble rates are high and discontinuous when they are low. This key feature is known as shape transition. By comparison with the Boltzmann distribution characteristic of thermodynamic equilibrium, this constitutes a qualitative indicator of the relative closeness (continuous density) or strong deviation (discontinuous density) from the equilibrium setting. Furthermore, the points where the density diverges represent typical states where the system spends most of its time in the low tumble rate regime. Building on and extending existing results concerning the regularity of the invariant measure of one-dimensional piecewise-deterministic Markov processes (PDMPs), we show how to characterize the shape transition even in situations where the invariant measure cannot be computed explicitly. Our analysis confirms shape transition as a robust, general feature of RTPs subjected to a potential. We improve the qualitative picture of the degree to which general RTPs deviate from equilibrium and identify their typical states in the low tumble rate regime. We also refine the regularity theory for the invariant measure of one-dimensional PDMPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02274v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leo Hahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizations of Erd\H{o}s-Kac theorem with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\omega(n)$ denote the number of distinct prime factors of a natural number $n$. In 1940, Erd\H{o}s and Kac established that $\omega(n)$ obeys the Gaussian distribution over natural numbers, and in 2004, the third author generalized their theorem to all abelian monoids. In this paper, we extend her theorem to any subsets of an abelian monoid satisfying some additional conditions, and apply this result to the subsets of $h$-free and $h$-full elements. We study generalizations of several arithmetic functions, such as the prime counting omega functions and the divisor function in a unified framework. Finally, we apply our results to number fields, global function fields, and geometrically irreducible projective varieties, demonstrating the broad relevance of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02432v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourabhashis Das, Wentang Kuo, Yu-Ru Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Khintchine inequalities, trace monoids and Tur\'an-type problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove scalar and operator-valued Khintchine inequalities for mixtures of free and tensor-independent semicircle variables, interpolating between classical and free Khintchine-type inequalities. Specifically, we characterize the norm of sums of $G$-independent semicircle variables in terms of the spectral radius of the Cayley graph associated with the trace monoid determined by the graph $G$. Our approach relies on a precise correspondence between closed paths in trace monoids and the norms of such operator sums. This correspondence uncovers connections between non-commutative probability, combinatorial group theory, and extremal graph theory. In particular, we formulate Tur\'an-type extremal problems that govern maximal norm growth under classical commutation constraints, and identify the extremal configurations. We hope that the methods and connections developed here will be useful in the study of non-commutative structures constrained by combinatorial symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02517v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Oliveira Santos, Raghavendra Tripathi, Pierre Youssef</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-exchangeable evolutionary and mean field games and their applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02644v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A replicator dynamic for non-exchangeable agents in a continuous action space is formulated and its well-posedness is proven in a space of probability measures. The non-exchangeability allows for the analysis of evolutionary games involving agents with distinct (and possibly infinitely many) types. We also explicitly connect this replicator dynamic to a stationary mean field game, which determines the pairwise actions of the heterogeneous agents. Moreover, as a byproduct of our theoretical results, we show that a class of nonlinear voter models, recently the subject of increasing interest, called q-voter models, can be viewed as a replicator dynamic driven by a utility that is a power of the probability density. This implies that non-exchangeable and/or mean-field game formulations of these models can also be constructed. We also present computational examples of evolutionary and mean field game models using a finite difference method, focusing on tragedy of the commons and the q-voter model with non-exchangeable agents, of which are interesting cases from theoretical and computational perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02644v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Yoshioka, M. Tsujimura, T. Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agnostic Learning under Targeted Poisoning: Optimal Rates and the Role of Randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03075v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the problem of learning in the presence of an adversary that can corrupt an $\eta$ fraction of the training examples with the goal of causing failure on a specific test point. In the realizable setting, prior work established that the optimal error under such instance-targeted poisoning attacks scales as $\Theta(d\eta)$, where $d$ is the VC dimension of the hypothesis class arXiv:2210.02713. In this work, we resolve the corresponding question in the agnostic setting. We show that the optimal excess error is $\tilde{\Theta}(\sqrt{d\eta})$, answering one of the main open problems left by Hanneke et al. To achieve this rate, it is necessary to use randomized learners: Hanneke et al. showed that deterministic learners can be forced to suffer error close to 1, even under small amounts of poisoning. Perhaps surprisingly, our upper bound remains valid even when the learner's random bits are fully visible to the adversary . In the other direction, our lower bound is stronger than standard PAC-style bounds: instead of tailoring a hard distribution separately for each sample size, we exhibit a single fixed distribution under which the adversary can enforce an excess error of $\Omega(\sqrt{d\eta})$ infinitely often.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03075v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Chornomaz, Yonatan Koren, Shay Moran, Tom Waknine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDEs with critical time dependent drifts: strong solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.05803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.05803v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Based on a compactness criterion for random fields in Wiener-Sobolev spaces, in this paper, we prove the unique strong solvability of time-inhomogeneous stochastic differential equations with drift coefficients in critical Lebesgue spaces, which gives an affirmative answer to a longstanding open problem. As an application, we also prove a regularity criterion for solutions of a stochastic system proposed by Constantin and Iyer (Comm. Pure. Appl. Math. 61(3): 330-345, 2008), which is closely related to the Navier-Stokes equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.05803v5</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael R\"ockner, Guohuan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Strassen's Theorem for support functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20402v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strassen established that there exists a two step martingale with marginal distributions $\mu$, $\nu$ if and only if $\mu$, $\nu$ are in convex order. Recently Chon\'e-Gozlan-Kramarz obtained a transport characterization of the stochastic order defined by convex positively 1-homogeneous functions, in the spirit of Strassen's theorem under certain technical assumptions. In this note we prove the Chon\'e-Gozlan-Kramarz result in full generality. We also observe that the restriction of the result to the case where $\mu, \nu$ are supported on a half space is equivalent to Strassen's classical theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20402v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/24-ECP618</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electron. Commun. Probab. 29: 1-12 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Schrott, Daniel Toneian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge statistics for random band matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00492v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider Hermitian and symmetric random band matrices on the $d$-dimensional lattice $(\mathbb{Z}/L\mathbb{Z})^d$ with bandwidth $W$, focusing on local eigenvalue statistics at the spectral edge in the limit $W\to\infty$. Our analysis reveals a critical dimension $d_c=6$ and identifies the critical bandwidth scaling as $W_c=L^{(1-d/6)_+}$. In the Hermitian case, we establish the Anderson transition for all dimensions $d&lt;4$, and GUE edge universality when $d\geq 4$ under the condition $W\geq L^{1/3+\epsilon}$ for any $\epsilon&gt;0$. In the symmetric case, we also establish parallel but more subtle transition phenomena after tadpole diagram renormalization. These findings extend Sodin's pioneering work [Ann. Math. 172, 2010], which was limited to the one-dimensional case and did not address the critical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00492v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dang-Zheng Liu, Guangyi Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming the Interacting Particle Langevin Algorithm: The Superlinear case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19587v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in stochastic optimization have yielded the interacting particle Langevin algorithm (IPLA), which leverages the notion of interacting particle systems (IPS) to efficiently sample from approximate posterior densities. This becomes particularly crucial in relation to the framework of Expectation-Maximization (EM), where the E-step is computationally challenging or even intractable. Although prior research has focused on scenarios involving convex cases with gradients of log densities that grow at most linearly, our work extends this framework to include polynomial growth. Taming techniques are employed to produce an explicit discretization scheme that yields a new class of stable, under such non-linearities, algorithms which are called tamed interacting particle Langevin algorithms (tIPLA). We obtain non-asymptotic convergence error estimates in Wasserstein-2 distance for the new class under the best known rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19587v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Johnston, Nikolaos Makras, Sotirios Sabanis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-Field Magnetohydrodynamics Models as Scaling Limits of Stochastic Induction Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07206v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic properties of a stochastic model for the induction equations of the magnetic field in a three dimensional periodic domain. The turbulent velocity field driving the electromotive force on the magnetic field is modeled by a noise white in time. For this model we rigorously take a scaling limit leading to a deterministic model. While in case of isotropic turbulence this produces an additional dissipation in the limit model which influences also the decay rate of the Magnetic field in the stochastic model, the case of turbulence devoloped in a preferential direction allows us to find a dynamo effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07206v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Butori, Eliseo Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Velocity surface disorder of large deviation rate functions of the random walk in strongly mixing environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06581v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we establish the existence of large deviation principles of random walk in strongly mixing environments. The quenched and annealed rate functions have the same zero set whose shape is either a singleton point or a line segment, with an illustrative example communicated and given by F. Rassoul-Agha. Whenever the level of disorder is controlled, the two rate functions are shown to conform on compact sets at the boundary and in the interior both under strongly mixing conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06581v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caputo fractional stochastic differential equations: Lipschitz continuity in the fractional order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19965v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a class of the Caputo fractional stochastic differential equations of fractional order $\alpha \in (\frac{1}{2},1]$. Our aim is to analyze of the continuous dependence of solutions on the fractional order $\alpha.$ We first provide explicit estimates for the rate of weak convergence the solutions. We then describe the exact asymptotic behavior of this convergence to show that the rate is optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19965v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. C. Son, N. T. Dung, P. T. P Thuy, T. M. Cuong, H. T. P. Thao, P. D. Tung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Halmos-Savage theorems and robust large financial markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a quantitative version of the classical Halmos-Savage Theorem for convex sets of probability measures and its dual counterpart, generalizing previous quantitative versions. These results are then used to derive robust versions of the fundamental theorem of asset pricing (FTAP) in large financial markets in a one period setting, characterizing the absence of arbitrage under Knightian uncertainty. To this end, we consider robust formulations of no asymptotic arbitrage of first kind (NAA1), which is the large market analogue of 'No unbounded profit with bounded risk' (NUPBR), as well as no asymptotic arbitrage of second kind (NAA2).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06686v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christa Cuchiero, Irene Klein, Georg K\"ostenberger, Thorsten Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic bounds for conditionally Gaussian vectors and applications to neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08335v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using entropic inequalities from information theory, we provide new bounds on the total variation and 2-Wasserstein distances between a conditionally Gaussian law and a Gaussian law with invertible covariance matrix. We apply our results to quantify the speed of convergence to Gaussian of a randomly initialized fully connected neural network and its derivatives - evaluated in a finite number of inputs - when the initialization is Gaussian and the sizes of the inner layers diverge to infinity. Our results require mild assumptions on the activation function, and allow one to recover optimal rates of convergence in a variety of distances, thus improving and extending the findings of Basteri and Trevisan (2023), Favaro et al. (2023), Trevisan (2024) and Apollonio et al. (2024). One of our main tools are the quantitative cumulant estimates established in Hanin (2024). As an illustration, we apply our results to bound the total variation distance between the Bayesian posterior law of the neural network and its derivatives, and the posterior law of the corresponding Gaussian limit: this yields quantitative versions of a posterior CLT by Hron et al. (2022), and extends several estimates by Trevisan (2024) to the total variation metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08335v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucia Celli, Giovanni Peccati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backward stochastic differential equations with nonlinear Young driver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18632v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs) involving a nonlinear Young integral of the form $\int_{t}^{T}g(Y_{r})\eta(dr,X_{r})$, where the driver $\eta(t,x)$ is a space-time H\"older continuous function and $X$ is a diffusion process. Solutions to such equations provide a probabilistic interpretation of the solutions to stochastic partial differential equations (SPDEs) driven by space-time noise. We first obtain the existence and uniqueness of the solutions to these BSDEs under the assumption that the driver $\eta(t,x)$ is bounded, by a modified Picard iteration method. Then, we derive the comparison principle by analyzing associated linear BSDEs and further establish regularity results for the solutions. Finally, by combining the regularity results with a localization argument, we extend the well-posedness result to the case where $\eta(t,x)$ is unbounded. As applications, we derive nonlinear Feynman-Kac formulae for a class of partial differential equations with Young drivers (Young PDEs), and further investigate BSDEs with non-Lipschitz coefficient functions, as well as linear stochastic heat equations subject to Neumann boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18632v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Song, Huilin Zhang, Kuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enriched functional limit theorems for dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2011.10153v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove functional limit theorems for dynamical systems in the presence of clusters of large values which, when summed and suitably normalised, get collapsed in a jump of the limiting process observed at the same time point. To keep track of the clustering information, which gets lost in the usual Skorohod topologies in the space of c\`adl\`ag functions, we introduce a new space which generalises the already more general spaces introduced by Whitt. Our main applications are to hyperbolic and non-uniformly expanding dynamical systems with heavy-tailed observable functions maximised at dynamically linked maximal sets (such as periodic points). We also study limits of extremal processes and record times point processes for observables not necessarily heavy tailed. The applications studied include hyperbolic systems such as Anosov diffeomorphisms, but also non-uniformly expanding maps such as maps with critical points of Benedicks-Carleson type or indifferent fixed points such as Pomeau-Manneville or Liverani-Saussol-Vaienti maps. The main tool is a limit theorem for point processes with decorations derived from a bi-infinite sequence called the transformed anchored tail process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2011.10153v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Cristina Moreira Freitas, Jorge Milhazes Freitas, Mike Todd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-ended spanning subforests and treeability of groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.07431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.07431v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that several new classes of groups are measure strongly treeable. In particular, finitely generated groups admitting planar Cayley graphs, elementarily free groups, and the group of isometries of the hyperbolic plane and all its closed subgroups. This provides the first examples of one-ended nonamenable groups which are measure strongly treeable. In higher dimensions, we also prove a dichotomy that the fundamental group of a closed aspherical $3$-manifold is either amenable or has strong ergodic dimension $2$. Our main technical tool is a method for finding measurable treeings of Borel planar graphs by constructing one-ended spanning subforests in their planar dual. Our techniques for constructing one-ended spanning subforests also give a complete classification of the locally finite pmp graphs which admit Borel a.e.\ one-ended spanning subforests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.07431v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clinton T. Conley, Damien Gaboriau, Andrew S. Marks, Robin D. Tucker-Drob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerate Langevin Sampling with Birth-Death Process and Exploration Component</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.05529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.05529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Sampling a probability distribution with known likelihood is a fundamental task in computational science and engineering. Aiming at multimodality, we propose a new sampling method that takes advantage of both birth-death process and exploration component. The main idea of this method is look before you leap. We keep two sets of samplers, one at warmer temperature and one at original temperature. The former one serves as pioneer in exploring new modes and passing useful information to the other, while the latter one samples the target distribution after receiving the information. We derive a mean-field limit and show how the exploration component accelerates the sampling process. Moreover, we prove exponential asymptotic convergence under mild assumption. Finally, we test on experiments from previous literature and compare our methodology to previous ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.05529v2</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lezhi Tan, Jianfeng Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The clique chromatic number of sparse random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03013v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The clique chromatic number of a graph is the smallest number of colors in a vertex coloring so that no maximal clique is monochromatic. In this paper, we determine the order of magnitude of the clique chromatic number of the random graph G_{n,p} for most edge-probabilities p in the range n^{-2/5} \ll p \ll 1. This resolves open problems and questions of Lichev, Mitsche and Warnke as well as Alon and Krievelevich.
  One major proof difficulty stems from high-degree vertices, which prevent maximal cliques in their neighborhoods: we deal with these vertices by an intricate union bound argument, that combines the probabilistic method with new degree counting arguments in order to enable Janson's inequality. This way we determine the asymptotics of the clique chromatic number of G_{n,p} in some ranges, and discover a surprising new phenomenon that contradicts earlier predictions for edge-probabilities p close to n^{-2/5}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03013v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Fernandez V, Lutz Warnke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of Optimal Stationary Singular Controls and Mean Field Game Equilibria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07945v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine the stationary relaxed singular control problem within a multi-dimensional framework for a single agent, as well as its mean field game equivalent. We demonstrate that optimal relaxed controls exist for two problem classes: one driven by queueing control and the other by harvesting models. These relaxed controls are defined by random measures across the state and control spaces, with the state process described as a solution to the associated martingale problem. By leveraging findings from [Kurtz-Stockbridge 2001], we establish the equivalence between the martingale problem and the stationary forward equation. This allows us to reformulate the relaxed control problem into a linear programming problem within the measure space. We prove the sequential compactness of these measures, thereby confirming the feasibility of achieving an optimal solution. Subsequently, our focus shifts to mean field games. Drawing on insights from the single-agent problem and employing Kakutani--Glicksberg--Fan fixed point theorem, we derive the existence of a mean field game equilibria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07945v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asaf Cohen, Chuhao Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion models for Gaussian distributions: Exact solutions and Wasserstein errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14250v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Diffusion or score-based models recently showed high performance in image generation. They rely on a forward and a backward stochastic differential equations (SDE). The sampling of a data distribution is achieved by numerically solving the backward SDE or its associated flow ODE. Studying the convergence of these models necessitates to control four different types of error: the initialization error, the truncation error, the discretization error and the score approximation. In this paper, we theoretically study the behavior of diffusion models and their numerical implementation when the data distribution is Gaussian. Our first contribution is to derive the analytical solutions of the backward SDE and the probability flow ODE and to prove that these solutions and their discretizations are all Gaussian processes. Our second contribution is to compute the exact Wasserstein errors between the target and the numerically sampled distributions for any numerical scheme. This allows us to monitor convergence directly in the data space, while experimental works limit their empirical analysis to Inception features. An implementation of our code is available online.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14250v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emile Pierret, Bruno Galerne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A local automaton for the 2D toric code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a local decoder for the 2D toric code using ideas from the hierarchical classical cellular automata of Tsirelson and G\'acs. Our decoder is a circuit of strictly local quantum operations preserving a logical state for exponential time in the presence of circuit-level noise without the need for non-local classical computation or communication. Our construction is not translation invariant in spacetime, but can be made time-translation invariant in 3D with stacks of 2D toric codes. This solves the open problem of constructing a local topological quantum memory below four dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19803v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shankar Balasubramanian, Margarita Davydova, Ethan Lake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dynamical evolution of randomness Part A: Random experiments as dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13978v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, Bernoulli's Law of Large Numbers, also known as the Golden theorem, has been extended to study the relations between empirical probability and empirical randomness of an otherwise random experiment. Using the example of a coin toss and a dice role, some interesting results are drawn. Analytically and using numerical computations, empirical randomness of each outcome has been shown to increase by \textit{ chance}, which itself depends on the growth rate of empirical probabilities. The analyses presented in this work, apart form depicting the nature of flow of random experiments in repetitions, also present dynamical behaviours of the random experiment, and experimental and simulation-based verifications of the mathematical analyses. It also presents an appreciation of the beauty of Bernoulli's Golden theorem and its applications by extension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13978v2</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen Lobo, Saravanan Arumugam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the transmission of texts: written cultures as complex systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19246v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Our knowledge of past cultures relies considerably on written material. For centuries, texts have been copied, altered, then transmitted or lost - eventually, from surviving documents, philologists attempt to reconstruct text phylogenies ("stemmata"), and past written cultures. Nonetheless, fundamental questions on the extent of losses, representativeness of surviving artefacts, and the dynamics of text genealogies have remained open since the earliest days of philology. To address these, we radically rethink the study of text transmission through a complexity science approach, integrating stochastic modelling, computer simulations, and data analysis, in a parsimonious mindset akin to statistical physics and evolutionary biology. Thus, we design models that are simple and general, while accounting for diachrony and other key aspects of the dynamical process underlying text phylogenies, such as the extinction of entire branches or trees. On the well-known case study of Medieval French chivalric literature, we find that up to 60% of texts and 99% of manuscripts were lost (consistent with recent synchronic "biodiversity" analyses). We also settle a hundred-year-old controversy on the bifidity of stemmata. Further, our null model suggests that pure chance ("drift") is not the only mechanism at play, and we provide a theoretical and empirical framework for future investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19246v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Baptiste Camps, Julien Randon-Furling, Ulysse Godreau</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
