<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS</link>
    <description>nlin.PS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal pattern formation of membranes induced by surface molecular binding/unbinding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonequilibrium membrane pattern formation is studied using meshless membrane simulation. We consider that molecules bind to either surface of a bilayer membrane and move to the opposite leaflet by flip-flop. When binding does not modify the membrane properties and the transfer rates among the three states are cyclically symmetric, the membrane exhibits spiral-wave and homogeneous-cycling modes at high and low binding rates, respectively, as in an off-lattice cyclic Potts model. When binding changes the membrane spontaneous curvature, these spatiotemporal dynamics are coupled with microphase separation. When two symmetric membrane surfaces are in thermal equilibrium, the membrane domains form 4.8.8 tiling patterns in addition to stripe and spot patterns. In nonequilibrium conditions, moving biphasic domains and time-irreversible fluctuating patterns appear. The domains move ballistically or diffusively depending on the conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23635v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Noguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillons from Q-balls through Renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using a renormalization-inspired perturbation expansion we show that oscillons in a generic field theory in (1+1)-dimensions arise as dressed Q-balls of a universal (up to the leading nonlinear order) complex field theory. This theory reveals a close similarity to the integrable complex sine-Gordon model which possesses exact multi-$Q$-balls. We show that excited oscillons, with characteristic modulations of their amplitude, are two-oscillons bound states generated from a two $Q$-ball solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24109v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Blaschke, T. Roma\'nczukiewicz, K. S{\l}awi\'nska, A. Wereszczy\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinks scattering in deformed $\varphi^6$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12599v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The deformed model $\tilde{\varphi}^{(6)}$ is introduced based on the $\varphi^4$ model using a deformation functional $F[\varphi]$ including a free parameter $a$. The kink solutions in different sectors and their internal modes are obtained as functions of the deformation parameter and their characteristics are evaluated as well. It is shown that the kinks of the deformed model inherit some of their dynamical properties (like internal modes) from the standard $\varphi^4$ potential and some of their characteristics from the $\varphi^6$ model. The dynamics of kink-antikink (antikink-kink) scattering is investigated in different sectors with various kink initial conditions as well as different values of deformation parameter. According to the kinks' initial velocity, colliding kinks may be bound together or scatter from each other after the interaction. These two situations are distinguished by the critical velocity, which itself depends on the deformation parameter of the model. Due to the difference in the rest mass of kink solutions related to different sectors, interesting and sometimes rare phenomena are observed during the kink scattering and their interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12599v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aliakbar Moradi Marjaneh, Azam Ghaani, Kurosh Javidan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapidly Rotating Wall-Mode Convection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20541v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the rapidly rotating limit, we derive a balanced set of reduced equations governing the strongly nonlinear development of the convective wall-mode instability in the interior of a general container. The model illustrates that wall-mode convection is a multiscale phenomenon where the dynamics of the bulk interior diagnostically determine the small-scale dynamics within Stewartson boundary layers at the sidewalls. The sidewall boundary layers feedback on the interior via a nonlinear lateral heat-flux boundary condition, providing a closed system. Outside the asymptotically thin boundary layer, the convective modes connect to a dynamical interior that maintains scales set by the domain geometry. In many ways, the final system of equations resembles boundary-forced planetary geostrophic baroclinic dynamics coupled with barotropic quasi-geostrophic vorticity. The reduced system contains the results from previous linear instability theory but captured in an elementary fashion, providing a new avenue for investigating wall-mode convection in the strongly nonlinear regime. We also derive the dominant Ekman-flux correction to the onset Rayleigh number for large Taylor number, Ra ~ 31.8 Ta^(1/2) - 4.43 Ta^(5/12) for no-slip boundaries. We demonstrate some of the reduced model's nonlinear dynamics with numerical simulations in a cylindrical container.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20541v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey M. Vasil, Keaton J. Burns, Daniel Lecoanet, Jeffrey S. Oishi, Benjamin P. Brown, Keith Julien</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
