<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS</link>
    <description>nlin.PS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 04:01:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Chaotic dynamics creates and destroys branched flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phenomenon of branched flow, visualized as a chaotic arborescent pattern of propagating particles, waves, or rays, has been identified in disparate physical systems ranging from electrons to tsunamis, with periodic systems only recently being added to this list. Here, we explore the laws governing the evolution of the branches in periodic potentials. On one hand, we observe that branch formation follows a similar pattern in all non-integrable potentials, no matter whether the potentials are periodic or completely irregular. Chaotic dynamics ultimately drives the birth of the branches. On the other hand, our results reveal that for periodic potentials the decay of the branches exhibits new characteristics due to the presence of infinitely stable branches known as superwires. Again, the interplay between branched flow and superwires is deeply connected to Hamiltonian chaos. In this work, we explore the relationships between the laws of branched flow and the structures of phase space, providing extensive numerical and theoretical arguments to support our findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12922v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Wagemakers, Aleksi Hartikainen, Alvar Daza, Esa R\"as\"anen, Miguel A. F. Sanju\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic breathing dromion-like structures in an anisotropic ferromagnetic medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The influence of Gilbert damping on the propagation of electromagnetic waves (EMWs) in an anisotropic ferromagnetic medium is investigated theoretically. The interaction of the magnetic field component of the electromagnetic wave with the magnetization of a ferromagnetic medium has been studied by solving the associated Maxwell's equations coupled with a Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert (LLG) equation. When small perturbations are made on the magnetization of the ferromagnetic medium and magnetic field along the direction of propagation of electromagnetic wave by using the reductive perturbation method, the associated nonlinear dynamics is governed by a time-dependent damped derivative nonlinear Schrodinger (TDDNLS) equation. The Lagrangian density function is constructed by using the variational method to solve the TDDNLS equation to understand the dynamics of the system under consideration. The propagation of EMW in a ferromagnetic medium with inherent Gilbert damping admits very interesting nonlinear dynamical structures. These structures include Gilbert damping-managing symmetrically breathing solitons, localized erupting electromagnetic breathing dromion-like modes of excitations, breathing dromion-like soliton, decaying dromion-like modes and an unexpected creation-annihilation mode of excitations in the form of growing-decaying dromion-like modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13320v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathishkumar Perumal, J. Sivapragasam, M. Lakshmanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wind-wave interaction in finite depth: linear and nonlinear approaches, blow-up and soliton breaking in finite time, integrability perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work is an analytical investigation of the evolution of surface water waves in Miles and Jeffreys theories of wind wave interaction in water of finite depth. The present review is divided into two major parts. The first corresponds to the surface water waves in a linear regime and its nonlinear extensions. In this part, Miles theory of wave amplification by wind is extended to the case of finite depth. The dispersion relation provides a wave growth rate depending on depth. Our theoretical results are in good agreement with the data from the Australian Shallow Water Experiment and the data from the Lake George experiment. In the second part of this study, Jeffreys theory of wave amplification by wind is extended to the case of finite depth, where the Serre-Green-Naghdi is derived. We find the solitary wave solution of the system, with an increasing amplitude under the action of the wind. This continuous increase in amplitude leads to the soliton breaking and blow-up of the surface wave in finite time. The theoretical blow-up time is calculated based on actual experimental data. By applying an appropriate perturbation method, the SGN equation yields Korteweg de Vries Burger equation (KdVB). We show that the continuous transfer of energy from wind to water results in the growth of the KdVB soliton amplitude, velocity, acceleration, and energy over time while its effective wavelength decreases. This phenomenon differs from the classical results of Jeffreys approach due to finite depth. Again, blow-up and breaking occur in finite time. These times are calculated and expressed for soliton- and wind-appropriate parameters and values. These values are measurable in usual experimental facilities. The kinematics of the breaking is studied, and a detailed analysis of the breaking time is conducted using various criteria. Finally, some integrability perspectives are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13701v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Latifi, M. A. Manna, R. A. Kraenkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing necks and wrinkles in inflated auxetic membranes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article presents the potentiality of inflatable, functionally-graded auxetic membranes to produce wrinkles and necks. We obtain elastic instabilities at desired locations in axisymmetric membranes and with prescribed patterns in square membranes. First, we use an analytical approach to obtain a series of universal results providing insights into the formation of wrinkles and necks in inflated, axisymmetric membranes. For example, we prove analytically that necks and wrinkles may never overlap in pressurized, axially symmetric membranes. Second, we implement the relaxed strain energy of tension field theory into a Finite Element solver (COMSOL). By tuning spatial inhomogeneities of the material moduli, we corroborate our universal results, describe the onset of wrinkling in an averaged way, and also generate non-trivial instabilities at desired locations. This study on membranes with morphing or corrugation on demand has potential applications in Braille reading and haptics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13442v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijmecsci.2024.109031</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Mechanical Sciences 268 (2024) 109031</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sairam Pamulaparthi Venkata, Valentina Balbi, Michel Destrade, Giuseppe Zurlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voltage-controlled non-axisymmetric vibrations of soft electro-active tubes with strain-stiffening effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13483v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Material properties of soft electro-active (SEA) structures are significantly sensitive to external electro-mechanical biasing fields (such as pre-stretch and electric stimuli), which generate remarkable knock-on effects on their dynamic characteristics. In this work, we analyze the electrostatically tunable non-axisymmetric vibrations of an incompressible SEA cylindrical tube under the combination of a radially applied electric voltage and an axial pre-stretch. Following the theory of nonlinear electro-elasticity and the associated linearized theory for superimposed perturbations, we derive the nonlinear static response of the SEA tube to the inhomogeneous biasing fields for the Gent ideal dielectric model. Using the State Space Method, we efficiently obtain the frequency equations for voltage-controlled small-amplitude three-dimensional non-axisymmetric vibrations, covering a wide range of behaviors, from the purely radial breathing mode to torsional modes, axisymmetric longitudinal modes, and prismatic diffuse modes. We also perform an exhaustive numerical analysis to validate the proposed approach compared with the conventional displacement method, as well as to elucidate the influences of the applied voltage, axial pre-stretch, and strain-stiffening effect on the nonlinear static response and vibration behaviors of the SEA tube. The present study clearly indicates that manipulating electro-mechanical biasing fields is a feasible way to tune the small-amplitude vibration characteristics of an SEA tube. The results should benefit experimental work on, and design of, voltage-controlled resonant devices made of SEA tubes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13483v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijsolstr.2024.112671</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Solids and Structures 290 (2024) 112671</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. Zhu, B. Wu, M. Destrade, H. Wang, R. Bao, W. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of uniform and oscillatory states resulting from nonreciprocity and conservation laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08634v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Employing a two-species Cahn-Hilliard model with nonreciprocal interactions we show that the interplay of nonreciprocity and conservation laws results in the coexistence of uniform stationary and oscillatory phases as well as of uniform and crystalline phases. For nonequilibrium models with a \textit{spurious gradient dynamics structure} [T. Frohoff-H{\"u}lsmann \textit{et al.}, Phys.\ Rev.\ E 107, 64210 (2023)] the coexistence between nonequilibrium phases can nevertheless be predicted by a Maxwell double-tangent construction including phases with sustained out-of-equilibrium dynamics. This is further corroborated by bifurcation studies and time simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08634v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Greve, Giorgio Lovato, Tobias Frohoff-H\"ulsmann, Uwe Thiele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersive shock waves in a one-dimensional droplet-bearing environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02998v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate the controllable generation of distinct types of dispersive shock-waves emerging in a quantum droplet bearing environment with the aid of step-like initial conditions. Dispersive regularization of the ensuing hydrodynamic singularities occurs due to the competition between meanfield repulsion and attractive quantum fluctuations. This interplay delineates the dominance of defocusing (hyperbolic) and focusing (elliptic) hydrodynamic phenomena respectively being designated by real and imaginary speed of sound. Specifically, the symmetries of the extended Gross-Pitaevskii model lead to a three-parameter family, encompassing two densities and a relative velocity, of the underlying Riemann problem utilized herein. Surprisingly, dispersive shock waves persist across the hyperbolic-to-elliptic threshold, while a plethora of additional wave patterns arise, such as rarefaction waves, traveling dispersive shock waves, (anti)kinks and droplet wavetrains. The classification and characterization of these features is achieved by deploying Whitham modulation theory. Our results pave the way for unveiling a multitude of unexplored coherently propagating waveforms in such attractively interacting mixtures and should be detectable by current experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02998v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathyanarayanan Chandramouli, Simeon I. Mistakidis, Garyfallia C. Katsimiga, Panayotis G. Kevrekidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
