<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS</link>
    <description>nlin.PS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 05:00:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On dynamics of gasless combustion in slowly varying periodic media: periodic fronts, their stability and propagation-extinction-diffusion-reignition pattern</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider a classical model of gasless combustion in a one dimensional formulation under the assumption of ignition temperature kinetics. We study the propagation of flame fronts in this model when the initial distribution of the solid fuel is a spatially periodic function that varies on a large scale. It is shown that in certain parametric regimes the model supports periodic traveling fronts. An accurate asymptotic formula for the velocity of the flame front is derived and studied. The stability of periodic fronts is also explored, and a critical condition in terms of parameters of the problem is derived. It is also shown that the instability of periodic fronts, in a certain parametric regimes, results in a propagation-extinction-diffusion-reignition pattern which is studied numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03144v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amanda Matson, Leonid Kagan, Claude-Michel Brauner, Gregory Sivashinsky, Peter V. Gordon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial amplitude equations for fully localised planar patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02949v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Isolated patches of spatially oscillating pattern have been found to emerge near a pattern-forming instability in a wide variety of experiments and mathematical models. However, there is currently no mathematical theory to explain this emergence or characterise the structure of these patches. We provide a method for formally deriving radial amplitude equations to planar patterns via non-autonomous multiple-scale analysis and convolutional sums of products of Bessel functions. Our novel approach introduces nonautonomous differential operators, which allow for the systematic manipulation of Bessel functions, as well as previously unseen identities involving infinite sums of Bessel functions. Solutions of the amplitude equations describe fully localised patterns with non-trivial angular dependence, where localisation occurs in a purely radial direction. Amplitude equations are derived for multiple examples of patterns with dihedral symmetry, including fully localised hexagons and quasipatterns with twelve-fold rotational symmetry. In particular, we show how to apply the asymptotic method to the Swift--Hohenberg equation and general reaction-diffusion systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02949v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan J. Hill, David J. B. Lloyd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton Frequency Combs in Elastomer Membrane-Cavity Optomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solitons, arising from nonlinear wave-matter interactions, stand out for their intrinsic stability during wave propagation and exceptional spectral characteristics1. Their applications span diverse physical systems, including telecommunications, atomic clocks, and precise measurements. In recent years, significant strides have been made in developing cavity-optomechanics based approaches to generate optical frequency combs (FCs). In this study, we present an innovative approach, never explored before, that leverages elastomer membrane (EM)-cavity optomechanics to achieve the generation of soliton FCs, a highly sought-after phenomenon in the realm of nonlinear wave-matter interactions. Our method represents a significant breakthrough due to its streamlined simplicity, relying on a single continuous-wave (CW) laser pump and an externally applied acoustic wave exciting an EM-cavity, which gives rise to phonons, quantized vibrational energy states intrinsic to the elastomer's crystalline lattice structure. The mechanical resonator and electromagnetic cavity resonance are parametrically coupled within the microwave frequency range, collectively orchestrate the process of soliton FCs formation with remarkable efficiency. Numerical simulations and experimental observations demonstrate the emergence of multiple stable localized opto-mechanical wave packets, characterized by a narrow pulses time-domain response. Crucially, by setting the acoustic wave frequency to match the natural frequency of the EM resonator, the solitons' teeth are precisely spaced, and the EM's motion is significantly amplified, giving rise to a Kerr medium. The successful realization of optomechanical stable solitons represents a monumental advancement with transformative potential across various fields, including quantum computing and spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03160v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sasan Rahmanian, Hamza Mouharrar, Amin Alibakhshi, Zeeshan Iqbal, Luis Saucedo-Mora, Francisco Javier Montans, Jan Awrejcewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaction-diffusion models of biological invasion: Open source computational tools, key concepts and analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01667v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This review provides open-access computational tools that support a range of mathematical approaches to analyse three related scalar reaction-diffusion models used to study biological invasion. Starting with the classic Fisher-Kolmogorov (Fisher-KPP) model, we illustrate how computational methods can be used to explore time-dependent partial differential equation (PDE) solutions in parallel with phase plane and regular perturbation techniques to explore invading travelling wave solutions moving with dimensionless speed $c \ge 2$. To overcome the lack of a well-defined sharp front in solutions of the Fisher-KPP model, we also review two alternative modeling approaches. The first is the Porous-Fisher model where the linear diffusion term is replaced with a degenerate nonlinear diffusion term. Using phase plane and regular perturbation methods, we explore the distinction between sharp- and smooth-fronted invading travelling waves that move with dimensionless speed $c \ge 1/\sqrt{2}$. The second alternative approach is to reformulate the Fisher-KPP model as a moving boundary problem on $0 &lt; x &lt; L(t)$, leading to the Fisher-Stefan model with sharp-fronted travelling wave solutions arising from a PDE model with a linear diffusion term. Time-dependent PDE solutions and phase plane methods show that travelling wave solutions of the Fisher-Stefan model can describe both biological invasion $(c &gt; 0)$ and biological recession $(c &lt; 0)$. Open source Julia code to replicate all computational results in this review is available on GitHub; we encourage researchers to use this code directly or to adapt the code as required for more complicated models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01667v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew J Simpson, Scott W McCue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable discretization of the vector/matrix nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation and the associated Yang-Baxter map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1505.07924</link>
      <description>arXiv:1505.07924v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The action of a B\"acklund-Darboux transformation on a spectral problem associated with a known integrable system can define a new discrete spectral problem. In this paper, we interpret a slightly generalized version of the binary B\"acklund-Darboux (or Zakharov-Shabat dressing) transformation for the nonlinear Schr\"odinger (NLS) hierarchy as a discrete spectral problem, wherein the two intermediate potentials appearing in the Darboux matrix are considered as a pair of new dependent variables. Then, we associate the discrete spectral problem with a suitable isospectral time-evolution equation, which forms the Lax-pair representation for a space-discrete NLS system. This formulation is valid for the most general case where the two dependent variables take values in (rectangular) matrices. In contrast to the matrix generalization of the Ablowitz-Ladik lattice, our discretization has a rational nonlinearity and admits a Hermitian conjugation reduction between the two dependent variables. Thus, a new proper space-discretization of the vector/matrix NLS equation is obtained; by changing the time part of the Lax pair, we also obtain an integrable space-discretization of the vector/matrix modified KdV (mKdV) equation. Because B\"acklund-Darboux transformations are permutable, we can increase the number of discrete independent variables in a multi-dimensionally consistent way. By solving the consistency condition on the two-dimensional lattice, we obtain a Yang-Baxter map of the NLS type, which can be considered as a fully discrete analog of the principal chiral model for projection matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1505.07924v5</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Tsuchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
