<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS</link>
    <description>nlin.PS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 03:02:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral theory of soliton gases for the defocusing NLS equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we derive Nonlinear Dispersion Relations (NDR) for the defocusing NLS (dark) soliton gas using the idea of thermodynamic limit of quasimomentum and quasienergy differentials on the underlying family of Riemann surfaces. It turns out that the obtained NDR are closely connected with the recently studied NDR for circular soliton gas for the focusing NLS. We find solutions for the kinetic equation for the defocusing NLS soliton condensate, which is defined by the endpoints of the spectral support $\G$ for the NDR.It turns out that, similarly to KdV soliton condensates (\cite{CERT}), the evolution of these endpoints is governed by the defocusing NLS-Whitham equations (\cite{Kodama}). We also study the Riemann problem for step initial data and the kurtosis of genus zero and one defNLS condensates, where we proved that the kurtosis of genus one condensate can not exceed 3/2, whereas for genus zero condensate the kurtosis is always 1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01132v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Tovbis, Fudong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High viscosity effects on solitary wave propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00095v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an experimental and numerical study of linear and non-linear viscous effects in transient non-linear long wave propagation in Newtonian and shear thinning fluids in the laminar flow regime. Using optical measuring techniques (Fourier Transform Profilometry) and numerical simulations (open-source CFD library OpenFOAM), we show that the wave phase speed decreases in both glycerin and carboxymethylcellulose (CMC) solutions with respect to that in water. A decrease in wave phase speed is observed, and a dispersion relation is obtained for surface waves through dimensional analysis from five dimensionless groups: the dimensionless wave celerity, the shallowness parameter, dimensionless amplitude, Reynolds number and the flow index. To complete the picture on wave propagation, an empirical dependence between the wave attenuation and the last four dimensionless groups mentioned above is found for non-linear long surface waves. We conclude quantitatively about all the viscosity effects in non-linear long wave propagation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00095v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Calvo, Aldo Tamburrino, Claudio Falc\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Measurement via Time Crystal Frequencies in One-Dimensional Quantum Droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00935v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a method for temperature measurement by analyzing the frequency of generated time crystals in one-dimensional (1D) quantum droplets. The system consists of a binary Bose-Einstein condensate mixture confined in a driven quasi-periodic optical lattice (QOL) with repulsive cubic effective mean-field and attractive quadratic beyond-mean-field interactions. By solving the 1D extended Gross-Pitaevskii equation, we derive the exact analytical wavefunction and investigate the droplet dynamics under different driving conditions. Specifically, we examine three cases: (i) constant driving frequency with linearly increasing QOL depth, (ii) constant QOL depth with linearly varying driving frequency, and (iii) constant driving frequency with sinusoidally modulated QOL depth. Fast Fourier Transform analysis reveals harmonic density oscillations, confirming time crystal formation. Additionally, we establish a non-trivial correlation between time crystal frequency and system temperature, demonstrating that an increase in time crystal frequency leads to oscillatory variations in the magnitude of the droplet's negative temperature. Finally, numerical stability analysis confirms that the obtained solutions remain robust, ensuring their feasibility for experimental realization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00935v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurab Das, Jagnyaseni Jogania, Jayanta Bera, Ajay Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularizations for shock and rarefaction waves in the perturbed solitons of the KP equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By means of an asymptotic perturbation method, we study the initial value problem of the KP equation with initial data consisting of parts of exact line-soliton solutions of the equation. We consider a slow modulation of the soliton parameters, which is described by a dynamical system obtained by the perturbation method. The system is given by a quasi-linear system, and in particular, we show that a singular solution ({shock wave}) leads to a generation of new soliton as a result of resonant interaction of solitons. We also show that a regular solution corresponding to a rarefaction wave can be described by a parabola (we call it {parabolic}-soliton). We then perform numerical simulations of the initial value problem and show that they are in excellent agreement with the results obtained by the perturbation method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01093v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangfu Han, Yuji Kodama, Chuanzhong Li, Lin Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear breathers with crystalline symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07244v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear lattice models can support "discrete breather" excitations that stay localized in space for all time. By contrast, the localized Wannier states of linear lattice models are dynamically unstable. Nevertheless, symmetric and exponentially localized Wannier states are a central tool in the classification of band structures with crystalline symmetries. Moreover, the quantized transport observed in nonlinear Thouless pumps relies on the fact that -- at least in a specific model -- discrete breathers recover Wannier states in the limit of vanishing nonlinearity. Motivated by these observations, we investigate the correspondence between nonlinear breathers and exponentially localised Wannier states for a family of discrete nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations with crystalline symmetries. We develop a formalism to analytically predict the breathers' spectrum, center of mass and symmetry data, and apply this to nonlinear generalizations of the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chain and the breathing kagome lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07244v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.064312</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 064312 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank Schindler, Vir B. Bulchandani, Wladimir A. Benalcazar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Law of Large Numbers and Central Limit Theorem for random sets of solitons of the focusing nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17036v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a random configuration of $N$ soliton solutions $\psi_N(x,t;\boldsymbol{\lambda})$ of the cubic focusing Nonlinear Schr\"odinger (fNLS) equation in one space dimension. The $N$ soliton solutions are parametrized by a $N$-dimension complex vector $\boldsymbol{\lambda}$ whose entries are the eigenvalues of the Zakharov-Shabat linear spectral problem and by $N$ nonzero complex norming constants. The randomness is obtained by choosing the complex eigenvalues i.i.d. random variables sampled from a probability distribution with compact support on the complex plane. The corresponding norming constants are interpolated by a smooth function of the eigenvalues. Then we consider the Zakharov-Shabat linear problem for the expectation of the random measure associated to the spectral data. We denote the corresponding solution of the fNLS equation by $\psi_\infty(x,t)$. This solution can be interpreted as a soliton gas solution. We prove a Law of Large Numbers and a Central Limit Theorem for the differences $\psi_N(x,t;\boldsymbol{\lambda})-\psi_\infty(x,t)$ and $|\psi_N(x,t;\boldsymbol{\lambda})|^2-|\psi_\infty(x,t)|^2$ when $(x,t)$ are in a compact set of $\mathbb R \times \mathbb R^+$; we additionally compute the correlation functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17036v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuela Girotti, Tamara Grava, Ken D. T-R McLaughlin, Joseph Najnudel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
