<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.PS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS</link>
    <description>nlin.PS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.PS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:11:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly chirped dissipative solitons in normal and anomalous dispersion regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop an adiabatic theory for strongly chirped dissipative solitons governed by the cubic-quintic complex Ginzburg-Landau equation and analyze their existence regions in both normal and anomalous dispersion regimes. Closed-form expressions for the frequency cut-off and peak power yield two physical branches whose admissibility is set by a compact dimensionless parameterization. The analysis reveals that dissipative-soliton resonance (chirp-driven temporal stretching with bounded peak power) naturally emerges on the scalable branch, providing a direct pathway to high-energy femtosecond oscillators without external amplification. We interpret these results within a thermodynamic framework that connects energy "condensation" in the soliton to a BEC-like metaphor, providing quantitative indicators for energy scalability limits and breakup onsets, and aligning with a recently formulated thermodynamic methodology for dissipative solitons. Beyond immediate laser design guidance, our approach suggests a generalized thermodynamic theory of strongly chirped dissipative solitons, including measurable entropy and temperature proxies, as well as a phase diagram that distinguishes between single- and multi-soliton states. This unifies practical laser engineering criteria with many-body concepts, pointing to optics-based, metaphorical simulations of condensate phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22806v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. L. Kalashnikov, A. Rudenkov, E. Sorokin, I. T. Sorokina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractal features of multimodal cardiac signals: Nonlinear dynamics of exercise recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the recovery dynamics of healthy cardiac activity after physical exertion using multimodal biosignals recorded with a polycardiograph. Multifractal features derived from the singularity spectrum capture the scale-invariant properties of cardiovascular regulation. Five supervised classification algorithms - Logistic Regression (LogReg), Suport Vector Machine with RBF kernel (SVM-RBF), k-Nearest Neighbors (kNN), Decision Tree (DT), and Random Forest (RF) - were evaluated to distinguish recovery states in a small, imbalanced dataset. Our results show that multifractal analysis, combined with multimodal sensing, yields reliable features for characterizing recovery and points toward nonlinear diagnostic methods for heart conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23317v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Maluckov, D. Stojanovic, M. Miletic, Lj. Hadzievski, J. Petrovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal interactions induce persistent active clusters in binary colloids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study binary colloids under AC electric fields, where electrohydrodynamic (EHD) flows generate nonreciprocal interactions. Mixing particles of different sizes produces self-propelled pairs that fragment and reassemble into persistent active clusters, unlike the static crystallization of single-sized systems. Agent-based and continuum models reproduce these dynamics and identify two key mechanisms: asymmetric pair propulsion and spray-like fission from excluded-volume polarity. These results establish a minimal, controllable platform for exploring nonreciprocal active matter and highlight nonreciprocity as a general route to engineer reconfigurable colloidal assemblies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23164v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoma Hara, Masazumi Okada, Keisuke Kittaka, Sho Tanami, Yuichi Iwasaki, Hiroaki Ishikawa, Kiwamu Yoshii, Yutaka Sumino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driven Dissipative Soliton Resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the enhancement of the dissipative soliton energy scalability by the injection of a low-power single-mode seed synchronized with a chirped-pulse oscillator round-trip. It is demonstrated that a threshold-like transition to multiple-pulse generation limits the maximum energies of dissipative solitons, in agreement with the thermodynamic interpretation of a strongly chirped pulse stability. We show that there are ``islands'' of instability within a stability range of energies which result from stochastic resonance between ``internal modes'' of soliton and quantum noise of the ``basin''. The transition to multiple-pulsing can be suppressed in a system driven by a comparatively low-power seed. However, seed power growth increases the mode-locking energy threshold and produces ``islands'' of instability as the dissipative soliton energy rises.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24503v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir L. Kalashnikov, Alexander Rudenkov, Evgeni Sorokin, Irina T. Sorokina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum-resolved two-dimensional spectroscopy as a probe of nonlinear quantum field dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25147v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Emergent collective excitations constitute a hallmark of interacting quantum many-body systems, yet in solid-state platforms their study has been largely limited by the constraints of linear-response probes and by finite momentum resolution. We propose to overcome these limitations by combining the spatial resolution of ultracold atomic systems with the nonlinear probing capabilities of two-dimensional spectroscopy (2DS). As a concrete illustration, we analyze momentum-resolved 2DS of the quantum sine-Gordon model describing the low energy dynamics of two weakly coupled one-dimensional Bose-Einstein condensates. This approach reveals distinctive many-body signatures, most notably asymmetric cross-peaks reflecting the interplay between isolated ($B_2$ breather) and continuum ($B_1$ pair) modes. The protocol further enables direct characterization of anharmonicity and disorder, establishing momentum-resolved 2DS as both a powerful diagnostic for quantum simulators and a versatile probe of correlated quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25147v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duilio De Santis, Alex G\'omez Salvador, Nataliia Bazhan, Sebastian Erne, Maximilian Pr\"ufer, Claudio Guarcello, Davide Valenti, J\"org Schmiedmayer, Eugene Demler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-Neural-Inspired Image Inpainting for Specific Objects-of-Interest Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12808v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conventional image inpainting techniques typically process entire images, which often leads to computational inefficiency and susceptibility to information redundancy, particularly in occluded or cluttered scenes. Inspired by cortical processing mechanisms, this study introduces a novel framework termed "Specific Object-of-Interest Imaging" (SIOI) to overcome these limitations. The proposed approach first extracts and encodes object-level representations from complex scenes, producing structural and semantic priors that can be seamlessly integrated into existing inpainting pipelines. Extensive evaluations on dedicated object datasets--Teapot, Elephant, Giraffe, and Zebra--demonstrate that models incorporating SIOI consistently outperform those without it across key metrics including SSIM, PSNR, MAE, and LPIPS. The framework also exhibits strong robustness under challenging conditions such as low illumination, high noise, multiple object occlusions, and motion blur. Furthermore, theoretical analysis grounded in cognitive neuroscience reveals meaningful connections between the "object-first" perceptual mechanism and dynamic feature modulation in visual cortical areas (V1-V4). By significantly enhancing object consistency and semantic coherence across diverse inpainting models, this work not only advances efficient and target-aware image restoration but also fosters interdisciplinary convergence between brain-inspired computation and cutting-edge inpainting technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12808v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonghao Wu, Chang Liu, Vladimir Filaretov, Dmitry Yukhimets</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
