<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent control of multiphoton ionization of lithium atoms by a bichromatic laser field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a left-right asymmetry control of the photo\-electron angular distribution in multi\-photon ionization of Li atoms by a bichromatic laser field. By delaying the fundamental (780 nm) and its second harmonic relative to each other in steps of 130 atto\-seconds, we can vary the relative phase between the two laser fields with sub-wavelength accuracy and thereby steer the ejected electrons. Good agreement is found between the measurements and calculations at the appropriate intensities of the two harmonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10420v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silva Mezinska, Alexander Dorn, Thomas Pfeifer, Klaus Bartschat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functionalized mm-scale vapor cells for alkali-metal spectroscopy and magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe micro-fabricated rubidium vapor cells with integrated temperature-control functionality and demonstrate their suitability for use in miniaturized ultra-sensitive magnetometers. These functionalized vapor cells (FVCs) embody a dual-chamber design in low-conductivity silicon with anti-permeation coatings and micro-structured thin-film platinum surface traces as resistive heaters and temperature sensors. Thermal tests show our ability to control alkali metal distribution within the FVCs, ensuring a clean sensing chamber for optical measurements. Optical absorption spectroscopy is used to correlate the temperature readings with vapor density and to measure buffer gas pressure, of interest for optimizing sensitivity. Finally, we demonstrate zero-field resonance magnetometry with 18 fT/Hz$^{1/2}$ sensitivity in the 10 Hz to 100 Hz band, limited by laser noise and magnetic shield noise, which indicates that the functionalization does not introduce significant magnetic noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10715v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harini Raghavan, Michael C. D. Tayler, Rachel Rae, Kostas Mouloudakis, Sami L\"ahteenm\"aki, Rasmus Zetter, Petteri Laine, Jacques Haesler, Laurent Balet, Thomas Overstolz, Sylvain Karlen, Morgan W. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute quantum gravimeters and gradiometers for field measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravity measurements provide valuable information on the mass distribution below the earth surface relevant to various areas of geosciences such as hydrology, geodesy, geophysics, volcanology, and natural resources management. During the past decades, the needs for sensitivity, robustness, compactness, and transportability of instruments measuring the gravitational acceleration have constantly increased. Today, applications typically call for 1 $\mu \mathrm{Gal} = 10 \mathrm{nm.s}^{-2}$ ~ $10^{-9}$ g resolution on time scales ranging from minutes to years. Absolute Quantum Gravimeters (AQGs) based on matter-wave interferometry with laser-cooled atoms address all these challenges at once, even in uncontrolled environments. Furthermore, to date, quantum gravimeters are the only technology capable of providing continuous absolute gravity data over long measurement durations (~1 day to months or more). In this paper we recall the AQG working principle and present the reproducible high performance at the {\mu}Gal level on all 16 units fabricated so far. We also describe recent progress on the Differential Quantum Gravimeter (DQG) which measures simultaneously the mean gravitational acceleration and its vertical gradient at the level of $10 \mathrm{nm.s}^{-2}$ and $1$ E (1 E[eotvos] = $10^{-9}$ s$^{-2}$) respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10844v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Antoni-Micollier, Maxime Arnal, Romain Gautier, Camille Janvier, Vincent M\'enoret, J\'er\'emie Richard, Pierre Vermeulen, Peter Rosenbusch, C\'edric Majek, Bruno Desruelle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapped-Ion Quantum Simulation of Electron Transfer Models with Tunable Dissipation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10368v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electron transfer is at the heart of many fundamental physical, chemical, and biochemical processes essential for life. Exact simulation of reactions in these systems is often hindered by the large number of degrees of freedom and by the essential role of quantum effects. In this work, we experimentally simulate a paradigmatic model of molecular electron transfer using a multi-species trapped-ion crystal, where the donor-acceptor gap, the electronic and vibronic couplings, and the bath relaxation dynamics can all be controlled independently. We employ the ground-state qubit of one ion to simulate the electronic degree of freedom and the optical qubit of another ion to perform reservoir engineering on a collective mode encoding a reaction coordinate. We observe the real-time dynamics of the spin excitation, measuring the transfer rate in several regimes of adiabaticity and relaxation dynamics. The setup allows access to the electron transfer dynamics in the non-perturbative regime, where there is no clear hierarchy among the energy scales in the model, as has been suggested to be optimal for many rate phenomena, including photosynthesis. Our results provide a testing ground for increasingly rich models of molecular excitation transfer processes that are relevant for molecular electronics and light-harvesting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10368v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Visal So, Midhuna Duraisamy Suganthi, Abhishek Menon, Mingjian Zhu, Roman Zhuravel, Han Pu, Peter G. Wolynes, Jos\'e N. Onuchic, Guido Pagano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporally multiplexed ion-photon quantum interface via fast ion-chain transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10501v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-rate remote entanglement between photon and matter-based qubits is essential for distributed quantum information processing. A key technique to increase the modest entangling rates of existing long-distance quantum networking approaches is multiplexing. Here, we demonstrate a temporally multiplexed ion-photon interface via rapid transport of a chain of nine calcium ions across 74 $\mathrm{\mu m}$ within 86 $\mathrm{\mu s}$. The non-classical nature of the multiplexed photons is verified by measuring the second-order correlation function with an average value of $g^{(2)}(0)$ = 0.060(13), indicating negligible crosstalk between the multiplexed modes. In addition, we characterize the motional degree-of-freedom of the ion crystal after transport and find that it is coherently excited to as much as $\bar{n}_\alpha\approx 110$ for the center-of-mass mode. Our proof-of-principle implementation paves the way for large-scale quantum networking with trapped ions, but highlights some challenges that must be overcome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10501v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingran You, Qiming Wu, David Miron, Wenjun Ke, Inder Monga, Erhan Saglamyurek, Hartmut Haeffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
