<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>First results from a search for axionlike dark matter using octupole-deformed nuclei in a crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02218v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most of the matter in the universe is in the form of dark matter. However, dark matter has never been observed to interact with normal matter in laboratory experiments. ALPs -- ultralight axionlike particles -- are a class of dark matter models that are consistent with astrophysical constraints, and produce measurable signatures in the form of oscillating violations of discrete symmetries in nuclei. We report the first results from a search for oscillating parity-odd time-reversal-odd nuclear moments of $^{153}$Eu ions in a crystal, which leads to an experimental constraint on the ALP-gluon coupling strength across a wide band of ALP masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02218v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyu Fan, Bassam Nima, Aleksandar Radak, Gonzalo Alonso-\'Alvarez, Amar Vutha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QED calculations of the E1 transition amplitude in neon-like iron and nickel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We calculated QED corrections to the $E1$ transition amplitudes in Ne-like iron and nickel. For the $2p \to 3d$ transitions the dominant effect came from the many-electron mixing, or electronic correlations. For the $2p \to 3s$ transitions the correlation and one-electron effects were comparable and tended to compensate each other. Our ab initio calculations showed that vertex corrections were negligible for both types of transitions. Other QED corrections were accurately reproduced by including effective QEDMOD operator in the many-electron relativistic configuration interaction calculation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02489v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. G. Kozlov, V. A. Yerokhin, M. Y. Kaygorodov., E. V. Tryapitsyna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atoms near a conducting wedge: decay rates and entanglement around a corner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The behavior of an atomic system is influenced by introducing a metallic surface. This work explores how the decay landscape can be altered by the presence of sharp corners. We examine two scenarios: the modified spontaneous decay of a single atom, which leads us to speculate about potential applications in microscopy, and the case of a more fundamental, theoretical interest - the behavior of an entangled pair of atoms near a corner. The latter, when two atoms are positioned ``out of the line of sight'' opens up a possible line of investigation into devices which are able to ``see around corners''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02349v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romuald Kilianski, Robert Bennett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion-Insensitive Time-Optimal Control of Optical Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In trapped-atom quantum computers, high-fidelity control of optical qubits is challenging due to the motion of atoms in the trap. If not corrected, the atom motion gets entangled with the qubit degrees of freedom through two fundamental mechanisms, (i) photon recoil and (ii) thermal motion, both leading to a reduction of the gate fidelity. We develop motion-insensitive pulses that suppress both sources of infidelity by modulating the phase of the driving laser field in time. To eliminate photon recoil, we use bang-bang pulses$-$derived using time-optimal control$-$which shorten the gate duration by about 20 times compared to conventional pulses. However, even when photon recoil is eliminated, we find that the gate error does not vanish, but is rather limited by a bound arising from thermal motion-induced entanglement. Remarkably, this bound is independent of the Rabi frequency, meaning that, unlike for photon recoil, operating in the resolved sideband regime does not mitigate this source of infidelity. To overcome this bound, we derive smooth-phase pulses, which allow for a further reduction of the gate error by more than an order of magnitude for typical thermal atoms. Motion-insensitive pulses can be refined to compensate for laser inhomogeneities, enhancing the gate performance in practical situations. Our results are validated through simulations of one-qubit gates operating on the optical clock transition of ${}^{88}$Sr atoms trapped in an optical tweezers array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02452v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'eo Van Damme, Zhao Zhang, Amit Devra, Steffen J. Glaser, Andrea Alberti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron rescollisional excitation of OCS$^+$ in phase-locked $\omega + 2\omega$ intense laser fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14148v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Photoelectron-photoion coincidence momentum imaging has been performed to investigate excitation processes on dissociative ionization of OCS, OCS $\to$ OCS$^+$ + e$^-$ $\to$ OC + S$^+$ + e$^-$, in phase-locked $\omega + 2\omega$ intense laser fields. The electron kinetic energy spectra depend on coincidentally produced ion species, OCS$^+$ or S$^+$. The observed electron momentum distribution shows clear asymmetry along the laser polarization direction with a 2$\pi$-oscillation period as a function of the phase difference between the $\omega$ and $2\omega$ laser fields. The asymmetry of electron emission in the OCS$^+$ channel flips at the electron kinetic energy of 8.2 eV where the dominant scattering direction switches from forward to backward. In the S$^+$ channel, the asymmetry flips at the lower kinetic energy of 4.2 eV. %, and this shift corresponds to an inelastic scattering process. In comparison with a classical trajectory Monte Carlo simulation, it has been clarified that this energy shift between the OCS$^+$ and S$^+$ channels corresponds to the excitation energy of the parent ion and that electron recollisional excitation takes place to form the fragment ion in intense laser fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14148v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoyuki Endo, Tomohito Otobe, Ryuji Itakura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of a radio-frequency two-photon atomic magnetometer in different magnetic induction measurement geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17935v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Measurements monitoring the inductive coupling between oscillating radio-frequency magnetic fields and objects of interest create versatile platforms for non-destructive testing. The benefits of ultra low frequency measurements, i.e., below 3 kHz, are sometimes outweighed by the fundamental and technical difficulties related to operating pick-up coils or other field sensors in this frequency range. Inductive measurements with the detection based on a two-photon interaction in rf atomic magnetometers address some of these issues, as the sensor gains an uplift in its operational frequency. The developments reported here integrate the fundamental and applied aspects of the two-photon process in magnetic induction measurements. In this paper, all spectral components of the two-photon process are identified, which result from the non-linear interactions between the rf fields and atoms. A method for the retrieval of the two-photon phase information, which is critical for inductive measurements, is also demonstrated. Furthermore, a self-compensation configuration is introduced, whereby high contrast measurements of defects can be obtained due to the sensor's insensitivity to the primary field, including using simplified instrumentation for this configuration by producing two rf fields with a single rf coil.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17935v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. Rushton, L. M. Ellis, J. D. Zipfel, P. Bevington, W. Chalupczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
