<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 04:01:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity holographic beam shaping with optimal transport and phase diversity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.17025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A phase-only spatial light modulator (SLM) provides a powerful way to shape laser beams into arbitrary intensity patterns, but at the cost of a hard computational problem of determining an appropriate SLM phase. Here we show that optimal transport methods can generate approximate solutions to this problem that serve as excellent initializations for iterative phase retrieval algorithms, yielding vortex-free solutions with superior accuracy and efficiency. Additionally, we show that analogous algorithms can be used to measure the intensity and phase of the input beam incident upon the SLM via phase diversity imaging. These techniques furnish flexible and convenient solutions to the computational challenges of beam shaping with an SLM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.17025v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hunter Swan, Andrii Torchylo, Michael J. Van de Graaff, Jan Rudolph, Jason M. Hogan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of strong coupling of a subradiant atom array to a cavity vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.17079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.17079v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By considering linear (Rayleigh) scattering of cold atoms inside an undriven high-finesse optical resonator, we experimentally demonstrate effects unique to a strongly coupled vacuum field. Arranging the atoms in an incommensurate lattice, with respect to the resonator mode, the scattering can be suppressed by destructive interference: resulting in a subradiant atomic array. We show however, that strong coupling leads to a drastic modification of the excitation spectrum, as evidenced by well-resolved vacuum Rabi splitting in the intensity of the fluctuations. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the strongly coupled vacuum mode induces polarization rotation in the linear scattering, which is incompatible with a linear polarizability model of isotropic objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.17079v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bence G\'abor, K. V. Adwaith, D\'aniel Varga, B\'alint S\'ark\"ozi, Andr\'as Dombi, T. W. Clark, F. I. B. Williams, David Nagy, Andr\'as Vukics, Peter Domokos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field at nucleus for ionized atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14535v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of the magnetic properties of atoms and nuclei was performed. A linear dependence between the strength of the magnetic field at the nucleus and the effective charge divided by the major quantum number were analyzed and explained. The calculations of the magnetic field at the nucleus were done for a wide set of electron configurations within the framework of relativistic Dirac-Hartree-Fock method. Results are compared to experimental results of $g$-factor measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14535v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Tucholski, Zygmunt Patyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Goldstino excitation through the tunneling transport in a Bose-Fermi mixture with explicitly broken supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14524v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the tunneling transport in a repulsively interacting ultracold Bose-Fermi mixture. A two-terminal model is applied to such a mixture and the supersymmetric-like tunneling current through the junction can be induced by the bias of fermion chemical potential between two reservoirs. The Goldstino, which is the Nambu-Goldstone fermionic mode associated with the spontaneous sypersymmetry breaking and appears as a gapped mode in the presence of the explicit supersymmetry breaking in existing Bose-Fermi mixtures, is found to contribute to the tunneling transport as a supercharge exchanging process. Our study provides a potential way to detect the Goldstino transport in cold atom experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14524v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.064512</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tingyu Zhang, Yixin Guo, Hiroyuki Tajima, Haozhao Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum thermodynamic derivation of the energy resolution limit in magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14687v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It was recently demonstrated that a multitude of realizations of several magnetic sensing technologies satisfy the energy resolution limit, which connects a quantity composed by the variance of the magnetic field estimate, the sensor volume and the measurement time, and having units of action, with $\hbar$. A first-principles derivation of this limit is still elusive. We here present such a derivation based on quantum thermodynamic arguments. We show that the energy resolution limit is a result of quantum thermodynamic work necessarily associated with quantum measurement and Landauer erasure, the work being exchanged with the magnetic field. We apply these considerations to atomic magnetometers, diamond magnetometers, and SQUIDs, spanning an energy resolution limit from $10^0\hbar$ to $10^7\hbar$. This connection between quantum thermodynamics and magnetometry can help advance quantum sensing technologies towards even more sensitive devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14687v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. K. Kominis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
