<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 04:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Slow molecular beams from a cryogenic buffer gas source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the properties of a cryogenic buffer gas source that uses a low temperature two-stage buffer gas cell to produce very slow beams of ytterbium monofluoride molecules. The molecules are produced by laser ablation inside the cell and extracted into a beam by a flow of cold helium. We measure the flux and velocity distribution of the beam as a function of ablation energy, helium flow rate, cell temperature, and the size of the gap between the first and second stages of the cell. We also compare the velocity distributions from one-stage and two-stage cells. The one-stage cell emits a beam with a speed of about 82 m s$^{-1}$ and a translational temperature of 0.63 K. The slowest beams are obtained using the two-stage cell at the lowest achievable cell temperature of 1.8 K. This beam has a peak velocity of 56 m s$^{-1}$ and a flux of $9 \times 10^9$ ground state molecules per steradian per pulse, with a substantial fraction at speeds below 40 m s$^{-1}$. These slow molecules can be decelerated further by radiation pressure slowing and then captured in a magneto-optical trap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01862v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. D. White, S. Popa, J. Mellado-Munoz, N. J. Fitch, B. E. Sauer, J. Lim, M. R. Tarbutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-optical atomic magnetometry using an elliptically polarized amplitude-modulated light wave</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a resonant interaction of an elliptically polarized light wave with $^{87}$Rb vapor (D$_1$ line) exposed to a transverse magnetic field. A $5$$\times$$5$$\times$$5$~mm$^3$ glass vapor cell is used for the experiments. The wave intensity is modulated at the frequency $\Omega_m$. By scanning $\Omega_m$ near the Larmor frequency $\Omega_L$, a magnetic resonance (MR) can be observed as a change in the ellipticity parameter of the wave polarization. This method for observing MR allows to significantly improve the signal-to-noise ratio compared to a classical Bell-Bloom scheme using a circularly polarized wave. The sensitivity of the magnetic field sensor is estimated to be $\approx\,$$130$~fT/$\surd$Hz in a $2$~kHz bandwidth, confidently competing with widely used Faraday-rotation Bell-Bloom schemes. The results can be used to develop a miniature all-optical magnetic field sensor for medicine and geophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01968v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Makarov, Katerina Kozlova, Denis Brazhnikov, Vladislav Vishnyakov, Andrey Goncharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internal diffraction dynamics of trilobite molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trilobite molecules are ultralong-range Rydberg molecules formed when a high angular momentum Rydberg electron scatters off of a ground-state atom. Their unique electronic structure and highly oscillatory potential energy curves support a rich variety of dynamical effects yet to be explored. We analyze the vibrational motion of these molecules using a framework of adiabatic wavepacket propagation dynamics and observe that for appropriate initial states, the trilobite potential acts as molecular diffraction grating. The quantum dynamic effects observed are explained using a Fourier analysis of the scattering potential and the associated scattered wavepacket. Furthermore, vibrational ground-states of the low angular momentum ultralong-range Rydberg molecules are found to be particularly suitable to prepare the relevant wavepackets. Hence, we propose a time resolved pump-probe scheme designed for the realization of the effect in question, and advertise the utilization of a single diatomic Rydberg molecule as a testbed for the study of exaggerated quantum dynamical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02134v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohan Srikumar, Seth T. Rittenhouse, Peter Schmelcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of 480 nm picosecond pulses for ultrafast excitation of Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atoms in Rydberg states are an important building block for emerging quantum technologies. While the excitation to the Rydberg orbitals are typically achieved in more than tens of nanoseconds, the physical limit is in fact much faster, at the ten picoseconds level. Here, we tackle such ultrafast Rydberg excitation of a Rubidium atom by designing a dedicated pulsed laser system generating 480 nm pulses of 10 ps duration. In particular, we improved upon our previous design by using an injection-seeded optical parametric amplifier (OPA) to obtain stable pulsed energy, decreasing the fluctuation from 30 % to 6 %. We then succeeded in ultrafast excitation of Rydberg atoms with excitation probability of ~90 %, not limited anymore by energy fluctuation but rather by the atomic state preparation, addressable in future works. This achievement broadens the range of applications of Rydberg atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02324v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tirumalasetty Panduranga Mahesh, Takuya Matsubara, Yuki Torii Chew, Takafumi Tomita, Sylvain de L\'es\'eleuc, Kenji Ohmori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence induced by dipole-dipole couplings between atomic species in rare-earth ion-doped Y$_2$SiO$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rare-earth ion doped crystals are state-of-the-art platforms for processing quantum information, particularly thanks to their excellent optical and spin coherence properties at cryogenic temperatures. Experimental observations have shown that the application of a static magnetic bias field significantly improves the coherence times in the rare-earth ions ensemble, but only a few studies have focused on its the dependency as a function of both magnetic field direction and amplitude. This is especially true for magnetic field amplitudes under the mT, and for low magnetic dipole moment ions. In this paper, we investigate the relationship between the magnetic field parameters and the decoherence caused by magnetic dipole-dipole coupling with the nearest neighbors nuclear spins in the crystal. The primary non-Kramers rare-earth ions investigated here are europium and praseodymium, but we also extend our study to the ytterbium Kramers ion due to its low magnetic dipole in the mT range. We perform theoretical investigations and simulations of the energy structure and coherence time evolution and identify good correspondences between experimental and simulated spin echo data. This work allows us to pinpoint the most relevant decoherence mechanisms in the considered magnetic field regime, and to predict favorable magnetic configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01958v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlotte Pignol, Antonio Ortu, Louis Nicolas, Virginia D'Auria, Sebastien Tanzilli, Thierry Chaneli\`ere, Mikael Afzelius, Jean Etesse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Spin-Motion Coupling in the Ultrafast Dynamics of Rydberg Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rydberg atoms in optical lattices and tweezers is now a well established platform for simulating quantum spin systems. However, the role of the atoms' spatial wavefunction has not been examined in detail experimentally. Here, we show a strong spin-motion coupling emerging from the large variation of the interaction potential over the wavefunction spread. We observe its clear signature on the ultrafast many-body nanosecond-dynamics of atoms excited to a Rydberg $S$ state, using picosecond pulses, from an unity-filling atomic Mott-insulator. We also propose a novel approach to tune arbitrarily the strength of the spin-motion coupling relative to the motional energy scale set by trapping potentials. Our work provides a new direction for exploring the dynamics of strongly-correlated quantum systems by adding the motional degree of freedom to the Rydberg simulation toolbox.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15575v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vineet Bharti, Seiji Sugawa, Masaya Kunimi, Vikas Singh Chauhan, Tirumalasetty Panduranga Mahesh, Michiteru Mizoguchi, Takuya Matsubara, Takafumi Tomita, Sylvain de L\'es\'eleuc, Kenji Ohmori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting Kerr-Newman Electromagnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12602v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study some of the properties of the $G \to 0$ limit of the Kerr-Newman solution of Einstein-Maxwell equations. Noting Carter's observation of the near equality between the $g = 2$ gyromagnetic ratio in the Kerr-Newman solution and that of the electron, we discuss additional such coincidences relating to the Kerr-Newman multipoles and properties of the electron. In contrast to the Coulomb field, this spinning Maxwell field has a finite Lagrangian. Moreover, by evaluating the Lagrangian for the superposition of two such Kerr-Newman electromagnetic fields on a flat background, we are able to find their interaction potential. This yields a correction to the Coulomb interaction due to the spin of the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12602v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sajad Aghapour, Lars Andersson, Kjell Rosquist, Tomasz Smo{\l}ka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
