<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 05:01:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Collapse in Exotic Atoms and Its Effect on Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the energy structures of muonic Ar atoms and find the muon orbital collapses at a critical angular momentum $l_c$ using density-functional theory (DFT). The $l_c$ may provide an upper limit for the muon-captured states in muon-Ar collisions. We confirm the existence of this upper limit by calculating the state-specified capture probability using the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation (TDSE) and a classical trajectory Monte Carlo (CTMC) methods with the single-active-particle approximation. Modifying the mapping between the classical binding energy and the principal quantum number led to a reasonable agreement in the state-specified muon capture probabilities obtained by the TDSE and CTMC methods. We also propose a simple method to estimate $l_c$ for exotic noble atoms from atomic model potentials. The estimated values agree with those calculated by DFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18747v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. M. Tong, K. Tokesi, D. Kato, T. Okumura, S. Okada, T. Azuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transferring vibrational states of trapped atoms via a Rydberg electron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show theoretically that it is possible to coherently transfer vibrational excitation between trapped neutral atoms over a micrometer apart. To this end we consider three atoms, where two are in the electronic ground state and one is excited to a Rydberg state whose electronic orbital overlaps with the positional wave functions of the two ground-state atoms. The resulting scattering of the Rydberg electron with the ground-state atoms provides the interaction required to transfer vibrational excitation from one trapped atom to the other. By numerically investigating the dependence of the transfer dynamics on the distance between traps and their relative frequencies we find that there is a "sweet spot" where the transfer of a vibrational excitation is nearly perfect and fast compared to the Rydberg lifetime. We investigate the robustness of this scenario with respect to changes of the parameters. In addition, we derive a intuitive effective Hamiltonian which explains the observed dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19016v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Pendse, Sebastian W\"uster, Matthew T. Eiles, Alexander Eisfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blue laser induced bright red fluorescence in hot cesium vapor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have observed laser-induced fluorescence using 456 nm laser radiation, resonant with the 6S1/2-7P3/2 transition in Cs atoms. It includes red emission lines in the range of 580-730 nm and a prominent line at 852 nm corresponding to the 6P3/2-6S1/2 transition. A T-shaped all-sapphire cell with a length of 1 cm, containing Cs atomic vapor and capable of being heated up to 500 oC, was used. The laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) power at 852 nm was investigated as a function of the cell temperature. The maximum LIF power was achieved at 130 oC, while a significant decrease was observed around 300 oC. At 130 oC, the Doppler-broadened LIF spectrum at 852 nm exhibited self-conversion, resulting in the formation of two distinct peaks within the spectrum. The LIF power at 852 nm was also studied as a function of the 456 nm radiation power. The Cs cell demonstrated potential as an efficient optical filter and down-converter, effectively transforming 456 nm radiation into 852 nm radiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19081v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armen Sargsyan, Anahit Gogyan, David Sarkisyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanofiber-based second-order atomic Bragg lattice for collectively enhanced coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose two experimental schemes for nanofiber-based compensated optical dipole traps that optimize the collective coupling of a one-dimensional array of atoms. The created array satisfies the second-order Bragg condition ($d=\lambda$), facilitating constructive interference of atomic radiation into the nanofiber and generating coherent back reflections of guided modes. Both schemes use far-off resonance light to minimize light scattering and atomic heating. Our numerical study focuses on $^{87}$Rb atoms. The results are generalizable to different atomic species and could improve the study of collective and nonlinear atomic effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19343v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Vera, P. Solano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nondipole circularly polarized laser-assisted photoelectron emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically study atomic laser-assisted photoelectric emission (LAPE) beyond the electric dipole approximation. We present a theoretical description for first-order nondipole corrections ($O(c^{-1})$ where $c$ is the speed of light) to the nonrelativistic description of the laser-atom interaction for a strong circularly polarized infrared (IR) laser field combined with a train of extreme-ultraviolet (XUV) laser pulses. We investigate the photoelectron momentum distribution (PMD) as the product of two main contributions: the intra- and interpulse factors. Whereas the interpulse factor gives rise to a sideband pattern with a shift opposite to the IR beam propagation direction, the intrapulse factor forms an angular streaking pattern following the IR time-dependent polarization direction. We explore the transition of the PMD from the dipole to the nondipole framework, showing the gradual break of the forward-backward symmetry as the laser parameters are varied. Furthermore, we find non-zero contributions in dipole forbidden directions independent of the IR polarization state, wherein Cooper-\textit{like} minima are observed. Our work lays a theoretical foundation for understanding time-resolved nondipole LAPE in cutting-edge ultrafast experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19378v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Della Picca, J. M. Randazzo, S. D. L\'opez, M. F. Ciappina, D. G. Arb\'o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High precision spectroscopy of trilobite Rydberg molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform three-photon photoassociation to obtain high resolution spectra of $^{87}$Rb trilobite dimers for the principal quantum numbers $n = 22,24,25,26$, and 27. The large binding energy of the molecules in combination with a relative spectroscopic resolution of $10^{-4}$ provides a rigorous benchmark for existing theoretical models. A recently developed Green's function framework, which circumvents the convergence issues that afflicted previous studies,, is employed to theoretically reproduce the vibrational spectrum of the molecule with high accuracy. The relatively large molecular binding energy are primarily determined by the low energy $S$-wave electron-atom scattering length, thereby allowing us to extract the $^3S_1$ scattering phase shift with unprecedented accuracy, at low energy regimes inaccessible to free electrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19710v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Exner, Rohan Srikumar, Richard Bl\"attner, Matthew T. Eiles, Peter Schmelcher, Herwig Ott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muonium fine structure: theory update, tests of Lorentz violation and experimental prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the status of the QED calculations for the muonium $2S_{1/2}-2P_{3/2}$ energy interval and provide the updated theoretical value of $9874.357\pm0.001\,\mathrm{MHz}$. Additionally, we present a model for probing Lorentz-violating coefficients within the Standard Model Extension framework using the fine structure measurement in the presence and absence of a weak external magnetic field, enabling novel tests of CPT and Lorentz symmetry. Using Monte Carlo simulations, we estimate that a precision of $\sim 10\,\mathrm{kHz}$ on the isolated $2S_{1/2}, F=1 - 2P_{3/2}, F=1$ transition could be achievable employing Ramsey's separate oscillatory fields (SOF) technique. Collecting the required statics will become feasible with the upcoming High-Intensity Muon Beam (HiMB) at the Paul Scherrer Institute (PSI) in Switzerland. These advancements will enable precise tests of radiative QED corrections and nuclear self-energy contributions, while also providing tests of new physics and sensitivity to unconstrained coefficients for Lorentz violation within the Standard Model Extension framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19580v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Blumer, Svenja Geissmann, Arnaldo J. Vargas, Gianluca Janka, Ben Ohayon, Paolo Crivelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the $\text{1}^\text{3}\text{S}_\text{1} \to \text{2}^\text{3}\text{S}_\text{1}$ interval in positronium using field-ionization of Rydberg states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02443v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a new 40 ppb measurement of the positronium $\text{1}^\text{3}\text{S}_\text{1} \to \text{2}^\text{3}\text{S}_\text{1}$ interval using pulsed two-photon optical spectroscopy. The transition is detected via field-ionization of atoms excited from the 2S to the 20P Rydberg state. Precise Monte-Carlo line-shape simulations allow for the accounting of effects such as Doppler and AC Stark shifts, while an optical heterodyne measurement of the excitation laser pulse is used to correct for laser frequency chirp. A value of $1\,233\,607\,210.5\pm 49.6\, \mathrm{MHz}$ was obtained. This scheme allows for the measurement of the velocity distribution of positronium atoms to correct for the second-order Doppler effect. This is the major source of systematic uncertainty expected for future measurements of this transition with a CW laser, thus, our technique paves the way toward a new generation of a high precision determination of this interval in positronium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02443v4</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael W. Heiss, Lucas de Sousa Borges, Artem Golovizin, Paolo Crivelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Informational analysis of the confinement of an electron in an asymmetric double quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22538v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A quasi-unidimensional one-electron double quantum dot is studied within the framework of Shannon informational entropy. Its confinement potential, which is described by an asymmetric harmonic-gaussian function, consists of two wells separated by a potential barrier, and the asymmetry of the potential in respect to the center of the barrier is parameterized by $x_0$. In this work we employ Shannon informational entropy as a tool to investigate changes in the electronic confinement resulting from the modifications in the degree of asymmetry $x_0$. In particular, we notice that Shannon entropy turns out to be very sensitive to the change from the symmetric to the antisymmetric regime. Moreover, we show that Shannon entropy as a function of $x_0$ for an electronic excited state displays an irregular behavior whenever the state energy is in the vicinity of a local extreme (a maximum or a minimum); connected with this we observe an oscillatory behavior of the energy of the excited states as a function of $x_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22538v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physb.2024.416769</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica B: Condensed Matter 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>W. S. Nascimento, A. M. Maniero, F. V. Prudente, C. R. de Carvalho, Ginette Jalbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentz violating backgrounds from quadratic, shift-symmetric, ultralight dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17636v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider an effective theory for a shift-symmetric, quadratically-coupled, ultralight spin-0 field. The leading CP-conserving interactions with Standard Model fields in the effective theory arise at dimension 8. We discuss the renormalization group evolution and positivity bounds on these operators, as well as their possible UV origins. Assuming that the spin-0 field is associated with an ultralight dark matter candidate, we discuss the effects of the dimension-8 operators on experiments searching for the oscillation of fundamental constants and Lorentz violation. We find that the direct bounds on these two effects are of similar strength but rather weak, corresponding to a UV cutoff scale of keV order, as they are mediated by dimension-8 operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17636v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP08(2024)114</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2024, 114 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Minyuan Jiang, Benjamin D. Pecjak, Gilad Perez, Somasundaram Sankaranarayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Architecture for fast implementation of qLDPC codes with optimized Rydberg gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18809v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an implementation of bivariate bicycle codes (Nature {\bf 627}, 778 (2024)) based on long-range Rydberg gates between stationary neutral atom qubits. An optimized layout of data and ancilla qubits reduces the maximum Euclidean communication distance needed for non-local parity check operators. An optimized Rydberg gate pulse design enables $\sf CZ$ entangling operations with fidelity ${\mathcal F}&gt;0.999$ at a distance greater than $12~\mu\rm m$. The combination of optimized layout and gate design leads to a quantum error correction cycle time of $\sim 1.28~\rm ms$ for a $[[144,12,12]]$ code, nearly a factor of two improvement over previous designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18809v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Poole, T. M. Graham, M. A. Perlin, M. Otten, M. Saffman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic generation with topological edge states and electron-electron interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04114v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been found previously that the presence or absence of topological edge states in the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model has a huge impact on harmonic generation spectra. More specifically, the yield of harmonics for harmonic orders that correspond to photon energies below the band gap is many orders of magnitude different in the trivial and topological phase. It is shown in this work that this effect is still present if electron-electron interaction is taken into account, i.e., if a Hubbard term is added to the SSH Hamiltonian. To that end, finite SSH-Hubbard chains at half filling are considered that are short enough to be accessible to exact diagonalization but already showing edge states in the topological phase. We show that the huge difference in the harmonic yield between the trivial and the topological phase can be reproduced with few-level models employing only the many-body ground state and a few excited many-body states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04114v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siamak Pooyan, Dieter Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
