<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 01:25:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Silicon nitride photonic integrated circuit for controlling chip-based cold-atom inertial sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have developed a silicon nitride based photonic integrated circuit (PIC) that is responsible for the cooling, pumping and imaging of an on-chip based cold atom inertial sensor. The photonic integrated circuit consists of two chips placed next to each other and has a total area of 2x2~cm$^2$. This greatly minimizes the area needed while still having all the optical control functions to create, control and measure a magneto-optical trap (MOT). The piezo electric material Lead Zirconate Titanate (PZT) on the PIC is employed for phase shifting a Mach-Zehnder type configuration where extinction ratios up to 50 dB and switching speeds of 1 MHz are achieved. For the first time two and three dimensional optical traps for rubidium 87 atoms are realized using an active photonic integrated circuit. For the three dimensional optical trap, we measure $7\times 10^7$ atoms with a temperature of 270~$\mu$K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03279v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Snijders, S. Hello, B. Wirtschafter, G. Feugnet, L. A. Tran, M. M. Zafar, R. Dekker, C. I. Westbrook, A. Brignon, M. Dupont-Nivet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-loop vacuum polarization in a Coulomb field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The leading-order two-loop vacuum-polarization potential, linear in the Coulomb field of a nucleus, was first derived in the seminal 1955 work of K\"all\'en-Sabry. The higher-order two-loop vacuum-polarization corrections, however, have remained unknown until now. In this work, we compute Coulomb corrections to the K\"all\'en-Sabry potential, specifically those involving three, five, and seven Coulomb interactions inside the vacuum-polarization loop. The potentials are evaluated in momentum space and subsequently used to calculate one-electron energy shifts. Our results drastically reduce the theoretical uncertainty of the two-loop vacuum-polarization contribution to transition energies, which is required for next-generation tests of bound-state QED in heavy one and few-electron ions as well as for the determination of nuclear charge radii.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03284v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. A. Volkov, V. A. Yerokhin, Z. Harman, C. H. Keitel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Painted loading: a toolkit for loading spatially large optical tweezer arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Arrays of neutral atoms in optical tweezers are widely used in quantum simulation and computation, and precision frequency metrology. The capabilities of these arrays are enhanced by maximising the number of available sites. Here we increase the spatial extent of a two-dimensional array of strontium-88 atoms by sweeping the frequency of the cooling light to move the atomic reservoir across the array. We load arrays with vertical heights of &gt;100 {\mu}m, exceeding the height of an array loaded from a static reservoir by a factor of &gt;3. We investigate the site-to-site atom number distribution, tweezer lifetime, and temperature, achieving an average temperature across the array of 1.49(3) {\mu}K. By controlling the frequency sweep we show it is possible to control the distribution of atoms across the array, including uniform and non-uniformly loaded arrays, and arrays with selectively loaded regions. We explain our results using a rate equation model which is in good qualitative agreement with the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03473v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mitchell J. Walker, Ryuji Moriya, Jack D. Segal, Liam A. P. Gallagher, Matthew Hill, Fr\'ed\'eric Leroux, Zhongxiao Xu, Matthew P. A. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid quantum memory leveraging slow-light and gradient-echo duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02810v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate a hybrid quantum memory that combines Gradient Echo Memory (GEM) and Electromagnetically Induced Transparency (EIT) protocols for reversible mapping between light and atomic coherence. By leveraging GEM and EIT complementarity, we realize time-to-frequency and frequency-to-time conversion mechanisms for spectro-temporal modes. This capability provides a versatile tool for quantum communication, where coherent frequency-time conversion enhances network interoperability. In addition, the protocol may enable fundamental studies of atomic coherence, including investigations of Rydberg polaritons and mapping of single Rydberg excitations and ionic impurities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02810v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanis{\l}aw Kurzyna, Mateusz Mazelanik, Wojciech Wasilewski, Micha{\l} Parniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Versatile, open-source program for simulating high-harmonic generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light sources based on high-harmonic generation (HHG) underpin ultrafast spectroscopy experiments across a large range of photon energies, spanning from the extreme-ultraviolet to the soft x-ray. To this day their design, implementation and improvement presents uniqe challenges, but can be aided by numerical tools. Here we present a new simulation program designed for this purpose, which accurately takes both macroscopic and microscopic aspects of high-harmonic generation into account and is therefore applicable across the broad range of parameters that HHG based light sources are today utilized in. The program is validated by calculating harmonic emission in four common experimental configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02867v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian A. Schr\"oder, Reinhard Kienberger, Stephen R. Leone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast single-photon interference with a dipole qubit in a nanocavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03428v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The stationary spectrum of individual dipole emitters in plasmonic nanocavities has been studied for a range of cavity geometries and dipole configurations. Less is known about the coherent dynamics of single photon creation in the nanocavity near field by an excited dipole. We address this gap by developing a Lorentzian kernel approximation that solves the time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation that describes the coupled dipole-photon dynamics in the single-excitation manifold. Our approach encodes the broadband nature of the nanocavity field through a non-Markovian memory kernel, derived from macroscopic QED theory. For a two-level dipole near a metallic nanosphere, we show that the single photon probability density in frequency space evolves in strong coupling from an initially localized source at the qubit frequency into a Rabi doublet over a timescale governed by the kernel spectrum. This dynamical crossover is accompanied by the formation of single-photon interference patterns in frequency and time, propagating coherently over a timescale limited by the shape of kernel spectrum to $\sim 100-150$ fs, which is accessible to ultrafast spectroscopy. We also show that the stationary spectrum of the coupled system can be manipulated by driving the nanocavity field using coherent pulses with variable spectral bandwidth. Using single-photon pulses narrower than the kernel spectrum, the Rabi splitting in a system that supports strong coupling can be effectively removed. The applicability of our results to other dipole-nanocavity configurations is discussed and a general strong coupling criterion for nanocavities is formulated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03428v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athul S. Rema, Adri\'an E. Rubio L\'opez, Felipe Herrera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic magnetic field imaging with hot atoms via single-pixel imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13869v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, sensors based on hot atomic vapor cells have emerged as a compact and highly sensitive means of measuring magnetic fields. Such sensors have been deployed in the field for the measurement of, e.g. biological systems, representing a promising practical application of quantum technologies. However, it remains challenging to obtain high-resolution magnetic field images from these sensors, and in most cases the spatial resolution of the system is limited by the sensor size. Here, we demonstrate the combination of single-pixel imaging (SPI) techniques with an atom vapor. Faraday magnetometer to achieve microscopic magnetic field imaging. We demonstrate magnetic field imaging with a spatial resolution of $\approx~62.5\mu m$, limited only by the resolution of our DMD projection system and the absence of magnetic shielding in our experimental setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13869v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyril Torre, Jordan Brass, Sebastien Bisdee, Mohammed T. Rasheed, Giacomo Ferranti, Carrie A. Weidner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Dick Effect for AI-based Dynamic Gravimeter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17765v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Atom interferometer (AI)-based dynamic gravimeter enable high-precision absolute gravity measurements, crucial for applications in geophysics, navigation, resource exploration, and metrology. Understanding their underlying mechanisms and minimizing measurement noise are essential for enhancing performance. This work investigates the gravity measurement noise in AI-based systems induced by the dead time of the classical accelerometer. Using actual dynamic gravity measurement data, we demonstrate that a dead time of 0.12 s introduces significant gravity measurement noise of 8 mGal. To elucidate the mechanism of this noise, we derive a formula for this noise in frequency domain, identifying high-frequency aliasing as its source. Analysis of the derived expressions indicates that reducing the dead time duration and suppressing the high-frequency noise of the acceleration are effective strategies for mitigating this noise. This work provides significant insights for noise analysis and future scheme design of AI-based dynamic gravimeters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17765v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Zhang Wang, Xi Chen, Jin-Ting Li, Dan-Fang Zhang, Wei-Hao Xu, Jia-Yi Wei, Jia-Qi Zhong, Biao Tang, Lin Zhou, Jin Wang, Ming-Sheng Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong-Field Photoelectron Interferometry with Near-Single-Cycle Yb Lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The concept of using photoelectron interferometry in short laser fields to probe electron dynamics and target structures was introduced more than two decades ago. However, the quality of experimental data has remained insufficient for quantitative analysis, largely due to the instability of few-cycle Ti:Sa laser pulses, the current workhorse of short pulses. Here, we report the first systematic strong-field ionization experiments performed with industrial-grade, carrier-envelope-phase (CEP) stabilized, near-single-cycle Yb lasers. By measuring photoelectron momentum distributions in the direct-ionization regime, we show that single-cycle cosine-shaped pulses can separate and enhance both spider-leg and fishbone holographic structures. The spider-leg structure enables extraction of the electron scattering phase from the Ar atomic potential-information typically accessible only through attosecond metrology, while the fishbone structure reveals the orbital-parity contrast between Ar atoms and nitrogen molecules. Our measurements are quantitatively reproduced by both semiclassical Herman-Kluk-propagator and \textit{ab initio} simulations, paving the way for precision studies of electron-molecule scattering with widely accessible industrial-grade lasers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01866v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmudul Hasan, Phi-Hung Tran, Jingsong Gao, Van-Hung Hoang, Ming-Shian Tsai, Ming-Chang Chen, Uwe Thumm, Charles Lewis Cocke, Chii-Dong Lin, Anh-Thu Le, and Meng Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rayleigh-Taylor instability in a binary quantum fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19807v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Instabilities, where small fluctuations seed the formation of large-scale structures, govern dynamics in a variety of fluid systems. The Rayleigh-Taylor instability (RTI), present from tabletop to astronomical scales, is an iconic example characterized by mushroom-shaped incursions appearing when immiscible fluids are forced together. Despite its ubiquity, RTI experiments are challenging; here, we report the observation of the RTI in an immiscible binary superfluid consisting of a two-component Bose-Einstein condensate. We force these components together to initiate the instability, and observe the growth of mushroom-like structures. The interface can also be stabilized, allowing us to spectroscopically measure the "ripplon" interface modes. Lastly, we use matter-wave interferometry to transform the superfluid velocity field at the interface into a vortex chain. These results-in agreement with our theory-demonstrate the close connection between the RTI in classical and quantum fluids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19807v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adw9752</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. Adv. 11, eadw9752 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yanda Geng, Junheng Tao, Mingshu Zhao, Shouvik Mukherjee, Stephen Eckel, Gretchen K. Campbell, Ian B. Spielman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Distinguishability and Determinism in Newly Created Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01203v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose and analyze experiments to test distinguishability and determinism in atoms. As a first step, we consider experiments to test if newly created atoms are distinguishable from each other due to small differences in the nuclear magnetic moment. The idea is to measure the hyperfine splitting for newly created stable isotopes and compare them to the same isotopes found in nature. The three cases analyzed are strontium-87 with an odd number of neutrons, lutetium-175 with an odd number of protons, and lutetium-176 with an odd number of protons and neutrons. We also propose that a time-dependent nuclear magnetic moment may enable deterministic tracking of the life cycle of an isotope, and prediction of age since creation and time until decay of radioisotopes. The case of thulium-170 is considered, it is particularly interesting as a radioisotope with an odd number of protons and neutrons. More generally, we argue that any atomic transition could change in time, either due to the atomic nucleus or to the electron charge distribution. The latter could be tested in a dual atomic clock in a ladder configuration to search for the aging of an electronic transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01203v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark G. Raizen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
