<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 02:55:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the ultra-narrow $^3\!P_2 \rightarrow \, ^3\!P_0$ electric quadrupole transition in Ni$^{12+}$ ion for an optical clock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Ni$^{12+}$ ion features an electronic transition with a natural width of only 8 mHz, allowing for a highly stable optical clock. We predict that the energy of this strongly forbidden $3s^2 3p^4\, ^3\!P_2 \rightarrow 3s^2 3p^4 \, ^3\!P_0$ electric quadrupole transition is 20081(10) cm$^{-1}$. For this, we use both a hybrid approach combining configuration interaction (CI) with coupled-cluster (CC) method and a pure CI calculation for the complete 16-electron system, ensuring convergence. The resulting very small theoretical uncertainty of only 0.05\% allowed us to find the transition experimentally in a few hours, yielding an energy of 20078.984(10) cm$^{-1}$. This level of agreement for a 16-electron system is unprecedented and qualifies our method for future calculations of many other complex atomic systems. While paving the way for a high-precision optical clock based on Ni$^{12+}$, our theory and code development will also enable better predictions for other highly charged ions and other complex atomic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05386v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Cheung, Sergey G. Porsev, Dmytro Filin, Marianna S. Safronova, Malte Wehrheim, Lukas J. Spie{\ss}, Shuying Chen, Alexander Wilzewski, Jos\'e R. Crespo L\'opez-Urrutia, Piet O. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Universal Transformer-Based Coarse-Grained Molecular Dynamics Framework for Protein Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel, universal, Transformer-based coarse-grained molecular dynamics (CG-MD) framework for simulating protein dynamics. Our trained model generalizes to all protein systems, regardless of sequence length or number of chains. First, we extend a tree-structured protein representation to accommodate multi-chain proteins, demonstrating sub-angstrom-level accuracy in reconstructing a 169-amino-acid protein structure. Then, representing collective variables as language-like sequences, we use a Transformer network as a propagator for stochastic differential equations, generating MD trajectories over 10,000 times faster than all-atom MD simulations. This single trained model accurately simulates both single-chain and two-chain proteins, and the generated trajectories closely resemble all-atom MD trajectories in their RMSD profiles. With sufficient training data, we anticipate that our model can achieve universality across all proteins, offering a ~10,000x acceleration of MD simulations with high accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05909v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinzhen Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of General-order Relativistic Coupled-cluster Theory to Estimate Electric-field Response Clock Properties of Ca$^+$ and Yb$^+$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate calculations of electric dipole polarizabilities ($\alpha_d$), quadrupole moments ($\Theta$), and quadrupole polarizabilities ($\alpha_q$) for the clock states of the singly charged calcium (Ca$^+$) and ytterbium (Yb$^+$) ions are presented using the general-order relativistic coupled-cluster (RCC) theory. Precise knowledge of these quantities is immensely useful for estimating uncertainties caused by major systematic effects such as the linear and quadratic Stark shifts and black-body radiation shifts in the optical Ca$^+$ and Yb$^+$ clocks. A finite-field approach is adopted for estimating these quantities, in which the first-order and second-order energy level shifts are analyzed by varying strengths of externally applied electric field and field-gradient. To achieve high-accuracy results in the heavier Yb$^+$ ion, we first calculate these properties in a relatively lighter clock candidate, Ca$^+$, which involves similar clock states. From these analyses, we learned that electron correlation effects arising from triple excitations in the RCC theory contribute significantly to the above properties, and are decisive factors in bringing the calculated values closer to the experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06225v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>YanMei Yu, B. K. Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Continuous Pump-Probe Experiment to Observe Rydberg Wave Packet Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rydberg atoms remain in the limelight due to their applications in quantum optics and information technologies. In this work, the dynamics of Rydberg atoms stored in a momentum spectrometer by an all-optical trap is studied by ionizing them in the field of a continuous wave optical dipole trap. While the addition of the optical dipole trap allows to further cool the atoms, it comes at the expense of the time of flight information which is required to retrieve photoelectron momentum distributions. Here, we report on a method that extends the standard COLTRIMS (cold target recoil ion momentum spectroscopy) technique, including continuous wave lasers in pump-probe schemes, by utilizing coincidence measurements. In particular, the photoionization of atomic $^6$Li initially in a spin-polarized $2^{2}P_{3/2}$ state is explored. Multi-photon excitation from a tunable-mode femtosecond pulse is exploited to produce Rydberg atoms, which can then be ionized by the dipole field. The resulting ionization rate becomes explicitly time-dependent, and analyzing its structure unlocks the real-time atomic dynamics on nanosecond time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06507v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin L. Romans, Kyle Foster, Shruti Majumdar, Bishnu P. Acharya, Onyx Russ, A. H. N. C. De Silva, Daniel Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of ultracold triatomic molecules by electric microwave association</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A theoretical model is proposed for the formation of ultracold ground-state triatomic molecules in weakly bound energy levels. The process is driven by the electric component of a microwave field, which induces the association of an ultracold atom colliding with an ultracold diatomic molecule. This model is exemplified using $^{39}$K atoms and $^{23}$Na$^{39}$K molecules, both in their ground states, a scenario of experimental relevance. The model assumes that the dynamics of the association are dominated by the long-range van der Waals interaction between $^{39}$K and $^{23}$Na$^{39}$K. The electric microwave association mechanism relies on the intrinsic electric dipole moment of $^{23}$Na$^{39}$K, which drives transitions between its lowest rotational levels ( $j$=0 and $j$=1). The energies of the uppermost triatomic energy levels are computed by numerically solving coupled Schr\"odinger equations using the Mapped Fourier Grid Hamiltonian method. Measurable association rates are derived within the framework of a perturbative approach. This method of electric microwave association provides an alternative to atom-molecule association via magnetic Feshbach resonances for forming ultracold, deeply bound triatomic molecules, and is applicable to a wide range of polar diatomic molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06590v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baraa Shammout, Leon Karpa, Silke Ospelkaus, Eberhard Tiemann, Olivier Dulieu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Coherent Quantum Tunneling of a Massive Atomic Cluster with 435 u</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tunneling is a genuine quantum phenomenon typically observed in low-mass particles such as electrons. However, it fades rapidly as mass increases due to the exponential decay of the matter-wave penetration depth. Cooling atoms to nanokelvin temperatures enhances their matter wave characteristics. Here, we report the observation of coherent quantum tunneling of a bonded cluster composed of 5 ultracold rubidium-87 atoms, collectively forming a massive object of 435 u. Using a double-well superlattice, integer occupancy states are prepared, with atoms bonded via strong on-site interactions. We demonstrate that the exponential base of tunneling strength can be tuned to approach unity, drastically reducing its decay for heavier masses and enabling a scalable strategy. Moreover, tunneling is harnessed to create spatially separated Schr\"{o}dinger-cat states (~320 nm apart), achieving quantum enhancement in measurements. This work markedly raises the mass threshold for quantum tunneling and paves the way for quantum metrology with massive particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06246v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Zhang, Yong-Kui Wang, Yi Zheng, Hai-Tao Bai, Bing Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion mediated pairing in the Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida to Efimov transition regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06266v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yoshida (RKKY) interaction and Efimov physics are two distinct quantum phenomena in condensed matter and nuclear physics, respectively. The RKKY interaction describes correlations between impurities mediated by an electron gas, while Efimov physics describes universal bound states of three particles with resonant interactions. Recently, both effects have been observed in Bose-Fermi mixtures in the weak and resonant interaction regimes, respectively. Intriguing conjectures exist to elucidate how the two phenomena meet in the transition regime where the mixture is strongly interacting. In this work, we explore the RKKY-Efimov transition in a mixture of bosonic Cs-133 and fermionic Li-6 near a tunable interspecies Feshbach resonance. From dispersion and relaxation measurements, we find that the transition is highlighted by a fermion-mediated scattering resonance between Cs atoms and a weaker resonance on Li atoms. These resonances represent reactive scattering of Cs and Li atoms in the many-body regime, which reduces to an Efimov resonance in the thermal gas regime. Our observation demonstrates the intriguing interplay of two-, three-, and many-body physics in an Bose-Fermi mixture that connects condensed matter physics, nuclear physics and quantum many-body chemistry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geyue Cai, Henry Ando, Sarah McCusker, Cheng Chin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the QCD $\bar \theta$ term with paramagnetic molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The experimental search for CP violation in paramagnetic atomic and molecular systems has made impressive progress in recent years. This has led to strong upper limits on the electron electric dipole moment. The same measurements can also be used to constrain hadronic sources of CP violation through CP-violating interactions between the electrons and the nucleus. We employ heavy-baryon chiral perturbation theory to compute such CP-violating semileptonic electron-nucleus interactions arising from the QCD theta term. We sharpen earlier results by determining the relevant short-distance effects and by an explicit two-loop calculation of meson-photon diagrams. We derive a bound of $|\bar{\theta}| &lt; 1.5 \cdot 10^{-8}$ at $90\%$ confidence, based on HfF$^+$ experiments at JILA. A further experimental improvement of one to two orders of magnitude would make paramagnetic molecular electric dipole moment experiments competitive with the neutron and diamagnetic atom program in constraining strong CP violation and higher-dimensional CP-odd quark-gluon operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06406v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heleen Mulder, Rob Timmermans, Jordy de Vries</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Magnon-Polarons in the Fermi-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interplay of magnetic excitations and itinerant charge carriers is a ubiquitous phenomenon in strongly correlated electron systems. In the vicinity of magnetically ordered phases, strong interactions between itinerant quasiparticles and magnetic excitations can result in the dramatic renormalization of both. A key theoretical question is understanding the renormalization of the magnon quasiparticle, a collective spin excitation, upon doping a magnetic insulator. Here, we report the observation of a new type of quasiparticle arising from the dressing of a magnon with the doped holes of a cold atom Fermi-Hubbard system, i.e. a magnon-Fermi-polaron. Utilizing Raman excitation with controlled momentum in a doped, spin-polarized band insulator, we address the spectroscopic properties of the magnon-polaron. In an undoped system with strong interactions, photoexcitation produces magnons, whose properties are accurately described by spin wave theory. We measure the evolution of the photoexcitation spectra as we move away from this limit to produce magnon-polarons due to dressing of the magnons by charge excitations. We observe a shift in the polaron energy with doping that is strongly dependent on the injected momentum, accompanied by a reduction of spectral weight in the probed energy window. We anticipate that the technique introduced here, which is the analog of inelastic neutron scattering, will provide atomic quantum simulators access to the dynamics of a wide variety of excitations in strongly correlated phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06757v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max L. Prichard, Zengli Ba, Ivan Morera, Benjamin M. Spar, David A. Huse, Eugene Demler, Waseem S. Bakr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling of a continuous superradiant laser on the sub-mHz $^1$S$_0\,\rightarrow\,^3$P$_0$ transition in neutral strontium-88</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06575v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Continuous superradiance using a narrow optical transition has the potential to improve the short-term stability of state-of-the-art optical clocks. Even though pulsed superradiant emission on a mHz linewidth clock transition has been shown, true continuous operation, without Fourier limitation, has turned out to be extremely challenging. The trade-off between maintaining a high atomic flux while minimizing decoherence effects presents a significant obstacle. Here, we discuss the design of a machine that could overcome this problem by combining a high-flux continuous beam of ultra cold strontium atoms with a bowtie cavity for the generation of superradiant lasing. To evaluate the feasibility of our design, we present simulation results for continuous high-efficiency cooling, loading, and pumping to the upper lasing state inside the bowtie cavity. We then present two different models for stimulating the generated superradiant field by taking into account position-dependent shifts, collisional decoherence, light shifts, and atom loss. Finally, we estimate a laser linewidth of less than 100 mHz, limited by atom number fluctuations, and resulting in an output power of hundreds of fW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06575v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swadheen Dubey, Georgy A. Kazakov, Benedikt Heizenreder, Sheng Zhou, Shayne Bennetts, Stefan Alaric Sch\"affer, Ananya Sitaram, Florian Schreck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulated optical molasses cooling of trapped antihydrogen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16512v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically and computationally investigate the cooling of antihydrogen, $\bar{H}$, using optical molasses cooling. This updates the results in Ref. [1] to the current capabilities of the ALPHA experiment. Through Monte Carlo simulation, we show that $\bar{H}$s do not give the standard cooling even in an ideal optical molasses because of their small mass and large transition frequency. For optical molasses cooling in the ALPHA trap, the photons are constrained to travel in one direction only. It is only through the phase space mixing in the trap that cooling in all directions can be achieved. We explore the nontrivial role that laser intensity plays in the cooling. We also investigate the possibility for simultaneously cooling atoms in either of the trapped ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16512v3</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6455/adaf88</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Spencer J. Walsh, C. {\O}. Rasmussen, F. Robicheaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical clock based on two-photon spectroscopy of the nuclear transition in ion $^{229}$Th in a monochromatic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15669v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For the isotope $^{229}$Th we investigate the possibility of two-photon laser spectroscopy of the nuclear clock transition (148.38 nm) using intense monochromatic laser field at twice the wavelength (296.76 nm). Our estimates show that due to the electron bridge process in the doubly ionized ion $^{229}$Th$^{2+}$ the sufficient intensity of a continuous laser field is about 10-100 kW/cm$^2$, which is within the reach of modern laser systems. This unique possibility is an result of the presence in the electronic spectrum of the ion $^{229}$Th$^{2+}$ of an exceptionally close intermediate (for the two-photon transition) energy level, forming a strong dipole ($E1$) transition with the ground state at the wavelength of 297.86 nm, which differs from the probe field wavelength (296.76 nm) by only 1.1 nm. The obtained results can be used for the practical creation of ultra-precise nuclear optical clocks based on thorium-229 ions. In addition, we develop an alternative approach to the description of the electron bridge phenomenon in an isolated ion (atom) using the hyperfine interaction operator, that is important for the general quantum theory of an atom. In particular, this approach shows that the contribution to the electron bridge from the nuclear quadrupole moment can be comparable to the contribution from the nuclear magnetic moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15669v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Yudin, A. V. Taichenachev, O. N. Prudnikov, M. Yu. Basalaev, A. N. Goncharov, S. V. Chepurov, V. G. Pal'chikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic configuration-interaction and coupled-cluster calculations of Ir$^{17+}$ transition energies and properties for optical clock applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01112v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The transition energies and properties of the Ir$^{17+}$ ion are calculated using the Kramers-restricted configuration-interaction (KRCI) and Fock-space coupled-cluster (FSCC) methods within the Dirac-Coulomb-Gaunt Hamiltonian framework. These calculations show several forbidden optical transitions between the $4f^{13}5s$ ground state and the $4f^{14}$ and $4f^{12}5s^2$ excited states, underscoring their potential as candidates for optical clock applications. Additionally, key properties of the ground and low-lying excited states are reported, including Lande $g_J$ factors, lifetimes, electric dipole polarizabilities, electric quadrupole moments, hyperfine structure constants, relativistic sensitivities, Lorentz-invariance coefficient tensor, and isotope shifts. The excellent agreement between the results from the KRCI and FSCC methods demonstrates the robustness of the calculations and confirms the reliability of the proposed clock transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01112v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. X. Liu, Y. M. Yu, B. B. Suo, Y. F. Ge, Y. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A large momentum transfer atom interferometer without $k$-reversal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03334v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an atom interferometer using large momentum transfer without $k$-reversal. More specifically, we use a microwave $\pi$/2 pulse to manipulate the spin state of $^{87}$Rb atoms before applying a Raman light $\pi$ pulse to achieve 4$\hbar k$ momentum transfer per Raman light pulse. A microwave $\pi$ pulse in the middle of the interferometer sequence reverses the spin states, which allows closing of the interferometer arms by the same Raman light $\pi$ pulses without $k$-reversal. We discuss the scalability of this large momentum transfer technique. Our results extend the scope of using large momentum transfer atom optics into atom interferometers where $k$-reversal optics are not available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03334v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanchen Peng, Bryony Lanigan, R. Shah, J. Lim, A. Kaushik, J. P. Cotter, E. A. Hinds, B. E. Sauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Resonance viewed as Weak Measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16281v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum resonance, i.e., amplification in transition probability available under certain conditions, offers a powerful means for determining fundamental quantities in physics, including the time duration of the second adopted in the SI units and neutron's electric dipole moment which is directly linked to CP violation. We revisit two of the typical examples, the Rabi resonance and the Ramsey resonance, and show that both of these represent the weak value amplification when involving significant enhancement of transition probabilities and that near the resonance points they share exactly the same behavior of transition probabilities except for the measurement strength whose difference leads to the known advantage of the Ramsey resonance in the sensitivity. Conversely, as a by-product of the relationship, we may measure the weak value through quantum resonance. In fact, we argue that previous measurements of neutron electric dipole moment based on the Ramsey resonance have potentially determined the weak value of neutron's spin with much higher precision than the conventional weak value measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16281v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Ueda, Izumi Tsutsui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on heavy axions with an X-ray free electron laser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17333v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present new exclusion bounds obtained at the European X-ray Free Electron Laser facility (EuXFEL) on axion-like particles (ALPs) in the mass range 10^{-3} eV &lt; m_a &lt; 10^4 eV. Our experiment exploits the Primakoff effect via which photons can, in the presence of a strong external electric field, decay into axions, which then convert back into photons after passing through an opaque wall. While similar searches have been performed previously at a 3^rd generation synchrotron, our work demonstrates improved sensitivity, exploiting the higher brightness of X-rays at EuXFEL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17333v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.055001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 134, 055001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jack W. D. Halliday, Giacomo Marocco, Konstantin A. Beyer, Charles Heaton, Motoaki Nakatsutsumi, Thomas R. Preston, Charles D. Arrowsmith, Carsten Baehtz, Sebastian Goede, Oliver Humphries, Alejandro Laso Garcia, Richard Plackett, Pontus Svensson, Georgios Vacalis, Justin Wark, Daniel Wood, Ulf Zastrau, Robert Bingham, Ian Shipsey, Subir Sarkar, Gianluca Gregori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial averaging for light reflection and transmission through cold atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18855v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We theoretically and computationally investigate the role that the spatial spread of atoms plays in the transmission and reflection of weak light from atom arrays. In particular, we investigate whether coherent wave functions for the atoms' positions leads to different results from a thermal distribution with the same spatial spread. We find that the coherence is not relevant when the light is weak and the electronic states evolve on time scales shorter than the oscillation period of the atoms in their traps. Full numerical calculations and derivations using the sudden approximation show that reflection and transmission agree with the simple averaging over atom positions for these conditions. For parameters outside these restrictions, the simple spatial averaging may lead to inaccurate results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18855v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.013711</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>F. Robicheaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Atomic Polarizability: From Charge Distortion to Non-Uniform Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16631v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the classical model of atomic polarizability, atomic charges are displaced by an applied electric field, assuming the electron cloud remains spherically symmetric but with its center shifted from the nucleus, thereby inducing an electric dipole. In this work, we propose that the applied electric field distorts the initially spherical electron cloud into a spheroidal shape, with the nucleus positioned at one of its focal points. We assume that the electron cloud's charge density remains uniform and is not altered by the applied field. We derive a modified expression for the polarizability that accounts for the distortion factor, represented by the eccentricity of the spheroid, and analyze an additional model incorporating non-uniform charge distribution. Furthermore, we present an expression for polarizability that combines the effects of both distortion and non-uniform charge density. These models aim to refine the classical approximation and offer deeper insights into the mechanisms underlying atomic polarizability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16631v2</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. F. de Alcantara Bonfim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
