<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Prospecting for lunar \textsuperscript{3}He with a radio-frequency atomic magnetometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mining $^3{\rm He}$ from lunar regolith has attracted significant interest in recent years due to the scarcity of $^3{\rm He}$ on Earth and its diverse applications, from cryogenics and medical imaging, to nuclear physics and future nuclear fusion. Given the stringent technical and economic challenges of mining lunar $^3{\rm He}$, precise prospecting is essential. Here we propose a prospecting methodology based on a radio-frequency atomic magnetometer, which can detect the dipolar magnetic field of thermally polarized $^3{\rm He}$ spins. With a 200 g regolith sample and an rf-magnetometer with sensitivity $1~{\rm fT/\sqrt{Hz}}$ we can detect $^3{\rm He}$ with abundance 5 ppb within a measurement time of just 5 min. The associated apparatus is lightweight and significantly more cost-effective than alternative measurement techniques. The proposed prospecting method is readily deployable and could substantially improve the technical and economic feasibility of mining lunar $^3{\rm He}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12386v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. K. Kominis, C. Kosmas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional Point-enhanced Rydberg Atomic Electrometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rydberg atoms, with their large transition dipole moments and extreme sensitivity to electric fields, have attracted widespread attention as promising candidates for next-generation quantum precision electrometry. Meanwhile, exceptional points (EPs) in non-Hermitian systems have opened new avenues for ultrasensitive metrology. Despite increasing interest in non-Hermitian physics, EP-enhanced sensitivity has rarely been explored in Rydberg atomic platforms. Here, we provide a new theoretical understanding of Autler-Townes (AT)-based Rydberg electrometry under non-Hermitian conditions, showing that dissipation fundamentally modifies the spectral response and enables sensitivity enhancement via EP-induced nonlinearity. Experimentally, we realize a second-order EP in a passive thermal Rydberg system without requiring gain media or cryogenics, and demonstrate the first EP-enhanced atomic electrometer. The EP can be tuned in real time by adjusting laser and microwave parameters, forming a flexible and scalable platform. Near the EP, the system exhibits a square-root response, yielding a nearly 20-fold enhancement in responsivity. Using amplitude-based detection, we achieve a sensitivity of $22.68~\mathrm{nV cm^{-1} Hz^{-1/2}}$ under realistic conditions. Our work establishes a practical, tunable platform for EP-enhanced sensing and real-time control, with broad implications for quantum metrology in open systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12861v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Liang, Ce Yang, Wei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blue-detuned Magneto-optical Trap of BaF molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the realization of a blue-detuned magneto-optical trap (BDM) of BaF molecules. The (1 + 1) type BDM and (1 + 2) type conveyor-belt MOT are explored. While the (1+1) BDM provides only weak trapping force, the conveyor-belt MOT significantly compresses the molecular cloud, achieving a radius of 320(20) {\mu}m, a temperature of 240(60) {\mu}K, and a peak density of 1.3{\times}10^7 cm^{-3}, representing a significant improvement over the red MOT. Interestingly, the conveyor-belt MOT of BaF exhibits a large capture velocity, and the loading efficiency from red MOT reaches near unity even without gray molasses. We confirm this by directly loading slowed molecules into the conveyor-belt MOT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12892v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixuan Zeng, Shoukang Yang, Shuhua Deng, Bo Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic hyperfine structure constants of $^{137}$BaF in the $^2\Pi_{1/2}$ and $^2\Pi_{3/2}$ excited states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-precision molecular experiments testing the Standard Model of particle physics require an accurate understanding of the molecular structure at the hyperfine level, both for the control of the molecules and for the interpretation of the results. In this work, we calculate the hyperfine structure constants for the excited states $^2\Pi_{1/2}$ and $^2\Pi_{3/2}$ of $^{137}$BaF due to the $^{137}$Ba nucleus. We use the 4-component relativistic Fock-space coupled-cluster method, extrapolating our results to the complete basis set limit. We investigate the effect of the basis sets and electron correlation, and estimate the uncertainty in our final results. Our results are used in the interpretation of the experimental spectroscopy of the hyperfine and rovibrational spectra of BaF, and the planning of laser-cooling schemes for future parity-violating anapole moment measurements [1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12972v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuly Chamorro, Felix Kogel, Tim Langen, Anastasia Borschevsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Series of molecular-like doubly excited states of a quasi-three-body Coulomb system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated resonant multiphoton excitation of high-angular-momentum planetary states of the strontium atom, a quasi-three-body Coulomb system, both experimentally and theoretically. A series of highly doubly excited electronic states converging to the double ionization threshold was identified and reproduced by first-principles calculations, which provided access to the two-electron wavefunctions of the resonances. In these states, the outer electron is dynamically localized at large distances by pendulum-like oscillations of the inner electron across the nucleus. A complementary simple molecular-like adiabatic model offers a clear interpretation of the correlated two-electron motion and suggests that the series is a general feature of highly doubly excited states of atoms and molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13495v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu G\'en\'evriez, Maxence Jungers, Christian Rosen, Ulrich Eichmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic echo protocols for robust quantum many-body state preparation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12138v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Entangled many-body states are a key resource for quantum technologies. Yet their preparation through analog control of interacting quantum systems is often hindered by experimental imperfections. Here, we introduce the adiabatic echo protocol, a general approach to state preparation designed to suppress the effect of static perturbations. We provide an analytical understanding of its robustness in terms of dynamically engineered destructive interference. By applying quantum optimal control methods, we demonstrate that such a protocol emerges naturally in a variety of settings, without requiring assumptions on the form of the control fields. Examples include Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger state preparation in Ising spin chains and two-dimensional Rydberg atom arrays, as well as the generation of quantum spin liquid states in frustrated Rydberg lattices. Our results highlight the broad applicability of this protocol, providing a practical framework for reliable many-body state preparation in present-day quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12138v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongda Zeng, Giuliano Giudici, Aruku Senoo, Alexander Baumg\"artner, Adam M. Kaufman, Hannes Pichler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron Impact Fragmentation Dynamics of Carbonyl Sulfide: A Combined Experimental and Theoretical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we examine the interactions of low- to intermediate-energy electrons (0$-$45 eV) with carbonyl sulfide (OCS). These collisions lead to the formation of several anionic fragments, including C$^-$, O$^-$, S$^-$, and SO$^-$. When the incident electron energy is below the first ionization potential of the molecule, dissociative electron attachment (DEA) process dominates, primarily yielding O$^-$ and S$^-$ fragments. At higher energies, beyond the ionization potential, ion-pair dissociation (IPD) becomes the dominant process, resulting in the emergence of additional fragments such as C$^-$ and SO$^-$. This leads to an increasingly intricate mechanism, necessitating a detailed analysis to elucidate the ion-pair dissociation pathways. The absolute cross section for S$^-$ ions has been determined using the well-established relative flow technique. Theoretical cross sections are calculated using the multi-configurational time-dependent hartree (MCTDH) method, with each potential energy curve obtained from equation-of-motion coupled-cluster singles and doubles (EOM-CCSD) calculations. The computed values are in excellent agreement with the experimental data. The analysis reveals contributions from both linear and bent anionic resonant states. Due to low count rates, only relative cross section curves have been obtained for the O$^-$ and SO$^-$ ions. At higher energies, the ion pair thresholds are evaluated using the Wannier threshold law, yielding values consistent with those derived from thermochemical data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12528v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Ghosh, Narayan Kundu, Aryya Ghosh, Dhananjay Nandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimode Bosonic State Tomography with Single-Shot Joint Parity Measurement of a Trapped Ion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The full characterization of a continuous-variable quantum system is a challenging problem. For the trapped-ion system, a number of methods of reconstructing the quantum states have been developed, including the measurement of the Q quasi-probability function and the density matrix elements in the Fock basis, but these approaches are often slow and difficult to scale to multi-mode states. Here, we demonstrate a novel and powerful scheme for reconstructing a continuous-variable quantum state that uses the direct single-shot measurement of the joint parity of the phonon states of a trapped ion. We drive a spin-dependent bichromatic beam-splitter interaction that coherently exchanges phonons between different harmonic oscillator modes of the ion. This interaction encodes the joint parity information into the relative phase between the two spin states, enabling measurement of the combined phonon-number parity across multiple modes in a single shot. Leveraging this capability, we directly measure multi-mode Wigner quasi-probability distributions to perform quantum state tomography of an entangled coherent state, and show that the generated state is non-positive under partial transpose, confirming its entanglement. We further show that the single-shot joint parity measurement can be used to detect parity-flip errors in real time. By post-selecting the parity measurement outcomes, we experimentally demonstrate the extension of the bosonic state lifetime, effectively implementing an error mitigation technique. Lastly, we identify the various sources of error affecting the fidelity of the spin-dependent beam-splitter operation and study the feasibility of high fidelity operations. The interaction studied in this work can be easily extended to more than two modes, and is highly relevant to continuous-variable quantum computing and quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12628v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honggi Jeon, Jiyong Kang, Wonhyeong Choi, Kyunghye Kim, Jaehun You, Taehyun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Dicke superradiance: Universal scaling of the peak emission rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12649v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum optics, superradiance is a phenomenon in which a system of $N$ fully excited quantum emitters radiate intense flashes of light during collective decay. However, computing its peak intensity for many spatially separated emitters remained challenging due to the exponential growth of the underlying Hilbert space with system size $N$. Derived from exact numerics, we present an analytically compact and easily computable formula for the peak photon emission rate of fully excited quantum emitter systems undergoing superradiant decay. The result applies to emitter configurations in any geometry and reveals a universal behavior: spatially extended quantum systems have a geometry-dependent optimal emitter number and always reach a peak photon emission rate that increases only linearly with $N$. Our results encompass quantum systems ranging from cold atomic gases and neutral-atom arrays to molecular aggregates and solid-state materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12649v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Holzinger, Susanne F. Yelin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving tricky quantum optics problems with assistance from (artificial) intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12770v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The capabilities of modern artificial intelligence (AI) as a ``scientific collaborator'' are explored by engaging it with three nuanced problems in quantum optics: state populations in optical pumping, resonant transitions between decaying states (the Burshtein effect), and degenerate mirrorless lasing. Through iterative dialogue, the authors observe that AI models--when prompted and corrected--can reason through complex scenarios, refine their answers, and provide expert-level guidance, closely resembling the interaction with an adept colleague. The findings highlight that AI democratizes access to sophisticated modeling and analysis, shifting the focus in scientific practice from technical mastery to the generation and testing of ideas, and reducing the time for completing research tasks from days to minutes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12770v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manas Pandey, Bharath Hebbe Madhusudhana, Saikat Ghosh, Dmitry Budker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle Properties of Long-Range Impurities in a Bose Condensate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12969v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An impurity immersed in a Bose condensate can form a quasiparticle known as a Bose polaron. When the impurity-boson interaction is short-ranged, the quasiparticle's properties are universal, characterized - independent of the bath density $n_0$ - by the impurity-boson scattering length $a_{IB}$. Long-ranged interactions - such as provided by Rydberg or ionic impurities - introduce an effective interaction range $r_{\mathrm{eff}}$, and boson-boson interactions provide a third length scale, the condensate coherence length $\xi $. These competing length scales raise the question of whether a universal description remains valid across different bath densities. In this study, we discuss the quasiparticle nature of long-range impurities and its dependence on the length scales $ n_0^{-1/3} $, $ r_{\mathrm{eff}} $, and $ \xi $. We employ two complementary theories - the coherent state Ansatz and the perturbative Gross-Pitaevskii theory - which incorporate beyond-Fr\"ohlich interactions. We derive an analytical expression for the beyond-Fr\"ohlich effective mass for a contact interaction and numerically compute the effective mass for long-range impurities. We argue that the coupling parameter $ |a_{IB}| n_0^{1/3} $ remains the principal parameter governing the properties of the polaron. For weak $ (|a_{IB}| n_0^{1/3} \ll 1) $ and intermediate $ (|a_{IB}| n_0^{1/3} \simeq 1) $ values of the coupling parameter, long-range impurities in a BEC are well-described as quasiparticles with a finite quasiparticle weight and a well-defined effective mass. However, the quasiparticle weight becomes significantly suppressed as the effective impurity volume is occupied by an increasing number of bath particles $ (r_{\mathrm{eff}} n_0^{1/3} \gg 1) $.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Alper Yo\u{g}urt, Matthew T. Eiles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Enhanced Simulated Annealing Using Rydberg Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum-classical hybrid algorithms offer a promising strategy for tackling computationally challenging problems, such as the maximum independent set (MIS) problem that plays a crucial role in areas like network design and data analysis. This study experimentally demonstrates that a Rydberg quantum-classical hybrid algorithm, termed as quantum-enhanced simulated annealing (QESA), provides a computational time advantage over standalone simulated annealing (SA), a classical heuristic optimization method. The performance of QESA is evaluated based on the approximation ratio and the Hamming distance, relative to the graph size. The analysis shows that QESA outperforms standalone SA by leveraging a warm-start input derived from two types of Rydberg atomic array experimental data: quench evolution (QE) (implemented on the Quera Aquila machine) and adiabatic quantum computing (AQC) (using the experimental dataset archieved in K. Kim et al., Scientific Data 11, 111 (2024). Based on these results, an estimate is provided for the maximum graph size that can be handled within a one-day computational time limit on a standard personal computer. These findings suggest that QESA has the potential to offer a computational advantage over classical methods for solving complex optimization problems efficiently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13264v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokho Jeong, Juyoung Park, Jaewook Ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of an Epsilon-Near-Zero Medium from Microscopic Atomic Principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that an effective near-zero refractive index can emerge from collective light scattering in a discrete atomic lattice, using essentially exact microscopic simulations. In a 25-layer array, cooperative response leads to over a thirtyfold increase in the effective optical wavelength within the medium, almost eliminating optical phase accumulation, with potential applications in spectroscopy and optical manipulation of quantum emitters. Crucially, the near-zero refractive index arises from first-principles microscopic theory, rather than being imposed through continuous phenomenological effective-medium model - providing conceptually important insight into the emergence of macroscopic electromagnetism from atomic-scale interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13294v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Ruks, J. Ruostekoski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Paradigm for Integrated sensing and Communication with Rydberg Atomic Receiver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The RYDberg Atomic Receiver (RYDAR) has been demonstrated to surmount the limitation on both the sensitivity and operating bandwidth of the classical electronic counterpart, which can theoretically detect indiscernible electric signals below -174 dBm/Hz with optical measurement through Rydberg-state atoms. Such miracle has established a new quantum-based paradigm for communications and sensing, which motivates a revolution of the transceiver design philosophies to fully unleash the potential of RYDAR towards next-generation networks. Against this background, this article provides a thorough investigation of Rydberg atomic communications and sensing from theory to hardware implementations. Specifically, we highlight the great opportunities from the hybridization between the RYDAR and the cutting-edge integrated sensing and communication (ISAC), followed by essential preliminaries of the quantum-based receiver. Then we propose a theoretical framework for broadband ISAC based on RYDAR, demonstrated by the proof-of-concept experiments. Afterwards, the enabling technologies for the ISAC framework are explored ranging from channel characterization, waveform design to array-based receiver configurations, where the open problems are also summarized. Finally, the future applications of RYDAR-based ISAC are envisioned, indicating its significant potential for both civilian and military purposes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13304v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minze Chen, Tianqi Mao, Yang Zhao, Wei Xiao, Dezhi Zheng, Zhaocheng Wang, Jun Zhang, Sheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient algorithms for quantum chemistry on modular quantum processors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum chemistry is a promising application of future quantum computers, but the requirements on qubit count and other resources suggest that modular computing architectures will be required. We introduce an implementation of a quantum chemistry algorithm that is distributed across several computational modules: the distributed unitary selective coupled cluster (dUSCC). We design a packing scheme using the pseudo-commutativity of Trotterization to maximize the parallelism while optimizing the scheduling of all inter-module gates around the buffering of inter-module Bell pairs. We demonstrate dUSCC on a 3-cluster (H$_4$)$_3$ chain and show that it naturally utilizes the molecule's structure to reduce inter-module latency. We show that the run time of dUSCC is unchanged with inter-module latency up to $\sim$20$\times$ slower than intra-module gates in the (H$_4$)$_3$ while maintaining chemical accuracy. dUSCC should be "free" in the weakly entangled systems, and the existence of "free" dUSCC can be found efficiently using classical algorithms. This new compilation scheme both leverages pseudo-commutativity and considers inter-module gate scheduling, and potentially provides an efficient distributed compilation of other Trotterized algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13332v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian Xue, Jacob P. Covey, Matthew Otten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitation-Pulse Intensity Mediated Coherent Control in V-Type Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: V-type three-level systems, where two excited states share a common ground state, serve as fundamental models for exploring coherent light-matter interactions in a range of quantum systems, from atomic gases to semiconductor nanostructures. In this work, we investigate the coherent evolution of such a system under strong femtosecond-pulse excitation by numerically solving the optical Bloch equations. We demonstrate that the coherent evolution of a three-level system critically depends on the product of the excitation-pulse duration and energy separation between the excited states. Using this understanding, we extend our analysis to simulate two-dimensional coherent spectra in a high-intensity regime. We show that by varying the pulse areas of the excitation pulses, one can selectively turn individual spectral features on or off, corresponding to distinct quantum pathways. Moreover, we can precisely adjust the phase of these peaks, illustrating an advanced level of coherent control within the system. Our approach provides a simple and robust framework for achieving advanced coherent control in multilevel systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13371v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Tripathi, Krishna K. Maurya, Rohan Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of many-body coherence in quasi-one-dimensional attractive Bose gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13597v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Macroscopic coherence is an important feature of quantum many-body systems exhibiting collective behaviors, with examples ranging from atomic Bose-Einstein condensates, and quantum liquids to superconductors. Probing many-body coherence in a dynamically unstable regime, however, presents an intriguing and outstanding challenge in out-of-equilibrium quantum many-body physics. Here, we experimentally study the first- and second-order coherence of degenerate quasi-one-dimensional (1D) Bose gases quenched from repulsive to modulationally unstable attractive interaction regimes. The resulting dynamics, monitored by in-situ density and matter-wave interference imaging, reveals phase-coherent density wave evolutions arising from the interplay between noise-amplified density modulations and dispersive shock waves of broad interest within nonlinear physics. At longer times, the gases become phase-scrambled, exhibiting a finite correlation length. Interestingly, following an interaction quench back to the repulsive regime, we observe that quasi-long-range coherence can be spontaneously re-established. This captivating rephasing dynamics can be attributed to the nucleation and annihilation of density defects in the quasi-1D geometry. These results shed light on out-of-equilibrium phase coherence in quantum many-body systems in a regime where beyond mean-field effects may arise and theoretical approaches have not been well-established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13597v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Tamura, Sambit Banerjee, Rongjie Li, Panayotis Kevrekidis, Simeon I. Mistakidis, Chen-Lung Hung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity entanglement and coherent multi-qubit mapping in an atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13632v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutral atoms in optical tweezer arrays possess broad applicability for quantum information science, in computing, simulation, and metrology. Among atomic species, Ytterbium-171 is unique as it hosts multiple qubits, each of which is impactful for these distinct applications. Consequently, this atom is an ideal candidate to bridge multiple disciplines, which, more broadly, has been an increasingly effective strategy within the field of quantum science. Realizing the full potential of this synergy requires high-fidelity generation and transfer of many-particle entanglement between these distinct qubit degrees of freedom, and thus between these distinct applications. Here we demonstrate the creation and coherent mapping of entangled quantum states across multiple qubits in Ytterbium-171 tweezer arrays. We map entangled states onto the optical clock qubit from the nuclear spin qubit or the Rydberg qubit. We coherently transfer up to 20 atoms of a $Z_2$-ordered Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state from the interacting Rydberg manifold to the metastable nuclear spin manifold. The many-body state is generated via a novel disorder-robust pulse in a two-dimensional ladder geometry. We further find that clock-qubit-based spin detection applied to Rydberg and nuclear spin qubits facilitates atom-loss-detectable qubit measurements and $&gt;90\%$ Rydberg decay detection. This enables mid-circuit and delayed erasure detection, yielding an error-detected two-qubit gate fidelity of $99.78(4)\%$ in the metastable qubits as well as enhanced GHZ state fidelities in analog preparation. These results establish a versatile architecture that advances multiple fields of quantum information science while also establishing bridges between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13632v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aruku Senoo, Alexander Baumg\"artner, Joanna W. Lis, Gaurav M. Vaidya, Zhongda Zeng, Giuliano Giudici, Hannes Pichler, Adam M. Kaufman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimer-projection contact and the clock shift of a unitary Fermi gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13707v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The time evolution of the contact parameter provides key insights into correlation dynamics in ultracold gases. However, most contact measurements to date have focused on equilibrium systems or slow, global dynamics. Here, we demonstrate that projecting a unitary Fermi gas onto a low-lying dimer state enables rapid probing of the contact. Using $^{40}$K near a broad s-wave Feshbach resonance, we compare the strength of the dimer-projection feature to the strength of the high-frequency tail of radio-frequency spectroscopy. By tuning the correlation strength through temperature, we find that the dimer signal scales proportionally with the contact parameter, in agreement with coupled-channels calculations. Our measurements enable us to constrain the clock shift of the unitary Fermi gas, to which the dimer feature is the dominant contributor. We observe deviations from universal predictions due to finite-range and multichannel effects. Our results establish new universal contact relations and shed light on the structure of the clock shift in strongly interacting Fermi gases. The demonstrated ability to resolve short-range correlations on timescales shorter than the inverse Fermi energy opens new avenues for studying contact correlators, hydrodynamic attractors, and quantum critical behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13707v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin G. S. Xie, Colin J. Dale, Kiera Pond Grehan, Maggie Fen Wang, Tilman Enss, Paul S. Julienne, Zhenhua Yu, Joseph H. Thywissen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging erasure errors in logical qubits with metastable $^{171}$Yb atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13724v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Implementing large-scale quantum algorithms with practical advantage will require fault-tolerance achieved through quantum error correction, but the associated overhead is a significant cost. The overhead can be reduced by engineering physical qubits with fewer errors, and by shaping the residual errors to be more easily correctable. In this work, we demonstrate quantum error correcting codes and logical qubit circuits in a metastable ${}^{171}$Yb qubit with a noise bias towards erasure errors, that is, errors whose location can be detected separate from any syndrome information. We show that dephasing errors on the nuclear spin qubit during coherent transport can be strongly suppressed, and implement robust entangling gates that maintain a high fidelity in the presence of gate beam inhomogeneity or pointing error. We demonstrate logical qubit encoding in the $[[4,2,2]]$ code, with error correction during decoding based on mid-circuit erasure measurements despite the fact that the code is too small to correct any Pauli errors. Finally, we demonstrate logical qubit teleportation between multiple code blocks with conditionally selected ancillas based on mid-circuit erasure checks, which is a key ingredient for leakage-robust error correction with neutral atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13724v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bichen Zhang, Genyue Liu, Guillaume Bornet, Sebastian P. Horvath, Pai Peng, Shuo Ma, Shilin Huang, Shruti Puri, Jeff D. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Bayesian optimization in deep cooling atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11793v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Laser cooling, which cools atomic and molecular gases to near absolute zero, is the crucial initial step for nearly all atomic gas experiments. However, fast achievement of numerous sub-$\mu$K cold atoms is challenging. To resolve the issue, we propose and experimentally validate an intelligent polarization gradient cooling approach enhanced by optical lattice, utilizing Maximum Hypersphere Compensation Sampling Bayesian Optimization (MHCS-BO). MHCS-BO demonstrates a twofold increase in optimization efficiency and superior prediction accuracy compared to conventional Bayesian optimization. Finally, approximate $10^8$ cold atoms at a temperature of 0.4$\pm$0.2 $\mu$K can be achieved given the optimal parameters within 15 minutes. Our work provides an intelligent protocol, which can be generalized to other high-dimension parameter optimization problems, and paves way for preparation of ultracold atom in quantum experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11793v4</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxiao Ma, Changwen Liang, Rong Sha, Chao Zhou, Qixue Li, Guochao Wang, Jixun Liu, Shuhua Yan, Jun Yang, Lingxiao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear Electric Quadrupole Moment-Induced Parity Doubling in Molecules for Symmetry-Violation Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10904v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Searches for the nuclear magnetic quadrupole moment (MQM) and nuclear Schiff moment (NSM) have high discovery potential for violations of time ($T$) and parity ($P$) reversal symmetries beyond the Standard Model. Molecules containing heavy nuclei are typically used to enhance the sensitivity to MQMs and NSMs due to their strong internal electric fields and potential octupole deformation. To extract these effects in the laboratory frame, a bias electric field is required to polarize the molecule by mixing states of opposite parity (parity doublets). Typical heavy nuclei that are sensitive to symmetry-violation also possess large nuclear electric quadrupole moments (EQMs) when its nuclear spin is $I\geq1$. We show that EQMs can significantly modify the energy splitting between parity doublet states and thus change the required polarizing electric field. As a result, the EQM-induced energy splitting must be taken into account in designing such experiments. We provide qualitative estimates of parity doubling from EQMs and supporting \textit{ab initio} calculations, along with implications for candidate molecules in symmetry-violation searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10904v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing Fan, Lan Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collectively enhanced ground-state cooling in subwavelength atomic arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18482v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Subwavelength atomic arrays feature strong light-induced dipole-dipole interactions, resulting in subradiant collective resonances characterized by narrowed linewidths. In this work, we present a sideband cooling scheme for atoms trapped in subwavelength arrays that utilizes these narrow collective resonances. Working in the Lamb-Dicke regime, we derive an effective master equation for the atomic motion by adiabatically eliminating the internal degrees of freedom of the atoms, and validate its prediction with numerical simulations of the full system. Our results demonstrate that subradiant resonances enable the cooling of ensembles of atoms to temperatures lower than those achievable without dipole interactions, provided the atoms have different trap frequencies. Remarkably, narrow collective resonances can be sideband-resolved even when the individual atomic transition is not. In such scenarios, ground-state cooling becomes feasible solely due to light-induced dipole-dipole interactions. This approach could be utilized for future quantum technologies based on dense ensembles of emitters, and paves the way towards harnessing many-body cooperative decay for enhanced motional control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18482v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oriol Rubies-Bigorda, Raphael Holzinger, Ana Asenjo-Garcia, Oriol Romero-Isart, Helmut Ritsch, Stefan Ostermann, Carlos Gonzalez-Ballestero, Susanne F. Yelin, Cosimo C. Rusconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unpolarized prethermal discrete time crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09461v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Prethermal discrete time crystals (DTCs) are a class of nonequilibrium phases of matter that exhibit robust subharmonic responses to periodic driving without requiring disorder. Prior realizations of prethermal DTCs have relied on the presence of either spontaneous or induced finite polarization. Here, we introduce a new class of prethermal DTCs termed unpolarized prethermal discrete time crystals (UPDTCs) that do not require finite polarization. By studying a spin model of periodically driven trapped ions, we show that robust period-doubled dynamics can persist in the autocorrelation function of the staggered magnetization for paramagnetic initial states, even when the staggered magnetization itself vanishes. The key insight is that quantum fluctuations alone are sufficient to reveal coherent DTC-like dynamics. We demonstrate that UPDTCs are exponentially long-lived in the high-frequency driving regime, consistent with Floquet prethermalization. Our results expand the known phenomenology of prethermal time crystals and underscore the role of quantum effects in stabilizing novel nonequilibrium phases. We propose an experimental protocol to observe UPDTCs in trapped-ion simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09461v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeru Yokota, Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
