<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 04:00:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>SI-Traceable Temperature Calibration Based on Optical Lattice Clocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a SI-traceable temperature calibration apparatus utilizing optical lattice clocks for precision metrology. The system employs a dual-blackbody radiation shield chamber with independent temperature control, enabling synchronous differential measurements of blackbody radiation (BBR)-induced frequency shifts in atomic ensembles. By correlating these shifts with chamber temperature, we achieve absolute temperature determination traceable to the SI second through the optical clock frequency. Comprehensive uncertainty analysis demonstrates an absolute temperature uncertainty below 15 mK across the $200 \sim 350$ K range based on $^{87}$Sr optical lattice clock, representing an improvement of two orders of magnitude over current temperature measurements based on BBR-induced Rydberg state transitions. This advancement in primary thermometry offers significant improvements in precision, reproducibility, and versatility, with potential applications in metrology, fundamental physics, and industrial processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08333v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Cao, Xiaotong Lu, Benquan Lu, Hong Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Electron Momentum Distribution upon Strong-Field Ionization of Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a scheme to synthesize a three-dimensional laser field that produces a chiral electron momentum distribution upon strong-field ionization of atoms. Our approach employs two orthogonally propagating two-color laser beams. This results in a time-dependent three-dimensional electric field vector of the combined light field which varies for different positions within the focal volume. For each position, we conduct a simulation of the corresponding electron momentum distributions that includes non-adiabatic dynamics and Coulomb interaction after tunneling. For suitable laser parameters, only a small region of the focal volume contributes to the final momentum distribution. Thus, integrating over all position coordinates, a specific chiral laser field dominates. This leads to a volume-averaged electron momentum distribution, which is chiral, as well. This work will serve as a benchmark for future strong-field experiments aiming at the synthetization of well-defined, three-dimensional laser fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08573v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Geyer, J. Stindl, I. Dwojak, M. Hofmann, N. Anders, P. Roth, P. Daum, J. Kruse, S. Jacob, S. Gurevich, N. Wong, M. S. Sch\"offler, L. Ph. H. Schmidt, T. Jahnke, M. Kunitski, R. D\"orner, S. Eckart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the dipole approximation in the theory of photoionization of the atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the nonrelativistic many-electron approximation of the theory of photoionization of the atom in the formalism of secondary quantization and the theory of irreducible tensor operators, analytical structures for the quadrupole transition operator and its matrix element are specified. A new form of the nonrelativistic criterion for the applicability of the dipole approximation is formulated as the ratio of the complete cross sections of one-electron photoionization of an atom via the channels of dipole and quadrupole transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08656v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey N. Hopersky, Alexey M. Nadolinsky, Rustam V. Koneev, Julia N. Tolkunova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active stabilization for ultralong acquisitions in an attosecond pump-probe beamline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Attosecond time-resolution experiments using noncollinear interferometers require precise and active control of the optical delay to prevent instabilities - including both slow drifts and rapid vibrations - that can obscure the time evolution of the physical system under investigation. In this work, we present the design and results of stability measurements for a double interferometer setup for extreme ultraviolet-infrared pump-probe spectroscopy. The attosecond pump-probe setup is driven by a high-average-power, high-repetition-rate laser system and offers sub-optical-cycle (+/-81 as) stability with a fast feedback rate over extended periods (up to several days). Due to the noncollinear arrangement, the setup enables independent control of both amplitude and phase in the two arms even across significantly different spectral regions. As a proof of concept, we demonstrate attosecond beating in angle-resolved photoemission during two-photon, two-color photoionization, highlighting the broad potential of the system for kinematically and dynamically complete studies of atomic-scale light-matter interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08448v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tam\'as Csizmadia, L\'en\'ard Guly\'as Oldal, Barnab\'as Gilicze, D\'aniel S\'andor Kiss, Tam\'as Bartyik, Katalin Varj\'u, Subhendu Kahaly, Bal\'azs Major</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaginary gauge potentials in a non-Hermitian spin-orbit coupled quantum gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08614v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1996, Hatano and Nelson proposed a non-Hermitian lattice model containing an imaginary Peierls phase [Phys. Rev. Lett. 77 570-573 (1996)], which subsequent analyses revealed to be an instance of a new class of topological systems. Here, we experimentally realize a continuum analog to this model containing an imaginary gauge potential using a homogeneous spin-orbit coupled Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC). Non-Hermiticity is introduced by adding tunable spin-dependent loss via microwave coupling to a subspace with spontaneous emission. We demonstrate that the resulting Heisenberg equations of motion for position and momentum depend explicitly on the system's phase-space distribution. First, we observe collective nonreciprocal transport in real space, with a "self-acceleration" that decreases with the BEC's spatial extent, consistent with non-Hermitian Gross-Pitaevskii simulations. We then examine localized edge states: the relatively strong interactions in our BEC suppress the formation of topological edge states, yielding instead highly excited states localized by an interplay between self-acceleration and wavefunction spreading. Finally, we confirm that our non-Hermitian description remains valid at all times by comparing to a multi-level master-equation treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08614v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junheng Tao, Emmanuel Mercado-Gutierrez, Mingshu Zhao, Ian Spielman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiparameter estimation with an array of entangled atomic sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum metrology, entangled states of many-particle systems are investigated to enhance measurement precision of the most precise clocks and field sensors. While single-parameter quantum metrology is well established, many metrological tasks require joint multiparameter estimation, which poses new conceptual challenges that have so far only been explored theoretically. We experimentally demonstrate multiparameter quantum metrology with an array of entangled atomic ensembles. By splitting a spin-squeezed ensemble, we create an atomic sensor array featuring inter-sensor entanglement that can be flexibly configured to enhance measurement precision of multiple parameters jointly. Using an optimal estimation protocol, we achieve significant gains over the standard quantum limit in key multiparameter estimation tasks, thus grounding the concept of quantum enhancement of field sensor arrays and imaging devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08677v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Li, Lex Joosten, Youcef Baamara, Paolo Colciaghi, Alice Sinatra, Philipp Treutlein, Tilman Zibold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applications of maximum likelihood estimations for analyzing photon counts in few atom experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a method for determining the atom number distribution of few atoms in a tight optical tweezer from their fluorescence distributions. In the tight tweezer regime, the detection light causes rapid atom loss due to light-assisted collisions. This in turn leads to non-Poissonian and overlapping fluorescence distributions for different initial atom numbers, and commonly used threshold techniques fail. We use maximum likelihood estimation algorithms to fit model distributions that account for the atom loss. This gives accurate atom number distributions for relatively few experimental runs (about 600 is sufficient) to sample a photon number distribution. We show that the method can be extended to situations when the photon number distributions for known initial atom numbers cannot be modeled, at the cost of requiring a higher number of experimental runs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17434v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Weyland, L. Sanchez, P. Ruksasakchai, M. F. Andersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
