<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optical field characterization at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution with a trapped ion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical systems capable of generating fields with sub-wavelength spatial features have become standard in science and engineering research and industry. Pertinent examples include atom- and ion-based quantum computers and optical lithography setups. So far, no tools exist to characterize such fields - both intensity and polarization - at sub-wavelength length scales. We use a single trapped atomic ion, confined to approximately 40 nm X 40 nm X 180 nm to sense a laser light field at a wavelength of 370 nm. With its spatial extent smaller than the absorption cross-section of a resonant detector, the ion-sensor operates at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution. Our technique relies on developing an analytical model of the ion-light interaction and using the model to extract the intensity and polarization. An important insight provided in this work is also that the inverse of this model can be learned, in a restricted sense, on a deep neural network, speeding up the intensity and polarization readout by five orders of magnitude. This speed-up makes the technique field-deployable to characterize optical instruments by probing light at the sub-wavelength scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07214v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikhil Kotibhaskar, Sainath Motlakunta, Anthony Vogliano, Lewis Hahn, Rajibul Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prevention of Yb adsorption by paraffin coating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ytterbium (Yb) is used in cold-atom systems, including magneto-optical traps and optical lattice clocks. However, the long-term operation of such systems may be associated with substantial degradation of optical transmittance through vacuum chamber viewports due to Yb adsorption. Here, we show that coating the surface with tetracontane effectively suppresses such adsorption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07364v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kanta Asakawa, Taichi Kobayashi, Masami Yasuda, Takao Aoki, Atsushi Hatakeyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking the Plane-Wave Born and Distorted Waves approximations for electron-impact collision strengthcomputations: the sample case of Sr II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of gravitational waves from a neutron star merger in 2017 (GW170817) and the associated kilonova (AT2017gfo) confirmed these events as key sites for heavy element production through the r-process. Subsequent observations, including late-time spectra with \textit{JWST}, have highlighted the need for accurate modeling of kilonova ejecta. In the photospheric phase, atomic level populations can be estimated under LTE using Boltzmann and Saha relations, but about a week after the merger the ejecta enters the nebular phase where non-LTE effects dominate. Modeling nebular spectra therefore requires a detailed treatment of radiative and collisional processes that affect the population of atomic levels. This work focuses on electron-impact excitation in Sr II, a heavy ion relevant for kilonova spectra. Two computational approaches are employed: the Plane Wave Born approximation within the pseudo-relativistic Hartree-Fock method, and a Distorted Waves method using AUTOSTRUCTURE. The resulting collision strengths are compared against reference R-matrix data to evaluate the accuracy of these approximations and their suitability for large-scale applications to all heavy elements. In addition, radiative parameters for forbidden transitions are computed. These results provide an essential benchmark of approximations that could be used to compute atomic data for nebular-phase kilonova modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07684v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\^ome Deprince, Lucas Maison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous cloud position spectroscopy using a magneto-optical trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a continuous spectroscopy technique with frequency sensitivity well below the natural transition linewidth, while maintaining a locking range hundreds of times larger. The method exploits the position dependence of a continuous, broadband magneto-optical trap operating on the 7.5 kHz-wide intercombination line of strontium. We show that the frequency sensitivity is fundamentally insensitive to the effective MOT laser linewidth. By applying active feedback on the MOT position to a dispersion-optimized frequency comb, which serves as the reference for stabilizing the MOT laser, we achieve a frequency instability below $4.4\times10^{-13}$ after 400 s of averaging in both the optical and radio-frequency domains, surpassing the performance of conventional hot-vapor modulation transfer spectroscopy. Our method is a broadly applicable alternative route to long-term frequency references in the high $10^{-14}$ range around 100 s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07736v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt Heizenreder, Ananya Sitaram, Sana Boughdachi, Andrew von H\"orsten, Yan Xie, Andreas Brodschelm, Florian Schreck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiprotonic atoms with nonperturbative inclusion of vacuum polarization and finite nuclear mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that energy levels of excited states in a hydrogenic system consisting of an arbitrary nucleus and an antiproton can be calculated within the framework of nonrelativistic quantum electrodynamics, even for a large nuclear charge $Z$. It is because for rotational states the expansion parameter is $Z\,\alpha/n$. The main advantage of this approach is the possibility of exact inclusion of the finite nuclear mass, which we achieve up to the $(Z\,\alpha)^6$ order. In addition, we include unperturbatively the one-loop and two-loop electron vacuum polarization (evp) potentials in the nonrelativistic Hamiltonian, as well as in the leading relativistic correction. The obtained results for $l&gt;1$ states of antiprotonic atoms with spinless nucleus are the most accurate to date. We make available a user-friendly {\sl Mathematica} code for antiprotonic atoms {\sl PbarSpectr}, which can be further improved by combining evp potentials with $(Z\,\alpha)^5$ QED effects, by adding three-loop evp, and by extending to an arbitrary nuclear spin. Finally, we note that rotational states of antiprotonic atoms can be used to determine the mean square nuclear charge radius much more accurately than from electronic or muonic atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07738v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Patk\'o\v{s}, K. Pachucki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Independent Atom Model -- Pixel Counting Method for Ion-Molecule Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The independent atom model - pixel counting method (IAM-PCM) for the description of ion-molecule collisions is reviewed. The method was introduced (in 2016) to improve on the simple additivity rule according to which scattering cross sections for a molecular target can be obtained by summing up the cross sections of the constituent atoms. The key idea of the IAM-PCM is the inclusion of weight factors in the summation, to be determined from a geometrical interpretation of the resultant cross section as a combined area of overlapping atomic contributions, which is calculated via a pixelization technique. We argue here that the IAM-PCM can be conceptualized in a different but equivalent way by associating each pixel in the area decomposition with a scattering event. The calculation of net and charge-state correlated capture and ionization cross sections is explained, and results for 10 keV to 10 MeV proton impact are discussed for a number of targets ranging from compact ten-electron systems to large biomolecules. A previously observed scaling behaviour of the net ionization cross sections is revisited and shown to be captured by a simple parametrization with remarkable accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07822v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Juergen Luedde, Marko Horbatsch, Tom Kirchner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A framework for continuous superradiant laser operation via sequential transport of atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a theoretical study of a continuous superradiant laser supporting its experimental realization at FEMTO-ST using two sequentially-emitting ensembles of ${}^{171}\mathrm{Yb}$ atoms coupled to the same Fabry-Perot cavity. Using an open quantum system approach, we identify for the simplest case the parameter space where the laser reaches tens of picowatts of power with a sub-millihertz linewidth. Studying the impact of inhomogeneous frequency broadening and variations in atom-cavity coupling on the superradiant emission, we find the laser properties robust with respect to such perturbations, also thanks to the occurrence of synchronization of the atomic dipoles. We then consider a two-site configuration, in which atoms in each site are equally coupled to the cavity and have equal detunings, with different values for the two ensembles. We find for balanced and imbalanced atom numbers that synchronization leads in a certain parameter space to a single narrow spectral line whose central frequency follows the weighted average frequency. This result indicates that sequential loading can enable continuous superradiant emission for metrological applications, provided that the relative frequencies of the two ensembles are controlled to the level required by the target stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07833v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jana El Badawi, Marion Delehaye, Bruno Bellomo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of the density of states in Bose-Einstein condensation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07089v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The onset of Bose-Einstein condensation in systems with { various} densities of states is examined, with particular attention to the role of the behavior of their {energy} spectrum at low and high energies. Specifically, the results of Chatterjee and Diaconis, which rely exclusively on the high-energy behavior, are compared and reconciled with those of the standard physics approach, where the existence of condensation is determined by the low-energy behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07089v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexios P. Polychronakos, Stephane Ouvry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Vapor Cells for Rydberg Atom-Based Electrometer Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive numerical investigation into the radio frequency (RF) field behavior within miniaturized all-glass and hybrid vapor cell geometries designed for Rydberg atom-based electrometry. Using full-vector finite element modeling (FEM), we analyze electromagnetic field enhancement across a wide frequency range (0.05 GHz to 150 GHz) as a function of polarization, incidence angle, and structural configuration. Two primary vapor cell designs are evaluated: translationally invariant "open" cells and periodically structured "supported" cells composed entirely of low-loss glass, as well as hybrid structures incorporating highly doped silicon. Our simulations reveal that the structured all-glass vapor cells exhibit sharp, angle- and polarization-dependent resonant peaks due to guided-mode coupling, resulting in localized RF power enhancements exceeding 8x. In contrast, silicon-based structures demonstrate significant electric field attenuation and suppression of resonant features due to their high dielectric losses. Through k-vector and angle-resolved analyses, we show how cell geometry and material properties critically influence the RF field distribution and coupling efficiency. Our findings open new possibilities for optimizing vapor cell architectures to enhance field sensitivity, directional and polarization selectivity, and integration potential in chip-scale quantum sensing platforms based on Rydberg atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07823v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhriti Maurya, Alexandra Artusio-Glimpse, Adil Meraki, Daniel Lopez, Vladimir Aksyuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-Range Hard-Sphere Potential and Coulomb Interaction: Deser-Trueman Formula for Rydberg States of Exotic Atomic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15973v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In exotic atomic systems with hadronic constituent particles, it is notoriously difficult to estimate the strong-interaction correction to energy levels. It is well known that, due to the strength of the nuclear interaction, the problem cannot be treated on the basis of Wigner-Brioullin perturbation theory. Recently, high-angular-momentum Rydberg states of exotic atomic systems with hadronic constituents have been identified as promising candidates for the search of New Physics in the low-energy sector of the Standard Model. In order to render this endeavor feasible, it is necessary to estimate the strong-interaction correction to the atomic energy levels. We thus derive a generalized Deser-Trueman formula for the induced energy shift for a general hydrogenic bound state with principal quantum number $n$ and orbital angular momentum quantum number~$\ell$, and find that the energy shift is given by the formula delta E = 2 alpha_{n, L} beta_L (a_h/a_0)^(2 L + 1) E_h/n^3, where alpha_{n,0} = 1, alpha_{n,L} is the product from s=1 to s=L of the expression (s^(-2) - n^(-2)), beta_L = (2 L + 1)/[(2 L + 1)!!]^2, where E_h is the Hartree energy, a_h is the hadronic radius and a_0 is the generalized Bohr radius. The square of the double factorial, [(2\ell + 1)!!]^2, in the denominator implies a drastic suppression of the effect for higher angular momenta.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15973v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. S. Adkins, U. D. Jentschura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics of multi-electron states and $J$-levels in atomic configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The number and nature of atomic configurations are cornerstones of atomic spectroscopy, especially for the calculation of hot-plasma radiative properties. The knowledge of the distributions of magnetic quantum number $M$ and angular momentum $J$ for $N$ identical fermions in a subshell with half-integer spin $j$ is a prerequisite to the determination of the structure of such configurations. The problem is rather complicated, since the possible occurrence of a specific values of $J$ is governed by the Pauli exclusion principle. Several methods, such as generating functions, recurrence relations or algebraic number theory, for instance via Gaussian polynomials, have proven effective in addressing this issue. However, up to now, no general formula was known. In the present work, we present exact and compact explicit formulas for the number of atomic configurations and for the distributions of the total magnetic quantum number $M$ and angular momentum $J$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04353v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Christophe Pain, Xavier Blanc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum annealing eigensolver as a NISQ era tool for probing strong correlation effects in quantum chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20464v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quantum-classical hybrid variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) algorithm is arguably the most popular noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era approach to quantum chemistry. We consider the underexplored quantum annealing eigensolver (QAE) algorithm as a worthy alternative. We use a combination of numerical calculations for a system where strong correlation effects dominate, and conclusions drawn from our preliminary scaling analysis for QAE and VQE to make the case for QAE as a NISQ era contender to VQE for quantum chemistry. For the former, we pick the representative example of computing avoided crossings in the H4 molecule in a rectangular geometry, and demonstrate that we obtain results to within about 1.2% of the full configuration interaction value on the D-Wave Advantage system 4.1 hardware. We carry out analyses on the effect of the number of shots, anneal time, and the choice of Lagrange multiplier on our obtained results. Following our numerical results, we carry out a detailed yet preliminary analysis of the scaling behaviours of both the QAE and the VQE algorithms. We analyze the non-recurring and recurring costs involved in both the algorithms and arrive at their net scaling behaviours.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20464v5</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aashna Anil Zade, Kenji Sugisaki, Matthias Werner, Ana Palacios, Jordi Riu, Jan Nogue, Artur Garcia-Saez, Arnau Riera, V. S. Prasannaa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unpolarized prethermal discrete time crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09461v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Prethermal discrete time crystals (DTCs) are a novel phase of periodically driven matter that exhibits robust subharmonic oscillations without requiring disorder. However, previous realizations of prethermal DTCs have relied on the presence of polarization, either spontaneous or induced. Here, we introduce a new class of prethermal DTCs termed ``unpolarized prethermal discrete time crystals'' (UPDTCs) that arise without any uniform/staggered polarization and propose an experiment to observe them in current trapped-ion quantum simulators. By studying a model of trapped ions using a quantum circuit simulator, we demonstrate that robust period-doubled dynamics can persist in the autocorrelation function of the staggered magnetization, even though its expectation value does not exhibit such dynamics. The period-doubled dynamics is not explained by the classical picture of flipping spins but by quantum fluctuations. We establish that UPDTCs are exponentially long-lived in the high-frequency driving regime, a hallmark of prethermalization. These results expand the known phenomenology and mechanism of prethermal time crystals and underscore the role of quantum effects in stabilizing novel nonequilibrium phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09461v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeru Yokota, Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
