<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 02:04:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Polarizabilities of low-lying states of silver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assembly of ultracold polar molecules containing silver (Ag) from laser-cooled atoms requires knowledge of the dynamic polarizabilities of Ag at convenient laser wavelengths. We present calculations and analysis of the energies and electric-dipole dc and ac polarizabilities of the low-lying states of neutral Ag. Calculations of the properties of the 4d^{10}x states, where x=5s,6s,7s,5p,6p,7p,5d,6d, and 4f, are performed using the linearized coupled cluster single-double method. The properties of the 4d^9 5s^2 ^2D_{5/2,3/2} states are obtained within the framework of configuration interaction with 11 and 17 electrons in the valence field. We analyze the different contributions to the polarizabilities and estimate the uncertainties of our predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08855v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. G. Porsev, D. Filin, C. Cheung, M. S. Safronova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of STIRAP from the 1S to the 2S states of the Hydrogen/Antihydrogen atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 1S-2S transition of hydrogen and antihydrogen atoms services a crucial role in comparing matter to antimatter and testing charge conjugation, parity, and time reversal similarities. Achieving high transition rates with low ionization rates when preparing atoms in the 2S level is essential for such tests. We propose and examine the efficiency of applying the STIRAP (Stimulated Raman Adiabatic Passage) process in achieving such transition. We simulated a circularly polarized Lyman alpha, Ly-$\alpha$, pulse to couple the 1S state to the 2P state and a microwave pulse to couple the 2P state and the 2S state. We calculate the efficiency of the STIRAP process for transferring the population between the stretched states $(1S_d, 2S_d)$ as a function of experimental parameters such as Rabi frequencies and the pulse durations. We find that a Ly-$\alpha$ pulse with an energy of a few nanojoules could produce nearly perfect transfer at zero detunings. We extended the analysis to a thermal ensemble of atoms where the Doppler detuning plays a crucial role in the velocity distribution of the produced hydrogen atoms in the 2S level. We found that the width of such velocity distribution is controlled by the Rabi frequency. We show that the peak velocity of the hydrogen atoms in the 2S level after STIRAP can be controlled by the Ly-$\alpha$ pulse detuning. The STIRAP efficiency in transferring population increases at low temperature (T$\sim$1~mK). Finally, we show that a background magnetic field improves the transfer rates between the other trappable states $(1S_c, 2S_c)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08932v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>AbdAlGhaffar K. Amer, A. Capra, T. Friesen, M. C. Fujiwara, T. Momose, C. So, F. Robicheaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stark-modulated Rydberg dissipative time crystals at room-temperature applied to sub-kHz electric-field sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Out-of-equilibrium Rydberg gases exhibit emergent many-body phases due to mode competition. Sustained limit cycle oscillations (OSC) emerge when driven by B-fields at room-temperature, forming robust Rydberg dissipative time crystals (DTC). These driven-dissipative Rydberg DTC have recently been shown to develop an effective transition centered at the OSC frequency (-10dB bandwidth of ~1.7kHz, centered at 9.8kHz). Weak RF signals injected within this emergent transition perturb and emerge on the OSC spectrum, from which sensitive and high-resolution sensing of E-fields (~1.6-2.3 uVcm-1Hz-1/2) near the OSC frequencies can be achieved. In this article, it is demonstrated that DC and AC Stark fields in the sub-kHz regime can be used effectively to shift (DC) or modulate (AC) the OSC frequency of Rydberg DTC at room-temperature. The AC-Stark driven modulation of the OSC is shown as an effective technique to sense weak AC E-fields in the sub-kHz regime. With a modest setup, a sensitivity of ~7.8 uVcm-1Hz-1/2 for AC signals at 300Hz (~8.7x improvement over state-of-art Rydberg atom techniques), and high-resolution detection to as low as sub-Hz is demonstrated. This approach enables the development of ultra-compact, extremely low-frequency E-field detectors for applications in remote sensing, communications, navigation, and bio-medical technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08972v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darmindra Arumugam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced atomic models for large-scale computations: Fe XIII near-infrared lines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09540v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate atomic models for astrophysical plasma can be very complex, requiring thousands of states. However, for a variety of applications such as large-scale forward models of the Stokes parameters of a spectral line in the solar corona, it is necessary to build much reduced atomic models. We present two examples of such models, focused on the two near-infrared Fe XIII lines observed on the ground at 10750, 10801 Angstroms. These lines are primary diagnostics for a range of missions (especially the Daniel K. Inouye Solar Telescope, DKIST) to measure electron densities and magnetic fields in the solar corona. We calculate the Stokes parameters for a range of coronal conditions using CHIANTI (for intensities) and P-CORONA (for intensities and polarization), and use P-CORONA and a realistic global MHD simulation to show that the reduced models provide accurate results, typically to within 5% those obtained with larger models. Reduced models provide a significant decrease (over three orders of magnitude) in the computational time in spectropolarimetric calculations. The methods we describe are general and can be applied to a range of conditions and other ions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09540v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf274</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Del Zanna, Supriya Hebbur Dayananda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
