<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body and QED effects in electron-atom inelastic scattering in EELS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The elemental composition and electronic structure analysis of materials in Electron Energy Loss Spectroscopy (EELS) is probed by the inner shell ionization of atoms. This is a localized process in the material which can be well approximated by the scattering of a beam electron from a free atom. The inelastic differential cross section is calculated in the context of Quantum Electrodynamics (QED). The interaction of the incoming electron with the atom factorizes and it is treated perturbatively in QED. The atomic transition currents are calculated in the context of the relaxed Dirac-Hartree-Fock method. Correlation effects, which are induced by the relaxation of the atomic orbitals due to the created core-hole, are analyzed. Such effects are particularly important for quantum many-body systems and they are shown to have important impact on the shape of the differential cross section near the ionization threshold in Electron Energy Loss Spectra. In addition to the ionization spectrum, we calculate the excitation spectrum of Sc and Dy oxides using the crystal field multiplet theory. The calculation is compared to experimental EELS data and shows good agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12254v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis Iatrakis, Valerii Brudanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body theory and Gaussian-basis implementation of positron annihilation $\gamma$-ray spectra on polyatomic molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Doppler-broadened $\gamma$-ray spectra for positron annihilation on molecules are calculated using many-body theory. By employing Gaussian bases for the electron and positron wavefunctions, a computable expression that involves a four-centre integral over the two-annihilation-photon momenta is derived for the $\gamma$ spectra in the independent particle model approximation to the annihilation vertex, and implemented in the open-source {\tt EXCITON+} code. The influence of electron-positron correlations on the $\gamma$ spectra is examined through \textit{ab initio} treatment of the positron wavefunction, whilst corrections to the annihilation vertex are treated approximately via enhancement factors previously calculated [D. G. Green and G. F. Gribakin, Phys.~Rev.~Lett.~{\bf 114}, 093201 (2015)] exactly for atoms. Calculated $\gamma$ spectra for furan and acetonitrile are presented for annihilation from the positron bound state with electrons of individual molecular orbitals. For such annihilation from the positron-molecule bound state, it is found that the magnitude of the partial contribution to the $\gamma$ spectra from individual molecular orbitals depends not just on the orbital energies, but also on the molecular symmetry, more precisely the relative localisation of the positron and electron densities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12364v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. K. Gregg, J. P. Cassidy, A. R. Swann, J. Hofierka, B. Cunningham, D. G. Green</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-enhanced spectroscopy in the deep cryogenic regime -- new hydrogen technologies for quantum sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectrometers based on high-finesse optical cavities have proven to be powerful tools for applied and fundamental studies. Extending this technology to the deep cryogenic regime is beneficial in many ways: Doppler broadening is reduced, peak absorption is enhanced, the Boltzmann distribution of rotational states is narrowed, all unwanted molecular species disturbing the spectra are frozen out, and dense spectra of complex polyatomic molecules become easier to assign. We demonstrate a cavity-enhanced spectrometer fully operating in the deep cryogenic regime down to 4 K. We solved several technological challenges that allowed us to uniformly cool not only the sample but also the entire cavity, including the mirrors and cavity length actuator, which ensures the thermodynamic equilibrium of a gas sample. Our technology well isolates the cavity from external noise and cryocooler vibrations. This instrument enables a variety of fundamental and practical applications. We demonstrate a few examples based on accurate spectroscopy of cryogenic hydrogen molecules: accurate test of the quantum electrodynamics for molecules; realization of the primary SI standards for temperature, concentration and pressure in the deep cryogenic regime; measurement of the H$_{2}$ phase diagram; and determination of the ortho-para spin isomer conversion rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12703v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamil Stankiewicz, Marcin Makowski, Micha{\l} S{\l}owi\'nski, Kamil L. So{\l}tys, Bogdan Bednarski, Hubert J\'o\'zwiak, Nikodem Stolarczyk, Mateusz Naro\.znik, Dariusz Kierski, Szymon W\'ojtewicz, Agata Cygan, Grzegorz Kowzan, Piotrz Mas{\l}owski, Mariusz Piwi\'nski, Daniel Lisak, Piotr Wcis{\l}o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly charged isomeric qubits from antiproton annihilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe how the annihilation of antiprotons can be utilized to generate highly charged synthetic qubits in an ion-trap setup. We identify the qubit transitions in the hyperfine splitting of Hydrogen-like atoms composed of an isomer and a single electron in the ground state. We identify promising candidates in the isomers of Y, Nb, Rh, In, and Sb, for which the hyperfine transition lies in the infrared and whose excited state level lifetime is in the hundreds of milliseconds, which is suitable for metrology applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12832v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Alfaro, Lorenz Panzl, Jakub Zieli\'nski, Sankarshan Choudapurkar, Fredrik Parnefjord Gustafsson, Matthias Germann, Tommaso Faorlin, Yannick Weiser, Thomas Lafenthaler, Thomas Monz, Michael Doser, Georgy Kornakov, Giovanni Cerchiari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Fermi superfluids with tunable pairing interactions under the influence of spin-dependent Rydberg molecular potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the energy spectrum and eigenstates of two-component atomic Fermi superfluids with tunable pairing interactions in the presence of spin-dependent ultra long-range Rydberg molecule (ULRM) potentials, within the Bogoliubov-de Gennes formalism. The attractive ULRM potentials lead to local density accumulation, while their difference results in a local polarization potential and induces the in-gap Yu-Shiba-Rusinov (YSR) states whose energies lie below the bulk energy gap. A transition from equal-population to population-imbalance occurs as the pairing strength falls below a critical value, accompanied by the emergence of local Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) like states characterized by out-of-phase wave functions and lower energies compared to the YSR states. The negative contribution emanating from the FFLO-like states also causes a sign change in the gap function within the ULRM potentials. Depending on the Rydberg state generating the ULRM potentials, the transition towards population-imbalance can be on either the BCS or the Bose-Einstein condensation side of the Fermi superfluid. Additionally, spin-polarized bound states arise along with oscillatory ``clumpy states" to compensate for the local density difference. Finally, we discuss possible experimental realizations and measurements of the composite Rydberg atom-Fermi superfluid system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09836v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Chun Chien, Seth T. Rittenhouse, S. I. Mistakidis, H. R. Sadeghpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy spectrum of the long-range Lennard-Jones potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discrete energy spectra of composite inverse power-law binding potentials of the form $V(r;\alpha,\beta,n)=-\alpha/r^2+\beta/r^n$ with $n&gt;2$ are studied {\it analytically}. In particular, using a functional matching procedure for the eigenfunctions of the radial Schr\"odinger equation, we derive a remarkably compact analytical formula for the discrete spectra of binding energies $\{E(\alpha,\beta,n;k)\}^{k=\infty}_{k=1}$ which characterize the highly-excited bound-state resonances of these long-range binding potentials. Our results are of practical importance for the physics of polarized molecules, the physics of composite polymers, and also for physical models describing the quantum interactions of bosonic particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12271v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The European Physical Journal Plus 133, 489 (2018)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shahar Hod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-mechanical numerical model of interaction between dark atom and nucleus of substance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The hypothesis of composite $XHe$ dark atoms may provide solution to the long-standing problem of direct searches for dark matter particles. The main problem of the $XHe$ dark atom is its ability to strongly interact with the nucleus of substance, arising from the unshielded nuclear attraction between the helium nucleus and the nucleus of matter. It is assumed that in order to prevent the destruction of the bound structure of dark atom, the effective potential of interaction between $XHe$ and the nucleus of substance must have dipole Coulomb barrier that prevents the fusion of dark matter atom particles with the nucleus of substance. The problem in describing the interaction between dark atom and substance nucleus is the three-body problem, for which an exact analytical solution is not available. Consequently, to assess the physical meaning of the proposed scenario, it is essential to develop a numerical approach. Our approach involves consistently developing an accurate quantum mechanical description of this three-body system, comprising bound dark atom and the external nucleus of substance. We incorporate the necessary effects and interactions to enhance the precision of the results, which helps to elucidate the most significant aspects of the proposed dark atom scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12407v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. E. Bikbaev, M. Yu. Khlopov, A. G. Mayorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing curved spacetime with a distributed atomic processor clock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum dynamics on curved spacetime has never been directly probed beyond the Newtonian limit. Although we can describe such dynamics theoretically, experiments would provide empirical evidence that quantum theory holds even in this extreme limit. The practical challenge is the minute spacetime curvature difference over the length scale of the typical extent of quantum effects. Here we propose a quantum network of alkaline earth(-like) atomic processors for constructing a distributed quantum state that is sensitive to the differential proper time between its constituent atomic processor nodes, implementing a quantum observable that is affected by post-Newtonian curved spacetime. Conceptually, we delocalize one clock between three locations by encoding the presence or absence of a clock into the state of the local atoms. By separating three atomic nodes over $\sim$km-scale elevation differences and distributing one clock between them via a W-state, we demonstrate that the curvature of spacetime is manifest in the interference of the three different proper times that give rise to three distinct beat notes in our non-local observable. We further demonstrate that $N$-atom entanglement within each node enhances the interrogation bandwidth by a factor of $N$. We discuss how our system can probe new facets of fundamental physics, such as the linearity, unitarity and probabilistic nature of quantum theory on curved spacetime. Our protocol combines several recent advances with neutral atom and trapped ions to realize a novel quantum probe of curved spacetime uniquely enabled by quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12954v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob P. Covey, Igor Pikovski, Johannes Borregaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Features of alkali D$_2$ line magnetically-induced transitions excited under {\pi}-polarized laser radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15607v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The impact of the optical field polarization on the spectrum of magnetically-induced transitions, a class of transitions forbidden at zero magnetic field, is studied with a weak-probe sub-Doppler technique. The high spectral resolution of the technique combined with the simplicity in interpreting the observed spectra, allows to follow the behavior of individual transitions as a function of the magnetic field amplitude. We observe only one intense transition (out of $2F_g+1$, where F is the quantum number associated with the total angular momentum of the atom) in the case of linear ($\pi$) polarization (a configuration where the applied magnetic field is parallel to the electric field from the laser radiation) in the $F_g\rightarrow F_g+2$ manifolds of $^{85}$Rb, $^{87}$Rb and $^{133}$Cs for fields above a few hundreds of gauss. We show that this behavior is in agreement with a model based on the diagonalization of the Zeeman Hamiltonian matrix. With the rapid development of micro-machined vapor-cell-based sensors these results will be of use to magnetometers operating above Earth field, wide-range laser frequency stabilization systems and atomic Faraday filters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15607v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Sargsyan, E. Klinger, A. Amiryan, D. Sarkisyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum control of ion-atom collisions beyond the ultracold regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06073v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tunable scattering resonances are crucial for controlling atomic and molecular systems. However, their use has so far been limited to ultracold temperatures. These conditions remain hard to achieve for most hybrid trapped ion-atom systems -- a prospective platform for quantum technologies and fundamental research. Here we measure inelastic collision probabilities for ${\text{Sr}^++\text{Rb}}$ and use them to calibrate a comprehensive theoretical model of ion-atom collisions. Our theoretical results, compared with experimental observations, confirm that quantum interference effects persist to the multiple-partial-wave regime, leading to the pronounced state and mass dependence of the collision rates. Using our model, we go beyond interference and identify a rich spectrum of Feshbach resonances at moderate magnetic fields with the Rb atom in its lower ($f=1$) hyperfine state, which persist at temperatures as high as 1 mK. Future observation of these predicted resonances should allow precise control of the short-range dynamics in ${\text{Sr}^+}+{\text{Rb}}$ collisions under unprecedentedly warm conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06073v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adr8256</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Adv. 11, eadr8256 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maks Z. Walewski, Matthew D. Frye, Or Katz, Meirav Pinkas, Roee Ozeri, Micha{\l} Tomza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tri-axial time-dependent magnetic field calibrated in-situ by harmonic analysis of adiabatically evolving atomic spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14574v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a methodology to calibrate in situ a set of coils generating bi- or tri-axial magnetic fields, at frequencies where a calibration performed under static conditions would be inaccurate. The methodology uses harmonic analysis of one component of the magnetization of an atomic sample whose spins adiabatically follow an ad hoc applied time-dependent field. The procedure enables the identification of phases and amplitudes of the coil currents required to produce a dynamic magnetic field with the assigned polarization. This determines coil constants that can be subsequently used to produce arbitrary three-dimensional time-dependent fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14574v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Bevilacqua, Valerio Biancalana, Yordanka Dancheva, Alessandro Fregosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomistic modeling of the channeling process with and without account for ionising collisions: A comparative study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07633v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a quantitative analysis of the impact of inelastic collisions of ultra-relativistic electrons and positrons, passing through oriented crystalline targets, on the channeling efficiency and on the intensity of the channeling radiation. The analysis is based on the numerical simulations of the channeling process performed using the MBNExplorer software package. The ionising collisions, being random, fast and local events, are incorporated into the classical molecular dynamics framework according to their probabilities. This methodology is outlined in the paper. The case studies presented refer to electrons with energy $\E$ ranging from 270 to 1500 MeV and positrons with $\E=530$ MeV incident on thick (up to 1 mm) single diamond, silicon and germanium crystals oriented along the (110) and (111) planar directions. In order to elucidate the role of the ionising collisions, the simulations were performed with and without account for the ionising collisions. The case studies presented demonstrate that both approaches yield highly similar results for the electrons. For the positrons, the ionising collisions reduce significantly the channeling efficiency. However, it has been observed that this effect does not result in a corresponding change in the radiation intensity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07633v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. B. Sushko, A. V. Korol, A. V. Solov'yov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-iterative Triples for Transcorrelated Coupled Cluster Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07858v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an implementation of a perturbative triples correction for the coupled cluster ansatz including single and double excitations based on the transcorrelated Hamiltonian. Transcorrelation introduces explicit electron correlation in the electronic Hamiltonian through similarity transformation with a correlation factor. Due to this transformation, the transcorrelated Hamiltonian includes up to three-body couplings and becomes non-Hermitian. Since the conventional coupled cluster equations are solved by projection, it is well suited to harbor non-Hermitian Hamiltonians. The arising three-body operator, however, creates a huge memory bottleneck and increases the runtime scaling of the coupled cluster equations. As it has been shown that the three-body operator can be approximated, by expressing the Hamiltonian in the normal-ordered form, we investigate this approximation for the perturbative triples correction. Results are compared with a code-generation based transcorrelated coupled cluster implementation up to quadruple excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07858v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jctc.4c01062</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian M\"orchen, Alberto Baiardi, Micha{\l} Lesiuk, Markus Reiher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent localization of spin-orbit and Rabi-coupled Bose-Einstein condensates in a random potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06005v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of the spin-orbit (SO) and Rabi couplings on the localization of the spin-1/2 condensate trapped in a one-dimensional random potential. Our studies reveal that the spin-dependent couplings create distinct localization regimes, resulting in various relations between localization and spin-related properties. First, we examine the localization in the linear condensate and find that the SO coupling can lead to a transition of the localized state from the "basin-like" to the "void" region of the potential. For a weak random potential upon an increase in the SO coupling, we find a re-entrant transition from a broad to narrow localized state and back at a higher SO coupling. Further, we analyze the competing role of inter-species and intra-species interactions on the localization of the condensate. We find the appearance of spin-dependent localization as the interactions increase beyond threshold values for a sufficiently strong disorder. Our findings on controlling spin-dependent localization may be useful for future ultracold atomic experiments and corresponding spin-related quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06005v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/adafd8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>New Journal of Physics 27, 023018 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Swarup K. Sarkar, Sh. Mardonov, E. Ya. Sherman, Paulsamy Muruganandam, Pankaj K. Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
