<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atom-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph</link>
    <description>physics.atom-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atom-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 05:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sawtooth wave adiabatic passage in a grating magneto-optical trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate sawtooth wave adiabatic passage (SWAP) in a grating magneto-optical trap (MOT) operating on the $^1$S$_0$ $\rightarrow$ $^3$P$_1$ transition of neutral $^{88}$Sr. From numerical simulations of SWAP using our laser beam geometry, we find that SWAP provides greater cooling than triangle wave frequency modulation despite the complex polarization environment of a grating MOT. The simulation is confirmed by our experimental results, where we demonstrate a factor of two improvement in transfer efficiency between our $^1$S$_0$ $\rightarrow$ $^1$P$_1$ grating MOT and our $^1$S$_0$ $\rightarrow$ $^3$P$_1$ grating MOT. We trap up to $3\times10^6$ $^{88}$Sr atoms in the $^1$S$_0$ $\rightarrow$ $^3$P$_1$ grating MOT, at an average temperature of 4.9 $\mu$K with a lifetime of approximately 0.7 s. Our results show that SWAP is effective in non-orthogonal laser beam geometries, allowing greater duty cycles or higher atom number in sensors based on narrow-line grating MOTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06230v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter K. Elgee, Ananya Sitaram, Sara Ahanchi, Nikolai N. Klimov, Stephen P. Eckel, Gretchen K. Campbell, Daniel S. Barker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio calculations of the electronic structure of Ac+</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate spectroscopic investigations of the heaviest elements are inherently challenging, due to their short lifetimes and low production yields. Success of such measurements requires both dedicated experimental techniques and strong theoretical support. Laser resonance chromatography (LRC) is a promising approach for heavy ion spectroscopy, in particularly for metals with low vapour pressure, such as actinium. We have employed the state-of-the-art relativistic Fock space coupled cluster approach as well as the configuration interaction with many-body perturbation theory method to calculate the energy levels, the transition amplitudes, the branching ratios, and the hyperfine structure parameters of the lowest excited states in Ac+. Knowledge of these properties is required for the design of experiments. Our calculations are in close agreement with experimental transition energies, leading us to expect a similar level of accuracy for the calculated hyperfine structure parameters. Based on these predictions, two possible experimental schemes are proposed for the planned LRC measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06528v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genevieve Geehan, Marten Luit Reitsma, Johan David Polet, Mustapha Laatiaoui, Julian Berengut, Anastasia Borschevsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability, degeneracy, and scalability of a 600-site cavity array microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06587v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical cavities are a foundational technology for controlling light-matter interactions. While interfacing a single cavity to either an atom or ensemble has become a standard tool, the advent of single atom control in large atomic arrays has spurred interest in a new frontier of ``many-cavity QED,'' featuring many independent resonators capable of separately addressing individual quantum emitters. In this fast-evolving landscape, the cavity array microscope was recently introduced -- employing free space intra-cavity optics to engineer a two-dimensional array of tightly spaced cavity TEM$_{00}$ modes with wavelength-scale waists, ideally suited for interfacing with atom arrays. Here we realize the next-generation of this architecture, achieving hundreds of degenerate cavity modes with improved, uniform finesse, and explore the technical features of the system which will enable further scalability. In particular, we study imperfections, including optical aberrations, field of view constraints, array non-degeneracies, and losses from optical elements. We identify the sensitivity to these various vectors and exposit the control knobs and techniques necessary to align and operate the system in a stable manner. Ultimately, we lay out a pathway towards operation with tens of thousands of independent cavities while maintaining compatibility with existing atom arrays, paving the way to myriad applications including highly parallelized remote entanglement generation, fast and non-destructive mid-circuit readout, and the implementation of hybrid atom-photon Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06587v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Soper, Danial Shadmany, Adam L. Shaw, Lukas Palm, David I. Schuster, Jonathan Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiperiodic dynamics in the nondipole x-ray strong field ionization in stabilization regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in strong x-ray laser techniques enable the study of nonlinear multiphoton ionization in extreme high-frequency fields. Although the stabilization regime in such fields is theoretically established, its modified properties in the nondipole regime for long laser pulses remains unknown. Here, we numerically investigate the strong-field ionization of an atom in a long XUV laser pulse in the nondipole regime. Our study of the time-dependent quantum dynamics reveals a quasiperiodic modulation of the ionization yield as a function of pulse duration. We demonstrate that the Coulomb-field-induced slow oscillation of the ionized electron wave packet during the interaction is responsible for the observed modulation of the ionization yield. Furthermore, we scrutinize the unusual photon momentum sharing between the photoelectron and the ion in this extreme regime. These effects are observable in upcoming x-ray free-electron laser facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06762v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr V. Boitsov, Karen Z. Hatsagortsyan, Christoph H. Keitel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton-Size Resolution of the Hyperfine Puzzle in Hydrogen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Baym and Farrar (arXiv:2601.02300v1) have recently pointed out a puzzle in understanding the role of the hyperfine interaction in the ground state of a hydrogen atom. If one uses a variational wave function in which the Bohr radius, $a_0$ is replaced by a variational radius parameter, $R$, first-order perturbation theory can give a contribution to the energy proportional to $-1/R^3$. This raises the question of why the hyperfine interaction does not lead to collapse of hydrogen. I show that including the effects of the non-zero size of the proton leads to a resolution of the puzzle such that the variational procedure yields a value of $R$ that is indistinguishable from $a_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06929v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerald A. Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the Dicke model in a two-dimensional ion crystal: chaos, quantum thermalization, and revivals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum many-body systems driven far from equilibrium can exhibit chaos, entanglement, and non-classical correlations, yet directly observing these phenomena in large, closed quantum systems remains challenging. Here we realize the Dicke model -- a fundamental description of light-matter interactions -- in a two-dimensional crystal of approximately 100 trapped ions. The ions' internal state is optically coupled to the center of mass vibrational mode via an optical spin-dependent force, enabling unitary many-body dynamics beyond the mean-field and few-body limits. In the integrable regime, where the phonons can be adiabatically eliminated, we observe a dynamical phase transition between ferromagnetic to paramagnetic spin phases. In contrast, when the spins and phonons are strongly coupled, we observe clear signatures of non-integrable chaotic dynamics, including erratic phase-space trajectories and the exponential growth of excitations and entanglement quantified by the one-body R\'enyi entropy. By quenching from an unstable fixed point in the near-integrable regime, quantum noise can generate correlated spin-phonon excitations. Our numerical calculations, in clear agreement with experiment, reveal the generation of two-mode spin-phonon squeezing, 2.6 dB below the standard quantum limit (4.6 dB relative to the initial thermal state), followed by generalized vacuum Rabi collapses and revivals. Our results establish large ion crystals as scalable analog quantum simulators of non-equilibrium light-matter dynamics and provide a controlled platform for experimental studies of information scrambling and entanglement in closed many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06114v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryce Bullock, Sean R. Muleady, Jennifer F. Lilieholm, Yicheng Zhang, Robert J. Lewis-Swan, John J. Bollinger, Ana Maria Rey, Allison L. Carter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Nonequilibrium Equation of State for a Turbulent 2D Bose Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonequilibrium equations of state can provide an effective thermodynamic-like description of far-from-equilibrium systems. We experimentally construct such an equation for a direct energy cascade in a turbulent two-dimensional Bose gas. Our homogeneous gas is continuously driven on a large length scale and, with matching dissipation on a small length scale, exhibits a nonthermal but stationary power-law momentum distribution. Our equation of state links the cascade amplitude with the underlying scale-invariant energy flux, and can, for different drive strengths, gas densities, and interaction strengths, be recast into a universal power-law form using scalings consistent with the Gross-Pitaevskii model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06131v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Jiang, Nikolai Maslov, Andrey Karailiev, Christoph Eigen, Martin Gazo, Zoran Hadzibabic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperfine-resolved optical spectroscopy of ultracold $^{87}$Rb$^{133}$Cs molecules: the $\mathrm{b}\,^3\Pi_0$ metastable state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using an ultracold gas of $^{87}$Rb$^{133}$Cs molecules, we perform hyperfine-resolved spectroscopy of transitions from the vibronic ground state to the lowest rovibrational states of the electronic state $\mathrm{b}\,^3\Pi_0$, as a function of magnetic field. These transitions are spin forbidden, resulting in narrow linewidths, and feature near-diagonal Franck-Condon factors. We develop a model of the hyperfine and Zeeman structure that includes coupling between the $0^+$ and $0^-$ components of $\mathrm{b}\,^3\Pi_0$. We fit the spectra to obtain rotational and hyperfine coupling constants. We measure transition dipole moments associated with specific transitions by directly observing Rabi oscillations as a function of a resonant laser pulse duration. Using resonant $\pi$ pulses, we prepare molecules in the electronically excited state and directly measure the spontaneous emission rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24660v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpita Das, Albert Li Tao, Luke M. Fernley, Fritz von Gierke, Philip D. Gregory, Simon L. Cornish, Jeremy M. Hutson, Romain Vexiau, Olivier Dulieu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum noise in a squeezed-light-enhanced multiparameter quantum sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study quantum enhancement of sensitivity using squeezed light in a multi-parameter quantum sensor, the hybrid dc-rf optically pumped magnetometer (hOPM) [Phys. Rev. Applied 21, 034054, (2024)]. Using a single spin ensemble, the hOPM acquires both the dc field strength (scalar magnetometry), and resonantly detects one quadrature of the ac magnetic field at a chosen frequency (rf magnetometry). In contrast to the Bell-Bloom scalar magnetometer [Phys. Rev. Lett. 127, 193601 (2021)], the back-action evasion in the hOPM is incomplete, leading to a nontrivial interplay of the three quantum noise sources in this system: photon shot noise, spin projection noise, and measurement back-action noise. We observe these interactions using squeezed light as a tool to control the distribution of optical quantum noise between $S_2$ and $S_3$ polarization Stokes components, and the resulting effect on readout quantum noise and measurement back-action. These results demonstrate quantum-enhanced sensitivity in a continuously operating multi-parameter sensor and reveal fundamental trade-offs between sensitivity, back-action, and bandwidth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08190v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Sierant, Diana M\'endez-Avalos, Santiago Tabares Giraldo, Morgan W. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
