<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 04:02:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Coupling of Hydrodynamics and Reactions in Nuclear Statistical Equilibrium for Modeling Convection in Massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build on the simplified spectral deferred corrections (SDC) coupling of hydrodynamics and reactions to handle the case of nuclear statistical equilibrium (NSE) and electron/positron captures/decays in the cores of massive stars. Our approach blends a traditional reaction network on the grid with a tabulated NSE state from a very large, $\mathcal{O}(100)$ nuclei, network. We demonstrate how to achieve second-order accuracy in the simplified-SDC framework when coupling NSE to hydrodynamics, with the ability to evolve the star on the hydrodynamics timestep. We discuss the application of this method to convection in massive stars leading up to core-collapse. We also show how to initialize the initial convective state from a 1D model in a self-consistent fashion. All of these developments are done in the publicly available Castro simulation code and the entire simulation methodology is fully GPU accelerated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14786v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Zingale, Zhi Chen, Eric T. Johnson, Max P. Katz, Alexander Smith Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emission Measures Demystified</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the terms, spectral radiance and spectral irradiance, and show how their precise definitions are crucial for interpreting observations made with different instruments covering widely different energy or wavelength ranges. We show how the use of column and volume emission measures in different solar physics and astrophysics communities has led to confusion in relating measured extreme ultraviolet and soft X-ray spectra with theoretical spectra generated, in particular, using CHIANTI. We describe a method for obtaining spatially integrated X-ray line and continuum spectra using CHIANTI that requires a column emission measure when only the plasma temperature and volume emission measure, but not the source area, are known from observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14845v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian R. Dennis, Kenneth J. H. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of Turbulent Fluctuations in the Sub-Alfvenic Solar Wind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parker Solar Probe (PSP) observed sub-Alfvenic solar wind intervals during encounters 8 - 14, and low-frequency magnetohydrodynamic turbulence in these regions may differ from that in super-Alfvenic wind. We apply a new mode-decomposition analysis (Zank et al 2023) to the sub-Alfv\'enic flow observed by PSP on 2021 April 28, identifying and characterizing entropy, magnetic islands, forward and backward Alfv\'en waves, including weakly/non-propagating Alfv\'en vortices, forward and backward fast and slow magnetosonic modes. Density fluctuations are primarily and almost equally entropy and backward propagating slow magnetosonic modes. The mode-decomposition provides phase information (frequency and wavenumber k) for each mode. Entropy-density fluctuations have a wavenumber anisotropy k_{||} &gt;&gt; k_{perp} whereas slow mode density fluctuations have k_{perp} &gt; k_{||}. Magnetic field fluctuations are primarily magnetic island modes (delta B^i) with an O(1) smaller contribution from uni-directionally propagating Alfven waves (delta B^{A+}) giving a variance anisotropy of &lt;{\delta B^i}^2&gt; / &lt;delta B^A}^2&gt; = 4.1. Incompressible magnetic fluctuations dominate compressible contributions from fast and slow magnetosonic modes. The magnetic island spectrum is Kolmogorov-like k_{perp}^{-1.6} in perpendicular wavenumber and the uni-directional Alfven wave spectra are k_{||}^{-1.6} and k_{perp}^{-1.5}. Fast magnetosonic modes propagate at essentially the Alfv\'en speed with anti-correlated transverse velocity and magnetic field fluctuations and are almost exclusively magnetic due to beta_p&lt;&lt;1. Transverse velocity fluctuations are the dominant velocity component in fast magnetosonic modes and longitudinal fluctuations dominate in slow modes. Mode-decomposition is an effective tool in identifying the basic building blocks of MHD turbulence and provides detailed phase information about each of the modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14861v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gary P. Zank, Lingling Zhao, Laxman Adhikari, Daniele Telloni, Prashant Baruwal, Prashrit Baruwal, Xingyu Zhu, Masaru Nakanotani, Alexander Pitna, Justin C. Kasper, Stuart D. Bale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-resolved XMM-Newton observations of the massive post-RLOF system HD 149404</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15034v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the X-ray emission of HD 149404, a 9.81-day period O-star binary in a post-Roche lobe overflow evolutionary stage. X-ray emission of O-star binaries consists of the intrinsic emission of the individual O stars and a putative additional component arising from the wind-wind interaction. Phase-locked variations in the X-ray spectra can be used to probe the properties of the stellar winds of such systems. XMM-Newton observations of HD 149404 collected at two conjunction phases and a quadrature phase were analysed. X-ray spectra were extracted and flux variations as a function of orbital phase were inferred. The flux ratios were analysed with models considering various origins for the X-ray emission. The highest and lowest X-ray fluxes are observed at conjunction phases respectively with the primary and secondary star in front. The flux variations are nearly grey with only marginal energy dependence. None of the models accounting for photoelectric absorption by homogeneous stellar winds perfectly reproduces the observed variations. Whilst the overall X-ray luminosity is consistent with a pure intrinsic emission, the best formal agreement with the observed variations is obtained with a model assuming pure wind-wind collision X-ray emission. The lack of significant energy-dependence of the opacity most likely hints at the presence of optically thick clumps in the winds of HD 149404.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15034v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Rauw, S. Lizin, S. Rosu, E. Mossoux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of the disk precession models with the photometric behavior of TT Ari in 2021-2023</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comparative analysis of photometric observations of the cataclysmic variable TT Ari in its bright state, obtained by the TESS orbital observatory in 2021 and 2023 and by ground-based amateur telescopes in 2022. The light curves from 2021 and 2022 are dominated by modulations with a period slightly shorter than the orbital one (negative superhumps), 0.13293 and 0.13273$\,$d respectively. In 2023, much stronger modulations appeared on a much longer time scale of a few days with an amplitude of up to 0.5 mag, compared to 0.2 mag in 2021. The negative superhump variability with the period of 0.13376$\,$d was also found in the first half of the 2023 observations, but then negative superhumps suddenly almost disappeared. Less significant additional modulations with a period exceeding the orbital one (positive superhumps) were detected in 2021 and 2022. Their periods were 0.15106 and 0.1523$\,$d, correspondingly. We also found a previously unnoticed periodic signal corresponding to the orbital period of 0.13755$\,$d in the TESS observations in 2021. Theoretical models of tidal precession of an elliptical disk predict a decrease in the precession period with increasing disk radius, which is consistent with the observed photometric behavior of the system. It enables us to estimate the mass ratio of the components in TT$\,$Ari to be $q\approx 0.235$. The tilted disk precession model predicts a period of nodal precession whose value is in general agreement with observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15254v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. F. Suleimanov, K. V. Belyakov, J. M. Perales, V. V. Neustroev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconnaissance ultracool spectra in the Euclid Deep Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Euclid will carry out a deep survey benefiting the discovery and characterisation of ultracool dwarfs (UCDs), especially in the Euclid Deep Fields (EDFs), which the telescope will scan repeatedly throughout its mission. The photometric and spectroscopic standards in the EDFs are important benchmarks, crucial for the classification and characterisation of new UCD discoveries and for the calibration of the mission itself. Aims. We aim to provide a list of photometric UCD candidates and collect near-infrared reconnaissance spectra for M, L, and T-type UCDs in the EDFs as future Euclid UCD references. Methods. In EDF North, we cross-matched public optical and infrared surveys with certain photometric criteria to select UCDs. In EDF Fornax and EDF South, we used photometrically classified samples from the literature. We also include UCDs identified by Gaia DR2. We selected 7 UCD targets with different spectral types from the lists and obtained low-resolution 0.9-2.5 {\mu}m spectra of them using GTC/EMIR and the VLT/X-shooter. We also selected a young, bright L dwarf near EDF Fornax to test the coherence of these two facilities. We included an extra T dwarf in EDF North with its published J-band spectrum. Results. We retrieved a list of 92 (49, 231) M, 33 (29, 115) L, and 1 (0, 2) T dwarf candidates in EDF North, Fornax, and South, respectively. They are provided to guide future UCD discoveries and characterisations by Euclid. In total, we collected near-infrared spectra for 9 UCDs, including 2 M types, 3 L types, and 4 T types in or close to the 3 EDFs. The Euclidised spectra show consistency in their spectral classification, which demonstrates that slitless Euclid spectroscopy will recover the spectral types with high fidelity for UCDs, both in the EDFs and in the wide survey. We also demonstrate that Euclid will be able to distinguish different age groups of UCDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15288v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerry Jun-Yan Zhang, Nicolas Lodieu, Eduardo Mart\'in</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Flavor Composition of Supernova Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14762v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that standard matter effects in the outer layers of core-collapse supernovae significantly constrain the flavor composition of the neutrino flux, even with the enormous uncertainties originating from self-induced flavor conversions in the supernova core. Under certain conditions, the neutrino flux resulting from self-induced conversions can be represented as a combination of flavor eigenstates in an arbitrary flavor ratio configuration. In this scenario, we find that, for the normal mass ordering, the fraction of neutrinos with electron flavor reaching the Earth, denoted as $f_{\nu_e}$, is constrained to be less than $0.5$ for all energies throughout the emission phase, whereas, for inverted mass ordering, we anticipate neutrinos arriving in near flavor equipartition ($f_{\nu_e}\approx 1/3$). In case adiabaticity is violated in the region of standard matter effects, the result is flavor equipartition for both mass orderings. Subsequently, we elaborate on the impact of wave-packet decoherence during self-induced conversions and explore alternative scenarios that could affect the aforementioned results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14762v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Capanema, Yago Porto, Maria Manuela Saez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millimeter and submillimeter spectroscopy of the deuterated molecular ion SD+</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15035v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Seven rotational and fine-structure transitions of the deuterated molecular ion SD+ in the X 3S- ground electronic state have been measured in the 271-863 GHz region in the laboratory. This ion has been produced by DC-glow discharge using a mixture of D2S and argon in a free space cell in a temperature range of -140 to -160C. The rotational, centrifugal distortion, spin-spin interaction, and hyperfine constants have been determined; the standard deviation of the residuals in the fitting is 109 kHz. The set of obtained spectroscopic parameters provides a list of accurate sub-millimeter rest frequencies of SD+ for astronomical detection. We have investigated lines of SD+ toward the quasar PKS 1830-211 using the ALMA archive, as the z = 0.89 molecular absorber exists in front of this quasar. A data set covering the 297 GHz region includes the N_J = 2_3-1_2 transition at 561 GHz due to redshift, providing an upper limit of the column density Ntot = 3 x 10^12 cm-2 for SD+.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15035v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mitsunori Araki, Valerio Lattanzi, Christian P. Endres, Paula Caselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear Three-mode Coupling of Gravity Modes in Rotating Slowly Pulsating B Stars: Stationary Solutions and Modeling Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02972v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Context. Slowly pulsating B (SPB) stars display multi-periodic variability in the gravito-inertial mode regime with indications of non-linear resonances between modes. Several have undergone asteroseismic modeling in the past few years to infer their internal properties in a linear setting. Rotation is typically included in the modeling by means of the traditional approximation of rotation (TAR).
  Aims. We aim to extend the set of tools available for asteroseismology, by describing time-independent (stationary) resonant non-linear coupling among three gravito-inertial modes within the TAR. Such coupling offers the opportunity to use mode amplitude ratios in the asteroseismic modeling process, instead of only relying on frequencies of linear eigenmodes.
  Methods. Following observational detections, we derive expressions for the resonant stationary non-linear coupling between three gravito-inertial modes in rotating stars. We assess selection rules and stability domains for stationary solutions and predict non-linear frequencies and amplitude ratio observables that can be compared with their observed counterparts.
  Results. The non-linear frequency shifts of stationary couplings are negligible compared to typical frequency errors derived from observations. The theoretically predicted amplitude ratios of combination frequencies match with some of their observational counterparts in the SPB targets. Other observed ratios could be linked to other saturation mechanisms, to interactions between different modes, or to different opacity gradients in the driving zone.
  Conclusions. Our non-linear mode coupling formalism can explain some of the stationary amplitude ratios of observed resonant mode couplings in single SPB stars monitored during 4 years by Kepler.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02972v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Van Beeck, Tim Van Hoolst, Conny Aerts, Jim Fuller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High mass function ellipsoidal variables in the Gaia Focused Product Release: searching for black hole candidates in the binary zoo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09531v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent Gaia Focused Product Release contains radial velocity time-series for more than 9,000 Gaia long-period photometric variables. Here we search for binary systems with large radial velocity amplitudes to identify candidates with massive, unseen companions. Eight targets have binary mass function $f(M)&gt;1\ M_\odot$, three of which are eclipsing binaries. The remaining five show evidence of ellipsoidal modulations. We fit spectroscopic orbit models to the Gaia radial velocities, and fit the spectral energy distributions of three targets. For the two systems most likely to host dark companions, J0946 and J1640, we use PHOEBE to fit the ASAS-SN light curves and Gaia radial velocities. The derived companion masses are $&gt;3 M_\odot$, but the high Galactic dust extinctions towards these objects limit our ability to rule out main sequence companions or subgiants hotter than the photometric primaries. These systems are similar to other stellar-mass black hole impostors, notably the Unicorn (V723 Mon) and the Giraffe (2M04123153$+$6738486). While it is possible that J1640 and J0946 are similar examples of stripped giant star binaries, high-resolution spectra can be used to determine the nature of their companions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09531v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. M. Rowan, Todd A. Thompson, T. Jayasinghe, C. S. Kochanek, K. Z. Stanek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Establishing a mass-loss rate relation for red supergiants in the Large Magellanic Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15163v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The high mass-loss rates of red supergiants (RSGs) drastically affect their evolution and final fate, but their mass-loss mechanism remains poorly understood. Various empirical prescriptions scaled with luminosity have been derived in the literature, yielding results with a dispersion of 2-3 orders of magnitude. We determine an accurate mass-loss rate relation with luminosity and other parameters using a large, clean sample of RSGs and explain the discrepancy between previous works. We assembled a sample of 2,219 RSG candidates in the Large Magellanic Cloud, with ultraviolet to mid-infrared photometry in up to 49 filters. We determined the luminosity of each RSG by integrating the spectral energy distribution and the mass-loss rate using the radiative transfer code DUSTY. Our derived RSG mass-loss rates range from $10^{-9} M_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$ to $10^{-5} M_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$, mainly depending on the luminosity. The average mass-loss rate is $9.3\times 10^{-7} M_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$ for $\log{(L/L_\odot)}&gt;4$. We established a mass-loss rate relation as a function of luminosity and effective temperature. Furthermore, we found a turning point in the relation of mass-loss rate versus luminosity relation at approximately $\log{(L/L_\odot)} = 4.4$, indicating enhanced rates beyond this limit. We show that this enhancement correlates with photometric variability. Moreover, we compared our results with prescriptions from the literature, finding an agreement with works assuming steady-state winds. Additionally, we examined the effect of different assumptions on our models and found that radiatively driven winds result in mass-loss rates higher by 2-3 orders of magnitude, which are unrealistically high for RSGs. Finally, we found that 21% of our sample constitute current binary candidates. This has a minor effect on our mass-loss relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15163v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Antoniadis, A. Z. Bonanos, S. de Wit, E. Zapartas, G. Munoz-Sanchez, G. Maravelias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring solar differential rotation and viscosity via passive imaging with inertial waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00488v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent discovery of inertial waves on the surface of the Sun offers new possibilities to learn about the solar interior. These waves are long-lived with a period on the order of the Sun rotation period ($\sim$27 days) and are sensitive to parameters deep inside the Sun. They are excited by turbulent convection, leading to a passive imaging problem. In this work, we present the forward and inverse problem of reconstructing viscosity and differential rotation on the Sun from cross-covariance observations of these inertial waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00488v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tram Thi Ngoc Nguyen, Thorsten Hohage, Damien Fournier, Laurent Gizon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining a relativistic mean field model using neutron star mass-radius measurements I: Nucleonic models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.17518v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Measurements of neutron star mass and radius or tidal deformability deliver unique insight into the equation of state (EOS) of cold dense matter. EOS inference is very often done using generalized parametric or non-parametric models which deliver no information on composition. In this paper we consider a microscopic nuclear EOS model based on a field theoretical approach. We show that current measurements from NICER and gravitational wave observations constrain primarily the symmetric nuclear matter EOS. We then explore what could be delivered by measurements of mass and radius at the level anticipated for future large-area X-ray timing telescopes. These should be able to place very strong limits on the symmetric nuclear matter EOS, in addition to constraining the nuclear symmetry energy that determines the proton fraction inside the neutron star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.17518v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Huang, Geert Raaijmakers, Anna L. Watts, Laura Tolos, Constan\c{c}a Provid\^encia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decaying turbulence in molecular clouds: how does it affect filament networks and star formation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12428v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The fragmentation of gas to form stars in molecular clouds is intrinsically linked to the turbulence within them. These internal motions are set at the birth of the cloud and may vary with galactic environment and as the cloud evolves. In this paper, we introduce a new suite of 15 high-resolution 3D molecular cloud simulations using the moving mesh code AREPO to investigate the role of different decaying turbulent modes (mixed, compressive and solenoidal) and virial ratios on the evolution of a $10^4\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ molecular cloud. We find that diffuse regions maintain a strong relic of the initial turbulent mode, whereas the initial gravitational potential dominates dense regions. Solenoidal seeded models thus give rise to a diffuse cloud with filament-like morphology, and an excess of brown dwarf mass fragments. Compressive seeded models have an early onset of star-formation, centrally condensed morphologies and a higher accretion rate, along with overbound clouds. 3D filaments identified using DisPerSE and analyzed through a new Python toolkit we develop and make publicly available with this work called FIESTA, show no clear trend in lengths, masses and densities between initial turbulent modes. Overbound clouds, however, produce more filaments and thus have more mass in filaments. The hubs formed by converging filaments are found to favour star-formation, with surprisingly similar mass distributions independent of the number of filaments connecting the hub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12428v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiten Dhandha, Zoe Faes, Rowan J. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of Lower Mass-gap Black Hole--Neutron Star Binary Mergers through Super-Eddington Stable Mass Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14256v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Super-Eddington accretion of neutron stars (NSs) has been suggested both observationally and theoretically. In this paper, we propose that NSs in close-orbit binary systems with companions of helium (He) stars, most of which systems form after the common-envelope phase, could experience super-Eddington stable Case BB/BC mass transfer (MT), and can sometimes occur accretion-induced collapses (AICs) to form lower mass-gap black holes (mgBHs). Our detailed binary evolution simulations reveal that AIC events tend to happen if the primaries NS have an initial mass $\gtrsim1.7\,M_\odot$ with an accretion rate of $\gtrsim300$ times the Eddington limit. These mgBHs would have a mass nearly equal to or slightly higher than the NS maximum mass. The remnant mgBH--NS binaries after the core collapses of He stars are potential progenitors of gravitational-wave (GW) source. Multimessenger observation between GW and kilonova signals from a population of high-mass binary NS and mgBH--NS mergers formed through super-Eddington stable MT are helpful in constraining the maximum mass and equation of state of NSs. S230529ay, a mgBH--NS merger candidate recently detected in the fourth observing run of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Collaboration, could possibly originate from this formation scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14256v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Ping Zhu, Ying Qin, Zhen-Han-Tao Wang, Rui-Chong Hu, Bing Zhang, Shichao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concerning S$H_0$ES Data: Discrepant $W_{0,VI}$ Absolute Magnitudes for Cepheids in the Keystone Galaxy NGC4258</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04834v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: S$H_0$ES $VI$-band photometry for classical Cepheids in the keystone galaxy NGC4258 yield discrepant absolute magnitudes. Specifically, the 2016 and 2022 published S$H_0$ES Cepheid data for NGC4258 exhibit a substantial offset of $\Delta W_{0,VI}\simeq0^{\rm m}.3$. That adds to a suite of existing concerns associated with the S$H_0$ES analysis, which in sum imply that their relatively non-changing Hubble constant for nearly twenty years warrants scrutiny.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04834v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Majaess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving Towards Automated Interstellar Boundary Explorer Data Selection with LOTUS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08891v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Interstellar Boundary Explorer (IBEX) satellite collects data on energetic neutral atoms (ENAs) that provide insight into the heliosphere, the region surrounding our solar system and separating it from interstellar space. IBEX collects information on these particles and on extraneous ``background'' particles. While IBEX records how and when the different particles are observed, it does not distinguish between heliospheric ENA particles and incidental background particles. To address this issue, all IBEX data has historically been manually labeled as ``good'' ENA data, or ``bad'' background data. This manual culling process is incredibly time-intensive and contingent on subjective, manually-induced decision thresholds. In this paper, we develop a three-stage automated culling process, called LOTUS, that uses random forests to expedite and standardize the labelling process. In Stage 1, LOTUS uses random forests to obtain probabilities of observing true ENA particles on a per-observation basis. In Stage 2, LOTUS aggregates these probabilities to obtain predictions within small windows of time. In Stage 3, LOTUS refines these predictions. We compare the labels generated by LOTUS to those manually generated by the subject matter expert. We use various metrics to demonstrate that LOTUS is a useful automated process for supplementing and standardizing the manual culling process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08891v2</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madeline A. Stricklin, Lauren J. Beesley, Brian P. Weaver, Kelly R. Moran, Dave Osthus, Paul H. Janzen, Grant David Meadors, Daniel B. Reisenfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
