<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 04:00:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The mass of the white dwarf in YY Dra (=DO Dra): Dynamical measurement and comparative study with X-ray estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a dynamical study of the intermediate polar cataclysmic variable YY Dra based on time-series observations in the $K$ band, where the donor star is known to be the major flux contributor. We covered the $3.97$-h orbital cycle with 44 spectra taken between $2020$ and $2022$ and two epochs of photometry observed in 2021 March and May. One of the light curves was simultaneously obtained with spectroscopy to better account for the effects of irradiation of the donor star and the presence of accretion light. From the spectroscopy, we derived the radial velocity curve of the donor star metallic absorption lines, constrained its spectral type to M0.5$-$M3.5 with no measurable changes in the effective temperature between the irradiated and non-irradiated hemispheres of the star, and measured its projected rotational velocity $v_\mathrm{rot} \sin i = 103 \pm 2 \, \mathrm{km}\,\mathrm{s}^{-1}$. Through simultaneous modelling of the radial velocity and light curves, we derived values for the radial velocity semi-amplitude of the donor star, $K_2 = 188^{+1}_{-2} \, \mathrm{km} \, \mathrm{s}^{-1}$, the donor to white dwarf mass ratio, $q=M_2/M_1 = 0.62 \pm 0.02$, and the orbital inclination, $i={42^{\circ}}^{+2^{\circ}}_{-1^{\circ}}$. These binary parameters yield dynamical masses of $M_{1} = 0.99^{+0.10}_{-0.09} \, \mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ and $M_2 = 0.62^{+0.07}_{-0.06} \, \mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ ($68$ per cent confidence level). As found for the intermediate polars GK Per and XY Ari, the white dwarf dynamical mass in YY Dra significantly differs from several estimates obtained by modelling the X-ray spectral continuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17562v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayoze \'Alvarez-Hern\'andez, Manuel A. P. Torres, Tariq Shahbaz, Pablo Rodr\'iguez-Gil, Kosmas D. Gazeas, Javier S\'anchez-Sierras, Peter G. Jonker, Jes\'us M. Corral-Santana, Jose A. Acosta-Pulido, Pasi Hakala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar Models are Reliable at Low Metallicity: An Asteroseismic Age for the Ancient Very Metal-Poor Star KIC 8144907</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Very metal-poor stars ([Fe/H]&lt;-2) are important laboratories for testing stellar models and reconstructing the formation history of our galaxy. Asteroseismology is a powerful tool to probe stellar interiors and measure ages, but few asteroseismic detections are known in very metal-poor stars and none have allowed detailed modeling of oscillation frequencies. We report the discovery of a low-luminosity Kepler red giant (KIC 8144907) with high S/N oscillations, [Fe/H]=-2.66+/-0.08 and [alpha/Fe]=0.38+/-0.06, making it by far the most metal-poor star to date for which detailed asteroseismic modeling is possible. By combining the oscillation spectrum from Kepler with high-resolution spectroscopy we measure an asteroseismic mass and age of 0.79+/-0.02(ran)+/-0.01(sys) Msun and 12.0+/-0.6(ran)+/-0.4(sys) Gyr, with remarkable agreement across different codes and input physics, demonstrating that stellar models and asteroseismology are reliable for very metal-poor stars when individual frequencies are used. The results also provide a direct age anchor for the early formation of the Milky Way, implying that substantial star formation did not commence until redshift z~3 (if the star formed in-situ) or that the Milky Way has undergone merger events for at least ~12 Gyr (if the star was accreted by a dwarf satellite merger such as Gaia Enceladus).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17566v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Huber, Ditte Slumstrup, Marc Hon, Yaguang Li, Victor Aguirre Borsen-Koch, Timothy R. Bedding, Meridith Joyce, J. M. Joel Ong, Aldo Serenelli, Dennis Stello, Travis Berger, Samuel K. Grunblatt, Michael Greklek-McKeon, Teruyuki Hirano, Evan N. Kirby, Marc H. Pinsonneault, Arthur Alencastro Puls, Joel Zinn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the structural content of NGC 6357 via kinematics and NIR variability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NGC 6357, a star-forming complex at $\sim 1.7$ kpc from the Sun, contains giant molecular clouds and three prominent star clusters alongside with HII regions, very massive stars and thousands of young stellar objects in different evolutionary stages. We present a combined infrared kinematic and time domain study of the line of sight towards this region enabled by the VVVX survey. In terms of kinematics, a novel discovery emerges: an asymmetrical distribution in the vector point diagram. Some stars in the sample exhibit spatial proximity to dusty regions, with their proper motions aligned with filament projections, hinting at a younger population linked to triggered star formation. However, this distribution could also stem from an asymmetric stellar expansion event within NGC 6357, warranting further investigation. Comparing this data with Gaia revealed inconsistencies likely due to high extinction levels in the region. Additionally, owing to accretion episodes and surface cool spots, young stars display high variability. Using the $K_s$-band time series data, we overcome the extreme levels of extinction towards the region, and compile a catalogue of $774$ infrared light curves of young stars. Each light curve has been characterized in terms of asymmetry and periodicity, to infer the dominant underlying physical mechanism. These findings are then correlated with evolutionary stages, aiming to uncover potential age disparities among the observed stars. This study contributes to our understanding the intricate dynamics and evolutionary processes within NGC 6357, offering valuable insights into the formation and development of stellar populations within such complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17577v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Ordenes-Huanca, M. Zoccali, A. Bayo, J. Cuadra, R. Contreras Ramos, A. Rojas-Arriagada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar rotation and activity for cycle 24 from SDO/AIA observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The differential rotation plays a crucial role in the dynamics of the Sun. We study the solar rotation and its correlation with solar activity by applying a modified machine learning algorithm to identify and track coronal bright points (CBPs) from the Solar Dynamics Observatory/Atmospheric Imaging Assembly observations at 193 \AA\ during cycle 24. For more than 321,440 CBPs, the sidereal and meridional velocities are computed. We find the occurring height of CBPs about 5627 km above the photosphere. We obtain a rotational map for the corona by tracking CBPs at the formation height of Fe\,{\sc xii} (193 \AA) emissions. The equator rotation (14.$^{\circ}$40 to 14.$^{\circ}$54 day$^{-1}$) and latitudinal gradient of rotation ($ - $3.$^{\circ}$0 to $ - $2.$^{\circ}$64 day$^{-1}$) show very slightly positive and negative trends with solar activity (sunspots and flares), respectively. For cycle 24, our investigations show that the northern hemisphere has more differential rotation than the southern hemisphere, confirmed by the asymmetry of the midlatitude rotation parameter. The asymmetry (ranked) of the latitudinal gradient of the rotation parameter is concordant with the sunspot numbers for 7 yr within the 9 yr of the cycle; however, for only 3 yr, it is concordant with the flare index. The minimum horizontal Reynolds stress changes from about $ - $2500 m$^{2}$ s$^{-2}$ (corresponding to high activity) in 2012 and 2014 to $ - $100 m$^{2}$ s$^{-2}$ (corresponding to low activity) in 2019 over 5$^{\circ}$ to 35$^{\circ}$ latitudes within cycle 24. We conclude that the negative horizontal Reynolds stress (momentum transfer toward the Sun's equator) is a helpful indication of solar activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Shokri, Nasibe Alipour, Hossein Safari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrogen-Atmosphere White Dwarfs Are Less Likely To Be Found with Wide-Binary Companions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fraction of white dwarfs found in wide binaries is estimated by cross referencing a catalogue of wide binaries with catalogues photometrically determined white-dwarf candidates and spectroscopically confirmed white dwarf stars. The wide-binary fraction of white dwarfs with hydrogen-dominated atmospheres is about 5%, but the fraction of white dwarfs with helium or carbon-dominated atmospheres is significantly larger. Using spectroscopic classifications, the binary fraction of DA white dwarfs is determined to be $0.063\pm0.002$ and for non-DA white dwarfs is larger at $0.080\pm0.004$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17634v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy Heyl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atmospheric parameters and chemical abundances within 100 pc. A sample of G, K, and M main-sequence stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To date, we have access to enormous inventories of stellar spectra that allow the extraction of atmospheric parameters and chemical abundances essential in stellar studies. However, characterizing such a large amount of data is complex and requires a good understanding of the studied object to ensure reliable and homogeneous results. In this study, we present a methodology to measure homogenously the basic atmospheric parameters and detailed chemical abundances of over 1600 thin disk main-sequence stars in the 100 pc solar neighborhood, using APOGEE-2 infrared spectra. We employed the code tonalli to determine the atmospheric parameters using a prior on log g. The log g prior in tonalli implies an understanding of the treated population and helps to find physically coherent answers. Our atmospheric parameters agree within the typical uncertainties (100 K in Teff, 0.15 dex in log g and $[M/H]$) with previous estimations of ASPCAP and Gaia DR3. We use our temperatures to determine a new infrared color-temperature sequence, in good agreement with previous works, that can be used for any main-sequence star. Additionally, we used the BACCHUS code to determine the abundances of Mg, Al, Si, Ca, and Fe in our sample. The five elements (Mg, Al, Si, Ca, Fe) studied have an abundance distribution centered around slightly sub-solar values, in agreement with previous results for the solar neighborhood. The over 1600 main-sequence stars atmospheric parameters and chemical abundances presented here are useful in follow-up studies of the solar neighborhood or as a training set for data-driven methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17640v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo L\'opez-Valdivia, Luc\'ia Adame, Eduardo Zagala Lagunas, Carlos G. Rom\'an-Z\'u\~niga, Jes\'us Hern\'andez, Edilberto S\'anchez, Jos\'e G. Fern\'andez-Trincado, Leticia Carigi, Marina Kounkel, Richard R. Lane, Keivan G. Stassun, Sandro Villanova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WASP 0346-21: An EL CVn-Type Eclipsing Binary with Multiperiodic Pulsations in a Triple System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: VLT/UVES spectroscopic and TESS photometric observations for WASP 0346-21 allow the direct determination of its physical properties, along with the detection of a circumbinary object and oscillating signals. The high-resolution spectra yielded the radial velocities of all three stars and the atmospheric parameters of $T_{\rm eff,A}$ = 7225$\pm42$ K, [M/H] = 0.30$\pm$0.03 dex, and $v_{\rm A}$$\sin i$ = 78$\pm$5 km s$^{-1}$ of the primary component. The combined analysis of these observations resulted in the fundamental parameters of the eclipsing components and the third light of $l_3$ = 0.043$\pm$0.004, which is consistent with the light contribution of the tertiary star observed in the echelle spectra. WASP 0346-21 A resides within the overlapping main-sequence domain of $\delta$ Sct and $\gamma$ Dor variables, while the secondary component of $M_{\rm B}$ = 0.185$\pm$0.013 M$_\odot$, $R_{\rm B}$ = 0.308$\pm$0.023 R$_\odot$, $T_{\rm eff,B}$ = 10,655$\pm$146 K, and $L_{\rm B}$ = 1.09$\pm$0.17 L$_\odot$ matches well with the low-mass white dwarf (WD) model for $Z$ = 0.01, corresponding to the thick-disk population classified by the Galactic kinematics. Multifrequency analyses were performed on the residual TESS data after removing the binarity effects. The low frequencies around 26.348 day$^{-1}$ and 17.683 day$^{-1}$ are $\delta$ Sct pulsations originating from WASP 0346-21 A, and the high frequencies of 97.996 day$^{-1}$ and 90.460 day$^{-1}$ are considered to be extremely low-mass WD oscillations. These results demonstrate that WASP 0346-21 is a hierarchical triple system, consisting of an EL CVn binary with multiperiodic pulsations in each component and a distant outer tertiary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17729v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae Woo Lee, Kyeongsoo Hong, Min-Ji Jeong, Marek Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIC441725813: A new bright hybrid sdB pulsator with differential core/envelope rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the detailed analysis of a new hybrid (p- and g-mode) sdB pulsator, TIC441725813 (TYC 4427-1021-1), discovered and monitored by TESS over 670 days. The TESS light curves available for this star were analysed using prewhitening techniques to extract mode frequencies accurately. The pulsation spectrum is then interpreted through methods that include asymptotic period spacing relationships and rotational multiplets identification. We also exploited a high signal-to-noise ratio (S/N), low-resolution spectrum of TIC441725813 using grids of non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (NLTE) model atmospheres to derive its atmospheric parameters. Interestingly, several frequency multiplets interpreted as rotational splittings of deep-probing g-modes indicate a slow rotation period of at least $85.3 \pm 3.6$ day, while splittings of mostly envelope-probing p-modes suggest a significantly shorter rotation period of $17.9 \pm 0.7$ day, which implies the core (mainly the helium mantle with possibly the deeper partially-mixed helium-burning core that it surrounds) rotates at least ~4.7 times slower than the envelope. The radial velocity curves indicate that TIC441725813 is in a close binary system with a low-luminosity companion, possibly a white dwarf. While elusive in the available TESS photometry, a low-frequency signal that would correspond to a period of $\sim 6.7$ h is found, albeit at low S/N. TIC441725813 is a particularly interesting sdB star whose envelope rotates faster than the core. We hypothesise that this might be caused by the effects of tidal interaction with a companion, although in the present case, the presence of such a companion will have to be further investigated. This analysis paves the way toward a more detailed seismic probing of TIC441725813 using optimisation techniques, which will be presented in a second paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17887v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenchao Su, St\'ephane Charpinet, Marilyn Latour, Weikai Zong, Elizabeth M Green, Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The operationally ready full three-dimensional magnetohydrodynamic (3D MHD) model from the Sun to Earth: COCONUT+Icarus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar wind modelling has become a crucial area of study due to the increased dependence of modern society on technology, navigation, and power systems. Accurate space weather forecasts can predict upcoming threats to Earth's geospace. In this study, we examine a novel full magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) chain from the Sun to Earth. The goal of this study is to demonstrate the capabilities of the full MHD modelling chain from the Sun to Earth by finalising the implementation of the full MHD coronal model into the COolfluid COroNa UnsTructured (COCONUT) model and coupling it to the MHD heliospheric model Icarus. The resulting coronal model has significant advantages compared to the pre-existing polytropic alternative, as it models a more realistic bi-modal wind, which is crucial for heliospheric studies.
  In this study, only thermal conduction, radiative losses, and approximated coronal heating function were considered in the energy equation. A realistic specific heat ratio was applied. The output of the coronal model was used to onset the 3D MHD heliospheric model Icarus. A minimum solar activity case was chosen as the first test case for the full MHD model. The numerically simulated data in the corona and the heliosphere were compared to observational products. We present a first attempt to obtain the full MHD chain from the Sun to Earth with COCONUT and Icarus. The coronal model has been upgraded to a full MHD model for a realistic bi-modal solar wind configuration. The approximated heating functions have modelled the wind reasonably well, but simple approximations are not enough to obtain a realistic density-speed balance or realistic features in the low corona and farther, near the outer boundary. The full MHD model was computed in 1.06 h on 180 cores of the Genius cluster of the Vlaams Supercomputing Center, which is only 1.8 times longer than the polytropic simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17903v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tinatin Baratashvili, Michaela Brchnelova, Luis Linan, Andrea Lani, Stefaan Poedts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduction of the downward energy flux of non-thermal electrons in the solar flare corona due to co-spatial return current losses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High energy electrons carry much of a solar flare's energy. Therefore, understanding changes in electron beam distributions during their propagation is crucial. A key focus of this paper is how the co-spatial return current reduces the energy flux carried by these accelerated electrons. We systematically compute this reduction for various beam and plasma parameters relevant to solar flares. Our 1D model accounts for collisions between beam and plasma electrons, return current electric-field deceleration, thermalization in a warm target approximation, and runaway electron contributions. The results focus on the classical (Spitzer) regime, offering a valuable benchmark for energy flux reduction and its extent. Return current losses are only negligible for the lowest nonthermal fluxes. We calculate the conditions for return current losses to become significant and estimate the extent of the modification to the beam's energy flux density. We also calculate two additional conditions which occur for higher injected fluxes: (1) where runaway electrons become significant, and (2) where current-driven instabilities might become significant, requiring a model that self-consistently accounts for them. Condition (2) is relaxed and the energy flux losses are reduced in the presence of runaway electrons. All results are dependent on beam and co-spatial plasma parameters. We also examine the importance of the reflection of beam electrons by the return-current electric field. We show that the interpretation of a number of flares needs to be reviewed to account for the effects of return currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17955v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meriem Alaoui, Gordon D. Holman, Marc Swisdak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-thermal radio emission in Sakurai's Object</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The very late thermal pulse (VLTP) affects the evolution of $\sim$20\% of 1--8\,$\mathrm M_\odot$ stars, repeating the last phases of the red giant within a few years and leading to the formation of a new, but hydrogen-poor nebula within the old planetary nebula (PN). The strong dust formation in the latter obscures the optical and near-infrared radiation of the star. We aimed to determine the reheating timescale of the central star in Sakurai's object, which is an important constraint for the poorly understood VLTP evolution. We observed the radio continuum emission of Sakurai's object for almost 20 years from 2004 to 2023. Continuous, multi-frequency observations proved to be essential to distinguish between phases dominated by photoionization and shock ionization. The flux density fluctuates by more than a factor 40 within months to years. The spectral index remained negative between 2006 and 2017 and is close to zero since 2019. The emission region is barely resolved since 2021. Non-thermal radio emission observed from 2004 to 2017 traces shocks induced by wind interactions due to discrete mass-loss events. Thermal emission dominates during the period 2019--2023 and may indicate photoionization of the nebula by the central star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18020v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcin Hajduk, Peter A. M. van Hoof, Albert A. Zijlstra, Griet Van de Steene, Stefan Kimeswenger, Daniela Barr\'ia, Daniel Tafoya, Jes\'us A. Toal\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Cluster Membership of Planetary Nebulae with High-Precision Proper Motions. I. HST Observations of JaFu 1 Near the Globular Cluster Palomar 6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If a planetary nebula (PN) is shown to be a member of a star cluster, we obtain important new constraints on the mass and chemical composition of the PN's progenitor star, which cannot be determined for PNe in the field. Cluster membership can be tested by requiring the projected separation between the PN and cluster to be within the tidal radius of the cluster, and the objects to have nearly identical radial velocities (RVs) and interstellar extinctions, and nearly identical proper motions (PMs). In an earlier study, we used PMs to confirm that three PNe, which had already passed the other tests, are highly likely to be members of Galactic globular clusters (GCs). For a fourth object, the PN JaFu 1, which lies in the Galactic bulge near the GC Palomar 6 on the sky and has a similar RV, the available PM measurement gave equivocal results. We have now obtained new high-resolution images of the central star of JaFu 1 with the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) which, combined with archival HST frames taken 14 and 16 years earlier, provide a high-precision PM. Unfortunately, we find that the PM of the central star differs from that of the cluster with high statistical significance, and thus is unlikely to be a member of Palomar 6. Nevertheless, JaFu 1 is of astrophysical interest because its nucleus appears to be a member of the rare class of "EGB 6-type" central stars, which are associated with compact emission-line knots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18135v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Howard E. Bond (Penn State, Space Telescope Science Institute), Andrea Bellini (Space Telescope Science Institute), Kailash C. Sahu (Space Telescope Science Institute, Eureka Scientific)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of reconnection flux during eruption of magnetic flux ropes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are powerful drivers of space weather, with magnetic flux ropes (MFRs) widely regarded as their primary precursors. However, the variation in reconnection flux during the evolution of MFR during CME eruptions remains poorly understood. In this paper, we develop a realistic 3D magneto-hydrodynamic model using which we explore the temporal evolution of reconnection flux during the MFR evolution using both numerical simulations and observational data. Our initial coronal configuration features an isothermal atmosphere and a potential arcade magnetic field beneath which an MFR emerges at the lower boundary. As the MFR rises, we observe significant stretching and compression of the overlying magnetic field beneath it. Magnetic reconnection begins with the gradual formation of a current sheet, eventually culminating with the impulsive expulsion of the flux rope. We analyze the temporal evolution of reconnection fluxes during two successive MFR eruptions while continuously emerging the twisted flux rope through the lower boundary. We also conduct a similar analysis using observational data from the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) and the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) for an eruptive event. Comparing our MHD simulation with observational data, we find that reconnection flux play a crucial role in determination of CME speeds. From the onset to the eruption, the reconnection flux shows a strong linear correlation with the velocity. This nearly realistic simulation of a solar eruption provides important insights into the complex dynamics of CME initiation and progression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18188v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samriddhi Sankar Maity, Piyali Chatterjee, Ranadeep Sarkar, Ijas S. Mytheen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subaru/CHARIS High-Resolution Mode Spectroscopy of the Brown Dwarf Companion HD 33632 Ab</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17531v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Brown dwarfs (BD) are model degenerate in age and mass. High-contrast imaging and spectroscopy of BD companions to host stars where the mass and age can be independently constrained by dynamics and stellar age indicators respectively provide valuable tests of BD evolution models. In this paper, we present a new epoch of Subaru/CHARIS H- and K-band observations of one such previously discovered system, HD 33632 Ab. We reanalyze the mass and orbit using our new epoch of extracted relative astrometry, and fit extracted spectra to the newest generation of equilibrium, disequilibrium, and cloudy spectral and evolution models for BDs. No spectral model perfectly agrees with evolutionary tracks and the derived mass and age, instead favoring a somewhat younger BD than the host star's inferred age. This tension can potentially be resolved using atmosphere and evolution models that consider both clouds and disequilibrium chemistry simultaneously, or by additional future spectra at higher resolution or in other band passes. Photometric measurements alone remain consistent with the luminosity predicted by evolutionary tracks. Our work highlights the importance of considering complexities like clouds, disequilibrium chemistry, and composition when comparing spectral models to evolutionary tracks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17531v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Gibbs, Briley Lewis, Michael Fitzgerald, Timothy Brandt, Minghan Chen, Yiting Li, Rachel Bowens-Rubin, Rebecca Jensen-Clem, Benjamin Mazin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of NH3 Binding Energy in the Early Evolution of Protostellar Cores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17891v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: NH$_{3}$(ammonia) plays a critical role in the chemistry of star and planet formation, yet uncertainties in its binding energy (BE) values complicate accurate estimates of its abundances. Recent research suggests a multi-binding energy approach, challenging the previous single-value notion. In this work, we use different values of NH$_{3}$ binding energy to examine its effects on the NH$_{3}$ abundances and, consequently, in the early evolution of protostellar cores. Using a gas-grain chemical network, we systematically vary the values of NH$_{3}$ binding energies in a model Class 0 protostellar core and study the effects of these binding energies on the NH$_{3}$ abundances. Our simulations indicate that abundance profiles of NH$_{3}$ are highly sensitive to the binding energy used, particularly in the warmer inner regions of the core. Higher binding energies lead to lower gas-phase NH$_{3}$ abundances, while lower values of binding energy have the opposite effect. Furthermore, this BE-dependent abundance variation of NH$_{3}$ significantly affects the formation pathways and abundances of key species such as HNC, HCN, and CN. Our tests also reveal that the size variation of the emitting region due to binding energy becomes discernible only with beam sizes of 10 arcsec or less. These findings underscore the importance of considering a range of binding energies in astrochemical models and highlight the need for higher resolution observations to better understand the subtleties of molecular cloud chemistry and star formation processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17891v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Kakkenpara Suresh, O. Sipila, P. Caselli, F. Dulieu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical simulations of exocomet transits: Insights from \{beta} Pic and KIC 3542116</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, the topic of existence and exploration of exocomets has been gaining increasing attention. The asymmetrical decrease in the stellar brightness due to the passage of a comet-like object in front of the star was successfully predicted. It was subsequently confirmed on the basis of the light curves of stars observed by Kepler and TESS orbital telescopes. Since then, there have been successful attempts to fit the asymmetrical dips observed in the stellar light curves utilizing a simple 1D model of an exponentially decaying optically thin dust tail. In this work, we propose fitting the photometric profiles of some known exocomet transits based on a Monte Carlo approach to build up the distribution of dust particles in a cometary tail. As the exocomet prototypes, we used the physical properties of certain Solar System comets belonging to the different dynamical groups and moving at heliocentric distances of 0.6 au, 1.0 au, 5.0 au, and 5.5 au. We obtained a good agreement between the observed and modeled transit light curves. We also show that the physical characteristics of dust particles, such as the particle size range, the power index of dust size distribution, the particle terminal velocity, and distance to the host star affect the shape of the transit light curve, while the dust productivity of the comet nucleus and the impact parameter influence its depth and duration. The estimated dust production rates of the transiting exocomets are at the level of the most active Solar System comets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17961v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Luk\'yanyk (AO of TSKU), I. Kulyk (MAO NAO of Ukraine), O. Shubina2 (IA, Slovac AS), Ya. Pavlenko (MAO, IAC), M. Vasylenko (MAO), D. Dobrycheva (MAO), P. Korsun (MAO)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon enrichment in APOGEE disk stars as evidence of mass transfer in binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18130v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Carbon abundances in first-ascent giant stars are usually lower than those of their main-sequence counterparts. At moderate metallicities, stellar evolution of single stars cannot account for the existence of red-giant branch stars with enhanced carbon abundances. The phenomenon is usually interpreted as resulting from past mass transfer from an evolved binary companion now in the white dwarf evolutionary stage. Aims: We aim to confirm the links between [C/O] enhancement, s-process element enhancement and binary fraction using large-scale catalogues of stellar abundances and probable binary stars. Methods: We use a large data set from the 17 data release of the SDSS-IV/APOGEE~2 survey to identify carbon-enhanced stars in the Galactic disk. We identify a continuum of carbon enrichment throughout three different sub-populations of disk stars and explore links between the degree of carbon enrichment and binary frequency, metallicity and chemical compositions. Results: We verify a clear correlation between binary frequency and enhancement in the abundances of both carbon and cerium, lending support to the scenario whereby carbon-enhanced stars are the result of mass transfer by an evolved binary companion. In addition, we identify clustering in the carbon abundances of high-$\alpha$ disk stars, suggesting that those on the high metallicity end are likely younger, in agreement with theoretical predictions for the presence of a starburst population following the gas-rich merger of the Gaia-Enceladus/Sausage system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18130v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve Foster, Ricardo P. Schiavon, Denise B. de Castro, Sara Lucatello, Christine Daher, Zephyr Penoyre, Adrian Price-Whelan, Carles Badenes, JJ. G. Fern\'andez-Trincado, D. A. Garc\'ia-Hern\'andez, Jon Holtzman, Henrik J\"onsson, Matthew Shetrone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polytropic Gas Effects in Parker's Solar Wind Model and Coronal Hole Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06122v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A detailed and systematic investigation of polytropic gas effects in Parker's solar wind model and coronal-hole flows is given. We present a viable equation governing the acceleration of solar wind of a polytropic gas and give its exact analytical and numerical solutions and deduce its asymptotic analytic properties (i) near the sun, (ii) far away from the sun, (iii) near the Parker sonic critical point (where the wind speed is equal to the speed of sound in the wind). We proceed to give a detailed and systematic investigation of coronal-hole polytropic gas outflows which contribute to bulk of the solar wind. We will model coronal-hole outflow by considering a single radial stream tube and use phenomenological considerations to represent its rapidly-diverging flow geometry. We give analytical and numerical solutions for this outflow and deduce its asymptotic analytic properties in the three flow regimes above. We find that, in general, the polytropic effects cause the Parker sonic critical point to move closer to the sun than that for the case with isothermal gas. Furthermore, the flow acceleration is found to exhibit (even for an infinitesimal deviation from isothermality of the gas) a power-law behavior rather than an exponential-law behavior near the sun or a logarithmic-law behavior far away from the sun, thus implying a certain robustness of the power-law behavior. The Parker sonic critical point is shown to continue to be of X-type, hence facilitating a smooth transition from subsonic to supersonic wind flow through the transonic regime. Our analytical and numerical solutions show that the super-radiality of the stream tube causes the Parker sonic critical point to move further down in the corona, and the gas to become more diabatic (the polytropic exponent gamma drops further below 5/3), and the flow acceleration to be enhanced further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06122v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. K. Shivamoggi, L. Pohl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MUSE spectroscopy of the high abundance discrepancy planetary nebula NGC 6153</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06385v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: (Abridged) The abundance discrepancy problem in planetary nebulae (PNe) has long puzzled astronomers. NGC6153, with its high Abundance Discrepancy Factor (ADF~10), provides an opportunity to understand the chemical structure and ionisation processes by constructing detailed emission line maps and examining variations in electron temperature and density. We used the MUSE spectrograph to acquire IFU data covering the wavelength range 4600-9300 \AA\ with a spatial sampling of 0.2 arcsec and spectral resolutions ranging from R = 1600-3500. We created emission line maps for 60 lines and two continuum regions. We developed a tailored methodology for the analysis of the data, including correction for recombination contributions to auroral lines and the contributions of different plasma phases. Our analysis confirmed the presence of a low-temperature plasma component in NGC6153. We find that electron temperatures derived from recombination line and continuum diagnostics are significantly lower than those derived from collisionally excited line diagnostics. Ionic chemical abundance maps were constructed, considering the weight of the cold plasma phase in the HI emission. Adopting this approach, we found ionic abundances that could be up to 0.2 dex lower for those derived from CELs and up to 1.1 dex higher for those derived from RLs than in the case of an homogeneous HI emission. The abundance contrast factor (ACF) between both plasma components was defined, with values, on average, 0.9 dex higher than the ADF. Different methods for calculating ionisation correction factors (ICFs) yielded consistent results. Our findings emphasise that accurate chemical abundance determinations in high-ADF PNe must account for multiple plasma phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06385v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. G\'omez-Llanos (IAC, Spain, ULL, Spain), J. Garc\'ia-Rojas (IAC, Spain, ULL, Spain), C. Morisset (IA-UNAM, Ensenada, Mexico, ICF-UNAM, Cuernavaca, Mexico), H. Monteiro (U. Itajub\'a, Brazil), D. Jones (IAC, Spain, ULL, Spain, NOT, Spain), R. Wesson (Cardiff Univ., UK), H. M. J. Boffin (ESO, Germany), R. L. M. Corradi (IAC, Spain, ULL, Spain, GTC, Spain)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of projection effects in the polar magnetic field measurements from the ecliptic view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The distribution and evolution of the magnetic field at the solar poles through a solar cycle is an important parameter in understanding the solar dynamo. The accurate observations of the polar magnetic flux is very challenging from the ecliptic view, mainly due to (a) geometric foreshortening which limits the spatial resolution, and (b) the oblique view of predominantly vertical magnetic flux elements, which presents rather small line-of-sight component of the magnetic field towards the ecliptic. Due to these effects the polar magnetic flux is poorly measured. Depending upon the measurement technique, longitudinal versus full vector field measurement, where the latter is extremely sensitive to the SNR achieved and azimuth disamiguation problem, the polar magnetic flux measurements could be underestimated or overestimated. To estimate the extent of systematic errors in magetic flux measurements at the solar poles due to aforementioned projection effects we use MHD simulations of quiet sun network as a reference solar atmosphere. Using the numerical model of the solar atmosphere we simulate the observations from the ecliptic as well as from out-of-ecliptic vantage points, such as from a solar polar orbit at various heliographic latitudes. Using these simulated observations we make an assessment of the systematic errors in our measurements of the magnetic flux due to projection effects and the extent of under- or over estimation. We suggest that such effects could contribute to reported missing open magnetic flux in the heliosphere and that the multi-viewpoint observations from out-of-the-ecliptic plane together with innovative Compact Doppler Magnetographs provide the best bet for the future measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09010v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Gosain, Han Uitenbroek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Method to Constrain Tidal Quality Factor from A Non-synchronized Exoplanetary System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07375v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel method to constrain the tidal quality factor, $Q'$, from an observed non-synchronized star-planet system consisting of a slowly rotating low-mass star and a close-in Jovian planet, taking into account the co-evolution of stellar spin and planetary orbit due to the tidal interaction and the magnetic braking. On the basis of dynamical system theory, the track of the co-evolution of angular momentum from the fast rotator regime for such a system exhibits the existence of a forbidden region in the $\Omega_\mathrm{orb}$ -- $\Omega_\mathrm{spin}$ plane , where $\Omega_\mathrm{spin}$ and $\Omega_\mathrm{orb}$ denote the angular velocity of the stellar spin and planetary orbit, respectively. The forbidden region is determined primarily by the strength of the tidal interaction. By comparing ($\Omega_\mathrm{orb},\Omega_\mathrm{spin}$) of a single star-planet system to the forbidden region, we can constrain the tidal quality factor regardless of the evolutionary history of the system. The application of this method to the star-planet system, NGTS-10 -- NGTS-10 b, gives $Q' \gtrsim 10^8$, leading to an tight upper bound on the tidal torque. Since this cannot be explained by previous theoretical predictions for non-synchronized star-planet systems, our result requires mechanisms that suppress the tidal interaction in such systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07375v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takato Tokuno, Akihiko Fukui, Takeru K. Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light Curve Classification with DistClassiPy: a new distance-based classifier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12120v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rise of synoptic sky surveys has ushered in an era of big data in time-domain astronomy, making data science and machine learning essential tools for studying celestial objects. While tree-based models (e.g. Random Forests) and deep learning models dominate the field, we explore the use of different distance metrics to aid in the classification of astrophysical objects. We developed DistClassiPy, a new distance metric based classifier. The direct use of distance metrics is unexplored in time-domain astronomy, but distance-based methods can help make classification more interpretable and decrease computational costs. In particular, we applied DistClassiPy to classify light curves of variable stars, comparing the distances between objects of different classes. Using 18 distance metrics on a catalog of 6,000 variable stars across 10 classes, we demonstrate classification and dimensionality reduction. Our classifier meets state-of-the-art performance but has lower computational requirements and improved interpretability. Additionally, DistClassiPy can be tailored to specific objects by identifying the most effective distance metric for that classification. To facilitate broader applications within and beyond astronomy, we have made DistClassiPy open-source and available at https://pypi.org/project/distclassipy/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12120v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ascom.2024.100850</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Chaini, Ashish Mahabal, Ajit Kembhavi, Federica B. Bianco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of stellar wind and supernovae on the star cluster formation: origins of extremely high N/O ratios and multiple stellar populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study metal enrichment originating from stellar wind and supernovae in low-metallicity clouds by performing three-dimensional radiation hydrodynamics simulations. We find that metals ejected from stellar wind are accumulated, leading to subsequent star formation in the nitrogen-enriched gas. During this early phase, the N/O ratios are similar to observed nitrogen-enriched galaxies (${\rm [N/O]}\gtrsim0.5$). Then, once supernovae occur, the N/O ratios decrease significantly. If the duration of star formation is comparable to the timescale of SNe, the mass fraction of nitrogen-enriched stars reaches half the mass of star clusters. We suggest that the mass of the star cluster needs to exceed $\sim 10^6~M_{\odot}$ to have multiple populations due to stellar wind, considering the condition for massive star cluster formation and the timescales of stellar evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10535v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Fukushima, Hidenobu Yajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inefficient star formation in high Mach number environments I. The turbulent support analytical model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17368v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The star formation rate (SFR), the number of stars formed per unit of time, is a fundamental quantity in the evolution of the Universe. While turbulence is believed to play a crucial role in setting the SFR, the exact mechanism remains unclear. Turbulence promotes star formation by compressing the gas, but also slows it down by stabilizing the gas against gravity. Most widely-used analytical models rely on questionable assumptions, including: $i)$ integrating over the density PDF, a one-point statistical description that ignores spatial correlation, $ii)$ selecting self-gravitating gas based on a density threshold that often ignores turbulent dispersion, $iii)$ assuming the freefall time as the timescale for estimating SFR without considering the need to rejuvenate the density PDF, $iv)$ assuming the density PDF to be lognormal. Improving upon the only existing model that incorporates the spatial correlation of the density field, we present a new analytical model. We calculate the time needed to rejuvenate density fluctuations of a given density and spatial scale, revealing that it is generally much longer than the freefall time, rendering the latter inappropriate for use. We make specific predictions regarding the role of the Mach number, $ M $, and the driving scale of turbulence divided by the mean Jeans length. At low to moderate Mach numbers, turbulence does not reduce and may even slightly promote star formation by broadening the PDF. However, at higher Mach numbers, most density fluctuations are stabilized by turbulent dispersion, leading to a steep drop in the SFR as the Mach number increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17368v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Hennebelle, No\'e Brucy, Tine Colman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inefficient star formation in high Mach number environments II. Numerical simulations and comparison with analytical models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17374v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Predicting the star formation rate (SFR) in galaxies is crucial to understand their evolution and morphology. To do so requires a fine understanding of how dense structures of gas are created and collapse. In that, turbulence and gravity play a major role. Within the gravo-turbulent framework, we assume that turbulence shapes the ISM, creating density fluctuations that, if gravitationally unstable, will collapse and form stars. The goal of this work is to quantify how different regimes of turbulence, characterized by the strength and compressibility of the driving, shape the density field. We are interested in the outcome in terms of SFR and how it compares with existing analytical models for the SFR. We run a series of hydrodynamical simulations of turbulent gas. The simulations are first conducted without gravity, so that the density and velocity are shaped by the turbulence driving. Gravity is then switched on, and the SFR is measured and compared with analytical models. The physics included in these simulations is very close to the one assumed in the classical gravo-turbulent SFR analytical models, which makes the comparison straightforward. We found that the existing analytical models convincingly agree with simulations at low Mach number, but we measure a much lower SFR in the simulation with a high Mach number. We develop, in a companion paper, an updated physically-motivated SFR model that reproduces well the inefficient high Mach regime of the simulations. Our work demonstrates that accurate estimations of the turbulent-driven replenishment time of dense structures and the dense gas spatial distribution are necessary to correctly predict the SFR in the high Mach regime. The inefficient high-Mach regime is a possible explanation for the low SFR found in dense and turbulent environments such as the centers of our Milky Way and other galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17374v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>No\'e Brucy, Patrick Hennebelle, Tine Colman, Ralf S. Klessen, Corentin Le Yhuelic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First detection of X-ray pulsations and spectrum of the high Galactic latitude pulsar PSR J0837-2454 and direct Urca cooling implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14952v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: PSR J0837-2454 is a young 629 ms radio pulsar whose uncertain distance has important implications. A large distance would place the pulsar far out of the Galactic plane and suggest it is the result of a runaway star, while a short distance would mean the pulsar is extraordinarily cold. Here we present further radio observations and the first deep X-ray observation of PSR J0837-2454. Data from the Parkes Murriyang telescope show flux variations over short and long timescales and also yield an updated timing model, while the position and proper motion (and, less strongly, parallax) of the pulsar are constrained by a number of low-significance detections with the Very Long Baseline Array. XMM-Newton data enable detection of X-ray pulsations for the first time from this pulsar and yield a spectrum that is thermal and blackbody-like, with a cool blackbody temperature ~70 eV or atmosphere temperature ~50 eV, as well as a small hotspot. The spectrum also indicates the pulsar is at a small distance of &lt;~1 kpc, which is compatible with the marginal VLBA parallax constraint that favours a distance of &gt;~330 pc. The low implied luminosity (~7.6x10^31 erg s^-1 at 0.9 kpc) suggests PSR J0837-2454 has a mass high enough that fast neutrino emission from direct Urca reactions operates in this young star and points to a nuclear equation of state that allows for direct Urca reactions at the highest densities present in neutron star cores.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14952v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wynn C. G. Ho (Haverford), Nihan Pol (Oregon State), Adam T. Deller (Swinburne), Werner Becker (MPE), Sarah Burke-Spolaor (West Virginia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violation of $\gamma$ in Brans-Dicke gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17771v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Brans Class I solution in Brans-Dicke gravity is a staple in the study of gravitational theories beyond General Relativity. Discovered in 1961, it describes the exterior vacuum of a spherical Brans-Dicke star and is characterized by two adjustable parameters. Surprisingly, the relationship between these parameters and the properties of the star has not been rigorously established. In this Proceeding, we bridge this gap by deriving $\textit{the}$ complete exterior solution of Brans Class I, expressed in terms of the total energy and total pressure of the spherisymmetric gravity source. The solution allows for the $\textit{exact}$ derivation of $\textit{all}$ post-Newtonian parameters in Brans-Dicke gravity for far field regions of a spherical source. Particularly for the $\gamma$ parameter, instead of the conventional result $\gamma_{\,\text{PPN}}=\frac{\omega+1}{\omega+2}$, we obtain the analytical expression $\gamma_{\,\text{exact}}=\frac{\omega+1+(\omega+2)\,\Theta}{\omega+2+(\omega+1)\,\Theta}$ where $\Theta$ is the ratio of the total pressure $P_{\parallel}^{*}+2P_{\perp}^{*}$ and total energy $E^{*}$ contained within the mass source. Our $\textit{non-perturbative}$ $\gamma$ formula is valid for all field strengths and types of matter comprising the mass source. Consequently, observational constraints on $\gamma$ thus set $\textit{joint}$ bounds on $\omega$ and $\varTheta$, with the latter representing a global characteristic of the mass source. More broadly, our formula highlights the importance of pressure (when $\varTheta\neq0$) in spherical Brans-Dicke stars, and potentially in stars within other modified theories of gravitation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17771v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ukr. J. Phys. 69, No. 7, 478 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Ky Nguyen, Bertrand Chauvineau</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
