<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 05:02:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Newborn Be star systems observed shortly after mass transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many classical Be stars acquire their very rapid rotation by mass and angular-momentum transfer in massive binaries. Short-lived intermediate-phase objects have only been discovered recently. Data archives and the literature have been searched for additional candidates exhibiting this patterns. Thirteen candidates were identified at various confidence levels. Adding to the two known systems identified as classical Be star+pre-subdwarf binaries (LB-1 and HR6819), two more (V742Cas, HD44637) could be confirmed with interferometry, with V742Cas setting a new record for the smallest visually observed angular semi-major axis, at a=0.663mas. Two further ones (V447Sct, V1362Cyg) are not resolved interferometrically, but other evidence puts them at the same confidence level as LB-1. V2174Cyg is a candidate with very high confidence, but was not observed interferometrically. The remaining ones are either candidates with varying levels of confidence. Of a mostly magnitude complete sample of 328 Be stars, 0.5-1% are found to have recently completed the mass overflow that led to their formation. Another 5% are systems with compact subdwarf companions, i.e., further evolved after a previous overflow, and possibly two more percent harbor white dwarfs. All these systems are of early B-subtypes, however, and if the original sample is restricted to early subtypes (136 objects), these percentages increase by a factor of about 2.5, while dropping to zero for the mid and late subtypes (together 204 objects). This strongly suggests that early- vs. mid- and late-type Be stars have differently weighted channels to acquire their rapid rotation, namely binary interaction vs. evolutionary spin-up.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09720v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th. Rivinius, R. Klement, S. D. Chojnowski, D. Baade, M. Abdul-Masih, N. Przybilla, J. Guarro Flo, B. Heathcote, P. Hadrava, D. Gies, K. Shepard, C. Buil, O. Garde, O. Thizy, J. D. Monnier, N. Anugu, C. Lanthermann, G. Schaefer, C. Davies, S. Kraus, J. Ennis, B. R. Setterholm, T. Gardner, N. Ibrahim, S. Chhabra, M. Gutierrez, I. Codron, D. Mortimer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 mm Spectroscopic Observations of Massive Star-Forming Regions with IRAM 30-m</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Broadband spectroscopic observations with high sensitivity provide an unbiased way to detect emissions of molecules in space. We present deep observations from ~ 105.8 GHz to 113.6 GHz toward 50 Galactic massive star-forming regions using IRAM 30-m millimeter telescope, with noise levels ranging from 6 to 29 at frequency channel spacing of 195 kHz, which corresponds to ~ 0.54 km/s at 110 GHz. Totally, 27 molecular species have been identified, of which 16 are complex organic molecules. The related parameters, such as peak temperature, integrated intensity, and line width of the identified molecular lines were obtained. The line widths of the chemically related molecules show strong positive correlations, suggesting they likely originate from similar gases within star-forming regions. This work highlights the fundamental properties of the detected molecular lines and offers a valuable dataset for further studies on the astrochemical evolution of molecules in massive star-forming cores.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09823v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuefang Xu, Junzhi Wang, Qian Gou, Juan Li, Donghui Quan, Di Li, Fei Li, Chunguo Duan, Juncheng Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for Systematic Planetary Nebulae Detection with the Census of the Local Universe Narrowband Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the efficacy of a systematic planetary nebula (PN) search in the Census of the Local Universe (CLU) narrowband (H$\alpha$) survey that covers a considerably larger sky region of above declination $-20^\circ$ than most previous surveys. Using PNe observed by the Isaac Newton Telescope Photometric H$\alpha$ Survey (IPHAS) as validation, we are able to visually recover 432 out of 441 cataloged PNe (98\%) within the CLU dataset, with 5 sources having unusable CLU images and 4 missed due to limitations of imaging quality. Moreover, the reference PNe are conventionally divided into three PN classes in decreasing order of identification confidence given their spectra and morphologies. We record consistently high recovery rate across all classes: 95\% of True, 71\% of Likely, and 81\% of Possible sources are readily recovered. To further demonstrate the ability of CLU to find new PNe, we undertake a preliminary search of compact PNe within a sub-region of the validation catalog, mainly utilizing the significance of narrow-band colors ($\Sigma$) as a metric for identification. In a $200\,\rm deg^2$ region, we search the CLU source catalog and find 31 PN candidates after automated and visual scrutiny, of which 12 are new sources not appearing in previous studies. As a demonstration of our ongoing follow-up campaign, we present medium-resolution optical spectra of six candidates and notice that four of them show emission signatures characteristic of confirmed PNe. As we refine our selection methods, CLU promises to provide a systematic catalog of PNe spanning $2/3$ of the sky.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09836v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rong Du (Peking University, Caltech), David O. Cook (Caltech), Soumyadeep Bhattacharjee (Caltech), Shrinivas R. Kulkarni (Caltech), Christoffer Fremling, David L. Kaplan, Mansi M. Kasliwal, Russ R. Laher, Frank J. Masci, David L. Shupe, Chaoran Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass-transferring binary stars as progenitors of interacting hydrogen-free supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09893v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stripped-envelope supernovae (SNe) are H-poor transients produced at the end of the life of massive stars that previously lost their H-rich envelope. Their progenitors are thought to be donor stars in mass-transferring binary systems, which were stripped of their H-rich envelopes some $10^6$yr before core collapse. A subset of the stripped-envelope SNe exhibit spectral and photometric features indicative of interaction between their ejecta and nearby circumstellar material (CSM). We examine whether mass transfer during, or shortly before, core collapse in massive binary systems can produce the CSM inferred from the observations of interacting H-poor SNe. We select 44 models from a comprehensive grid of detailed binary evolution models in which the mass donors are H-free and explode while transferring mass to a main-sequence companion. We find that in these models, mass transfer starts less than $\sim20$kyr before, and often continues until the core collapse of the donor star. Up to $0.8M_\odot$ of H-free material are removed from the donor star during this phase, which may produce a He-rich circumbinary material. We explore plausible assumptions for its spatial distribution at the time of explosion. When assuming that the CSM accumulates in a circumbinary disk, we find qualitative agreement with the supernova and CSM properties inferred from observed Type Ibn SNe, and to a lesser extent with constraints from Type Icn SNe. We find that our mass transferring stripped envelope SN progenitor models may produce up to $\sim$10% of all stripped envelope supernovae. The binary channel proposed in this work can qualitatively account for the observed key properties and rate of interacting H-poor SNe. Models for the evolution of the circumbinary material and the spectral evolution of exploding progenitors from this channel are needed to further test its significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09893v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Ercolino, Harim Jin, Norbert Langer, Luc Dessart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Geometry of the Near-Core Magnetic Field in Massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well-known that the cores of massive stars sustain a stellar dynamo with a complex magnetic field configuration. However, the same cannot be said for the field's strength and geometry at the convective-radiative boundary, which are crucial when performing asteroseismic inference. In this Letter, we present three-dimensional (3D) magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations of a 7 solar mass mid-main sequence star, with particular attention given to the convective-radiative boundary in the near-core region. Our simulations reveal that the toroidal magnetic field is significantly stronger than the poloidal field in this region, contrary to recent assumptions. Moreover, the rotational shear layer, also important for asteroseismic inference, is specifically confined within the extent of the buoyancy frequency peak. These results, which are based on the inferred properties of HD 43317, have widespread implications for asteroseismic studies of rotation, mixing and magnetism in stars. While we expect our results to be broadly applicable across stars with similar buoyancy frequency profiles and stellar masses, we also expect the MHD parameters and the initial stellar rotation rate to impact the geometry of the field and differential rotation at the convective-radiative interface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09986v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad95f8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rathish P. Ratnasingam, Philipp V. F. Edelmann, Dominic M. Bowman, Tamara M. Rogers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PAStar: a model for stellar surface from the Sun to active stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. The characterization of exoplanets requires a good description of the host star. Stellar activity acts as a source of noise which can alter planet radii as derived from the transit depth or atmospheric characterization. Aims. Here, we propose PAStar, a model to describe photospheric activity in the form of spots and faculae which could be applied to a wide range of stellar observations, from photometric to spectroscopic time series, to be able to correctly extract planetary and stellar properties. Methods. The adopted stellar atmosphere is a combination of three components, the quiet photosphere, spots and faculae. The model takes into account the effects of star inclination, doppler shifts due to stellar rotation as well as for limb darkening, independent for each component. Several synthetic products have been presented to show the capabilities of the model. Results. The model is able to retrieve the input surface inhomogeneities configuration through photometric or spectroscopic observations. The model has been validated against optical solar data and compared to alternative stellar surface activity models; e.g. SOAP code. The Sun is a unique laboratory to test stellar models because of the possibility to relate unambiguously flux variations to surface inhomogeneities configuration. This validation has been done by analyzing a photometric time series from the VIRGO photometer on board of SOHO mission. Results have been compared to real solar images from the HMI instrument on board of SDO to confirm the goodness of the results in terms of surface inhomogeneities position and dimensions. Conclusions. The description of stellar activity is a fundamental step in several astrophysical contexts and it is covered by the method we have presented. Our model offers a flexible and valuable tool to describe the activity of stars when it is dominated by spots and faculae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10035v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonino Petralia, Jes\'us Maldonado, Giuseppina Micela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De-Biasing Structure Function Estimates From Sparse Time Series of the Solar Wind: A Data-Driven Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structure functions, which represent the moments of the increments of a stochastic process, are essential complementary statistics to power spectra for analysing the self-similar behaviour of a time series. However, many real-world environmental datasets, such as those collected by spacecraft monitoring the solar wind, contain gaps, which inevitably corrupt the statistics. The nature of this corruption for structure functions remains poorly understood - indeed, often overlooked. Here we simulate gaps in a large set of magnetic field intervals from Parker Solar Probe in order to characterize the behaviour of the structure function of a sparse time series of solar wind turbulence. We quantify the resultant error with regards to the overall shape of the structure function, and its slope in the inertial range. Noting the consistent underestimation of the true curve when using linear interpolation, we demonstrate the ability of an empirical correction factor to de-bias these estimates. This correction, "learnt" from the data from a single spacecraft, is shown to generalize well to data from a solar wind regime elsewhere in the heliosphere, producing smaller errors, on average, for missing fractions &gt;25%. Given this success, we apply the correction to gap-affected Voyager intervals from the inner heliosheath and local interstellar medium, obtaining spectral indices similar to those from previous studies. This work provides a tool for future studies of fragmented solar wind time series, such as those from Voyager, MAVEN, and OMNI, as well as sparsely-sampled astrophysical and geophysical processes more generally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10053v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Wrench, Tulasi N. Parashar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flaring together: A preferred angular separation between sympathetic flares on the Sun</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sympathetic solar flares are eruptions that occur nearby in space and time, driven by an apparent interaction between the active regions in which they are triggered. Their statistical existence on the Sun has yet to be firmly established. The main goal of this paper is to identify a statistical signature of sympathetic flares, characterize their properties and determine a potential mechanism driving their interaction. We perform a statistical analysis of a large number of flares observed by the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) onboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO), the Reuven Ramaty High Energy Solar Spectroscopic Imager (RHESSI) and the Spectrometer Telescope for Imaging X-rays (STIX) on Solar Orbiter during solar cycle 24 and 25. We examine the spatiotemporal distribution of consecutive flare pairs across solar cycle phases and hemispheres, along with the propagation velocity of potential causal interactions and the relationship between flare magnitudes. We observe an excess of hemispheric flares separated by about 30 degrees of longitude and triggered in less than 1.5 hours from each other. This peak in angular separation varies with the solar cycle phase and hemisphere. Moreover, we identify a deficit of transequatorial events separated by 25-30 degrees in latitude and less than 5 degrees in longitude, a phenomenon we term unsympathetic flares. We provide strong statistical evidence for the existence of sympathetic flares on the Sun, demonstrating that their occurrence rate reaches approximately 5% across the three instruments used in this study. Additionally, we propose an interpretation of the observed angular scale of the sympathetic phenomenon, based on the separation between magnetic field line footpoints derived from potential field source surface extrapolations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10143v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis-Simon Guit\'e, Antoine Strugarek, Paul Charbonneau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Old Dogs, New Tricks: Re-examining Photographic Spectra of Plaskett's Star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photographic spectra of Plaskett's Star (PS; HR2420, HD47129, V640 Mon) that were recorded at the Dominion Astrophysical Observatory (DAO) have been digitized with a flatbed scanner. Many of the spectra were recorded during campaigns in 1922 and 1937, and sample wavelengths between 0.39 and 0.50um. Spectra of poor quality are identified. Mean spectra near orbital phases 0.25 and 0.75 match many characteristics of synthetic spectra, although Hgamma and HeI 4388 are exceptions. Evidence is presented that Hgamma was affected by transient activity in 1937, but not in 1922. Emission lines of NIII and HeII move with wavelength in a manner that is consistent with them tracking the motion of the secondary, indicating that an 'f' spectral type designation should be assigned to the secondary. The location of the peak that is associated with the secondary in cross-correlation functions changes with time near phase 0.75, although the mean amplitude of the radial velocity curve of the secondary did not change between the two campaigns. There is also an offset in velocities of the primary measured from Hgamma and HeI 4472 near phase 0.25. The velocity curves of the components suggest a mass ratio that is larger than previous estimates, although uncertainties associated with the spectroscopic features attributed to the secondary, coupled with the wavelength resolution of the spectra, complicate efforts to determine robust masses. We conclude that peculiarities in the radial velocity curves of the components have thus been in place for over a thousand orbital cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10355v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. J. Davidge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protoplanetary discs around sun-like stars appear to live longer when the metallicity is low</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Previous Hubble Space Telescope (HST) observations of the star-forming cluster NGC 346 in the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC) had revealed a large population of pre-main sequence (PMS) candidates, characterised by Halpha excess emission in their photometry. However, without access to spectroscopy, the nature of these objects remained unclear. Using the NIRSpec instrument on board JWST, we studied a sample of these stars, with masses in the range ~0.9-1.8 Msun, effective temperatures in the range 4,500-8,000 K, and PMS ages between ~0.1 and 30 Myr. Here we present the first spectra of solar-mass PMS stars in the metal-poor SMC (Z=1/8 Zsun) and discuss the physical properties of ten representative sources with good signal-to-noise ratio. The observations indicate that even the oldest of these PMS candidates are still accreting gas with typical rates of ~10^{-8} Msun/yr for stars older than ~10 Myr, confirming their PMS nature. The spectra also reveal near-infrared excess and molecular hydrogen excitation lines consistent with the presence of discs around these stars. These findings suggest that in a low-metallicity environment circumstellar discs can live longer than previously thought.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10361v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad7a63</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ, 977 (2024) 214</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guido De Marchi, Giovanna Giardino, Katia Piazzo, Nino Panagia, Elena Sabbi, Tracy L. Beck, Massimo Robberto, Peter Zeidler, Olivia C. Jones, Margaret Meixner, Katja Fahrion, Nolan Habel, Conor Nally, Alec S. Hirschauer, David R. Soderblom, Omnarayani Nayak, Laura Lenkic, Ciaran Rogers, Bernhard Brandl, Charles D. Keyes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OGLE-2015-BLG-1609Lb: Sub-jovian planet orbiting a low-mass stellar or brown dwarf host</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09676v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive analysis of a planetary microlensing event OGLE-2015-BLG-1609. The planetary anomaly was detected by two survey telescopes, OGLE and MOA. Each of these surveys collected enough data over the planetary anomaly to allow for an unambiguous planet detection. Such survey detections of planetary anomalies are needed to build a robust sample of planets that could improve studies on the microlensing planetary occurrence rate by reducing biases and statistical uncertainties. In this work, we examined different methods for modeling microlensing events using individual datasets, particularly we incorporated a Galactic model prior to better constrain poorly defined microlensing parallax. Ultimately, we fitted a comprehensive model to all available data, identifying three potential typologies, with two showing comparably high Bayesian evidence. Our analysis indicates that the host of the planet is a brown dwarf with a probability of 34%, or a low-mass stellar object (M-dwarf) with the probability of 66%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09676v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Mr\'oz (OGLE Collaboration), R. Poleski (OGLE Collaboration), A. Udalski (OGLE Collaboration), T. Sumi (OGLE Collaboration), Y. Tsapras (OGLE Collaboration), M. Hundertmark (OGLE Collaboration), P. Pietrukowicz (OGLE Collaboration), M. K. Szyma\'nski (OGLE Collaboration), J. Skowron (OGLE Collaboration), P. Mr\'oz (OGLE Collaboration), M. Gromadzki (OGLE Collaboration), P. Iwanek (OGLE Collaboration), S. Koz{\l}owski (OGLE Collaboration), M. Ratajczak (OGLE Collaboration), K. A. Rybicki (OGLE Collaboration), D. M. Skowron (OGLE Collaboration), I. Soszy\'nski (OGLE Collaboration), K. Ulaczyk (OGLE Collaboration), M. Wrona (OGLE Collaboration), F. Abe (MOA Collaboration), K. Bando (MOA Collaboration), D. P. Bennett (MOA Collaboration), A. Bhattacharya (MOA Collaboration), I. A. Bond (MOA Collaboration), A. Fukui (MOA Collaboration), R. Hamada (MOA Collaboration), S. Hamada (MOA Collaboration), N. Hamasaki (MOA Collaboration), Y. Hirao (MOA Collaboration), S. Ishitani Silva (MOA Collaboration), Y. Itow (MOA Collaboration), N. Koshimoto (MOA Collaboration), Y. Matsubara (MOA Collaboration), S. Miyazaki (MOA Collaboration), Y. Muraki (MOA Collaboration), T. Nagai (MOA Collaboration), K. Nunota (MOA Collaboration), G. Olmschenk (MOA Collaboration), C. Ranc (MOA Collaboration), N. J. Rattenbury (MOA Collaboration), Y. Satoh (MOA Collaboration), D. Suzuki (MOA Collaboration), S. K. Terry (MOA Collaboration), P. J. Tristram (MOA Collaboration), A. Vandorou (MOA Collaboration), H. Yama (MOA Collaboration), R. A. Street (RoboNet Collaboration), E. Bachelet (RoboNet Collaboration), M. Dominik (RoboNet Collaboration), A. Cassan (RoboNet Collaboration), R. Figuera Jaimes (RoboNet Collaboration), K. Horne (RoboNet Collaboration), R. Schmidt (RoboNet Collaboration), C. Snodgrass (RoboNet Collaboration), J. Wambsganss (RoboNet Collaboration), I. A. Steele (RoboNet Collaboration), J. Menzies (RoboNet Collaboration), U. G. J{\o}rgensen (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), P. Longa-Pe\~na (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), N. Peixinho (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), J. Skottfelt (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), J. Southworth (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), M. I. Andersen (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), V. Bozza (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), M. J. Burgdorf (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), G. D'Ago (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), T. C. Hinse (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), E. Kerins (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), H. Korhonen (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), M. K\"uffmeier (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), L. Mancini (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), M. Rabus (MiNDSTEp Collaboration), S. Rahvar (MiNDSTEp Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>oMEGACat V: Helium Enrichment in $\omega$ Centauri as a Function of Metallicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Constraining the helium enhancement in stars is critical for understanding the formation mechanisms of multiple populations in star clusters. However, measuring helium variations for many stars within a cluster remains observationally challenging. We use Hubble Space Telescope photometry combined with MUSE spectroscopic data for over 7,200 red-giant branch stars in \omc\ to measure helium differences between distinct groups of stars as a function of metallicity separating the impact of helium enhancements from other abundance variations on the pseudo-color (chromosome) diagrams. Our results show that stars at all metallicities have subpopulations with significant helium enhancement ($\Delta Y_{min} \gtrsim$ 0.11). We find a rapid increase in helium enhancement from low metallicities ($\rm{[Fe/H] \simeq -2.05}$ to $\rm{[Fe/H] \simeq -1.92})$, with this enhancement leveling out at \deltay\ $= 0.154$ at higher metallicities. The fraction of helium-enhanced stars steadily increases with metallicity ranging from 10\% at $\rm{[Fe/H] \simeq -2.04}$ to over $90\%$ at $\rm{[Fe/H] \simeq -1.04}$. This study is the first to examine helium enhancement across the full range of metallicities in \omc{}, providing new insight into its formation history and additional constraints on enrichment mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09783v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Clontz, A. C. Seth, Z. Wang, S. O. Souza, M. H\"aberle, M. S. Nitschai, N. Neumayer, M. Latour, A. P. Milone, A. Feldmeier-Krause, N. Kacharov, M. Libralato, A. Bellini, G. van de Ven, M. Alfaro-Cuello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional tearing instability of flux-tube-like magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10065v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection, a fundamental plasma process, is pivotal in understanding energy conversion and particle acceleration in astrophysical systems. While extensively studied in two-dimensional (2D) configurations, the dynamics of reconnection in three-dimensional (3D) systems remain under-explored. In this work, we extend the classical tearing mode instability to 3D by introducing a modulation along the otherwise uniform direction in a 2D equilibrium, given by $g(y)$, mimicking a flux tube-like configuration. We perform linear stability analysis (both analytically and numerically) and direct numerical simulations to investigate the effects of three-dimensionality. Our findings reveal that the 3D tearing instability exhibits reduced growth rates compared to 2D by a factor of $\int g(y)^{1/2} dy~/\int dy$, with the dispersion relation maintaining similar scaling characteristics. We show that the modulation introduces spatially varying resistive layer properties, which influence the reconnection dynamics. Remarkably, we find that Sweet-Parker scaling for the reconnection rate persists even in the absence of a guide field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10065v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Kumar, Pallavi Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D projection analysis: characterizing the morphological stability of nearby open clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Context. The study of open cluster morphology is pivotal for exploring their formation and evolutionary processes. Aims. We manage to assess the morphological stability of 105 nearby open clusters within tidal radii on the X-Y, X-Z, and Y-Z planes of the heliocentric Cartesian coordinate system, utilizing member catalogs from the literature. Meanwhile, we also delve into factors potentially impacting the clusters' morphological stability on these projection planes. Methods. We used the rose diagram method by constructing the 3D projected morphology of sample clusters to quantify the morphological stability of their 3D projected morphology. Results. Our analysis indicates there is a demonstrated linear positive correlation between the number of sample clusters' member stars within tidal radii and their morphological stability in different 3D projection planes. This may suggest that the more member stars there are within the tidal radius of a cluster, the stronger its own gravitational binding capacity is, resulting in strong morphological stability. We find a direct link between the clusters' morphological stabilities in the X-Z plane within tidal radii and their velocity dispersion in the same plane, suggesting that the morphological stabilities in the X-Z plane may be dependent on internal dynamics. Moreover, the morphological stability of the clusters' 3D projection is influenced by their spatial positions along the Y axis, but not linearly, indicating that the environmental changes at the clusters' location may affect their morphological stability. Likewise, specific external forces can have an effect on their morphological stability. Conclusions. This research introduces a novel perspective for understanding the morphological stability of open clusters, with a particular focus on their 3D projected morphologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10158v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingshun Hu, Songmei Qin, Yangping Luo, Yuting Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering Pulsar Braking Index from a Population of Millisecond Pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10169v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The braking index, $n$, of a pulsar is a measure of its angular momentum loss and the value it takes corresponds to different spin-down mechanisms. For a pulsar spinning down due to gravitational wave emission from the principal mass quadrupole mode alone, the braking index would equal exactly 5. Unfortunately, for millisecond pulsars, it can be hard to measure observationally due to the extremely small second time derivative of the rotation frequency, $\ddot{f}$. This paper aims to examine whether it could be possible to extract the distribution of $n$ for a whole population of pulsars rather than measuring the values individually. We use simulated data with an injected $n=5$ signal for 47 millisecond pulsars and extract the distribution using hierarchical Bayesian inference methods. We find that while possible, observation times of over 20 years and RMS noise of the order of $10^{-5}$ ms are needed, which can be compared to the mean noise value of $3\times10^{-4}$ ms for the recent wideband 12.5-year NANOGrav sample, which provided the pulsar timing data used in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10169v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. L. Hewitt, M. Pitkin, I. M. Hook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commissioning of the MIRAC-5 Mid-Infrared Instrument on the MMT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10189v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present results from commissioning observations of the mid-IR instrument, MIRAC-5, on the 6.5-m MMT telescope. MIRAC-5 is a novel ground-based instrument that utilizes a state-of-the-art GeoSnap (2 - 13 microns) HgCdTe detector with adaptive optics support from MAPS to study protoplanetary disks, wide-orbit brown dwarfs, planetary companions in the contrast-limit, and a wide range of other astrophysical objects. We have used MIRAC-5 on six engineering observing runs, improving its performance and defining operating procedures. We characterize key aspects of MIRAC-5's performance, including verification that the total telescope, atmosphere, instrument, and detector throughput is approximately 10%. Following a planned dichroic upgrade, the system will have a throughput of 20% and background limiting magnitudes (for SNR = 5 and 8 hour exposure times) of 18.0, 15.6, and 12.6 for the L', M', and N' filters, respectively. The detector pixels experience 1/f noise but, if the astrophysical scene is properly modulated via chopping and nodding sequences, it is less than 10% the Poisson noise from the observed background in an 85 Hz frame. We achieve close to diffraction-limited performance in the N-band and all bands are expected to reach diffraction-limited performance following the adaptive optics system commissioning. We also present an exposure time calculator calibrated to the on-sky results. In its current state, MIRAC-5 will be capable of achieving several scientific objectives including the observation of warm wide-orbit companions. Once the adaptive optics is commissioned and a coronagraph installed in 2025, MIRAC-5 will have contrast-limited performance comparable to JWST, opening new and complementary science investigations for close-in companions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10189v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rory Bowens, Jarron Leisenring, Michael R. Meyer, Taylor L. Tobin, Alyssa L. Miller, John D. Monnier, Eric Viges, Bill Hoffmann, Manny Montoya, Olivier Durney, Grant West, Katie Morzinski, William Forrest, Craig McMurtry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equation of State Independent Determination on the Radius of a 1.4 $M_{\odot}$ Neutron Star Using Mass-Radius Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional methods for determining the radius of a 1.4 $M_{\odot}$ neutron star ($R_{1.4}$) rely on specific equations of state (EOS) models that describe various types of dense nuclear matter. This dependence on EOS models can introduce substantial systematic uncertainties, which may exceed the measurement uncertainties when constraining $R_{1.4}$. In this study, we explore a novel approach to constraining $R_{1.4}$ using data from NICER observations of PSR J0030+0451 (J0030) and PSR J0437-4715 (J0437). However, this work presents a more data-driven analysis framework, substantially decreasing the need for EOS assumptions. By analyzing the Mass-Radius measurements of these two neutron stars, we infer $R_{1.4}$ using statistical methods based mostly on observational data. We examine various hotspot configurations for J0030, along with new J0437 observations, and their effects on the inferred radius. Our results are consistent with X-ray timing, gravitational wave, and nuclear physics constraints, while avoiding EOS-related biases. The same method has also been applied to a simulated mass-radius dataset, based on our knowledge of future X-ray telescopes, demonstrating the model's ability to recover the injected $R_{1.4}$ value in certain cases. This method provides a data-driven pathway for extracting neutron star properties and offers a new approach for future observational efforts in neutron star astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10242v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A search for self-lensing binaries with TESS and constraints on their occurrence rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13939v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Five self-lensing binaries (SLBs) have been discovered with Kepler light curves. They contain white dwarfs (WDs) in AU-scale orbits that gravitationally lens solar-type companions. Forming SLBs likely requires common envelope evolution when the WD progenitor is an AGB star and has a weakly bound envelope. No SLBs have yet been discovered with data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), which observes far more stars than Kepler did. Identifying self-lensing in TESS data is made challenging by the fact that TESS only observes most stars for $\sim$25 days at a time, so only a single lensing event will be observed for typical SLBs. TESS's smaller aperture also makes it sensitive only to SLBs a factor of $\sim$100 brighter than those to which Kepler is sensitive. We demonstrate that TESS has nevertheless likely already observed $\sim$4 times more detectable SLBs than Kepler. We describe a search for non-repeating self-lensing signals in TESS light curves and present preliminary candidates for which spectroscopic follow-up is ongoing. We calculate the sensitivity of our search with injection and recovery tests on TESS and Kepler light curves. Based on the 5 SLBs discovered with Kepler light curves, we estimate that $(1.1 \pm 0.6)\%$ of solar-type stars are orbited by WDs with periods of 100-1000 d. This implies a space density of AU-scale WD + main sequence (MS) binaries a factor of 20-100 larger than that of astrometrically-identified WD + MS binaries with orbits in Gaia DR3. We conclude that the Gaia sample is still quite incomplete, mainly because WD + MS binaries can only be unambiguously identified as such for high mass ratios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13939v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natsuko Yamaguchi, Kareem El-Badry, Nicholas M. Sorabella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbit determination of visual binary systems observed with CST telescope in 2010-2013</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08333v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present new orbital solutions for 15 binaries, which were astrometrically measured during 2010-2013. We observe the binary systems using the FastCam ``lucky-imaging'' camera, installed at the 1.5-m Carlos S\'anchez Telescope (CST) at the Observatorio del Teide, Tenerife (Spain). We present first orbital solutions for four binaries and revise orbits for other 11 systems. We apply two orbital calculation techniques, the ``three-dimensional grid search method'' and the Docobo's analytical method. In addition, we use our tool ``Binary Deblending'', which is based on deblending the entire observed multiband photometry into fundamental and photometric parameters for each stellar component based on PARSEC isochrones. This method allows us to obtain the total mass for all systems. Our findings include the identification of a binary system consisting of two M-type dwarfs (WOR 19), a binary of evolved components (twin F6IV-V stars) in BU 1292, accompanied by a newly discovered wide (10.5 arcsec) and faint companion with G=17.05 mag. Additionally, we explore the X-ray emission system STF 147 and a very young quadruple system, WDS 04573+5345. This comprehensive analysis significantly contributes to our understanding on the formation and evolution of these stellar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08333v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. M. Rica, R. Barrena, J. A. Henr\'iquez, G. V\'azquez, C. V\'azquez, D. Hern\'andez, J. L. del Rosario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A BCool survey of stellar magnetic cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09365v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magnetic cycle on the Sun consists of two consecutive 11-yr sunspot cycles and exhibits a polarity reversal around sunspot maximum. Although solar dynamo theories have progressively become more sophisticated, the details as to how the dynamo sustains magnetic fields are still subject of research. Observing the magnetic fields of Sun-like stars are useful to contextualise the solar dynamo. The BCool survey studies the evolution of surface magnetic fields to understand how dynamo-generated processes are influenced by key ingredients, like mass and rotation. Here, we focus on six Sun-like stars with mass between 1.02 and 1.06 MSun and with 3.5-21 d rotation period. We analysed high-resolution spectropolarimetric data collected with ESPaDOnS, Narval and Neo-Narval. We measured the longitudinal magnetic field from least-squares deconvolution line profiles and inspected its long-term behaviour with a Lomb-Scargle periodogram and a Gaussian process. We applied Zeeman-Doppler imaging to reconstruct the large-scale magnetic field geometry at the stellar surface for different epochs. Two stars, namely HD 9986 and HD 56124 (Prot ~ 20 d) exhibit repeating polarity reversals of the radial or toroidal field component on time scales of 5 to 6 yr. HD 73350 (Prot = 12 d) has one polarity reversal of the toroidal component and HD 76151 (Prot=17 d) may have short-term evolution (2.5 yr) modulated by the long-term (16 yr) chromospheric cycle. HD 166435 and HD 175726 (Prot =3-5 d), manifest complex magnetic fields without cyclic evolution. Our findings indicate the potential dependence of the magnetic cycles nature with stellar rotation period. For the two stars with likely cycles, the polarity reversal time scale seems to decrease with decreasing rotation period or Rossby number. These results represent important observational constraints for dynamo models of solar-like stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09365v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bellotti, P. Petit, S. V. Jeffers, S. C. Marsden, J. Morin, A. A. Vidotto, C. P. Folsom, V. See, J. -D. do Nascimento Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring faint white dwarfs and the luminosity function with Subaru HSC and SDSS in Stripe 82</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17677v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present 5,080 white dwarf (WD) candidates selected from stars matching between the multi-band imaging datasets of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) Survey and the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) in the Stripe82 region covering about 165~deg$^2$. We select WD candidates from the ``reduced proper motion'' diagram by combining the apparent magnitude in the range $i=19$ -- 24 and the proper motion measured from the datasets among a baseline of $\sim$ 14~years. We refine the WD candidates by fitting blackbody and template WD atmosphere models to HSC photometries for each candidate, enabling the estimation of distance and tangential velocity ($v_{\rm t}$). The deep HSC data allow us to identify low-temperature ($&lt;4000$~K) and faint WD candidates down to absolute magnitude, $M_{\rm bol}\simeq 17$. We evaluate the selection function of our WD candidates using a mock catalogue of spatial and kinematic distributions of WDs in the (thin and thick) disc and halo regions based on a Galactic model. We construct samples of disc and halo WD candidates by selecting WDs with tangential velocity, $40&lt;v_{\rm t}/[{\rm km}~{\rm s}^{-1}]&lt;80$ and $200&lt;v_{\rm t}/[{\rm km}~{\rm s}^{-1}]&lt;500$, respectively. The total number densities of the disc and halo WDs are $(9.33 \pm 0.89) \times 10^{-3}$~pc$^{-3}$ and $(6.34 \pm 2.90) \times 10^{-4}$~pc$^{-3}$. Our luminosity functions (LF) extend down to fainter absolute magnitudes compared with previous work. The faint WDs could represent the oldest generation of building blocks over the past $\sim$10 billion years of the assembly history of our Milky Way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17677v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2355</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS 535, 3611-3629 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tian Qiu, Masahiro Takada, Naoki Yasuda, Akira Tokiwa, Kazumi Kashiyama, Yoshihisa Suzuki, Kenta Hotokezaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of non-Solar elemental composition in the clocked X-ray burster SRGA J144459.2$-$604207</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10993v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In February and March 2024, a series of many Type I X-ray bursts from the accreting neutron star SRGA J144459.2$-$604207, which has been identified by multiple X-ray satellites, with the first reports coming from INTEGRAL and NinjaSat. These observations reveal that after exhibiting very regular behavior as a ``clocked'' burster, the peak luminosity of the SRGA J144459.2$-$604207 X-ray bursts shows a gradual decline. The observed light curves exhibit a short plateau feature, potentially with a double peak, followed by a rapid decay in the tail-features unlike those seen in previously observed clocked bursters. In this study, we calculate a series of multizone X-ray burst models with various compositions of accreted matter, specifically varying the mass fractions of hydrogen ($X$), helium ($Y$), and heavier CNO elements or metallicity ($Z_{\rm CNO}$). We demonstrate that a model with higher $Z_{\rm CNO}$ and/or lower $X/Y$ compared to the solar values can reproduce the observed behavior of SRGA J144459.2$-$604207. Therefore, we propose that this new X-ray burster is likely the first clocked burster with non-solar elemental compositions. Moreover, based on the X-ray burst light curve morphology in the decline phase observed by NinjaSat, a He-enhanced model with $X/Y \approx 1.5$ seems preferred over high-metallicity cases. We also give a brief discussion on the implications for the neutron star mass, binary star evolution, inclination angle, and the potential for a high-metallicity scenario, the last of which is closely related to the properties of the hot CNO cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10993v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akira Dohi, Nobuya Nishimura, Ryosuke Hirai, Tomoshi Takeda, Wataru Iwakiri, Toru Tamagawa, Amira Aoyama, Teruaki Enoto, Satoko Iwata, Yo Kato, Takao Kitaguchi, Tatehiro Mihara, Naoyuki Ota, Takuya Takahashi, Sota Watanabe, Kaede Yamasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starkiller: subtracting stars and other sources from IFU spectroscopic data through forward modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14705v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present starkiller, an open-source Python package for forward-modeling flux retrieval from integral field unit spectrograph (IFU) datacubes. Starkiller simultaneously provides stellar spectral classification, relative velocity, and line-of-sight extinction for all sources in a catalog, alongside a source-subtracted datacube. It performs synthetic difference imaging by simulating all catalog sources in the field of view, using the catalog for positions and fluxes to scale stellar models, independent of the datacube. This differencing method is particularly powerful for subtracting both point-sources and trailed or even streaked sources from extended astronomical objects. We demonstrate starkiller's effectiveness in improving observations of extended sources in dense stellar fields for VLT/MUSE observations of comets, asteroids and nebulae. We also show that starkiller can treat satellite-impacted VLT/MUSE observations. The package could be applied to tasks as varied as dust extinction in clusters and stellar variability; the stellar modeling using Gaia fluxes is provided as a standalone function. The techniques can be expanded to imagers and to other IFUs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14705v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Ridden-Harper, Michele T. Bannister, Sophie E. Deam, Thomas Nordlander</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
