<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 04:02:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>JOYS+ study of solid state $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C isotope ratios in protostellar envelopes: Observations of CO and CO$_2$ ice with JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The carbon isotope ratio is a powerful tool for studying the evolution of stellar systems. Recent detections of CO isotopologues in disks and exoplanet atmospheres pointed towards significant fractionation in these systems. In order to understand the evolution of this quantity, it is crucial to trace the isotope abundance from stellar nurseries to planetary systems. During the protostellar stage the multiple vibrational modes of CO$_2$ and CO ice provide a unique opportunity to examine the carbon isotope ratio in the solid state. Now with the sensitivity of the \textit{James Webb Space Telescope}, these absorption features have become accessible at high S/N in Solar-mass systems. We quantify the $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ and the $^{12}$CO/$^{13}$CO isotope ratios in 17 class 0/I low mass protostars from the $^{12}$CO$_2$ combination modes (2.70 ${\mu}$m and 2.77 ${\mu}$m), the $^{12}$CO$_2$ stretching mode (4.27 ${\mu}$m), the $^{13}$CO$_2$ stretching mode (4.39 ${\mu}$m), the $^{12}$CO$_2$ bending mode (15.2 ${\mu}$m), the $^{12}$CO stretching mode (4.67 ${\mu}$m) and the $^{13}$CO stretching mode (4.78 ${\mu}$m) using JWST observations. We also report a detection of the $^{12}$CO overtone mode at 2.35 ${\mu}$m. The $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ ratios are in agreement and we find mean ratios of 85 $\pm$ 23, 76 $\pm$ 12 and 97 $\pm$ 17 for the 2.70 ${\mu}$m, 4.27 ${\mu}$m and the 15.2 ${\mu}$m bands, respectively. The main source of uncertainty stem from the error on the band strengths. The $^{12}$CO/$^{13}$CO ratios derived from the 4.67 ${\mu}$m bands are consistent, albeit elevated with respect to the $^{12}$CO$_2$/$^{13}$CO$_2$ ratios and we find a mean ratio of 165 $\pm$ 52. These findings indicate that ices leave the pre-stellar stage with elevated carbon isotope ratios relative to the interstellar medium and that fractionation becomes significant during the later stages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17237v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. G. C. Brunken, E. F. van Dishoeck, K. Slavicinska, V. J. M. le Gouellec, W. R. M. Rocha, L. Francis, L. Tychoniec, M. L. van Gelder, M. G. Navarro, A. C. A. Boogert, P. J. Kavanagh, P. Nazari, T. Greene, M. E. Ressler, L. Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative study of the W UMa type binaries S Ant and Epsilon CrA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contact binaries challenge contemporary stellar astrophysics with respect to their incidence, structure and evolution. We explore these issues through a detailed study of two bright examples: S Ant and Eps CrA, that permit high-resolution spectroscopy at a relatively good S/N ratio. The availability of high-quality photometry, including data from the TESS satellite as well as Gaia parallaxes, allows us to apply the Russell paradigm to produce reliable up-to-date information on the physical properties of these binaries. As a result, models of their interactive evolution, such as the thermal relaxation oscillator scenario, can be examined. Mass transfer between the components is clearly evidenced, but the variability of the O'Connell effect over relatively short time scales points to irregularities in the mass transfer or accretion processes. Our findings indicate that S Ant may evolve into an R CMa type Algol, while the low mass ratio of Eps CrA suggests a likely merger of its components in the not-too-distant future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17303v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volkan Bakis, Edwin Budding, Ahmet Erdem, Tom Love, Mark G. Blackford, Wu Zihao, Adam Tang, Michael D. Rhodes, Timothy S. Banks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millinovae: a new class of transient supersoft X-ray sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Some accreting binary systems containing a white dwarf (such as classical novae or persistent supersoft sources) are seen to emit low energy X-rays with temperatures of ~10^6 K and luminosities exceeding 10^35 erg/s. These X-rays are thought to originate from nuclear burning on the white dwarf surface, either caused by a thermonuclear runaway (classical novae) or a high mass accretion rate that sustains steady nuclear burning (persistent sources). The discovery of transient supersoft X-rays from ASASSN-16oh challenged these ideas, as no signatures of nuclear fusion were detected, and the origin of these X-rays remains controversial. It was unclear whether this star was one of a kind or representative of a larger, as yet undiscovered, group. Here we present the discovery of 29 stars located in the direction of the Magellanic Clouds exhibiting long-duration, symmetrical optical outbursts similar to that seen in ASASSN-16oh. We observed one of these objects during an optical outburst and found it to be emitting transient supersoft X-rays, while no signatures of mass ejection (indicative of a classical nova eruption) were detected. We therefore propose that these objects form a homogeneous group of transient supersoft X-ray sources, which we dub `millinovae' because their optical luminosities are approximately a thousand times fainter than those of ordinary classical novae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17338v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Przemek Mr\'oz, Krzysztof Kr\'ol, H\'el\`ene Szegedi, Philip Charles, Kim L. Page, Andrzej Udalski, David A. H. Buckley, Gulab Dewangan, Pieter Meintjes, Micha{\l} K. Szyma\'nski, Igor Soszy\'nski, Pawe{\l} Pietrukowicz, Szymon Koz{\l}owski, Rados{\l}aw Poleski, Jan Skowron, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Mariusz Gromadzki, Krzysztof Rybicki, Patryk Iwanek, Marcin Wrona, Mateusz J. Mr\'oz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar Active Regions Emergence Prediction Using Long Short-Term Memory Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We developed Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) models to predict the formation of active regions (ARs) on the solar surface. Using the Doppler shift velocity, the continuum intensity, and the magnetic field observations from the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI), we have created time-series datasets of acoustic power and magnetic flux, which are used to train LSTM models on predicting continuum intensity, 12 hours in advance. These novel machine learning (ML) models are able to capture variations of the acoustic power density associated with upcoming magnetic flux emergence and continuum intensity decrease. Testing of the models' performance was done on data for 5 ARs, unseen from the models during training. Model 8, the best performing model trained, was able to make a successful prediction of emergence for all testing active regions in an experimental setting and three of them in an operational. The model predicted the emergence of AR11726, AR13165, and AR13179 respectively 10, 29, and 5 hours in advance, and variations of this model achieved average RMSE values of 0.11 for both active and quiet areas on the solar disc. This work sets the foundations for ML-aided prediction of solar ARs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17421v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spiridon Kasapis, Irina N. Kitiashvili, Alexander G. Kosovichev, John T. Stefan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A data-driven MHD simulation of the 2011-02-15 coronal mass ejection from Active Region NOAA 11158</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a boundary data-driven magneto-hydrodynamic (MHD) simulation of the 2011-02-15 coronal mass ejection (CME) event of Active Region (AR) NOAA 11158. The simulation is driven at the lower boundary with an electric field derived from the normal magnetic field and the vertical electric current measured from the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) Helioseismic Magnetic Imager (HMI) vector magnetograms. The simulation shows the build up of a pre-eruption coronal magnetic field that is close to the nonlinear force-free field (NLFFF) extrapolation, and it subsequently develops multiple eruptions. The sheared/twisted field lines of the pre-eruption magnetic field show qualitative agreement with the brightening loops in the SDO Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) hot passband images. We find that the eruption is initiated by the tether-cutting reconnection in a highly sheared field above the central polarity inversion line (PIL) and a magnetic flux rope with dipped field lines forms during the eruption. The modeled erupting magnetic field evolves to develop a complex structure containing two distinct flux ropes and produces an outgoing double-shell feature consistent with the Solar TErrestrial RElations Observatory B / Extreme UltraViolet Imager (STEREO-B/EUVI) observation of the CME. The foot points of the erupting field lines are found to correspond well with the dimming regions seen in the SDO/AIA observation of the event. These agreements suggest that the derived electric field is a promising way to drive MHD simulations to establish the realistic pre-eruption coronal field based on the observed vertical electric current and model its subsequent dynamic eruption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17507v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhong Fan, Maria D. Kazachenko, Andrey N. Afanasyev, George H. Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walking the Line: Young Stars on the Boundary of the Epsilon Cha and Lower Centaurus-Crux Associations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gaia Data Release 3 (DR3) has provided the largest and most astrometrically precise catalogue of nearby stars to date, allowing for a more complete membership census of nearby, young stellar moving groups. These loose associations of young (age $&lt;$100 Myr) stars within $\sim$100 pc are vital laboratories for the study of the early evolution of low-mass stars and planetary systems. We have exploited DR3 data to examine the boundary region between two of the youngest nearby moving groups, the $\sim$3--8 Myr-old $\epsilon$ Cha Association (ECA) and an $\sim$8 Myr-old sub-population of the sprawling Lower Centaurus Crux (LCC) young star complex. Using spatio-kinematic and color-magnitude criteria designed to select stars in the ECA, we identify $\sim$54 new young-star candidates that extend from the ECA core to the southern edge of the LCC. Included among our new candidates are six previously unidentified ultra-low-mass, mid- to late-M stars, lying near the future hydrogen-burning limit, that display significant infrared excesses. Our spatial, kinematic, and CMD analysis of these new candidates and previously established LCC and ECA members blurs the boundary between these groups and provides evidence for a wave of continuous star formation extending from north (LCC) to south (ECA). We discuss the factors which studies of nearby young moving groups must consider when constraining the ages of stars in these groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17521v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ad7deb</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Attila Varga, Joel H. Kastner, D. Annie Dickson-Vandervelde, Alex S. Binks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Correlation between Positive-Charged Cosmic Ray Flux and Solar Magnetic Field Variation: Insights from Delayed Modulation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an analysis of the time-dependent modulation of galactic cosmic rays near Earth, with a focus on the cosmic proton flux and solar magnetic field strength. Using data from the Alpha Magnetic Spectrometer (AMS) and the Wilcox Solar Observatory, we identify a significant time-lagged relationship between the observation of two missions. Our model incorporates a weighted magnetic field parameter to address the hemispheric asymmetry in solar magnetic fields and captures the temporal evolution of cosmic-ray proton spectra in relation to solar activity. We find a time lag of approximately 10 months, varying with cosmic ray rigidity. At 1 GV, the time lag is 360 days, while it is 300 days above 3 GV. This offers predictive insights into cosmic ray modulation within the heliosphere. These results enhance the accuracy of space weather forecasting models, with significant implications for the safety of space missions and aviation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17646v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaokun Gong, Linjing Duan, Jiawei Zhao, Xueyu Wei, Jie Feng, Zhibing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convective vortices in collapsing stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies show that non-radial structures arising from massive star shell convection play an important role in shaping core-collapse supernova explosions. During the collapse phase, convective vortices generate acoustic waves that interact with the supernova shock. This amplifies turbulence in the post-shock region, contributing to explosion. We study how various physical parameters influence the evolution of these convective vortices during stellar collapse using simplified simulations. We model the collapsing star with a transonic Bondi flow and represent convection as solenoidal velocity perturbations. Our results are consistent with previous studies, demonstrating that the peak perturbation amplitude scales linearly with the pre-collapse convective Mach number and inversely with the angular wavenumber of convection. While the shell radius and width primarily determine the timescale of accretion, they have little impact on the peak perturbation amplitudes. Finally, we show that when the convective Mach number is below approximately 0.2, the dynamics remain within the linear regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17737v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yerassyl Telman, Ernazar Abdikamalov, Thierry Foglizzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the origin of a broad QFP wave train: unwinding jet as the driver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17741v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large-scale extreme-ultraviolet (EUV) waves commonly exhibit as single wavefront and are believed to be caused by coronal mass ejections (CMEs). Utilizing high spatiotemporal resolution imaging observations from the Solar Dynamics Observatory, we present two sequentially generated wave trains originating from the same active region: a narrow quasiperiodic fast-propagating (QFP) wave train that propagates along the coronal loop system above the jet and a broad QFP wave train that travels along the solar surface beneath the jet. The measurements indicate that the narrow QFP wave train and the accompanying flare's quasiperiodic pulsations (QPPs) have nearly identical onsets and periods. This result suggests that the accompanying flare process excites the observed narrow QFP wave train. However, the broad QFP wave train starts approximately 2 minutes before the QPPs of the flare, but consistent with the interaction between the unwinding jet and the solar surface. Moreover, we find that the \zx{period of the broad QFP wave train, approximately 130\,s, closely matches that of the unwinding jet}. This period is significantly longer than the 30\,s period of the accompanying flare's QPPs. Based on these findings, we propose that the intermittent energy release of the accompanying flare excited the narrow QFP wave train confined propagating in the coronal loop system. The unwinding jet, rather than the intermittent energy release in the accompanying flare, triggered the broad QFP wave train propagating along the solar surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17741v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinping Zhou, Zehao Tang, Zhining Qu, Ke Yu, Chengrui Zhou, Yuqi Xiang, Ahmed Ahmed Ibrahim, Yuandeng Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing solar magnetic fields from historical observations X. Effect of magnetic field inclination and boundary structure on AIA 1600 {\AA} emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The relation between the intensity of chromospheric emissions and the photospheric magnetic field strength has been examined in several studies, but the effect of the magnetic field inclination on chromospheric emissions remains almost unexplored. We study how the inclination of the photospheric magnetic field, as measured by the full 3D magnetic vector from the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI), affects the relationship between the magnetic field strength and the far-ultraviolet emission at around 1600 {\AA} observed by the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA). We also study how these parameters change spatially close to the active region perimeter. We analyzed the mutual dependence of 1168 co-temporal AIA and HMI observations from 2014 to 2017. We focused on magnetically active regions outside sunspots (e.g., plages and network) close to the solar disk center. We studied how the AIA and HMI parameters change with distance from the active region perimeter. The AIA 1600 emission typically decreases with increasing (more horizontal) inclination. For all inclinations, AIA 1600 emission increases with increasing magnetic field strength until saturating at some peak intensity, which depends on the cosine of the inclination, with horizontal regions saturating at lower intensities. In addition, we find that activity clusters have a narrow boundary (&lt; 2 arcseconds) in which the AIA 1600 intensity, magnetic field strength, and inclination distributions and relations differ significantly from those in the inner layers. This study demonstrates the significant effect that magnetic field inclination and activity cluster border regions have on chromospheric emissions. Although the observed effects are likely reduced in low-resolution observations where different regions are averaged together, a detailed study is needed to examine the emission--magnetic field relation at different resolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17771v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismo T\"ahtinen, Alexei A. Pevtsov, Timo Asikainen, Kalevi Mursula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Classification of Hot Subdwarf Binaries Using Artificial Intelligence Techniques and Gaia DR3 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17783v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hot subdwarfs are compact blue evolved objects, burning helium in their cores surrounded by a tiny hydrogen envelope. Most models agree on a common envelope binary evolution scenario in the Red Giant phase. However, the binarity rate for these objects is yet unsolved. We aim to develop a novel classification method for identifying hot subdwarf binaries within large datasets using Artificial Intelligence methods and Gaia DR3 data. The results will be compared with those obtained previously using VOSA (Virtual Observatory Sed Analyzer) on coincident samples. The methods include several machine learning techniques. We used Support Vector Machines (SVM) to classify 3084 hot subdwarf stars based on their color-magnitude properties. Of these, 2815 objects have Gaia Data Release 3 BP/RP spectra, which were classified using Self-Organizing Maps (SOM) and Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN). The findings demonstrate a high agreement level (70-90%) with VOSA's classification, indicating that machine learning methods effectively classify sources with an accuracy comparable to human inspection or non-AI techniques. SVM in a radial basis function achieves 70.97% reproducibility for binary targets using photometry. CNN reaches 84.94% for binary detection using spectroscopy. We also found that the single-binary differences are especially observable on the infrared flux in our GDR3 BP/BR spectra, at wavelengths larger than 700 nm. We found that all our methods are effective in discerning between single and binary systems and are consistent with the results previously obtained with VOSA. In global terms, considering all quality metrics, CNN is the method that provides the best accuracy. The methods are also effective for detecting peculiarities in the spectra. Further research is needed to refine our techniques and enhance automated classification reliability, especially for large-scale surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17783v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Viscasillas V\'azquez, E. Solano, A. Ulla, M. Ambrosch, M. A. \'Alvarez, M. Manteiga, L. Magrini, R. Santove\~na-G\'omez, C. Dafonte, E. P\'erez-Fern\'andez, A. Aller, A. Drazdauskas, \v{S}. Mikolaitis, C. Rodrigo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can the solar atmosphere generate very high energy cosmic rays?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The origin and acceleration of high-energy particles in space (cosmic rays), constitute important topics in modern astrophysics. Among the
  two categories of cosmic rays - galactic and solar cosmic rays - the latter are much less investigated. Primary source of solar cosmic ray particles are impulsive explosions of the magnetized plasma known as solar flares and coronal mass ejections. These particles are characterized by relatively low energies compared to their galactic counterparts. In this work, we explore resonance wave-wave (RWW) interaction between the polarized electromagnetic radiation emitted by the solar active region and the quantum waves associated with high-energy, relativistic electrons generated during solar flares. We find that RWW could accelerate the relativistic electrons to enormous energies even comparable to energies in the galactic cosmic rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17801v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. N. Osmanov, D. Kuridze, S. M. Mahajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slowly Rotating Peculiar Star BD+00$^\circ$1659 as a Benchmark for Stratification Studies in Ap/Bp Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results of a self-consistent analysis of the magnetic silicon star BD+00$^\circ$1659, based on its high-resolution spectra taken from the ESPaDOnS archive (R = 68,000). This narrow-lined star shows the typical high Si abundance and Si II-III anomaly, making it an ideal prototype for investigating the vertical distribution of Si and Fe in the stellar atmosphere. The derived abundances, ranging from helium to lanthanides, confirm the star's classification as a silicon Bp spectral type. Silicon and iron are represented by lines of different ionisation stages (Fe I-III, Si I-III), indicating an ionisation imbalance interpreted as evidence of atmospheric stratification. Our stratification analysis reveals that there is a jump in iron and silicon abundances of 1.5 dex at atmospheric layers with an optical depth of $log\tau_{5000}$ = $-$0.85-$-$1.00. Non-LTE calculations for iron in this stratified atmosphere show minor non-LTE effects. Our results can be applied to studying the impact of stratification on the emergent flux in rapidly rotating Si stars with similar atmospheric parameters and abundance anomalies (for example, MX TrA), where direct stratification analysis is challenging due to line~blending.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17855v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/galaxies12050055</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Galaxies 2024, 12, 55</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Romanovskaya, T. Ryabchikova, Y. Pakhomov, I. Potravnov, T. Sitnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Dynamics of CME-Driven Shocks by Comparing Numerical Modeling and Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shocks driven by coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are primary drivers of gradual solar energetic particle (SEP) events, posing significant risks to space technology and astronauts. Concurrently, particles accelerated at these shocks may also propagate back to the Sun, potentially generating gamma-ray emissions through pion decay. We incorporated advanced modeling and multi-messenger observations to explore the role of CME-driven shocks in gamma-ray emissions and SEPs. Motivated by Fermi-LAT long-duration solar flares, we used the AWSoM MHD model to investigate the connection between the shocks and the properties of observed gamma-ray emissions. By coupling the AWSoM with iPATH model, we evaluate the impact of shock evolution complexity near the Sun on SEP intensity and spectra. Our result points to the importance of accurate background coronal and solar wind modeling, as well as detailed observations of CME source regions, in advancing our understanding of CME-driven shocks and the dynamics of associated energetic particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18020v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Jin, Gang Li, Nariaki Nitta, Wei Liu, Vahe Petrosian, Ward Manchester, Christina Cohen, Frederic Effenberger, Zheyi Ding, Melissa Pesce-Rollins, Nicola Omodei, Nat Gopalswamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetohydrodynamic simulations of A-type stars: Long-term evolution of core dynamo cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Early-type stars have convective cores due to a steep temperature gradient produced by the CNO cycle. These cores can host dynamos, and the generated magnetic fields can be relevant to explain the magnetism observed in Ap/Bp stars. Our main objective is to characterise the convective core dynamos and differential rotation, and to do the first quantitative analysis of the relation between magnetic activity cycle and rotation period. We use numerical 3D star-in-a-box simulations of a $2.2~M_\odot$ A-type star with a convective core of roughly $20\%$ of the stellar radius surrounded by a radiative envelope. Rotation rates from 8 to 20 days are explored. We use two models of the entire star, and an additional zoom set, where $50\%$ of the radius is retained. The simulations produce hemispheric core dynamos with cycles and typical magnetic field strengths around 60 kG. However, only a very small fraction of the magnetic energy is able to reach the surface. The cores have solar-like differential rotation, and a substantial part of the radiative envelope has quasi-rigid rotation. In the most rapidly rotating cases the magnetic energy in the core is roughly 40\% of the kinetic energy. Finally, we find that the magnetic cycle period $P_\mathrm{cyc}$ increases with decreasing the rotation period $P_\mathrm{rot}$ which is also observed in many simulations of solar-type stars. Our simulations indicate that a strong hemispherical core dynamo arises routinely, but that it is not enough the explain the surface magnetism of Ap/Bp stars. Nevertheless, as the core dynamo produces dynamically relevant magnetic fields it should not be neglected when other mechanisms are explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18066v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Hidalgo, P. J. K\"apyl\"a, D. R. G Schleicher, C. A. Ortiz-Rodr\'iguez, F. H. Navarrete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron Star with Dark Matter Admixture: A Candidate for Bridging the Mass Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars and black holes are the after death remnants of massive stars. However, according to the most recent observations, the neutron stars maximum mass is between $2.0-2.5 M_{\odot}$ while black holes of less than 5 $M_{\odot}$ rarely has been observed. The region between the most massive neutron star and the least massive black hole is called the mass gap. If indeed its existence is confirmed by future observations, that indicates a gap in our understanding which seeks for explanation. In addition, the existence of compact objects within the mass gap should also be supported with the help of possible new theoretical scenarios. In this letter, we propose a possible explanation for the existence of compact objects within the mass gap region. Specifically, we propose that the mass gap region could be bridged by the existence of a hybrid compact object, composed of hadronic and self interacting - non annihilating fermionic dark matter, considering that the interaction between these two fluids its only gravitational. Fundamental questions about how these objects form and how they can be detected are also addressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17188v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Vikiaris, V. Petousis, M. Veselsky, Ch. C. Moustakidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially correlated stellar accretion in the Lupus star forming region: Evidence for ongoing infall from the interstellar medium?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17220v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Growing evidence suggests that protoplanetary discs may be influenced by late stage infall from the interstellar medium (ISM). It remains unclear the degree to which infall shapes disc populations at ages $\gtrsim 1$~Myr. We explore possible spatial correlations between stellar accretion rates in the Lupus star forming region, which would support the hypothesis that infall can regulate stellar accretion. We consider both the `clustered' stars towards the center of Lupus 3, and the `distributed' stars that are more sparsely distributed across the Lupus complex. We take the observed accretion rates in the literature and explore spatial correlations. In particular, we test whether the clustered stars exhibit a radial gradient in normalised accretion rates, and whether the distributed stars have spatially correlated accretion rates. We find statistically significant correlations for both the clustered and distributed samples. The clustered sample exhibits higher accretion rates in the central region, consistent with the expected Bondi-Hoyle-Lyttleton accretion rate. Stars that are spatially closer among the distributed population also exhibit more similar accretion rates. These results cannot be explained by the stellar mass distribution for either sample. Age gradients are disfavoured, though not discounted, because normalised disc dust masses are not spatially correlated across the region. Spatially correlated stellar accretion rates within the Lupus star forming region argue in favour of an environmental influence on stellar accretion, possibly combined with internal processes in the inner disc. Refined age measurements and searches for evidence of infalling material is a potential way to further test this finding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17220v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew J. Winter, Myriam Benisty, Carlo Manara, Aashish Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Red giant - jet collisions in galactic nuclei I: 3D hydrodynamical model of a few stellar orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17773v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Several models have been proposed to explain missing red giants (RGs) near the Galactic centre. Recently, a scenario has been suggested that predicts, among other processes, a long-term ablation of the surface layers of RGs during their repetitive passages through the Galactic jet (Zaja\v{c}ek et al., 2020). In this study, we perform detailed three-dimensional numerical modelling of this phenomenon. We calculate the ablation rate of the surface layers of a RG orbiting the supermassive black hole (SMBH) as it passes through the nuclear jet. In particular, we model the jet-star interaction for approximately 10 passages for the closer orbital distance of $10^{-3}\,\text{pc}$ and 2 passages for $10^{-2}\,\text{pc}$. We find that the mass loss due to ablation by the jet behaves with time as $\Delta M_{\star}\propto \sqrt{t}$ and the total ablated mass during a single active galactic nucleus (AGN) phase ($10^5$ years) is $\sim 10^4\,M_{\odot}$. We arrive at similar rates of the stellar ablation for the relatively smaller jet luminosity $10^{42}\,\text{erg}\,\text{s}^{-1}$ as in the previous analytical calculations. For larger jet luminosities of $10^{44}$ and $10^{48}\,\text{erg}\,\text{s}^{-1}$, the ablation rates inferred from $\sim 10$ interactions as well as extrapolated power-law fits are significantly lower than analytical values. For the smallest orbital distance of $10^{-3}\,\text{pc}$, we also track the thermal behaviour of the stellar surface layer, whose temperature appears to grow rapidly during the first 10 passages from $\sim 3600\,{\rm K}$ (spectral type M) to $\sim 8500\,{\rm K}$ (spectral type A). RG-jet interactions can thus lead to observable changes in the nuclear late-type stellar population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17773v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Kurf\"urst (MUNI, Brno), Michal Zaja\v{c}ek (MUNI, Brno), Norbert Werner (MUNI, Brno), Ji\v{r}\'i Krti\v{c}ka (MUNI, Brno)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical models for secular descents in hierarchical triple systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20377v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Triple body systems are prevalent in nature, from planetary to stellar to supermassive black hole scales. In a hierarchical triple system, oscillations of the inner orbit's eccentricity and inclination can be induced on secular timescales. Over many cycles, the octupole-level terms in the secular equations of motion can drive the system to extremely high eccentricities via the Eccentric Kozai-Lidov (EKL) mechanism. The overall decrease in the inner orbit's pericenter distance has potentially dramatic effects for realistic systems, such as tidal disruption events. We present an analytical approximation in the test particle limit to describe individual step-wise increases in eccentricity of the inner orbit. A second approximation, also in the test particle limit, is obtained by integrating the equations of motion and calibrating to numerical simulations to estimate the overall octupole-level time evolution of the eccentricity. The latter approach is then extended beyond the test particle to the general case. The three novel analytical approximations are compared to numerical solutions to show that the models accurately describe the form and timescale of the secular descent from large distances to a close-encounter distance (e.g., the Roche limit). By circumventing the need for numerical simulations to obtain the long-term behavior, these approximations can be used to readily estimate properties of close encounters and descent timescales for populations of systems. We demonstrate by calculating rates of EKL-driven migration for Hot Jupiters in stellar binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20377v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grant C. Weldon, Smadar Naoz, Bradley M. S. Hansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The JWST/NIRISS Deep Spectroscopic Survey for Young Brown Dwarfs and Free-Floating Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12639v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The discovery and characterization of free-floating planetary-mass objects (FFPMOs) is fundamental to our understanding of star and planet formation. Here we report results from an extremely deep spectroscopic survey of the young star cluster NGC1333 using NIRISS WFSS on the James Webb Space Telescope. The survey is photometrically complete to K~21, and includes useful spectra for objects as faint as K~20.5. The observations cover 19 known brown dwarfs, for most of which we confirm spectral types using NIRISS spectra. We discover six new candidates with L-dwarf spectral types that are plausible planetary-mass members of NGC1333, with estimated masses between 5-15 MJup. One, at ~5 MJup, shows clear infrared excess emission and is a good candidate to be the lowest mass object known to have a disk. We do not find any objects later than mid-L spectral type (M &lt; ~4 MJup). The paucity of Jupiter-mass objects, despite the survey's unprecedented sensitivity, suggests that our observations reach the lowest mass objects formed like stars in NGC1333. Our findings put the fraction of FFPMOs in NGC1333 at ~10% of the number of cluster members, significantly more than expected from the typical log-normal stellar mass function. We also search for wide binaries in our images and report a young brown dwarf with a planetary-mass companion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12639v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ad6f0c</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Adam B. Langeveld, Aleks Scholz, Koraljka Mu\v{z}i\'c, Ray Jayawardhana, Daniel Capela, Lo\"ic Albert, Ren\'e Doyon, Laura Flagg, Matthew de Furio, Doug Johnstone, David Lafr\`eniere, Michael Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
