<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric Hard X-ray Radiation of Two Ribbons in a Thermal-Dominated C-Class Flare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The asymmetry in hard X-ray (HXR) emission at the footpoints (FPs) of flare loops is a ubiquitous feature closely associated with nonthermal electron transport. We analyze the asymmetric HXR radiation at two flare ribbons which is thermal-dominated during a long-duration C4.4 flare that occurred on March 20, 2023, combining multi-view and multi-waveband observations from the ASO-S, SolO, and SDO spacecraft. We find that the H I Ly$\alpha$ emission captures similar features to the He II $\lambda$304 in both light curve and spatio-temporal evolution of a pair of conjugate flare ribbons. The spectra and imaging analysis of the HXR emission, detected by STIX in 4-18 keV, reveal that the two-ribbon flare radiation is thermal dominated by over 95%, and the radiation source mainly concentrates on the northern ribbon, leading to an asymmetric distribution. To understand the underlying reasons for the HXR radiation asymmetry, we extrapolate the magnetic field within the active region using the NLFFF model. For 78% of the magnetic field lines starting from the northern flare ribbon, their lengths from the loop-tops (LTs) to the northern FPs are shorter than those to the southern FPs. For 62% of the field lines, their magnetic field strengths at the southern FPs exceed those at the northern FPs. In addition, considering the larger density, $\approx1.0\times10^{10}$ cm$^{-3}$, of the low-lying flare loops (&lt; 32 Mm), we find the shorter path from the LT to the northern FP enables more electrons to reach the northern FP more easily after collisions with the surrounding plasma. Therefore, in this thermal-dominated C-class flare, the asymmetric location of the flare LT relative to its two FPs plays a dominant role in the HXR radiation asymmetry, while such asymmetry is also slightly influenced by the magnetic mirror effect resulting in larger HXR radiation at the FPs with weaker magnetic strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13099v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanglu Shi, Li Feng, Jun Chen, Beili Ying, Shuting Li, Qiao Li, Hui Li, Ying Li, Kaifan Ji, Yu Huang, Weiqun Gan, the LST team</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LAMA: LAMOST Medium-Resolution Spectral Analysis Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) has obtained more than 23 million spectra, opening an unprecedented opportunity to study stellar physics, as well as the formation and evolution of our Milky Way. In order to obtain the accurate stellar parameters, we develop a LAMOST Medium-Resolution Spectral Analysis Pipeline (LAMA), which estimates the stellar parameters from the LAMOST medium-resolution spectra, including the effective temperature (Teff), surface gravity (logg), metallicity ([Fe/H]), radial velocity, and rotational velocity (vsini). LAMA estimates these parameters utilizing the template-matching method. The comparison between our results and those from the high-resolution ones, including APOGEE, GALAH, and PASTEL, shows no obvious bias, indicating the reliability of our results. The accuracy of Teff and [Fe/H] can reach 75 K and 0.12 dex, respectively, for the LAMOST Medium-Resolution Spectroscopic Survey (MRS) spectra with a signal-to-noise ratio higher than 10. For dwarfs, the uncertainty of logg is around 0.17 dex, while, for giants, it ranges from 0.18 to 0.30 dex, with the errors decreasing as logg increases. Using LAMA for the LAMOST-MRS spectra, we estimate the stellar parameters of 497,412 stars. This sample will be very helpful for investigating the formation and evolution of our Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13134v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/ad5002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJS (2024), 273, 18</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chun-qian Li, Jian-rong Shi, Hong-liang Yan, Zhong-rui Bai, Jiang-tao Wang, Ming-yi Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The prospect of confining the equation of state of neutron star with future mass and radius measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simultaneous measurement of mass and radius with high precision is essential to unravel the equation of state of matter at the centre of neutron stars. Measurement of massive pulsars indicates that the equation of state has to be stiff at low densities. The radius measurement of PSR J0030+0451 has rejected several relatively softer equations of state. In this work, an ensemble of agnostically constructed EoS was studied for the mass and radius measurement. The range of radius of neutron stars obtained from the ensemble was confined within a radius bound from 10.5 - 14.5 km. It is seen that higher masses prefer stiffer EoS. However, the slope of the speed of sound (the stiffness of the EoS) is very sensitive to the radius measurement. Assuming the radius measurement to be precise up to 2 km, then a higher radius indicates sharp stiffening of the equation of state at low density; however, it also indicates a sharp fall after the peak, indicating a relatively softer core for massive neutron stars. On the other hand, for the same precision, a lower radius measurement indicates a relatively softer equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13149v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asim Kumar Saha, Ritam Mallick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A common law for the differential rotation of planets and stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13484v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: All planets and stars rotate. All gas planets in our solar system, the Sun, and many stars show a pattern of east- or westward mean flows. This phenomenon is known as differential rotation in the stellar and as zonal jets in the planetary context. Observations, laboratory experiments and simulations show that the zonal flow kinetic energy scales like $\ell^{-5}$, where $\ell$ is the spherical harmonic degree (which is effectively a latitudinal wave number). Here, we analyze observation of the Sun, as well as simulations of the dynamics in Saturn and in the outer atmosphere of an ultra-hot Jupiter. While these systems are very different, they all develop strong zonal winds that obey the $\ell^{-5}$ scaling. Our results strongly suggest that there is a simple common mechanism that shapes zonal mean flows in planets and stars independent of the flow driving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13484v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent G. A. B\"oning, Johannes Wicht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-period Post-Common Envelope Binaries with Balmer Emission from SDSS and LAMOST Based on ZTF Photometric Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13525v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present here 55 short period PCEBs containing a hot WD and a low-mass MS. Based on the photometric data from ZTF DR19, the light curves are analyzed for about 200 WDMS binaries with emission line(s) identified from SDSS or LAMOST spectra, in which 55 WDMS binaries are found to exhibit variability in their luminosities with a short period and are thus short-period binaries (i.e. PCEBs). In addition, it is found that the orbital periods of these PCEBs locate in a range from 2.2643 to 81.1526 hours. However, only 6 short-period PCEBs are newly discovered and the orbital periods of 19 PCEBs are improved in this work. Meanwhile, it is found that three objects are newly discovered eclipsing PCEBs, and a object (i.e. SDSS J1541) might be the short-period PCEB with a late M-type star or a brown dwarf companion based on the analysis of its spectral energy distribution. At last, the mechanism(s) being responsible for the emission features in the spectra of these PCEBs are discussed, the emission features arising in their optical spectra might be caused by the stellar activity or an irradiated component owing to a hot white dwarf companion because most of them contain a white dwarf with an effective temperature higher than $\sim$10,000 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13525v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lifang Li, Fenghui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are the surface abundance structures stable in rapidly rotating Ap star 56 Ari?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The surface magnetic and abundance inhomogeneities in chemically peculiar Ap/Bp stars are coupled and responsible for their rotationally modulated variability. Within the framework of fossil field hypothesis these inhomogeneities are considered to be essentially stable over the Main Sequence (MS) timescale. However, a small group of Ap/Bp stars show rotational period changes, which are currently not well understood. We present results of Doppler Imaging (DI) of rapidly rotating Ap star 56 Ari for which changes in period were previously detected. Reconstruction of the surface distribution of silicon in 56 Ari reveals its complex spot pattern, which is responsible for the rotationally light variability and correlated with magnetic field modulation. Comparison of abundance maps obtained over the unprecedentedly long for such studies interval from 1986 to 2014 confirms stability and rigid rotation of the spot pattern. Thus, the period change in 56 Ari is not caused by rearrangement of the surface magnetic structures and/or atomic diffusion operating on short time scale. It is also unlikely to be explained by the visibility changes of the spots due to free-body precession of stellar rotational axis. In the end of the paper we briefly discuss possible alternative explanations of period variability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13645v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Potravnov, N. Piskunov, T. Ryabchikova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging the jet of MWC 349A with resolved Radio Recombination Line emission from ALMA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Jets and disk winds arise from materials with excess angular momentum ejected from the accretion disks in forming stars. How these structures are launched and how they impact the gas within the innermost regions of these objects remains poorly understood. MWC349A is a massive star that has a circumstellar disk which rotates in accord with Kepler's Law, with an ionized wind and a high-velocity jet launched from the disk surface. The strongly maser-amplified emission of hydrogen radio recombination lines (RRLs) observed toward this system provides a comprehensive picture of its ionized environment with exquisite detail. In this Letter, we present ALMA observations of the H26$\alpha$ RRL and continuum emission obtained with the highest angular resolution ever used toward this source (beam of $\sim$0.02"). The maser RRL emission is resolved for the first time and clearly delineates the ionized disk, wind and jet. We analyzed the RRL data cubes with the 3D non-LTE radiative transfer model MORELI, confirming that the jet is poorly collimated. We found that the jet orientation is closer to the rotation axis of the system than derived from spatially unresolved data. This study confirms that hydrogen RRL masers are powerful probes of the physical structure and kinematics of the innermost ionized material around massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13681v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad638d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Mart\'inez-Henares, Qizhou Zhang, Izaskun Jim\'enez-Serra, Jes\'us Mart\'in-Pintado, Nuria Hu\'elamo, Sirina Prasad, James Moran, Alejandro B\'aez-Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the Far-Infrared Polarization Spectrum of a High-Mass Star Forming Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The polarization spectrum, or wavelength dependence of the polarization fraction, of interstellar dust emission provides important insights into the grain alignment mechanism of interstellar dust grains. We investigate the far-infrared polarization spectrum of a realistic simulated high-mass star forming cloud under various models of grain alignment and emission. We find that neither a homogeneous grain alignment model nor a grain alignment model that includes collisional dealignment is able to produce the falling spectrum seen in observations. On the other hand, we find that a grain alignment model with grain alignment efficiency dependent on local temperature is capable of producing a falling spectrum that is in qualitative agreement with observations of OMC-1. For the model most in agreement with OMC-1, we find no correlation between temperature and the slope of the polarization spectrum. However, we do find a positive correlation between column density and the slope of the polarization spectrum. We suggest this latter correlation to be the result of wavelength-dependent polarization by absorption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12917v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Lee, Che-Yu Chen, Giles Novak, David T. Chuss, Erin G. Cox, Kaitlyn Karpovich, Peter Ashton, Marc Berthoud, Zhi-Yun Li, Joseph M. Michail</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition to turbulence in the wide-gap spherical Couette system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12981v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The spherical Couette system consists of two differentially rotating concentric spheres with a fluid filled in between. We study a regime where the outer sphere is rotating rapidly enough so that the Coriolis force is important and the inner sphere is rotating either slower or in the opposite direction with respect to the outer sphere. We numerically study the sudden transition to turbulence at a critical differential rotation seen in experiments at BTU Cottbus - Senftenberg, Germany and investigate its cause. We find that the source of turbulence is the boundary layer on the inner sphere, which becomes centrifugally unstable. We show that this instability leads to generation of small scale structures which lead to turbulence in the bulk, dominated by inertial waves, a change in the force balance near the inner boundary, the formation of a mean flow through Reynolds stresses, and consequently, to an efficient angular momentum transport. We compare our findings with axisymmetric simulations and show that there are significant similarities in the nature of the flow in the turbulent regimes of full 3D and axisymmetric simulations but differences in the evolution of the instability that leads to this transition. We find that a heuristic argument based on a Reynolds number defined using the thickness of the boundary layer as a length scale helps explain the scaling law of the variation of critical differential rotation for transition to turbulence with rotation rate observed in the experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12981v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankit Barik, Santiago A. Triana, Michael Hoff, Johannes Wicht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a complete picture of the Sco-Cen outflow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previous studies have shown strong evidence that the Sun is crossing an outflow originating from the Sco-Cen OB association. Understanding this outflow's origin and structure illuminates how massive star formation shapes the interstellar medium (ISM) and helps predict future Galactic conditions affecting our Solar System. We analysed H I emission and optical ISM absorption lines towards 47 early-type stars around the Upper Sco region to refine the map of the Sco-Cen outflow. Combined with data for nearby stars, we find that the outflow has at least two components: a faster, low-density component traced by Ca II, and a slower, possibly lower-density component traced by Mg II and Fe II in the UV that is passing through the Earth. A constant flow model successfully describes both components with $(l,b,|\vec{v}|) = (335.4^{\circ}, -6.8^{\circ}, 14.0 \,\,\textrm{km}\,\textrm{s}^{-1})$ and $(305.5^{\circ}, +17.6^{\circ}, 21.2\,\,\textrm{km}\,\textrm{s}^{-1})$, respectively. The origin of the faster component points towards the Sco-Cen 15 Myr population, which is consistent with the origin of the slower component within 2 $\sigma$. A simple model comparison indicates that a constant flow is favoured over a spherical flow geometry, implying an extended distribution of feedback sources within Sco-Cen. We also found that a poorly studied 25 pc long H I cloud at a distance of 107 pc belongs to the established Sco-Cen flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13226v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Piecka, S. Hutschenreuter, J. Alves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star and Planet Formation with the Single Aperture Large Telescope for Universe Studies (SALTUS) Space Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13430v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Single Aperture Large Telescope for Universe Studies (SALTUS) is a far-infrared space mission concept with unprecedented spatial and spectral resolution. Saltus consists of a 14-m inflatable primary, providing 16 times the sensitivity and 4 times the angular resolution of Herschel, and two cryogenic detectors spanning a wavelength range of 34-660 microns and spectral resolving power of 300 - 1e7. Spectroscopic observations in the far-infrared offer many unique windows into the processes of star and planet formation. These include observations of low energy water transitions, the H2 mass tracer HD, many CHONS constraining molecules such as NH3 and H2S, and emission lines from the phonon modes of molecular ices. Observing these species will allow us to build a statistical sample of protoplanetary disk masses, characterize the water snowline, identify Kuiper Belt like debris rings around other stars, and trace the evolution CHONS from prestellar cores, through to protoplanetary disks and debris disks. This paper details details several key star and planet formation science goals achievable with SALTUS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13430v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamber Schwarz, Alexander Tielens, Joan Najita, Jennifer Bergner, Quentin Kral, Carrie Anderson, Gordon Chin, David Leisawitz, David Wilner, Peter Roelfsema, Floris van der Tak, Erick Young, Christopher Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic constraints on the ages and kick velocities of Galactic neutron star binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13667v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The systems creating binary neutron stars (BNSs) experience systemic kicks when one of the components goes supernova. The combined magnitude of these kicks is still a topic of debate, and has implications for the eventual location of the transient resulting from the merger of the binary. For example, the offsets of short-duration gamma-ray bursts (SGRBs) resulting from BNS mergers depend on the BNS kicks. We investigated Galactic BNSs, and traced their motion through the Galaxy. This enabled us to estimate their kinematic ages and construct a BNS kick distribution, based on their Galactic trajectories. We used the pulsar periods and their derivatives to estimate the characteristic spin-down ages of the binaries. Moreover, we used a Monte Carlo estimation of their present-day velocity vector in order to trace back their trajectory and estimate their kinematic ages. These trajectories, in turn, were used to determine the eccentricity of their Galactic orbit. Based on simulations of kicked objects in the Galactic potential, we investigated the relationship between this eccentricity and kick velocity, in order to constrain the kicks imparted to the binaries at birth. We find that the Galactic BNSs are likely older than $\sim40$ Myr, which means their current (scalar) galactocentric speeds are not representative of their initial kicks. However, we find a close relationship between the eccentricity of a Galactic trajectory and the experienced kick. Using this relation, we constrained the kicks of the Galactic BNSs, depending on the kind of isotropy assumed in estimating their velocity vectors. These kick velocities are well-described by a log-normal distribution peaking around $\sim40-50$ km/s, and coincide with the peculiar velocities of the binaries at their last disc crossing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13667v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Disberg, Nicola Gaspari, Andrew J. Levan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the full Spitzer microlensing sample I: Dark remnant candidates and Gaia predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the pursuit of understanding the population of stellar remnants within the Milky Way, we analyze the sample of $\sim 950$ microlensing events observed by the Spitzer Space Telescope between 2014 and 2019. In this study we focus on a sub-sample of nine microlensing events, selected based on their long timescales, small microlensing parallaxes and joint observations by the Gaia mission, to increase the probability that the chosen lenses are massive and the mass is measurable. Among the selected events we identify lensing black holes and neutron star candidates, with potential confirmation through forthcoming release of the Gaia time-series astrometry in 2026. Utilizing Bayesian analysis and Galactic models, along with the Gaia Data Release 3 proper motion data, four good candidates for dark remnants were identified: OGLE-2016-BLG-0293, OGLE-2018-BLG-0483, OGLE-2018-BLG-0662, and OGLE-2015-BLG-0149, with lens masses of $2.98^{+1.75}_{-1.28}~M_{\odot}$, $4.65^{+3.12}_{-2.08}~M_{\odot}$, $3.15^{+0.66}_{-0.64}~M_{\odot}$ and $1.4^{+0.75}_{-0.55}~M_{\odot}$, respectively. Notably, the first two candidates are expected to exhibit astrometric microlensing signals detectable by Gaia, offering the prospect of validating the lens masses. The methodologies developed in this work will be applied to the full Spitzer microlensing sample, populating and analyzing the time-scale ($t_{\rm E}$) vs. parallax ($\pi_{\rm E}$) diagram to derive constraints on the population of lenses in general and massive remnants in particular.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13740v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof A. Rybicki, Yossi Shvartzvald, Jennifer C. Yee, Sebastiano Calchi Novati, Eran O. Ofek, Ian A. Bond, Charles Beichman, Geoff Bryden, Sean Carey, Calen Henderson, Wei Zhu, Michael M. Fausnaugh, Benjamin Wibking, Andrzej Udalski, Radek Poleski, Przemek Mr\'oz, Michal K. Szyma\'nski, Igor Soszy\'nski, Pawe{\l} Pietrukowicz, Szymon Koz{\l}owski, Jan Skowron, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Patryk Iwanek, Marcin Wrona, Yoon-Hyun Ryu, Michael D. Albrow, Sun-Ju Chung, Andrew Gould, Cheongho Han, Kyu-Ha Hwang, Youn Kil Jung, In-Gu Shin, Hongjing Yang, Weicheng Zang, Sang-Mok Cha, Dong-Jin Kim, Hyoun-Woo Kim, Seung-Lee Kim, Chung-Uk Lee, Dong-Joo Lee, Yongseok Lee, Byeong-Gon Park, Richard W. Pogge, Fumio Abe, Richard Barry, David P. Bennett, Aparna Bhattacharya, Akihiko Fukui, Ryusei Hamada, Shunya Hamada, Naoto Hamasaki, Yuki Hirao, Stela Ishitani Silva, Yoshitaka Itow, Rintaro Kirikawa, Naoki Koshimoto, Yutaka Matsubara, Shota Miyazaki, Yasushi Muraki, Tutumi Nagai, Kansuke NUNOTA, Greg Olmschenk, Clement Ranc, Nicholas J. Rattenbury, Yuki K. Satoh, Takahiro Sumi, Daisuke Suzuki, Paul . J. Tristram, Aikaterini Vandorou, Hibiki Yama, Lukasz Wyrzykowski, Kornel Howil, Katarzyna Kruszy\'nska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ALMA Legacy survey of Class 0/I disks in Corona australis, Aquila, chaMaeleon, oPhiuchus north, Ophiuchus, Serpens (CAMPOS). I. Evolution of Protostellar disk radii</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We surveyed nearly all the embedded protostars in seven nearby clouds (Corona Australis, Aquila, Chamaeleon I &amp; II, Ophiuchus North, Ophiuchus, Serpens) with the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array at 1.3mm observations with a resolution of 0.1$"$. This survey detected 184 protostellar disks, 90 of which were observed at a resolution of 14-18 au, making it one of the most comprehensive high-resolution disk samples across various protostellar evolutionary stages to date. Our key findings include the detection of new annular substructures in two Class I and two flat-spectrum sources, while 21 embedded protostars exhibit distinct asymmetries or substructures in their disks. We find that protostellar disks have a substantially large variability in their radii across all evolutionary classes. In particular, the fraction of large disks with sizes above 60\,au decreases as the protostar evolves from Class 0 to Class I. Compiling the literature data, we discovered an increasing trend of the gas disk radii to dust disk radii ratio ($R_{\rm gas,Kep}/R_{\rm mm}$) with increasing bolometric temperature (${\rm T}_{\rm bol}$). Our results indicate that the dust and gas disk radii decouple during the early Class I stage. However, in the Class 0 stage, the dust and gas disk sizes are similar, which allows a direct comparison between models and observational data at the earliest stages of protostellar evolution. We show that the distribution of radii in the 52 Class 0 disks in our sample is in high tension with various disk formation models, indicating that protostellar disk formation remains an unsolved question.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02809v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Han Hsieh, H\'ector G. Arce, Mar\'ia Jos\'e Maureira, Jaime E. Pineda, Dominique Segura-Cox, Diego Mardones, Michael M. Dunham, Aiswarya Arun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regimes of stratified turbulence at low Prandtl number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06424v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantifying transport by strongly stratified turbulence in low Prandtl number ($Pr$) fluids is critically important for the development of better models for the structure and evolution of stellar and planetary interiors. Motivated by recent numerical simulations showing strongly anisotropic flows suggestive of scale-separated dynamics, we perform a multiscale asymptotic analysis of the governing equations. We find that, in all cases, the resulting slow-fast systems take a quasilinear form. Our analysis also reveals the existence of several distinct dynamical regimes depending on the emergent buoyancy Reynolds and P\'eclet numbers, $Re_b = \alpha^2 Re$ and $Pe_b = Pr Re_b$, respectively, where $\alpha$ is the aspect ratio of the large-scale turbulent flow structures, and $Re$ is the outer scale Reynolds number. Scaling relationships relating the aspect ratio, the characteristic vertical velocity, and the strength of the stratification (measured by the Froude number $Fr$) naturally emerge from the analysis. When $Pe_b \ll \alpha$, the dynamics at all scales is dominated by buoyancy diffusion, and our results recover the scaling laws empirically obtained from direct numerical simulations by Cope et al. (2020). For $Pe_b \ge O(1)$, diffusion is negligible (or at least subdominant) at all scales and our results are consistent with those of Chini et al. (2022) for strongly stratified geophysical turbulence at $Pr = O(1)$. Finally, we have identified a new regime for $\alpha \ll Pe_b \ll 1$, in which slow, large scales are diffusive while fast, small scales are not. We conclude by presenting a map of parameter space that clearly indicates the transitions between isotropic turbulence, non-diffusive stratified turbulence, diffusive stratified turbulence and viscously-dominated flows, and by proposing parameterisations of the buoyancy flux, mixing efficiency and turbulent diffusion coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06424v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kasturi Shah, Gregory P. Chini, Colm-cille P. Caulfield, Pascale Garaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polytropic stellar structure in 5$\mathcal{D}$ Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03026v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polytropic stars are useful tools for learning about stellar structure without the complexity of comprehensive stellar models. These models rely on a certain power-law correlation between the star's pressure and density. This paper proposes a polytropic star model to investigate some new features in the context of $5\mathcal{D}$ Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet (EGB) gravity using the Finch-Skea {\em ansatz} [{\em M. R. Finch and J. E. Skea, Classical and Quantum Gravity 6, 467 (1989)}]. Analytical results are better described by graphical representations of the physical parameters for various values of the Gauss-Bonnet coupling constant $\alpha$. The solution for a specific compact object, EXO 1785-248, with radius $\mathfrak{R} = 8.849_{-0.04}^{+0.04}$ km and mass $\mathcal{M} = 1.3 \pm 0.02~\mathcal{M}_{\odot}$, is shown here. We analyze the essential physical attributes of the star, which reveal the influence of the coupling parameter $\alpha$ on the values of the parameters. Ultimately, we conclude that our current model is realistic because it satisfies all the physical criteria for an acceptable model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03026v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cjph.2024.05.037</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Journal of Physics 90, 1125-1142 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Akashdip Karmakar, Ujjal Debnath, Pramit Rej</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superluminous supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12302v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superluminous supernovae (SLSNe) are a population of supernovae (SNe) whose peak luminosities are much larger than those of canonical SNe. Although SLSNe were simply defined by their peak luminosity at first, it is currently recognized that they show rich spectroscopic diversities including hydrogen-poor (Type I) and hydrogen-rich (Type II) subtypes. The exact mechanisms making SLSNe luminous are still not fully understood, but there are mainly four major suggested luminosity sources (radioactive decay of 56Ni, circumstellar interaction, magnetar spin-down, and fallback accretion). We provide an overview of observational properties of SLSNe and major theoretical models for them. Future transient surveys are expected to discover SLSNe at high redshifts which will provide a critical information in revealing their nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12302v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi J. Moriya</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
