<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 01:51:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Applications of Atomic Data to Studies of the Sun</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Sun is a standard reference object for Astrophysics and also a fascinating subject of study in its own right. X-ray and extreme ultraviolet movies of the Sun's atmosphere show an extraordinary diversity of plasma phenomena, from barely visible bursts and jets to coronal mass ejections that impact a large portion of the solar surface. The processes that produce these phenomena, heat the corona and power the solar wind remain actively studied and accurate atomic data are essential for interpreting observations and making model predictions. For the Sun's interior intense effort is focused on resolving the "solar problem," (a discrepancy between solar interior models and helioseismology measurements) and atomic data are central to both element abundance measurements and interior physics such as opacity and nuclear reaction rates. In this article, topics within solar interior and solar atmosphere physics are discussed and the role of atomic data described. Areas of active research are highlighted and specific atomic data needs are identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09166v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter R. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical simulations of temperature anisotropy instabilities stimulated by suprathermal protons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The new in situ measurements of the Solar Orbiter mission contribute to the knowledge of the suprathermal populations in the solar wind, especially of ions and protons whose characterization, although still in the early phase, seems to suggest a major involvement in the interaction with plasma wave fluctuations. Recent studies point to the stimulating effect of suprathermal populations on temperature anisotropy instabilities in the case of electrons already being demonstrated in theory and numerical simulations. Here, we investigate anisotropic protons, addressing the electromagnetic ion-cyclotron (EMIC) and the proton firehose (PFH) instabilities. Suprathermal populations enhance the high-energy tails of the Kappa velocity (or energy) distributions measured in situ, enabling characterization by contrasting to the quasi-thermal population in the low-energy (bi-)Maxwellian core. We use hybrid simulations to investigate the two instabilities (with ions or protons as particles and electrons as fluid) for various configurations relevant to the solar wind and terrestrial magnetosphere. The new simulation results confirm the linear theory and its predictions. In the presence of suprathermal protons, the wave fluctuations reach increased energy density levels for both instabilities and cause faster and/or deeper relaxation of temperature anisotropy. The magnitude of suprathermal effects also depends on each instability's specific (initial) parametric regimes. These results further strengthen the belief that wave-particle interactions govern space plasmas. These provide valuable clues for understanding their dynamics, particularly the involvement of suprathermal particles behind the quasi-stationary non-equilibrium states reported by in situ observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09180v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202348780</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astronomy and Astrophysics 2014</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. M. Shaaban, R. A. Lopez, M. Lazar, S. Poedts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying different types of solar wind plasma with uncertainty estimations using machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decades of in-situ solar wind measurements have clearly established the variation of solar wind physical parameters. These variable parameters have been used to classify the solar wind magnetized plasma into different types leading to several classification schemes being developed. These classification schemes, while useful for understanding the solar wind originating processes at the Sun and early detection of space weather events, have left open questions regarding which physical parameters are most useful for classification and how recent advances in our understanding of solar wind transients impact classification. In this work, we use neural networks trained with different solar wind magnetic and plasma characteristics to automatically classify the solar wind in coronal hole, streamer belt, sector reversal and solar transients such as coronal mass ejections comprised of both magnetic obstacles and sheaths. Furthermore, our work demonstrates how probabilistic neural networks can enhance the classification by including a measure of prediction uncertainty. Our work also provides a ranking of the parameters that lead to an improved classification scheme with ~96% accuracy. Our new scheme paves the way for incorporating uncertainty estimates into space weather forecasting with the potential to be implemented on real-time solar wind data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09230v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21203/rs.3.rs-4743958/v1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tom Narock, Sanchita Pal, Aryana Arsham, Ayris Narock, Teresa Nieves-Chinchilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of two totally eclipsing B-type binaries with extremely low mass ratios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The detection of O- and B-type stars with extremely low-mass companions is very important for understanding the formation and evolution of binary stars. However, their finding remains a challenge because the low-mass components in such systems contribute such small flux to the total. During the searching for pulsations among O- and B-type stars by using the TESS data, we found two short-period and B-type (B9) eclipsing binaries with orbital periods of 1.61613 and 2.37857 days. Photometric solutions of the two close binaries were derived by analyzing the TESS light curves with the W-D method. It is discovered that both of them are detached binaries with extremely low mass ratios of 0.067(2) for TIC 260342097 and 0.140(3) for TIC 209148631, respectively. The determined mass ratio indicates that TIC 260342097 is one of the lowest mass ratios among known B-type binary systems. We showed that the two systems have total eclipses with a broad and flat secondary minimum, suggesting that the photometric parameters could be derived reliably. The absolute parameters of the two binaries are estimated and it is found that the secondary components in the two systems are over-luminous and over-size when compared with the normal low-mass and cool main-sequence (MS) stars. These findings may imply that the two systems are composed of a B-type MS primary and a cool pre-MS secondary with orbital periods shorter than 2.5 days. They are valuable targets to test theories of binary star formation and evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09246v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad643b</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Linfeng Chang, Shengbang Qian, Lei Zang, Fuxing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Envelopes, Gamma Rays, and Sudden Spectral Changes of Novae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A common envelope (CE) is proposed as the origin of the early postoutburst spectra of many novae. A simple model is proposed to explain the properties of the CE based on the emission line strengths and an assumed density distribution. Rapid changes in the spectrum during postoutburst decline are suggested as possible evidence for a CE. Time-resolved spectra from the ARAS group show sudden spectral shifts that are correlated with detected gamma ray emission, suggestive of its possible origin on the WD that produces a change in condition within the CE. Episodic mass loss, formation of thea transient heavy element absorption systems, and dissipation of the CE may be triggered by gamma ray emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09565v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Williams, Russell Ryan, Richard Rudy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible anti-correlations between pulsation amplitudes and the disk growth of Be stars in giant-outbursting Be X-ray binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanism of X-ray outbursts in Be X-ray binaries remains a mystery, and understanding their circumstellar disks is crucial for a solution of the mass-transfer problem. In particular, it is important to identify the Be star activities (e.g., pulsations) that cause mass ejection and, hence, disk formation. Therefore, we investigated the relationship between optical flux oscillations and the infrared (IR) excess in a sample of five Be X-ray binaries. Applying the Lomb-Scargle technique to high-cadence optical light curves from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), we detected several significant oscillation modes in the 3 to 24 hour period range for each source. We also measured the IR excess (a proxy for disk growth) of those five sources, using J-band light curves from Palomar Gattini-IR. In four of the five sources, we found anti-correlations between the IR excess and the amplitude of the main flux oscillation modes. This result is inconsistent with the conventional idea that non-radial pulsations drive mass ejections. We propose an alternative scenario where internal temperature variations in the Be star cause transitions between pulsation-active and mass-ejection-active states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09581v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masafumi Niwano, Michael M. Fausnaugh, Ryan M. Lau, Kishalay De, Roberto Soria, George R. Ricker, Roland Vanderspek, Michael C. B. Ashley, Nicholas Earley, Matthew J. Hankins, Mansi M. Kasliwal, Anna M. Moore, Jamie Soon, Tony Travouillon, Mahito Sasada, Ichiro Takahashi, Yoichi Yatsu, Nobuyuki Kawai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nature of elongated granulations and stretched dark lanes in a newly emerging flux region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we explore the elongated granulations and stretched dark lanes within the emerging anti-Hale active region NOAA 12720. Utilizing high-resolution observations from the New Vacuum Solar Telescope, we discern a prevalence of elongated granules and stretched dark lanes associated with the emergence of new magnetic flux positioned between two primary opposing magnetic polarities. These elongated granulations and stretched dark lanes exhibit an alignment of strong transverse fields and a significant inclination angle. The endpoints of these features separate from each other, with their midpoints predominantly characterized by blue-shifted signals in the photosphere. This suggests a close association between elongated granules and stretched dark lanes with the newly emerging flux. Additionally, we find that the stretched dark lanes display a more pronounced correlation with strong blue shifts and photospheric transverse magnetic fields compared to the elongated granulations. The transverse magnetic field within these stretched dark lanes reaches magnitudes of approximately 300 to 400 G, and the inclination angle demonstrates an "arch-like" pattern along the trajectory of the stretched dark lane. Based on these observed characteristics, we infer the presence of an emerging flux tube with an "arch-like" shape situated along the stretched dark lane. Consequently, we conclude that the stretched dark lanes likely represent manifestations of the emerging flux tube, while the elongated granulations may correspond to the gaps between the emerging flux tubes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09688v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jincheng Wang, Xiaoli Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A possible explanation of W-type phenomena in V694 Peg</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Three sets of complete multi-color light curves of V694 Peg observed in 2013, 2015 and 2019 were presented and analyzed. Our photometric solutions show that this system is an A-type shallow contact binary in 2013 and 2015, while it converted to a W-type one in 2019. A large cool spot on the component of this binary could explain the conversion, implying the W-type phenomena may be caused by magnetic activity of the components. We have collected available data of this binary and calculated 505 times of light minimum, which span 17 years. The orbital period investigation based on these timings shows there is a long-term period increase at a rate of $dP/dt$ = 4.3($\pm$ 0.3)$\times$ 10$^{-9}$ d yr$^{-1}$ superposed on a periodic variation with a period of 11.81($\pm$ 0.06) years. The cyclic orbital variation may be the result of magnetic activity cycles or the existence of a third body. Till now, only 8 transformed systems including V694 Peg have been reported. Compared with other converting contact systems between A-type and W-type, V694 Peg is recorded as the shortest-period one. All of these converting systems are late-type (later than F7) contact binaries with O'Connell effect and show cyclic period variation, which indicates that magnetic activity may be the reason for the conversion between the two types of contact binaries. For investigating the nature of A-type and W-type phenomena, the discovery of more converting contact binaries is essential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09705v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hu-Shan Xu, Li-Ying Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photometric and Spectroscopic analysis of eight totally eclipsing contact binaries with small mass ratios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper selected eight totally eclipsing contact binaries for photometric and spectroscopic studies, spectral data were analyzed by ULySS, and photometric data were analyzed using PHOEBE through MCMC sampling. We used two methods to calculate the initial values for running MCMC: one method is a new approach proposed by ourselves to model light curves without spots, while the other method is the genetic algorithm (GA) which can determine physical parameters with spot. Due to the results, these eight targets are all small mass ratio contact binary stars with a mass ratio below 0.25. There are four systems exhibiting O'Connell effect. By adding a dark spot on the primary component, the ideal fitting can be obtained. Meanwhile, it was found that two systems are shallow contact binaries, while the remaining six are moderate contact binaries. An O-C analysis of the eight eclipsing binary stars revealed that seven of them exhibit long-term changes. Four of them display a long-term decreasing trend, while the other three show a long-term increasing trend, and two targets exhibit periodic variations. The decrease in period may be caused by the transfer of matter from the more massive component to the less massive component, while the increase in period may be caused by the transfer of matter from the less massive component to the more massive component. The absolute physical parameters, orbital angular momentum, initial masses, and ages of these eight systems were calculated. Additionally, their mass-luminosity and mass-radius distributions were analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09743v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Heng Wang, Kai Li, Ya-Ni Guo, Jing-Yi Wang, Xiang Gao, Xing Gao, Guo-You Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass-loss Rate of Highly Evolved Stars in the Magellanic Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Asymptotic giant branch stars (AGBs) and red supergiant stars (RSGs) exhibit significant mass loss phenomena and are considered important sources of interstellar dust. In this work, we employed an uniform method of spectral energy distribution fitting to analyze a large, and hence statistically significant, sample of approximately 40,000 RSGs and AGBs in the Magellanic Clouds (MCs), providing a new catalog of evolved stars that includes stellar parameters and dust properties. Our results reveal that the total dust-production rate (DPR) of the Large Magellanic Cloud is approximately $9.69\times10^{-6}\,\rm{M_{\odot }\, yr^{-1}}$, while it is around $1.75\times10^{-6}\,\rm{M_{\odot }\,yr^{-1}}$ for the Small Magellanic Cloud, with a few stars significantly contributing to the total DPR. No significant differences were observed in the contributions to DPR from carbon-rich and oxygen-rich (O-rich) evolved stars in the MCs. We explored the relations between stellar parameters (luminosity, infrared color, period, amplitude) and mass-loss rate (MLR) for evolved stars. A prominent turning point at $\log{(L/L_{\odot})} \approx 4.4$ appears in the luminosity-MLR diagram of RSGs, potentially related to the mass-loss mechanism of RSGs. The luminosity-MLR relation of AGBs is highly scattered. The DPR of AGBs shows a clear change with pulsation period and amplitude, with DPR exhibiting a drastic increase at pulsation periods of approximately 300 days and I-band amplitudes greater than 0.5 mag. Metallicity has some impact on the DPR of O-rich stars, with lower metallicity seeming to result in lower mean DPR and a higher proportion of optically thin stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09751v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Wen, Ming Yang, Jian Gao, Bingqiu Chen, Yi Ren, Biwei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Grand Minima in Solar Activity: Confronting Observations with Dynamo Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The grand minimum in the Sun's activity is a distinctive mode characterized by a magnetic lull that almost completely lacks the emergence of sunspots on the solar surface for an extended duration. The factors driving this transition of an otherwise magnetically active star into a quiescent phase, the processes occurring within the solar interior and across the heliosphere during this period, and the mechanisms leading to the eventual resurgence of surface magnetic activity remain enigmatic. However, there have been sustained efforts in the past few decades to unravel these mysteries by employing a combination of observation, reconstruction and simulation of solar magnetic variability. Here, we summarize recent research on the solar grand minimum and highlight some outstanding challenges - both intellectual and practical - that necessitate further investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09775v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chitradeep Saha, Dibyendu Nandy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shape of convection in 2D and 3D global simulations of stellar interiors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Theoretical descriptions of convective overshooting often rely on a one-dimensional parameterization of the flow called the filling factor for convection. Several definitions of the filling factor have been developed, based on: (1) the percentage of the volume, (2) the mass flux, and (3) the convective flux that moves through the boundary. We examine these definitions of the filling factor with the goal of establishing their ability to explain differences between 2D and 3D global simulations of stellar interiors that include fully compressible hydrodynamics and realistic microphysics for stars. We study pairs of identical two- and three-dimensional global simulations of stars produced with MUSIC, a fully compressible, time-implicit hydrodynamics code. We examine (1) a $3 M_\odot$ red giant star near the first dredge-up point, (2) a $1 M_\odot$ pre-main-sequence star with a large convection zone, (3) the current sun, and (4) a $20 M_\odot$ main-sequence star with a large convective core. Our calculations of the filling factor based on the volume percentage and the mass flux indicate asymmetrical convection near the surface for each star with an outer convection zone. However, near the convective boundary, convective flows achieve inward-outward symmetry; for 2D and 3D simulations, these filling factors are indistinguishable. A filling factor based on the convective flux is contaminated by boundary-layer-like flows, making theoretical interpretation difficult. We present two new alternatives to these standard definitions, which compare flows at two different radial points. The first is the penetration parameter of Anders et al. (2022). The second is a new statistic, the plume interaction parameter. We demonstrate that both of these parameters capture systematic differences between 2D and 3D simulations around the convective boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09815v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. -G. Dethero, J. Pratt, D. G. Vlaykov, I. Baraffe, T. Guillet, T. Goffrey, A. Le Saux, A. Morison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Current State of the Controversy over Screening in Nuclear Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A controversy about the possibility of dynamic effects in nuclear screening has been around for several decades. On the one hand, there is the claim that there are no dynamic effects, and that the classic Salpeter correction based on static Debye screening is all that is needed for astrophysical applications. The size of the correction is on the order of 5% in typical solar fusion reactions. On the other hand, numerical simulations have shown that there is a dynamical effect, which essentially cancels the Salpeter correction. The results of the numerical simulations were later independently confirmed. The astrophysical community, however, has so far largely ignored the possibility of dynamical screening. The present paper is meant to serve as a reminder of the controversy. Not only does the claim of an absence of a dynamical effect equally warrant an independent confirmation, but there is motivation for further investigation, such as the assessment of current laboratory experiments and a quantitative study of the dynamical effect in case it will turn out to be real.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09826v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Werner D\"appen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the time variability of the Solar Wind using LOFAR pulsar data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-precision pulsar timing is highly dependent on precise and accurate modeling of any effects that impact the data. It was shown that commonly used Solar Wind models do not accurately account for variability in the amplitude of the Solar wind on both short and long time scales. In this study, we test and validate a new, cutting-edge Solar wind modeling method included in the \texttt{enterprise} software suite through extended simulations, and we apply it to investigate temporal variability in LOFAR data. Our model testing scheme in itself provides an invaluable asset for pulsar timing array (PTA) experiments. As improperly accounting for the solar wind signature in pulsar data can induce false-positive signals, it is of fundamental importance to include in any such investigations. We employ a Bayesian approach utilizing a continuously varying Gaussian process to model the solar wind referred to as Solar Wind Gaussian Process (SWGP). We conduct noise analysis on eight pulsars from the LOFAR dataset with most pulsars having a timespan of $\sim 11$ years encompassing one full solar activity cycle. Our analysis reveals a strong correlation between the electron density at 1 AU and the ecliptic latitude (ELAT) of the pulsar. Pulsars with $|ELAT|&lt; 3^{\circ}$ exhibit significantly higher average electron densities. We observe distinct temporal patterns in electron densities in different pulsars. In particular, pulsars within $|ELAT|&lt; 3^{\circ}$ exhibit similar temporal variations, while the electron densities of those outside this range correlate with the solar activity cycle. The continuous variability in electron density offered in this model represents a substantial improvement over previous models, which assume a single value for piece-wise bins of time. This advancement holds promise for solar wind modeling in future International Pulsar Timing Array data combinations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09838v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. C. Susarla, A. Chalumeau, C. Tiburzi, E. F. Keane, J. P. W. Verbiest, J. S. Hazboun, M. A. Krishnakumar, F. Iraci, G. M. Shaifullah, A. Golden, A. S. Bak Nielsen, J. Donner, J. M. Grie{\ss}meier, M. J. Keith, S. Os{\l}owski, N. K. Porayko, M. Serylak, J. M. Anderson, M. Br\"uggen, B. Ciardi, R. J. Dettmar, M. Hoeft, J. K\"unsem\"oller, D. Schwarz, C. Vocks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TV Mon - post mass transfer Algol type binary with $\delta$ Scuti pulsations in primary component</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a study of the detached eclipsing binary TV~Mon using spectra from the LAMOST medium-resolution survey and ASAS-SN, CoRoT photometry. We applied multiple-epochs spectral fitting to derive RV and spectral parameters. The analysis of eclipses in CoRoT data told us relative sizes of the stellar components and almost edge-on circular orbit. Combining spectral and photometrical solution we estimated masses and radii of the components: $M_{A,B}=2.063\pm0.033,~0.218\pm0.004~M_\odot$, $R_{A,B}=2.427\pm0.014,~2.901\pm0.016~R_\odot$. SED analysis and Gaia parallax allowed us to get estimation of temperatures $T_{A,B}=7624^{+194}_{-174},~5184^{+130}_{-123}$ K and distance $d=907\pm11$ pc. We identified three $\delta$ Scuti type pulsation frequencies in primary component, while we also suspect TV~Mon having a long period variability with period $P_{\rm long}\sim128$ days and spot activity in secondary component. This system experienced intensive mass transfer and mass ratio reversal in the past, currently showing no signs of mass transfer in the spectra. The low mass component will lose its outer envelope and shrink to the helium white dwarf, which mass and orbital period are in good agreement with evolutionary models predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09902v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Kovalev, Zhenwei Li, Jianping Xiong, Azizbek Matekov, Zhang Bo, Xuefei Chen, Zhanwen Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the asteroseismic estimates of stellar radii with surface brightness-colour relations and Gaia DR3 parallaxes. Red giants and red clump stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compared stellar radii derived from asteroseismic scaling relations with those estimated using two independent surface brightness-colour relations (SBCRs) and Gaia DR3 parallaxes. We cross-matched asteroseismic and astrometric data for over 6,400 RGB and RC stars from the APO-K2 catalogue with the TESS Input Catalogue v8.2 to obtain precise V band magnitudes and E(B-V) colour excesses. We then adopted two different SBCRs from the literature to derive stellar radius estimates, denoted as $R^a$ and $R^b$, respectively. We analysed the ratio of these SBCR-derived radii to the asteroseismic radius estimates, $R$, provided in the APO-K2 catalogue. Both SBCRs exhibited good agreement with asteroseismic radius estimates. On average, $R^a$ was overestimated by 1.2% with respect to $R$, while $R^b$ was underestimated by 2.5%. For stars larger than 20 $R_{\odot}$, SBCR radii are systematically lower than asteroseismic ones. The agreement with asteroseismic radii shows a strong dependence on the parallax. The dispersion is halved for stars with a parallax greater than 2.5 mas. In this subsample, $R^b$ showed perfect agreement with $R$, while $R^a$ remained slightly overestimated by 3%. A trend with [Fe/H] of 4% to 6% per dex was found. For stars less massive than about 0.95 $M_{\odot}$, SBCR radii were significantly higher than asteroseismic ones, by about 6%. This overestimation correlated with the presence of extended helium cores in these stars' structures relative to their envelopes. Furthermore, radius ratios showed a dichotomous behaviour at higher masses, mainly due to the presence of several RC stars with SBCR radii significantly lower with respect to asteroseismology. This behaviour originates from a different response of asteroseismic scaling relations and SBCR to [$\alpha$/Fe] abundance ratios for massive stars, both in RGB and RC phases, which is reported here for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10050v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Valle, M. Dell'Omodarme, P. G. Prada Moroni, S. Degl'Innocenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photometry and spectroscopy of a deep Algol-like minimum of WW Vul in 2016</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report analysis of photometry and spectroscopy of a deep Algol-like minimum of the pre-main-sequence star WW Vul in July and August 2016. This revealed substantial reddening due to absorption by circumstellar material. After dereddening, our spectra of WW Vul were consistent with spectral type A3V throughout the event. H{\alpha} is normally in emission in WW Vul. During the minimum, H{\alpha} emission dropped by ~30% and FWHM of the H{\alpha} line reduced by ~15%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10073v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Boyd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling Pulsating Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulsating stars have been studied using non-linear hydrodynamic codes since the pioneering work of Robert Christy in the 1960s. Modern codes include improvements such as allowing for convection but there is a penalty in terms of computation speed and for some stars convection is not significant. In this work a new version of the Christy program has been developed which can run hundreds of star models to convergence in a day or two of computer time. This allows overall patterns of behaviour to be studied and suitable models for individual case stars to be identified. The star SZ Lyn was chosen as a test case for the model. Light curve and radial velocity data were obtained for this star using amateur equipment. A run of 625 parameter sets (mass, luminosity, effective temperature and hydrogen fraction) identified the best fit parameters for SZ Lyn. Model results show a good fit to the observed data in terms of amplitude, period and shape of the light and velocity curves. In this paper we report on the model developed by PM and radial velocity observations by RL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10116v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Masding, Robin Leadbeater</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying activity induced RV periodicities and correlations using Central Line Moments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The radial velocity (RV) method of exoplanet detection requires mitigation of nuisance signals arising from stellar activity. Using analytic cool and facular spot models, we explore the use of central line moments (CLMs) for recovering and monitoring rotation induced RV variability. Different spot distribution patterns, photosphere-spot contrast ratios and the presence or absence of the convective blueshift lead to differences in CLM signals between M dwarfs and G dwarfs. Harmonics of the rotation period are often recovered with the highest power in standard periodogram analyses. By contrast, we show the true stellar rotation may be more reliably recovered with string length minimisation. For solar minimum activity levels, recovery of the stellar rotation signal from CLMs is found to require unfeasibly high signal-to-noise observations. The stellar rotation period can be recovered at solar maximum activity levels from CLMs for reasonable cross-correlation function (CCF) signal-to-noise ratios $&gt; 1000 - 5000$. The CLMs can be used to recover and monitor stellar activity through their mutual correlations and correlations with RV and bisector inverse span. The skewness of a CCF, a measure of asymmetry, is described by the third CLM, $M_3$. Our noise-free simulations indicate the linear RV vs $M_3$ correlation is up to 10 per cent higher than the RV vs bisector inverse span correlation. We find a corresponding $\sim 5$ per cent increase in linear correlation for CARMENES observations of the M star, AU Mic. We also assess the effectiveness of the time derivative of the second CLM, $M_2$, for monitoring stellar activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10306v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. R. Barnes, S. V. Jeffers, C. A. Haswell, M. Damasso, F. Del Sordo, F. Liebing, M. Perger, G. Anglada-Escud\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Model of the C IV $\lambda\lambda$ 1548, 1550 Doublet Line in T Tauri Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The C IV doublet in the UV has long been associated with accretion in T Tauri stars. However, it is still unclear where and how the lines are formed. Here, we present a new C IV line model based on the currently available accretion shock and accretion flow models. We assume axisymmetric, dipolar accretion flows with different energy fluxes and calculate the properties of the accretion shock. We use Cloudy to obtain the carbon level populations and calculate the emerging line profiles assuming a plane-parallel geometry near the shock. Our model generally reproduces the intensities and shapes of the C IV emission lines observed from T Tauri stars. We find that the narrow component is optically thin and originates in the postshock, while the broad component is optically thick and emerges from the preshock. We apply our model to seven T Tauri stars from the Hubble Ultraviolet Legacy Library of Young Stars as Essential Standards Director's Discretionary program (ULLYSES), for which consistently determined accretion shock properties are available. We can reproduce the observations of four stars, finding that the accretion flows are carbon-depleted. We also find that the chromospheric emission accounts for less than 10 percent of the observed C IV line flux in accreting T Tauri stars. This work paves the way toward a better understanding of hot line formation and provides a potential probe of abundances in the inner disk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10361v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanawuth Thanathibodee, Connor Robinson, Nuria Calvet, Catherine Espaillat, Caeley Pittman, Nicole Arulanantham, Kevin France, Hans Moritz G\"unther, Seok-Jun Chang, P. Christian Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the formation height of low-corona and chromospheric channels of the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) on board the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The multi-wavelength data from the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) is extensively used in studying the physics of the Sun and its atmosphere. In this study, we estimate the formation heights of low-corona and chromospheric channels of the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) over the atmospheres of sunspot umbrae during the quiet condition period within 20 different active regions. The upward propagating slow magnetoacoustic waves (slow MAWs) of 3-min period, which are perpetually present in sunspots, are utilized for this purpose. Employing a cross-correlation technique, the most frequent time lag between different channel pairs is measured. By combining this information with the local sound speed obtained from the characteristic formation temperatures of individual channels, we estimate the respective formation heights. The median values of formation heights obtained across all active regions in our sample are 356, 368, 858, 1180, and 1470 km, respectively, for the AIA 1600 {\AA}, 1700 {\AA}, 304 {\AA}, 131 {\AA}, and 171 {\AA} channels. The corresponding ranges in the formation heights are 247 $\--$ 453, 260 $\--$ 468, 575 $\--$ 1155, 709 $\--$ 1937, and 909 $\--$ 2585 km, respectively. These values are measured with respect to the HMI continuum. We find the formation height of UV channels is quite stable (between 250 $\--$ 500 km) and displays only a marginal difference between the AIA 1600 {\AA} and 1700 {\AA} during quiet conditions. On the other hand, the formation height of coronal channels is quite variable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10451v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Sanjay, S. Krishna Prasad, R. Erdelyi, M. B. Korsos, D. Banerjee, P. S. Rawat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino flux sensitivity to the next galactic core-collapse supernova in COSINUS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While neutrinos are often treated as a background for many dark matter experiments, these particles offer a new avenue for physics: the detection of core-collapse supernovae. Supernovae are extremely energetic, violent and complex events that mark the death of massive stars. During their collapse stars emit a large number of neutrinos in a short burst. These neutrinos carry 99\% of the emitted energy which makes their detection fundamental in understanding supernovae. This paper illustrates how COSINUS (Cryogenic Observatory for SIgnatures seen in Next-generation Underground Searches), a sodium iodide (NaI) based dark matter search, will be sensitive to the next galactic core-collapse supernova. The experiment is composed of two separate detectors which will be sensitive to far and nearby supernovae. The inner core of the experiment will consist of NaI crystals operating as scintillating calorimeters, mainly sensitive to the Coherent Elastic Scattering of Neutrinos (CE$\nu$NS) against the Na and I nuclei. The low mass of the cryogenic detectors gives the experiment a sensitivity to close supernovae below 1kpc without pileup. They will see up to hundreds of CE$\nu$NS events from a supernova happening at 200pc. The crystals reside at the center of a cylindrical 230T water tank, instrumented with 30 photomultipliers. This tank acts as a passive and active shield able to detect the Cherenkov radiation induced by impinging charged particles from ambient and cosmogenic radioactivity. A supernova near the Milky Way Center (10kpc) will be easily detected inducing $\sim$60 measurable events, and the water tank will have a 3$\sigma$ sensitivity to supernovae up to 22kpc, seeing $\sim$10 events. This paper shows how, even without dedicated optimization, modern dark matter experiments will also play their part in the multi-messenger effort to detect the next galactic core-collapse supernova.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09109v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gode Angloher, Mukund Bharadwaj, Mariano Cababie, Ivan Colantoni, Ioan Dafinei, Alessio Ludovico De Santis, Natalia Di Marco, Leonie Einfalt, Francesco Ferella, Fernando Ferroni, Stephan Fichtinger, Adriano Filipponi, Torsten Frank, Markus Friedl, Zengwei Ge, Matti Heikinheimo, Maximilian Hughes, Katri Huitu, Moritz Kellermann, Rituparna Maji, Michele Mancuso, Lorenzo Pagnanini, Federica Petricca, Stefano Pirro, Franz Pr\"obst, Gianni Profeta, Andrei Puiu, Florian Reindl, Karoline Sch\"affner, Jochen Schieck, Philipp Schreiner, Christoph Schwertner, Kumrie Shera, Martin Stahlberg, Alex Stendhal, Matthew Stukel, Cesare Tresca, Felix Wagner, Shihai Yue, Vanessa Zema, Yong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Initial-Mass Function via Stellar Transients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09118v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The stellar initial-mass function (IMF) represents a fundamental quantity in astrophysics and cosmology, describing the mass distribution of stars from low to very-high masses. It is intimately linked to a wide variety of topics, including stellar and binary evolution, galaxy evolution, chemical enrichment, and cosmological reionization. Nonetheless, the IMF still remains highly uncertain. In this work, we aim at determining the IMF with a novel approach based on the observed rates of transients of stellar origin. We parametrize the IMF with a simple, but flexible, Larson shape, and insert it into a parametric model for the cosmic UV luminosity density, local stellar mass density, type Ia supernova (SN Ia), core-collapse supernova (CCSN), and long gamma-ray burst (LGRB) rates as function of redshift. We constrain our free parameters by matching the model predictions to a set of empirical determinations for the corresponding quantities, via a Bayesian Markov-Chain Monte Carlo method. Remarkably, we are able to provide an independent IMF determination, with characteristic mass $m_c=0.10^{+0.24}_{-0.08}\:M_{\odot}$, and high-mass slope $\xi=-2.53^{+0.24}_{-0.27}$, that is in accordance with the widely-used IMF parameterizations (e.g. Salpeter, Kroupa, Chabrier). Moreover, the adoption of an up-to-date recipe for the cosmic metallicity evolution, allows us to constrain the maximum metallicity of LGRB progenitors to $Z_{max}=0.12^{+0.29}_{-0.05}\:Z_{\odot}$. We also find what progenitor fraction actually leads to SN Ia or LGRB emission, put constraints on the CCSN and LGRB progenitor mass ranges, and test the IMF universality. These results show the potential of this kind of approach for studying the IMF, its putative evolution with galactic environment and cosmic history, and the properties of SN Ia, CCSN and LGRB progenitors, especially considering the wealth of data incoming in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09118v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Gabrielli, Lumen Boco, Giancarlo Ghirlanda, Om Sharan Salafia, Ruben Salvaterra, Mario Spera, Andrea Lapi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic study of the Orion Complex: Analysing the young stellar clusters from big and small structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09206v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we analysed young stellar clusters with spatial and kinematic coherence in the Orion star-forming complex. For this study, we selected a sample of pre-main sequence candidates using parallaxes, proper motions and positions on the colour-magnitude diagram. After applying a hierarchical clustering algorithm in the 5D parameter space provided by Gaia DR3, we divided the recovered clusters into two regimes: Big Structures and Small Structures, defined by the number of detected stars per cluster. In the first regime, we found 13 stellar groups distributed along the declination axis in the regions where there is a high density of stars. In the second regime, we recovered 34 clusters classified into two types: 14 as small groups completely independent from the larger structures, including four candidates of new clusters, and 12 classified as sub-structures embedded within five larger clusters. Additionally, radial velocity data from APOGEE-2 and GALAH DR3 was included to study the phase space in some regions of the Orion complex. From the Big Structure regime, we found evidence of a general expansion in the Orion OB1 association over a common centre, giving a clue about the dynamical effects the region is undergoing. Likewise, in the Small Structure regime, the projected kinematics shows the ballistic expansion in the $\lambda$ Orionis association and the detection of likely events of clusters' close encounters in the OB1 association.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09206v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio S\'anchez-Sanju\'an, Jes\'us Hern\'andez, \'Angeles P\'erez-Villegas, Carlos Rom\'an-Z\'u\~niga, Luis Aguilar, Javier Ballesteros-Paredes, Andrea Bonilla-Barroso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio calculation of the $^3$He$(\alpha,\gamma)^7$Be astrophysical S factor with chiral two- and three-nucleon forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $^3$He$(\alpha,\gamma)^7$Be radiative capture reaction plays a key role in the creation of elements in stars as well as in the production of solar neutrinos, the observation of which is one of the main tools to study the properties of our sun. Since accurate experimental measurements of this fusion cross section at solar energies are difficult due to the strong Coulomb repulsion between the reactants, the onus falls on theory to provide a robust means for extrapolating from the region where experimental data is available down to the desired astrophysical regime. We present the first microscopic calculations of $^3$He$(\alpha,\gamma)^7$Be with explicit inclusion of three-nucleon forces. Our prediction of the astrophysical $S$ factor qualitatively agrees with experimental data. We further incorporate experimental bound-state and scattering information in our calculation to arrive at a more quantitative description. This process reveals that our current model lacks sufficient repulsion in the $1/2^+$ channel of our model space to simultaneously reproduce elastic-scattering data. This deficit suggests that $^3$He$(\alpha,\gamma)^7$Be probes aspects of the nuclear force that are not currently well-constrained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09515v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. C. Atkinson, K. Kravvaris, S. Quaglioni, P. Navr\'atil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Evolution of Four Old Galactic Open Clusters traced by their constituent stars with \textit{Gaia} DR3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the evolutionary stages of four open clusters, Berkeley 39, Collinder 261, NGC 6819, and NGC 7789, of ages ranging from 1.6 -- 6 Gyr. These clusters have previously been classified into dynamically young and intermediate age groups based on the segregation level of BSS with respect to red giant branch stars and main sequence stars, respectively. We identify members of these four clusters using the ML-MOC algorithm on Gaia DR3 data. To examine the relative segregation of cluster members of different evolutionary stages, we utilize cumulative radial distributions, proper motion distributions, and spatial distributions in galactocentric coordinates. Our analysis shows that Berkeley 39 and NGC 6819 exhibit moderate signs of population-wise segregation from evolved to less-evolved members. NGC 7789 shows signs of mass segregation only in the cumulative radial distributions. On the other hand, Collinder 261 exhibits high segregation of BSS in the cumulative radial distribution, while other populations show the same level of segregation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10186v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shanmugha Balan, Khushboo K Rao, Kaushar Vaidya, Manan Agarwal, Souradeep Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D ISM structure challenges the Serkowski relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Serkowski relation is the cornerstone of studies of starlight polarization as a function of wavelength. Although empirical, its extensive use since its inception to describe polarization induced by interstellar dust has elevated the relation to the status of an indisputable "law", serving as the benchmark for validating interstellar dust grain models. We revisit the effects of the 3D structure of the interstellar medium (ISM) on the wavelength dependence of interstellar polarization. We use analytical models to show how the wavelength dependence of both the polarization fraction and direction is affected by the presence of multiple clouds along the line of sight (LOS), accounting for recent developments in dust distribution modelling and utilizing an expanded archive of stellar polarization measurements. We highlight concrete examples of stars whose polarization profiles are severely affected by LOS variations of the dust grain and magnetic field properties, and we provide a recipe to accurately fit multiple cloud Serkowski models to such cases. We present, for the first time, compelling observational evidence that the 3D structure of the magnetized ISM often results to the violation of the Serkowski relation. We show that 3D effects impact interstellar cloud parameters derived from Serkowski fits. In particular, the dust size distribution in single - cloud sightlines may differ from analyses that ignore 3D effects, with important implications for dust modelling in the Galaxy. Our results suggest that multiband stellar polarization measurements offer an independent probe of the LOS variations of the magnetic field, constituting a valuable new tool for the 3D cartography of the ISM. We caution that, unless 3D effects are explicitly accounted for, a poor fit to the Serkowski relation does not, by itself, constitute conclusive evidence that a star is intrinsically polarized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10317v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Mandarakas, Konstantinos Tassis, Raphael Skalidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The James Webb Space Telescope Absolute Flux Calibration. II. Mid-Infrared Instrument Imaging and Coronagraphy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The absolute flux calibration of the Mid-Infrared Instrument Imaging and Coronagraphy is based on observations of multiple stars taken during the first 2.5 years of JWST operations. The observations were designed to ensure that the flux calibration is valid for a range of flux densities, different subarrays, and different types of stars. The flux calibration was measured by combining observed aperture photometry corrected to infinite aperture with predictions based on previous observations and models of stellar atmospheres. A subset of these observations were combined with model point-spread-functions to measure the corrections to infinite aperture. Variations in the calibration factor with time, flux density, background level, type of star, subarray, integration time, rate, and well depth were investigated, and the only significant variations were with time and subarray. Observations of the same star taken approximately every month revealed a modest time-dependent response loss seen mainly at the longest wavelengths. This loss is well characterized by a decaying exponential with a time constant of ~200 days. After correcting for the response loss, the band-dependent scatter around the corrected average (aka repeatability) was found to range from 0.1 to 1.2%. Signals in observations taken with different subarrays can be lower by up to 3.4% compared to FULL frame. After correcting for the time and subarray dependencies, the scatter in the calibration factors measured for individual stars ranges from 1 to 4% depending on the band. The formal uncertainties on the flux calibration averaged for all observations are 0.3 to 1.0%, with longer-wavelength bands generally having larger uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10443v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karl D. Gordon, G. C. Sloan, Macarena Garcia Marin, Mattia Libralato, George Rieke, Jonathan A. Aguilar, Ralph Bohlin, Misty Cracraft, Marjorie Decleir, Andras Gaspar, David R. Law, Alberto Noriega-Crespo, Michael Regan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-ion heating partition in imbalanced solar-wind turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13048v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A likely candidate mechanism to heat the solar corona and solar wind is low-frequency "Alfv\'enic" turbulence sourced by magnetic fluctuations near the solar surface. Depending on its properties, such turbulence can heat different species via different mechanisms, and the comparison of theoretical predictions to observed temperatures, wind speeds, anisotropies, and their variation with heliocentric radius provides a sensitive test of this physics. Here we explore the importance of normalized cross helicity, or imbalance, for controlling solar-wind heating, since it is a key parameter of magnetized turbulence and varies systematically with wind speed and radius. Based on a hybrid-kinetic simulation in which the forcing's imbalance decreases with time -- a crude model for a plasma parcel entrained in the outflowing wind -- we demonstrate how significant changes to the turbulence and heating result from the "helicity barrier" effect. Its dissolution at low imbalance causes its characteristic features -- strong perpendicular ion heating with a steep "transition-range" drop in electromagnetic fluctuation spectra -- to disappear, driving more energy into electrons and parallel ion heat, and halting the emission of ion-scale waves. These predictions seem to agree with a diverse array of solar-wind observations, offering to explain a variety of complex correlations and features within a single theoretical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13048v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad0779</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL, 957 L30 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Squire, Romain Meyrand, Matthew W. Kunz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of an Extremely r-process-enhanced Thin-disk Star with [Eu/H] = +0.78</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Highly r-process-enhanced stars are rare and usually metal-poor ([Fe/H] &lt; - 1.0), and mainly populate the Milky Way halo and dwarf galaxies. This study presents the discovery of a relatively bright (V = 12.72), highly r-process-enhanced (r-II) star ([Eu/Fe] = +1.32, [Ba/Eu] = - 0.95), LAMOST J020632.21 + 494127.9. This star was selected from the Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) medium-resolution (R ~ 7500) spectroscopic survey; follow-up high-resolution (R ~ 25,000) observations were conducted with the High Optical Resolution Spectrograph (HORuS) installed on the Gran Telescopio Canarias (GTC). The stellar parameters (${T_{\rm eff}}$ = 4130 K, $\rm log\,g $ = 1.52, $ \rm[Fe/H] $ = $ - $0.54, $\xi$ = 1.80 $ \rm{km\,{s^{-1}}} $) have been inferred taking into account non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (NLTE) effects. The abundances of [Ce/Fe], [Pr/Fe], and [Nd/Fe] are +0.19, +0.65 and +0.64, respectively, relatively low compared to the Solar r-process pattern normalized to Eu. This star has a high metallicity ([Fe/H] = - 0.54) compared to most other highly r-process-enhanced stars, and has the highest measured abundance ratio of Eu to H ([Eu/H] = +0.78). It is classified as a thin-disk star based on its kinematics, and does not appear to belong to any known stream or dwarf galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11572v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad5ffd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL, 2024, Volume 970, Number 2, L30</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Jin Xie, Jianrong Shi, Hong-Liang Yan, Tian-Yi Chen, Carlos Allende Prieto, Timothy C. Beers, Shuai Liu, Chun-Qian Li, Ming-Yi Ding, Yao-Jia Tang, Ruizhi Zhang, Renjing Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling of eclipsing binary systems with pulsating components and tertiary companions: BF Vel and RR Lep</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive analysis of RR Lep and BF Vel, two short-period semi-detached oscillating Algols (oEA stars), which are shown to be triple systems. Spectral types of their primaries were determined and radial velocities calculated from spectra observed with the Australian National University's 2.3 m telescope and Wide Field Spectrograph. Spectra of the Na I D doublet confirmed the presence of tertiary components which were apparent in the broadening function analyses and, with H_a spectra during primary eclipses, indicated chromospherical activity in their secondaries. Ground-based telescopes were used for observations in several pass bands for photometric analyses. These data were complemented by data from the TESS mission to enable the modelling of the light curves, followed by a detailed analysis of pulsations. Eclipse-timing variation (ETV) analyses of both systems were used to determine the most likely mechanisms modulating the orbital period. We found mass values M1 = 2.9 M_sun and M2 = 0.75 M_sun for the components of RR Lep, and M1 = 1.93 M_sun and M2 = 0.97 M_sun for those of BF Vel. By integrating information from photometry, spectroscopy and ETV analysis, we found that tertiary components revolve around both systems. The primary star of RR Lep pulsates in 36 frequencies, of which five were identified as independent modes, with the dominant one being 32.28 d^-1. The pulsating component of BF Vel oscillates in 37 frequencies, with the frequency 46.73 d^-1 revealed as the only independent mode. For both systems, many frequencies were found to be related to the orbital frequency. Their physical properties were compared with other oEA stars in Mass-Radius and H-R diagrams, and the pulsational properties of their delta Sct components were compared with currently known systems of this type within the orbital-pulsation period and logg-pulsation period diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04359v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexios Liakos, David J. W. Moriarty, Ahmet Erdem, Julian F. West, Phil Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic-gamma-ray emission at low-luminosity from CCO 1E 1207.4-5209 and its Host SNR G296.5+10.0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.10903v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The origin and acceleration mechanisms of energetic particles in the universe remain enigmatic in contemporary astrophysics. Recent efforts have focused on identifying Galactic sources capable of accelerating particles to 1 PeV, known as PeVatrons, and also identifying sources contributing to the spectrum at lower energies. The different morphology of galactic supernova remnants is directly related to the type of stellar explosion and the existence of a possible Compact Central Object (CCO), which possess intense radiative-gravitational fields on their surfaces. These CCOs, due to their strong fields and interactions with surrounding magnetic clouds, are potential candidates for gamma ray production. Through observations of the compact X-ray source 1E 1207.4-5209, located near the remnant G296.5+10.0, and using the enhanced GALPROP code, we analyze the emission of gamma-ray and cosmic-ray production through propagation. Additionally, we calculate the contribution of the G296.5+10.0 source to the overall observed Galactic cosmic-ray flux, taking into account cosmic-ray propagation within the Galaxy, which includes energy losses and particle interactions. Our findings suggest that this setup offers a fertile environment for producing a wide range of cosmic-ray energies at low energy within the Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.10903v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luana N. Padilha, Rita C. dos Anjos, Jaziel G. Coelho, Luiz A. S. Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A high-velocity star recently ejected by an intermediate-mass black hole in M15</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00923v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The existence of intermediate-mass black holes (IMBHs) is crucial for understanding various astrophysical phenomena, yet their existence remains elusive, except for the LIGO-Virgo detection. We report the discovery of a high-velocity star J0731+3717, whose backward trajectory about 21 Myr ago intersects that of globular cluster M15 within the cluster tidal radius. Both its metallicity [Fe/H] and its alpha-to-iron abundance ratio [$\alpha$/Fe] are consistent with those of M15. Furthermore, its location falls right on the fiducial sequence of the cluster M15 on the color-absolute magnitude diagram, suggesting similar ages. These support that J0731+3717 is originally associated with M15 at a confidence level of "seven nines". We find that such a high-velocity star ($V_{\rm ej} = 548^{+6}_{-5}$ km s$^{-1}$) was most likely tidally ejected from as close as one astronomical unit to the center of M15, confirming an IMBH ($\ge 100 M_{\odot}$ with a credibility of 98%) as the exclusive nature of the central unseen mass proposed previously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00923v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Huang (UCAS/NAOC), Qingzheng Li (YNAO/UCAS), Jifeng Liu (NAOC), Xiaobo Dong (YNAO), Huawei Zhang (PKU), Youjun Lu (NAOC), Cuihua Du (UCAS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The K2-24 planetary system revisited by CHEOPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02995v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: K2-24 is a planetary system composed of two transiting low-density Neptunians locked in an almost perfect 2:1 resonance and showing large TTVs, i.e., an excellent laboratory to search for signatures of planetary migration. Previous studies performed with K2, Spitzer and RV data tentatively claimed a significant non-zero eccentricity for one or both planets, possibly high enough to challenge the scenario of pure disk migration through resonant capture. With 13 new CHEOPS light curves (seven of planet -b, six of planet -c), we carried out a global photometric and dynamical re-analysis by including all the available literature data as well. We got the most accurate set of planetary parameters to date for the K2-24 system, including radii and masses at 1% and 5% precision (now essentially limited by the uncertainty on stellar parameters) and non-zero eccentricities $e_b=0.0498_{-0.0018}^{+0.0011}$, $e_c=0.0282_{-0.0007}^{+0.0003}$ detected at very high significance for both planets. Such relatively large values imply the need for an additional physical mechanism of eccentricity excitation during or after the migration stage. Also, while the accuracy of the previous TTV model had drifted by up to 0.5 days at the current time, we constrained the orbital solution firmly enough to predict the forthcoming transits for the next ~15 years, thus enabling an efficient follow-up with top-level facilities such as JWST or ESPRESSO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02995v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Nascimbeni, L. Borsato, P. Leonardi, S. G. Sousa, T. G. Wilson, A. Fortier, A. Heitzmann, G. Mantovan, R. Luque, T. Zingales, G. Piotto, Y. Alibert, R. Alonso, T. B\'arczy, D. Barrado Navascues, S. C. Barros, W. Baumjohann, T. Beck, W. Benz, N. Billot, F. Biondi, A. Brandeker, C. Broeg, M. -D. Busch, A. Collier Cameron, A. C. M. Correia, Sz. Csizmadia, P. E. Cubillos, M. B. Davies, M. Deleuil, A. Deline, L. Delrez, O. D. S. Demangeon, B. -O. Demory, A. Derekas, B. Edwards, D. Ehrenreich, A. Erikson, L. Fossati, M. Fridlund, D. Gandolfi, K. Gazeas, M. Gillon, M. G\"udel, M. N. G\"unther, Ch. Helling, K. G. Isaak, F. Kerschbaum, L. Kiss, J. Korth, K. W. F. Lam, J. Laskar, A. Lecavelier des Etangs, A. Leleu, M. Lendl, D. Magrin, P. F. L. Maxted, B. Mer\'in, C. Mordasini, G. Olofsson, R. Ottensamer, I. Pagano, E. Pall\'e, G. Peter, D. Pollacco, D. Queloz, R. Ragazzoni, N. Rando, H. Rauer, I. Ribas, N. C. Santos, G. Scandariato, D. S\'egransan, A. E. Simon, A. M. S. Smith, R. Southworth, M. Stalport, S. Sulis, M. Gy. Szab\'o, S. Udry, B. Ulmer, V. Van Grootel, J. Venturini, E. Villaver, N. A. Walton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
