<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 05:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical evolution of massless particles in star clusters with NBODY6++GPU-MASSLESS: I. Free-floating MLPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Low-mass bodies, such as comets, asteroids, planetesimals, and free-floating planets, are continuously injected into the intra-cluster environment after expulsion from their host planetary systems. These can be modeled as massless particles (MLPs, hereafter). The dynamics of large populations of MLPs, however, has yet received little attention in literature. Aims. We investigate the dynamical evolution of MLP populations in star clusters, and characterize their kinematics and ejection rates. Methods. We present NBODY6++GPU-MASSLESS, a modified version of the N-body simulation code NBODY6++GPU, that allows fast integration of star clusters that contain large numbers of massless particles (MLPs). NBODY6++GPU-MASSLESS contains routines specifically directed at the dynamical evolution of low-mass bodies, such as planets. Results. Unlike stars, MLPs do not participate in the mass segregation process. Instead, MLPs mostly follow the gravitational potential of the star cluster, which gradually decreases over time due to stellar ejections and stellar evolution. The dynamical evolution of MLPs is primarily affected by the evolution of the core of the star cluster. This is most apparent in the outer regions for clusters with higher initial densities. High escape rates of MLPs are observed before the core-collapse, after which escape rates remain stable. Denser star clusters undergo a more intense core collapse, but this does not impact the dynamical evolution of MLPs. The speeds of escaping stars are similar to those of escaping MLPs, when disregarding the high-velocity ejections of neutron stars during the first 50 Myr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08785v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Flammini Dotti, M. B. N. Kouwenhoven, Peter Berczik, Qi Shu, Rainer Spurzem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discoveries and Properties of EL CVn-type Binaries in the TESS Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: EL CVn-type systems represent a rare evolutionary stage in binary star evolution, providing ideal laboratories for investigating stable mass transfer processes and the formation of extremely low-mass white dwarfs (ELM WDs). The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has delivered an extensive collection of high-precision time-domain photometric data, which is invaluable for studying EL CVn binaries. In this study, we identified 29 EL CVn systems from the TESS eclipsing binary catalogs (sectors 1-65), 11 of which are newly discovered. These systems consist of smaller, hotter pre-He white dwarfs and A/F main-sequence stars. The orbital periods of these binaries range from 0.64 to 2.5 days. Utilizing TESS light curves, Gaia distances, and multi-band photometric data (e.g., GALEX, 2MASS, WISE, SkyMapper), we modeled the light curves and spectral energy distributions to derive system parameters, including effective temperatures, masses, and radii. These systems were then compared with the white dwarf mass-period relation and the evolutionary tracks of ELM WDs. The comparison reveals that these binaries are consistent with the expected mass-period relation for white dwarfs and align well with the evolutionary tracks on the Teff-logg diagram for ELM WDs. This result suggests that these EL CVn systems likely formed through stable mass transfer processes. We provide a catalog of complete parameters for 29 EL CVn systems identified from the TESS survey. This catalog will serve as an essential resource for studying binary mass transfer, white dwarf formation, and pulsation phenomena in EL CVn-type systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08877v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianping Xiong, Zhenwei Li, Jiao Li, Xiaobin Zhang, Xiaodian Chen, Kaifan Ji, Zhanwen Han, Xuefei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary Evolution Pathways to Blue Large-Amplitude Pulsators: Insights from HD 133729</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blue Large-Amplitude Pulsators (BLAPs) represent a recently identified class of pulsating stars distinguished by their short pulsation periods (22-40 minutes) and asymmetric light curves. This study investigates the evolutionary channel of HD 133729, the first confirmed BLAP in a binary system. Through binary evolution simulations with MESA, we explored various mass ratios and initial orbital periods, finding that a mass ratio of q = 0.30 coupled with non-conservative mass transfer ($\rm \beta$ = 0.15) successfully reproduces the observational characteristics (including luminosity, surface gravity, and effective temperature) of the binary system. Our models not only match the observed pulsational properties but also predict significant helium and nitrogen enhancements on the surface of the main-sequence companion. The system is expected to eventually undergo a common envelope phase leading to a stellar merger. Our findings provide crucial insights into the formation mechanism and evolutionary fate of BLAPs with main-sequence companions, while also placing constraints on the elemental abundances of their binary companions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08903v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengyang Zhang, Chengyuan Wu, Xianfei Zhang, Bo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Long-term Evolution of the Solar Transition Region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-term evolution characteristics of the solar transition region have been unclear. In this study, daily images of the solar full disk derived from the observations by the Solar Dynamics Observatory/Atmospheric Imaging Assembly at 304 A wavelength from 2011 January 1 to 2022 December 31 are used to investigate long-term evolution of the solar transition region. It is found that long-term variation in the transition region of the full disk is in phase with the solar activity cycle, and thus the polar brightening should occur in the maximum epoch of the solar cycle. Long-term variation of the background transition region is found to be likely in anti-phase with the solar activity cycle at middle and low latitudes. The entire transition region, especially the active transition region is inferred to be mainly heated by the active-region magnetic fields and the ephemeral-region magnetic fields, while the quieter transition region is believed to be mainly heated by network magnetic fields. Long-term evolution characteristics of various types of the magnetic fields at the solar surface are highly consistent with these findings, and thus provide an explanation for them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08910v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Q. Chen, K. J. Li, J. C. Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar parameter prediction and spectral simulation using machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We applied machine learning to the entire data history of ESO's High Accuracy Radial Velocity Planet Searcher (HARPS) instrument. Our primary goal was to recover the physical properties of the observed objects, with a secondary emphasis on simulating spectra. We systematically investigated the impact of various factors on the accuracy and fidelity of the results, including the use of simulated data, the effect of varying amounts of real training data, network architectures, and learning paradigms. Our approach integrates supervised and unsupervised learning techniques within autoencoder frameworks. Our methodology leverages an existing simulation model that utilizes a library of existing stellar spectra in which the emerging flux is computed from first principles rooted in physics and a HARPS instrument model to generate simulated spectra comparable to observational data. We trained standard and variational autoencoders on HARPS data to predict spectral parameters and generate spectra. Our models excel at predicting spectral parameters and compressing real spectra, and they achieved a mean prediction error of approximately 50 K for effective temperatures, making them relevant for most astrophysical applications. Furthermore, the models predict metallicity ([M/H]) and surface gravity (log g) with an accuracy of approximately 0.03 dex and 0.04 dex, respectively, underscoring their broad applicability in astrophysical research. The models' computational efficiency, with processing times of 779.6 ms on CPU and 3.97 ms on GPU, makes them valuable for high-throughput applications like massive spectroscopic surveys and large archival studies. By achieving accuracy comparable to classical methods with significantly reduced computation time, our methodology enhances the scope and efficiency of spectroscopic analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vojt\v{e}ch Cvr\v{c}ek, Martino Romaniello, Radim \v{S}\'ara, Wolfram Freudling, Pascal Ballester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Substellar candidates at the earliest stages: the SUCANES database</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Brown dwarfs are the bridge between low-mass stars and giant planets. One way of shedding light on their dominant formation mechanism is to study them at the earliest stages of their evolution, when they are deeply embedded in their parental clouds. Several works have identified pre- and proto-brown dwarfs candidates using different observational approaches. The aim of this work is to create a database with all the objects classified as very young substellar candidates in the litearature in order to study them in an homogeneous way. We have gathered all the information about very young substellar candidates available in the literature until 2020. We have retrieved their published photometry from the optical to the centimeter regime, and we have written our own codes to derive their bolometric temperatures and luminosities, and their internal luminosities. We have also populated the database with other parameters extracted from the literature, like e.g. the envelope masses, their detection in some molecular species, and presence of outflows. The result of our search is the SUCANES database, containing 174 objects classified as potential very young substellar candidates in the literature. We present an analysis of the main properties of the retrieved objects. Since we have updated the distances to several star forming regions, this has allowed us to reject some candidates based on their internal luminosities. We have also discussed the derived physical parameters and envelope masses for the best substellar candidates isolated in SUCANES. As an example of a scientific exploitation of this database, we present a feasibility study for the detection of radiojets with upcoming facilities: the ngVLA and the SKA interferometers. The SUCANES database is accessible through a Graphical User Interface and it is open to any potential user.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09091v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M. P\'erez-Garc\'ia (ISDEFE), N. Hu\'elamo (CAB/INTA-CSIC), A. Garc\'ia-L\'opez (ISDEFE), R. P\'erez-Mart\'inez (ISDEFE), E. Verdugo (ESAC), A. Palau (UNAM), I. De Gregorio-Monsalvo (ESO), O. Morata (ICE-CSIC), D. Barrado (CAB/INTA-CSIC), M. Morales-Calder\'on (CAB/INTA-CSIC), M. Mass-Hesse (CAB/INTA-CSIC), A. Bayo (ESO), K. Mauco (CNRS), H. Bouy (CNRS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic observations of flares and superflares on AU Mic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The young active flare star AU~Mic is the planet host star with the highest flare rate from TESS data. Therefore, it represents an ideal target for dedicated ground-based monitoring campaigns with the aim to characterize its numerous flares spectroscopically. We performed such spectroscopic monitoring with the ESO1.52m telescope of the PLATOSpec consortium. In more than 190 hours of observations, we find 24 flares suitable for detailed analysis. We compute their parameters (duration, peak flux, energy) in eight chromospheric lines (H$\alpha$, H$\beta$, H$\gamma$, H$\delta$, Na I D1&amp;D2, He I D3, He I 6678) and investigate their relationships. Furthermore, we obtained simultaneous photometric observations and low-resolution spectroscopy for part of the spectroscopic runs. We detect one flare in the g'-band photometry which is associated with a spectroscopic flare. Additionally, an extreme flare event occurred on 2023-09-16 of which only a time around its possible peak was observed, during which chromospheric line fluxes were raised by up to a factor of three compared to the following night. The estimated energy of this event is around $10^{33}$ erg in H$\alpha$ alone, i.e. a rare chromospheric line superflare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09113v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Odert, M. Leitzinger, R. Greimel, P. Kab\'ath, J. Lipt\'ak, P. Heinzel, R. Karjalainen, J. Wollmann, E. W. Guenther, M. Skarka, J. Srba, P. \v{S}koda, J. Fr\'yda, R. Brahm, L. Vanzi, J. Jan\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemodynamic evolution of Sun-like stars in nearby moving groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sun-like stars are well represented in the solar neighbourhood but are currently under-utilised, with many studies of chemical and kinematic evolution focusing on red giants (which can be observed further away) or turn-off stars (which have well measured ages). Recent surveys (e.g. GALAH) provide spectra for large numbers of nearby Sun-like stars, which provides an opportunity to apply our newly developed method for measuring metallicities, temperatures, and surface gravities - the EPIC algorithm - which yields improved ages via isochrone fitting. We test this on moving groups, by applying it to the large GALAH DR3 sample. This defines a sample of 72,288 solar analogue targets for which the stellar parameter measurements are most precise and reliable. These stars are used to estimate, and test the accuracy and precision of, age measurements derived with the SAMD isochrone fitting algorithm. Using these ages, we recover the age-metallicity relationships for nearby (&lt;= 1 kpc) moving groups, traced by solar analogues, and analyse them with respect to the stellar kinematics. In particular, we found that the age-metallicity relationships of all moving groups follows a particular trend of young (age &lt; 6 Gyr) stars having constant metallicity and older (age &gt;= 6 Gyr) stars decreasing in metallicity with increasing age. The Hercules stream carries the highest fraction of metal-rich young stars (~ 0.1 dex) in our sample, which is consistent with a migrating population of stars from the inner Galaxy, and we discuss the possible causes of this migration in the context of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09128v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1736</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Christian Lehmann, Michael T. Murphy, Fan Liu, Chris Flynn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Reconnection between a Solar Jet and a Filament Channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The solar corona is highly structured by bunches of magnetic field lines forming either loops, or twisted flux ropes representing prominences/filaments, or very dynamic structures such as jets. The aim of this paper is to understand the interaction between filament channels and jets. We use high-resolution H$\alpha$ spectra obtained by the ground-based Telescope Heliographique pour lEtude du Magnetisme et des Instabilites Solaires (THEMIS) in Canary Islands, and data from Helioseismic Magnetic Imager (HMI) and Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) aboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO). In this paper we present a multi-wavelength study of the interaction of filaments and jets. They both consist of cool plasma embedded in magnetic structures. A jet is particularly well studied in all the AIA channels with a flow reaching 100-180 km s$^{-1}$. Its origin is linked to cancelling flux at the edge of the active region. Large Dopplershifts in H$\alpha$ are derived in a typical area for a short time (order of min). They correspond to flows around 140 km s$^{-1}$. In conclusion we conjecture that these flows correspond to some interchange of magnetic field lines between the filament channel and the jets leading to cool plasmoid ejections or reconnection jets perpendicularly to the jet trajectory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09206v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Garima Karki, Brigitte Schmieder, Pooja Devi, Ramesh Chandra, Nicolas Labrosse, Reetika Joshi, Bernard Gelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast-rotating A- and F-type stars with H{\alpha} emissions in NGC 3532, candidate UV-dim stars?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extended main-sequence stars that are dim in the ultraviolet passbands of Hubble Space Telescope (UV-dim stars) are found in several young and intermediate-age Magellanic Cloud star clusters. The obscuring of the dust in the discs of stars expelled due to fast rotation have been suggested to be responsible for the appearance of UV-dim stars, and play an important role in the formation of extended main-sequences. In this paper, we report a population of A- and F-type stars who show H{\alpha} emission features in their spectra in a young (~ 340 Myr-old) Galactic neighboring star cluster NGC 3532. By fitting the observed absorption profiles, we found that most H{\alpha} emitters are fast rotating stars, indicating that they form decretion discs by fast rotation like Be stars. As A- and F-type stars dominate the extended main-sequence turn-off regions of intermediate-age clusters, their appearance provides observational evidence to support the dust extinction scenario for these clusters, and might be the counterparts of UV-dim stars that are detected in remote Magellanic Cloud star clusters like NGC 1783.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09217v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu He, Chengyuan Li, Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theoretical framework for BL Her stars III. A case study: Robust light curve optimisation in the LMC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We carry out an extensive light curve comparison of BL Her stars using observations from Gaia DR3 and stellar pulsation models computed using MESA-RSP with the goal to obtain the best-matched modeled-observed pairs for BL Her stars in the LMC. We use the Fourier decomposition technique to analyse the light curves in the G band obtained from Gaia DR3 and from MESA-RSP and use a robust light curve fitting approach to score the modeled-observed pairs with respect to their pulsation periods and over their Fourier parameter space. We obtain the best-fit models for 48 BL Her stars in the LMC and thereby provide the stellar parameter estimates of these stars, 30 of which are labelled as the gold sample with superior light curve fits. We find a relatively flat distribution of stellar masses between 0.5-0.65 Msolar for the gold sample of modeled-observed pairs. An interesting result is that the majority of the best-matched models in the gold sample are computed using the convection parameter sets without radiative cooling. The period-Wesenheit relation for the best-matched gold sample of 30 BL Her models exhibits a slope of $-2.805 \pm 0.164$ while the corresponding period-radius relation exhibits a slope of $0.565 \pm 0.035$, both in good agreement with the empirical PW and PR slopes from BL Her stars in the LMC, respectively. We also used the Wesenheit magnitudes of the 30 best-matched modeled-observed pairs to estimate a distance modulus of $\mu_{\rm LMC} = 18.582 \pm 0.067$ to the LMC, which lies within the bounds of previous literature values. We also discuss the degeneracy in the stellar parameters of the BL Her models that result in similar pulsation periods and light curve structure, and highlight that caution must be exercised while using the stellar parameter estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09287v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susmita Das, L\'aszl\'o Moln\'ar, G\'abor B. Kov\'acs, Radoslaw Smolec, Meridith Joyce, Shashi M. Kanbur, Tam\'as Szklen\'ar, Anupam Bhardwaj, Harinder P. Singh, Marcella Marconi, Vincenzo Ripepi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using nebular near-IR spectroscopy to measure asymmetric chemical distributions in 2003fg-like thermonuclear supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an analysis of three near-infrared (NIR; 1.0-2.4 $\mu$m) spectra of the SN 2003fg-like/"super-Chandrasekhar" type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) SN 2009dc, SN 2020hvf, and SN 2022pul at respective phases +372, +296, and +294~d relative to the epoch of $B$-band maximum. We find that all objects in our sample have asymmetric, or "tilted", [Fe~II] 1.257 and 1.644 $\mu$m profiles. We quantify the asymmetry of these features using five methods: velocity at peak flux, profile tilts, residual testing, velocity fitting, and comparison to deflagration-detonation transition models. Our results demonstrate that, while the profiles of the [Fe II] 1.257 and 1.644 $\mu$m features are widely varied between 2003fg-likes, these features are correlated in shape within the same SN. This implies that line blending is most likely not the dominant cause of the asymmetries inferred from these profiles. Instead, it is more plausible that 2003fg-like SNe have aspherical chemical distributions in their inner regions. These distributions may come from aspherical progenitor systems, such as double white dwarf mergers, or off-center delayed-detonation explosions of Chandrasekhar-mass Carbon-Oxygen white dwarfs. Additional late-phase NIR observation of 2003fg-like SNe and detailed 3-D NLTE modeling of these two explosion scenarios are encouraged.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09352v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. O'Hora, C. Ashall, M. Shahbandeh, E. Hsiao, P. Hoeflich, M. D. Stritzinger, L. Galbany, E. Baron, J. DerKacy, S. Kumar, J. Lu, K. Medler, B. Shappee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A BCool survey of stellar magnetic cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic cycle on the Sun consists of two consecutive 11-yr sunspot cycles and exhibits a polarity reversal around sunspot maximum. Although solar dynamo theories have progressively become more sophisticated, the details as to how the dynamo sustains magnetic fields are still subject of research. Observing the magnetic fields of Sun-like stars are useful to contextualise the solar dynamo. The BCool survey studies the evolution of surface magnetic fields to understand how dynamo-generated processes are influenced by key ingredients, like mass and rotation. Here, we focus on six Sun-like stars with mass between 1.02 and 1.06 MSun and with 3.5-21 d rotation period. We analysed high-resolution spectropolarimetric data collected with ESPaDOnS, Narval and Neo-Narval. We measured the longitudinal magnetic field from least-squares deconvolution line profiles and inspected its long-term behaviour with a Lomb-Scargle periodogram and a Gaussian process. We applied Zeeman-Doppler imaging to reconstruct the large-scale magnetic field geometry at the stellar surface for different epochs. Two stars, namely HD 9986 and HD 56124 (Prot ~ 20 d) exhibit cyclic variability with polarity reversals of the radial or toroidal field component on time scales of 5 to 6 yr. HD 73350 (Prot = 12 d) has one polarity reversal of the toroidal component and HD 76151 (Prot=17 d) may have short-term evolution (2.5 yr) modulated by the long-term (16 yr) chromospheric cycle. HD 166435 and HD 175726 (Prot =3-5 d), manifest complex magnetic fields without cyclic evolution. Our findings indicate the strong dependence of the magnetic cycles nature with stellar rotation period. For the stars with an identified cyclic evolution, the polarity reversal time scale seems to decrease with decreasing rotation period or Rossby number. These results represent important observational constraints for dynamo models of solar-like stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09365v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bellotti, P. Petit, S. V. Jeffers, S. C. Marsden, J. Morin, A. A. Vidotto, C. P. Folsom, V. See, J. -D. do Nascimento Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial evolution of a density structure within a solar wind magnetic sector boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study focuses on a radial alignment between Parker Solar Probe (PSP) and Solar Orbiter (SolO) on the 29$^{\text{th}}$ of April 2021 (during a solar minimum), when the two spacecraft were respectively located at $\sim 0.075$ and $\sim 0.9$~au from the Sun. A previous study of this alignment allowed the identification of the same density enhancement (with a time scale of $\sim$1.5~h), and substructures ($\sim$20-30~min timescale), passing first by PSP, and then SolO after a $\sim 138$~h propagation time in the inner heliosphere. We show here that this structure belongs to the large scale heliospheric magnetic sector boundary. In this region, the density is dominated by radial gradients, whereas the magnetic field reversal is consistent with longitudinal gradients in the Carrington reference frame. We estimate the density structure radial size to remain of the order L$_R \sim 10^6$~km, while its longitudinal and latitudinal sizes, are estimated to expand from L$_{\varphi, \theta} \sim 10^4$-$10^5$~km in the high solar corona, to L$_{\varphi, \theta} \sim 10^5$-$10^6$~km at PSP, and L$_{\varphi, \theta} \sim 10^6$-$10^7$~km at SolO. This implies a strong evolution of the structure's aspect ratio during the propagation, due to the plasma's nearly spherical expansion. The structure's shape is therefore inferred to evolve from elongated in the radial direction at $\sim$2-3 solar radii (high corona), to sizes of nearly the same order in all directions at PSP, and then becoming elongated in the directions transverse to the radial at SolO. Measurements are not concordant with local reconnection of open solar wind field lines, so we propose that the structure has been generated through interchange reconnection near the tip of a coronal streamer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09395v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etienne Berriot, Pascal D\'emoulin, Olga Alexandrova, Arnaud Zaslavsky, Milan Maksimovic, Georgios Nicolaou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the evolutionary nature of massive B-type supergiants: a modern empirical reappraisal using data from IACOB, Gaia and TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09454v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive stars are key contributors to the chemodynamical evolution of galaxies and the Universe. Despite their significance, discrepancies between observational data and theoretical models of massive stars challenge our understanding of these objects. A major uncertainty is the overdensity of B-type supergiants (BSGs) in the Hertzsprung-Russell diagram, where models predict the end of the main sequence phase (or TAMS). Is uncertain whether the TAMS needs to be redefined or if the overdensity results from overlapping populations following different evolutionary paths. Conceived as direct descendants of O-type stars, BSGs may include stars not only evolving in the main sequence but also returning from a post-red supergiant phase. A representative fraction of massive stars are predicted to be products of binary interaction, creating additional evolutionary channels. In addition, some fundamental properties of BSGs such as the spin- and mass-loss rates are not as well constrained as in O-type stars, having a significant impact on massive star evolution. To overcome this situation, statistically significant spectroscopic samples offer a unique opportunity to study the physical and chemical properties of BSGs. Moreover, the advent of space astrometry and photometry missions such as Gaia and TESS has brought a new era for studying additional properties in detail. This thesis comprises the study of 1000 Galactic blue supergiants (O- and B-type) combining multi-epoch high-resolution spectroscopic data from the IACOB project and the ESO archive with Gaia distances and TESS photometry, becoming the largest holistic empirical study of the physical, chemical, and pulsational properties of these objects performed to date. All these properties gathered into a unique volume-limited sample allowed to provide an empirical reassessment of the main properties of BSGs and investigate their intricate nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09454v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abel de Burgos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear evolution of fluting oscillations in coronal flux tubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic flux tubes in the solar corona support a rich variety of transverse oscillations, which are theoretically interpreted as magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) modes with a fast and/or Alfv\'enic character. In the standard flux tube model made of a straight cylindrical tube, these modes can be classified according to their azimuthal wavenumber, $m$. Sausage $m=0$ modes produce periodic expansion and contraction of the tube cross section and are observed during solar flares. Kink $m=1$ modes laterally displace the tube axis and are related to, for example, post-flare global transverse oscillations of coronal loops. Fluting $m \geq 2$ modes produce disturbances that are mainly confined to the tube boundary, but their observation remains elusive to date. We use 3D ideal MHD numerical simulations to investigate the nonlinear evolution of fluting modes in coronal flux tubes with transversely nonuniform boundaries. The simulations show that fluting modes are short-lived as coherent, collective motions of the flux tube. Owing to the process of resonant absorption, fluting oscillations become overdamped modes in tubes with wide enough nonuniform boundaries. During the nonlinear evolution, shear flows drive the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability at the tube boundary, which further disrupts the coherent fluting oscillation. For large-enough oscillation amplitudes, baroclinic instabilities of Rayleigh-Taylor type are also present at locations in the boundary where the plasma acceleration is normal to the boundary. The evolution of the instabilities drives turbulence in the flux tube, which may inhibit the resonant damping. However, the oscillations remain strongly damped even in this case. As a result of the combination of the strong damping and the induced instabilities, it is unlikely that coronal flux tubes can support fluting modes as sufficiently enduring coherent oscillations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09547v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Soler, Andrew Hillier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Technique for Long-term Timing of Redback Millisecond Pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present timing solutions spanning nearly two decades for five redback (RB) systems found in globular clusters (GC), created using a novel technique that effectively "isolates" the pulsar. By accurately measuring the time of passage through periastron ($T_0$) at points over the timing baseline, we use a piecewise-continuous, binary model to get local solutions of the orbital variations that we pair with long-term orbital information to remove the orbital timing delays. The isolated pulse times of arrival can then be fit to describe the spin behavior of the millisecond pulsar (MSP). The results of our timing analyses via this method are consistent with those of conventional timing methods for binaries in GCs as demonstrated by analyses of NGC 6440D. We also investigate the observed orbital phase variations for these systems. Quasi-periodic oscillations in Terzan 5P's orbit may be the result of changes to the gravitational-quadruple moment of the companion as prescribed by the Applegate model. We find a striking correlation between the standard deviation of the phase variations as a fraction of a system's orbit ($\sigma_{\Delta T_0}$) and the MSP's spin frequency, as well as a potential correlation between $\sigma_{\Delta T_0}$ and the binary's projected semi-major axis. While long-term RB timing is fraught with large systematics, our work provides a needed alternative for studying systems with significant orbital variations, especially when high-cadence monitoring observations are unavailable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08688v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyle A. Corcoran, Scott M. Ransom, Alexandra C. Rosenthal, Megan E. DeCesar, Paulo C. C. Freire, Jason W. T. Hessels, Ryan S. Lynch, Prajwal V. Padmanabh, Ingrid H. Stairs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PICS: Planetary Nebulae in Cosmological Simulations -- Revelations of the Planetary Nebula Luminosity Function from Realistic Stellar Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08702v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Even after decades of usage as an extragalactic standard candle, the universal bright end of the planetary nebula luminosity function (PNLF) still lacks a solid theoretical explanation. Until now, models have modeled planetary nebulae (PNe) from artificial stellar populations, without an underlying cosmological star formation history. We present PICS (PNe In Cosmological Simulations), a novel method of modeling PNe in cosmological simulations, through which PN populations for the first time naturally occur within galaxies of diverse evolutionary pathways. We find that only by using realistic stellar populations and their metallicities is it possible to reproduce the bright end of the PNLF for all galaxy types. In particular, the dependence of stellar lifetimes on metallicity has to be accounted for to produce bright PNe in metal-rich populations. Finally, PICS reproduces the statistically complete part of the PNLF observed around the Sun, down to six orders of magnitude below the bright end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08702v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas M. Valenzuela, Rhea-Silvia Remus, Marcelo M. Miller Bertolami, Roberto H. M\'endez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Status and Perspectives on Axion Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08733v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The search for axions and axion-like particles (ALPs) remains a major endeavor in modern physics investigation. Axions play essential roles in the quest to understand dark matter, the strong CP problem, and various astrophysical phenomena. This paper provides a very brief overview of the current status of experimental efforts, highlighting significant advancements, ongoing projects, and future opportunities. Particular attention is given to cavity haloscopes, helioscopes, and laboratory-based light-shining-through-wall experiments, as well as astrophysical probes. Some future perspectives are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08733v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurizio Giannotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Fields in Massive Star-forming Regions (MagMaR). V. The Magnetic Field at the Onset of High-mass Star Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08790v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A complete understanding of the initial conditions of high-mass star formation and what processes determine multiplicity require the study of the magnetic field (B-field) in young, massive cores. Using ALMA 250 GHz polarization (0.3" = 1000 au) and ALMA 220 GHz high-angular resolution observations (0.05" = 160 au), we have performed a full energy analysis including the B-field at core scales and have assessed what influences the multiplicity inside a massive core previously believed to be in the prestellar phase. With 31 Msun, the G11.92 MM2 core has a young CS outflow with a dynamical time scale of a few thousand years. At high-resolution, the MM2 core fragments into a binary system with a projected separation of 505 au and a binary mass ratio of 1.14. Using the DCF method with an ADF analysis, we estimate in this core a B-field strength of 6.2 mG and a mass-to-flux ratio of 18. The MM2 core is strongly subvirialized with a virial parameter of 0.064, including the B-field. The high mass-to-flux ratio and low virial parameter indicate that this massive core is very likely undergoing runaway collapse, which is in direct contradiction with the core-accretion model. The MM2 core is embedded in a filament that has a velocity gradient consistent with infall. In line with clump-fed scenarios, the core can grow in mass at a rate of 1.9--5.6 x 10^-4 Msun/yr. In spite of the B-field having only a minor contribution to the total energy budget at core scales, it likely plays a more important role at smaller scales by setting the binary properties. Considering energy ratios and a fragmentation criterion at the core scale, the binary could have been formed by core fragmentation. The binary properties (separation and mass ratio), however, are also consistent with radiation-magnetohydrodynamic simulations with super-Alfvenic, supersonic (or sonic) turbulence that form binaries by disk fragmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08790v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patricio Sanhueza, Junhao Liu, Kaho Morii, Josep Miquel Girart, Qizhou Zhang, Ian W. Stephens, James M. Jackson, Paulo C. Cortes, Patrick M. Koch, Claudia J. Cyganowski, Piyali Saha, Henrik Beuther, Suinan Zhang, Maria T. Beltran, Yu Cheng, Fernando A. Olguin, Xing Lu, Spandan Choudhury, Kate Pattle, Manuel Fern andez-Lopez, Jihye Hwang, Ji-hyun Kang, Janik Karoly, Adam Ginsburg, A. -Ran Lyo, Kotomi Taniguchi, Wenyu Jiao, Chakali Eswaraiah, Qiu-yi Luo, Jia-Wei Wang, Benoit Commercon, Shanghuo Li, Fengwei Xu, Huei-Ru Vivien Chen, Luis A. Zapata, Eun Jung Chung, Fumitaka Nakamura, Sandhyarani Panigrahy, Takeshi Sakai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DAmodel: Hierarchical Bayesian Modelling of DA White Dwarfs for Spectrophotometric Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use hierarchical Bayesian modelling to calibrate a network of 32 all-sky faint DA white dwarf (DA WD) spectrophotometric standards ($16.5 &lt; V &lt; 19.5$) alongside the three CALSPEC standards, from 912 \r{A} to 32 $\mu$m. The framework is the first of its kind to jointly infer photometric zeropoints and WD parameters ($\log g$, $T_{\text{eff}}$, $A_V$, $R_V$) by simultaneously modelling both photometric and spectroscopic data. We model panchromatic HST/WFC3 UVIS and IR fluxes, HST/STIS UV spectroscopy and ground-based optical spectroscopy to sub-percent precision. Photometric residuals for the sample are the lowest yet yielding $&lt;0.004$ mag RMS on average from the UV to the NIR, achieved by jointly inferring time-dependent changes in system sensitivity and WFC3/IR count-rate nonlinearity. Our GPU-accelerated implementation enables efficient sampling via Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, critical for exploring the high-dimensional posterior space. The hierarchical nature of the model enables population analysis of intrinsic WD and dust parameters. Inferred SEDs from this model will be essential for calibrating the James Webb Space Telescope as well as next-generation surveys, including Vera Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time, and the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08809v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin M. Boyd, Gautham Narayan, Kaisey S. Mandel, Matthew Grayling, Aidan Berres, Mai Li, Aaron Do, Abhijit Saha, Tim Axelrod, Thomas Matheson, Edward W. Olszewski, Ralph C. Bohlin, Annalisa Calamida, Jay B. Holberg, Ivan Hubeny, John W. Mackenty, Armin Rest, Elena Sabbi, Christopher W. Stubbs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrical Distances of Extragalactic Binaries through Spectroastrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The growing ``Hubble tension'' has prompted the need for precise measurements of cosmological distances. This paper demonstrates a purely geometric approach for determining the distance to extragalactic binaries through a joint analysis of spectroastrometry (SA), radial velocity (RV), and light curve (LC) observations. A parameterized model for the binary system is outlined, and simulated SA, RV, and LC data are computed to infer the probability distribution of model parameters based on the mock data. The impact of data quality and binary parameters on distance uncertainties is comprehensively analyzed, showcasing the method's potential for high-precision distance measurements. For a typical eclipsing binary in the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC), the distance uncertainty is approximately 6% under reasonable observational conditions. Within a specific range of data quality and input parameters, the distance measurement precision of individual binary star systems is generally better than 10%. As a geometric method based on the simplest dynamics, it is independent of empirical calibration and the systematics caused by model selections can be tested using nearby binaries with known distances. By measuring multiple binary star systems or monitoring one binary system repeatedly, geometric distance measurements of nearby galaxies can be achieved, providing valuable insights into the Hubble tension and advancing our understanding of the universe's structure and evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08889v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Yang Songsheng, Jian-Min Wang, Yuan Cao, XueFei Chen, JianPing Xiong, Zhi-Xiang Zhang, Rong-Gen Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into the Properties of Type Ibn/Icn Supernovae and Their Progenitor Channels through X-ray Emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Type Ibn/Icn supernovae (SNe Ibn/Icn), which are characterized by narrow helium or carbon lines originated in hydrogen-poor dense circumstellar medium (CSM), provide new insights into the final evolution of massive stars. While SNe Ibn/Icn are expected to emit strong X-rays through the strong SN-CSM interaction, the X-ray emission modeling effort has been limited so far. In the present study, we provide broad-band X-ray light curve (LC) predictions for SNe Ibn/Icn. We find that the soft X-ray LC provides information about the CSM compositions, while the hard X-ray LC is a robust measure of the CSM density, the explosion energy, and the ejecta mass. In addition, considering the evolution of the ionization state in the unshocked CSM, a bright soft X-ray is expected in the first few days since the explosion, which encourages rapid X-ray follow-up observations as a tool to study the nature of SNe Ibn/Icn. Applying our model to the soft X-ray LCs of SNe Ibn 2006jc and 2022ablq, we derive that the CSM potentially contains a larger fraction of carbon and oxygen for SN 2006jc than 2022ablq, highlighting the power of the soft X-ray modeling to address the nature of the CSM. We also discuss detectability and observational strategy, with which the currently operating telescopes such as NuSTAR and Swift can offer an irreplaceable opportunity to explore the nature of these enigmatic rapid transients and their still-unclarified progenitor channel(s).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09066v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Inoue, Keiichi Maeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Roche Lobe Overflow in the Formation of Merging Black Hole Binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate a new methodology to model Roche lobe overflow (RLO) systems to unprecedented resolution simultaneously across the envelope, donor wind, tidal stream, and accretion disk regimes without reliance upon previously-universal symmetry, mass flux, and angular momentum flux assumptions. We have applied this method to the semidetached high-mass X-ray binary (HMXB) M33 X-7 in order to provide a direct comparison to recent observations of an RLO candidate system at two overflow states of overfilling factors f = 1.01 and f = 1.1. We found extreme overflow ( f = 1.1) to exhibit entirely conservative unstable mass transfer (MT), with tidal stream density and deflected angle comparable to predictions. The f = 1.01 case differed in stream geometry, accretion disk size, and efficiency, demonstrating non-conservative stable MT through a ballistic uniform-width stream. The non-conservative and stable nature of the f = 1.01 case MT also suggests that existing assumptions of semi-detached binaries undergoing RLO may mischaracterize the parameter space of stability for the L1 flow. We also conducted a piecewise evolution of M33 X-7 across nearly the entirety of RLO phase from onset to runaway unstable MT. We present the first model of the efficiency of MT and its associated angular momentum across overfilling factor parameter space. We also present novel relations for binary separation, mass ratio, L1 mass transfer rate, and Roche timescale as they vary with respect to the overfilling factor. These provide constraints on the threshold for the onset of unstable MT which ultimately led in our system to exponentially faster MT evolution. Collectively these parameter constraints, relations, and explorations probe RLO dynamics in HMXBs and their role and distribution as progenitors of binary black holes and common envelopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09172v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Dickson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring nuclear force with pulsar glitch observation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We connect nuclear forces to one of the most notable irregular behaviors observed in pulsars, already detected in approximately 6\% known pulsars, with increasingly accurate data expected from upcoming high-precision timing instruments on both ground and space. Built on \cite{Shang2021_ApJ923-108}, we conduct a case study on the 2001 glitch of the Vela pulsar. For our purpose, we adopt the Relativistic Mean Field (RMF) model as the theoretical many-body framework to describe nuclear systems. We refit three representative RMF parameter sets (DD-ME2, PKDD, NL3), considering the uncertainties in nuclear matter saturation properties. Utilizing the resulting star structure, composition and nucleon properties in the medium obtained in a consistent manner, we calculate the pinning energy of superfluid vortex in the nuclear lattice in the inner crust. This leads to the evolution of associated pinning force that acts on the vortex, which can be confronted with observed glitch amplitude and short-time relaxation in the 2000 Vela glitch event, following the superfluidity model of pulsar glitch. We discuss how the vortex configuration and pinning properties depend on the nuclear parameters, and find an interesting and dominant role of the nuclear symmetry energy slope on pinning strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09219v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Hao Tu, Ang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Galactic Winds in M82 I: the recent starburt and launch of outflow in simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the launch of the galactic outflow in M82 through high-resolution hydrodynamic simulations. Employing a sink-particle module, we self-consistently resolve the star formation and feedback processes, avoiding the reliance on various assumed models as in previous works. We probe the effects of different stellar feedback mechanisms, the gas return from star-forming clouds and initial gas disc mass on the starburst and launch of outflow. Our simulations can generate a starburst that lasts 20-30 Myr, peaking at 20-50 $\rm{M_{\odot} yr^{-1}}$. However, the total stellar mass formed in the starburst in our simulations often exceeds M82's estimated value. The outflow's launch occurs in two stages. Initially, continuous SNe explosions form numerous small bubbles, merging into a super bubble foam composed of low-density warm/hot gas and high-density cool filaments. After approximately 10 Myr of SN energy injection, the super bubble breakout the disc, marking the second stage, which takes 10-15 Myr to develop a multiphase, kpc-scale outflow. Our simulations reveal that cool filaments within the turbulent ISM can survive from the feedback associated to the starburst, then were entrained into the outflow and stretched to hundreds pc in length due to interaction with the hot wind. While the mass loading factor of the well-developed outflow is comparable to M82, the cool gas mass outflow rate is often lower, and its velocity is slower than the estimated value in M82 by $50\%-60\%$. Warm and hot gas are $20\%-30\%$ slower. SN feedback acts as the primary driver of the outflow, while gas return significantly influences the starburst and outflow properties. The initial mass of gas disc has a moderate effect, while stellar wind and radiation feedback have minor effect. To address the shortcomings in our results, enhanced SN feedback effect, due to clustered SNe, is likely necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09452v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Rui Wang, Weishan Zhu, Xue-Fu Li, Wen-Sheng Hong, Long-Long Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of Star-planet Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1712.02814</link>
      <description>arXiv:1712.02814v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Planets interact with their host stars through gravity, radiation and magnetic fields, and for those giant planets that orbit their stars within ~10 stellar radii (~0.1 AU for a sun-like star), star-planet interactions (SPI) are observable with a wide variety of photometric, spectroscopic and spectropolarimetric studies. At such close distances, the planet orbits within the sub-alfvenic radius of the star in which the transfer of energy and angular momentum between the two bodies is particularly efficient. The magnetic interactions appear as enhanced stellar activity modulated by the planet as it orbits the star rather than only by stellar rotation. Such observations allowed for the determination of the magnetic field strengths on the surfaces of four hot Jupiters. These vary between 20 G and 120 G, in line with scaling laws that connect the strength of the magnetic field to the internal heat flow in giant planets. These field strengths are informative for the study of the internal dynamics and atmospheric evolution of exoplanets. The nature of magnetic SPI is modeled to be strongly affected by both the stellar and planetary magnetic fields, possibly influencing the magnetic activity of both, as well as affecting the particle environment, the migration of the planet, and even the rotational evolution of the star. As phase-resolved observational techniques are applied to a large statistical sample of hot Jupiter systems, extensions to other tightly orbiting stellar systems, such as smaller planets close to M dwarfs become possible. In these systems, star-planet separations of tens of stellar radii begin to coincide with the radiative habitable zone where planetary magnetic fields are likely a necessary condition for surface habitability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1712.02814v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgenya L. Shkolnik, Joe Llama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-common-envelope planetary nebulae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06831v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Close-binary central stars of planetary nebulae offer a unique tool with which to study the critical and yet poorly understood common-envelope phase of binary stellar evolution. Furthermore, as the nebula itself is thought to comprise the ionised remnant of the ejected common envelope, such planetary nebulae can be used to directly probe the mass, morphology and dynamics of the ejecta. In this review, I summarise our current understanding of the importance of binarity in the formation of planetary nebulae as well as what they may be able to tell us about the common-envelope phase - including the possible relationships with other post-common-envelope phenomena like stellar mergers, novae and type Ia supernovae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06831v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Temperature versus Orbital Period relation of AM CVns: Insights from their Donors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05442v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We studied the spectral energy distribution (SED) of 22 known AM~CVns with orbital periods ($P_{orb}$) larger than 35~min using multiwavelength public photometric data to estimate the effective temperature of the accreting white dwarf. We find an infrared (IR) excess in all systems when compared to a single blackbody, both when the disk should be extended and when it should be truncated by the accretor's magnetic field. This suggests a dominant contribution from the donor to the IR flux. When fitting two blackbodies, the temperature of the hot component decreases with $P_{orb}$, as expected by evolutionary models. Temperatures for systems with $35&lt;P_{orb}&lt;45~\text{min}$ are consistent with models. Systems with $P_{orb}\gtrsim45~\text{min}$ have higher temperatures than expected. The second blackbody temperature does not correlate with $P_{orb}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05442v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2515-5172/ad9a64</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Colin W. Macrie, Liliana Rivera Sandoval, Yuri Cavecchi, Tin Long Sunny Wong, Manuel Pichardo Marcano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong signature of right-handed circularly polarized photoionization close to the cyclotron line in the atmosphere of magnetic white dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06627v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic fields break the symmetry of the interaction of atoms with photons with different polarizations, yielding chirality and anisotropy properties. The dependence of the absorption spectrum on the polarization, a phenomenon known as dichroism, is present in the atmosphere of magnetic white dwarfs. Its evaluation for processes in the continuum spectrum has been elusive so far due to the absence of appropriate ionization equilibrium models and incomplete data on photoionization cross sections. We combined rigorous solutions to the equilibrium of atomic populations with approximate cross sections to calculate the absolute opacity due to photoionization in a magnetized hydrogen gas. We predict a strong right-handed circularly polarized absorption ($\chi^+$) formed blueward of the cyclotron resonance for fields from about 14 to several hundred megagauss. In energies lower than the cyclotron fundamental, this absorption shows a deep trough with respect to linear and left-handed circular polarizations that steepens with the field strength. The jump in $\chi^+$ is due to the confluence of a large number of photoionization continua produced by right-handed circularly polarized transitions from atomic states with a nonnegative magnetic quantum number toward different Landau levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06627v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ren\'e D. Rohrmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST captures a sudden stellar outburst and inner disk wall destruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00136v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present JWST/MIRI observations of T~Cha, a highly variable ($\Delta V \sim$3-5\,mag) accreting Sun-like star surrounded by a disk with a large ($\sim 15$\,au) dust gap. We find that the JWST mid-infrared spectrum is signiticantly different from the {\it Spitzer} spectrum obtained 17 years before, where the emission at short wavelengths ($5-10 \mu m$) has decreased by $\sim 2/3$ while at longer wavelengths ($15-25 \mu m$) it increased by up to a factor of $\sim 3$. This 'seesaw' behavior is contemporary with a fairly constant higher optical emission captured by the All Sky Automated Survey. By analyzing and modelling both SEDs, we propose that JWST caught the star during an outburst that destructed the asymmetric inner disk wall responsible for the high optical variability and lower $15-25$\,micron\ emission during the {\it Spitzer} time. The dust mass lost during this outburst is estimated to be comparable ($\sim 1/5$) to the upper limit of the total micron-sized dust mass in the inner disk of T~Cha now. Monitoring this system during possible future outbursts and more observations of its quiescent state will reveal if the inner disk can be replenished or will continue to be depleted and vanish.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00136v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad90a1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chengyan Xie, Ilaria Pascucci, Dingshan Deng, Naman S. Bajaj, Richard Alexander, Andrew Sellek, Agnes Kospal, Giulia Ballabio, Uma Gorti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
