<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 05:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A new estimate of the zero-point shift of the Gaia DR3 parallaxes obtained from a comparison with VLBI measurements of masers and radio stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The most complete sample of radio stars and masers with trigonometric parallaxes measured by the VLBI method, common with the Gaia EDR3 and Gaia DR3 catalogs, has been compiled using literature data. The sample contains 151 stars. An analysis of the differences in parallaxes and proper motions of Gaia-VLBI stars has been performed. A new estimate of the systematic shift of the Gaia parallax zero point relative to the inertial coordinate system has been obtained: $\Delta\pi=-0.038\pm0.011$ mas. The obtained estimates of the relative rotation rates confirm the absence of a significant rotation of the Gaia\,DR3 system relative to the extragalactic coordinate system, which in this case is represented by VLBI measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11871v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astronomy Letters, 2025, Vol. 51, No. 7</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vadim Vadimovich Bobylev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atmospheric Response to Large Electron Beam Fluxes in Solar Flares III: Comprehensive Modeling of the Brightest Observed Near-Ultraviolet Continuum Source in an X9 Solar Flare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I report on the high resolution spectra of the remarkable X9 solar flare of 2024 Oct 03 (SOL2024-10-03T12:08) and evaluate the extent to which nonthermal electron beams that generate dense chromospheric condensations can power very bright kernels in solar flares. 1D Radiative-hydrodynamic models predict extreme H$\alpha$ near-wing broadening, bright continuum intensities, and a rapid Fe II red wing asymmetry evolution at the brightest NUV continuum source in the flare. Detailed comparisons to the spectral observations reveal that the H$\alpha$ line is too broad, the Fe II red wing is too bright, and the NUV continuum decays too slowly in a fiducial high-flux beam model. However, chromospheric condensations with maximum electron densities of $n_e \approx 5 \times 10^{14}$ cm$^{-3}$ and optical depths $\tau \approx 1$ in the near wing of H$\alpha$ are consistent with the observed intensity of a broad spectrum in the Southern ribbon. Model similarities demonstrate that Fe I emission lines and the FUV continuum intensity can form at chromospheric heights during flares, but I find that the ratios of the NUV to FUV continuum intensities are generally too large in the models. This suggests that radiative-hydrodynamic models of chromospheric condensations cool through $T \approx 30,000$ K too rapidly. The larger than expected FUV continuum intensities are not nearly bright enough to explain recent stellar megaflare spectra from the Hubble Space Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11915v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam F. Kowalski (University of Colorado, National Solar Observatory, Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Physics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>He-star donor pathway for the hypervelocity star D6-2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Type Ia supernovae are thermonuclear explosions of white dwarfs, yet the nature of their progenitor systems remains uncertain. Recent discoveries of hypervelocity stars provide unique constraints, as these stars likely represent the surviving companions of such explosions. Using detailed binary evolution models computed with MESA and population synthesis with MSE, we investigate the outcomes of hot subdwarf + white dwarf binaries undergoing helium accretion. We find that donors can nearly exhaust their helium and form compact, C/O cores before explosion. The predicted ejection velocities span a broad distribution reaching up to $\sim 1000\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$, with D6-2 representing the extreme high-velocity tail of this population. We estimate analytically that the thin residual helium envelope can be stripped by the supernova ejecta, producing a C/O-rich surface composition consistent with the observed spectrum. The Type Ia supernova rate from this channel is ${\sim}(1.69\pm0.06)\times10^{-5}\,\mathrm{M_\odot^{-1}}$, consistent with 1% of the observed Type Ia supernova rate. Hot subdwarf + white dwarf binaries containing nearly exhausted He-star donors can therefore naturally explain the velocity and composition of D6-2 while providing a quantitatively consistent contribution to the observed Type Ia supernova rate. Our models predict a distribution of surviving donor remnants with various core He fractions and with ejection velocities extending down to $\sim 450\,\mathrm{ km\,s^{-1}}$. The orbital velocities of donor stars in this progenitor channel naturally yield orbital velocities consistent with US 708, LP 40-365 stars, and D6-2, indicating that a single class of thermonuclear supernova progenitors can account for their entire range of ejection velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11998v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abinaya Swaruba Rajamuthukumar, Ruediger Pakmor, Stephen Justham, Aakash Bhat, Ken J Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doppler imaging combined with high-cadence photometry. I. Revisiting the surface of a pre-main-sequence flare star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Latitude distribution of stellar magnetic activity is not well constrained by observations, despite its importance for a better understanding of stellar dynamos. We aim to obtain an accurate reconstruction of the surface spot distribution on the young, rapidly rotating K2 star PW And by combining spectroscopic and photometric diagnostics. In particular, we seek to assess how the inclusion of continuous high-precision TESS photometry in parallel with high-resolution spectroscopy improves latitude recovery of starspots, especially at low latitudes and in the southern hemisphere, which are poorly constrained by Doppler imaging (DI) alone. We explore the spatial origins of the observed white-light flares. We performed simultaneous Doppler imaging and light curve inversion (DI+LCI) using contemporaneous high-resolution GAOES-RV spectra from the 3.8 m Seimei telescope (R~65000) and high-precision TESS light curves. Surface reconstructions employ the SpotDIPy code to model both line profiles and continuum brightness variations. We compare DI+LCI maps with DI-only solutions, conduct artificial-spot simulations to evaluate the effects of latitude, phase coverage, and S/N on reconstruction reliability. We also investigate the spatial correlation between the DI+LCI reconstructed map and flares detected in the TESS data. The DI+LCI reconstruction reveals significant spot features at mid-to-low latitudes, equatorial regions, and even in the southern hemisphere. Simulations show that DI+LCI provides more accurate reconstructions than DI-only, especially under conditions of incomplete phase coverage and low S/N, by better recovering both spot latitudes and filling factors. A comparison between the DI+LCI map and the TESS flare timings also suggests potential association between flare occurrence and reconstructed spot longitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12190v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanghee Lee, Engin Bahar, Hakan Volkan \c{S}enavc{\i}, Emre I\c{s}{\i}k, Kai Ikuta, Kosuke Namekata, Haruhi Nagata, Kiyoe Kawauchi, Masashi Omiya, Hideyuki Izumiura, Akito Tajitsu, Bun'ei Sato, Satoshi Honda, Daisaku Nogami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pre-Supernova Multiple Giant Eruptions in Massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive stars can exhibit giant eruptions with high mass loss shortly before their explosion as a core-collapse Supernova. These multiple giant eruptions (MGEs) may have a commutative effect that brings the star to a different state, possible one that favors the explosion. To address this problem, we evolve a 100 solar mass star and initiate a series of three giant eruptions lasting one year each, testing different mass loss rates and different metallicities. Following each eruption, we track the recovery phase to examine the post-eruption behavior of the star and its recovery timescale. The MGEs lead to a decrease in luminosity, accompanied by a slight increase in temperature. Later, during the recovery phases as the star starts to retain its equilibrium state, its luminosity increases. The recovery time-scale varies significantly after each eruption for independent on the mass loss rate, but it is shorter for lower metallicities. For the higher mass-loss rates during the recovery phase, the outer layers of the star exhibit oscillations and undergo compression at higher metallicity. These oscillations are most likely a consequence of thermal imbalance in the outer envelope. This behavior at higher mass-loss rates also suggests that the thermal readjustments during recovery may create favorable conditions for a subsequent eruption of the star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12312v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhawna Mukhija, Amit Kashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling eMSTO in NGC 2355: Stellar Rotation and Binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The extended Main Sequence Turn-off (eMSTO) in the open cluster NGC 2355 is investigated using precise astrometry and photometry from Gaia DR3 and spectroscopic data from the Gaia-ESO Survey. We find a clear positive correlation between the rotational velocity (v sin i) and color of eMSTO stars, supporting the role of stellar rotation and gravity darkening in causing the observed color spread. Contrary to predictions from binary tidal-locking scenarios, spatial distribution analysis reveals that fast-rotating stars are preferentially concentrated in the cluster's central regions. This finding provides the observational evidence favoring star-disk interactions during the pre-main-sequence phase, rather than tidal locking in binaries, as the primary mechanism responsible for the origin of rotational spread in eMSTO stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12496v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jayanand Maurya, Yu Zhang, Hubiao Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulations of structured upflows from plumes and their connection to the solar wind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12557v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Small-scale transient jetlet activity and associated upflows from coronal hole plumes are potential sources of the solar wind. To elucidate the magnetic origins and driving mechanisms of such upflows, we perform three-dimensional radiative magnetohydrodynamic simulations using the MURaM code, spanning from the upper convection zone to the low corona. We synthesize Fe\,{\sc x} 174\,{\AA} emission to capture the plume evolution comparable to observations, examining underlying plasma flows, thermal structures, and magnetic topologies. We identify a pronounced transition from cool downflows in the lower atmosphere to hot upflows in the corona at the interface between plume-rooted like-polarity flux concentrations. These upflows are threaded by a complex, filamentary network of Quasi-Separatrix Layers (QSLs) -- a topology distinct from standard interchange reconnection scenarios. The domain-averaged mass flux over a 38-minute interval ranges from $10^{-9}$ to $10^{-8}\,\mathrm{g\,cm^{-2}\,s^{-1}}$, substantially exceeding observed solar-wind loss rates. Our results demonstrate that highly structured plasma outflows are channeled along strong QSLs at open--open field boundaries, providing a pathway to sustain the solar wind from coronal-hole plumes without requiring interchange reconnection triggered by opposite-polarity flux emergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12557v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamlesh Bora, Lakshmi Pradeep Chitta, Yajie Chen, Damien Przybylski, David Pontin, Nikil Panyam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IdentYS: A Python-Based Tool for Identifying Young Stars in Star-Forming Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Research on young stellar populations is essential to understand the properties of embedded clusters and advance theories of their formation. This has driven advancements in methodologies for star detection, leading to the development of valuable databases and software. We present the scientific justification and operating principles of the IdentYS tool, which is designed to identify young stellar objects (YSOs) in star-forming regions. The tool facilitates the identification of young stars with infrared (IR) excess in remote and embedded star-forming regions, focusing primarily on Class I and II YSOs. For this purpose, near- and mid-IR photometric data and five colour-colour diagrams (J - H) vs. (H - K), K - [3.6] vs. [3.6] - [4.5], [3.6] - [4.5] vs. [5.8] - [8.0], [3.6] - [4.5] vs. [8.0] - [24], and [3.4] - [4.6] vs. [4.6] - [12] are used. The purity of the YSOs sample is enhanced by excluding field contamination from stellar and extragalactic objects. As a result, we compile a list of YSO candidates displaying the source designation, astrometric, and photometric parameters, as well as information on the evolutionary stage determined by the presence of IR excess, as indicated by certain diagrams. The application of this program can greatly streamline the statistical analysis of young stellar populations across diverse star-forming regions, including distant and deeply embedded ones, which typically require processing large volumes of initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12696v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Nikoghosyan, D. Baghdasaryan, D. Andreasyan, N. Azatyan, A. Samsonyan, A. Yeghikyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observations of Five Southern-Hemisphere Cataclysmic Binary Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present observations and analyses of five little-studied cataclysmic binary stars in the southern celestial hemisphere. Our new observations are from the South African Astronomical Observatory. The objects and salient results are as follows: (i) 6dF0752-54 is a dwarf nova with an orbital period Porb = 5.05 hr that shows a contribution from a mid-M type secondary in its mean spectrum. (ii) J0916-26 had been suspected of being a magnetic CV with an eclipse period of 3.37 hr. Our spectrum corroborates this classification. (iii) GSC 08944 is a novalike variable with Porb = 3.80 hr. Archival photometry also shows a persistent photometric period near 4.03 hr, apparently from a positive super- hump. Its emission line behavior is consistent with an SW Sextantis-type novalike. (iv) MGAB-V253, also Gaia20eys, had been identified as a short-period eclipsing novalike with Porb = 1.44 hr. Our spectrum shows shows broad emission lines consistent with this, and the extensive TESS data show a persistent modulation near 1.35 hr, evidently a negative superhump. It is less luminous than most novalikes, but significantly brighter than quiescent dwarf novae with comparably short periods. (v) Finally, DDE 45 shows a complicated variability history, cycling rapidly between high and low states for a time and more recently showing outbursts resembling a U Gem-type dwarf nova. We find a 2.07 hr radial velocity period, which also appears in archival TESS photometry. The emission lines are double-peaked, with an orbital S-wave similar to low-inclination dwarf novae.
  To be published in Astronomical Journal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12762v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John R. Thorstensen (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Annabelle E. Niblett (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Shreya Gandhi (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Lauren P. Zanarini (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Gavin D. Goss (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Arnav Singh (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Divik Verma (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Ryan C. Hickox (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Emmanuel A. Durodola (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College), Jiaqi Martin Ying (Department of Physics,Astronomy, Dartmouth College)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Temporal Variability in the Magnetic Dichotomy of Late M Dwarf Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapidly rotating late M dwarfs are observed in two different branches of magnetic activity, although they operate in the same stellar parameter range. Current empirical evidence indicates that M dwarfs with spectral types ranging from M3 / M4 to late-type M dwarfs, stellar masses smaller than 0.15 M$_\odot$, and rotational period shorter than four days display either a stable dipolar magnetic field or magnetic structures with significant time variability. The magnetic activity of fully convective M dwarfs is known to be regulated by a mechanism named the ${\alpha}^2$ dynamo. To further constrain the physics of this mechanism, we use a low-dimensional model for thermally driven magnetoconvection producing an ${\alpha}^2$ dynamo, specifically a modified magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) shell model. Although the model neglects density stratification, it captures the essential nonlinear dynamics of an $\alpha^2$ dynamo. Therefore, the results should be interpreted in a qualitative sense, highlighting possible trends rather than providing direct quantitative predictions for fully convective stars. The model is validated by comparing the statistical properties of magnetic polarity reversals with paleomagnetic data, since the geodynamo provides the only natural ${\alpha}^2$ dynamo with sufficiently rich reversal statistics. Our findings reveal that increased convective heat transport correlates with more frequent magnetic-polarity reversals, resulting in enhanced magnetic variability. This suggests that the observed magnetic dichotomy in late M dwarfs could be interpreted in terms of differences in global heat transport efficiency. However, additional models and observations of M dwarfs are needed to further constrain this interpretation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12807v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppina Nigro, Francesco Berrilli, Giuseppe Bono, Dario Del Moro, Luca Giovannelli, Valentina Penza, Raffaele Reda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling stellar convective transport with plumes : II. Transport Properties of Locally and Non-locally driven Convection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform three-dimensional hydrodynamic simulations of two idealized regimes of stellar convection: a cooling-driven model (Model C) and an entropy-gradient-driven model (Model S). The two regimes exhibit striking contrasts: while Model S develops large, relatively stationary eddies excited at depth, Model C is dominated near the surface by intermittent plume-like downflows that produce broad non-Gaussian velocity distributions and a turbulent energy flux that exceeds Model S by nearly an order of magnitude in the upper convection zone. Conventional gradient-diffusion (GD) closures reproduce the transport in Model S but significantly underestimate it in Model C, demonstrating that plume-driven convection lies beyond the scope of local, gradient-based models. To address this, we introduce a Time-Space Double Averaging (TSDA) method that extracts coherent fluctuations, yielding a diagnostic variable $\tilde{\boldsymbol{u}}$ that peaks where the flux is largest. Building on this insight, we propose a modified GD closure in which the turbulent diffusivity is corrected by a plume-mediated term, achieving quantitative agreement with simulation results. Although the closure requires a calibrated model parameter and a careful choice of the averaging window, it provides a physically transparent framework that links coherent plume dynamics to mean-field transport, and offers a pathway toward improved subgrid models for non-equilibrium stellar convection zones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12824v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youhei Masada, Tomoya Takiwaki, Nobumitsu Yoko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SN 2016iog: A fast declining Type II-L supernova with an ultra-faint tail, persistently interacting with circumstellar material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present optical photometric and spectroscopic observations of the rapidly declining Type IIL supernova (SN) 2016iog. SN 2016iog reached its peak $\sim$ 14 days after explosion, with an absolute magnitude in the $V$ band of $-18.64 \pm 0.15$ mag, followed by a steep decline of $8.85 \pm 0.15$~mag~(100\,d)$^{-1}$ post-peak. Such a high decline rate makes SN~2016iog one of the fastest declining Type~IIL SNe observed to date. The rapid rise in the light curve, combined with the nearly featureless continuum observed in the spectrum at +9.3 days, suggests the presence of interaction. In the recombination phase, we observed broad H$\alpha$ lines that persist at all epochs. In addition, the prominent double-peaked H$\alpha$ feature observed in the late-time spectrum (+190.8 days) is likely attributable either to significant dust formation within a cool dense shell or to asymmetric circumstellar material. These features suggest the presence of sustained interaction around SN~2016iog. We propose that the observed characteristics of SN~2016iog can be qualitatively explained by assuming a low-mass H-rich envelope surrounding a red supergiant progenitor star with low-density circumstellar material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12929v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. -H. Peng, S. Benetti, Y. -Z. Cai, A. Pastorello, G. Valerin, A. Reguitti, A. Fiore, Q. -L. Fang, Z. -Y. Wang, M. Berton, L. Borsato, E. Cappellaro, E. Congiu, N. Elias-Rosa, V. Granata, J. Isern, G. La Mura, P. Ochner, R. Raddi, G. Terreran, L. Tomasella, M. Turatto, S. -Y. Yan, S. -P. Pei, C. -Y. Wu, S. Zha, X. -F. Wang, B. Wang, Y. Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The B[e] Phenomenon in Supergiants. A Result of Mass Transfer in Binaries, Mergers, or What?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13058v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The B[e] phenomenon discovered nearly 50 years ago features the presence of forbidden emission lines due to extended and dense circumstellar gas and large IR excesses due to the radiation from circumstellar dust in a wide variety of objects from pre-main-sequence stars to Planetary Nebulae. It also shows up in a small group of supergiants that includes Luminous Blue Variables, such as {\eta} Carinae. Over the years, some of them were proven to be binary systems, but the presence of a secondary component in other is still elusive. At the same time, there is growing evidence that the B[e] phenomenon can be due to binary mergers or interactions in triple systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13058v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatoly S. Miroshnichenko, Sergey V. Zharikov, Nadezhda L. Vaidman, Serik A. Khokhlov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral component imaging of solar X-ray flares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13213v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar hard X-ray observations provide diagnostics of the hottest plasmas and of nonthermal electron populations present during solar flares and coronal mass ejections. HXR images of specific energy ranges often contain overlapping contributions of these components, complicating their interpretation. This is even more challenging as HXR imagers generally use an indirect imaging system. Our work aims to separately image individual spectral components, such as thermal loops, superhot sources, and nonthermal footpoint sources, rather than obtaining images of specific energy ranges that show a combination of all components. We introduce a new method called spectral component imaging and apply it to observations provided by the Spectrometer/Telescope for Imaging X-rays (STIX) aboard Solar Orbiter. First, the flare integrated HXR spectrum is fitted with individual spectral components to get the relative contributions of each component in each native STIX energy channel. In a second step, a set of linear equations is created based on these weights and the observed, energy-dependent STIX visibilities. The visibilities of the individual spectral components are derived by means of a linear least-squares approach and are subsequently utilized for image reconstructions. We demonstrate the effectiveness of spectral component imaging on four different flares observed by STIX. This method provides powerful diagnostics, particularly for flares with hot and superhot components, allowing us to spatially separate these two thermal components. We apply our methodology to the nonthermal peak of the X7.1 flare SOL2024-10-01, and we find that the superhot component is located 4.8 Mm away from the hot thermal loops. The thermal energy of the superhot component is approximately 20% of the energy content of the hot component, highlighting the significance of superhot components in the total flare energy budget.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13213v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muriel Zo\"e Stiefel, Paolo Massa, Alessia Guidetti, Marina Battaglia, S\"am Krucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spontaneous Genesis of Solar Prominence Structures Driven by Supergranulation in Three-Dimensional Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar prominences usually have a horizontally elongated body with many feet extending to the solar surface, resembling a multi-arch bridge with many bridge piers. The basic mechanism by which solar prominences acquire these common structures during their evolution, however, remains an unresolved question. For the first time, our three-dimensional magneto-frictional simulation, driven by supergranular motions, self-consistently replicates the commonly observed multi-arch bridge morphology and its characteristic structures of solar quiescent prominences in a magnetic flux rope. In comparison with traditional views, our simulations demonstrate that the spine, feet, and voids (bubbles) are inherent prominence structures spontaneously forming as the flux rope evolves to a mature state. The voids mainly consist of legs of sheared magnetic loops caused by unbalanced supergranular flows, and prominence feet settle at the bottom of helical field lines piled up from the photosphere to the spine. Similarities between the simulated prominences and observed real prominences by the Chinese H$\alpha$ Solar Explorer, the New Vacuum Solar Telescope, and NASA's Solar Dynamics Observatory suggest the high validity of our model. This work corroborates the pivotal role of photospheric supergranulation as a helicity injection source in the formation and shaping of quiescent prominence structures within the solar atmosphere, thereby paving a new avenue for future investigations into their fine dynamics and stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13252v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanxin Chen, Chun Xia, Hechao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stray Light Correction for the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a point spread function (PSF) and deconvolution procedure to remove stray light from the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) data. Pre-launch calibration observations, post-launch Venus transit and lunar transit data were used to develop the PSF and evaluate how well it reproduced the observed scattering. The PSF reported differs from previous stray light removal efforts since we do not use Gaussians as the central mathematical component. Instead, we use a Lorenztian convolved with an Airy function. In 2018, the HMI team began providing full-disk, stray-light-corrected data daily. Intensity, Doppler, magnetogram, and vector magnetic field data are provided. The deconvolution uses a Richardson-Lucy algorithm and takes less than one second per full-disk image. The results, on average, show decreases in umbral continuum intensity, a doubling of the granulation intensity contrast, increases in the total field strength, most notably in plage by $\sim$1.4--2.5 the original value, and a partial correction for the convective blueshift. Local helioseismology analyses using corrected data yield results that are consistent with those from uncorrected data, with only negligible differences, except in sunspot regions. The new data are found in JSOC with names similar to the original but with the qualifying term '$\_dcon$' or '$\_dconS$' appended, denoting whether the deconvolution was applied to the filtergrams or Stokes images. The HMI team recommends using the corrected data for improved visual clarity, more accurate irradiance reconstruction, better co-alignment with high-resolution data, reduced errors in tracking algorithms, and improved magnetic field strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13348v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Norton, T. L. Duvall, Jr., J. Schou, R. S. Bogart, J. Zhao, C. Rabello-Soares, P. J. Levens, J. T. Hoeksema, C. S. Baldner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Unusual Velocity Field in a Sunspot Penumbra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The photospheric Evershed flow is normally oriented radially outward, yet sometimes opposite velocities are observed not only in the chromosphere but also in the photospheric layers of the penumbra. We study the velocity field in a special case of an active region with two mature sunspots, where one of them formed several days later than the main one. Between the two spots, flux emergence is still ongoing influencing the velocity pattern. We observed the active region NOAA 12146 on August 24, 2014, with the GREGOR Fabry-P\'erot Interferometer (GFPI) and the Blue Imaging Channel (BIC) of the GREGOR solar telescope at Observatorio del Teide on Tenerife. Context data from the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) onboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) complement the high-resolution data. In the penumbra of a newly formed spot, we observe opposite Doppler velocity streams of up to +-2 km/s very close to each other. These velocities extend beyond the outer penumbral boundary and cross also the polarity-inversion line. The properties of the magnetic field do not change significantly between these two streams. Although the magnetic field is almost horizontal, we do not detect large transversal velocities in horizontal flow maps obtained with the local correlation technique. The ongoing emergence of magnetic flux in an active region causes flows of opposite directions intruding the penumbra of a pre-existing sunspot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13374v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Balthasar, C. Denker, A. Diercke, S. J. Gonz\'alez Manrique, C. Kuckein, J. L\"ohner B\"ottcher, R. E. Louis, M. Sobotka, M. Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating magnetic activity cycles in solar-like oscillators using asteroseismic data from the K2 mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results of an investigation into the possible presence of magnetic activity cycles in stars observed in two observational campaigns by the K2 mission. This study was based on the KEYSTONE asteroseismic sample of solar-like oscillators, which contained 20 stars for which we were able to determine whether the asteroseismic p-mode frequencies varied in time. These frequency shifts ($\delta\nu$) were determined using a cross-correlation method and using the individual mode frequencies, obtained by fitting power spectra. Three stars were found to exhibit $\delta\nu$ larger than their associated errors ($\sigma_{\delta\nu}$) using both methods, while two more stars exhibited $\delta\nu&gt;\sigma_{\delta\nu}$ when the cross correlation was used and a further two stars exhibited $\delta\nu&gt;\sigma_{\delta\nu}$ when the fitted frequencies were used. When considering the whole sample of 20 stars, the amplitude of $\delta\nu$ showed no dependence on the large frequency separation and metallicity. However, $\delta\nu$ was observed to increase with rotation rate and effective temperature. Our sample contained a number of evolved subgiant stars, allowing us to expand the parameter space usually considered when comparing $\delta\nu$ with stellar parameters. While $\delta\nu$ was small for all of the evolved stars, one was found to have $\delta\nu&gt;\sigma_{\delta\nu}$, raising the possibility that these evolved stars may still exhibit variable magnetic activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13398v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gleb Berloff, Anne-Marie Broomhall, George T. Hookway, Mikkel N. Lund, Laura Jade Millson, Dmitrii Kolotkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic fields in the close neighborhood of LDN 328 core</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linearly polarized dust emission traces the plane-of-sky magnetic field structure, thus allowing us to investigate the role of magnetic fields in the formation and evolution of cloud cores. In this work, we present observations of dust polarization at 850 $\mu{\rm m}$ wavelength toward the LDN\,328 (hereafter, L328) core and its neighborhood regions, classified as R1, R2, and R3, using the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope (JCMT) with SCUBA-2/POL-2. This study extends our previous work on magnetic fields in L328 across different spatial scales. We used the JCMT/POL-2 data in the near vicinity of the L328 core to study the magnetic fields in its nearby regions. We identified clumps in these regions using the \texttt{FellWalker} algorithm and derived the dust temperature and column density by fitting the spectral energy distribution (SED) using combined JCMT and \textit{Herschel} dust continuum maps. We analyzed the magnetic field morphology in the vicinity of the L328 core and employed the structure function analysis to determine the magnetic field dispersion angle. We used the modified Davis-Chandrasekhar-Fermi (DCF) method to estimate magnetic field strengths and also derived the mass-to-flux ratio and Alfv\'en Mach number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13427v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Gupta, Archana Soam, Janik Karoly, Chang Won Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Precision Multi-Period Analysis of the Ellipsoidal Variable Candidate TIC~470127886 from TESS Photometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first detailed photometric characterization of TIC 470127886, a previously unstudied multi-periodic variable star discovered in TESS photometry. Analysis of 145,374 high-cadence observations spanning 696 days (944-day baseline, 2023 January-2024 October) across 10 sectors (60, 59, 58, 53, 52, 73, 86, 79, 78, 85) reveals complex periodic variability with a primary period of 5.544527 +/- 0.004307 days and false alarm probability 1.47 x 10^-87. Lomb-Scargle analysis identifies three significant periods at 5.545, 5.801, and 8.874 days with amplitudes of 15,702, 12,772, and 12,670 ppm. The phase-folded light curve shows smooth, sinusoidal morphology consistent with ellipsoidal variation from tidal distortion in a close binary, with no eclipse features. A three-component sinusoidal model, appropriate for ellipsoidal variables, provides excellent fit quality. Validation tests confirm signal authenticity and persistence, and systematic checks verify no contamination from nearby stars (&gt;3 mag fainter). We classify TIC 470127886 as an ellipsoidal variable candidate with 0.70 confidence, with multi-period behavior suggesting additional variability mechanisms beyond tidal distortion. This work demonstrates high-precision characterization of complex multi-periodic variables in TESS photometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13610v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roo Weerasinghe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis of eclipsing binaries with monotonic orbital-period variations: A-type W UMa contact systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On the basis of monotonic orbital-period variations, this study aims to identify genuine relationships between binary parameters and the rates of mass transfer (MT), mass loss (ML), and angular momentum loss (AML). Sample binaries with monotonic period variations are collected from the literature, together with well-determined binary parameters. Assuming the monotonic variations are responsible for any one of the MT, ML, and AML, their rates are calculated with the rates of change of period. After selecting crucial parameters using partial least-squares analysis, a parameter that exhibits the closest correlation with any one of the derived rates is further selected using partial regression plots. Moreover, power-law relationships are found for the discovered correlations. The properties of the sample binaries are also investigated by examining associations between binary parameters. In the systems with negative period variations, it is found that the rate of MT from more- to less-massive stars is a function of the primary radius; the AML rate is a function of the fill-out factor. In addition, the relationships between the mass ratio and stellar masses indicate that the ML rate relative to the MT rate decreases with increasing mass ratio below ~0.46. Meanwhile, in the systems with positive variations, it is found that the rate of MT from less- to more-massive stars is a function of the luminosity ratio and/or mass ratio; the ML rate is a function of the secondary temperature. The discussion also addresses possible processes occurring in the sample binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13617v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinjirou Kouzuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The physical properties of post-mass-transfer binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aims. We present and analyse the detailed physical properties of six binary stellar systems, originally proposed as possible star-black hole binaries on the basis of radial velocities from Gaia's third data release, but soon recognised as likely post-mass-transfer binary systems with stripped companions. Methods. We used multi-epoch high-resolution FEROS spectra and spectral disentangling paired with stellar templates to derive effective temperatures, $T_\mathrm{eff}$; stellar radii, R*; and projected rotational velocities, v$\sin{i}$ for both components in all systems along with the mass ratio, q = $M_\mathrm{accretor}/M_\mathrm{donor}$ and the components' flux ratio as a function of wavelength. Results. Our analysis directly confirms that all systems are post-mass-transfer binaries with two luminous stars, i.e. no black hole companions. Each system contains an A-type accretor component that is rapidly rotating and a cooler very low-mass donor (~ 0.25M$\odot$) that is overluminous. Five of the systems show no trace of any emission lines, implying that there is no current mass transfer, consistent with our inferred radii, in all cases within the Roche volume. The data are generally consistent with stable case AB mass transfer with $\beta$ (the fraction of mass lost from the accretor) less than 0.7. While the accretor components rotate rapidly, they rotate well below the critical rotation rate, $v_\mathrm{crit}$, even though there must have been enough mass transfer to spin them up to a significant fraction of $v_\mathrm{crit}$, according to theoretical models of angular momentum transfer. As neither magnetic braking nor tidal synchronisation should have been effective in spinning down the stars, our results suggest that either mass accretion does not increase the angular momentum of the accretors to their critical values or the systems never reached these values in the first place.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rhys Seeburger, Hans-Walter Rix, Kareem El-Badry, Johanna M\"uller-Horn, Alex J. Dimoff, Jan Henneco, Jaime I. Villase\~nor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar Flares in the TESS Light Curves of Planet-hosting M dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: M dwarfs are magnetically active stars that frequently produce flares, which have implications for both stellar evolution and exoplanet studies. Flare occurrence rates and activity levels of M dwarfs correlate with stellar characteristics such as age, mass, and rotation period. We search TESS observations of a known active population of M dwarfs as well as a volume-limited sample of M dwarfs within 15 parsecs. We detect flares in the light curves of these stars, including 276 of 538 M dwarfs within 15 pc, and calculate cumulative flare frequency distributions (FFDs) for each star. Based on flaring behavior, we categorize stars into relatively higher and lower activity groups and fit power laws to their FFDs to compare the power law exponent ($\alpha$) across activity levels. We find $\alpha =1.99 \pm 0.07$ for the combined FFD of the lower activity M dwarfs, compared to averages of $\alpha = 1.94 \pm 0.58$ for highly active stars with 10-100 detected flares, and $\alpha = 2.03 \pm 0.43$ for those with &gt; 100 detected flares, suggesting little evolution in the power law distribution of flares as M dwarfs transition from high to low activity states. The uncertainties for the active star groups reflect the standard deviation of $\alpha$ values across individual stars within each subset. Because stellar flares and associated stellar activity complicate exoplanet observations, we also examine the subset of M dwarfs with JWST transmission spectroscopy follow-up observations in Cycles 1-3. The flares we detect for these targets are consistent with the broader 15 pc sample, providing context for interpreting planetary atmosphere retrievals from JWST spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13716v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae1ddf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin K. Capistrant, Jason Dittmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamic instabilities in long-term three-dimensional simulations of neutrino-driven supernovae of 13 red supergiant progenitors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present long-term three-dimensional (3D) simulations of Type-IIP supernovae (SNe) for 13 non-rotating, single-star, red-supergiant (RSG) progenitors with zero-age-main-sequence masses between 12.5 M$_{\odot}$ and 27.3 M$_{\odot}$. The explosions were modelled with a parametric treatment of neutrino heating to obtain defined energies, ${}^{56}$Ni yields, and neutron-star properties in agreement with previous results. Our 3D SN models were evolved from core bounce until 10 days to study how the large-scale mixing of chemical elements depends on the progenitor structure. Rayleigh-Taylor instabilities (RTIs), which grow at the (C+O)/He and He/H interfaces and interact with the reverse shock forming after the SN shock has passed the He/H interface, play a crucial role in the outward mixing of ${}^{56}$Ni into the hydrogen envelope. We find most extreme ${}^{56}$Ni mixing and the highest maximum ${}^{56}$Ni velocities in lower-mass (LM) explosions despite lower explosion energies, and the weakest ${}^{56}$Ni mixing in the 3D explosions of the most massive RSGs. The efficiency of radial ${}^{56}$Ni mixing anti-correlates linearly with the helium-core mass and correlates positively with the magnitude of a local maximum of $\rho r^3$ in the helium shell. This maximum causes shock deceleration and therefore facilitates high growth factors of RTI at the (C+O)/He interface in the LM explosions. Therefore fast-moving ${}^{56}$Ni created by the asymmetric neutrino-heating mechanism is carried into the ubiquitous RT-unstable region near the He/H interface and ultimately far into the envelopes of the exploding RSGs. Our correlations may aid improving mixing prescriptions in 1D SN models and deducing progenitor structures from observed SN properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11796v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Giudici, Michael Gabler, Hans-Thomas Janka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Transition from Giant Planets to Brown Dwarfs beyond 1 au from the Stellar Metallicity Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Giant planets and brown dwarfs are thought to form via a combination of pathways, including bottom-up mechanisms in which gas is accreted onto a solid core and top-down mechanisms in which gas collapses directly into a gravitationally-bound object. One can distinguish the prevalence of these mechanisms using host star metallicities. Bottom-up formation thrives in metal-rich environments, whereas top-down formation is weakly dependent on ambient metal content. Using a hierarchical Bayesian model and the results of the California Legacy Survey (CLS), a low-bias and homogeneously analyzed radial velocity survey, we find evidence for a transition in the stellar metallicity distribution at a companion mass of $\gamma = 27_{-8}^{+12} \, M_{\rm Jup}$ for companions with orbital separations between $1-50$ au. Companions below and above this threshold tend to orbit stars with higher ($\rm{[Fe/H]} = 0.17 \pm 0.12$ dex) and lower ($\rm{[Fe/H]} = -0.03 \pm 0.10$ dex) metallicities, respectively. Previous studies of relatively close-in companions reported evidence of a lower transition mass of $\leq 10 \, {\rm M_{\rm Jup}}$. When applied to the CLS sample, our model predicts the probability of a transition in the stellar metallicity distribution at or below $10 \, { M_{\rm Jup}}$ to be $&lt; 1 \%$. We compare our results to estimates of $\gamma$ gleaned from other observational metrics and discuss implications for planet formation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11818v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Giacalone, Andrew W. Howard, Gregory J. Gilbert, Judah Van Zandt, Erik A. Petigura, Luke B. Handley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuaRT: A toolkit for the exploration of quantum methods for radiation transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: QuaRT is a Python library for quantum simulation of radiative transfer in astrophysical and cosmological problems. It features a novel angular redistribution methodology for lattice Boltzmann methods which improves the isotropy of simulations of objects such as stars in non-scattering media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12356v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasmit Devkota, John H. Wise</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of type Ibn SNe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Type Ibn supernovae (SNe) are characterized by narrow helium (He I) lines from photons produced by the unshocked circumstellar material (CSM). About 80 SNe Ibn have been discovered to date, and only a handful have extensive observational records. Thus, many open questions regarding the progenitor system and the origin of the CSM remain. Here we investigate potential correlations between the spectral features of the prominent He I $\lambda$5876 line and the optical and X-ray light curve properties of SNe Ibn. We compile the largest sample of 61 SNe Ibn to date, of which 24 SNe have photometric and spectroscopic data from the Young Supernova Experiment and 37 SNe have archival data sets. We fit 24 SNe Ibn with sufficient photometric coverage ($B$ to $z$ bands) using semi-analytical models from MOSFiT. We demonstrate that the light curves of SNe Ibn are more diverse than previous analyses suggest, with absolute $r$-band peak magnitudes of $-19.4\pm0.6$~mag and rise (from $-10$ days to peak) and decay-rates (from peak to +10 days) of $-0.08\pm0.06$ and $0.08\pm0.03$ mag/day, respectively. We find that the majority of SNe Ibn in the sub-sample are consistent with a low-energy explosion ($&lt;10^{51}$ erg) of a star with a compact envelope surrounded by $\sim$0.1 M$_{\odot}$ of helium-rich CSM. The inferred ejecta masses are small ($\sim 1$ M$_{\odot}$) and expand with a velocity of $\sim$5000 km/s. Our spectroscopic analysis shows that the mean velocity of the narrow component of the He I lines, associated to the CSM, peaks at $\sim1100$ km/s. The mean CSM and ejecta masses inferred for a sub-sample of SNe Ibn indicate that their progenitors are not massive ($\sim10$ M$_{\odot}$), single stars at the moment of explosion, but are likely binary systems. This agrees with the detection of potential companion stars of SNe Ibn progenitors, and the inferred CSM properties from stellar evolution models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12362v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Farias, C. Gall, V. A. Villar, K. Auchettl, K. M. de Soto, A. Gagliano, W. B. Hoogendam, G. Narayan, A. Sedgewick, S. K. Yadavalli, Y. Zenati, C. R. Angus, K. W. Davis, J. Hjorth, W. V. Jacobson-Gal\'an, D. O. Jones, C. D. Kilpatrick, M. J. Bustamante Rosell, D. A. Coulter, G. Dimitriadis, R. J. Foley, A. Gangopadhyay, H. Gao, M. E. Huber, L. Izzo, J. L. Johnson, A. L. Piro, A. Rest, C. Rojas-Bravo, M. R. Siebert, K. Taggart, S. Tinyanont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Quarkyonic Matter and Its Implications for Neutron Star Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12669v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The structure and basic properties of dense nuclear matter still remain one of the open problems of Physics. In particular, the composition of the matter that composes neutron stars is under theoretical and experimental investigation. Among the theories that have been proposed, apart from the classical one where the composition is dominated by hadrons, the existence or coexistence of deconfined quark matter is a dominant guess. An approach towards this solution is the phenomenological view according to which the existence of quarkyonic matter plays a dominant role in the construction of the equation of state (EOS). According to it the structure of the EOS is based on the existence of the quarkyonic particle which is a hybrid state of a particle that combines properties of hadronic and quark matter with a corresponding representation in momentum space. In this paper we propose a phenomenological model for hot quarkyonic matter, borrowed from corresponding applications in hadronic models, where the interaction in the quarkyonic matter depends not only on the position but also on the momentum of the quarkyonic particles. This consideration, as we demonstrate, can have a remarkable consequence on the shape of the EOS and thus on the properties of neutron stars, especially in those for which the effect of temperature is significant, offering a sufficiently flexible model. Comparison with recent observational data can place constraints on the parameterization of the particular model and help improve its reliability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12669v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Folias, Ch. C. Moustakidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Eccentricities Suggest a Gradual Transition from Giant Planets to Brown Dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To date, hundreds of sub-stellar objects with masses between $1-80\ M_{\rm Jup}$ have been detected orbiting main-sequence stars. The current convention uses the deuterium-burning limit, $M_c \approx 13 M_{\rm Jup}$ to divide this population between giant planets and brown dwarfs. However, this classification heuristic is largely divorced from any formation physics and may not accurately reflect the astrophysical nature of these objects. Previous work has suggested that a transition from ``planet-like'' to ``brown-dwarf-like'' characteristics occurs somewhere in the range $1-10 M_{\rm Jup}$, but precise the crossover mass and whether the transition is gradual or abrupt remains unknown. Here, we explore how the occurrence rate, host star metallicity, and orbital eccentricities vary as a function of mass in a sample of 70 Doppler-detected sub-stellar objects ($0.8 &lt; M_c/M_{\rm Jup} &lt; 80$) from the California Legacy Survey. Our population consists of objects near and beyond the water ice line ($1 &lt; a / \text{AU} &lt; 10$), providing valuable clues to the details of giant planet formation physics at a location in the proto-stellar disk where planet formation efficiency is thought to be enhanced. We find that occurrence rate, host star metallicity, and orbital eccentricity all change gradually across the mass range under consideration, suggesting that ``bottom-up'' core accretion mechanisms and ``top-down'' gravitational instability mechanisms produce objects that overlap in mass. The observed eccentricity distributions could arise either from different formation channels or from post-formation dynamical interactions between massive sub-stellar objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12816v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory J. Gilbert, Judah Van Zandt, Erik A. Petigura, Steven Giacalone, Andrew W. Howard, Luke B. Handley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational properties of a Schwarzschild black hole surrounded by a Dehnen-type dark matter halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13156v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the accretion process and observational signatures of thin accretion disks around a Schwarzschild black hole (BH) embedded in a Dehnen-type dark matter (DM) halo. We examine the influence of the density {\rho}_{s} and radius r_{s} of the DM halo on key disk properties, including the energy flux, temperature distribution, and emission spectrum. Our results show that all three of these quantities decrease with increasing {\rho}_{s} or r_{s}. Furthermore, by generating and analyzing both direct and secondary images of the accretion disk, we explore how the observational inclination angle and the DM halo parameters {\rho}_{s} and rs affect image profiles. Finally, the observed flux distributions are presented for different inclination angles. Our findings indicate that the accretion disk becomes colder and dimmer as the DM halo parameters increase, highlighting the significant role of DM in shaping BH observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13156v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14911-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025EPJC...85.1170L</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Li, Jiancheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining r-process nucleosynthesis with multi-objective Galactic chemical evolution models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13372v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The astrophysical site(s) of the r-process are uncertain, with candidates such as neutron star mergers and magneto-rotational supernovae predicting different event rates, delay times, and heavy-element yields. Galactic chemical evolution models constrain these properties by comparing model predictions with observed abundances. We explore, in a systematic and data-driven way, the astrophysical conditions under which r-process enrichment can reproduce the observed trends of multiple neutron-capture elements in the Milky Way. Rather than assuming a fixed site, we adopt a flexible, parametric approach to test whether a common set of r-process parameters can explain the chemical evolution of several heavy elements. We compute a grid of one-infall, homogeneous models varying: Eu yield per event, r-process event rate, enrichment delay time, and progenitor mass range. For each of the $\sim 1.5 \times 10^5$ models, we predict [X/Fe] vs. [Fe/H] trends by scaling Eu yields with the solar r-process pattern. A multi-objective optimisation based on Pareto fronts identifies models that best reproduce the abundance trends. Best-fitting models favour short delay times ($\leq 30\ \rm Myr$), low-mass progenitors ($\sim 20-25\ \rm M_\odot$), and an effective Eu injection of $\sim 2 \times 10^{-7}\ \rm M_\odot$ per event. Stars more massive than $\sim 80\ \rm M_\odot$ are too rare to dominate the enrichment. While heavy elements can be reproduced, lighter ones show stronger conflicts with Eu, reflecting that the solar r-process scaling relation becomes less valid toward lighter elements. No single class of r-process events, under solar-scaled yields, can explain light and heavy neutron-capture elements; at least two components are required: a main r-process consistent with solar and r-rich stars, and a weaker component producing enhanced light r-process elements, similar to that observed in r-poor stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13372v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Molero, A. Arcones, F. Montes, C. J. Hansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sense and Sensitivity - I. Uncertainty analysis of the gas-phase chemistry in AGB outflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chemical reaction networks are central to all chemical models. Each rate coefficient has an associated uncertainty, which is generally not taken into account when calculating the chemistry. We performed the first uncertainty analysis of a chemical model of C-rich and O-rich AGB outflows using the Rate22 reaction network. Quantifying the error on the model predictions enables us to determine the need for adding complexity to the model. Using a Monte Carlo sampling method, we quantified the impact of the uncertainties on the chemical kinetic data on the predicted fractional abundances and column densities. The errors are caused by a complex interplay of reactions forming and destroying each species. Parent species show an error on their envelope sizes, which is not caused by the uncertainty on their photodissociation rate, but rather the chemistry reforming the parent after its photodissociation. Using photodissociation models to estimate the envelope size might be an oversimplification. The error on the CO envelope impacts retrieved mass-loss rates by up to a factor of two. For daughter species, the error on the peak fractional abundance ranges from a factor of a few to three orders of magnitude, and is on average about 10\% of its value. This error is positively correlated with the error on the column density. The standard model suffices for many species, e.g., the radial distribution of cyanopolyynes and hydrocarbon radicals around IRC +10216. However, including spherical asymmetries, dust-gas chemistry, and photochemistry induced by a close-by stellar companion are still necessary to explain certain observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13638v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Van de Sande, M. Gueguen, T. Danilovich, T. J. Millar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of triple evolution in the formation of LISA double white dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09607v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galactic double white dwarfs will be prominent gravitational-wave sources for the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA). While previous studies have primarily focused on formation scenarios in which binaries form and evolve in isolation, we present the first detailed study of the role of triple stellar evolution in forming the population of LISA double white dwarfs. In this work, we present the first detailed study of the role of triple stellar evolution in forming the population of LISA double white dwarfs. We use the multiple stellar evolution code (MSE) to model the stellar evolution, binary interactions, and the dynamics of triple star systems then use a Milky Way-like galaxy from the TNG50 simulations to construct a representative sample of LISA double white dwarfs. In our simulations about $7\times10^6$ Galactic double white dwarfs in the LISA frequency bandwidth originate from triple systems, whereas $\sim4\times10^6$ form from isolated binary stars. The properties of double white dwarfs formed in triples closely resemble those formed from isolated binaries, but we also find a small number of systems $\sim\mathcal{O}(10)$ that reach extreme eccentricities $(&gt;0.9)$, a feature unique to the dynamical formation channels. Our population produces $\approx 10^{4} $ individually resolved double white dwarfs (from triple and binary channels) and an unresolved stochastic foreground below the level of the LISA instrumental noise. About $57\,\%$ of double white dwarfs from triple systems retain a bound third star when entering the LISA frequency bandwidth. However, we expect the tertiary stars to be too distant to have a detectable imprint in the gravitational-wave signal of the inner binary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09607v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abinaya Swaruba Rajamuthukumar, Valeriya Korol, Jakob Stegmann, Holly Preece, R\"udiger Pakmor, Stephen Justham, Silvia Toonen, Selma E. de Mink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energetics of star-planet magnetic interactions: Novel insights from 3D modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23277v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Star-planet magnetic interactions (SPMI) occurring in the sub-Alfvenic regime can, in principle, induce stellar chromospheric hotspots. Currently, estimates of the power generated by SPMI primarily rely on analytical scaling laws that relate stellar and planetary parameters to the interaction energetics. The existing scaling laws published in the literature so far do not agree with each other by at least an order of magnitude. Our aim is to quantify an absolute upper limit on the power that a planet can channel back to its host star during such interactions, which in turn lead to the formation of stellar hotspots. By performing a series of 3D MHD simulations with varied parameters known to influence the energetics of SPMI, we derive a numerically supported scaling law that can be used to reliably estimate the energy channeled from the planet back to the star. Our results suggest that existing analytical scaling laws may not fully capture the power transferred from the planet to the star through SPMI. The scaling law derived from our numerical simulations appears to provide a more comprehensive estimate, reflecting dependencies on common stellar and planetary parameters also considered in earlier models. Moreover, our findings indicate that power generation involves not only the planetary obstacle itself but also the extended magnetic structure of the Alfven wings interacting with the streaming stellar wind. This study suggests that care should be taken when applying analogies directly from jovian sub-Alfvenic interactions to SPMI, as the underlying physical conditions (specifically the value of the Alfvenic Mach number) may not be directly comparable. Our numerically derived scaling law offers a potentially improved approach for estimating SPMI power, capturing some of the interaction's complexities exclusive to SPMI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23277v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202556212</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arghyadeep Paul, Antoine Strugarek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar Populations with MaNGA: Iron Kink and Nitrogen Fuzz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08827v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent analysis of 2968 MaNGA early type galaxies has yielded two notable trends with velocity dispersion ($\sigma$) not previously discussed in the literature. First, Fe abundance rises with $\sigma$, but only until $\sigma\approx100$ km s$^{-1}$, after which it falls. This kink is reproduced by TNG100 simulations, implying that hierarchical merger processes might explain it. Second, astrophysical scatter in N is high for galaxies with $\sigma &lt; 100$ km s$^{-1}$. Due to the restricted list of nucleosynthetic sources for N, it is likely that asymptotic giant branch stars provide most of this N. A varied star formation history (compared to that of massive galaxies) along with variable retention and recycling of N-enriched gas might explain the fuzz of N abundance in low-$\sigma$ galaxies. Because a timescale argument seems necessary to explain the nitrogen fuzz, and an initial mass function argument is ruled out, similar timescale arguments for the [Mg/Fe] trend as a function of velocity dispersion are supported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08827v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Worthey, Tathagata Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
