<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 01:39:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of stellar rotations and binaries on the shape of upper main sequence near turn off in open cluster NGC\,6067</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the analysis of the extended Main Sequence Turn-Off (eMSTO) in the open cluster NGC\,6067. We derive the projected rotational velocity, \textit{v}sin\textit{i}, of the stars belonging to the eMSTO region of the main sequence (MS) utilizing \textit{Gaia}-ESO spectra. Our results reveal a positive correlation between \textit{v}sin\textit{i} and the color of eMSTO stars, where fast-rotating stars predominantly occupy the red part of the MS while slow-rotating ones prefer a bluer side of the MS. The gravity-darkening effect might be a reason for this correlation. We find that most of the close binaries present in the eMSTO population would be slow-rotating due to the tidal-locking phenomenon. We identify four double-lined spectroscopic binaries (SB2) featuring slow-rotating companions, further supporting this tidal-locking hypothesis. However, the spatial distribution and the cumulative radial distribution indicate a higher concentration of red eMSTO stars in the cluster's central region than their bluer counterparts. This suggests that tidal locking is less likely to be the cause of the observed spread in rotation rates among eMSTO stars. Instead, we propose that star-disk interactions during the pre-main-sequence phase might have played a crucial role in spreading the rotation rates of stars, leading to the eMSTO phenomenon in NGC\,6067.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14433v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adef40</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jayanand Maurya, Yu Zhang, Sebastian Kamann, Hubiao Niu, Yves Fr\'emat, Kaixiang Lang, Y. C. Joshi, M. R. Samal, Peter De Cat, Ali Esamdin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The formation and evolution of dust in the colliding-wind binary Apep revealed by JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Carbon-rich Wolf-Rayet (WR) stars are significant contributors of carbonaceous dust to the galactic environment, however the mechanisms and conditions for formation and subsequent evolution of dust around these stars remain open questions. Here we present JWST observations of the WR+WR colliding-wind binary Apep which reveal an intricate series of nested concentric dust shells that are abundant in detailed substructure. The striking regularity in these substructures between successive shells suggests an exactly repeating formation mechanism combined with a highly stable outflow that maintains a consistent morphology even after reaching 0.6 pc (assuming a distance of 2.4 kpc) into the interstellar medium. The concentric dust shells show subtle deviations from spherical outflow, which could reflect orbital modulation along the eccentric binary orbit or some mild degree of non-sphericity in the stellar wind. Tracking the evolution of dust across the multi-tiered structure, we measure the dust temperature evolution that can broadly be described with an amorphous carbon composition in radiative thermal equilibrium with the central stars. The temperature profile and orbital period place new distance constraints that support Apep being at a greater distance than previously estimated, reducing the line-of-sight and sky-plane wind speed discrepancy previously thought to characterise the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14498v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinuo Han, Ryan M. T. White, Joseph R. Callingham, Ryan M. Lau, Benjamin J. S. Pope, Noel D. Richardson, Peter G. Tuthill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variations of the Ca II K Line Profile Parameters with Solar Latitude and Time Observed from Kodaikanal Solar Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Calcium-K line profiles as functions of solar latitude and time were obtained through our observations from the Kodaikanal Solar Observatory using the solar tunnel telescope and spectrograph with a CCD detector. Observations were conducted on all days with favourable sky conditions. We analysed the data collected over a period of about ten years to study the variations in the Ca II K line profiles recorded between 2015 and 2024, of which 709 days of data were found useful. The temporal and time-averaged latitudinal variations of the K$_{1}$ width, K$_{2}$ width, K$_{3}$ intensity and the intensity ratios of K$_{2v}$/K$_{2r}$ and K$_{2v}$/K$_{3}$ were computed using a semi-automated program. The parameters showed asymmetric increases towards the higher latitudes, with the rates of increase being higher in the southern hemisphere. The temporal plots for K$_{1}$ width and K$_{3}$ intensity showed positive correlations with the plage and spot filling factors, whereas the temporal plots for K$_{2}$ width, K$_{2v}$/K$_{2r}$ and K$_{2v}$/K$_{3}$ intensity ratios showed negative correlations. The time-averaged latitudinal plot for K$_{1}$ width has small peaks near 25{\deg}N and 20{\deg}S. The K$_{2}$ width has a small peak at 0{\deg}. The K$_{3}$ intensity has peaks at 20{\deg}N and 15{\deg}S. The K$_{2v}$/K$_{2r}$ intensity ratio shows peaks at 50$\degree$N, 0{\deg} and 40{\deg}S. The K$_{2v}$/K$_{3}$ intensity ratio shows peaks at 60{\deg}N, 0{\deg} and 60{\deg}S. Slope profiles show spectral response to magnetic activity peaks near K$_{3}$ with north-south asymmetries. Such variations in the line profiles are important in the studies of solar irradiance, surface flux transport and solar dynamo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14609v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1163</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Apoorva Srinivasa (Department of Physics, Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham, Amritapuri, India), Anu Sreedevi (Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology), K P Raju (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, India), K Nagaraju (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, India), Jagdev Singh (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, India), Narayanankutty Karuppath (Department of Physics, Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham, Amritapuri, India), P Devendran (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal, India), T Ramesh Kumar (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal, India), P Kumaravel (Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Kodaikanal, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Serpent Eating Its Own Tail: Dust Destruction in the Apep Colliding-Wind Nebula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Much of the carbonaceous dust observed in the early universe may originate from colliding wind binaries (CWBs) hosting hot, luminous Wolf-Rayet (WR) stars. Downstream of the shock between the stellar winds there exists a suitable environment for dust grain formation, and the orbital motion of the stars wraps this dust into richly structured spiral geometries. The Apep system is the most extreme WR-CWB in our Milky Way: two WR stars produce a complex spiral dust nebula, whose slow expansion has been linked to a gamma-ray burst progenitor. It has been unclear whether the O-type supergiant 0.7" distant from the WR+WR binary is physically associated with the system, and whether it affects the dusty nebula. Multi-epoch VLT/VISIR and JWST/MIRI observations show that this northern companion star routinely carves a cavity in the dust nebula - the first time such an effect has been observed in a CWB - which unambiguously associates the O star as a bound component to the Apep system. These observations are used together with a new geometric model to infer the cavity geometry and the orbit of the WR+WR binary, yielding the first strong constraints on wind and orbital parameters. We confirm an orbital period of over 190 years for the inner binary - nearly an order of magnitude longer than the next longest period dust-producing WR-CWB. This, together with the confirmed classification as a hierarchical triple, cements Apep as a singular astrophysical laboratory for studying colliding winds and the terminal life stages of the most massive star systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14610v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan M. T. White, Benjamin J. S. Pope, Peter G. Tuthill, Yinuo Han, Shashank Dholakia, Ryan M. Lau, Joseph R. Callingham, Noel D. Richardson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D fast-mode Wave Propagation from Corona to Chromosphere: Triggering Mechanism for 3D Oscillations of filaments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moreton waves are widely regarded as the chromospheric counterpart of extreme ultraviolet (EUV) waves propagating in the corona. However, direct observational evidence confirming their simultaneous propagation across multiple atmospheric layers from the corona through the transition region to the chromosphere has been lacking. In this study, we present comprehensive observational evidence of a three-dimensional (3D) fast-mode wave propagating from the corona through the transition region into the chromosphere, exhibiting a gradual deceleration. Additionally, this wave interacts with three filaments (F1, F2, and F3) along its path, inducing oscillation with multiple amplitudes: Filaments F1 and F2 exhibit simultaneous horizontal and vertical large-scale oscillations ($\sim$\speed{20}), while Filament F3 only exhibits vertical small-scale oscillation ($\sim$\speed{4}). Interestingly, F1 displays a similar oscillation period of about 500\,s in both horizontal and vertical directions, whereas F2 shows significantly different periods in these two dimensions (1100\,s and 750\,s), and F3 exhibits only a vertical oscillation with a period of about 450\,s. Based on this kinematic behavior, we propose that their oscillations were likely triggered by compression from the flanks of the dome-shaped wavefront. We further estimate the magnetic fields of the filaments. The radial (axial) magnetic fields for F1 and F2 are estimated to be 14.9\,G (28.6\,G) and 9.9\,G (18.6\,G), respectively. For F3, we estimate its radial magnetic field to be 16.6\,G.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14837v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunxue Huang, Qin Feng, Yuhu Miao, Zhining Qu, Ke Yu, Hongfei Liang, Yu Liu, Xinping Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving magnetic lives of Sun-like stars. I. Characterisation of the large-scale magnetic field with Zeeman-Doppler imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Planets orbiting young, solar-type stars are embedded in a more energetic environment than that of the solar neighbourhood. They experience harsher conditions due to enhanced stellar magnetic activity and wind shaping the secular evolution of a planetary atmosphere. This study is dedicated to the characterisation of the magnetic activity of eleven Sun-like stars, with ages between 0.2 and 6.1 Gyr and rotation periods between 4.6 and 28.7 d. Based on a sub-sample of six stars, we aim to study the large-scale magnetic field, which we then use to simulate the associated stellar wind and environment. Finally, we want to determine the conditions during the early evolution of planetary habitability. We analysed high-resolution spectropolarimetric data collected in 2018 and 2019 with Narval. We computed activity diagnostics from chromospheric lines such as CaII H&amp;K, H$\alpha$, and the CaII infrared triplet, as well as the longitudinal magnetic field from circularly polarised least-squares deconvolution profiles. For six stars exhibiting detectable circular polarisation signals, we reconstructed the large-scale magnetic field at the photospheric level by means of Zeeman-Doppler imaging (ZDI). In agreement with previous studies, we found a global decrease in the activity indices and longitudinal field with increasing age and rotation period. The large-scale magnetic field of the six sub-sample stars displays a strength between 1 and 25 G and reveals substantial contributions from different components such as poloidal (40-90 %), toroidal (10-60 %), dipolar (30-80 %), and quadrupolar (10-40 %), with distinct levels of axisymmetry (6-84 %) and short-term variability of the order of months. Ultimately, this implies that exoplanets tend to experience a broad variety of stellar magnetic environments after their formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14861v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bellotti, T. Lueftinger, S. Boro Saikia, C. P. Folsom, P. Petit, J. Morin, M. Gudel, J. -F. Donati, E. Alecian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A deep Search for Ethylene Glycol and Glycolonitrile in the V883 Ori Protoplanetary Disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ethylene glycol ($\mathrm{(CH_2OH)_2}$, hereafter EG) and Glycolonitrile ($\mathrm{HOCH_2CN}$, hereafter GN) are considered molecular precursors of nucleic acids. EG is a sugar alcohol and the reduced form of Glycolaldehyde ($\mathrm{CH_2(OH)CHO}$, hereafter GA). GN is considered a key precursor of adenine formation (nucleotide) and can be a precursor of glycine (amino acid). Detections of such prebiotic molecules in the interstellar medium are increasingly common. How much of this complexity endures to the planet formation stage, and thus is already present when planets form, remains largely unknown. Here we report Atacama Large Millimeter/sub-millimeter Array (ALMA) observations in which we tentatively detect EG and GN in the protoplanetary disk around the outbursting protostar V883 Ori. The observed EG emission is best reproduced by a column density of $\mathrm{3.63^{+0.11}_{-0.12} \times 10^{16} \; cm^{-2}}$ and a temperature of at least 300 K. The observed GN emission is best reproduced by a column density of $\mathrm{3.37^{+0.09}_{-0.09} \times 10^{16} \; cm^{-2}}$ and a temperature of $88^{+1.2}_{-1.2}$ K. Comparing the abundance of EG and GN relative to methanol in V883 Ori with other objects, V883 Ori falls between hot cores and comets in terms of increasing complexity. This suggests that the build up of prebiotic molecules continues past the hot core phase into the epoch of planet formation. Nascent planets in such environments may inherit essential building blocks for life, enhancing their potential habitability. Further observations of this protoplanetary disk at higher spectral resolution are required to resolve blended lines and to confirm these tentative detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14905v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abubakar M. A. Fadul, Kamber R. Schwarz, Tushar Suhasaria, Jenny K. Calahan, Jane Huang, Merel L. R. van 't Hoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary Analysis and Period Study of the Long-Period, High Mass Ratio Contact Binary KIC 7766185</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14979v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an in-depth photometric and spectroscopic study of the contact binary KIC 7766185. Spectroscopic observations were conducted on the Mayall 4-m telescope at Kitt Peak National Observatory and used to extract radial velocities. Using the radial velocity measurements, Kepler photometry, and Gaia multi-color photometry, binary analysis was performed in PHOEBE to determine orbital and stellar parameters. The results classify KIC 7766185 as an A-type W UMa system and reveal one of the largest and most massive secondary stars in the sample of well studied W UMa systems. The two stars are in a shallow contact state, with a small fillout factor of $0.029\pm0.002$. Along with the binary analysis, we conduct a period study that reveals evidence for a cyclic variation in the eclipse timings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14979v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conor M Larsen, Andrej Prsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Asteroseismology of the High-amplitude Delta Scuti Star EH Librae, an AE UMa Analogue in the Hertzsprung Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A subclass of intermediate mass variables Delta Scuti stars, known as High-amplitude Delta Scuti (HADS) stars, exhibits pronounced radial pulsations with high amplitudes. The ground-based and space-based observations of the HADS star EH Lib are used to help making asteroseismological analysis of this pulsating star. Following the reduction of the light curves, the frequency analysis reveals the fundamental frequency as $f_0=11.3105$ c day$^{-1}$ and two more significant frequencies $f_1$ and $f_2$, in addition to the harmonics of $f_0$ and a linear combination. The period change rate is determined as $(1/P_0)(dP_0/dt)=(5.4\pm0.5)\times10^{-9}$ yr$^{-1}$ derived from an O-C diagram, which is constructed from 342 times of maximum light spanning over 70 years. Using these observational constraints, along with the metallicity reported in the literature, we construct theoretical models using the stellar evolution code MESA and calculate the theoretical frequencies of the eigen modes using the oscillation code GYRE. The appropriate models are selected by matching both $f_0$ and $(1/P_0)(dP_0/dt)$ within their respective uncertainties. The results indicate that the observed period change of EH Lib can be attributed to stellar evolutionary effects. The stellar parameters of EH Lib are derived as: the mass of $1.715\pm0.065$ M$_{\odot}$, the luminosity of log $(L/L_{\odot})=1.38\pm0.06$, and the age of $(1.14\pm0.13)\times10^{9}$ years. EH Lib is classified as a single-mode HADS star, locating currently in the Hertzsprung gap, with a helium core and a hydrogen-burning shell. This work expands the asteroseismological sample of HADS stars and establishes a foundation for future investigations into their commonalities and specific properties, thereby advancing our understanding of these variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15044v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiran Xie, Jianning Fu, Gang Meng, Lester Fox Machado, Ra\'ul Michel, Huifang Xue, Nian Liu, Zhongyang Liu, Jie Su, Mingfeng Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar Population Astrophysics (SPA) with the TNG: NLTE atmospheric parameters and abundances of giant stars in 33 Open Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Open clusters serve as important tools for accurately studying the chemical evolution of the Milky Way. By combining precise chemical data from high-resolution spectra with information on their distances and ages, we can effectively uncover the processes that have shaped our Galaxy. This study aims to derive NLTE atmospheric parameters and chemical abundances for approximately one hundred giant stars across 33 open clusters with near-solar metallicity. The clusters span a wide range of ages, enabling an assessment of the presence and extent of any age-related abundance gradients. In the Stellar Population Astrophysics (SPA) project, we acquired new high-resolution spectra of open clusters using the HARPS-N echelle spectrograph at the Telescopio Nazionale Galileo. We chemically characterized nine open clusters for the first time and reanalyzed previously studied SPA clusters, resulting in a consistent and homogeneous sample. We determined NLTE atmospheric parameters using the equivalent width method and derived NLTE chemical abundances through spectral synthesis for various elements, including alpha elements (Mg, Si, and Ti), light odd-Z elements (Na, Al), iron-peak elements (Mn, Co, and Ni), and neutron-capture elements (Sr, Y, and Eu). Our findings are compared with the existing literature, revealing good agreement. We examine the trends of [X/Fe] versus age, confirming previous observations and the enrichment patterns predicted by nucleosynthesis processes. Positive correlations with age are present for Mg, Si, Ti, Al, Mn, Co, Ni, and Sr, while Na and Y and Eu show a negative trend. This study emphasizes the significance of NLTE corrections and reinforces the utility of open clusters as tracers of Galactic chemical evolution. Furthermore, we provide a benchmark sample of NLTE abundances for upcoming open cluster surveys within large-scale projects such as 4MOST and WEAVE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15122v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Dal Ponte, V. D'Orazi, A. Bragaglia, A. R. Casey, N. Storm, L. Spina, J. Alonso-Santiago, G. Andreuzzi, A. Frasca, J. Kos, S. Lucatello, D. Romano, A. Vallenari, N. Vernekar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemical Diagnostics for Tracing the Physical Structures in Disk-Forming Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To understand the chemical origin of the Solar system, the chemical evolution along the star/planet formation is a key issue. Extensive observational studies have demonstrated a chemical diversity in young low-mass protostellar sources so far. Furthermore, chemical differentiations in the vicinity of the protostars have recently been reported. This suggests that molecular distribution is sensitive to a change in the physical conditions associated with disk formation. Some kinds of molecular lines, especially Sulfur-bearing species, are therefore prospected to work as molecular markers to highlight particular structures of disk-forming regions. Conversely, detailed physical characterization is essential for elucidating the chemical evolution occurring there. Machine learnings may help us to disentangle the observed structures. Angular momentum of the gas is the key topic to understand the structure formation, which is also essential to the integration of the chemical and physical characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15371v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoko Oya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Probable Direct-Imaging Detection of the Stellar Companion to Betelgeuse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Betelgeuse -- the closest M-supergiant to the Sun -- has recently been predicted to host a lower-mass stellar companion that orbits the primary with a period of $\sim 6$ years. The putative stellar companion is thought to cause the long photometric modulation observed in Betelgeuse, which cannot be explained by stellar pulsations. Additionally, radial velocity and astrometric data also point to a stellar companion. Here we present diffraction-limited optical speckle imaging observations obtained on the 8.1-meter Gemini North telescope in 2020 and 2024. The 2020 observations were taken during the Great Dimming event, and at a time when the stellar companion was predicted to be unobservable because it was directly in-line with Betelgeuse itself. The 2024 observations were taken three days after the predicted time of greatest elongation for the companion. A comparison of the 2020 and 2024 data reveal no companion in 2020 (as expected) and the probable detection of a companion in 2024. The presumed stellar companion has an angular separation and position angle of 52 mas and $115^\circ$ east of north, respectively, which is in excellent agreement with predictions from dynamical considerations. The detected companion is roughly six magnitudes fainter than Betelgeuse at 466 nm.\bf{While this is only a 1.5$\sigma$ detection, the results are in reasonable agreement with the predictions: the appearance of the companion at quadrature; the angular separation from Betelgeuse; the position angle with respect to Betelgeuse; the magnitude difference; and the estimated mass of the companion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15749v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve B. Howell, David R. Ciardi, Catherine A. Clark, Douglas A. Hope, Colin Littlefield, Elise Furlan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inside the Iron Curtain: A Long Term Look at the Iron Stars XX Oph and AS 325</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15750v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Iron Stars XX Oph and AS 325, both binaries consisting of a Be + late K,M II star present remarkable optical spectra. Low velocity, dense winds from the late type star collide with high velocity, optically thin material expelled from the hot Be star producing a plethora of emission lines and complex P Cygni absorption profiles. The members of the American Association of Variable Star Observers have faithfully observed XX Oph for 85 years and AS 325 for 32 years. This long term photometric monitoring has revealed AS 325 to be an eclipsing system while XX Oph shows a complex light curve behavior. We present archival and recent photometry, new high-resolution optical imaging, and new high-resolution optical spectroscopy of the two stars. The orbital period of AS 325 is refined as 512.943 days and the stellar components are Be+K2.5 II. XX Oph is shown to be non-eclipsing and consists of Be+M6II stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15750v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve B. Howell, Venu M. Kalari, Andy Adamson, Mark Everett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accretion from a shock-inflated companion: double-peaked supernova lightcurve with periodic modulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the observational signatures from the interactions between a newly born neutron star and a companion star that is impacted by the supernova ejecta. We focus on the cases with bound post-explosion orbits, where the neutron star may periodically gravitationally capture gas from the companion. We find that neutron star accretion must occur if the pre-supernova binary separation is less than about 20 Rsun. This is because the stellar radius expands beyond this radius before the shock-inflated envelope undergoes Kelvin-Helmholtz contraction back to the main sequence. We then consider the internal shocks formed between adjacent episodes of disk wind. The shocks efficiently convert the wind kinetic energy into radiation (due to inverse-Compton cooling), which heats up the supernova ejecta located at much larger radii. The extra heating powers bright optical emission that is periodically modulated on the orbital timescale. The shocks also accelerate non-thermal particles which produce gamma-ray and neutrino emission from 100 MeV to 10 PeV via hardronic pp collisions. The high-energy photons leak out of the supernova ejecta after a delay of several months to one year. Photo-ionization of the slowest parts of the disk wind produces hydrogen recombination lines. We then use the model to explain the puzzling Type Ic supernova SN2022jli which shows a double-peaked optical lightcurve along with many peculiar properties, including delayed onset and rapid shutoff of the second peak, periodic modulations, delayed GeV emission, and narrow Balmer lines. Under this model, SN2022jli had a close-by companion at a pre-supernova binary separation of 10 to 20 Rsun, likely due to an earlier phase of common-envelope evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14284v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenbin Lu (UC Berkeley), Savannah Cary (UC Berkeley), Daichi Tsuna (Caltech)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tools for High Precision Photometry from Wide-Field Color Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present AstroWISP: a collection of image processing tools for source extraction, background determination, point spread function/pixel response function fitting, and aperture photometry. AstroWISP is particularly well-suited for working with detectors featuring a Bayer mask (an array of microfilters applied to each detector pixel to allow color photography), such as consumer DSLR cameras. Such detectors pose significant challenges for existing tools while offering a much cheaper alternative to specialized devices. As a result, consumer DSLR cameras with Bayer masks are often underutilized for precision photometry. \astrowisp{} addresses this limitation in an effort to democratize precision photometry and support broader community participation in research. We demonstrate that our tools produce high-precision photometry from such images, enabling the use of such devices for detecting exoplanet transits. We package our tools for all major operating systems to ensure accessibility for amateur astronomers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14289v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaloyan Penev, Angel Romero, S. Javad Jafarzadeh, Olivier Guyon, Wilfred Gee, Preethi Krishnamoorthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Emission from Double Detonation Type Ia Supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A popular model for Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) is the detonation of a CO white dwarf (WD) that is triggered by the prior detonation of a thin surface layer of helium, known as a double detonation (DD). We explore the unique early electromagnetic signatures that are expected from collision of the CO detonation with the He detonation. The three features are (1) a shock breakout flash, (2) a stage of planar shock breakout cooling, and finally (3) shock cooling emission from the thermal energy released by the collision. The planar phase is unique to the unusual density profile of the He-detonated layer in comparison to the steep profile at a stellar edge as is usually considered for shock breakout. The shock cooling emission can be modified by recombination, and we explore these effects. All together, we expect an initial flash dominated by the planar phase of $\sim6\times10^{43}\,{\rm erg\,s^{-1}}$, which lasts ~5 s in the soft X-rays. This is followed by ~12-24 hrs of shock cooling at a luminosity of $3-10\times10^{40}\,{\rm erg\,s^{-1}}$ in the optical/UV. We discuss prospects for detection of this early DD emission with current and upcoming surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14290v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony L. Piro, Ehud Nakar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Frontiers in the Study of Magnetic Massive Stars with the Habitable Worlds Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-mass stars are notable for several reasons: they are characterized by strong winds, which inject momentum and enriched material into their surroundings, and die spectacularly as supernovae, leaving behind compact remnants and heavy elements (such as those that make life on Earth possible). Despite their relative rarity, they play a disproportionate role in the evolution of the galaxies that host them, and likely also played a significant role in the early days of the Universe. A subset ($\sim$10\%) of these stars was also found to host magnetic fields on their surface. These fields impact their evolution, and may lead to exotic physics (e.g., heavy stellar-mass black holes, pair-instability supernovae, magnetars, etc.). However, the detection and measurement of magnetic fields is limited, due to current instrumentation, to nearby massive stars in the Milky Way. To truly understand how magnetism arises in massive stars, and what role it might have played in earlier stages of our Universe, we require next-generation hardware, such as the proposed near-infrared-to-ultraviolet spectropolarimeter Pollux, on the Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO). In this contribution, we detail how Pollux @ HWO will enable new frontiers in the study of magnetic massive stars, delivering results that will profoundly impact the fields of stellar formation, stellar evolution, compact objects, and stellar feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14441v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre David-Uraz (Central Michigan University, Mount Pleasant, Michigan, USA), V\'eronique Petit (University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware, USA), Coralie Neiner (LESIA, Paris Observatory, PSL University, CNRS, Sorbonne University, Paris-Cit\'e University, Meudon, France), Jean-Claude Bouret (Aix-Marseille University, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France), Ya\"el Naz\'e (Groupe d'Astrophysique des Hautes Energies, STAR, Universit\'e de Li\`ege, Li\`ege, Belgium), Christiana Erba (Space Telescope Science Institute, Baltimore, Maryland, USA), Miriam Garcia (Centro de Astrobiolog\'ia, CSIC-INTA, Madrid, Spain), Kenneth Gayley (University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA), Richard Ignace (East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, Tennessee, USA), Ji\v{r}i Krti\v{c}ka (Masaryk University, Brno, Czech Republic), Hugues Sana (KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium), Nicole St-Louis (Universit\'e de Montr\'eal, Montr\'eal, Qu\'ebec, Canada), Asif ud-Doula (Penn State Scranton, Scranton, Pennsylvania, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new long period radio transient: Discovery of pulses repeating every 1.16 hours from ASKAP J175534.9-252749.1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of several new pulses from the source ASKAP J175534.9-252749.1 (J1755-2527), originally identified from a single 2-min long pulse, confirming it as a long period transient (LPT) with a period of ~1.16 hours. The pulses are significantly scattered, consistent with Galactic electron density models. Two of the new pulses also had measurable polarisation, but unlike the originally detected pulse, the polarisation angle does not behave as expected from the rotating vector model. We interpret historical non-detections of J1755-2527 as an intrinsic intermittency that occurs on month-long timescales, and discuss possible causes. We conjecture that, like some other LPTs with periods &gt;~ 1 hour, J1755-2527 may host a white dwarf in a binary orbit, but note that its period is marginally shorter than the canonical orbital period minimum of cataclysmic variables. Our work highlights the importance of additional observations in establishing the nature of unusual radio-emitting objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14448v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel J. McSweeney, Natasha Hurley-Walker, Csan\'ad Horv\'ath, Akash Anumarlapudi, Angie Waszewski, Dougal Dobie, David L. Kaplan, John Morgan, Kovi Rose, Ziteng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ALMA Survey of 70 $\mu$m Dark High-mass Clumps in Early Stages (ASHES). XII. Unanchored Forked Stream in the Propogating Path of a Protostellar Outflow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Outflows are key indicators of ongoing star formation. We report the discovery of an unanchored forked stream within the propagating path of an extremely young protostellar outflow in the 70 $\mu$m-dark clump G34.74-0.12, based on ALMA 1.3 mm observations with an angular resolution of 1''.6 (~ 5000 au). This outflow originate from a 9.7 $M_{\odot}$ core, exhibits a fork-shaped stream structure in its red-shifted lobe, which is traced by CO (2-1), SiO (5-4), and H$_2$CO (3$_{0,3}$-2$_{0,2}$). It has a momentum of 13 $M_{\odot}$ km s$^{-1}$, an energy of 107 $M_{\odot}$ km$^{2}$ s$^{-2}$, and a dynamical timescale of ~10$^{4}$ yr. Significantly, the enhanced relative abundances of SiO, H$_2$CO, and CH$_3$OH with respect to CO, along with the increased temperature at the forked point, indicate a collisional origin. The forked point does not coincide with any dust continuum core &gt; 0.1 $M_{\odot}$. Moreover, CO (2-1) emission also traces three other outflows in this region, characterized by their masses (0.40, 0.02 and 0.15 $M_{\odot}$) and momenta (5.2, 0.2, 1.8 $M_{\odot}$ km s$^{-1}$), as part of the ALMA Survey of 70 $\mu$m dark High-mass clumps in Early Stages (ASHES) project. All the newly discovered morphological and kinematic features associated with these extremely young protostellar outflows (with timescales of 10$^3$ - 10$^4$ years) suggest that the initial stages of star formation are more complicated than previously understood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14564v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuting Lin, Siyi Feng, Patricio Sanhueza, Ke Wang, Zhi-Yu Zhang, Yichen Zhang, Fengwei Xu, Junzhi Wang, Kaho Morii, Hauyu Baobab Liu, Sheng-Yuan Liu, Lile Wang, Hui Li, Daniel Tafoya, Willem Baan, Shanghuo Li, Giovanni Sabatini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallicity fluctuation statistics in the interstellar medium and young stars -- II. Elemental cross-correlations and the structure of chemical abundance space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observations of Milky Way stars by multiplexed spectroscopic instruments and of gas in nearby galaxies using integral field units have made it possible to measure the abundances of multiple elements in both the interstellar medium and the stars that form out of it. These observations have revealed complex correlations between elemental abundances, but thus far there has been no theoretical framework to interpret these data. In this paper we extend the simple stochastically-forced diffusion model of Krumholz &amp; Ting (2018), which has proven successful at explaining the spatial abundance patterns of single elements, to multiple elements, clarifying why elements are correlated and what controls their degree of correlation, and making quantitative predictions for the degree of correlation in both gas and young stars. We show that our results are qualitatively consistent with observed patterns, and point out how application of this theory to measured correlations should enable determination of currently unknown parameters describing r-process nucleosynthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14572v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark R. Krumholz, Yuan-Sen Ting, Zefeng Li, Chuhan Zhang, Jennifer Mead, Melissa K. Ness</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of compact objects in quadratic non-metricity gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14591v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrophysical compact objects are studied in the context of quadratic non-metricity gravity. The solutions to the gravitational field equations, which include fluid components, are analyzed to investigate the density and pressure properties of radio pulsars. It is explicitly demonstrated that the theoretically stable models are consistent with astronomical data, due to the geometric features of the quadratic component. Furthermore, it is shown that, in contrast to the compactness limits of black holes in general relativity, the core density can significantly exceed the density at which nuclear saturation occurs, and the surface density can also surpass the value of nuclear saturation. Additionally, it is found that the radial sound speed remains below the conformal upper bound for sound velocity established by perturbative quantum chromodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14591v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2025.170139</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annals of Physics, 170139 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. G. L. Nashed, Kazuharu Bamba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Cowling Approximation: A Verification of Ansatz via Methods of Functional and Asymptotic Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14737v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the Cowling approximation by analytical means as applied to a system of linear differential equations arising from models of non-radial stellar pulsation. We consider various asymptotic cases, including those of high harmonic degree and high oscillation frequency. Our methods involve a reformulation of the system in terms of an integro-differential equation for which certain Hilbert-space methods apply. By way of a more complete asymptotic study, we extend our results to certain fundamental solution sets, characterized according to certain multi-point boundary-value problems: Such asymptotics further enable us to produce sharp estimates as confirmation of our general results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14737v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1515/jaa-2025-0037</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Christopher J. Winfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic helicity flux density for radiative systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14966v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electromagnetic (EM) helicity flux density and the magnetic helicity are related by topological Chern-Simons terms. We show that the helicity flux density is distinguished from magnetic helicity by analysing Hopf solitons. We find the helicity flux density for a point charge moving with an acceleration, extending the Li\'enard-Wiechert angular distribution of radiant power. We also derive the multipole expansion of the helicity flux density, generalizing the Larmor's formula for the radiant power. These formulae have been applied to discuss the helicity flux density in several toy models such as circular and helical motion as well as soft bremsstrahlung. We also comment on the potential applications of the EM helicity flux density to pulsar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14966v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Heng, Jiang Long, Run-Ze Yu, Xin-Hao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar-Mass Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15270v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stellar-mass black holes ($3$ $M_\odot \lesssim M_{\rm BH} \lesssim 150$ $M_\odot$) are the natural product of the evolution of heavy stars ($M_{\rm star} \gtrsim 20$ $M_\odot$). In our Galaxy, we expect $10^8$-$10^9$ stellar-mass black holes formed from the gravitational collapse of heavy stars, but currently we know less than 100 objects. We also know $\sim 100$ stellar-mass black holes in other galaxies, most of them discovered by gravitational wave observatories in the past 10 years. The detection of black holes is indeed extremely challenging and possible only in very special cases. This article is a short review on the physics and astrophysics of stellar-mass black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15270v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cosimo Bambi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified model for long-period radio transients and white dwarf binary pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15352v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Long-period radio transients (LPTs) represent a recently uncovered class of Galactic radio sources exhibiting minute-to-hour periodicities and highly polarised pulses of second-to-minute duration. Their phenomenology does not fit exactly in any other class, although it might resemble that of radio magnetars or of white dwarf (WD) radio emitting binary systems. Notably, two LPTs with confirmed multi-wavelength counterparts have been identified as synchronised white dwarf-M dwarf binaries (polars). Meanwhile, systems such as AR Scorpii and J1912-44 exhibit short-period pulsations in a hr-tight orbit, with polarized radio emission proposed to be generated by the interaction of the WD magnetosphere with the low-mass companion wind.
  Here we demonstrate that both LPTs and WD binary pulsars can be explained within a single geometric model in which radio emission is triggered when the magnetic pole of a rotating white dwarf intersects its companion's wind in the binary orbital plane. We use a 36-year timing baseline to infer the orbital period and binary geometry solely from radio data of GPM J1839-10, the longest-active LPT known. The model naturally predicts its intermittent emission and double-pulse structure. Crucially, we show that the beat period between the spin and the orbit matches the observed pulse substructure and polarisation signatures, providing strong support for the model. Applying this model to the WD binary pulsar J1912-44, it can also reproduce the system emission and geometry. Our results place GPM J1839-10, and other LPTs in general and radio emitting WD binaries, at different stages of a continuum between intermediate and synchronised polars, suggesting a unified population of magnetic WD binaries driving coherent radio emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15352v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Csan\'ad Horv\'ath, Nanda Rea, Natasha Hurley-Walker, Samuel J. McSweeney, Richard A. Perley, Emil Lenc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and challenges to study solar neutrinos with a Q-Pix pixel readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of solar neutrinos presents significant opportunities in astrophysics, nuclear physics, and particle physics. However, the low-energy nature of these neutrinos introduces considerable challenges to isolate them from background events, requiring detectors with low-energy threshold, high spatial and energy resolutions, and low data rate. We present the study of solar neutrinos with a kiloton-scale liquid argon detector located underground, instrumented with a pixel readout using the Q-Pix technology. We explore the potential of using volume fiducialization, directional topological information, light signal coincidence and pulse-shape discrimination to enhance solar neutrino sensitivity. We find that discriminating neutrino signals below 5 MeV is very difficult. However, we show that these methods are useful for the detection of solar neutrinos when external backgrounds are sufficiently understood and when the detector is built using low-background techniques. When building a workable background model for this study, we identify {\gamma} background from the cavern walls and from capture of {\alpha} particles in radon decay chains as both critical to solar neutrino sensitivity and significantly underconstrained by existing measurements. Finally, we highlight that the main advantage of the use of Q-Pix for solar neutrino studies lies in its ability to enable the continuous readout of all low-energy events with minimal data rates and manageable storage for further offline analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15459v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, G. Ruiz, S. Kubota, A. Navrer-Agasson, G. V. Stenico, E. Gramellini, R. Guenette, J. Asaadi, J. B. R. Battat, V. A. Chirayath, E. Church, Z. Djurcic, A. C. Ezeribe, J. N. Gainer, G. Gansle, K. Keefe, N. Lane, C. Mauger, Y. Mei, F. M. Newcomer, D. R. Nygren, M. Rooks, P. Sau, O. Seidel, S. S\"oldner-Rembold, I. Tzoka, R. Van Berg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar disk gamma-rays emission via synthetic magnetic field from photosphere to low corona</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gamma-ray emission in the GeV-TeV range from the solar disk is likely to arise from collisions of galactic cosmic rays (GCRs) with solar atmospheric plasma. In a previous study, we demonstrated that closed turbulent magnetic arcades trap efficiently GCRs leading to a gamma-ray flux consistent with the Fermi-HAWC observations (from $\sim 0.1$ GeV to $\sim 1$ TeV). Here, we model a synthetic magnetic field with a static, laminar structure of open field lines in the chromosphere increasingly braiding near the solar surface, with a scale height of $\sim 10^{-2} R_\odot$. The height-dependent increase in magnetic field line braiding is modulated by an exponential scalar function, mimicking the bending of the photo- and chromo-spheric magnetic field revealed by polarimetric observations and reproduced by MHD simulations. Employing 3D test-particle numerical simulations, we investigate how distorted magnetic field lines affect the gamma-rays production by injecting GeV-TeV protons into both magnetically laminar and braided regions. We find that with the chosen spatial resolution this synthetic magnetic field can account for the $&gt; 10$ GeV gamma-ray spectrum observed by Fermi-LAT/HAWC. A rebrightening between approximately $30$ and $100$ GeV (following a $\sim 30$ GeV spectral dip), suggests an enhanced confinement within the photo-/chromospheric layer by a stronger braiding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15468v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleonora Puzzoni, Federico Fraschetti, J\'ozsef K\'ota, Joe Giacalone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Common Origin of Normal Type Ia Supernovae Suggested by the Photometric Diversity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15609v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, with an increasing number of type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) discovered soon after their explosions, a non-negligible fraction of SNe Ia with early-excess emissions (EExSNe Ia) have been confirmed. In this letter, we present a total of \textbf{67} early-phase normal SNe Ia from published papers and ongoing transient survey projects to systematically investigate their photometric behaviors from very early time. We found that EExSNe Ia in our sample have longer rise and brighter peak luminosities compared to those of non-EExSNe Ia. Moreover, EExSNe Ia commonly have ``red-bump" features in the early $B-V$ color while non-EExSNe Ia show blueward evolution from the very beginning. Here, we propose that the thin-helium double-detonation scenario can phenomenologically explain the photometric diversities of normal SNe Ia considering different white dwarf-He-shell mass combinations and the viewing-angle effect, implying a unified explosion mechanism of normal-type SNe Ia. To further testify the possible common origin of normal SNe Ia, systematical studies of multiband photometric and spectral properties of early-phase SNe Ia through the new generation wide-field time-domain survey facilities and global real-time follow-up networks are highly demanded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15609v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyu Wu, Ji-an Jiang, Dezheng Meng, Zelin Xu, Keiichi Maeda, Mamoru Doi, Ken'ichi Nomoto, Naoki Yasuda, Masaomi Tanaka, Toshikazu Shigeyama, Nozomu Tominaga, \v{Z}eljko Ivezi\'c, Peter Yoachim, Saurabh W. Jha, Tinggui Wang, Nao Suzuki, Hisanori Furusawa, Andrew J. Connolly, Satoshi Miyazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New theoretical instability regions, period-luminosity relations and masses for blue large-amplitude pulsators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16912v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Blue large-amplitude pulsators (BLAPs) are a recently discovered group of hot pulsating stars whose evolutionary status remains uncertain. Their supposed progenitors are either $\simeq 0.3M_{\odot}$ shell H-burning stars or $\simeq 1.0M_{\odot}$ core He-burning stars, both relying on mass loss or a merger event in a (rarely observed) close interacting binary system. With the goal to understand the stellar masses of BLAPs, we therefore carried out a linear non-adiabatic analysis of a grid of models computed using mesa-rsp, with appropriate input stellar parameters $ZXMLT_{\rm eff}$ and convection parameter sets. We discuss the impact of stellar mass, metallicity, helium abundance and convection parameters on the theoretical instability regions of BLAPs. We also derive new theoretical period relations; our theoretical period relations using low stellar masses seem to be in better agreement with the observed period relations. Although only two BLAPS have been observed to be multi-periodic oscillator so far, we analyse theoretical $P_{1O}/P_F$ ratios and compare these values with other classical pulsators. Furthermore, we provide the first asteroseismic mass estimate for the triple-mode pulsator, OGLE-BLAP-030 which seems to be well-constrained in the range of $0.62-0.64 M_{\odot}$ with a high metallicity of $Z=0.07$, albeit with a few sources of uncertainty involved. This would place the BLAP star intermediate to the two proposed mass scenarios so far.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16912v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susmita Das, Daniel Jadlovsk\'y, L\'aszl\'o Moln\'ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Determination of the Mass of NGC 3603-A1: the Most Massive Binary Known?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13522v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The star NGC 3603-A1 has long been known to be a very massive binary, consisting of a pair of O2-3If*/WN5-6 stars, which show Wolf-Rayet-like emission due to their luminosities being near the Eddington limit. The system has been poorly characterized until now, due to the difficulties of obtaining reliable radial velocities from broad, blended emission lines and the extreme crowding in the cluster. However, previously unpublished archival HST/STIS spectra revealed that some of the upper Balmer lines (seen in absorption) are well separated at favorable orbital phases, prompting us to obtain our own carefully-timed new HST/STIS spectra, which we have analyzed along with the older data. Radial velocities measured from these spectra allow us to obtain an orbit for this 3.77298 day system. We also used archival STIS imaging of the cluster to obtain a more accurate light curve for this eclipsing system, which we then modeled, yielding the orbital inclination and providing values for the stellar radii and temperatures. Together, these data show that the NGC 3603-A1 system consists of a 93.3+/-11.0 Mo O3If*/WN6 primary with an effective temperature of 37,000 K, and a 70.4+/-9.3 Mo O3If*/WN5 secondary that is slightly hotter, 42,000 K. Although a more massive binary is known in the LMC, NGC 3603-A1 is as massive as any binary known in our own Galaxy for which a direct measurement of its mass has been made. The secondary has been spun up by mass accretion from the primary, and we discuss the evolutionary status of this intriguing system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13522v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Massey, Sarah Bodansky, Laura R. Penny, Nidia I. Morrell, Kathryn F. Neugent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bringing the Norma Dark Cloud to Light in X-rays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09047v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The filamentary dark cloud complex in Norma reveals signs of active low-mass star formation including protostars, H-alpha emission line stars, Herbig Haro objects, and the eruptive FU Orionis-like star V346 Nor. We present results of the first pointed X-ray observations of the Norma dark cloud, focusing on the westernmost Sandqvist 187 region. Chandra detected 75 X-ray sources and a complementary XMM-Newton observation detected 92 sources within the Chandra field-of-view, of which 46 are cross-matched to Chandra, yielding 121 unique X-ray sources. We present a catalog of X-ray sources along with basic X-ray properties and candidate IR and optical counterparts. Existing near-IR photometry reveals several X-ray sources with color excesses as typical of young stars with disks. Gaia parallaxes single out foreground stars and X-ray sources with distances of 500 - 1000 pc that are probable cloud members. The known emission line stars Sz 136 and Sz 137 were detected but V346 Nor was not. Interestingly, the optical and IR counterparts of the brightest Chandra source are not known with certainty but the prime suspects are very faint. Thus, the nature of the object responsible for the bright X-ray emission remains speculative. The X-ray observations presented here will serve as a pathfinder for identifying and characterizing the young stellar population in the Norma dark cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09047v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen L. Skinner, Manuel Guedel, Luisa M. Rebull</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass-gap Black Holes in Coalescing Neutron Star Black Hole Binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20415v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The existence of a mass gap of $3-5\,M_{\odot}$ between the heaviest neutron stars (NSs) and the lightest black holes (BHs), inferred from the BH mass distribution in low mass X-ray binaries (LMXBs), has been suggested for decades. The recently reported gravitational-wave source GW230529 has been confidently identified as a NSBH merger, with the BH mass falling within this lower mass gap. This detection provides strong evidence against the existence of the latter and introduces new implications for the coalescing NSBH population, including a revised BH mass distribution and an updated local merger rate. In this study, we employ POSYDON, a binary population synthesis code that integrates detailed single- and binary-star models, to investigate coalescing NSBH binaries formed through isolated binary evolution. In particular, we focus on the BH mass distribution of the intrinsic NSBH merger population. We find that, with a high common-envelope efficiency of $\alpha_{\rm{CE}} =2 $, the BH masses in NSBH mergers concentrate in the lower mass gap, aligning more closely with observations. However, after accounting for the constraints of the selection bias against mass-gap BHs in LMXBs, which suggests that the maximum NS birth mass is below $\simeq 2\,M_{\odot}$, we find that introducing a high $\alpha_{\rm{CE}}$ is not required to match observations. Additionally, we explore the impact of core-collapse supernova kicks. Finally, we present the property distributions of observable NSBH mergers from our simulation and find that they match well with the observations. We find that the fraction of electromagnetic counterparts in observable populations is $\approx 4-30\%$, depending on different NS equations of state. Future detections of coalescing NSBH binaries would provide invaluable insights into SN mechanisms, common envelope evolution, and NS physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20415v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zepei Xing, Vicky Kalogera, Tassos Fragos, Jeff J. Andrews, Simone S. Bavera, Max Briel, Seth Gossage, Konstantinos Kovlakas, Matthias U. Kruckow, Kyle A. Rocha, Meng Sun, Philipp M. Srivastava, Emmanouil Zapartas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The angular momentum of stars reflects the relationship between star-forming environment and galactic evolution history</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01035v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study focuses on stars with masses above the Kraft break in the \textit{Kepler} field. Their rotational angular momenta are essentially the same as those at the zero-age main sequence. The angular momentum dissipation experienced by these stars during their pre-main sequence phase is also relatively weak, so their rotational angular momentum can reflect the parameters of their parental molecular clouds. The reliability of angular momentum measurements was evaluated based on the phenomenon of angular momentum conservation observed in stars before and after the turn-off point in observational data. We find that stars with masses between 1.4$M_\odot$ and 1.8$M_\odot$ show an inverse proportionality between angular momentum and isochrone age. We propose that the angular momentum-age correlation reflects changes in the star-forming environment in the Milky Way's history. Besides, the observed inverse proportionality implies that, as the Milky Way has evolved, the stars formed within it tend to possess greater rotational angular momenta. This trend would promote the fragmentation of stars during the pre-main sequence phase and inhibit the formation of massive stars, providing a useful perspective for explaining variations in the initial mass function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01035v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ade399</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 988:125, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Fu Shen, Yan Xu, Yi-Bo Wang, Xiu-Lin Huang, Xing-Xing Hu, Qi Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$g$-mode oscillations of dark matter admixed neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18892v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate $g$-mode oscillations in dark matter admixed neutron stars employing a relativistic mean field model to describe hadronic matter and a model for self-interacting fermionic dark matter motivated by the neutron decay anomaly. Following the construction of such admixed configurations, we derive the equilibrium and adiabatic speeds of sound therein, leading to a computation of the star's $g$-mode spectrum in the Cowling approximation. In particular, we explore the effect of dark matter self-interaction, the nucleon effective mass and dark matter fraction on the principal $g$-mode frequency, and its first overtone. We show that the effect on $g$-mode frequency depends predominantly on the dark matter fraction, and demonstrate an equation of state-independent constraint for the latter. Prospects of identifying the presence of dark matter in neutron stars using $g$-mode are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18892v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swarnim Shirke, Debarati Chatterjee, Prashanth Jaikumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
