<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 01:46:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>What determines the brightness of magnetically open solar corona?: Insights from three-dimensional radiative MHD simulations and observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the relationship between solar coronal holes and open-field regions using three-dimensional radiative magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations combined with remote-sensing observations from the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO). Our numerical simulations reveal that magnetically open regions in the corona can exhibit brightness comparable to quiet regions, challenging the conventional view that open-field regions are inherently dark coronal holes. We find that the coronal brightness is primarily determined by the total energy input from photospheric magnetic activities, such as the small-scale dynamo, rather than differences in dissipative processes within the corona. Using synthesized EUV intensity maps, we show that brightness thresholds commonly used to identify coronal holes may overlook open-field regions, especially at lower spatial resolutions. Observational analysis utilizing SDO/HMI and AIA synoptic maps supports our simulation results, demonstrating that magnetic field extrapolation techniques, such as the Potential Field Source Surface (PFSS) model, are sensitive to the chosen parameters, including the source surface height. We suggest that discrepancies in estimates of open magnetic flux (the ``open flux problem'') arise both from the modeling assumptions in coronal magnetic field extrapolation and systematic biases in solar surface magnetic field observations. Our findings indicate the need for reconsidering criteria used to identify coronal holes as indicators of open-field regions to better characterize the solar open magnetic flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14049v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruhisa Iijima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Period Variation Rates of Four Radial Single-Mode High-Amplitude Delta Scuti Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present a study on the long time-scale period variations of four single-mode high-amplitude delta Scuti stars (HADS) via the classical $O-C$ analysis. The target HADS are (i) XX Cygni, (ii) YZ Bootis, (iii) GP Andromedae, and (iv) ZZ Microscopii. The newly determined times of maximum light came from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), American Association of Variable Star Observers (AAVSO), and Bundesdeutsche Arbeitsgemeinschaft f$\ddot{\rm u}$r Ver$\ddot{\rm a}$nderliche Sterne (BAV) projects. Together with the times of maximum light obtained in the historical literature, the $O-C$ analysis was performed on these HADS, in which we obtained the linear period variation rates $\dot{P}/P$ as $(9.2 \pm 0.2) \times 10^{-9} \ \mathrm{yr^{-1}}$, $(3.2\pm 0.2)\times 10^{-9} \ \mathrm{yr^{-1}}$, $(4.22\pm 0.03) \times 10^{-8} \ \mathrm{yr^{-1}}$, and $(-2.06 \pm 0.02) \times 10^{-8} \ \mathrm{yr^{-1}}$, respectively. Based on these results and some earlier research, we also discuss the evolutionary stages and the mechanisms of the period variation of these four HADS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14186v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe11030086</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2025, 11(3), 86</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Fang Ma, Jia-Shu Niu, Hui-Fang Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CY Aquarii: A Triple System with Twin Companions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we conducted a comprehensive analysis of the SX Phoenicis (SX Phe) type star CY Aquarii (CY Aqr). Our investigation included a detailed $O-C$ analysis based on a 90-year observational dataset, augmented by 1,367 newly determined times of maximum light. The $O-C$ diagram reveals that (i) the primary star of CY Aqr exhibits a linear period variation rate of $(1/P_0)(\mathrm{d} P/ \mathrm{d} t) = (2.132 \pm 0.002) \times 10^{-8} \mathrm{yr}^{-1}$ for its dominant pulsation mode; (ii) the primary star is disturbed by two companions and part of a triple system; (iii) Companion A has an orbital period of approximately 60.2 years and Companion B has an orbital period of approximately 50.8 years. It is highly probable that both Companion A and B are white dwarfs, with Companion A's elliptical orbit displaying an eccentricity of $e = 0.139 \pm 0.002$, which is the lowest confirmed value in similar binary and triple systems to date. Most notably, Companion A and B have masses that are identical within the uncertainties, with a mass ratio exceeding 0.99. Whether this is considered a coincidental event or the result of an underlying mechanism, CY Aqr is an exceptionally rare case that broadens our understanding of multiple star systems and offers a unique opportunity to delve into the enigmatic evolutionary histories of such configurations. Further intriguing characteristics of this system warrant investigation in future studies, based on additional observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14189v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adc376</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 983:140 (11pp), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ming Lian, Jia-Shu Niu, Hui-Fang Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-wavelength spectropolarimetric observations of AR13724 performed by GRIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14358v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-line spectropolarimetric observations allow for the simultaneous inference of the magnetic field at different layers of the solar atmosphere and provide insight into how these layers are magnetically coupled. The new upgrade of the Gregor Infrared Spectrograph (GRIS) instrument offers such a possibility, allowing for the simultaneous observation of the Ca II line at 8542 A, the Si I line at 10827 A, and the He I triplet at 10830 A in addition to some additional weaker spectral lines that can probe deeper in the photosphere. Because these spectral lines are sensitive to the plasma properties at different regions of the solar atmosphere, their combined analysis can help understand the stratification of its thermal and magnetic properties from the photosphere to the chromosphere. This work showcases recent observations of the upgraded GRIS at the active region AR13724, which shows the instrument's potential for unravelling the most minute details of solar phenomena. In particular, we analyse the spatial distribution of the polarisation signals as well as the distribution of Stokes profiles for different regimes of the magnetic field strength. We also conduct a preliminary data analysis using relatively simple and approximate methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14358v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Quintero Noda, J. C. Trelles Arjona, T. del Pino Alem\'an, C. M\'endez L\'apido, M. J. Mart\'inez Gonz\'alez, T. Felipe, S. Regalado Olivares, P. G\'omez Gonz\'alez, J. Bienes, J. Quintero Nehrkorn, A. Matta-G\'omez, M. Barreto, M. Collados</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fate of the progenitors of Luminous Red Novae: Infrared detection of LRNe years after the outburst</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present late-time optical and infrared (IR) observations of a sample of nine extragalactic Luminous Red Novae (LRNe) discovered in the last three decades. In all these cases, the LRN survivors fade below the pre-outburst luminosity of the progenitors in the optical region. Instead, they remain visible in the near-IR (NIR), and bright in the mid-IR (MIR) domains for years. We recover AT 1997bs in $Spitzer$ images from 2004, and a residual source is visible in HST and $JWST$ NIR images 27 years after the outburst. Its spectral energy distribution (SED) is consistent with that of a red supergiant star with a photospheric temperature of 3200 K and a radius of 220 $R_{\odot}$, without a significant circumstellar dust attenuation, as the source is not detected at 4.5 $\mu$m. Another LRN, AT 2011kp, is detected by $JWST$ 12.5 years after the outburst. From its SED, we find evidence for three black-body components: a warm/hot stellar component, a colder component from cool dust at 425 K, emitting between 3 and 6 $\mu$m, and a third even colder component responsible for the excess at 8 $\mu$m, possibly due to an IR echo. We construct the $[3.6]-[4.5]$ colour curves extending up to +7 years for six LRNe, which show a similar evolution: the MIR colour is $\sim0$ before the optical maximum light, it becomes bluer ($\sim-0.5$ mag) at around +1 year, then it gradually turns to redder colours ($\sim+0.5$ mag) in the following years, before reaching $[3.6]-[4.5]\sim+1.5$ mag 7 years after the outburst. Finally, we also estimate the masses and the temperatures of newly-formed dust years after the LRN onset for different chemical compositions (silicates or graphite) and grain sizes (0.1 or 1.0 $\mu$m). We find that LRNe produce dust masses of the order of (0.1-30)$\times10^{-6}$ $M_{\odot}$ between 3.6 and 13 years after the outbursts, with temperatures in the range from 350 to 770 K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14592v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Reguitti, A. Pastorello, G. Valerin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Semidetached Eclipsing Binaries from TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semidetached binaries, distinguished by their mass transfer phase, play a crucial role in elucidating the physics of mass transfer within interacting binary systems. To identify these systems in eclipsing binary light curves provided by large-scale time-domain surveys, we have developed a methodology by training two distinct models that establish a mapping relationship between the parameters (orbital parameters and physical parameters) of semidetached binaries and their corresponding light curves. The first model corresponds to scenarios where the more massive star fills its Roche lobe, while the second model addresses situations where the less massive star does so. In consideration of the O'Connell effect observed in the light curves, we integrated a cool spot parameter into our models, thereby enhancing their applicability to fit light curves that exhibit this phenomenon. Our two-model framework was then harmonized with the Markov Chain Monte Carlo algorithm, enabling precise and efficient light-curve fitting and parameter estimation. Leveraging 2 minute cadence data from the initial 67 sectors of the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite, we successfully identified 327 systems where the less massive component fills its Roche lobe, alongside three systems where the more massive component fills its Roche lobe. Additionally, we offer comprehensive fundamental parameters for these binary systems, including orbital inclination, relative radius, mass ratio, and effective temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14612v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Ding, KaiFan Ji, QiYuan Cheng, ZhiMing Song, JinLiang Wang, XueFen Tian, ChuanJun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Survival Guide: Searching for Stars in the Galactic Center That Endure Partial Tidal Disruption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Once per 10,000-100,000 years, an unlucky star may experience a close encounter with a supermassive black hole (SMBH), partially or fully tearing apart the star in an exceedingly brief, bright interaction called a tidal disruption event (TDE). Remnants of partial TDEs are expected to be plentiful in our Galactic Center, where at least six unexplained, diffuse, star-like "G objects" have already been detected which may have formed via interactions between stars and the SMBH. Using numerical simulations, this work aims to identify the characteristics of TDE remnants. We take 3D hydrodynamic FLASH models of partially disrupted stars and map them into the 1D stellar evolution code MESA to examine the properties of these remnants from tens to billions of years after the TDE. The remnants initially exhibit a brief, highly luminous phase, followed by an extended cooling period as they return to stable hydrogen burning. During the initial stage (&lt; 10,000 yr) their luminosities increase by orders of magnitude, making them intriguing candidates to explain a fraction of the mysterious G objects. Notably, mild TDEs are the most common and result in the brightest remnants during this initial phase. However, most remnants exist in a long-lived stage where they are only modestly offset in temperature and luminosity compared to main-sequence stars of equivalent mass. Nonetheless, our results indicate remnants will sustain abnormal, metal-enriched envelopes that may be discernible through spectroscopic analysis. Identifying TDE survivors within the Milky Way could further illuminate some of the most gravitationally intense encounters in the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14705v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rewa Clark Bush, Samantha C. Wu, Rosa Wallace Everson, Ricardo Yarza, Ariadna Murguia-Berthier, Enrico Ramirez-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initiation Route of Coronal Mass Ejections: II. The Role of Filament Mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thorough understanding on the initiation of coronal mass ejections (CMEs), which is manifested as a slow rise of pre-eruptive structures before the impulsive ejection in kinematics, is the key for forecasting the solar eruptions. In our previous work, we showed that the slow rise of a hot flux rope with coronal mass density is caused by the moderate magnetic reconnection occurring in the hyperbolic flux tube (HFT) combined with the torus instability. However, it remains unclear how the initiation process varies when a filament is present in the pre-eruptive flux rope. In this work, we reveal the complete initiation route of a CME containing filament mass with a state-of-the-art full-magnetohydrodynamics simulation. The comprehensive analyses show that the filament mass has an important impact on the CME initiation through triggering and driving the slow rise of flux rope with its drainage, besides the contributions of HFT reconnection and torus instability. Finally, in combination with our previous work, we propose that the enhanced drainage of filament mass and various features related to the HFT reconnection, such as, the split of pre-eruptive structure and the pre-flare loops and X-ray emissions, can serve as the precursors of CME initiation in observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14876v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Xing, Xin Cheng, Guillaume Aulanier, Mingde Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of angular scattering and H+p, H+H collisions on the properties of interstellar atoms in the heliosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interstellar hydrogen atoms (H atoms) penetrate into the heliosphere through the region of the solar wind interaction with the interstellar plasma due to their large mean free path. Resonant charge exchange of H atoms with protons has been considered as the main interaction process between the components. In the majority of models, other processes like elastic H-H and H-p collisions are not included. Moreover, it has been assumed that the velocities of the colliding particles remain unchanged during charge exchange. This corresponds to the scattering on the angle of $\pi$ in the centre mass rest frame.
  The goal of this paper is to explore effects of the elastic H-H and H-p collisions as well as the angular scattering during charge exchange on the distribution of the interstellar atoms in the heliosphere and at its boundary.
  We present results of simple (and therefore, easily repeatable) kinetic model of the interstellar atom penetration through the region of the solar and interstellar winds interaction into the heliosphere. As a result of the model we compute the distribution function of the interstellar atoms at different heliospheric distances. Further, this distribution function is used to compute its moments and potentially observable features such as absorption and backscattered spectra in the Lyman-alpha line.
  Results show that there are differences in the behavior of the distribution function when considering elastic collisions and the changes in the moments of the distribution achieve 10%. Therefore, in cases where precise calculation of H atom parameters is essential, such as in the modeling of backscattered Lyman-$\alpha$ emission, elastic collisions must be considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14976v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/pasa.2025.33</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia, pp. 1-14, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Titova, V. V. Izmodenov, S. D. Korolkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Formation Mechanism of Counterstreaming Mass Flows in Filaments and the Doppler Bullseye Pattern in Prominences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14984v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The eruption of solar prominences can eject substantial mass and magnetic field into interplanetary space and cause geomagnetic storms. However, various questions about prominences and their eruption mechanism remain unclear. In particular, what causes the intriguing Doppler bullseye pattern in prominences has not yet been solved, despite some preliminary studies proposing that they are probably associated with counterstreaming mass flows. Previous studies are mainly based on single-angle and short timescale observations, making it difficult to determine the physical origin of Doppler bullseye patterns in prominences. Here, taking advantage of stereoscopic observations taken by the Solar Dynamics Observatory and the Solar Terrestrial Relations Observatory and a three-dimensional numerical simulation, we investigate the origin of prominence Doppler bullseye pattern by tracing a long-lived transequatorial filament/prominence from July 23 to August 4, 2012. We find that repeated coronal jets at one end of the prominence can launch the Doppler bullseye pattern. It is evidenced in our observations and simulation that during the forward traveling of jet plasma along the helical magnetic field structure of the prominence, part of the ejecting plasma can not pass through the apex of the prominence due to the insufficient kinetic energy and therefore forms a backward-moving mass flow along the same or neighboring magnetic field lines. This process finally forms counterstreaming mass flows in on-disk filaments. When the on-disk filament rotates to the solar limb to be a prominence, the counterstreaming mass flows are naturally observed as a Doppler bullseye pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14984v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengrui Zhou, Yuandeng Shen, Chun Xia, Dongxu Liu, Zehao Tang, Surui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Height-Dependent Slow Magnetoacoustic Wave Amplitude and Energy Flux in Sunspot Atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15030v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Slow magnetoacoustic waves (SMAWs) have been considered in the past as a possible candidate for chromospheric heating. This study analyzes 20 active regions observed between 2012 and 2016 to examine the amplitude and energy flux variation of SMAWs in the umbral atmosphere. Six different wavelength channels from the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly onboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory, covering regions from the photosphere to the low corona, were utilized for this purpose. The wave amplitude estimations show a gradual increase in 3-minute oscillation amplitude, peaking between 700--900 km, followed by a steady decrease; at altitudes greater than 1800 km, the amplitude appears to increase and then decrease again. The corresponding energy flux, on the other hand, displays a steady and monotonous decrease with a significant reduction in value from approximately $3.32 \pm 0.50~\mathrm{kW,m^{-2}}$ near the photosphere to about $(6.47 \pm 3.16) \times 10^{-4}~\mathrm{W,m^{-2}}$ at an altitude of 2585 km. This decay may be attributed to radiative damping and shock dissipation in the lower altitudes, and thermal conduction and viscosity in the higher altitudes. The missing flux is a factor of 3--15 lower than that required to counterbalance the chromospheric radiative losses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15030v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Sanjay, S. Krishna Prasad, P. S. Rawat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Period-luminosity and period-luminosity-metallicity relation for $\delta$ Scuti Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $\delta$ Scuti ($\delta$ Sct) stars are potential distance tracers for studying the Milky Way structure. We conduct a comprehensive analysis of the period-luminosity (PL) and period-luminosity-metallicity (PLZ) relation for $\delta$ Sct stars, integrating data from the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF), the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST), Apache Point Observatory Galactic Evolution Experiment (APOGEE), and Gaia. To mitigate the impact of the Gaia parallax zero point offset, we applied a correction method, determining the optimal zero point value to be $zp_\varpi = 35 \pm 2 \, \mu\text{as}$. Using the three best bands, by varying the parallax error threshold, we found that the total error of the PLR zero point was minimized to 0.9\% at a parallax error threshold of 6\%. With this threshold, we derived the PL and PLZ relation for nine bands (from optical to mid-infrared) and five Wesenheit bands. Through our analysis, we conclude that the influence of metallicity on the PLR of $\delta$ Sct stars is not significant, and the differences across various bands are minimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15045v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-qi Liu, Xiao-dian Chen, Shu Wang, Kun Wang, Qi Jia, Li-cai Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-constrained Magnetohydrodynamic Simulation of a Filament Eruption in a Decaying Active Region 13079 on a Global Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Filaments are special plasma phenomena embedded in the solar atmosphere, characterized by unique thermodynamic properties and magnetic structures. Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations are useful to investigate the eruption mechanisms of filaments. We conduct a data-constrained zero-$\beta$ MHD simulation in spherical coordinates to investigate a C3.5 class flare triggered by an eruptive filament on 2022 August 15 in a decaying weak active region 13079. We reconstruct the three-dimensional coronal magnetic field using vector magnetograms and synoptic maps from the Solar Dynamics Observatory/Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (SDO/HMI). We transform vector magnetic field into Stonyhurst heliographic spherical coordinates combined with a synoptic map and constructed a potential field source surface (PFSS) model with a magnetic flux rope (MFR) embedded using the Regularized Biot--Savart Laws (RBSL). Subsequently, we conduct a spherical zero-$\beta$ MHD simulation using the Message Passing Interface Adaptive Mesh Refinement Versatile Advection Code (MPI-AMRVAC) and replicated the entire dynamic process of the filament eruption consistent with observations. With the calculation of time-distance profile, Qusai-Separatrix Layers (QSL), and synthetic radiation from simulated current density, we find a good agreement between our simulation and observations in terms of dynamics and magnetic topology. Technically, we provide a useful method of advanced data-constrained simulation of weak active regions in spherical coordinates. Scientifically, the model allows us to quantitatively describe and diagnose the entire process of filament eruption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15069v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihua Li, Yang Guo, Jinhan Guo, M. D. Ding, Chun Xia, Rony Keppens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiwavelength Observations of the Precursors Before the Eruptive X4.9 Limb Solar Flare on 25 February, 2014: Current Sheet, Eruptive Filament, Flare and Eruption Onset in the Frame of the Tether-Cutting Magnetic Reconnection Scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present multiwavelength analysis of the pre-flare phase and onset of the powerful X4.9 near-limb eruptive solar flare on February 25, 2014, revealing the tether-cutting (TC) geometry. We aim at determining relationship between the region of pre-flare energy release with the regions where the flare started to develop, and to investigate a detailed chronology of energy release during the pre-flare time interval and the beginning of the impulse phase. Using X-ray, ultraviolet and radio microwave data we found that the pre-flare energy release site was compact and localized in the vicinity of TC interaction of magnetic structures near the polarity inversion line. The analysis indicates that a pre-flare current sheet (CS) could be in this region. Good correspondence between the location of the pre-flare and flare emission sources visible at the very beginning of the impulsive phase is shown. We found relationship between dynamics of the energy release in the pre-flare CS and formation of the future flare eruptive structure. The growth of the magnetic flux rope was associated with activation of plasma emissions, flows and an increase of UV radiation fluxes from the region where the pre-flare CS was located. The eruptive flux rope gradually grew due to feeding by magnetized plasma ejected from the reconnecting pre-flare CS. Finally, it is shown that the most probable trigger of the eruption was a local fast microflare-like magnetic reconnection in the pre-flare CS. Some local instability in the pre-flare sheet could lead to a transition from the slow to fast reconnection regime. As a result, an ejection from the sheet was initiated and the eruptive flux rope lost its stability. Then, the eruptive flux rope itself initiated formation of the main reconnecting flare CS as in the Standard Flare Model during its movement, and intense emissions associated with the impulsive phase were observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15097v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharykin I. N., Zimovets I. V., Motorina G. G., Meshalkina N. S</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multidimensional half-moment multigroup radiative transfer. Improving moment-based thermal models of circumstellar disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Common radiative transfer methods, such as flux-limited diffusion (FLD) and the M1 closure, suffer from artificial interactions between crossing beams. In protoplanetary disks, this leads to an overestimation of the midplane temperature due to the merging of vertical inward and outward fluxes. Methods that avoid these artifacts typically require angular discretization, which can be computationally expensive. In the spirit of the two-stream approximation, we aim to remove the interaction between beams in a fixed spatial direction by introducing a half-moment (HM) closure, which integrates the radiative intensity over hemispheres. We derive a multidimensional HM closure via entropy maximization and replace it with an approximate expression that closely matches it, coinciding in the diffusion and free-streaming regimes while remaining expressible through simple operations. We implement the HM and M1 closures via implicit-explicit (IMEX) schemes, including multiple frequency groups. We test these methods in numerical benchmarks, including computing the temperature in an irradiated disk around a T Tauri star, comparing the results with Monte Carlo (MC) radiative transfer simulations. The resulting HM closure tends to the correct limit in the diffusion regime and prevents interactions between crossing fluxes in a chosen spatial direction. In disk simulations with 22 frequency groups, the M1 closure disagrees with the MC midplane temperature by up to 21%, while HM reduces this discrepancy to 6%. Even with just 3 frequency groups, HM significantly outperforms M1, with maximum departures of 8% compared to M1's 23%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13999v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Melon Fuksman, Mario Flock, Hubert Klahr, Giancarlo Mattia, Dhruv Muley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ice sublimation in the dynamic HD 100453 disk reveals a rich reservoir of inherited complex organics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14023v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Protoplanetary disks around luminous young A-type stars are prime observational laboratories to determine the abundances of complex organic molecules (COMs) present during planet formation. In contrast to their lower stellar mass counterparts, these warmer disks contain the sublimation fronts of complex molecules such as CH3OH on spatial scales accessible with the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA). We present ALMA observations of the Herbig Ae disk HD 100453 that uncover a rich reservoir of COMs sublimating from the dust cavity edge. In addition to CH3OH, we detect 13CH3OH for the first time in a Class II disk, revealing a factor of three enhancement of 13C in the disk large organics. A tentative detection of CH2DOH is also reported, resulting in a D/H of 1-2%, which is consistent with the expected deuterium enhancement from the low temperature CH3OH formation in molecular clouds and with the deuteration of CH3OH measured in comets. The detection of methyl-formate (CH3OCHO), at only a few percent level of CH3OH is an order of magnitude lower compared to claims towards other organic-rich Herbig Ae disks but is more in line with organic abundance patterns towards the earlier stages of star formation. Together these data provide multiple lines of evidence that disks, and therefore the planet and comet-forming materials, contain inherited interstellar ices and perhaps the strongest evidence to date that much of the interstellar organic ice composition survives the early stages of planet formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14023v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice S. Booth, Lisa W\"olfer, Milou Temmink, Jenny Calahan, Lucy Evans, Charles J. Law, Margot Leemker, Shota Notsu, Karin \"Oberg, Catherine Walsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refractory phosphorus in the HD 100546 protoplanetary disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14228v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The phosphorus budget of planets is intertwined with their formation history and is thought to influence their habitability. The chemical reservoirs and volatile \emph{vs} refractory budget of phosphorus in planet-forming environments have so far eluded empirical characterisation. We employ high-resolution spectra from HST/STIS in the ultraviolet and APEX in the sub-mm to constrain the phosphorus budget in the well-characterized HD\,100546 star and protoplanetary disk system. We measure $\log{(P/H)_{\star}}=-7.50^{+0.23}_{-0.28}$ on the stellar surface, which traces the total inventory of P in accreting gas \emph{and }dust from the inner disk. The inner disk gas, inside of the main dust trap, has $\log{(P/H)_{\rm in}}\lesssim-8.70$, and the outer disk gas $\log{(P/H)_{\rm out}}\lesssim-9.30$. Phosphorus in the disk is carried by a relatively refractory reservoir, consistent with minerals such as apatite or schreibersite, or with ammonium phosphate salts, in terms of sublimation temperature. We discuss the impact this might have on the two protoplanets around HD\,100546. Our results contribute to our understanding of the chemical habitability of planetary systems and lay a foundation for future explorations, especially in the context of JWST and \emph{Ariel} which can study phosphorus in exoplanet atmospheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14228v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihkel Kama, Oliver Shorttle, Sandipan P. D. Borthakur, Luke Keyte, Jennifer B. Bergner, Luca Fossati, Colin P. Folsom, Heleri Ramler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Dense Confined Circumstellar Medium around Supernova Progenitors via Long-term Hydrodynamical Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Circumstellar interaction of supernova (SN) ejecta is an essential process in its evolution and observations of SNe have found the signature of circumstellar interaction both in the early and late evolutionary phase of SNe. In this Letter, we show that if the SN forward shock plunges into tenuous stellar wind from dense circumstellar medium (CSM) in the vicinity of the progenitor (i.e., confined CSM), the subsequent time evolutions of the SN-CSM interaction system deviates from the prediction of self-similar solution. In this case, after all of the confined CSM is swept up by the SN forward shock (roughly $10$ days after the explosion), the propagation of the shocked shell will be driven by the freely expanding ram pressure of the confined CSM component, instead of the SN ejecta. Meanwhile, the forward shock decelerates faster than the prediction of thin-shell approximation once the confined CSM component reaches homologous expansion. This lasts until the reverse shock in the confined CSM component reaches the head of the SN ejecta, leading to the restoration of the system into the evolutionary model without confined CSM, where the SN ejecta drives the expansion of the system. We also show that this peculiar evolution will be reflected in observational signatures originating from SN-CSM interaction, taking rapid decline and rebrightening of radio emission as examples. Our results shed light on the importance of taking into account the effect of initial SN-CSM interaction even when we focus on observational properties of SNe a few years after the explosion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14255v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoki Matsuoka, Keiichi Maeda, Ke-Jung Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ophiuchus DIsk Survey Employing ALMA (ODISEA): A Unified Evolutionary Sequence of Planet-Driven Substructures Explaining the Diversity of Disk Morphologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14318v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the origin of substructures in protoplanetary disks and their connection to planet formation is currently one of the main challenges in astrophysics. While some disks appear smooth, most exhibit diverse substructures such as gaps, rings, or inner cavities, with varying brightness and depth. As part of the Ophiuchus Disk Survey Employing ALMA (ODISEA), we previously proposed an evolutionary sequence to unify this diversity, driven by the formation of giant planets through core accretion and subsequent planet-disk interactions. By combining the disk evolution and planet formation code PLANETALP with the radiative transfer code RADMC-3D, we have now reproduced the key aspects of the proposed evolutionary sequence. Starting with a smooth disk (like e.g., WLY 2-63), we modeled the evolution of a fiducial disk with a 1 Jupiter-mass planet at 57 au. Within a few hundreds of orbits, a narrow gap forms, resembling ISO-Oph 17. By $\sim$0.1 Myr, the gap widens, and dust accumulates at the cavity edge, producing a structure similar to Elias 2-24. At $\sim$0.4 Myr, the disk evolves further into a morphology akin to DoAr 44, characterized by a smaller inner disk and a brighter inner rim. By $\sim$1 Myr, the system transitions to a single narrow ring, resembling RXJ1633.9-2442. This line of work strongly supports the planetary origin of substructures and enables the possibility of identifying a population of planets that is currently beyond the reach of more direct detection techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14318v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adcd58</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Orcajo, Lucas A. Cieza, Octavio Guilera, Sebastian Perez, Fernando R. Rannou, Camilo Gonzalez-Ruilova, Grace Batalla-Falcon, Trisha Bhowmik, Prachi Chavan, Simon Casassus, Anuroop Dasgupta, Kevin Diaz, Jose L. Gomez, Antonio S. Hales, J. M. Miley, Marcelo M. Miller Bertolami, P. H. Nogueira, Maria Paula Ronco, Dary Ruiz-Rodriguez, Anibal Sierra, Julia Venturini, Philipp Weber, Jonathan P. Williams, Alice Zurlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dusty stellar sources classification by implementing machine learning methods based on spectroscopic observations in the Magellanic Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dusty stellar point sources are a significant stage in stellar evolution and contribute to the metal enrichment of galaxies. These objects can be classified using photometric and spectroscopic observations with color-magnitude diagrams (CMD) and infrared excesses in spectral energy distributions (SED). We employed supervised machine learning spectral classification to categorize dusty stellar sources, including young stellar objects (YSOs) and evolved stars (oxygen- and carbon-rich asymptotic giant branch stars, AGBs), red supergiants (RSGs), and post-AGB (PAGB) stars in the Large and Small Magellanic Clouds, based on spectroscopic labeled data from the Surveying the Agents of Galaxy Evolution (SAGE) project, which used 12 multiwavelength filters and 618 stellar objects. Despite missing values and uncertainties in the SAGE spectral datasets, we achieved accurate classifications. To address small and imbalanced spectral catalogs, we used the Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE) to generate synthetic data points. Among models applied before and after data augmentation, the Probabilistic Random Forest (PRF), a tuned Random Forest (RF), achieved the highest total accuracy, reaching $\mathbf{89\%}$ based on recall in categorizing dusty stellar sources. Using SMOTE does not improve the best model's accuracy for the CAGB, PAGB, and RSG classes; it remains $\mathbf{100\%}$, $\mathbf{100\%}$, and $\mathbf{88\%}$, respectively, but shows variations for OAGB and YSO classes. We also collected photometric labeled data similar to the training dataset, classifying them using the top four PRF models with over $\mathbf{87\%}$ accuracy. Multiwavelength data from several studies were classified using a consensus model integrating four top models to present common labels as final predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14332v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepideh Ghaziasgar, Mahdi Abdollahi, Atefeh Javadi, Jacco van Loon, Iain McDonald, Joana Oliveira, Amirhossein Masoudnezhad, Habib Khosroshahi, Bernard Foing, Fatemeh Fazel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic search for blue hyper-velocity stars from LAMOST survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hypervelocity stars (HVSs) represent a unique class of objects capable of escaping the gravitational pull of the Milky Way due to extreme acceleration events, such as close encounters with the supermassive black hole at the Galactic center (GC), supernova explosions in binary systems, or multi-body dynamical interactions. Finding and studying HVSs are crucial to exploring these ejection mechanisms, characterizing central black holes, probing the GC environment, and revealing the distribution of dark matter in our galaxy. The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) spectroscopic surveys have so far identified four B-type unbound HVSs. To expand this sample with the second-phase LAMOST survey that started in 2018, we conducted a systematic search for early-type HVSs using the LAMOST Data Release 10. We identified 125 early-type high-velocity candidates with total velocities exceeding 300 km\,s$^{-1}$. Among them, we report ten new unbound B- and A-type hypervelocity star (HVS) candidates (designated LAMOST-HVS5 through LAMOST-HVS14), tripling the number of unbound HVSs previously identified by LAMOST. Kinematic analyses suggest that these newly discovered HVS candidates likely originated either from the Galactic Center or via dynamical interactions. Future high-resolution follow-up observations promise to refine the stellar parameters, distances, and elemental abundances of these candidates, thereby providing deeper insights into their origins and broadening their potential applications across astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14836v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongkang Sun, Yang Huang, Jifeng Liu, Haozhu Fu, Huawei Zhang, Yinbi Li, Cuihua Du, Jianrong Shi, Xiao Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud-cloud collision and star formation in G013.313+0.193</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14943v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the G013.313+0.193 G013.313 region, a complex environment characterized by molecular cloud interactions indicative of cloud-cloud collision (CCC). Observations of the NH3(1,1) and (2,2) inversion transitions were obtained using the Nanshan 26 m radio telescope, while HCO+ (1-0), 12CO, 13CO, and C18O(1-0) transitions from the Purple Mountain Observatory Delingha 14 m telescope. Archival data are also included. We identified key observational signatures of CCC, including complementary spatial distributions, U-shaped structures, bridge features, and V-shaped velocity distributions. The position-velocity diagrams (P-V) reveal clear indications of gas interaction between two velocity components, suggesting an ongoing collision at an estimated angle of approximately 45 degree to the line of sight. The estimated collision timescale is 0.35-1.03 Myr, aligned with the inferred ages of young stellar objects (YSOs) in the region, supporting the hypothesis of collision-induced star formation. Hub-filament system (HFS) are identified in the compressed gas region, where filaments converge toward a dense hub, suggesting the CCC as a potential driver of HFS formation and massive star formation. The high column density suggests favorable conditions for the formation of massive stars. Although alternative kinematic drivers such as longitudinal collapse and shear motion are considered, CCC remains the most plausible explanation for the observed features. Our findings contribute to our understanding of the mechanisms of cloud dynamics and massive star formation in turbulent molecular environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14943v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dilda Berdikhan, Jarken Esimbek, Christian Henkel, Ye Xu, Jianjun Zhou, De-Jian Liu, Ernazar Abdikamalov, Yingxiu Ma, Toktarkhan Komesh, Yuxin He, Wenjun Zhang, Xindi Tang, Gang Wu, Dalei Li, Dongdong Zhou, Kadirya Tursun, Hailiang Shen, Ernar Imanaly, Qaynar Jandaolet, Arailym Manapbayeva, Duriya Tuiakbayeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Short History of (Orbital) Decay: Roman's Prospects for Detecting Dying Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Roman Space Telescope Galactic Bulge Time Domain Survey (GBTDS) is expected to detect ~10^5 transiting planets. Many of these planets will have short orbital periods and are thus susceptible to tidal decay. We use a catalog of simulated transiting planet detections to predict the yield of orbital decay detections in the Roman GBTDS. Assuming a constant stellar tidal dissipation factor, Q^{'}_{*}, of 10^6, we predict ~ 5 - 10 detections. We additionally consider an empirical period-dependent parameterization of Q^{'}_{*} \propto P^{-3} and find a substantially suppressed yield. We conclude that Roman will provide constraints on the rate of planet engulfment in the Galaxy and probe the physics of tidal dissipation in stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15277v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kylee Carden, B. Scott Gaudi, Robert F. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation of global and local flows in the solar convection zone during activity cycles 24 and 25</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02607v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Convection, differential rotation, and meridional circulation of solar plasma are studied based on helioseismic data covering the period from May 2010 to August 2024, significantly prolonged compared to that previously considered. Depth variation in the spatial spectrum of convective motions indicates a superposition of differently scaled flows. The giant-cell-scale component of the velocity field demonstrates a tendency to form meridionally elongated (possibly bananashaped) structures. The integrated spectral power of the flows is anticorrelated with the solar-activity level in the near-surface layers and positively correlates with it in deeper layers. An extended 22-year cycle of zonal flows ("torsional oscillations" of the Sun) and variations of the meridional flows are traced. A secondary meridional flow observed at the epoch of the maximum of Solar Cycle 24 to be directed equatorward in the subsurface layers is clearly manifest in Cycle 25.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02607v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Getling, A. G. Kosovichev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unravelling the role of merger histories in the population of In situ stars: linking IllustrisTNG cosmological simulation to H3 survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07169v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We undertake a comprehensive investigation into the distribution of in~situ stars within Milky Way-like galaxies, leveraging TNG50 simulations and comparing their predictions with data from the H3 survey. Our analysis reveals that 28% of galaxies demonstrate reasonable agreement with H3, while only 12% exhibit excellent alignment in their profiles, regardless of the specific spatial cut employed to define in~situ stars. To uncover the underlying factors contributing to deviations between TNG50 and H3 distributions, we scrutinise correlation coefficients among internal drivers(e.g., virial radius, star formation rate [SFR]) and merger-related parameters (such as the effective mass-ratio, mean distance, average redshift, total number of mergers, average spin-ratio and maximum spin alignment between merging galaxies). Notably, we identify significant correlations between deviations from observational data and key parameters such as the median slope of virial radius, mean SFR values, and the rate of SFR change across different redshift scans. Furthermore, positive correlations emerge between deviations from observational data and parameters related to galaxy mergers. We validate these correlations using the Random Forest Regression method. Our findings underscore the invaluable insights provided by the H3 survey in unravelling the cosmic history of galaxies akin to the Milky Way, thereby advancing our understanding of galactic evolution and shedding light on the formation and evolution of Milky Way-like galaxies in cosmological simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07169v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PAS-2024-0140.R2</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Razieh Emami, Lars Hernquist, Randall Smith, James F. Steiner, Grant Tremblay, Douglas Finkbeiner, Mark Vogelsberger, Josh Grindlay, Federico Marinacci, Kung-Yi Su, Cecilia Garraffo, Yuan-Sen Ting, Phillip A. Cargile, Rebecca L. Davies, Chlo\"e E. Benton, Yijia Li, Letizia Bugiani, Amir H. Khoram, Sownak Bose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Polarized Electrons from Magnetically Aligned Grains and Chiral Symmetry Breaking: Effects of Cosmic Rays in Protostellar Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02291v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Low-energy spin-polarized electrons (SPEs) are thought to cause symmetry breaking and could explain the origin of homochirality of prebiotic molecules such as amino acids and sugars. Here we study the effect of cosmic rays (CRs) on the emission of SPEs from aligned grains in dense protostellar environments and explore their effects on chiral asymmetry of prebiotic molecules. We first show that icy grains in protostellar environments can align with magnetic fields due to magnetically enhanced radiative torque mechanism. We then study the production of thermal electrons by CR ionization of H$_2$ and the CR-induced UV radiation using the attenuated CR spectra in dense cores obtained from a continuous slowing down model. Next, we show that thermal electrons with initial random spins captured by aligned grains will become spin-polarized due to the Barnett effect, converting unpolarized electrons into SPEs. We calculate the rate of photoemission of such SPEs by CRs-induced UV radiation and secondary electron emission from aligned grains and find that the photoemission by CRs-induced UV radiation is dominant. Finally, we calculate the total production rate of SPEs inside aligned dust grains by CRs. We estimate the alignment degree of SPEs from superparmagnetic (SPM) grains and find that it is only significant for SPM grains having large iron clusters and fast rotation. We suggest that low-energy secondary SPEs from aligned superparamagnetic grains with large iron inclusions induced by CRs might cause the chiral asymmetry of chiral prebiotic molecules formed in the ice mantle of aligned grains, in analogous to UV circularly polarized light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02291v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiem Hoang (KASI,UST)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disk reflection and energetics from the accreting millisecond pulsar SRGA J144459.2-604207</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08239v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accreting millisecond pulsars (AMSPs) are excellent laboratories to study reflection spectra and their features from an accretion disk truncated by a rapidly rotating magnetosphere near the neutron star surface. These systems also exhibit thermonuclear (type-I) bursts that can provide insights on the accretion physics and fuel composition. We explore spectral properties of the AMSP SRGA J144459 observed during the outburst that recently led to its discovery in February 2024. We aim to characterize the spectral shape of the persistent emission and to analyze type-I bursts properties employing XMM + NuSTAR overlapping observations taken during the most recent outburst. We perform spectral analysis of the time-averaged persistent (i.e., non-bursting) emission. For this, we first employ a semi-phenomenological continuum model made of a dominant thermal Comptonization plus two thermal contributions. A separate fit has also been performed employing a physical reflection model. We also perform time-resolved spectral analysis of a type-I burst employing a blackbody model. We observe a broadened iron emission line, thus suggesting relativistic effects, supported by the physical model accounting for relativistically blurred reflection. The resulting accretion disk extends down to 6 gravitational radii, inclined at ~$53^{\circ}$, and only moderately ionized (log$\xi\simeq2.3$). We observe an absorption edge at ~9.7 keV that can be interpreted as an Fe XXVI edge blueshifted by an ultrafast ($\simeq0.04$c) outflow. Our broadband observations of type-I bursts do not find evidence of photospheric radius expansion. The burst recurrence time shows a dependence on the count rate with the steepest slope ever observed in these systems. We also observe a discrepancy of ~3 between the observed and expected burst recurrence time, which we discuss in the framework of fuel composition and high NS mass scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08239v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Malacaria, Alessandro Papitto, Sergio Campana, Alessandro Di Marco, Tiziana Di Salvo, Maria Cristina Baglio, Giulia Illiano, Riccardo La Placa, Arianna Miraval Zanon, Maura Pilia, Juri Poutanen, Tuomo Salmi, Andrea Sanna, Manoj Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SolarZip: An Efficient and Adaptive Compression Framework for Solar EUV Imaging Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13504v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Context: With the advancement of solar physics research, next-generation solar space missions and ground-based telescopes face significant challenges in efficiently transmitting and/or storing large-scale observational data. Aims: We develop an efficient compression and evaluation framework for solar EUV data, specifically optimized for Solar Orbiter Extreme Ultraviolet Imager (EUI) data, significantly reducing data volume while preserving scientific usability. Methods: We systematically evaluated four error-bounded lossy compressors across two EUI datasets. However, the existing methods cannot perfectly handle the EUI datasets (with continuously changing distance and significant resolution differences). Motivated by this, we develop an adaptive hybrid compression strategy with optimized interpolation predictors. Moreover, we designed a two-stage evaluation framework integrating distortion analysis with downstream scientific workflows, ensuring that observational analysis is not affected at high compression ratios. Results: Our framework SolarZip achieved up to 800x reduction for Full Sun Imager (FSI) data and 500x for High Resolution Imager (HRI$_{\text{EUV}}$) data. It significantly outperformed both traditional and advanced algorithms, achieving 3-50x higher compression ratios than traditional algorithms, surpassing the second-best algorithm by up to 30%. Simulation experiments verified that SolarZip can reduce data transmission time by up to 270x while ensuring the preservation of scientific usability. Conclusions: The SolarZip framework significantly enhances solar observational data compression efficiency while preserving scientific usability by dynamically selecting optimal compression methods based on observational scenarios and user requirements. This provides a promising data management solution for deep space missions like Solar Orbiter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13504v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zedong Liu, Song Tan, Alexander Warmuth, Fr\'ed\'eric Schuller, Yun Hong, Wenjing Huang, Yida Gu, Bojing Zhu, Guangming Tan, Dingwen Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
