<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 04:02:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The binary fraction of Blue Horizontal-Branch (BHB) Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blue horizontal-branch (BHB) stars are old, low-mass, metal-poor stars that serve as important tracers of the Galactic halo structure, kinematics, and evolution.Understanding their binary properties provides key insights into their formation channels and the role of binary interactions in the evolution of horizontal branch stars. We intend to investigate the intrinsic binary fraction $f_{\rm b}^{\rm in}$ of BHB stars and its dependencies on metallicity, kinematics, and effective temperature. We collect \GG{299} BHB stars from LAMOST with multiple radial velocity (RV) measurements and classify the sample into halo-like and disk-like BHBs based on their kinematics and metallicity, as well as into bluer and redder BHBs based on their \G{effective temperature}. We then investigate the observed binary fraction for each group based on the radial velocity variations and apply a set of Monte Carlo simulations, assuming distributions of $f(P) \propto P^\pi$ and $f(q) \propto q^\kappa$, to correct the observed binary fraction for observational biases and derive the intrinsic binary fraction. After correcting for observational biases, the intrinsic binary fraction increases to 31% for n &gt; 2 and 32% for n &gt; 3. A clear contrast is observed between halo-like and disk-like BHB stars, with halo-like BHBs exhibiting a lower intrinsic binary fraction (28% for n &gt; 2 and 29% for n&gt; 3) compared to disk-like BHBs (46% and 51%, respectively), indicating different formation pathways. Additionally, we find that bluer BHB stars exhibit a significantly higher binary fraction (42% for n &gt; 2 and 45% for n&gt; 3) than redder BHB stars (24% and 23%, respectively), which suggests a possible link between binarity and the effective temperature, although more samples are required to confirm this.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02790v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanjun Guo, Kun Chen, Zhenwei Li, Jie Ju, Chao Liu, Xiangxiang Xue, Matti Dorsch, Zhanwen Han, XueFei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic ages for 4 million main-sequence dwarf stars from LAMOST DR10 estimated with data-driven approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stellar age determination for large samples of stars opens new avenues for a broad range of astronomical sciences. While precise stellar ages for evolved stars have been derived from large ground- and space-based stellar surveys, reliable age determination for cool main-sequence dwarf stars remains a challenge. In this work, we set out to estimate the age of dwarf stars from the LAMOST spectra with a data-driven approach. We build a training set by using wide binaries that the primary component has reliable isochrone age estimate thus gives the age of the secondary. This training set is further supplemented with field stars and cluster stars whose ages are known. We then train a data-driven model for inferring age from their spectra with the XGBoost algorithm. Given a spectral signal-to-noise ratio greater than 50, the age estimation precise to 10% to 25% for K-type stars, as younger stars have larger relative errors. Validations suggest that the underlying information used for our age estimation is largely attributed to the LAMOST spectral features of chemical abundances. It means our result is a manifestation of stellar chemical clock effectively acted on LAMOST spectra ($R\simeq1800$). Applying our model to the LAMOST DR10 yields a massive age catalog for $\sim4$ million dwarf stars. Statistical properties, such as the age distribution, age-abundance and age-stellar activity relations of the sample stars are discussed. The catalog is publicly accessible and can be helpful for extensive sciences from detection and characterization of Earth-like planets to Galactic archaeology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03019v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Hui Wang, Maosheng Xiang, Meng Zhang, Jiwei Xie, Jian Ge, Jinghua Zhang, Lanya Mou, Jifeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Li-enrichment in red clump giants: Clues for past binary interaction or merger events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To understand the underlying mechanisms for high lithium abundances among core He-burning or red clump (RC) giants, we analyzed a sample of 5227 RC giants of mass M $\leq$ 2~M$_{\odot}$ using spectra and asteroseismic data. We found 120 RC giants ($\sim$2~$\%$) with a lower limit of A(Li) = 0.7~dex, a factor of 40 more than their predecessors close to the RGB tip. Of the 120 RC giants, we could measure actual rotations for 16 RC giants using stellar spots from the Kepler light curve analysis. We found that most of the high rotation RC giants are also very high Li-rich RC giants, and the rotation seems to decline rapidly with Li abundance depletion, suggesting that both the high rotation and high Li abundance are transient phenomena and associated with a single source. Further, we found a significantly high occurrence of 15~$\%$ and 12~$\%$ of Li-rich RC giants among extremely low-mass RC giants and RC giants with anomalous [C/N] ratios, respectively. The extremely low mass, fast rotation and anomalous [C/N] values of RC giants are attributed to their past binary interaction/merger history. The results pose a question of whether the binary interaction/merger is a prerequisite along with the He-flash for Li-enhancement among RC giants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03089v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raghubar Singh, Bacham E. Reddy, Anohita Mallick, Gang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protostellar Outflows at the EarliesT Stages (POETS). VIII. The jets in the intermediate-mass star-forming region G105.42+9.88 (alias LkH{\alpha} 234)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03161v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our aim is to investigate the protostellar jets inside the young stellar object (YSO) cluster G105.42+9.88 (alias LkH$\alpha$ 234). This is one of the least luminous targets of the Protostellar Outflows at the EarliesT Stages (POETS) survey, which has been recently carried out to study young outflow emission on scales of 10-100 au. The combination of multi-epoch water maser very long baseline interferometry (VLBI) observations with sensitive Jansky Very Large Array (JVLA) continuum and Large Binocular Telescope (LBT) H$_2$ 2.12 $\mu$m observations, allows us to study the protostellar outflows from the intermediate-mass binary system VLA 3A and 3B, separated by ~0.22", and from VLA 2, an intermediate-mass YSO placed ~1" to northwest of VLA 3. Toward VLA 2, the 2001 and 2011 Very Long Baseline Array (VLBA) observations consistently show that the water masers are tracing a jet. The analysis of the 3D flow velocities proves that the jet is magneto-centrifugally launched in a magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) disk wind (DW). We infer launch radii in the range 10-50 au for the streamlines traced by the water masers. The global VLBI 2023 water maser observations indicate that the jet propagation can be hindered by a very dense clump placed northeast of VLA 2 and that is consistent with the large-scale LBT H$_2$ emission, tracing only the southwest lobe of the VLA 2 jet. Instead, the parallel jets emitted by the nearby YSOs VLA 3A and 3B can be reliably tracked with the H$_2$ emission at scales of a few 10" to both the southwest and the northeast. In particular, northeast of VLA 3 the direction of these two jets crosses a linear chain of spaced H$_2$ knots, which is a clear signature of an episodic jet. The variable ejection from VLA 3B, witnessed by the water masers at scales of ~10 au, could be the origin of the episodic jet observed at larger scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03161v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Moscadelli, Fabrizio Massi, Olga Bayandina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seismic test of the mass-radius relationship of hydrogen-atmospheric white dwarf stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pulsation of white dwarfs provides crucial information on stellar parameters for understanding the atmosphere and interior structure of these stars. In this study, we present a comprehensive statistical analysis of known ZZ Ceti stars from historical literature. Our dataset includes stellar parameters and oscillation properties from 339 samples, with 194 of them having undergone asteroseismological analysis. We investigated the empirical instability strip of ZZ Ceti stars and confirmed the linear relationship between temperature and weighted mean pulsation periods (WMP). We found that the WMP distribution is well-described with two groups of stars with peak values at $\sim254$ s and $\sim719$ s. Using seismic mass and trigonometrical radii derived from GAIA DR3 parallaxes, we tested the mass-radius relationship of white dwarfs through observational and seismic analysis of ZZ Cetis. They are generally larger than the theoretical values, with the discrepancy reaching up to $\sim15\%$ for massive stars with a mass estimated by seismology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03184v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianqi Cang, Jiayi Zhang, Jian-Ning Fu, He Zhao, Weikai Zong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray Polarimetry of Accreting White Dwarfs: A Case Study of EX Hydrae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first first X-ray polarization measurements of a white dwarf, the intermediate polar EX Hya. We measured significant polarization only in the 2 -- 3 keV energy band with a polarization degree of 8 percent at a $3\sigma$ significance. No significant polarization was detected above 3 keV, which we attribute to the higher energy bands having lower signal-to-noise. We found that the scattering surface detected by the IXPE is nearly perpendicular to the optical scattering plane, showing that the X-ray scattering surface is the WD and close to the base of the accretion column. Finally, we show how the polarization can be used to estimate the height of the accretion shock above the white dwarf's surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03412v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sean J. Gunderson, Swati Ravi, Herman L. Marshall, Dustin K. Swarm, Richard Ignace, Yael Naze, David P. Huenemoerder, Pragati Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating a Characteristic Time Lag in the Ionospheric F-region's Response to Solar Flares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray and EUV solar flare emission cause increases in the Earth's dayside ionospheric electron density. While the response of the lower ionosphere to X-rays is well studied, the delay between EUV flare emission and the response of the ionospheric F-region has not been investigated. Here, we calculate the delays between incident He II 304 Angstrom emission, and the TEC response for 10 powerful solar flares, all of which exhibit delays under 1 minute. We assess these delays in relation to multiple solar and geophysical factors, and find a strong negative correlation (-0.85) between delay and He II flux change and a moderate negative correlation (-0.55) with rate of increase in He II flux. Additionally, flare magnitude and the X-ray-to-He II flux ratio at peak He II emission show strong negative correlations (-0.80 and -0.75, respectively). We also identify longer delays for flares occurring closer to the summer solstice. These results may have applications in upper-ionospheric recombination rate calculations, atmospheric modelling, and other solar-terrestrial studies. We highlight the importance of incident EUV and X-ray flux parameters on the response time of the ionospheric electron content, and these findings may also have implications for mitigating disruptions in communication and navigation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03425v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/atmos16080937</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Atmosphere, 2025, 16, 937</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aisling N. O'Hare, Susanna Bekker, Harry J. Greatorex, Ryan O. Milligan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Cascade and Damping in Fast-Mode Compressible Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter presents hybrid and fully kinetic particle-in-cell simulations of fast-mode compressible turbulence. Turbulence damping at magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) scales closely follows linear transit-time damping theory. Despite strong phase steepening, turbulence sustains robust cross-scale energy cascading. These findings resolve the long-standing question about the validity of classical wave theories in strongly nonlinear regimes and overturn the common presumption that wave steepening disrupts compressible turbulence cascade, thereby providing a more complete picture of MHD turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03443v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanpeng Hou, Huirong Yan, Siqi Zhao, Parth Pavaskar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST observations of the Ring Nebula (NGC 6720) -- II. PAH emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) and carbonaceous dust have been observed in clumpy circumstellar environments, yet their formation and evolutionary pathways in such environments remain elusive. We aim to characterize the PAH emission in a clumpy planetary nebula to decipher their formation and evolution pathways. We obtained JWST Near-Infrared Spectrograph (NIRSpec) and Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI) integral field unit spectroscopic observations of two individual knots in the Ring Nebula (NGC 6720), a clumpy planetary nebula, and determine the PAH spectral characteristics. We detect the 3.3 and 11.2 um PAH emission bands in both knots but do not detect PAH emission in the 6-9 um range. We supplement our data with Spitzer Infrared Spectrograph (IRS) Short-Low 1 (SL1) and SL2 data, containing 11.2, weak 6.2, and weak 7.7 um PAH emission bands. The JWST data confirm the unusual profile of the 11.2 um band, which is very broad and redshifted with respect to typical 11.2 um PAH profiles. We estimate the PAH population to be largely neutral. The relative integrated surface brightness of the 3.3 and 11.2 um bands indicates the presence of small-sized PAHs, consisting of 35 +/- 6 carbon atoms. We find that the PAH emission is concentrated outside of the clumps, in the inter-clump medium, and confirm the existence of enhanced PAH emission in a narrow 'PAH ring' centred on the central star. This morphology suggests that PAHs formed during the Ring Nebula's asymptotic giant branch phase, in the central star's dust-driven wind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03451v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf826</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS 540, 1984-1997 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Clark, Els Peeters, Nick L. J. Cox, Jan Cami, Michael J. Barlow, Patrick J. Kavanagh, Griet Van de Steene, Mikako Matsuura, Albert Zijlstra, Isabel Aleman, Jeronimo Bernard-Salas, Harriet L. Dinerstein, Kay Justtanont, Kyle F. Kaplan, Arturo Manchado, Raghvendra Sahai, Peter van Hoof, Kevin Volk, Roger Wesson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micro-turbulence across the Hertzsprung-Russell diagram. Observational constrains for stars in the MW</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We assemble a homogeneous database of precise and consistent determinations of effective temperature, surface gravity, projected rotational rate, and macro- and micro-turbulent velocities for over 1800 Galactic stars spanning spectral types O to K and luminosity classes I to V. By carefully minimizing biases due to target selection, data quality, and disparate analysis techniques, we carry out statistical tests and comparative analyses to probe potential dependencies between these parameters and micro-turbulence. Our findings indicate that photospheric micro-turbulence is a genuine physical phenomenon rather than a modelling artifact. A direct comparison between observed micro-turbulent velocities and corresponding theoretical predictions for the turbulent pressure fraction strongly suggests that this phenomenon most likely arises from photospheric motions driven by envelope convection zones, with an additional pulsational component likely operating in main-sequence B stars. We show that neglecting micro-turbulent broadening in Fourier transform analyses can partly explain the dearth of slow rotators and the scarcity of stars with extremely low macro-turbulent velocity. We argue that including micro-turbulent pressure in atmospheric modelling can significantly mitigate (even resolve) the mass discrepancy for less massive O stars. Our database offers a valuable resource for testing and refining theoretical scenarios, particularly those addressing puzzling phenomena in hot massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03576v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Markova, M. Cantiello, L. Grassitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coronal Cells in Coronal Holes: Systematic Analysis and Implications for Coronal Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using advanced processing techniques, we analyze high-cadence, high-resolution extreme ultraviolet images and show that, throughout the solar cycle, mid-latitude coronal holes (CHs) are made up of ubiquitous and space-filling funnel-shaped structures (or cells) anchored to unipolar magnetic flux concentrations in network lanes. We demonstrate that the coronal cells, previously documented in the magnetically closed regions, as well as coronal plumes, inside CHs, are a particular manifestation of ubiquitous cells. The cell properties depend on the magnetic field intensity at their footpoint and connectivity in the corona, either closing in opposite polarity regions (CF-cells) or extending to form open-field (OF-cells). The OF-cells reach size scales on the order of super-granules and are characterized by dark lanes delimiting ray-like features both showing, at different levels, persistent jet-like ejections. The cells' lifetime mirrors that of magnetic flux concentrations revealed by magnetograms, slowly emerging and then disappearing in a matter of a few hours to a few days in a one-to-one correspondence. When a cell forms along the CH boundary, it can alter the CH boundary by shrinking or expanding the CH by an approximately supergranular cell unit. Therefore, coronal cells can contribute to the dynamics of CH boundary. We contextualize these observations in a "coronal cell" theory potentially able to provide an explanation for fine scale coronal structures and jetting activity in polar coronal holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03607v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathalia Alzate, Simone Di Matteo, Aleida Higginson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Characteristics of Interstellar Object 3I/ATLAS from SOAR Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02777v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Interstellar objects (ISOs) provide unique insights into the building blocks and conditions of extrasolar planetary systems. The newly discovered object, 3I/ATLAS (C/2025 N1), represents the third known ISO after 1I/'Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov. We present initial spectroscopic characterizations of 3I using observations from the Goodman High Throughput Spectrograph on the 4.1 m SOAR Telescope in Chile during the night of July 3rd. The reflectance spectrum of 3I, covering 3700-7000\,\AA\, reveals a red continuum, comparable to extreme trans-Neptunian objects, with a weak UV-optical turnover indicative of complex carbonaceous and irradiated organics. At the time of observation, when 3I was at a heliocentric distance of 4.4 AU, we detected no discernible gas emission from canonical cometary species (CN, C$_3$, C$_2$, CO$^+$, [O{\sc i}]). This is in agreement with expectations from our thermal-evolution model, which indicates sublimation-driven activity should commence once 3I/ATLAS approaches smaller heliocentric distances. Nonetheless, the paradoxical situation of early onset coma without evidence of sublimation tracers calls for other dust-liberating mechanisms that ancient ISOs may be subjected to at large heliocentric distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02777v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas H. Puzia, Rohan Rahatgaonkar, Juan Pablo Carvajal, Prasanta K. Nayak, Baltasar Luco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survey of (sub)mm water masers in low-mass star-forming regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02842v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Water masers are common in star-forming regions (SFRs), with the 22.235 GHz transition widely detected in both high- and low-mass protostars. In contrast, (sub)millimeter water maser transitions remain poorly studied, especially in low-mass SFRs. We search for millimeter water masers in a sample of low-mass SFRs previously known to exhibit 22 GHz emission. We target the transitions at 183.3, 321.2, and 325.2 GHz, respectively. We also examine their potential as probes of evolutionary stage by comparing them with previously reported Class I methanol masers (MM). We used the APEX 12m telescope. To assess the evolutionary stage of each source, we modeled their spectral energy distributions (SEDs) using archival data and used the derived dust temperatures as proxies of ages. We then compared the occurrence of water and methanol masers across the sample. We detected 183.3 GHz water masers in 5 out of 18 sources. IRAS 16293-2422 shows all three transitions, while Serpens FIRS 1 also displays the 321.2 GHz line. Despite excellent observing conditions, detection rates drop with increasing frequency, reflecting both intrinsic line weakness and variability. Notably, the brightest (sub)millimeter masers can reach flux densities comparable to the 22 GHz line. Comparisons of velocity profiles show that different transitions often trace distinct gas components. Water masers generally appear at earlier or comparable evolutionary stages than MM, suggesting no universal maser-based age sequence. Our results demonstrate the detectability of submillimeter water in low-mass SFRs, although their occurrence is sparse. Velocity overlap between some centimeter and millimeter components suggests partial spatial coincidence, but many features appear uniquely in one frequency regime, indicating that different transitions often trace distinct gas regions with varying physical conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02842v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. K. Humire, C. Goddi, G. N. Ortiz-Le\'on, A. Hern\'andez-G\'omez, J-C Loison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intergalactic Wandering Stars in the Local Universe: Theoretical Predictions for Their Distance and Luminosity Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Intergalactic wandering stars (IWSs) within 10 Mpc remain a poorly explored area of astronomy. Such stars, if they exist, are supposed to be wandering objects as they are not bounded by the gravitational potential of any galaxy. We set out to conduct dedicated studies for unraveling such a wandering stellar population. As the first paper of the series, in the present work we model the distance distribution and luminosity function of IWSs formed via the Hills mechanism of the Galactic central massive black hole (GCMBH). We implement a numerical simulation to generate IWSs taking the ejection history of the GCMBH and the stellar evolution process into consideration, and present their luminosity function in the distance range of 200kpc - 10Mpc. Our results suggest that a few hundred thousand IWSs have been generated by the GCMBH via the Hills mechanism in the past 14 billion years. These IWSs have an apparent magnitude peaking at 30 to 35 mag in SDSS $r-$band, which are hard to detect. However, a few thousand of them at the bright end are detectable by upcoming wide-field deep surveys, such as China Space Station Telescope (CSST) and Vera Rubin Observatory (LSST). The forthcoming discovery of such a wandering stellar population will open a door for precise understanding of the matter constitution of the nearby intergalactic space and the dynamical history of galaxies in the local universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03022v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Hui Wang, Maosheng Xiang, Ji-Feng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The compact object and innermost ejecta of SN 1987A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03395v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The first JWST observations of SN 1987A provided clear evidence that a compact object is ionizing the innermost ejecta. Here we analyze a second epoch of JWST NIRSpec and MIRI/MRS observations to better characterize the properties of this region, aided by a higher spectral resolving power for the new NIRSpec data. We confirm the presence of the previously identified narrow lines from the central region; [Ar VI] 4.5292 $\mu$m, [Ar II] 6.9853 $\mu$m, [S IV] 10.5105 $\mu$m, and [S III] 18.7130 $\mu$m, and also identify similar components in [Ca V] 4.1585 $\mu$m, [Cl II] 14.3678 $\mu$m, and possibly [Fe II] 1.6440 $\mu$m. These lines are blueshifted by $\sim$ -250 km/s, while the emission region is spatially unresolved and located southeast of the center. The offset and blueshift could imply a kick velocity of $510 \pm 55$ km/s for the neutron star. We also identify [Ca IV] 3.2068 $\mu$m near the center, but it is displaced to the north and has a redshift of $\sim 700$ km/s. We find that scattering by dust in the ejecta with a typical grain size $\sim 0.3\ \mu$m can explain the [Ca IV] properties and the absence of other narrow lines at shorter wavelengths, while dust absorption is important at $\lambda \gtrsim 8\ \mu$m. Photoionization models for a pulsar wind nebula and a cooling neutron star are both compatible with the observations, with the exception of the [Fe II] feature. The two models primarily differ at short wavelengths, where new lines are expected to emerge over time as the optical depth of dust in the expanding ejecta decreases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03395v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Larsson, C. Fransson, P. J. Kavanagh, B. Sargent, M. J. Barlow, M. Matsuura, C. Gall, R. D. Gehrz, N. Habel, A. S. Hirschauer, O. C. Jones, R. P. Kirshner, M. Meixner, S. Rosu, T. Temim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detectability of compact intermediate-mass black hole binaries as low-frequency gravitational wave sources: the influence of dynamical friction of dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03582v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The black hole (BH) spin could significantly change the density of dark matter (DM) in its vicinity, creating a mini-spike of the density of DM. The dynamical friction (DF) between DM and the companion star of a BH can provide an efficient loss of angular momentum, driving the BH-main sequence (MS) star binary to evolve toward a compact orbit system. We investigate the influence of the DF of DM on the detectability of intermediate-mass black hole (IMBH)-MS binaries as low-frequency gravitational wave (GW) sources. Taking into account the DF of DM, we employ the detailed binary evolution code MESA to model the evolution of a large number of IMBH-MS binaries. Our simulation shows that the DF of DM can drive those IMBH-MS binaries to evolve toward low-frequency GW sources for a low donor-star mass, a high spike index, or a short initial orbital period. When the spike index $\gamma=1.60$, those IMBH-MS binaries with donor-star masses of $1.0-3.4~ M_{\odot}$ and initial orbital periods of $0.65-16.82~ \rm days$ could potentially evolve into visible LISA sources within a distance of $10~\rm kpc$. The DF of DM can enlarge the initial parameter space and prolong the bifurcation periods. In the low-frequency GW source stage, the X-ray luminosities of those IMBH X-ray binaries are $\sim 10^{35}-10^{36}~\rm erg\,s^{-1}$, hence they are ideal multimessenger objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03582v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Qing Jia, Wen-Cong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative Nonideal MHD Simulations of Inner Protoplanetary Disks: Temperature Structures, Asymmetric Winds, and Episodic Surface Accretion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform two-dimensional global magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations including the full nonideal MHD effects (Ohmic diffusion, Hall effect, and ambipolar diffusion) and approximate radiation transport to understand the dynamics and thermal structure of the inner protoplanetary disks (PPDs). We have developed a simple radiative transfer model for PPDs that reasonably treats stellar non-thermal (XUV), stellar thermal (optical/infrared), and re-emitted radiations, reproducing the temperature structures from Monte Carlo radiative transfer. Our simulations show fast one-sided surface accretion ($\sim 10\%$ of Keplerian velocity) and asymmetric disk winds when the vertical magnetic field is aligned with the disk angular momentum. The asymmetry is due to the failure of the wind on the side with the accretion layer. On the accreting surface, clumps are repeatedly generated and accrete, driven by radiative feedback. For the anti-aligned fields, surface accretion becomes more moderate and time-variable, while the winds remain largely symmetric. For the thermal structure, accretion heating does not affect the disk temperature in any of our runs. This is because (1) the accretion energy dissipates via Joule heating at 2--3 gas scale heights, where low optical depth enables efficient radiative cooling, and (2) the winds remove $\gtrsim 10\%$ of the accretion energy. In contrast, the winds enhance radiative heating by elevating the irradiation front. These results highlight the importance of coupling between gas dynamics and radiation transport in PPDs, and provide observable magnetic activities such as fast episodic accretion, wind asymmetry, and molecular survival in XUV-irradiated winds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03624v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoji Mori, Xue-Ning Bai, Kengo Tomida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid Quick Data Release (Q1) -- Spectroscopic search, classification and analysis of ultracool dwarfs in the Deep Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22442v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Near-Infrared Spectrometer and Photometer onboard the Euclid space mission has obtained near-infrared (NIR) slitless spectra of millions of objects, including hundreds of ultracool dwarfs. Euclid observations retrieve images and spectra simultaneously. This observing mode marks a new era in the discovery of new objects, such as L- and T-type dwarfs, which can be found from direct identification through the H2O and CH4 absorption bands. NISP spectral resolution (R~450) is enough to classify the objects by the spectral type using known standard templates. Q1 provided more than 4 million NIR spectra in one visit to the Euclid Deep Fields. The large amount of spectra released in these fields allowed us to: a) confirm the ultracool dwarf nature of almost half of the photometric candidates compiled by Zhang et al. (2024); b) discover at least 11 new late L- and T-type dwarfs by a specific spectral index search in Q1 data; and c) spectroscopically confirm one hundred more candidates from a new photometric selection conducted by Zerjal et al. (in prep.). We present a preliminary list of Euclid ultracool dwarf templates built by the combination of the best spectra from all these searches. We include the first spectral analysis of confirmed ultracool dwarfs from Q1 data; spectral classifications; determination of effective temperatures; H2O, CH4 and NH3 spectral indices; and measurements of the KI absorption doublet. This paper is a first step in the study of Euclid ultracool dwarfs and will be improved with each subsequent data release.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22442v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adf72d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>C. Dominguez-Tagle, M. \v{Z}erjal, N. Sedighi, P. Mas-Buitrago, E. L. Mart\'in, J. -Y. Zhang, N. Vitas, V. J. S. B\'ejar, S. Tsilia, S. Mu\~noz Torres, N. Lodieu, D. Barrado, E. Solano, P. Cruz, R. Tata, N. Phan-Bao, A. Burgasser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double White Dwarf Tides with Multi-messenger Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07919v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Short-period Galactic double white dwarf (DWD) systems will be observable both in visible light through photometric monitoring and in mHz-range gravitational waves (GWs) with forthcoming space-based laser interferometry such as LISA. When only photometric variability is used to measure DWD intrinsic properties, there is a degeneracy between the chirp mass and binary tidal interaction, as orbital frequency time derivative is set by both GW radiation and tides. Without expensive radial velocity data from spectroscopic monitoring, this degeneracy may be lifted in principle by directly measuring the second time derivative of the orbital frequency through photometric monitoring over an ultra-long time baseline. Alternatively, the degeneracy can be removed by exploiting information in both photometric variability and the coherent GW waveform. Investigating both approaches, we find that direct measurement of the second time derivative is likely infeasible for most DWDs, while the multi-messenger method will disentangle measurements of the chirp mass and the binary moments of inertia, for a large sample of tidally locked systems. The latter information will enable empirical tests of WD structure models with finite temperature effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07919v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Leslie, Liang Dai, Kevin Burdge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Second Stellar Spectrum: Rotating hot massive star linear spectropolarimetry with the Ohman Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01962v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To understand better the polarized radiative transfer near the surface of rotating massive stars that remain nearly spherically symmetric, we use plane-parallel stellar atmosphere models to explore the unique opportunity presented by the Ohman effect. This effect refers to the predicted variation in linear polarization across a rotationally broadened absorption line, due to the interaction of that line with the spatially varying continuum polarization across the face of a strongly scattering photosphere, such as found in hot stars. Even if the rotation is weak enough for the star to remain spherically symmetric, the Ohman effect persists because differential absorption induced by the rotational Doppler shift of the line breaks the symmetry that would otherwise cancel the continuum polarization in the absence of that line. Neglecting rotational distortion effects, the net polarization across the line vanishes, yet resolved line profiles display a telltale triple-peak polarization pattern, with one strong polarization peak at line center and two smaller ones in the line wings at a position angle that is rotated 90 degrees from the line center. The far ultraviolet (FUV) is emphasized because both the polarization amplitude and the specific luminosity are greatest there for photospheres with effective temperatures between about 15,000 and 20,000K. There is a high density of spectral lines in the FUV, leading to a rich "second stellar spectrum" in linear polarization (analogous to the "second solar spectrum") that is made observable with stellar rotation. Polarizations at the level of 0.1% to 1% are achievable across individual lines for a wide variety of B-type stars. We highlight the prospects for accessing the unique information encoded in the Ohman effect with future moderate-resolution spaceborne spectropolarimetric missions in the FUV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01962v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Patrick Harrington, R. Ignace, K. G. Gayley, J. J. Drake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics motivated models of pulsar X-ray hotspots: off-center dipole configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15881v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, it was proposed that an off-center dipole magnetic configuration, together with a non-trivial temperature profile, may be the best model to explain the X-ray light curve of PSR J0030+0451 observed by the Neutron Star Interior Composition Explorer (\emph{NICER}). Using a theoretical model for the electric current density in a force-free pulsar magnetosphere, we compute from first principles the distribution of electric current over the polar cap associated with an off-center magnetic dipole. We then use a simple prescription to compute the resulting temperature distribution, which allows us to derive the observed X-ray light curve. We investigate the role of the volumetric return current region in the polar cap and find that although it does not make a big difference in an aligned dipole case, the difference can be bigger in the case of an off-center dipole. Finally, we apply Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) fitting to the X-ray light curves of pulsars PSR J0030+0451 and PSR J0437--4715 with and without the volumetric return current, and find that our model can reasonably recover the observed X-ray light curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15881v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Huang, Alexander Y. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-metallicity nova explosions: a site for weak rp-process nucleosynthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15162v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical novae are common cataclysmic events involving a binary system of a white dwarf and a main sequence or red giant companion star. In metal-poor environments, these explosions produce ejecta different from their solar counterparts due to the accretion of sub-solar metallicity material onto the white dwarf. In particular, it has been suggested that the nucleosynthesis flow in such low-metallicity nova explosions extends up to the Cu-Zn region, much beyond the expected endpoint, around Ca, predicted for solar-metallicity classical novae. This behavior resembles a weak rp-process, and such nuclear activity has never been observed in accreting white dwarf binaries with typical accretion flows. In this work, we study the characteristics of the weak rp-process for four nova models with metallicities $Z= 2\times 10^{-9}$, $10^{-7}$, $2\times 10^{-6}$, and $2\times 10^{-5}$, and explore the impact of the nuclear physics uncertainties via a Monte Carlo sensitivity study. We identify nuclear reactions whose uncertainties affect the production of intermediate-mass nuclei under these conditions. These reactions and relevant nuclear quantities are targets for measurements at stable or radioactive beam facilities to reduce their rate uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15162v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athanasios Psaltis, Jordi Jos\'e, Richard Longland, Christian Iliadis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Nuclear Matter with Quenched $g_A$ to Compact-Star Matter with a Signal for Emergent Hidden Scale Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04939v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An ``unorthodox" idea is developed that the long-standing mystery in nuclear physics of the effective axial-current coupling constant in nuclei, $g_A^{\rm eff}\approx 1$, could be interpreted in terms of an emerging hidden scale symmetry in dense compact-star matter. Arguments are presented using an effective field theory anchored on a renormalization-group approach to interacting baryons on the Fermi surface coupled with hidden symmetric heavy mesonic degrees of freedom that enables one to go beyond Weinberg's nuclear effective field theory involving nucleon and pion fields only, referred hereon to as $\chi$EFT$_\pi$. Both hidden local and scale symmetries, the former involving the vector mesons $\rho$ and $\omega$ and the latter the hidden scalar meson, a dilaton $\hat{\sigma}$ (i.e., $f_0(500)$), play the crucial role. Going beyond the density regime applicable to normal nuclear matter $n_0$, the notion of ``hadron-quark continuity HQC)" is brought in via the skyrmion structure of the nucleon argued to be valid in QCD at large $N_c$ limit and the large $N^\prime$ limit of the Grassmannian model $G/H= [O(N^\prime)/O(N^\prime-p) \times O(p)]$ where $N^\prime=4$ and $p=2$ for hidden local symmetry and the IR fixed point in QCD for $N_f \leq 3$ involving ``genuine/QCD-conformal dilaton" for hidden scale symmetry. The connection between the quenched $g_A$ and the sound speed $v^2_{s}/c^2\approx 1/3$ inside dense compact stars could be interpreted as a signal for emergent ``pseudo-conformal" symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04939v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mannque Rho</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
