<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 05:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Distributions and evolution of the equatorial rotation velocities of 2937 BAF-type main-sequence stars from asteroseismology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studies of the rotational velocities of intermediate-mass main-sequence stars are crucial for testing stellar evolution theory. They often rely on spectroscopic measurements of the projected rotation velocities. These not only suffer from the unknown projection factor but tend to ignore additional line-profile broadening mechanisms aside from rotation, such as pulsations and turbulent motions near the stellar surface. This limits the accuracy of Veq distributions. We use asteroseismic measurements to investigate the distribution of the equatorial rotation velocity, its ratio with respect to the critical rotation velocity, and the specific angular momentum for several thousands of BAF-type stars, covering a mass range from 1.3M$_\odot$ to 8.8M$_\odot$ and almost the entire core-hydrogen burning phase. We rely on high-precision model-independent internal rotation frequencies, as well as on masses and radii from asteroseismology to deduce Veq, Veq/Vcrit, and J/M for 2937 gravity-mode pulsators in the Milky Way. The sample stars have rotation frequencies between almost zero and 33$\mu$Hz, corresponding to rotation periods above 0.35d. We find that intermediate-mass stars experience a break in their J/M occurring in the mass interval $[2.3,2.7]\,$M$_\odot$. We establish unimodal Veq and Veq/Vcrit distributions for the mass range $[1.3,2.5[$M$_\odot$, while stars with $M\in[2.5,8.8]$M$_\odot$ reveal some structure in their distributions. We find that the near-core rotation slows down as stars evolve, pointing to very efficient angular momentum transport. The kernel density estimators of the asteroseismic internal rotation frequency, equatorial rotation velocity, and specific angular momentum of this large sample of intermediate-mass field stars can conveniently be used for population synthesis studies and to fine-tune the theory of stellar rotation across the main sequence evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02909v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conny Aerts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying how Surface Complexity Influences Properties of the Solar Corona and Solar Wind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03011v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Sun's magnetic field is a key driver in coronal heating and consequently solar wind acceleration. Remote measurement of the photosphere provides the magnetic surface boundary condition necessary for data-constrained 3D global coronal models. With one such model, we explore how the spatial resolution of the surface boundary condition influences the global properties of the magnetic field and coronal heating. Using spherical harmonic decomposition, we quantify how three different resolution simulations vary in the low and middle corona. Through examination of the magnetic field, the squashing factor, and the heating rate, we demonstrate that small-scale photospheric magnetic flux enhances heating across spatial regimes. We calculate 40% more heating in our best resolution simulation as compared to our base resolution. We describe a strong correlation between the structure of the magnetic field and structure of the heating rate in the low corona across resolutions. These results provide key information as to what more efficient, low-resolution models might inherently miss. This can provide context to incorporate the effects of unresolvable features in future modeling efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03011v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caroline L. Evans, Cooper Downs, Donald Schmit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive stars in the era of large spectroscopic surveys: The MEIGAS project</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the era of large spectroscopic surveys, a vast amount of spectra of massive stars will be gathered and supplemented by the wealth of astrometric and photometric data provided by the Gaia satellite. Released data will mean a major step forward in the study of massive stars, giving us the chance to create statistically significant samples to explore the role of almost any parameter. In this contribution, I introduce to the community the Multi-wavelength Exploration of massIve star-forminG regions and ASsociations project (MEIGAS) and long-term plans for conducting comprehensive studies in the major galactic and near extragalactic star-forming regions and OB associations. Benefiting from current and forthcoming data from large scale spectroscopic surveys such as WEAVE and 4MOST (among others), as well as complementary observations at different wavelength ranges, the project aims to achieve crucial and complementary information to adequately characterize these regions and their stellar content, something imperative to improve our understanding of star formation and poorly known evolutionary pathways of massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03018v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. R. Berlanas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Medium-resolution spectroscopic study of the intermediate-mass pre-main sequence binary $\theta^1$ Ori E</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03067v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $\theta^1$ Ori E is a very young and relatively massive pre-main sequence (PMS) spectroscopic and eclipsing binary with nearly identical components. We analyze \'Echelle spectra of the system obtained over fifteen years and report 91 radial velocities measured from cross-correlating the observations with a suitable synthetic spectrum. The spectra of individual binary components are indistinguishable from each other, with a composite spectral type around G4 III. The projected equatorial velocity is estimated to be $v \sin{i} = 32\pm 3~km~s^{-1}$, consistent with rotational synchronization. We find that the circular orbit has $P_{\rm orb} = 9.89522 \pm 0.00003~d$, $K_1 = 83.36 \pm 0.29~km~s^{-1}$, $K_2 = 84.57 \pm 0.28~km~s^{-1}$, and $asini = 32.84\pm0.08\ R_\odot$. The mass ratio is $q = 0.9856 \pm 0.0047$, indicating nearly identical but significantly different masses. The systemic velocity of the binary, $\gamma = 29.7 \pm 0.2~km~s^{-1}$, is similar to that of other Trapezium members. Using Spitzer light curves and our results, we derive $M_1 = 2.755\pm0.043\ M_{\odot}$, $M_2 = 2.720\pm0.043\ M_{\odot}$, $R_1=6.26\pm0.31R_{\odot}$ and $R_2=6.25\pm0.30R_{\odot}$. Together with our estimate of the effective temperature, $T_{\rm eff}=5150\pm200\ K$, a bolometric luminosity of $28.8\pm4.6\ L_{\odot}$ is derived for each component. Compared to evolutionary models of PMS stars, the binary age turns out to be less than or equal to $\sim 10^5$ years. Its components are probably the most massive stars known with masses determined with precision better than 2 percent, with both being PMS stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03067v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Costero, Juan Echevarr\'ia, Yilen G\'omez Maqueo Chew, Alex Ruelas-Mayorga, Leonardo J. S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ISOSCELES project: A grid-based quantitative spectroscopic analysis of massive stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive stars play a fundamental role in galactic evolution through their strong stellar winds, chemical enrichment, and feedback mechanisms. Accurate modelling of their atmospheres and winds is critical for understanding their physical properties and evolutionary pathways. Traditional spectroscopic analyses often rely on the $\beta$-law approximation for wind-velocity profiles, which may not capture the complexity of observed phenomena. This study aims to introduce and validate the grId of Stellar atmOSphere and hydrodynamiC modELs for massivE Stars (ISOSCELES), a grid-based framework for the quantitative spectroscopic analysis of massive stars. The project leverages hydrodynamic wind solutions derived from the m-CAK theory, including both fast and $\delta$-slow solutions, to improve the accuracy of derived stellar and wind parameters. We constructed a comprehensive grid of models based on hydrodynamic wind solutions from the Hydwind code and synthetic spectral line profiles generated by the Fastwind code. The grid spans a broad parameter space covering OBA-type stars with solar metallicity. A semi-automatic fitting procedure was developed to analyse key spectral lines and derive the stellar and wind parameters. Applying ISOSCELES to six stars demonstrates its ability to reproduce observed spectral profiles with high fidelity. The $\delta$-slow solution proved effective for two early-type B supergiants. The grid also highlights the difference of using the $\beta$-law in modelling stellar winds compared with the m-CAK wind solutions. The ISOSCELES database represents a step forward in quantitatively analysing massive stars, offering an alternative to the $\beta$-law approximation. Future work will address the inclusion of UV lines and metallicity effects to further refine its applicability across diverse stellar populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03184v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Araya, M. Cur\'e, N. Machuca, R. O. J. Venero, S. Cu\'ellar, C. Arcos, L. S. Cidale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the Shock Properties of the 2023 March 13 Event from In-Situ and Remote-Sensing Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shocks driven by coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are the most powerful accelerators of gradual solar energetic particles (SEPs) in the inner heliosphere. On 2023 March 13, a halo CME, as seen from the Solar Heliospheric Observatory (SoHO) and the Sun TErrestrial Relations Observatory (STEREO), gave rise to a strong SEP event. In this work, we aim to analyze this CME-driven shock from multiple spacecraft, using both remote sensing observations from STEREO-A/COR2 and in-situ data from Parker Solar Probe (PSP), Solar Orbiter (SolO), and Wind. In order to determine its direction of propagation and kinematic properties, we model the shock geometry using STEREO-A/COR2 and SoHO/LASCO/C3 observations as an expanding ellipsoid. The density compression ratio of the shock is determined by fitting the brightness profile from the coronagraphic images with that obtained from raytracing simulations of a double-Gaussian shock density profile. We compare physical quantities such as compression ratio and Alfv\'enic Mach number derived from remote sensing observations with in-situ measurements by PSP, SolO, STEREO-A, and Wind. From STEREO-A/COR2, we determine the compression ratio around the entire shock front in the corona, finding significant non-homogeneities that can impact the values found during in-situ crossings. Following the evolution of the parameters characterizing the CME from the source to space, we find that closer to the Sun, both the gas compression ratio and the Alfv\'enic Mach number remain almost constant, while they increase at larger radial distances. This indicates a non-trivial evolution of the shock parameters during its journey through the interplanetary space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03496v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federica Chiappetta, Giuseppe Nistic\`o, Massimo Chimenti, Andrea Larosa, Francesco Malara, Francesco Pucci, Luca Sorriso-Valvo, Gaetano Zimbardo, Silvia Perri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark-Matter-Powered Population III Evolution: Lifetimes, Rotation, and Quasi-Homogeneity in massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Population III stars supplied the first light and metals in the Universe, setting the pace of re-ionisation and early chemical enrichment. In dense haloes their evolution can be strongly influenced by the energy released when WIMPs annihilate inside the stellar core. We follow the evolution of a \(20\,M_\odot\) Population III model with the \textsc{genec} code, adding a full treatment of spin dependent WIMP capture and annihilation. Tracks are calculated for six halo densities from \(10^{8}\) to \(3\times10^{10}\,\mathrm{GeV\,cm^{-3}}\) and three initial rotation rates between zero and \(0.4\,v/v_{\mathrm{crit}}\). As soon as the capture product reaches \(\rho_\chi\sigma_{\mathrm{SD}}\simeq2\times10^{-28}\,\mathrm{GeV\,cm^{-1}}\), the dark-matter luminosity rivals hydrogen fusion, stretching the main-sequence lifetime from about ten million years to more than a gigayear. The extra time allows meridional circulation to smooth out differential rotation; a star that begins at \(0.4\,v/v_{\mathrm{crit}}\) finishes core hydrogen burning with near solid-body rotation and a helium core almost twice as massive as in the dark-matter-free case. Because the nuclear timescale is longer, chemically homogeneous evolution now sets in at only \(0.2\,v/v_{\mathrm{crit}}\), rather than the \(\gtrsim0.5\,v/v_{\mathrm{crit}}\) required without WIMPs. For a star with \(0.4\,v/v_{\mathrm{crit}}\), the surface hydrogen fraction drops to \(X\!\sim\!0.27\), helium rises to \(Y\!\sim\!0.73\), and primary \(^{14}\mathrm N\) increases by four orders of magnitude at He exhaustion. Moderate rotation combined with plausible dark-matter densities can therefore drive primordial massive stars towards long-lived, quasi-homogeneous evolution with distinctive chemical and spectral signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03540v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anais Pauchet, Devesh Nandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observed Joys law of Bipolar Magnetic Region tilts at the emergence supports the thin flux tube model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bipolar sunspots, or more generally, Bipolar Magnetic Regions, BMRs, are the dynamic magnetic regions that appear on the solar surface and are central to solar activity. One striking feature of these regions is that they are often tilted with respect to the equator, and this tilt increases with the latitude of appearance, popularly known as Joys law. Although this law has been examined for over a century through various observations, its physical origin is still not established. An attractive theory that has been put forward behind Joys law is the Coriolis force acting on the rising flux tube in the convection zone, which has been studied using the thin flux tube model. However, observational support for this theory is limited. If the Coriolis force is the cause of the tilt, then we expect BMRs to hold Joys law at their initial emergence on the surface. By automatically identifying the BMRs over the last two solar cycles from high resolution magnetic observations, we robustly capture their initial emergence signatures on the surface. We find that from their appearance, BMRs exhibit tilts consistent with Joys law. This early tilt signature of BMRs suggests that the tilt is developed underneath the photosphere, driven by the Coriolis force and helical convection, as predicted by the thin flux tube model. Considerable scatter around Joys law observed during the emergence phase, which reduces in the post emergence phase, reflects the interaction of the vigorous turbulent convection with the rising flux tubes in the near surface layer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03558v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anu Sreedevi, Bidya Binay Karak, Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Rambahadur Gupta, Dipankar Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bow-Shock Nebula Around the Z Camelopardalis-type Cataclysmic Variable FY Vulpeculae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03587v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present deep images of the faint nebulosity StDr 90, which we have discovered surrounds the cataclysmic variable (CV) star FY Vulpeculae. Archival photometric and spectroscopic observations, and a new optical spectrum, confirm that FY Vul belongs to the Z Camelopardalis subclass of CVs. Our imagery, obtained by accumulating long exposures with amateur telescopes equipped with CMOS cameras, shows a prominent bow shock in the light of [O III] 5007 A, collisionally excited in front of the star as it passes through a relatively dense region in the surrounding interstellar medium (ISM). FY Vul also lies near the edge of an extended faint Halpha-emitting nebula, which we interpret as a "recombination wake," i.e., a Stromgren zone recombining after being photoionized by the star's ultraviolet radiation. FY Vul joins five other CVs known to be associated with optical bow shocks and off-center nebulae. All of them are characterized by luminous accretion disks, which drive fast winds into the ISM that produce the bow shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03587v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Howard E. Bond (Penn State, STScI), Calvin Carter (Rocket Girls Ranch Observatory), Eric Coles (Glen Ellyn, IL, Sierra Remote Observatories), Peter Goodhew (Deep Space Imaging Network), Jonathan Talbot (Stark Bayou Observatory), Gregory R. Zeimann (Hobby-Eberly Telescope)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling the Solar Cycle Nonlinearities into the Algebraic Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding and predicting solar-cycle variability requires accounting for nonlinear feedbacks that regulate the buildup of the Sun's polar magnetic field. We present a simplified but physically grounded algebraic approach that models the dipole contribution of active regions (ARs) while incorporating two key nonlinearities: tilt quenching (TQ) and latitude quenching (LQ). Using ensembles of synthetic cycles across the dynamo effectivity range $\lambda_R$, we quantify how these mechanisms suppress the axial dipole and impose self-limiting feedback.
  Our results show that (i) both TQ and LQ reduce the polar field, and together they generate a clear saturation (ceiling) of dipole growth with increasing cycle amplitude; (ii) the balance between LQ and TQ, expressed as $R(\lambda_R) = \mathrm{dev(LQ)}/\mathrm{dev(TQ)}$, transitions near $\lambda_R \approx 12^\circ$, with LQ dominating at low $\lambda_R$ and TQ at high $\lambda_R$; (iii) over $8^\circ \leq \lambda_R \leq 20^\circ$, the ratio follows a shallow offset power law with exponent $n \approx 0.36 \pm 0.04$, significantly flatter than the $n=2$ scaling assumed in many surface flux--transport (SFT) models; and (iv) symmetric, tilt-asymmetric, and morphology-asymmetric AR prescriptions yield nearly identical $R(\lambda_R)$ curves, indicating weak sensitivity to AR geometry for fixed transport.
  These findings demonstrate that nonlinear saturation of the solar cycle can be captured efficiently with algebraic formulations, providing a transparent complement to full SFT simulations. The method highlights that the LQ\--TQ balance is primarily controlled by transport ($\lambda_R$), not by active-region configuration, and statistically disfavors the SFT-based $1/\lambda_R^{2}$ dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03611v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11207-025-02574-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed H. Talafha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moderate Nesting and Cross-Equatorial Asymmetry of Active Regions in Solar Cycle 24</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar Cycle 24 data are used to determine how often the Sun emerges sunspots in `activity nests', i.e., regions where sunspots and active regions (ARs) repeatedly emerge. We use the Solar Photospheric Ephemeral Active Region (SPEAR) catalog created from Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) data as well as the HMI Carrington Rotation maps of radial magnetic field, $B_r$. The Sun shows moderate nesting behavior with 41\% (48\%) of AR magnetic flux found in Northern (Southern) hemispheric nests that are short-lived ($\sim$4 months). Different rotation rates are used to search for nests that may not be evident `by eye'. The maximum number of nests are found with slightly prograde rotational velocities, with significant nest flux also found at synodic 451--452 nHz prograde and 409--411 nHz retrograde frequencies. Nest patterns show strong hemispheric asymmetry, indicating that the physical origin of nests identified herein must also be asymmetric or antisymmetric across the equator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03646v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aimee Norton, Alex Mendez, Ruizhu Chen, Mausumi Dikpati, Aswin Raj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Echoes of the First Stars: Massive Star Evolution in Extremely Metal-Poor Environments with the Habitable Worlds Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A remarkable span of frontier astrophysics, from gravitational-wave archaeology to the origin of the elements to interpreting snapshots of the earliest galaxies, depends sensitively on our understanding of massive star formation and evolution in near-pristine, relatively enriched gas. From the surprisingly massive black holes detected by LIGO/Virgo to highly ionized nebulae with peculiar enrichment patterns observed in galaxies at Cosmic Dawn, evidence is mounting that our understanding of massive-star populations at very low metallicity remains critically incomplete. The fundamental limitation is the hand nature has dealt us: only a few star-forming galaxies within $\lesssim$1 Mpc can currently be resolved into individual stars, and none reach the extreme metallicities and star-formation intensities that characterized the early Universe. With an ultraviolet integral-field spectrograph aboard the Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO), this barrier will finally be broken. HWO will bring rare, actively star-forming, extremely metal-poor dwarf galaxies at $\sim$10-20 Mpc such as I Zw 18 within reach of resolved UV-optical spectroscopy, providing our first direct, statistical view of individual massive stars and the feedback they drive at $&gt;$30 $M_\odot$ and $&lt;$10% $Z_\odot$. This science is deeply synergistic with many next-generation facilities, yet requires the unique combination of spatial resolution and UV/optical sensitivity that only HWO can provide. The massive star science enabled by HWO within the Local Volume represents a transformational advance in our ability to probe the earliest stellar populations - those that seeded the Milky Way and other galaxies with the first heavy elements, and paved the way for life in the transparent, reionized Universe we inhabit today.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03715v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Senchyna, Calum Hawcroft, Miriam Garcia, Aida Wofford, Janice C. Lee, Chris Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Exospace Weather Frontier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Space weather is among the most powerful and least understood forces shaping planetary atmospheres. In our Solar System, we observe its effects directly: atmospheric escape, chemical disruption, and spectacular auroral displays. Yet for exoplanets, we lack the tools and data to comprehensively assess the impacts of space weather, especially invisible elements like stellar winds, coronal mass ejections, energetic particles, and variable interplanetary magnetic fields. This problem lies at the intersection of four key fields: heliophysics, planetary science, astrobiology, and astrophysics. In 2023--2025, experts from these four fields convened at the W. M. Keck Institute for Space Studies to explore pathways for advancing the study of exospace weather. Organizing the subject into five core themes -- planets and their stellar particle environments, stellar magnetism and space weather modeling, quasi-steady stellar winds, transient events, and programmatic pathways -- our team synthesized concepts from across relevant fields and identified a wide array of opportunities for progress. This report is the product of that effort. It assembles cross-disciplinary knowledge; highlights outstanding theoretical challenges; explores promising innovations in observation, modeling, methodology, and instrumentation; and makes recommendations for accelerating community-wide progress. Together, these lay out a path to transforming the challenging, yet tractable problem of exospace weather into a foundational element of our understanding exoplanetary systems, and our own Solar System, in their entirety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02871v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.26206/gmhk5-amp17</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 W. M. Keck Institute of Space Studies (KISS), California Institute of Technology</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. O. Parke Loyd, Evgenya L. Shkolnik, Joseph Lazio, Gregg W. Hallinan, Juli\'an Alvarado-G\'omez, Laura Amaral, Ivey Davis, Alison Farrish, James Green, Dave Brain, Bin Chen, Christina Cohen, Shannon Curry, Karin Dissauer, Arika Egan, Nat Gopalswamy, Guillaume Gronoff, Shadia Habbal, Renyu Hu, Meng Jin, James Paul Mason, Ruth Murray-Clay, Kosuke Namekata, Rachel Osten, Ant\'igona Segura, Astrid Veronig, Aline Vidotto, Maurice Wilson, Yu Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining the impact of post-main-sequence stellar evolution on the transiting giant planet population</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02896v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The post-main sequence evolution of stars is expected to impact the exoplanets residing on close-in orbits around them. Using photometric data from the TESS Full-Frame-Images we have performed a transit search for exoplanets with post-main sequence hosts to search for the imprints of these impacts on the giant planet population. We detect 130 short period planets and candidates, thirty-three of which are newly discovered candidates, from a sample of \Ntotal\ post-main sequence stars spanning the evolutionary stages from the end of the main sequence to the bottom of the red giant branch. We measure an occurrence rate of $0.28 \pm 0.04$% for short period giant planets orbiting post-main sequence stars. We also measure occurrence rates for two stellar sub-populations, measuring values of $0.35 \pm 0.05$% for a sub-population representing the earliest stages of post-main sequence evolution and $0.11^{+0.06}_{-0.05}$% for a sub-population of more evolved stars. We show that the giant planet occurrence rate decreases with increasing stellar evolution stage, with a larger occurrence rate decrease observed for shorter period planets. Our results are clear evidence that the population of short period giant planets is being sculpted by the post-main sequence evolution of the host stars, and we conclude that this is most likely through the destruction of these giant planets through the increased strength of planet-star tidal interactions resulting in the rapid tidal decay of the planets' orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02896v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1771</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Edward M. Bryant, Vincent Van Eylen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of an Alfv\'en Wave-Driven Proton Beam in the Expanding Solar Wind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the self-consistent formation and long-term evolution of proton beams in the expanding solar wind using an ensemble of one-dimensional hybrid expanding box simulations. Initial conditions are chosen to represent a range of plasma states observed by the Helios spacecraft at 0.3 AU, including an amplitude-modulated Alfv\'en wave that nonlinearly drives a proton beam aligned with the magnetic field. We compare simulation results with solar wind data out to 1.5 AU and show that our model reproduces key observed features of proton beams on average, such as the radial evolution of the drift and the relative core-to-beam density ratio. These findings support the theory that the observed evolution of the proton beam drift in the solar wind is determined by kinetic instabilities. More broadly, our results indicate that the interplay between nonlinear Alfv\'en wave dynamics, expansion effects and kinetic instabilities plays a fundamental role in solar wind dynamics, with implications for interpreting solar wind heating rate estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02940v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. S. Bianco, A. Tenerani, C. Gonzalez, L. Matteini, K. G. Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SPHEREx Satellite Mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02985v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: SPHEREx, a NASA explorer satellite launched on 11 March 2025, is carrying out the first all-sky near-infrared spectral survey. The satellite observes in 102 spectral bands from 0.75 to 5.0 um with a resolving power ranging from 35 to 130 in 6.2 arcsecond pixels. The observatory obtains a 5-sigma depth of 19.5 - 19.9 AB mag for 0.75 to 3.8 um and 17.8 - 18.8 AB mag for 3.8 to 5.0 um after mapping the full sky four times over two years. Scientifically, SPHEREx will produce a large galaxy redshift survey over the full sky, intended to constrain the amplitude of inflationary non-Gaussianity. The observations will produce two deep spectral maps near the ecliptic poles that will use intensity mapping to probe the evolution of galaxies over cosmic history. By mapping the depth of infrared absorption features over the Galactic plane, SPHEREx will comprehensively survey the abundance and composition of water and other biogenic ice species in the interstellar medium. The initial data are rapidly released in the form of spectral images to the public. The project will release specialized data products over the life of the mission as the surveys proceed. The science team will also produce specialized spectral catalogs on planet-bearing and low-mass stars, solar system objects, and galaxy clusters 3 years after launch. We describe the design of the instrument and spacecraft, which flow from the core science requirements. Finally, we present an initial evaluation of the in-flight performance and key characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02985v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James J. Bock, Asad M. Aboobaker, Joseph Adamo, Rachel Akeson, John M. Alred, Farah Alibay, Matthew L. N. Ashby, Yoonsoo P. Bach, Lindsey E. Bleem, Douglas Bolton, David F. Braun, Sean Bruton, Sean A. Bryan, Tzu-Ching Chang, Shuang-Shuang Chen, Yun-Ting Cheng, James R. Cheshire IV, Yi-Kuan Chiang, Jean Choppin de Janvry, Samuel Condon, Walter R. Cook, Brendan P. Crill, Ari J. Cukierman, Olivier Dore, C. Darren Dowell, Gregory P. Dubois-Felsmann, Spencer Everett, Beth E. Fabinsky, Andreas L. Faisst, James L. Fanson, Allen H. Farrington, Tamim Fatahi, Candice M. Fazar, Richard M. Feder, Eric H. Frater, Henry S. Grasshorn Gebhardt, Utkarsh Giri, Tatiana Goldina, Varoujan Gorjian, William G. Hart, Joseph L. Hora, Zhaoyu Huai, Howard Hui, Young-Soo Jo, Woong-Seob Jeong, Jae Hwan Kang, Miju Kang, Branislav Kecman, Chul-Hwan Kim, Jaeyeong Kim, Minjin Kim, Young-Jun Kim, Yongjung Kim, J. Davy Kirkpatrick, Phil M. Korngut, Elisabeth Krause, Bomee Lee, Ho-Gyu Lee, Jae-Joon Lee, Jeong-Eun Lee, Carey M. Lisse, Giacomo Mariani, Daniel C. Masters, Philip D. Mauskopf, Gary J. Melnick, Mary H. Minasyan, Jordan Mirocha, Hiromasa Miyasaka, Anne Moore, Bradley D. Moore, Giulia Murgia, Bret J. Naylor, Christina Nelson, Chi H. Nguyen, Jinyoung K. Noh, Stephen Padin, Roberta Paladini, Konstantin I. Penanen, Dustin S. Putnam, Jeonghyun Pyo, Nesar Ramachandra, Keshav Ramanathan, Daniel J. Reiley, Eric B. Rice, Jennifer M. Rocca, Ji Yeon Seok, Jeremy Stober, Sara Susca, Harry I. Teplitz, Michael P. Thelen, Volker Tolls, Gabriela Torrini, Amy R. Trangsrud, Stephen Unwin, Phani Velicheti, Pao-Yu Wang, Robin Y. Wen, Michael-W. -Werner, Ross Williamson, James Wincentsen, Soung-Chul Yang, Yujin Yang, Michael Zemcov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Impact of Starspot-Crossing Events on Retrieved Parameters from Transit Lightcurves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03045v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starspot-crossing events (SCEs) in exoplanet transit lightcurves are becoming increasingly common as we focus on cooler host stars and observe higher precision photometric and spectroscopic lightcurves. In this work we explore how these events affect our retrievals of transit depths, and the accuracy with which we can derive spot properties. We inject and recover synthetic SCEs in photometric lightcurves using starry. We find that for high signal-to-noise SCEs we constrain the spot longitudes tightly (&gt;80% within 1 degree of the true value), but degeneracies complicate retrieving spot contrasts, radii and latitudes (within 17%, 19%, and 9 degrees respectively). On average the difference between injected and recovered transit depths is 0.78% or 78.3ppm. In most (80%) injections we recover the transit depth to within 0.6%. For transit depths inflated &gt;1.3% by the Transit Light Source Effect (TLSE), fitting for a spot-crossing improves the transit depth retrieval over masking the SCE in &gt;95% of cases. However, we find that for spots with small contrasts (&lt;5%) and/or covering fractions (&lt;2%), we are likely to over-correct for the TLSE, recovering a worse transit depth than simply masking. In addition, even when fitted, we find SCEs can inflate the uncertainties on recovered transit depths significantly, especially for JWST-like precisions. Finally, we determine how SCE observables can narrow the degenerate spot parameter space to provide useful priors for MCMC sampling, demonstrating this technique on a real SCE observed in Kepler-51d's lightcurve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03045v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. A. Murray, Z. Berta-Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of Free-Floating Planets via Ejection: Population Synthesis with a Realistic IMF and Comparison to Microlensing Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Microlensing observations suggest that the mass distribution of free-floating planets (FFPs) follows a declining power-law with increasing mass. The origin of such distribution is unclear. Using a population synthesis framework, we investigate the formation channel and properties of FFPs, and compare the predicted mass function with observations. Assuming FFPs originate from planet-planet scattering and ejection in single star systems, we model their mass function using a Monte Carlo based planet population synthesis model combined with N-body simulations. We adopt a realistic stellar initial mass function, which naturally results in a large fraction of planetary systems orbiting low-mass stars. The predicted FFP mass function is broadly consistent with observation: it follows the observed power-law at higher masses ($10 \lesssim m/M_\oplus &lt; 10^4$), while at lower masses ($0.1 &lt; m/M_\oplus \lesssim 10$) it flattens, remaining marginally consistent with the lower bound of the observational uncertainties. Low-mass, close-in planets tend to remain bound, while Neptune-like planets at wide orbits dominate the ejected population due to their large Hill radii and shallow gravitational binding. We also compare the mass distribution of bound planets with microlensing observations and find reasonably good agreement with both surveys. Our model predicts $\simeq 1.20$ ejected planets per star in the mass range of $0.33 &lt; m/M_\oplus &lt; 6660$, with a total FFP mass of $\simeq 17.98~M_\oplus$ per star. Upcoming surveys will be crucial in testing these predictions and constraining the true nature of FFP populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03246v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangrou Guo, Shigeru Ida, Masahiro Ogihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life in the dark: Potential urability of moons of rogue planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Free-floating planets are thought to be numerous in the Galaxy and may retain their moons after ejection from their natal systems. If those satellites acquire or preserve orbital eccentricity, tidal dissipation could provide a long-lasting internal heat source, potentially creating urable environments (capable of enabling abiogenesis) in the absence of stellar radiation. We explore (i) whether moons remain bound to planets expelled by a core-collapse supernova, (ii) how the explosion reshapes their orbits, and (iii) under which circumstances tidal heating can sustain urable subsurface oceans. We carried out three-dimensional N-body simulations with an 8th-order Runge-Kutta scheme, modelling homologous stellar mass loss for progenitors of 10 M$_{\odot}$. Post-explosion orbital elements of single moons and resonant moon systems were analysed, and tidal heating power was estimated with a constant phase-lag model for several tidal dissipation functions and moon densities. All simulated moons survive the supernova and remain bound to their planets. The explosion excites moon eccentricities up to $\sim7\times10^{-4}$ and $\sim3\times10^{-3}$ for single moons of planets with circular and eccentric orbits, respectively. For resonant pairs, an eccentricity of $\leq2\times10^{-2}$ is preserved. The semi-major axis of the moons changes by $\leq0.2\%$. For 12-15\% of cases -- preferentially moons at $a\leq15\,R_{\mathrm{planet}}$ and with $e\geq10^{-3}$ -- the specific tidal heating power lies between 0.1 and 10 times what is estimated on Europa or Enceladus, sufficient to maintain liquid oceans beneath an ice crust. Eccentricity damping timescales exceed the age of the Solar System for $a\geq10\,R_{\mathrm{planet}}$, implying billions of years of continuous heating on the moons. Such worlds represent promising targets for future searches for extraterrestrial life.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03392v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vikt\'oria Fr\"ohlich, Zsolt Reg\'aly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Detection of CH3OD in Prestellar Cores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The isotopic ratios of deuterated methanol derived around protostars are commonly used to infer the physical conditions under which they formed in the earlier prestellar stage. However, there is a discrepancy in the ratio of the singly deuterated methanol isotopologues, CH2DOH/CH3OD, between low- and high-mass protostars, which puts into question whether prestellar isotopic ratios are generally preserved during the star- and planet-forming process. Resolving this puzzle is only made harder by the complete lack of data on this ratio in the prestellar stage. This work presents observations with the IRAM 30m telescope that securely detect CH3OD in the prestellar core L1448 in Perseus and tentatively in B213-C6 in Taurus. This work constrains the ratio of CH2DOH/CH3OD and the D/H ratios for both singly deuterated methanol isotopologues for the first time at the prestellar stage. Column densities calculated under the assumption of local thermal equilibrium lead to a CH2DOH/CH3OD ratio of 2.8-8.5 in L1448 and $\leq$ 5.7 in B213-C6. The values are marginally consistent with the statistically expected ratio of 3, but most assumptions put the values in an elevated range in line with values found around low-mass protostars. The D/H ratio in CH2DOH is between 3.6% and 6.8% in L1448 and in the range of 2.4-5.8% in B213-C6. The D/H ratio derived for CH3OD is lower, namely 1.4-4.4% in L1448 and $\leq$ 3.8% in B213-C6.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03581v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice M. Kulterer, Asunci\'on Fuente, Maria N. Drozdovskaya, Silvia Spezzano, Gisela Esplugues, David Navarro-Almaida, Marina Rodr\'iguez Baras, Ang\`ele Taillard, Karin \"Oberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidally Torn: Why the Most Common Stars May Lack Large, Habitable-Zone Moons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03625v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Earth-like planets in the habitable zone (HZ) of M-dwarfs have recently been targeted in the search for exomoons. We study the stability and lifetime of large (Luna-like) moons, accounting for the effects of 3-body interactions and tidal forces using the N-body simulator rebound and its extension library reboundx. We find that those moons have a notably different likelihood of existence (and, by implication, observability). Large moons orbiting Earth-like planets in the HZs of M4 and M2 dwarfs become unstable well before $10^7$ and $10^8 \textrm{ yr}$, respectively, and in most cases, those orbiting M0-dwarfs become unstable in much less than $10^9 \textrm{ yr}$. We conclude that HZ planets orbiting M-dwarfs are unlikely to harbor large moons, thus affecting the total number of possible moons in our galaxy and the Universe at large. Since moons may help enhance the habitability of their host planet, besides being possibly habitable themselves, these results may have notable implications for exolife, and should also be considered when seeking solutions to the Drake equation and the Fermi paradox.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03625v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaan D. Patel, Billy Quarles, Nevin N. Weinberg, Manfred Cuntz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar and Stellar Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20202v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This chapter provides an overview of the magnetic activity of the Sun and stars, discussing its underlying physical origin, manifestations, and fundamental role in exoplanet studies. It begins with a summary of the Sun's magnetic activity from the surface towards the outer atmospheric layers, highlighting features such as sunspots, faculae, chromospheric structures, and their temporal modulation known as the activity cycle. These phenomena are sustained throughout the lifetime of the Sun by the magnetic dynamo, which is driven by differential rotation and convective flows. Furthermore, extending these concepts to other stars, the chapter examines the diagnostics that are typically employed to track and quantify the magnetic activity level of stars, and it reviews spectropolarimetry, an observational technique with which to characterise stellar magnetic fields. We finally outline results from both observations and theoretical modelling of stellar activity across distinct spectral types, and we describe the variety of methods used to search for stellar activity cycles, underscoring the multi-wavelength nature of this field of research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20202v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bellotti, J. Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recalibration of the Landolt UBVRI Standard Stars and the Generation of 5.4 Million New UBVRI Standard Stars using LAMOST and Gaia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02528v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an independent validation and recalibration of the Landolt 2013 (celestial equator and $\delta \sim -50^\circ$) and 2016 ($\delta \sim -50^\circ$) standard stars in the Johnson $UBV$ and Kron-Cousins $RI$ systems, using tens of thousands of XPSP data from the BEst STar (BEST) database. Our analysis reveals an overall zero-point offset between the 2016 and 2013 datasets. We further identify zero-point offsets for each standard field, ranging from 5 -- 14 mmag across all $UBVRI$ bands, with correlations between offsets in different bands. Additionally, we confirm the spatial structures up to 7 -- 10 mmag in the $BVRI$ bands. We also find that spatial structures are similar across bands for the same field, and similar across different fields for the same band. These similarities may arise from the averaged flat-fields from each observing run. The recalibrated results are consistent with the XPSP data within 48 mmag in the $U$ band, 11 mmag in the $B$ band, and 5 -- 6 mmag in the $VRI$ bands in the brightness $G&lt;16$. Furthermore, based on stellar atmospheric parameters from LAMOST DR12 and Gaia DR3 photometry, along with the XPSP data, we derive temperature- and extinction-dependent extinction coefficients for the $UBVRI$ bands as well as a LAMOST \&amp; Gaia-based catalog of 5.4 million standard stars in the $UBVRI$ bands, for which the U-band photometry of the vast majority of sources exhibits significantly higher precision than XPSP. The recalibrated Landolt standard stars and LAMOST \&amp; Gaia-based standard stars will be available on the BEST website (https://nadc.china-vo.org/data/best/) and (https://doi.org/10.12149/101704).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02528v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Huang, Haibo Yuan, Kai Xiao, Ruoyi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on neutrino-Majoron couplings using SN1987A data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11517v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutrino decay to a lighter neutrino and a massless or almost massless (pseudo)scalar Goldstone boson remains of wide interest, as in the search for ultralight dark matter or for neutrinoless double beta-decay, and for its implications in astrophysics and cosmology. Neutrino interactions with Majorons can affect the dynamics of supernovae and impact the emitted neutrino flux. Using a three-neutrino framework and detailed supernova simulations, we perform the first likelihood analysis of the 24 neutrino events from SN1987A, including nonradiative decay in matter to a massless (pseudo)scalar boson like a Majoron. Focusing on the induced spectral distortions, we present bounds on the neutrino-Majoron couplings, as a function of the lightest neutrino mass, that are either complementary or competitive with current ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11517v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/d4vp-m261</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pilar Iv\'a\~nez-Ballesteros (APC, Paris), M. Cristina Volpe (APC, Paris)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALMA chemical survey of disk-outflow sources in Taurus (ALMA-DOT) VII: the layered molecular outflow from HL Tau and its relationship with the ringed disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03920v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ringed disk around HL Tau stands out as the iconic signature of planet formation, but the origin of the substructures is still debated. The HL Tau system also drives a powerful bipolar wind, and we analyze its outermost component traced by CO emission, to determine the relationship of the flow with the disk and its substructures. We use ALMA observations of the ${}^{12}$CO (2-1) line at 1.3 mm, with 0.2 km/s and ~ 0.28" resolution, conducted within the ALMA-DOT project. The channel maps and position-velocity diagrams show a rich structure of concatenated bubble- and arc-shaped features, whose size and distance from the source increase with velocity. The superposition of the features generates the apparent conical shape. The tomographic reconstruction of the morphology and kinematics of the red-shifted lobe suggests the presence of distinct nested shells having higher velocity and steeper velocity gradient for shells closer to the axis, rotating in the same sense of the disk. Such configuration can be justified by different classes of models. In this paper we compare the derived wind parameters with the predictions of magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) disk winds. Under this hypothesis, the launch radii of the three outermost shells are found to be at about the position of three adjacent dust rings in the disk at 58, 72 and 86 au. The wind may be capable of removing angular momentum from the outer disk, and we derive a magnetic lever arm of $\lambda \sim 4 - 5$, higher than that commonly adopted for MHD winds from these regions. Interpretations are discussed. The arrangement of the wind in nested shells with brighter emission rooted at the location of ring substructures could support the results of non-ideal MHD simulations according to which magnetic instabilities can generate the disk ring-gap system with a connected layered wind, alternatively to the action of yet undetected protoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03920v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202453649</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>F. Bacciotti, T. Nony, L. Podio, C. Dougados, A. Garufi, S. Cabrit, C. Codella, N. Zimniak, J. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EP250108a/SN2025kg: A Magnetar-powered Gamma-Ray Burst Supernova Originating from a Close Helium-star Binary via Isolated Binary Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18544v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: SN\,2025kg, linked to EP250108a, is among the brightest broad-lined Type Ic supernova (SN Ic-BL) known, showing unique helium absorptions, a late-time broad H$\alpha$, and an early bump. In this {\em{Letter}}, we propose a jet-cocoon origin to explain EP250108a as off-axis cooling emission from a mildly relativistic inner cocoon viewed at $\sim45^\circ$ and the early bump of SN\,2025kg as the outer cocoon cooling emission, both constraining an energy of $\sim(1-2)\times10^{52}{\rm{erg}}$ and a progenitor radius of $\sim5\,R_\odot$. To explain SN\,2025kg's exceptionally luminous peak, potential energy injection into the $\sim2.5\,M_\odot$ ejecta from a magnetar with initial period $\sim1.7\,{\rm{ms}}$ and magnetic field $\sim2\times10^{15}{\rm{G}}$ may be required, implying a rapidly rotating $\sim4\,M_\odot$ progenitor. Thus, the progenitor may be a low-mass helium star with an extended helium envelope, supported by helium absorption lines and an inferred weak pre-SN wind. Hydrogen-rich material may reside in the inner ejecta layers, as suggested by the late-time broad H$\alpha$, possibly originating from main-sequence companion material evaporated by the magnetar wind. Since the observed near-solar metallicity challenges the popular quasi-chemically homogeneous evolution channel, the rapidly rotating helium-star progenitor of EP250108a/SN\,2025kg might attain angular momentum by being tidally spun up by a main-sequence companion in a close binary formed through isolated binary evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18544v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Ping Zhu, Jian-He Zheng, Bing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of the Host Binary of the Directly Imaged Exoplanet HD 143811 AB b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06727v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: HD~143811~AB is the host star to the directly imaged planet HD~143811~AB~b, which was recently discovered using data from the Gemini Planet Imager and Keck NIRC2. A member of the Sco-Cen star-forming region with an age of $13 \pm 4$ Myr, HD~143811~AB is somewhat rare among hosts of directly imaged planets as it is a close stellar binary, with an $\sim$18 day period. Accurate values for the orbital and stellar parameters of this binary are needed to understand the formation and evolutionary history of the planet in orbit. We utilize archival high-resolution spectroscopy from FEROS on the MPG/ESO 2.2-meter telescope to fit the orbit of the binary, and combine with unresolved photometry to derive the basic stellar properties of the system. From the orbit, we derive precise values of orbital period of $18.59098 \pm 0.00007$ days, and mass ratio of $0.885 \pm 0.003$. When combined with stellar evolutionary models, we find masses of both components of $M_A = 1.30^{+0.03}_{-0.05}$ M$_\odot$ and $M_B = 1.15^{+0.03}_{-0.04}$ M$_\odot$. While the current data are consistent with the planet and stellar orbits being coplanar, the 3D orientations of both systems are currently poorly constrained, with additional observations required to more rigorously test for coplanarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06727v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne E. Peck (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), William Roberson (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), Eric L. Nielsen (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), Robert J. De Rosa (European Southern Observatory, Alonso de C\'ordova 3107, Vitacura, Casilla 19001, Santiago, Chile), Nathalie Jones (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Northwestern University, 2145 Sheridan Road, Evanston, IL 60208-3112, USA, Center for Interdisciplinary Exploration and Research in Astrophysics, 1800 Sherman Ave, Northwestern University, Evanston, IL 60201, USA), Jason Wang (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Northwestern University, 2145 Sheridan Road, Evanston, IL 60208-3112, USA, Center for Interdisciplinary Exploration and Research in Astrophysics, 1800 Sherman Ave, Northwestern University, Evanston, IL 60201, USA), Bruce Macintosh (Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics, UC Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz CA 95064), Bailey L. Lewis (Department of Physics, University of California, Santa Barbara, CA 93106, USA), Gaspard Duch\^ene (Department of Astronomy, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA, Univ. Grenoble Alpes/CNRS, IPAG, F-38000 Grenoble, France), Stanimir Metchev (Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, Institute for Earth and Space Exploration, The University of Western Ontario, London, ON N6A 3K7, Canada), Asif Abbas (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), Jerry W. Xuan (Department of Astronomy, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), Aniket Sanghi (Cahill Center for Astronomy and Astrophysics, California Institute of Technology, 1200 E. California Boulevard, MC 249-17, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), Jennifer Panience (School of Earth and Space Exploration, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ 85287, USA), Travis S. Barman (Lunar and Planetary Lab, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721, USA), Joanna Bulger (Institute for Astronomy, University of Hawai`i, 2680 Woodlawn Drive, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA), Jeffrey K. Chilcote (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Notre Dame, 225 Nieuwland Science Hall, Notre Dame, IN, 46556, USA), Thomas M. Esposito (Department of Astronomy, 501 Campbell Hall, University of California Berkeley, Berkeley, CA 94720-3411, USA, SETI Institute, Carl Sagan Center, 339 Bernardo Ave Ste 200, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA), Michael P. Fitzgerald (Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA), Katherine B. Follette (Physics and Astronomy Department, Amherst College, 25 East Drive, Amherst, MA 01002, USA), Hannah Gallamore (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), Stephen Goodsell (Department of Physics, Durham University, Stockton Road, Durham DH1, UK, Gemini Observatory, Casilla 603, La Serena, Chile), James R. Graham (Department of Astronomy, 501 Campbell Hall, University of California Berkeley, Berkeley, CA 94720-3411, USA), Alexandra Z. Greenbaum (IPAC, Mail Code 100-22, Caltech, 1200 E. California Blvd., Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), Pascale Hibon (European Southern Observatory, Alonso de C\'ordova 3107, Vitacura, Casilla 19001, Santiago, Chile), Patrick Ingraham (Vera C. Rubin Observatory, 950 N Cherry Ave, Tucson AZ, 85719, USA), Paul Kalas (Department of Astronomy, 501 Campbell Hall, University of California Berkeley, Berkeley, CA 94720-3411, USA, SETI Institute, Carl Sagan Center, 339 Bernardo Ave Ste 200, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA, SETI Institute, Carl Sagan Center, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA, Institute of Astrophysics, FORTH, GR-71110 Heraklion, Greece), Quinn M. Konopacky (Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA), Franck Marchis (SETI Institute, Carl Sagan Center, 339 Bernardo Ave Ste 200, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA), J\'er\^ome Maire (Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA), Christian Marois (National Research Council of Canada Herzberg, 5071 West Saanich Rd, Victoria, BC, V9E 2E7, Canada, Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, University of Victoria, 3800 Finnerty Rd., Victoria, BC V8P 5C2, Canada), Brenda Matthews (Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy, University of Victoria, 3800 Finnerty Rd., Victoria, BC V8P 5C2, Canada), Dimitri Mawet (Department of Astronomy, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA 91109, USA 48), Maxwell A. Millar-Blanchaer (Department of Physics, University of California, Santa Barbara, CA 93106, USA), Rebecca Oppenheimer (American Museum of Natural History, Department of Astrophysics, Central Park West at 79th Street, New York, NY 10024, USA), David W. Palmer (Lawrence 50 Livermore National Laboratory, 7000 East Avenue, Livermore, CA, 94550, USA), Marshall D. Perrin (Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA), Lisa Pointer (Lawrence 50 Livermore National Laboratory, 7000 East Avenue, Livermore, CA, 94550, USA), Laurent Pueyo (Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA), Abhijith Rajan (Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA), Julien Rameau (Trottier Institute for Research on Exoplanets, Universit\'e de Montr\'eal, D\'epartement de Physique, C.P. 6128 Succ. Centre-ville, Montr\'eal, QC H3C 3J7, Canada, University of Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, IPAG, F-38000 Grenoble, France), Fredrik T. Rantakyr\"o (Gemini Observatory, Casilla 603, La Serena, Chile), Bin Ren (Observatoire de la C\^ote d`Azur, 96 Bd de l`Observatoire, 06304 Nice, France), Jean-Baptiste Ruffio (Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA), Dmitry Savransky (Sibley School of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA, Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Dr., Pasadena, CA 91109, USA), Adam C. Schneider (United States Naval Observatory, Flagstaff Station, 10391 West Naval Observatory Road, Flagstaff, AZ 86005, USA, Department of Physics and Astronomy, George Mason University, MS3F3, 4400 University Drive, Fairfax, VA 22030, USA), Anand Sivaramakrishnan (Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA), Adam J. R. W. Smith (Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University, P.O. Box 30001, MSC 4500, Las Cruces, NM 88003, USA), Inseok Song (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602, USA), Remi Summer (Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21218, USA), Sandrine Thomas (Vera C. Rubin Observatory, 950 N Cherry Ave, Tucson AZ, 85719, USA), Kimberly Ward-Duong (Department of Astronomy, Smith College, Northampton, MA, 01063, USA), Schuyler G. Wolff (Steward Observatory, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Walk on the Retrograde Side (WRS) project. II. Chemistry to disentangle in situ and accreted components in Thamnos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06332v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the results of the first systematic and dedicated high-resolution chemical analysis of the Thamnos substructure, a candidate relic of the process of hierarchical merger of the Milky Way. The analysis was perfomed in comparison with the Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus (GSE) remnant, within the fully self-consistent and homogeneous framework established by the 'A Walk on the Retrograde Side' (WRS) project. We analysed high-resolution and high signal-to-noise ratio spectra obtained with UVES at VLT for 212 red giant branch stars classified as candidate members of Thamnos and GSE, based on selections in the space of the integrals of motion. We derived precise abundances for 16 atomic species. Compared to GSE, stars attributed to the Thamnos substructure are, on average, more metal-poor, yet most of them show higher [X/Fe] abundance ratios in several elements, such as Na, Mg, Al, Ca, Cu, Zn, as well as lower [Eu/Fe]. The majority of candidate Thamnos stars show chemical signatures more consistent with the in situ Milky Way halo rather than a typical low-mass accreted dwarf galaxy. Our findings are further supported by comparisons with tailored galactic chemical evolution models, which fall short in reproducing the observed enhancement in the $\alpha$-elements, but are able to fit the more metal-poor component present in the Thamnos substructure. These results confirm a high level of contamination in the Thamnos substructure from the in situ population and to a lesser degree from GSE, while still leaving room for a genuine accreted population from a small disrupted dwarf galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06332v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Ceccarelli, D. Massari, M. Palla, A. Mucciarelli, M. Bellazzini, A. Helmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
