<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 01:34:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>HST Observations of the CV Propeller LAMOST J024048.51+195226.9</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Hubble Space Telescope (HST) FUV spectra and light curves of the magnetic cataclysmic variable (CV) LAMOST J024048.51+195226.9 (J0240), the second known CV propeller. The five consecutive HST orbits span a full 7.34 hour binary orbital period. We detect a 24.939 $\pm$ 0.006 s FUV modulation, confirming that J0240 contains the fastest spinning white dwarf (WD) in a CV. A high N V/C IV emission line ratio is considered an indicator of a recent episode of thermal time-scale mass transfer. The observed ratio in J0240 is higher than seen in typical magnetic CVs, but far less than observed in the only other confirmed propeller, AE Aquarii (AE Aqr). We also find that J0240 is significantly less luminous than AE Aqr during both low- and high-flux states. Around orbital phase 0.5, the Si IV emission line displays a P-Cygni absorption profile likely related to the gas accelerated in the propeller. We derive new mass-dependent temperature limits for the surface temperature of the WD of T $\leq$ 11,000-15,000 K. This temperature is low enough to allow for WD core crystallization, which may be linked to magnetism in WDs, particularly those in CVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00990v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Tweddale, Peter Garnavich, Colin Littlefield, Paula Szkody</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GW231123 Formation from Population III Stars: Isolated Binary Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: GW231123 is a merger of two black holes (BHs) whose inferred masses exceed $100\;{\rm M}_\odot$ typically; they are the most massive BHs among those discovered by gravitational wave (GW) observations. We examine if GW231123-like events can be formed from isolated Population (Pop) III binary stars by means of binary population synthesis calculations. We find that Pop III isolated binary stars can create GW231123-like events at a rate large enough to explain the discovery of GW231123, if two conditions are satisfied. First, Pop III stars evolve with inefficient convective overshooting, and second the $^{12}{\rm C}(\alpha,\gamma)^{16}{\rm O}$ rate is $2\sigma$ lower than the standard value. On the other hand, GW190521, which is the most massive BHs in Gravitational Wave Transient Catalog 3, can be formed from isolated Pop III binary stars even if the $^{12}{\rm C}(\alpha,\gamma)^{16}{\rm O}$ rate is the standard value. We reveal that the discovery of GW231123 is progressively putting constraints on possible parameter ranges of single star evolution models, assuming that all the GW events are formed through isolated binary evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01135v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ataru Tanikawa, Shuai Liu, WeiWei Wu, Michiko S. Fujii, Long Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Catalog of Forty-two Heartbeat Stars Discovered in TESS Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heartbeat stars (HBSs) are ideal laboratories for studying the formation and evolution of binary stars in eccentric orbits and their internal tidal interactions. We present 42 new HBSs discovered based on TESS photometric data. Their light curves are modeled by using a corrected version of Kumar et al.'s model or the PHOEBE binary model code. Tidally excited oscillations (TEOs) are detected in ten systems, with most pulsation phases can be explained by the dominant being $l=2$, $m=0$, or $\pm2$ spherical harmonic. For TIC 156846634, the harmonic with large deviation ($&gt;3\sigma$) can be expected to be a traveling wave or nonadiabatic. The $n$ = 16 harmonic in TIC 184413651 may not be considered as a TEO candidate due to its large deviation ($&gt;2\sigma$) and lower amplitude. Moreover, TIC 92828790 shows no TEOs but exhibits a significant gamma Doradus pulsation. The eccentricity-period (e$-$P) relation also shows a positive correlation between eccentricity and period, as well as the existence of orbital circularization. The Hertzsprung-Russell diagram shows that TESS HBSs have higher temperatures and greater luminosities than Kepler HBSs. This significantly enhances the detectability of massive HBSs and those containing TEOs. Currently, the search for HBSs using TESS data has become a research focus, and these intriguing objects may serve as valuable additions to the TESS HBS catalog.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01156v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min-Yu Li, Sheng-Bang Qian, Ai-Ying Zhou, Li-Ying Zhu, Wen-Ping Liao, Lin-Feng Chang, Xiang-Dong Shi, Fu-Xing Li, Qi-Bin Sun, Ping Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corotating Interaction Regions (CIRs): impacts with exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Corotating interaction regions (CIRs) are compressions that form in stellar winds when streams of different speeds collide. They form an Archimedean spiral around the star and can compress any exoplanetary magnetospheres they impact. They may also steepen into shocks capable of accelerating particles to high energies. We model the frequency and strength of these CIRS for stars of spectral types F-M. We show that the minimum radius, $r_{CIR}=\Delta \phi u_{slow}/\Omega$, at which CIRs form varies strongly with the rotation rate (and hence age) of the star. For some exoplanets, such as those in Earth or Mars orbits, CIRs can form within the exoplanet's orbit at all stellar rotation rates, depending on the angular size of the fast wind segment ($\Delta \phi$). These exoplanets will experience CIR impacts at all stellar ages. However, for closer-in orbits such as Mercury or Venus, this may only be the case at higher stellar rotation rates. Both the frequency and impact of CIRs depend on the stellar rotation rate. For exoplanets with $P_{orbit}\gg P_*$, CIR impacts lasting for a time $\Delta t$ raise the exoplanetary outflow rate by a factor $R$. If $P_*\leq N\Delta t$ the CIR pulses overlap in time, whereas if $N\Delta t &lt; P_* \leq N\Delta t(R+1)$, the planet experiences discrete pulses of compression and relaxation and the CIR-related outflow is more than 50$\%$ of the total. For $P_* &gt; N\Delta t(R+1)$ the pulses are less frequent, and contribute less than $50\%$ of the total outflow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01267v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rose Waugh, Moira Jardine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting symbiotic binaries with interferometry: II. New PIONIER data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symbiotic stars, which generally comprise a red giant and an accreting white dwarf, are excellent laboratories to understand mass transfer in wide binaries, with application to a wide family of systems. One of the fundamental questions is how mass is transferred from the red giant to the white dwarf. We use interferometric measurements made with the VLTI/PIONIER instrument, combined with Gaia data, to measure the radius of the giant in seven symbiotic systems. We further place the giants in the H-R diagramme, which allows us to estimate their mass and to show that they are all very evolved and likely on the asymptotic giant branch. We compare our measured giant radii to their Roche-lobe radius and show that, except for ZZ CMi, all giants are well within their Roche lobe and that mass transfer likely takes place via stellar wind. Our interferometric data provide further evidence that the giant in ZZ CMi (nearly) fills its Roche lobe. Our conclusions are still hampered by the poor characterisation of some of the giants or their binary orbit, and we encourage the community to make an effort to provide these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01304v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri M. J. Boffin, Jaroslav Merc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary stellar evolution yields in galactic chemical evolution calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01717v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a framework for the computation of effective stellar yields that accounts for a mixed population of binary and single stars under an adjustable mix of binary evolution settings: the binary fraction, the accretion efficiencies of winds, Roche-lobe overflow, and supernovae. We emphasise the critical need for more complete yield coverage of the binary nucleosynthesis and evolution, without which the ability to make accurate predictions on the true role of binarity on GCE calculations is hamstrung. We also provide clear guidelines for future stellar modelling works to ensure their results are maximally useful to the wider community. We compute effective stellar yields using detailed binary stellar yields accounting for binary induced mass-loss from a solar-metallicity donor star. We study the effect of varying the binary mixture and accretion efficiencies, and consider a range of models for the treatment of accreted material on the secondary in detail. In the absence of detailed binary yields for the secondary, we put forth a model for the composition of accreted material that preserves the signature of the primary's nuclear processing within the post-mass-transfer secondary yields. Among the binary parameters, we find that the binary fraction, which determines the ratio of binary and single star systems, has the most significant effect on the effective stellar yields, with widespread impact across most isotopes. In contrast, varying the accretion efficiencies produces comparatively minor changes. We also find that the binary fraction has a significant influence on the logarithmic elemental abundance ratios relative to H present in the effective yield; this impact is largest for the lower-mass primaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01717v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Kemp, Tejpreet Kaur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multi-faceted variability of HD 192639: Stochastic behaviour, regularities, and an exceptional mass-ejection event</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectroscopic and photometric variability is widespread among O-type supergiants. It is linked to various phenomena affecting the star and its circumstellar environment, thereby providing direct information concerning them. To investigate such connections, we decided to revisit the prototypical O7.5 Iabf supergiant HD 192639. High-cadence spectroscopic monitoring was performed simultaneously with intensive space-borne photometric observations. The data were analysed with several methods to characterise the variability. Besides the usual stochastic, low-frequency photometric variability, our observations reveal the presence of recurrent - but transient - modulations on a timescale of about five days. The same signal is present in the spectroscopic data and was already seen two decades ago. This stability suggests that this timescale corresponds to the stellar rotation. Furthermore, our observations unveil, for the first time, an unusually strong dimming event in the light curve associated with absorption and emission changes in H I and He I lines. This unprecedented trough corresponds to an episodic ejection of a rather large amount of mass (its column density being comparable to that of the steady wind). While rare, such an event could hint at an overlooked aspect of mass loss in massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01870v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregor Rauw, Ya\"el Naz\'e, Charles-Antoine Gilon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Second Stellar Spectrum: Rotating hot massive star linear spectropolarimetry with the Ohman Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01962v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To understand better the polarized radiative transfer near the surface of rotating massive stars that remain nearly spherically symmetric, we use plane-parallel stellar atmosphere models to explore the unique opportunity presented by the Ohman effect. This effect refers to the predicted variation in linear polarization across a rotationally broadened absorption line, due to the interaction of that line with the spatially varying continuum polarization across the face of a strongly scattering photosphere, such as found in hot stars. Even if the rotation is weak enough for the star to remain spherically symmetric, the Ohman effect persists because differential absorption induced by the rotational Doppler shift of the line breaks the symmetry that would otherwise cancel the continuum polarization in the absence of that line. Neglecting rotational distortion effects, the net polarization across the line vanishes, yet resolved line profiles display a telltale triple-peak polarization pattern, with one strong polarization peak at line center and two smaller ones in the line wings at a position angle that is rotated 90 degrees from the line center. The far ultraviolet (FUV) is emphasized because both the polarization amplitude and the specific luminosity are greatest there for photospheres with effective temperatures between about 15,000 and 20,000K. There is a high density of spectral lines in the FUV, leading to a rich "second stellar spectrum" in linear polarization (analogous to the "second solar spectrum") that is made observable with stellar rotation. Polarizations at the level of 0.1% to 1% are achievable across individual lines for a wide variety of B-type stars. We highlight the prospects for accessing the unique information encoded in the Ohman effect with future moderate-resolution spaceborne spectropolarimetric missions in the FUV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01962v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Patrick Harrington, R. Ignace, K. G. Gayley, J. J. Drake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary Systems Search with TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hot subdwarf B (sdB) stars are post-main-sequence stars of high temperature and gravity. Approximately 30$\%$ of sdBs exhibit stable pressure and/or gravity-mode pulsations, which can be used via the timing method to test for companion stars and determine their orbital solutions. We used short cadence data from the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) to search for previously undiscovered companions to sdBs. In this paper, we focus on searching for companions with orbital periods shorter than 13.5$\,$d which are detectable within one sector of TESS data (about 27$\,d$). The timing method requires that we derive pulsation frequencies in subsets of data significantly shorter than the periods we are searching for, which we set at 0.5 to 1.5$\,$d. We investigated ten sdB stars with previously detected p-mode pulsations for which at least one p-mode pulsation remains detectable with a signal-to-noise ratio (S/N) $&gt;$ 4 within data subsets of duration 0.5 - 1.5$\,$d. We find that two (TIC$\,$202354658 and TIC$\,$69298924) of these ten sdB stars likely have white dwarf companions and set limits on companion masses for the other eight sdB stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02181v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomomi Otani, A. S. Baran, Lindsay C. Spence, Ted von Hippel, E. Lynum-Lozano, Julia. M. Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Challenging Classical Paradigms: Recurrent Nova M31N 2017-01e, a BeWD system in M31?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: M31N 2017-01e is the second-fastest recurrent nova known, with a recurrence period of 2.5 years in the Andromeda Galaxy (M31). This system exhibits a unique combination of properties: a low outburst amplitude ($\sim3$ magnitude), starkly contrasting with known recurrent novae (typically $\geq 6$ magnitudes), and a very fast evolution ($t_{2}\sim 5 $ days). Its position coincides with a bright variable source ($\mathrm{{M_V \sim -4.2,\, B-V= 0.042}}$) displaying a 14.3 day photometric modulation, which has been suggested as the likely progenitor.
  We present a multi-wavelength analysis of optical and UV data spanning quiescence and the 2019 and 2024 outbursts. Archival high-resolution imaging reveals two nearby faint sources within $5^{\prime\prime}$ of the proposed nova system, which we identified as unrelated field stars. Color analysis and spectral energy distribution fitting suggest the progenitor is likely an early-type star. Combined with archival spectra consistent with a B-type star with H$\alpha$ in emission, this points to the quiescent counterpart being a Be star with a circumstellar disc.
  We propose that M31N 2017-01e arises from a rare Be-WD binary, where the WD accretes from the decretion disk of its companion, explaining its rapid recurrence, low-amplitude outbursts, and unusual quiescent luminosity and color. This analysis highlights M31N 2017-01e as a compelling outlier among recurrent novae, suggesting a distinct accretion mechanism and evolutionary path that challenges the prevailing paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02227v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shatakshi Chamoli, Judhajeet Basu, Sudhanshu Barway, G. C. Anupama, Vishwajeet Swain, Varun Bhalero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PARSEC V2.0: Rotating tracks and isochrones for seven addtional metallicities in the range Z=0.0001-0.03</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PARSEC v2.0 rotating stellar tracks were previously presented for six values of metallicity from subsolar to solar values, with initial rotation rates ($\omega_\mathrm{i}$, defined as the ratio of angular velocity and its critical value) spanning from the non-rotating case to very near the critical velocity (i.e. $\omega_\mathrm{i}=0.99$), and for initial masses covering the $\sim 0.7 M_\odot$ to $14 M_\odot$ interval. Furthermore, we provided the corresponding isochrones converted into several photometric systems, for different inclination angles between the line-of-sight and the rotation axes, from $0^\circ$ (pole-on) to $90^\circ$ (equator-on). In this work, we expand this database with seven other sets of metallicity, including five sets of low metallicity ($Z=0.0001-0.002$) and two sets of super-solar values (up to $Z=0.03$). Here, we present the new stellar tracks, comprising $\sim$3\,040 tracks in total ($\sim$5\,500 including previous sets), along with the new corresponding rotating isochrones. We also introduce the possibility of creating isochrones, by interpolation, for values of rotating rates not available in the initial set of tracks. We compare a selection of our new models with rotating stellar tracks from the Geneva Stellar Evolution Code, and we assess the quality of our new tracks by fitting the colour-magnitude diagram of the open cluster NGC6067. We take advantage of the projected rotational velocity of member stars measured by Gaia to validate our results and examine the surface oxygen abundances in comparison with the observed data. All newly computed stellar tracks and isochrones are retrievable via our dedicated web databases and interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02393v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. T. Nguyen, G. Costa, A. Bressan, L. Girardi, G. Cescutti, A. J. Korn, G. Volpato, Y. Chen, G. Pastorelli, M. Trabucchi, K. G. Shepherd, G. Ettorre, S. Zaggia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic Confirmation: Fast rotators in the young clusters NGC 1856 and NGC 1953</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results of a spectroscopic investigation of two Large Magellanic Cloud globular clusters, NGC 1953 and NGC 1856. Both clusters have similar ages (250 and 300 Myr, respectively). Spectra were recorded with the Michigan/Magellan Fiber System located on the Magellan-Clay 6.5m telescope. Spectra were visually inspected to assess the presence of stellar H$\alpha$ emission lines attributed to B stars rotating close to breakup velocity (Be stars). High fractions of Be stars in the cluster typically indicate the presence of a large population of fast rotating stars, predicted by some models to explain the observed split and extended main sequence. There are numerous Be star candidates in NGC 1856, exhibiting weak but broad H$\alpha$ emission. However, only one such target was detected in NGC 1953. This stark contrast between the observed populations for NGC 1856 and NGC 1953 may suggest that cluster density plays a key role in determining the fraction of Be stars. These results provide essential constraints for the different scenarios attempting to explain the bimodal distribution of rotational velocities and the multiple populations of stars observed in globular clusters. The impact of stellar radial velocity and nebular emission on photometric measures is assessed through simulations relying on the spectra. These simulations suggest that photometric studies can under-estimate the fraction of H$\alpha$ emitters in a cluster, in particular for stars with relatively weak emission features. The results also show that nebular emission has minimal impact on the photometric H$\alpha$ excesses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02599v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul I. Cristofari, Andrea K. Dupree, Antonino P. Milone, Mario Mateo, Matias Chiarpotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical and near-infrared nebular-phase spectroscopy of SN 2024ggi: constraints on the structure of the inner ejecta, progenitor mass, and dust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present optical and near-infrared (NIR) spectroscopic observations of the nearby Type II supernova SN\,2024ggi from 250 and 420 days after the explosion. Comparing the evolution of the [\ion{O}{1}] at 6300, 6363 \text{\AA} doublet normalized to the continuum with spectral models from the literature, we estimate a progenitor star zero-age main-sequence mass ($M_{\mathrm{ZAMS}}$) of $\approx 14$ M$_\odot$. This value is consistent with $M_{\mathrm{ZAMS}}$ reported in the literature from independent methodologies. The nebular spectra are used to study the structure of the inner ejecta. The broad H$\alpha$ line has a full-width at half maximum (FWHM) of $\simeq 3900$ km s$^{-1}$, with small deviations from a symmetric Gaussian profile centred at zero velocity, and the [\ion{O}{1}] doublet is blue-shifted by $\approx -940$ km s$^{-1}$. In the NIR, the nebular spectra reveal double-peaked emission features of \ion{Mg}{1} and [\ion{Fe}{2}] lines, suggesting a bipolar distribution of intermediate mass and iron peak elements in the line-of-sight. Such a double-peaked feature in these NIR lines has not been previously reported. No corresponding asymmetries are observed in the hydrogen lines, suggesting that the asymmetry is mostly confined to intermediate mass and iron peak elements in the innermost core of the supernova ejecta. Additionally, we detect first-overtone carbon monoxide (CO) emission at $2.3$ $\mu$m from 250 to 319 days in the NIR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02656v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilio Hueichap\'an, R\'egis Cartier, Jose L. Prieto, Carlos Contreras, Aleksandar Cikota, Thallis Pessi, Franz E. Bauer, Giuliano Pignata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the Origins of Galactic Globular Clusters via Their Mg-Al Abundances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many Galactic globular clusters (GCs) originated in diverse host galaxies before being subsequently incorporated into the Milky Way through hierarchical galaxy assembly. Identifying their origins is crucial for revealing galaxy properties at early times. Traditional classification methods relying on dynamical properties face inherent uncertainties stemming from the evolving Galactic potential and complex merger histories. Chemically driven classification confronts a distinct obstacle: multiple populations - abundance variations in light elements of GC members. In this Letter, we identify primordial populations exhibiting lower [Al/Fe] as reliable tracers of their birth environments' chemical evolution. A clear chemical dichotomy emerges between in-situ and accreted GC populations at [Fe/H] &gt; -1.5, particularly in the [Mg/Fe]-[Al/Fe] plane, indicating that their progenitor galaxies have experienced fundamentally different enrichment histories. While our chemically driven classification demonstrates general consistency with dynamically driven classifications, notable discrepancies emerge: NGC 288 and M4 are reclassified as in-situ, and Terzan 9 as accreted. This chemically driven GC classification provides promising application for Galactic archaeology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00526v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihui Lin, Baitian Tang, Genghao Liu, Jos\'E G. Fern\'andez-Trincado, Douglas Geisler, Guy Worthey, Dante Minnitit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Distant and Metal-Poor Milky Way with SDSS-V</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fifth-generation Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS-V) is conducting the first all-sky low-resolution spectroscopic survey of the Milky Way's stellar halo. We describe the stellar parameter pipeline for the SDSS-V halo survey, which simultaneously models spectra, broadband photometry, and parallaxes to derive stellar parameters, metallicities, alpha abundances, and distances. The resulting BOSS-MINESweeper catalog is validated across a wide range of stellar parameters and metallicities using star clusters and a comparison to high-resolution spectroscopic surveys. We demonstrate several scientific capabilities of this dataset: identifying the most chemically peculiar stars in our Galaxy, discovering and mapping distant halo substructures, and measuring the all--sky dynamics of the Milky Way on the largest scales. The BOSS-MINESweeper catalog for SDSS DR19 is publicly available and will be updated for future data releases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00978v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vedant Chandra, Phillip A. Cargile, Alexander P. Ji, Charlie Conroy, Hans-Walter Rix, Emily Cunningham, Bruno Dias, Chervin Laporte, William Cerny, Guilherme Limberg, Avrajit Bandyopadhyay, Ana Bonaca, Andrew R. Casey, John Donor, Jose G. Fernandez-Trincado, Peter M. Frinchaboy, Pramod Gupta, Keith Hawkins, Jennifer A. Johnson, Juna A. Kollmeier, Madeline Lucey, Ilija Medan, Szabolcs Meszaros, Sean Morrison, Jose Sanchez-Gallego, Andrew K. Saydjari, Conor Sayres, Kevin C. Schlaufman, Keivan G. Stassun, Jamie Tayar, Zachary Way</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detailed radial scale height profile of dust grains as probed by dust self-scattering in HL Tau</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The vertical settling of dust grains in a circumstellar disk, characterized by their scale height, is a pivotal process in the formation of planets. This study offers in-depth analysis and modeling of the radial scale height profile of dust grains in the HL Tau system, leveraging high-resolution polarization observations. We resolve the inner disk's polarization, revealing a significant near-far side asymmetry, with the near side being markedly brighter than the far side in polarized intensity. This asymmetry is attributed to a geometrically thick inner dust disk, suggesting a large aspect ratio of $H/R \ge 0.15$. The first ring at 20 au exhibits an azimuthal contrast, with polarization enhanced along the minor axis, indicating a moderately thick dust ring with $H/R \approx 0.1$. The absence of the near-far side asymmetry at larger scales implies a thin dust layer, with $H/R &lt; 0.05$. Taken together, these findings depict a disk with a turbulent inner region and a settled outer disk, requiring a variable turbulence model with $\alpha$ increasing from $10^{-5}$ at 100 au to $10^{-2.5}$ at 20 au. This research sheds light on dust settling and turbulence levels within protoplanetary disks, providing valuable insights into the mechanisms of planet formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01233v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haifeng Yang, Ian W. Stephens, Zhe-Yu Daniel Lin, Manuel Fern\'andez-L\'opez, Zhi-Yun Li, Leslie W. Looney, Rachel Harrison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SN 2024gy: Multi-epoch Spectroscopic Evidence for Delayed Detonation in a Type Ia Supernova</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01428v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present photometric and spectroscopic observations of SN 2024gy, a Type Ia supernova (SN Ia) exhibiting high-velocity features (HVFs) in its early-time spectra. This SN reaches a peak $B$-band magnitude of $-19.25 \pm 0.28$ mag and subsequently declines by $\Delta m_{15}(B) \approx 1.12$ mag, consistent with the luminosity-width relation characteristic of normal SNe Ia. Based on the peak thermal luminosity of $(1.2 \pm 0.3) \times 10^{43}$ erg s$^{-1}$, we estimate that $0.57 \pm 0.14~\rm M_{\odot}$ of $^{56}$Ni was synthesized during the explosion. Our dense early spectral monitoring revealed significant velocity disparities within the ejecta. Notably, absorption features from the \CaII\ near-infrared triplet were observed at velocities exceeding 25,000 km s$^{-1}$, while the \SiII\, \ld 6355 line velocity at the same epoch was significantly lower at $\sim$ 16,000 km s$^{-1}$. This velocity disparity likely reflects distinct ionization states of intermediate-mass elements in the outermost layers. The prominent \CaII\, HVFs may originate from ionization suppression within the highest-velocity ejecta, potentially indicative of minimal hydrogen mixing in a delayed-detonation explosion scenario. Additionally, the Ni/Fe ratio derived from the nebular spectrum of SN 2024gy provides further support for this model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01428v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liping Li, Zhenyu Wang, Jialian Liu, Yu Pan, Alexei V. Filippenko, Jujia Zhang, Xiaofeng Wang, Brajesh Kumar, Yi Yang, Thomas G. Brink, WeiKang Zheng, Xiangcun Meng, Lingzhi Wang, Zeyi Zhao, Qian Zhai, Yongzhi Cai, Giuliano Pignata, Xinlei Chen, Xingzhu Zou, Jiewei Zhao, Xiangkun Liu, Xiaowei Liu, Xinzhong Er, A. Reguitti, R. Michael Rich, Jon M. Rees, Mark A. Croom, K. Itagaki, Bo Wang, Jinming Bai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Analysis of X-ray Sources in Terzan 5 Using Chandra Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze photometry, spectra, and variability of over 100 faint X-ray sources in the globular cluster Terzan 5, using 737 ks of Chandra data. X-ray colors and spectral fitting allow clear separation of foreground sources (with less extinction than the cluster), quiescent low-mass X-ray binaries (qLMXBs), and sources with harder spectra. We identify 22 candidate qLMXBs, over twice that found in any other cluster. This is consistent with Terzan 5's stellar interaction rate, the highest among Galactic globular clusters. We do not see qLMXBs dominated by thermal emission below $L_X\sim10^{32}$ erg/s, though qLMXBs with stronger nonthermal emission could be missed. We find that more than 50 % of the qLMXB sources have neutron star thermal component contributing over 80 % of the total luminosity. We report an unusual spectral feature around 1.75 keV in the combined spectrum of Ter 5 X-3. The concentration of the qLMXBs within the cluster is consistent with that of a population of mass $1.46 \pm 0.14$ M$_\odot$. We identify secure X-ray counterparts to millisecond pulsars Terzan 5 ar and Terzan 5 at, using positional coincidence and orbital X-ray light curves matching those expected for spider pulsars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02526v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gourav Kumawat, Craig O. Heinke, Jiaqi Zhao, Arash Bahramian, Haldan N. Cohn, Phyllis M. Lugger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINDS. Young binary systems with JWST/MIRI: Variable water-rich primaries and extended emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As part of the JWST GTO program MINDS, we analyze the mid-infrared emission of three Class II binary systems: VW Cha, WX Cha, and RW Aur, to investigate the impact of stellar multiplicity on the chemistry and physics of their inner disk. We analyze the 1D spectrum from JWST/MIRI-MRS for primary and secondary disks separately, extracted by combining forward modeling with a theoretical PSF and aperture photometry. We modeled the molecular lines with 0D slab models. We interpret the results by comparing our JWST spectra to VLT/CRIRES+, Spitzer/IRS, and ALMA. Primary and secondary disks are dramatically different in their mid-infrared emission, with primary disks showing H2O-rich spectra, and secondary disks being mostly line poor to the sensitivity of our spectra. When comparing MIRI-MRS to Spitzer/IRS, we observe large variability in the line emission of VW Cha A, as well as in the continuum of RW Aur A. The disks around VW Cha BC and RW Aur B show evidence of ionizing radiation, and a further comparison with ALMA at high angular resolution dust continuum suggest that the spectrum of RW Aur B is well explained by its ~4 au cavity. All the systems show [Ne II] jet emission, and three of them also show spatially resolved emission structures in H2, likely originated by outflows and dynamical interactions. Many of the observed features in the primary disks, such as enhanced water emission, could be linked to the increased accretion and radial drift produced by dynamical disk truncation. However, additional mechanisms are needed to explain the large differences between primary and secondary disks, potentially inner disk substructures. This work is an example of the need for combining multiple facilities to fully understand the observations from JWST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02576v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas T. Kurtovic, Sierra L. Grant, Milou Temmink, Andrew D. Sellek, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Thomas Henning, Inga Kamp, Valentin Christiaens, Andrea Banzatti, Danny Gasman, Till Kaeufer, Lucas M. Stapper, Riccardo Franceschi, Manuel G\"udel, Pierre-Olivier Lagage, Marissa Vlasblom, Giulia Perotti, Kamber Schwarz, Alice Somigliana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multi-physics analysis, design and testing of CUSP, a CubeSat mission for space weather and solar flares x-ray polarimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The space-based CUbesat Solar Polarimeter (CUSP) mission aims to measure the linear polarization of solar flares in the hard X-ray band by means of a Compton scattering polarimeter. CUSP is a project in the framework of the Alcor Program of the Italian Space Agency aimed at developing new CubeSat missions. As part of CUSP's Phase B study, which began in December 2024 and will last one year, we present the current development status of the design solutions adopted for the mission's most critical multi-physics design drivers. These solutions have been formulated and applied to demonstrate compliance with system requirements at both the spacecraft and platform levels. In particular, we describe the mechanical design of each structural component, the results of static, dynamic finite element analyses, and a proposal for topological optimization of the interface between the platform and payload and some fixture for test, and the preliminary environmental testing campaign (e.g., vibration, shock) that will be carried out on a mechanical demonstrator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Lombardi, Sergio Fabiani, Ettore Del Monte, Andrea Alimenti, Riccardo Campana, Mauro Centrone, Enrico Costa, Nicolas De Angelis, Giovanni De Cesare, Sergio Di Cosimo, Giuseppe Di Persio, Abhay Kumar, Alessandro Lacerenza, Pasqualino Loffredo, Gabriele Minervini, Fabio Muleri, Paolo Romano, Alda Rubini, Emanuele Scalise, Enrico Silva, Paolo Soffitta, Davide Albanesi, Ilaria Baffo, Daniele Brienza, Valerio Campamaggiore, Giovanni Cucinella, Andrea Curatolo, Giulia de Iulis, Andrea Del Re, Vito Di Bari, Simone Di Filippo, Immacolata Donnarumma, Pierluigi Fanelli, Nicolas Gagliardi, Paolo Leonetti, Matteo Merge, Dario Modenini, Andrea Negri, Daniele Pecorella, Massimo Perelli, Alice Ponti, Francesca Sbop, Paolo Tortora, Alessandro Turchi, Valerio Vagelli, Emanuele Zaccagnino, Alessandro Zambardi, Costantino Zazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PSR J0614-3329: A NICER case for Strange Quark Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise measurements of neutron star masses and radii by the NICER mission impose important constraints on the nuclear equation of state. The most recent NICER measurement of PSR J0614-3329 reported an equatorial radius of $R_{eq} = 10.29^{+1.01}_{-0.86}$ km for a mass of $M = 1.44^{+0.06}_{-0.07} M_{\odot}$. Considering all the NICER measurements to date, we demonstrate using Bayesian hypothesis ranking that strange quark stars are preferred over all the physically motivated models of neutron stars compatible with this low radius. This provides a strong case for the possible existence of strange quark stars, suggesting that they should be considered among the population of compact stars during analyses of astrophysical data. Using a wide sample of equations of state, we report the nucleonic equations of state that best fit current observations and rule out one model of strange quark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02652v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swarnim Shirke, Rajesh Maiti, Debarati Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the metallicity dependence of the mass-loss rate relation of red supergiants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05876v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Red supergiants (RSGs) are cool and evolved massive stars exhibiting enhanced mass loss compared to their main sequence phase, affecting their evolution and fate. However, the theory of the wind-driving mechanism is not well-established and the metallicity dependence has not been determined. We aim to uniformly measure the mass-loss rates of large samples of RSGs in different galaxies with $-0.7\lesssim[Z]\lesssim0$ to investigate whether there is a potential correlation with metallicity. We collected photometry from the ultraviolet to the mid-infrared for all our RSG candidates to construct their spectral energy distribution (SED). Our final sample includes 893 RSG candidates in the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC), 396 in NGC 6822, 527 in the Milky Way, 1425 in M31, and 1854 in M33. Each SED was modelled using the radiative transfer code DUSTY under the same assumptions to derive the mass-loss rate. The mass-loss rates range from approximately $10^{-9} \ M_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$ to $10^{-5} \ M_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$ with an average value of $1.5\times10^{-7} \ M_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$. We provided a new mass-loss rate relation as a function of luminosity and effective temperature for both the SMC and Milky Way and compared our mass-loss rates with those derived in the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC). The turning point in the mass-loss rate vs. luminosity relation differs by around 0.2 dex between the LMC and SMC. The mass-loss rates of the Galactic RSGs at $\log(L/L_\odot)&lt;4.5$ were systematically lower than those determined in the other galaxies, possibly due to uncertainties in the interstellar extinction. We found 60-70% of the RSGs to be dusty. The results for M31 and M33 are inconclusive because of source blending at distances above 0.5 Mpc, given the resolution of Spitzer. Overall, we found similar mass-loss rates among the galaxies, indicating no strong correlation with metallicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05876v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Antoniadis, E. Zapartas, A. Z. Bonanos, G. Maravelias, S. Vlassis, G. Munoz-Sanchez, C. Nally, M. Meixner, O. C. Jones, L. Lenkic, P. J. Kavanagh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An interferometric study of B star multiplicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02300v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Massive stars can have extreme effects on their environments from local to galactic scales. While O star multiplicity has been studied over a broad separation range (to the point where absolute masses of these systems have been determined and investigations into multiple system formation and interactions have been performed), studies of B star multiplicity are lacking. Using interferometry, we investigated the multiplicity of a statistically significant sample of B stars over a range of separations (~0.5-35 au, given that the average distance to our sample is 412 pc). We analysed high angular resolution interferometric data taken with VLTI/PIONIER for a sample of 32 B stars. Using parametric modelling of the closure phases and visibilities, we determined best-fitting models to each of the systems and investigated whether each source was best represented by a single star or a higher-order system. The detection limits were calculated for companions to determine whether they were significant. We then combined our findings from the interferometric data with results from a literature search to determine whether other companions were reported at different separation ranges. Within the interferometric range 72+/-8% of the B stars are resolved as multiple systems. The most common type of system is a binary system, followed by single stars, triple systems, and quadruple systems. The interferometric companion fraction derived for the sample is 1.88+/-0.24. When we accounted for spectroscopic companions that have been confirmed in the literature and wide companions inferred from Gaia data in addition to the companions we found with interferometry, we obtain multiplicity and companion fractions of 0.88+/-0.06 and 2.31+/-0.27, respectively, for our sample. The number of triple systems increases to the second-most populous type of system when accounting for spectroscopic companions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02300v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. J. Frost, H. Sana, J-B Le Bouquin, H. B. Perets, J. Bodensteiner, A. P. Igoshev, G. Banyard, L. Mahy, A. M\'erand, O. H. Ram\'irez-Agudelo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asteroseismology of the G8 subgiant beta Aquilae with SONG-Tenerife, SONG-Australia and TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00493v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present time-series radial velocities of the G8 subgiant star beta Aql obtained in 2022 and 2023 using SONG-Tenerife and, for the first time, SONG-Australia. We also analyse a sector of TESS photometry that overlapped with the 2022 SONG data. The resulting power spectrum clearly shows solar-like oscillations centred at 430 muHz. The TESS light curve shows the oscillations at lower signal-to-noise, reflecting the fact that photometric measurements are much more affected by the granulation background than are radial velocities. The simultaneous observations in velocity and photometry represent the best such measurements for any star apart from the Sun. They allowed us to measure the ratio between the bolometric photometric amplitude and the velocity amplitude to be 26.6 +/- 3.1 ppm/(m/s). We measured this ratio for the Sun from published SOHO data to be 19.5 +/- 0.7 ppm/(m/s) and, after accounting for the difference in effective temperatures of and the Sun, these values align with expectations. In both the Sun and beta Aql, the photometry-to-velocity ratio appears to be a function of frequency. We also measured the phase shift of the oscillations in beta Aql between SONG and TESS to be -113 +/- 7 deg, which agrees with the value for the Sun and also with a 3-D simulation of a star with similar properties to beta Aql. Importantly for exoplanet searches, we argue that simultaneous photometry can be used to predict the contribution of oscillations to radial velocities. We measured frequencies for 22 oscillation modes in beta Aql and carried out asteroseismic modelling, yielding an excellent fit to the frequencies. We derived accurate values for the mass and age, and were able to place quite strong constraints on the mixing-length parameter. Finally, we show that the oscillation properties of beta Aql are very similar to stars in the open cluster M67.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00493v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202554633</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hans Kjeldsen, Timothy R. Bedding, Yaguang Li, Frank Grundahl, Mads Fredslund Andersen, Duncan J. Wright, Jack Soutter, Robert Wittenmyer, Claudia Reyes, Dennis Stello, Courtney Crawford, Yixiao Zhou, Mathieu Clerte, Pere L. Palle, Sergio Simon-Diaz, Joergen Christensen-Dalsgaard, Rasmus Handberg, Hasse Hansen, Paul Heeren, Jens Jessen-Hansen, Mikkel N. Lund, Mia S. Lundkvist, Karsten Brogaard, Rene Tronsgaard, Jonatan Rudrasingam, Luca Casagrande, Jonathan Horner, Daniel Huber, John Lattanzio, Sarah L. Martell, Simon J. Murphy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid stellar and binary population synthesis with COMPAS: methods paper II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The COMPAS public rapid binary population synthesis code has undergone a number of key improvements since the original COMPAS methods paper (Team COMPAS: Riley et al., 2022) was published. These include more sophisticated and robust treatments of binary interactions: mass transfer physics, common-envelope events, tides and gravitational-wave radiation reaction; and updated prescriptions for stellar evolution, winds and supernovae. The code structure and outputs have also been updated, with a focus on improving resolution without sacrificing computational speed. This paper describes the substantive changes in the code between the previous methods paper and COMPAS v03.22.01.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02316v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Mandel, Jeff Riley, Adam Boesky, Adam Brcek, Ryosuke Hirai, Veome Kapil, Mike Y. M. Lau, JD Merritt, Nicol\'as Rodr\'iguez-Segovia, Isobel Romero-Shaw, Yuzhe Song, Simon Stevenson, Avi Vajpeyi, L. A. C. van Son, Alejandro Vigna-G\'omez, Reinhold Willcox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating Supermassive Pop III Stars On The Main Sequence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08268v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detection of billion-solar-mass supermassive black holes (SMBHs) within the first billion years of cosmic history challenges conventional theories of black hole formation and growth. Simultaneously, recent JWST observations revealing exceptionally high nitrogen-to-oxygen abundance ratios in galaxies at high redshifts raise critical questions about rapid chemical enrichment mechanisms operating in the early universe. Supermassive stars (SMSs) with masses of 1000 to 10000 M$_{\odot}$ are promising candidates to explain these phenomena, but existing models have so far neglected the pivotal role of stellar rotation. Here, we present the first comprehensive evolutionary models of rotating Pop III SMSs computed using the GENEC stellar evolution code, including detailed treatments of rotation-induced chemical mixing, angular momentum transport, and mass loss driven by the $\Omega\Gamma$ limit. We demonstrate that rotation significantly enlarges the convective core and extends stellar lifetimes by up to 20%, with moderate enhancement of mass-loss rates as stars approach critical rotation thresholds. Our results further indicate that the cores of SMSs rotate relatively slowly (below $\sim 200$ km s$^{-1}$), resulting in dimensionless spin parameters $a* &lt; 0.1$ for intermediate-mass black hole (IMBH) remnants that are notably lower than theoretical maximum spins. These findings highlight rotation as a key factor in determining the structural evolution, chemical yields, and black hole spin properties of SMSs, providing critical insights to interpret observational signatures from the high-redshift universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08268v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Devesh Nandal, Ga\"el Buldgen, Daniel J. Whalen, John Regan, Tyrone E. Woods, Jonathan C. Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of non-thermal processes in the quiescent and active millimeter spectrum of a young M dwarf</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19779v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Millimeter (mm) emission from F - M dwarfs (cool stars) primarily traces chromospheric activity, with thermal emission thought to dominate in quiescence. Despite the high chromospheric activity, the quiescent mm spectral fluence (mm-S($\nu$)) of young (&lt; 1 Gyr) M dwarfs (dMs) remain largely unexplored. We present the quiescent mm-S($\nu$) of a young dM, ADLeo, observed around 94 GHz using the Northern Extended Millimetre Array (NOEMA). The observed quiescent mm-S($\nu$) exceeds the thermal flux density from a 1D chromospheric model, constrained by optical-UV spectroscopic data, by up to a factor of 7. This indicates a quasi-steady non-thermal emission powered by supra-thermal electrons unlike in old (&gt; 1 Gyr) cool stars, whose quiescent mm-S($\nu$) generally agree with 1D thermal models. The mm-brightness temperature spectral index ($\alpha_{mm}$; $T_B(\nu)\propto \nu^{- \alpha_{mm}}$) of AD Leo deviates by a factor of 3 from the $\alpha_{mm}$ - $T_{eff}$ scaling law for old sun-like stars (Mohan, A., et al., 2022), while UV Ceti, an older M6V star, follows the trend. Also, we report a double-hump flare with second-scale variability in flux density and spectral index, and a frequency-rising nature with brightness increasing with frequency. The flare resemble certain solar events, but is unlike the second-scale events reported in dMs. The non-thermal flare humps suggest multiple injections of accelerated electrons. The mean flare luminosity (2 - 5 $\times 10^{15} erg s^{-1} Hz^{-1}$) and duration ($18\pm 2$ s) are comparable to flares reported in AU Mic and Proxima Cen, but 100 - 1000 times weaker than the minutes-long dM flares observed by the South Pole Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19779v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ade9bf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ.989(2025)1-20</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Atul Mohan, Peter H. Hauschildt, Birgit Fuhrmeister, Surajit Mondal, Vladimir Airapetian, Sven Wedemeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Robust Detection of Linear Polarization from Metric Solar Emissions: Challenging Established Paradigms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polarimetric radio observations of the Sun can provide rich information about emission mechanisms and the propagation medium. For the past five decades, solar polarimetric studies at low radio frequencies have almost always assumed the absence of linear polarization. This has been based on the expectations from coronal propagation effects. Here we present the first robust evidence of linear polarization from solar emissions at meter wavelengths using simultaneous measurements with two telescopes of very different designs separated by thousands of kilometers - the Murchison Widefield Array and the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope. Both datasets show consistent linear polarization fractions, confirming this detection. Rapid changes in morphology, as well as the fractional linear polarization at small time and frequency spans, further rule out any possibilities of an instrumental origin. Assuming the absence of linear polarization in solar radio emissions can result in incorrect interpretation of solar observations as well as those of other flare stars, which are often guided by learnings from solar studies. This discovery highlights the need for relaxing this assumption, and is essential for precise estimation of polarization signatures, ultimately leading to a better understanding of the plasma conditions in the Sun and other stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05196v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adef0e</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL 988 L73 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Soham Dey, Devojyoti Kansabanik, Divya Oberoi, Surajit Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase II of the LAMOST-Kepler/K2 Survey. II. Time Domain of Medium-resolution Spectroscopic Observations from 2018 to 2023</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19751v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The LAMOST-Kepler/K2 Medium-Resolution Spectroscopic Survey (LK-MRS) conducted time-domain medium-resolution spectroscopic observations of 20 LAMOST plates in the Kepler and K2 fields from 2018 to 2023, a phase designated as LK-MRS-I. A catalog of stellar parameters for a total of 36,588 stars, derived from the spectra collected during these five years, including the effective temperature, the surface gravity, the metallicity, the {\alpha}-element abundance, the radial velocity, and v sin i of the target stars, is released, together with the weighted averages and uncertainties. At S/N = 10, the measurement uncertainties are 120 K, 0.18 dex, 0.13 dex, 0.08 dex, 1.9 km/s, and 4.0 km/s for the above parameters, respectively. Comparisons with the parameters provided by the APOGEE and GALAH surveys validate the effective temperature and surface gravity measurements, showing minor discrepancies in metallicity and {\alpha}-element abundance values. We identified some peculiar star candidates, including 764 metal-poor stars, 174 very metal-poor stars, and 30 high-velocity stars. Moreover, we found 2,333 stars whose radial velocity seems to be variable. Using Kepler/K2 or TESS photometric data, we confirmed 371 periodic variable stars among the radial velocity variable candidates and classified their variability types. LK-MRS-I provides spectroscopic data being useful for studies of the Kepler and K2 fields. The LK-MRS project will continue collecting time-domain medium-resolution spectra for target stars during the third phase of LAMOST surveys, providing data to support further scientific research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19751v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingfeng Qin, Jian-Ning Fu, Weikai Zong, Peter De Cat, Antonio Frasca, Tianqi Cang, Jiangtao Wang, Jianrong Shi, Ali Luo, Haotong Zhang, Hongliang Yan, J. Molenda- \.Zakowicz, R. O. Gray, Jiaxin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt identification of solar wind stream interaction regions from Survey Burst 1 Mode observations of the Radio and Plasma Wave experiment on Solar Orbiter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00517v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Studying stream interaction regions (SIRs), from their inception and the dynamics of their development, can provide insight into solar-terrestrial connections. Some in-situ instruments on the Solar Orbiter (SolO) space mission are designed to measure solar wind (SW) and interplanetary magnetic field parameters along the flight path. These instruments are ideal for studying the dynamics of SIR evolution at heliocentric distances of 0.28-1.0 AU and with changes in heliolatitude of $0^\circ$- $33^\circ$. To address the challenges of promptly identifying SIRs and predicting their arrival time on Earth, we consider using trigger events from the Radio and Plasma Wave (RPW)/SolO instrument, which are transmitted in telemetry data packages. We suggest that multiple activations of the trigger mode (SBM1 mode) in the RPW instrument over an interval of up to four hours may reflect the fine structure of large-scale events in SW. Such events can serve as markers for the spacecraft's location within the SIR. In this regard, the 2023 analysis revealed that multiple activations of the SBM1 trigger mode throughout the day accounted for more than 50$\%$ of the total number of days for which such events were recorded. Of this number, 63$\%$ were events when the trigger algorithm was prompted repeatedly within a time interval of up to four hours. A comparison of the registration times of SBM1 trigger events with the SW parameters obtained from the SWA-PAS and MAG instruments showed that repeated activations of the trigger algorithm occurred at the stream interface surface when a high-speed SW stream and a formed compression region were present.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00517v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/swsc/2025034</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dmytro Chechotkin, Oleksiy Dudnik, Oleksandr Yakovlev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spot-Crossing Variations Confirm a Misaligned Orbit for a Planet Transiting an M Dwarf</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11998v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: TOI-3884~b is an unusual 6.4~R$_\oplus$ planet orbiting an M4 host, whose transits display large and persistent spot-crossing events. We used the \textit{Tierras} Observatory to monitor both the long-term photometric variability of TOI-3884 and changes in the spot-crossing events across multiple transits of the planet. We show that the star rotates with a period of $11.020 \pm 0.015$~days. We simultaneously model the rotational modulation of the star and variations in transit shapes that arise due to rotation of the spot, allowing us to determine the true stellar obliquity, $\psi_\star$. The data are best described by a planet on a misaligned orbit around a highly inclined star ($\psi_\star = {77.4^\circ} ^{+2.3^\circ}_{-2.5^\circ}$; $i_\star = {22.3^\circ}^{+1.8^\circ}_{-1.6^\circ}$) that hosts a large polar starspot ($r_\mathrm{spot} = {31.2^\circ}^{+2.4^\circ}_{-1.9^\circ}$; $\lambda_\mathrm{spot} = {80.5^\circ}\pm1.2^\circ$). Archival photometry from the Zwicky Transient Facility suggests that this polar spot has persisted on TOI-3884 for at least seven years. The TOI-3884 system provides a benchmark for studying the evolution of a polar spot on an M dwarf.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11998v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Tamburo, Samuel W. Yee, Juliana Garc\'ia-Mej\'ia, David Charbonneau, Allyson Bieryla, Karen A. Collins, Avi Shporer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Nuclear Matter with Quenched $g_A$ to Compact-Star Matter with a Signal for Emergent Hidden Scale Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04939v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An ``unorthodox" idea is developed that the long-standing mystery in nuclear physics of the effective axial-current coupling constant in nuclei, $g_A^{\rm eff}\approx 1$, could be interpreted in terms of an emerging hidden scale symmetry in dense compact-star matter. Arguments are presented using an effective field theory anchored on a renormalization-group approach to interacting baryons on the Fermi surface coupled with hidden symmetric heavy mesonic degrees of freedom that enables one to go beyond Weinberg's nuclear effective field theory involving nucleon and pion fields only, referred hereon to as $\chi$EFT$_\pi$. Both hidden local and scale symmetries, the former involving the vector mesons $\rho$ and $\omega$ and the latter the hidden scalar meson, a dilaton $\hat{\sigma}$ (i.e., $f_0(500)$), play the crucial role. Going beyond the density regime applicable to normal nuclear matter $n_0$, the notion of ``hadron-quark continuity HQC)" is brought in via the skyrmion structure of the nucleon argued to be valid in QCD at large $N_c$ limit and the large $N^\prime$ limit of the Grassmannian model $G/H= [O(N^\prime)/O(N^\prime-p) \times O(p)]$ where $N^\prime=4$ and $p=2$ for hidden local symmetry and the IR fixed point in QCD for $N_f \leq 3$ involving ``genuine/QCD-conformal dilaton" for hidden scale symmetry. The connection between the quenched $g_A$ and the sound speed $v^2_{s}/c^2\approx 1/3$ inside dense compact stars could be interpreted as a signal for emergent ``pseudo-conformal" symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04939v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mannque Rho</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
