<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 09:28:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of limited core rejuvenation on the properties of massive contact binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Massive contact binaries are both stellar merger and gravitational wave progenitors, but their evolution is still uncertain. An open problem in the population synthesis of massive contact binaries is the predicted mass ratio distribution. Current simulations evolve quickly to mass ratios close to unity, which is not supported by the sample of observed systems. It has been shown that modifying the near core mixing properties of massive stars can alter the evolution of contact binaries, but it has not been tested on a whole population. Aims. We implement a prescription of the convective core overshooting based on the molecular gradient. The goal of the implementation is to limit the rejuvenation efficiency of the accretor. We aim to investigate the effects of the reduced rejuvenation on the mass ratio distribution of massive contact binaries. Methods. We calculate a grid of 4896 models with the binary-evolution code MESA with our convective overshoot formulation, and we compare the simulations with the known observations of massive contact binaries. Results. We find that by limiting the core rejuvenation through the convective core overshoot, the predicted mass-ratio distribution shifts significantly to values away from unity. This improves the theoretical predictions of the mass ratios of massive contact binaries. Conclusions. The core rejuvenation of the components in massive contact binaries is a key parameter for their predicted mass ratio distribution. Establishing the rejuvenation efficiency with the contact binary population should therefore be possible. The sample size and uncertainties associated to the characterization of contact binaries however prevents us from doing so, and other methods like asteroseismology can place constraints on the rejuvenation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17544v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jelle Vandersnickt, Matthias Fabry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Extremely Hot Pulsating Pre-White Dwarf from OGLE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the blue 18.3-minute variable object discovered in the Galactic disk by the OGLE-III survey and named OGLE-GD-WD-0001 is a pulsating pre-white dwarf of PG 1159 spectral type. With an effective temperature of about 160,000 K it is among the hottest known pulsators being located close to the blue edge of the GW Virginis instability strip. The long-term OGLE observations indicate that the object has a positive period change rate of about $5 \times 10^{-10}$ $s~s^{-1}$ and thus already contracts. There are no traces of a planetary nebula around this star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17577v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Pietrukowicz, K. Werner, M. J. Mroz, M. Ratajczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The arc-shaped radio source at the center of NGC 6334A: Is it a colliding wind region of two young massive stars or the bow shock of a runaway star?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New multi-wavelength Karl G. Jansky VLA observations of CKR02A, the compact radio source in the center of the compact HII region NGC 6334A, are presented. The observations were carried out in five epochs and included the frequency ranges 8.0 - 12.0 GHz (X-band), 18.0 - 26.0 GHz (K-band), and 29.0 - 37.0 GHz (Ka-band). The source is detected and resolved in all the observed epochs and in all bands. The source shows a clear arc-shaped structure consistent with a bow shock. The analysis of the spectral index maps indicates that its spectral index is $\alpha=-0.68\pm0.17$, suggesting that the emission is non-thermal. Two astronomical objects can explain the emission nature and morphology of the source: a colliding wind region of two massive stars or the bow shock of a massive runaway star. However, no massive stars are reported so far in the center of NGC 6334A, though its presence is also suggested by the free-free radio emission of the C-HII region itself. Using ancillary VLA data, we measured a preliminary proper motion of $19\pm6$ mas yr$^{-1}$, equivalent to a velocity of $120\pm40$ km s$^{-1}$. A detailed discussion of the implications of both scenarios is provided. Finally, a list of compact radio sources in the vicinity of NGC 6334A is given and briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17588v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanessa Yanza, Sergio A. Dzib, Aina Palau, Luis F. Rodr\'iguez, Josep M. Masqu\'e, Pedro R. Rivera-Ortiz, Sac-Nict\'e X. Medina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the near-core rotation frequency of 2,497 intermediate-mass stars from their dominant gravito-inertial mode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We combined Gaia DR3 and TESS photometric light curves to estimate the internal physical properties of 2,497 gravity-mode pulsators. We relied on asteroseismic properties of Kepler $\gamma\,$Dor and SPB stars to derive the near-core rotation frequency, $f_{\rm rot}$, of the Gaia-discovered pulsators from their dominant prograde dipole gravito-inertial pulsation mode. We offer a recipe based on linear regression to deduce $f_{\rm rot}$ from the dominant gravito-inertial mode frequency. It is applicable to prograde dipole modes with an amplitude above 4mmag and occurring in the sub-inertial regime. By applying it to the 2,497 pulsators, we have increased the sample of intermediate-mass dwarfs with such an asteroseismic observable by a factor of 4. We used the estimate of $f_{\rm rot}$ to deduce spin parameters between 2 and 6, while the sample's near-core rotation rates range from 0.7% to 25% of the critical Keplerian rate. We used $f_{\rm rot}$, along with the Gaia effective temperature and luminosity to deduce the (convective core) mass, radius, and evolutionary stage from grid modelling based on rotating stellar models. We derived a decline of $f_{\rm rot}$ with a factor of 2 during the main-sequence evolution for this population of field stars, which covers a mass range from 1.3M$_\odot$ to 7M$_\odot$. We found observational evidence for an increase in the radial order of excited gravity modes as the stars evolve. For 307 pulsators, we derived an upper limit of the radial differential rotation between the convective core boundary and the surface from Gaia's vbroad measurement and found values up to 5.4. Our recipe for the near-core rotation frequency from the dominant gravito-inertial mode detected in the independent Gaia and TESS light curves is easy to use, facilitates applications to large samples, and allows to map their angular momentum and evolutionary stage in the Milky Way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conny Aerts, Timothy Van Reeth, Joey S. G. Mombarg, Daniel Hey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for new Galactic Wolf-Rayet stars using Gaia DR3. I. Candidate selection and the follow-up of the bright sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gaia DR3, released in June 2022, included low-resolution XP spectra that have been used for the classification of various types of emission-line objects through machine-learning techniques. The Gaia Extended Stellar Parametrizer for Emission-Line Stars (ESP-ELS) algorithm identified 565 sources as potential Wolf-Rayet (WR) stars. Over half of them were already known as WR stars in the Milky Way and Magellanic Clouds. This study aimed to utilize Gaia DR3 data to identify new Galactic WR stars. We extracted all sources classified as WC or WN type stars by the ESP-ELS algorithm from the Gaia catalog. By applying judicious 2MASS color selection criteria, leveraging Gaia H$\alpha$ measurements, and filtering out objects already cataloged in various databases, we selected 37 bright candidates ($G \leq $ 16 mag) and 22 faint candidates ($G &gt; $ 16 mag). Spectroscopic follow-up observations of these candidates were conducted using the 2SPOT facilities in Chile and France, as well as 1-m C2PU's Epsilon telescope at the Calern Observatory. This paper focuses on the brighter sample. Among the 37 targets, we confirmed 17 and 16 new Galactic WC and WN type WR stars, respectively. Three of them were recently reported as new WR stars in an independent study. The Gaia mission provides a valuable resource for uncovering WR stars missed in earlier surveys. While this work concentrated on a relatively small starting sample provided by the ESP-ELS algorithm, our findings highlight the potential for refining selection criteria to identify additional candidates not included in the outputs of the algorithm. Furthermore, the observation program underscores the utility of small telescopes in acquiring initial spectral data for sources with magnitudes up to $G \sim 16$ mag.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17695v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lionel Mulato, Jaroslav Merc, St\'ephane Charbonnel, Olivier Garde, Pascal Le D\^u, Thomas Petit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detectability of Solar Rotation Period Across Various Wavelengths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The light curves of old G-dwarfs obtained in the visible and near-infrared wavelength ranges are highly irregular. This significantly complicates the detectability of the rotation periods of stars similar to the Sun in large photometric surveys, such as Kepler and TESS. In this study, we show that light curves collected in the ultraviolet wavelength range are much more suitable for measuring rotation periods. Motivated by the observation that the Sun's rotational period is clearly discernible in the UV part of the spectrum, we study the wavelength dependence of the rotational period detectability. We employ the Spectral and Total Solar Irradiance Reconstructions model, SATIRE-S, to characterize the detectability of the solar rotation period across various wavelengths using the autocorrelation technique. We find that at wavelengths above 400 nm, the probability of detecting the rotation period of the Sun observed at a random phase of its activity cycle is approximately 20\%. The probability increases to 80\% at wavelengths shorter than 400 nm. These findings underscore the importance of ultraviolet stellar photometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17719v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adb0b3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Valeriy Vasilyev, Timo Reinhold, Alexander I. Shapiro, Theodosios Chatzistergos, Natalie Krivova, Sami K. Solanki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erosion of a dense molecular core by a strong outflow from a massive protostar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array Band 3 observations of N$_2$H$^+$ (1-0) and CH$_3$CN (5-4), as well as Band 7 observations of the H$_2$CO molecular line emissions from the protostellar system GGD 27-MM2(E). Through position-velocity diagrams along and across the outflow axis, we study the kinematics and structure of the outflow. We also fit extracted spectra of the CH$_3$CN emission to obtain the physical conditions of the gas. We use the results to discuss the impact of the outflow on its surroundings. We find that N$_2$H$^+$ emission traces a dense molecular cloud surrounding GGD 27-MM2(E). We estimate that the mass of this cloud is $\sim$13.3-26.5 M$_\odot$. The molecular cloud contains an internal cavity aligned with the H$_2$CO-traced molecular outflow. The outflow, also traced by $\mathrm{CH_3 CN}$, shows evidence of a collision with a molecular core (MC), as indicated by the distinctive increases in the distinct physical properties of the gas such as excitation temperature, column density, line width, and velocity. This collision results in an X-shape structure in the northern part of the outflow around the position of the MC, which produces spray-shocked material downstream in the north of MC as observed in position-velocity diagrams both along and across of the outflow axis. The outflow has a mass of 1.7-2.1 M$_\odot$, a momentum of 7.8-10.1 M$_\odot$ km s$^{-1}$, a kinetic energy of 5.0-6.6$\times 10^{44}$ erg, and a mass loss rate of 4.9--6.0$\times10^{-4}$ M$_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$. The molecular outflow from GGD 27-MM2(E) significantly perturbs and erodes its parent cloud, compressing the gas of sources such as MC and ALMA 12. The feedback from this powerful protostellar outflow contributes to maintain the turbulence in the surrounding area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17786v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. L\'opez-V\'azquez, M. Fern\'andez-L\'opez, J. M. Girart, S. Curiel, R. Estalella, G. Busquet, Luis A. Zapata, Chin-Fei Lee, Roberto Galv\'an-Madrid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Compressible Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations of Solar Convection Zones with CHORUS++</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17805v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The objective of this study is to develop a fully compressible magnetohydrodynamic solver for fast simulations of the global dynamo of the Sun using unstructured grids and GPUs. Accurate modeling of the Sun's convective layers is vital to predicting the Sun's behavior, including the solar dynamo and sunspot cycles. Currently, there are many efficient codes capable of conducting these large simulations; however, many assume an anealastic density distribution. The anelastic assumption is capable of producing accurate results for low mach numbers; however, it fails in regions with a higher mach number and a fully compressible flow must be considered. To avoid these issues, Wang et al. [1] created a Compressible High-ORder Unstructured Spectral difference (CHORUS) code for simulating fluid dynamics inside stars and planets. CHORUS++ augmented the CHORUS code to adopt a higher degree of polynomials by using cubed-sphere meshing and transfinite mapping to perform simulations on unstructured grids [2]. Recently, CHORUS++ was further developed for parallel magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) solutions on GPUs at Clarkson University. In this study the solar benchmark problems presented by Chen et al. [2] are extended to unsteady solar dynamo problems, with two different density scale heights. The CHORUS-MHD code is further accelerated by multiple GPUs and used to successfully solve these solar dynamo benchmark problems.
  [1] Wang, J., Liang, C., and Miesch, M. S., "A Compressible High-Order Unstructured Spectral Difference Code for Stratified Convection in Rotating Spherical Shells," Journal of Computational Physics, Vol. 290, 2015, pp. 90-111.
  [2] Chen, K., Liang, C., and Wan, M., "Arbitrarily high-order accurate simulations of compressible rotationally constrained convection using a transfinite mapping on cubed-sphere grids," Physics of Fluids, Vol. 35, 2023, p. 086120.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17805v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Paoli, Chunlei Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial dependence of ion fluences in the 2023 July 17 SEP event from Parker Solar Probe to STEREO and ACE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the latter moments of 17 July 2023, the solar active region 13363, near the southwestern face of the Sun, was undergoing considerable evolution, which resulted in a significant solar energetic particle (SEP) event measured by Parker Solar Probe's Integrated Science Investigation of the Sun (ISOIS) and near-Earth spacecraft. Remote observations from GOES and CHASE captured two M5.0+ solar flares that peaked at 23:34 and 00:06 UT from the source region. In tandem, STEREO COR2 first recorded a small, narrow coronal mass ejection (CME) emerging at 22:54 UT and then saw a major halo CME emerge at 23:43 UT with a bright, rapidly expanding core and CME-driven magnetic shock with an estimated speed of $\sim$1400 $kms^{-1}$. Parker Solar Probe was positioned at 0.65 au, near-perfectly on the nominal Parker spiral magnetic field line which connected Earth and the active region for a 537 $kms^{-1}$ ambient solar wind speed at L1. This fortuitous alignment provided the opportunity to examine how the SEP velocity dispersion, energy spectra, elemental composition, and fluence varied from 0.65 to 1 au along a shared magnetic connection to the Sun. We find a strong radial gradient, which is best characterized for H and He as $r^{-4.0}$ and most surprisingly is stronger for O and Fe which is better described by $r^{-5.7}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17806v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adadf7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>G. D. Muro, C. M. S Cohen, Z. Xu, R. A. Leske, E. R. Christian, A. C. Cummings, G. De Nolfo, M. I. Desai, F. Fraschetti, J. Giacalone, A. Labrador, D. J. McComas, J. G. Mitchell, D. G. Mitchell, J. Rankin, N. A. Schwadron, M. Shen, M. E. Wiedenbeck, S. D. Bale, O. Romeo, A. Vourlidas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observed Dispersive Properties of the Slow Magnetoacoustic Waves Propagating in Coronal Fan Loops above Sunspots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recurrent and propagating intensity perturbations are frequently observed in extreme ultraviolet (EUV) channels along coronal fan loops above sunspots, and these perturbations are suggested to be slow magnetoacoustic waves. Numerous studies have been conducted to investigate their propagation speeds, damping, and excitation sources; however, there have been limited observational analyses on whether these waves are dispersive despite some theoretical studies. In this study, we apply cross-correlation analysis in the Fourier domain on slow magnetoacoustic waves using three different datasets: EUV intensity observed by SDO/AIA, differential emission measure (DEM) temperature maps, and Doppler velocities from Hinode/EIS spectrometer observations. The apparent phase velocities of the waves, which are the plane-of-sky component of the waves' phase velocities, are derived as functions of frequency for all the three datasets. It is found that the phase velocities show clear frequency dependency, with a general trend of increase with frequency, ranging from approximately 30 km/s around 3 mHz to about 80 km/s around 10 mHz. The frequency dependency of the phase velocities demonstrates that the slow magnetoacoustic waves in the coronal loops are dispersive. The dispersiveness of these waves can provide a useful tool for the diagnosis of physical conditions inside the coronal loops along which these waves travel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17870v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junwei Zhao, Tongjiang Wang, Ruizhu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The orbital period of the long-period and colliding-wind binary WR 146 from radio interferometry of the shock cone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the first measurement of the orbital period of a long-period colliding-wind binary (CWB) system WR 146, derived by tracing the rotational morphology of its wind-colliding region (WCR) and the relative orientation of the two binary components. This result is based on our imaging observations using the Very Long Baseline Array (VLBA) and the European Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) Network (EVN), combined with archival data from VLBA, EVN, the Very Large Array (VLA), the enhanced Multi-Element Radio-Linked Interferometer Network (eMERLIN) arrays, and optical images from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST). We evaluated two methods for determining the binary's orbital period based on the images of the WCR: (I) fitting the shock cone of the WCR and (II) stacking images using the cross-correlation function. Using these techniques, we find orbital period estimates of 810+120-90 years from method I and 1120+540-270 years from method II, both of which support a long orbital period of approximately 1,000 years. Furthermore, we analyzed archival spectral data of WR 146 to estimate the stellar wind velocities of the binary components, finding no significant orbital phase lag between the binary orientation and the WCR rotation. We also estimate the range of the binary's mass using the currently measured parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17930v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiming Wen, Bo Zhang, Shuangjing Xu, Yan Sun, Xiaofeng Mai, Jingdong Zhang, Lang Cui, Xiaofeng Li, Helge Todt, Xi Yan, Pengfei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Analyses of Solar Active Region in SDO/HMI Magnetograms detected by Unsupervised Machine Learning Method DSARD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar active regions (ARs) are the places hosting the majority of solar eruptions. Studying the evolution and morphological features of ARs is not only of great significance to the understanding of the physical mechanisms of solar eruptions, but also beneficial for the hazardous space weather forecast. An automated DBSCAN-based Solar Active Regions Detection (DSARD) method for solar ARs observed in magnetograms is developed in this work, which is based on an unsupervised machine learning algorithm called Density-Based Spatial Clustering of Applications with Noise (DBSCAN). The method is then employed to identify ARs on the magnetograms observed by the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) onboard Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) during solar cycle 24 and the rising phase of solar cycle 25. The distributions of the number, area, magnetic flux, and the tilt angle of bipolar of ARs in latitudes and time intervals during solar cycle 24, as well as the butterfly diagram and drift velocities are obtained. Most of these statistical results based on our method are in agreement with previous studies, which also guarantees the validity of the method. In particular, the dipole tilt angles in ARs in solar cycle 24 and the rising phase of solar cycle 25 are analyzed which reveal that 13% and 16% of ARs, respectively, violate Hale's law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17990v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruishuo Chen, Wutong Lu, Qi Hao, Yifan Meng, Pengfei Chen, Chenxi Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Pulsating Variables and Eclipsing Binaries in NGC 2126 using Ground and Space-based Photometry, Astrometry, Spectroscopy and Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulsating variables are prevalent in the classical {\delta} Scuti instability strip of intermediate-age open star clusters. The cluster membership of these stars facilitates a comparative analysis of their evolution in analogous environments. In this study, we integrate ground-based observations, TESS Full Frame Images (FFIs), and Gaia DR3 data to investigate variable stars in the intermediate-age open star cluster NGC 2126. We performed ground-based time-series observations of NGC 2126 to identify variable stars within its vicinity. Next, we determined the membership of these stars using parallax and the proper motions from Gaia DR3 archive. Then, we searched the TESS Full Frame Images (FFIs) for counterparts to the variables identified above and performed their frequency analysis and classification. Finally, we modeled the light curves (LCs) of detected eclipsing binaries (EBs), including V551 Aur, which has a pulsating component. We found 25 members and 85 field variable stars. In TESS FFIs, we found LCs for 11 known variables and a new rotational variable. We determined that the pulsating EB V551 Aur is a member of the cluster. The low- and medium-resolution spectra revealed the line profile variation and the basic parameters for the star, respectively. Simultaneous modeling of the eclipses and the embedded pulsations resulted in improved orbital parameters for the binary system. We also report the determination of orbital parameters for the previously uncharacterized EB system UCAC4 700-043174.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18112v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athul Dileep (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences, M.J.P. Rohilkhand University), Santosh Joshi (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Sneh Lata (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Patricia Lampens (Royal Observatory of Belgium), Peter De Cat (Royal Observatory of Belgium), Sebastian Z\'u\~niga-Fern\'andez (Universit\'e de Li\`ege), David Mkrtichian (National Astronomical Research Institute of Thailand), Pramod Kumar S (Indian Institute of Astrophysics), Mrinmoy Sarkar (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Alaxender Panchal (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences, Physical Research Laboratory), Yogesh C. Joshi (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Rishi C. (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Neelam Panwar (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Arjav Jain (Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences), Neeraj Rathore (Bareilly College)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogeneous search for spot transits in Kepler and TESS photometry of K $-$ M-type main-sequence stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18129v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Late-type stars are known to host numerous exoplanets, and their photometric variability, primarily caused by rotational modulation, provides a unique opportunity to study starspots. As exoplanets transit in front of their host stars, they may occult darker, spotted regions on the stellar surfaces. The monitoring of starspots from planetary transits, known as transit mapping, offers a possibility to detect small dark regions on magnetically active, late-type stars. These spots may be so small that they would be undetectable to other methods used to reconstruct stellar magnetic activity. We describe a Bayesian analysis framework on the transit light curves of planets orbiting K- and M-type main-sequence stars in search for spot occultation event candidates. We present a systematic analysis of high-precision, high-cadence light curves from Kepler and TESS to detect and characterise starspots during exoplanetary transits. According to our tests, the set of criteria applied in the analysis is robust and not prone to false positives. Our sample comprises K- and M-dwarfs hosting transiting exoplanets observed by the Kepler or TESS space telescopes at a high cadence, totalling 99 planets meeting our selection criteria. After analysing 3273 transit light curves from 99 planets, we find 105 candidates for starspot occultation events by six planets. We report new spot occultation candidates for the K-dwarfs HD 189733 and TOI-1268. The identified dark regions have a lower limit for radii between 1.6 degrees and 29.5 degrees and contrasts up to 0.69. We estimate a spot detection frequency of 3.7% and 4.2% for K- and M-dwarfs by TESS, and 37.5% for K-dwarfs by Kepler.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18129v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'as Haris, Mikko Tuomi, Thomas Hackman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Kinetic Model of Solar Wind Acceleration Driven by Ambipolar Electric Potential and Velocity-Space Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parker Solar Probe (PSP) observations revealed that most of the solar wind acceleration occurs very close to the Sun. This acceleration is partly due to the global electric potential originating from the mass disparity between electrons and protons, coupled with the constraints of charge quasi-neutrality and zero-current conditions in the solar wind plasma. However, the exact mechanism that accounts for the remaining acceleration is still not identified. We aim to provide a framework incorporating the electric field-driven component of the acceleration while also introducing an additional acceleration mechanism via velocity-space diffusion of the particles. This will help us determine the extent of extra acceleration, beyond the electric field-driven component, required to fully reproduce the acceleration of the solar wind in theoretical models. We modified an existing kinetic exospheric model to account for the unexplained solar wind acceleration by including velocity-space diffusion. We compared the electric field derived from the sunward deficit of velocity distribution functions observed by PSP between 13.3 and 50 solar radii ($R_s$) with the electric field found self-consistently by the kinetic exospheric model. The effect of velocity-space diffusion is found to reduce the temperature anisotropy and impact the solar wind acceleration while maintaining the electric potential unchanged. Our approach allows for adjusting the diffusion to effectively reduce or increase the solar wind acceleration, providing a way to account for the unexplained acceleration within the kinetic exospheric framework. It is found that, even without diffusion, the model can reproduce the anticorrelation between the electric potential and the solar wind terminal velocity found by PSP. This suggests that the electric potential might still be of major importance in explaining the solar wind acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18132v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilien P\'eters de Bonhome, Viviane Pierrard, Fabio Bacchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variable stars in Galactic globular clusters II. Population II Cepheids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We identified a sample of 88 bona fide Population II Cepheids (henceforth referred to as Cepheids) and 44 candidates in Galactic globular clusters (GCs). Seventy-eight of the Cepheids in the sample align within $2\,\sigma$ of the period-luminosity relation for Milky Way Type II Cepheids (T2CEPs). Nine align with the period-luminosity relation for fundamental-mode anomalous Cepheids (ACEPs), and only one (BL Bo\"otis) follows the relation for first-overtone ACEPs, as determined from observations of ACEPs in the Large Magellanic Cloud. For sources in common between our catalog and the OGLE catalog, the classification agrees in 94% of cases. In comparison, for sources shared between the Gaia Specific Object Study (SOS) and OGLE, the agreement is 74%. In the dense environments of GCs, our analysis shows that the completeness of the Gaia catalogs for Cepheids is 64% for the SOS and 74% for the classifier of variable stars. We determined the red and blue edges of the instability strip for T2CEPs using linear MESA-RSP models. We find that the best-fit models, with $M = 0.6\,{\rm M}_\odot$ and Z = 0.0003, are able to fit $90%$ of the stars in our sample. This percentage is the same for helium abundances $Y = 0.220$ and $0.245$. Higher values of $Y$ lower this percentage, and the same effect is observed with lower values of $Z$. In the future, combining the sample of T2CEPs with the precise parallaxes obtained from GCs will strengthen the geometric calibration of a distance ladder based on Population II stars. This will be useful for determining distances within the Milky Way and for cross-checking distances to Local Group galaxies determined through other methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18158v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Cruz Reyes, Richard I. Anderson, Susmita Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLARE: A Framework for Stellar Flare Forecasting using Stellar Physical Properties and Historical Records</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18218v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stellar flare events are critical observational samples for astronomical research; however, recorded flare events remain limited. Stellar flare forecasting can provide additional flare event samples to support research efforts. Despite this potential, no specialized models for stellar flare forecasting have been proposed to date. In this paper, we present extensive experimental evidence demonstrating that both stellar physical properties and historical flare records are valuable inputs for flare forecasting tasks. We then introduce FLARE (Forecasting Light-curve-based Astronomical Records via features Ensemble), the first-of-its-kind large model specifically designed for stellar flare forecasting. FLARE integrates stellar physical properties and historical flare records through a novel Soft Prompt Module and Residual Record Fusion Module. Our experiments on the publicly available Kepler light curve dataset demonstrate that FLARE achieves superior performance compared to other methods across all evaluation metrics. Finally, we validate the forecast capability of our model through a comprehensive case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18218v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingke Zhu, Xiaoxiao Wang, Minghui Jia, Yihan Tao, Xiao Kong, Ali Luo, Yingying Chen, Ming Tang, Jinqiao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helical flows along coronal loops following the launch of a coronal mass ejection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solar flares and coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are manifestations of energy release in the solar atmosphere, which can be accompanied by dynamic mass motions and waves in the surrounding atmosphere. Here, we present observations of plasma moving in a helical trajectory along a set of coronal loops formed following the eruption of a CME on 2024 May 14. This helical motion was observed in extreme ultraviolet (EUV) images from the Solar Dynamic Observatory (SDO), which provides new insights into plasma properties in a set of post-eruption coronal loops. We utilize images from the SDO Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) instrument to track the helical motion of plasma and to characterize its speed, acceleration, and physical properties. Additionally, we explore the evolution of the plasma density and temperature along the helical structure using the differential emission measure technique. The helical structure was visible in AIA for approximately 22 minutes, having a diameter of 22 Mm, and a total trajectory of nearly 184 Mm. Analysis of the AIA observations reveals that the plasma flow along this helical coronal loop exhibits speeds of 77-384 km s$^{-1}$ and temperatures ranging from 3.46 to 10.2 MK. Additionally, the densities were estimated to be between 4.3.106 and 1.55.107 cm-3, with an estimated magnetic field strength of 0.05-0.3 G. Following the launch of a CME, we find clear evidence for impulsive heating and expansion of plasma that travels a helical trajectory along a set of post-eruption loops. These observations provide an insight into impulsive plasma flows along coronal loops and indeed the topology of coronal loops.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18271v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Nedal, David M. Long, Catherine Cuddy, Lidia Van Driel-Gesztelyi, Peter T. Gallagher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Effects of Atmospheric Stratification on Coronal Active Region Field Modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18358v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the evolution of the complex magnetic fields found in solar active regions is an active area of research. There are numerous models for such fields which range in their complexity due to the number of known physical effects included in them, the one common factor being they all extrapolate the field up from the photosphere. In this study we focus on the fact that, above the photosphere, and below the corona, lies the relatively cool and dense chromosphere -- which is often neglected in coronal models due to it being comparatively thin and difficult hard to model. We isolate and examine the effect including this boundary layer has on a 2.5D class of driven MHD models of an active region eruption. We find that it can result in significant changes to the dynamics of an erupting field far higher in the atmosphere than the chromosphere itself, generally delaying eruption and increasing the magnetic energy released in each eruption. We also test whether these effects can be approximated using a variation of the more computationally efficient magnetofrictional model, finding a number of simple adaptations of the standard magnetofrictional model capture the effect the chromospheric stratification well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18358v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Rice, Christopher Prior</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OGLE-2002-BLG-360: a dusty anomaly among red nova remnants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: OGLE-2002-BLG-360 is an example of a Galactic red nova, the aftermath of a non-compact stellar merger. The dusty nature of the circumstellar environment makes observations of this particular source difficult, meaning the properties of the central star and its surrounding environment are poorly understood. We aim to establish the parameters of the merger remnant, as well as of the dusty environment and its structure. We attempt to establish similarities with other Galactic red novae and try to understand how such an environment has been formed. We use optical, infrared, and sub-millimetre observations to construct the spectral energy distribution (SED) between 2 um and 1.27 mm for an epoch 15-21 years after the red nova eruption. We use various radiative transfer codes to model the SED and retrieve the physical properties of both the central star and the surrounding dust. We show that the SED is best replicated by a spherically symmetric model consisting of an M-type supergiant surrounded by 0.012 Msun of dust concentrated within two spherical shells. The dust extends out to a maximum distance of 9500 AU from the central source, whilst the inner shell extends out to 1000 AU. The dust composition is dominated by iron grains (58%), but also contains olivine silicates (25%) and alumina dust (17%), which are both required to reproduce the profile of the observed 10 um absorption feature. The inner shell likely originates from merger and post-merger ejecta, whilst the outer shell consists of material lost much earlier, before the merger event occurred. Evolution of the SED indicates continued dust formation within the expanding inner shell, which may be analogous to winds of red supergiants. The object is extremely dusty compared to other red nova remnants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18365v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Steinmetz, T. Kami\'nski, C. Melis, M. Gromadzki, K. Menten, K. Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Birth of a Major Coronal Mass Ejection with Intricate Magnetic Structure from Multiple Active Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are the eruptions of magnetised plasma from the Sun and are considered the main driver of adverse space weather events. Hence, undrstanding its formation process, particularly the magnetic topology, is critical for accurate space weather prediction. Here, based on imaging observations and three-dimensional (3D) data-constrained thermodynamic magnetohydrodynamical (MHD) simulation in spherical coordinates, we exhibit the birth of a CME with intricate magnetic structure from multiple active regions (ARs) due to 3D magnetic reconnection. It is observed as a coronal jet between active regions, accompanied by the back-flowing of filament materials along the jet spine after the passage of the eruptive filament. This jet connects two dimming regions within different active regions. This is an observational proxy of 3D magnetic reconnection between the CME flux rope and the null-point magnetic field lines crossing active regions. Hereafter, the thermodynamic data-constrained MHD simulation successfully reproduces the observed jet and the reconnection process that flux ropes partake in, leading to a CME flux rope with a complex magnetic structure distinct from its progenitor. The generality of this scenario is then validated by data-inspired MHD simulations in a simple multipolar magnetic configuration. This work demonstrates the role of multiple active regions in forming CMEs with intricate magnetic structures. On the one hand, a non-coherent flux rope where not all twisted magnetic field lines wind around one common axis is naturally formed. On the other hand, our findings suggest that the topology of a real CME flux rope may not be solely determined by a single active region, particularly during periods of solar maximum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18367v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinhan Guo, Y. W. Ni, B. Schmieder, Y. Guo, C. Xia, P. Devi, R. Chandra, S. Poedts, R. Joshi, Y. H. Zhou, H. T. Li, P. F. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Does a Protostar Form by Magnetized Gravitational Collapse?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17530v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Star formation through the dynamical magnetized collapse remains an active area of astrophysical research. We carry out a comprehensive exploration on the magnetized gravitational collapse of a non-rotating self-gravitating initially spherically symmetric prestellar cloud core using two-dimensional nonideal magnetohydrodynamic simulations incorporating ambipolar diffusion and Ohmic dissipation. Our study encompasses a broader range of equations of state (EOSs) in the form of $P(\rho) \propto \rho^{\Gamma}$, with the aim of constraining the choice of EOSs for allowing star formation. Our results reveal that the collapse with a $\Gamma$ no stiffer than $4/3$, complemented by magnetized virial theorem, allows the dynamical contraction of the prestellar core to happen continuously where a central point mass forms and steadily builds up its mass from the infalling envelope, with a mass accretion rate of a scale of the order of $c_{\rm s}^3/G$. The choice of an isothermal EOS most naturally facilitates the collapse as a magnetic analog of the inside-out collapse. In addition to that, our study exhibits that the nonisothermal magnetized collapse models with a $\Gamma$ no stiffer than 4/3 qualitatively demonstrate similar infall features to those of an isothermal EOS. Furthermore, the collapse models with a $\Gamma$ stiffer than $4/3$ fail to ensure the sufficient cooling to allow the direct mass growth of the central point mass, thus delaying the infall. Our work can offer deeper insights in understanding the significance of EOSs on the magnetized gravitational collapse, enabling star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17530v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indrani Das, Hsien Shang, Ruben Krasnopolsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining the Density of the Sun with Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17546v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discovery of solar neutrinos confirmed that the inner workings of the Sun generally match our theoretical understanding of the fusion process. Solar neutrinos have also played a role in discovering that neutrinos have mass and that they oscillate. We combine the latest solar neutrino data along with other oscillation data from reactors to determine the Sun's density profile. We derive constraints given the current data and show the anticipated improvements with more reactor neutrino data from JUNO constraining the true oscillation parameters and more solar neutrino data from DUNE which should provide a crucial measurement of $hep$ neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17546v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter B. Denton, Charles Gourley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing the Outer Edge of the Infant Type Ia Supernova 2024epr in the Optical and Near Infrared</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present optical-to-near infrared (NIR) photometry and spectroscopy of the Type Ia supernova (SN Ia) 2024epr, including NIR spectra observed within two days of first light. The early-time optical spectra show strong, high-velocity Ca and Si features near rarely-observed velocities at $\sim$0.1$c$, and the NIR spectra show a \CI\ "knee." Despite these high-velocity features at early times, SN~2024epr evolves into a normal SN Ia, albeit with stronger peak-light Ca absorption than other SNe Ia with the same light curve shape. Although we infer a normal decline rate, $\Delta m_{15}(B)=1.09\pm0.12$ mag, from the light-curve rise, SN 2024epr is a Branch "cool" object and has red early-time colors ($g-r\approx0.15$ mag at $-10$ days). The high velocities point to a density enhancement in the outer layers of the explosion, but thick-shell He-detonation models do not match the smoothly rising light curve or lack of He in our early-time NIR spectra. No current models (e.g., delayed detonation or thin He shell double detonation) appear to reproduce all of the observed properties. Such constraints are only possible for SN 2024epr from the earliest optical and NIR observations, highlighting their importance for constraining SN Ia models. Finally, we find several other SNe Ia with intermediate mass elements at $\sim$30\,000 km s$^{-1}$ within days after the explosion that evolve into otherwise normal SNe Ia at peak light, suggesting the early-time spectra of SNe Ia may hide a broad diversity of observational characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17556v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. B. Hoogendam, D. O. Jones, C. Ashall, B. J. Shappee, R. J. Foley, M. A. Tucker, M. E. Huber, K. Auchettl, D. D. Desai, A. Do, J. T. Hinkle, S. Romagnoli, J. Shi, A. Syncatto, C. R. Angus, K. C. Chambers, D. A. Coulter, K. W. Davis, T. de Boer, A. Gagliano, M. Kong, C. -C. Lin, T. B. Lowe, E. A. Magnier, P. Minguez, Y. -C. Pan, K. C. Patra, S. A. Severson, K. Taggart, A. R. Wasserman, S. K. Yadavalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing Machine Learning to Predict Host Stars and the Key Elemental Abundances of Small Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stars and their associated planets originate from the same cloud of gas and dust, making a star's elemental composition a valuable indicator for indirectly studying planetary compositions. While the connection between a star's iron (Fe) abundance and the presence of giant exoplanets is established (e.g. Gonzalez 1997; Fischer &amp; Valenti 2005), the relationship with small planets remains unclear. The elements Mg, Si, and Fe are important in forming small planets. Employing machine learning algorithms like XGBoost, trained on the abundances (e.g., the Hypatia Catalog, Hinkel et al. 2014) of known exoplanet-hosting stars (NASA Exoplanet Archive), allows us to determine significant "features" (abundances or molar ratios) that may indicate the presence of small planets. We test on three groups of exoplanets: (a) all small, R$_{P}$ $&lt;$ 3.5 $R_{\oplus}$, (b) sub-Neptunes, 2.0 $R_{\oplus}$ $&lt;$ R$_{P}$ $&lt;$ 3.5 $R_{\oplus}$, and (c) super-Earths, 1.0 $R_{\oplus}$ $&lt;$ R$_{P}$ $&lt;$ 2.0 $R_{\oplus}$ -- each subdivided into 7 ensembles to test different combinations of features. We created a list of stars with $\geq90\%$ probability of hosting small planets across all ensembles and experiments ("overlap stars"). We found abundance trends for stars hosting small planets, possibly indicating star-planet chemical interplay during formation. We also found that Na and V are key features regardless of planetary radii. We expect our results to underscore the importance of elements in exoplanet formation and machine learning's role in target selection for future NASA missions: e.g., the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope (NGRST), Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) -- all of which are aimed at small planet detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17563v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Am\'ilcar R. Torres-Quijano, Natalie R. Hinkel, Caleb H. Wheeler III, Patrick A. Young, Luan Ghezzi, Augusto P. Baldo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematics of metallicity populations in Omega Centauri using Gaia Focused Product Release and Hubble Space Telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Context. Omega Cen is the largest known globular cluster in the Milky Way. It is also quite a complex object with a large metallicity spread and multiple stellar populations. Despite a number of studies over the past several decades, the series of events that led to the formation of this cluster is still poorly understood. One of its peculiarities is the presence of a metal-rich population which does not show the phenomenon of light-element anti-correlations (C-N, Na-O, Mg-Al), a trait that is considered as characteristic of Galactic Globular Clusters, and is in fact present among more metal-poor Omega Cen stars, leading to speculations that such anomalous population was accreted by the cluster. In this paper, we aim at investigating the kinematics of Omega Cen populations to gain insight on the formation scenario of the cluster. Using the newly released Gaia FPR and DR3 catalogue, we conducted a detailed kinematical analysis of cluster members within Omega Cen. The cluster members were divided into four metallicity populations and their mean proper motion in radial and tangential components were compared with each other. We also performed Gaussian Mixture Model fitting on the metallicity distribution to estimate the number of populations within our sample and an independent analysis of the HST catalogue as confirmation. The mean proper motions (mu_r and mu_t) of the metallicity populations do not show any significant differences. It is also not dependent on the approach chosen to determine the number of metallicity populations. We do find clear signature of rotation in all of the populations (including the metal-rich) with similar velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17755v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nagaraj Vernekar, Sara Lucatello, Pete Kuzma, Lorenzo Spina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The First Chemical Census the Milky Way's Nuclear Star Cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An important step in understanding the formation and evolution of the Nuclear Star Cluster (NSC) is to investigate its chemistry and chemical evolution. Additionally, exploring the relationship of the NSC to the other structures in the Galactic Center and the Milky Way disks is of great interest. Extreme optical extinction has previously prevented optical studies, but near-IR high-resolution spectroscopy is now possible. Here, we present a detailed chemical abundance analysis of 19 elements - more than four times as many as previously published - for 9 stars in the NSC of the Milky Way, observed with the IGRINS spectrometer on the Gemini South telescope. This study provides new, crucial observational evidence to shed light on the origin of the NSC. We demonstrate that it is possible to probe a variety of nucleosynthetic channels, reflecting different chemical evolution timescales. Our findings reveal that the NSC trends for the elements F, Mg, Al, Si, S, K, Ca, Ti, Cr, Mn, Co, Ni, Cu, and Zn, as well as the s-process elements Ba, Ce, Nd, and Yb, generally follow the inner bulge trends within uncertainties. This suggests a likely shared evolutionary history and our results indicate that the NSC population is consistent with the chemical sequence observed in the inner Galaxy (the inner-disk sequence). However, we identify a significant and unexplained difference in the form of higher Na abundances in the NSC compared to the inner-bulge. This is also observed in few Galactic globular clusters, and may suggest a common enrichment process at work in all these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17756v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Govind Nandakumar, Nils Ryde, Mathias Schultheis, R. Michael Rich, Paola Di Matteo, Brian Thorsbro, Gregory Mace</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDO68-C: HST confirms yet another companion of the isolated dwarf galaxy DDO 68</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the results of deep Hubble Space Telescope photometry of the dwarf galaxy DDO 68-C, proposed as possibly associated with the isolated peculiar dwarf DDO 68. The new data resolve for the first time the stars of DDO 68-C down to well below the tip of the Red Giant Branch (RGB), revealing a low mass (M$_{*}$ $\sim$ 1.5 $\times$ 10$^7$ M$_{\odot}$) star forming galaxy with a backbone of old stars. By means of a fully homogeneous analysis and using the RGB tip as a standard candle, we find that DDO 68 and DDO 68-C lie at the same distance from us, within the uncertainties (D = 12.6 $\pm$ 0.3 Mpc and D = 12.7 $\pm$ 0.4 Mpc, respectively), thus confirming that the two dwarfs are physically associated. While paired dwarf galaxies with mutual projected distance similar to DDO 68 and DDO 68-C are not exceptional in the Lynx-Cancer Void where they live, DDO 68 remains a unicum as, in addition to the newly confirmed companion, it records the evidence of at least two other satellites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18171v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Correnti, Francesca Annibali, Michele Bellazzini, Mariarosa Marinelli, Alessandra Aloisi, Michele Cignoni, Monica Tosi, Raffaele Pascale, John M. Cannon, Lila Schisgal, Leslie K. Hunt, Elena Sacchi, Sangmo T. Sohn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal relations for non-rotating objects made of dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18338v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We obtain universal relations for fluid spheres without rotation made of dark energy assuming the Extended-Chaplygin Gas equation-of-state. After integrating the relevant differential equations, we make a fit to obtain the unknown coefficients of the functions a) normalized moment of inertia versus dimensionless deformability and b) normalized moment of inertia versus factor of compactness. We find that the form of the functions does not depend on the details of the underlying equation-of-state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18338v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Panotopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revised Point-Spread Functions for the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly onboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08967v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present revised point-spread functions (PSFs) for the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) onboard the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO). These PSFs provide a robust estimate of the light diffracted by the meshes holding the entrance and focal plane filters and the light that is diffusely scattered over medium- to long-distance by the micro-roughness of the mirrors. We first calibrate the diffracted light using flare images. Our modeling of the diffracted light provides reliable determinations of the mesh parameters and finds that about 24 to 33% of the collected light is diffracted, depending on the AIA channel. Then, we fit for the diffuse scattered light using partially lunar occulted images. We find that the diffuse scattered light can be modeled as a superposition of two power law functions that scatter light over the entire length of the detector. The amount of diffuse scattered light ranges from 10 to 35 %, depending on the AIA channel. In total, AIA diffracts and scatters about 40 to 60 % of the collected light over medium to long distances. When correcting for this, bright image regions increase in intensity by about 30 %, dark image regions decrease in intensity by up to 90 %, and the associated differential emission measure analysis of solar features are affected accordingly. Finally, we compare the image reconstructions using our new PSFs to those using the AIA team PSFs and the PSFs of Poduval et al. (2013). We find that our PSFs outperform the others; our PSFs correct well for the flare diffraction pattern and predict accurately the long-distance scattered light in lunar occultations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08967v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Hofmeister, Daniel Wolf Savin, Michael Hahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAMBO I: Project introduction and first results with uGMRT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17032v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic hot stars can emit both coherent and incoherent non-thermal radio emission. Understanding the nature of these emissions and their connection to stellar rotation and magnetic field characteristics remains incomplete. The RAdio Magnetospheres of B and O stars (RAMBO) project aims to address this gap by systematically detecting and characterizing gyrosynchrotron and cyclotron maser radio emission in rapidly rotating magnetic hot stars. Using the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope, we present the first detection of radio emission from HD55522 at 650 MHz, confirming it as a new radio-bright magnetic hot star. This supports the predictions of the Centrifugal Breakout model, furthering its application in understanding particle acceleration mechanisms in centrifugal magnetospheres of hot stars. Additionally, we report non-detections for four other targets, improving sensitivity limits by a factor of a few compared to previous observations. These findings demonstrate the potential of RAMBO to uncover the complexities of radio emission in massive stars and highlight the need for broader, multi-wavelength observations to probe magnetospheric physics comprehensively. The sensitivity of the Square Kilometre Array will enable significant advancements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17032v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Keszthelyi, K. Kurahara, Y. Iwata, Y. Fujii, H. Sakemi, K. Takahashi, S. Yoshiura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLTE abundances of Eu for a sample of metal-poor stars in the Galactic Halo and Metal-poor Disk with 1D and &lt;3D&gt; models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06277v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate measurements of europium abundances in cool stars are essential for an enhanced understanding of the r-process mechanisms. We measure the abundance of Eu in solar spectra and a sample of metal-poor stars in the Galactic halo and metal-poor disk, with the metallicities ranging from \GG{$-2.4$} to $-0.5$ dex, using non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (NLTE) line formation. We compare these measurements with Galactic Chemical Evolution (GCE) models to \GG{explore the impact of the NLTE corrections on the contribution of r-process site in Galactic chemical evolution. In this work, we use NLTE line formation, as well as one-dimensional (1D) hydrostatic and spatial averages of 3D hydrodynamical ($&lt;$3D$&gt;$) model atmospheres to measure the abundance of Eu based on both the Eu II 4129 \AA\ and Eu II 6645 \AA\ lines for solar spectra and metal-poor stars. We find that \GG{for Eu II 4129 \AA\ line the NLTE modelling leads to higher (0.04 dex) solar Eu abundance in 1D and higher (0.07 dex) in \GG{$&lt;$3D$&gt;$} NLTE while} NLTE modelling leads to higher (0.01 dex) solar Eu abundance in 1D and lower (0.03 dex) in \GG{$&lt;$3D$&gt;$} NLTE for Eu II 6645 \AA\ line. Although the NLTE corrections for the Eu II $\lambda$ 4129 \AA\ and Eu II $\lambda$ 6645 \AA\ lines are opposite, the discrepancy between the abundances derived from these individual lines reduces after applying NLTE corrections, highlighting the critical role of NLTE abundance determinations. By comparing these measurements with Galactic chemical evolution (GCE) models, we find that the \G{amount of NLTE correction does not require significant change of the parameters for Eu production} in the GCE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06277v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451536</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 693, A211 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yanjun Guo, Nicholas Storm, Maria Bergemann, Jianhui Lian, Sofya Alexeeva, Yangyang Li, Rana Ezzeddine, Jeffrey Gerber, XueFei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survey of Orion Disks with ALMA (SODA) III: Disks in wide binary systems in L1641 and L1647</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11485v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aims. The goal of this work is to comprehensively characterize the impact of stellar multiplicity on Class II disks in the L1641 and L1647 regions of Orion A (~1-3 Myr), part of the Survey of Orion Disks with ALMA (SODA). We characterize the protostellar multiplicity using the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA), the ESO-VISTA, and Hubble Space telescopes. The resulting sample of 65 multiple systems represents the largest catalogue of wide binary systems to date (projected separation &gt;1000 AU), allowing a more robust statistical characterization of the evolution and properties of protoplanetary disks. Methods. The disk population was observed in continuum with ALMA at 225 GHz, with a median rms of 1.5 Mearth. Combining these data (resolution ~1.1arcsec ) with the ESO-VISTA near-infrared survey of the Orion A cloud (resolution ~0.7arcsec ), multiple systems are assembled and selected by an iterative inside-out search in projected separation (&gt;1000 AU). Results. We identify 61 binary systems, 3 triple systems, and one quadruple system. The separation range is between 1000 and 10^4 AU. The dust mass distributions inferred with the Kaplan-Meier estimator yield a median mass of 3.23+0.6-0.4 Mearth for primary disks and 3.88+0.3-0.3 Mearth for secondary disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11485v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Ricciardi, Sierk E. van Terwisga, Veronica Roccatagliata, Alvaro Hacar, Thomas Henning, Walter Del Pozzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of a PRS associated with FRB 20240114A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the discovery of the fourth persistent radio source (PRS) associated with a fast radio burst (FRB). Following previous indications of a candidate PRS associated with FRB20240114A, we performed deep VLBA observations at 5 GHz to test the presence of a compact radio source within the uncertainty position of this FRB ($\pm$200 mas). We detect a component $\sim$50 mas northwards the nominal position provided by the PRECISE collaboration. The corresponding radio luminosity, together with the Faraday rotation measure provided by previous observations of the FRB, locate this PRS in the expected region of the $L$ vs |RM| relation for the nebular model, further supporting it. The comparison of the measured flux density with the values collected at lower frequency by previous studies indicates a possible steepening of the radio spectrum in the 1-5 GHz range. Optical observations performed with the LBT could reveal that the FRB and its PRS lie at $\sim$1 kpc from the centre of the host galaxy, which is a dwarf sub-solar metallicity starburst galaxy with SFR $\sim 1 M_\odot\;\mathrm{yr^{-1}}$ and stellar mass $M\sim10^8 M_\odot$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01478v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Bruni, L. Piro, Y. -P. Yang, E. Palazzi, L. Nicastro, A. Rossi, S. Savaglio, E. Maiorano, B. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deriving pulsar pair-production multiplicities from pulsar wind nebulae using H.E.S.S. and LHAASO observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01318v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Pulsar wind nebulae (PWNe) dominate the galactic gamma-ray sky at very high energies and they are major contributors to the leptonic cosmic ray flux. However, the question of whether or not pulsars also accelerate ions to comparable energies has not yet been experimentally confirmed. We aim to constrain the birth period and pair-production multiplicity for a set of pulsars. In doing so, we aim to constrain the proportion of ions in the pulsar magnetosphere and, hence, the proportion of ions that could enter the pulsar wind. We estimated possible ranges of the value of the average pair production multiplicity for a sample of 26 pulsars in the Australia Telescope National Facility (ATNF) catalogue, which have also been observed by the High Energy Stereoscopic System (H.E.S.S.) telescopes. We then derived lower limits for the pulsar birth periods and average pair production multiplicities for a subset of these sources where the extent of the pulsar wind nebula and surrounding supernova shell have been measured in the radio. We also derived curves for the average pair production multiplicities as a function of birth period for sources recently observed by the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO). We show that there is a potential for hadrons entering the pulsar wind for most of the H.E.S.S. and LHAASO sources we consider here, which is dependent upon the efficiency of luminosity conversion into particles. We also present estimates of the pulsar birth period for six of these sources, all falling into the range of $\sim$10-50 ms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01318v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451276</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 649 (2025) A324</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel T. Spencer, Alison M. W. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
