<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.SR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR</link>
    <description>astro-ph.SR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.SR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>New Rotation Periods from the Kepler Bonus Background Light Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kepler field hosts the best studied sample of field star rotation periods. However, due to Kepler's large 4" pixels, many of its light curves are at high risk of contamination from background sources. The new Kepler Bonus Background light curves are de-blended using a PSF algorithm, providing light curves of over 400,000 new background sources in addition to over 200,000 re-analyzed Kepler prime targets. These light curves provide the opportunity to search for new rotation periods. Here we apply a convolutional neural network trained on synthetic spot-modulated light curves to regress rotation periods from the Kepler Bonus light curves. We obtained periods for 32,159 total sources, 19,650 of which had previously been measured and 9,811 of which are new periods for both Kepler prime and background sources. Our method also detected 608 pulsation frequencies from asteroseismic oscillations in red giants. We validate our Kepler prime periods against literature values and present the full period sample. We find excellent agreement with previously-known literature periods, validating deep learning as a viable class of period determination methods. Comparing the periods and light curves of foreground-background pairs, we find that as many as 63% of periodic background light curves are still blended with the foreground, highlighting limitations of the de-blending technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03248v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary R. Claytor, Jamie Tayar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geomagnetic Storms and Satellite Orbital Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energetic events on the Sun, particularly coronal mass ejections and high speed streams, regulate the near Earth space environment and give rise to space weather. A major terrestrial manifestation of such events are geomagnetic storms. A geomagnetic storm results in dissipation of energy from the solar wind into the atmosphere, leading to Joule heating and thermospheric expansion. This has serious consequences on Low Earth Orbit satellite lifetimes. Our work demonstrates the impact of different kinds of geomagnetic storms on satellite orbits. We also briefly discuss about some physical attributes of satellites that can make them prone to higher orbital decay. Our work highlights the importance of monitoring and predicting space weather, and assessing their impacts on space-based human technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03305v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshita Baruah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical mass of the Serpens intermediate-mass young stellar system EC\,95 with DYNAMO--VLBA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present dynamical mass measurements, obtained from multi-epoch Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) observations, for the young multiple stellar system EC\,95, located in the core of the Serpens star-forming region. Our dataset includes both archival data and more recent observations obtained as part of the \textit{Dynamical Masses of Young Stellar Multiple Systems with the VLBA project} (DYNAMO--VLBA), totalling 32 epochs over 12 years of observation. The observations span more than half of the EC\,95AB orbit, which has an estimated period of $21.6\pm0.1$ years, and yield masses of $2.15\pm0.10$ M$_\odot$ for EC\,95A and $2.00\pm0.12$ M$_\odot$ for EC\,95B. Furthermore, for the first time, we have estimated the mass of the third component (EC\,95C) using four available radio detections as well as an infrared observation. We find it to be 0.26 $^{+0.53}_{-0.46}$ M$_\odot$, suggesting that E\,95C is a low-mass T Tauri star. We conclude that EC\,95 is a hierarchical triple system comprised of a tight central binary proto-Herbig\,AeBe system and a lower mass companion on a wider orbit. These results contribute to improve our understanding of the stellar dynamics in this system and provide valuable insights into its triple nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03322v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jazm\'in Ord\'o\~nez-Toro (Instituto de Radioastronom\'ia y Astrof\'isica, Universidad Nacional Aut\'onoma de M\'exico, M\'exico), Sergio A. Dzib (Max Planck Institut f\"ur Radioastronomie, Germany), Laurent Loinard (Instituto de Radioastronom\'ia y Astrof\'isica, Universidad Nacional Aut\'onoma de M\'exico, M\'exico, Black Hole Initiative at Harvard University, USA, David Rockefeller Center for Latin American Studies, Harvard University, USA), Gisela Ortiz-Le\'on (Instituto Nacional de Astrof\'isica, \'Optica y Electr\'onica, M\'exico), Marina A. Kounkel (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of North Florida, USA), Phillip A. B. Galli (Instituto de Astronomia, Geof\'isica e Ci\^encias Atmosf\'ericas, Universidade de S\~ao Paulo, Brazil), Josep M. Masqu\'e (Departamento de Astronom\'ia, Universidad de Guanajuato, M\'exico), Luis H. Quiroga-Nu\~nez (Department of Aerospace, Physics and Space Sciences, Florida Institute of Technology, USA), Sundar Srinivasan (Instituto de Radioastronom\'ia y Astrof\'isica, Universidad Nacional Aut\'onoma de M\'exico, M\'exico), S. -N. X. Medina (Max Planck Institut f\"ur Radioastronomie, Germany, German Aerospace Center, Germany), Luis F. Rodr\'iguez (Instituto de Radioastronom\'ia y Astrof\'isica, Universidad Nacional Aut\'onoma de M\'exico, M\'exico)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray spectroscopy method of white dwarf mass determination in intermediate polars. External systematic uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The masses of white dwarfs (WDs) in intermediate polars (IPs) can be determined from the shape of their hard X-ray spectra. Here we study the importance of all possible systematic uncertainties in this X-ray spectroscopy method, including finite radii and rotation of magnetospheres, finite accretion column height and accretion-flow inclination relative to the WD surface. We also investigate the importance of accretion-heated envelopes on WD surfaces in IPs which are increasing WD radii. Their presence changes the commonly used mass-radius relation for cold white dwarfs. As a first approximation we use thick ($10^{-4}M_\odot$) hydrogen envelope models with a surface temperature of 30 kK. We present a new model grid of hard X-ray spectra of high-luminous IPs computed among other things with using a new mass-radius relation. This grid is used for fitting Swift/BAT spectra of 47 IPs. The average WD mass in this sample is 0.82 $M_\odot$ and coincides with the average WD mass in cataclysmic variables obtained by optical methods. This means that the calculated hard X-ray spectra and the assumptions made that the magnetospheric radii in IPs are close to the corotation radii, and the relative heights of the accretion columns are small are basically correct, because most IPs have high luminosities. But this universal grid (as well as previous universal grids) cannot give correct results for the low-luminous IPs with probably relatively tall accretion columns on the WD surfaces. Such IPs have to be investigated with individual accretion column models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03711v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. F. Suleimanov (IAAT, University of Tuebingen), L. Ducci (IAAT, University of Tuebingen), V. Doroshenko (IAAT, University of Tuebingen), K. Werner (IAAT, University of Tuebingen)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal evolution of UV pulsations and their connection to 3D magnetic reconnection and particle acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasi-periodic pulsations (QPPs) are a common feature of impulsive solar flare emissions, yet their driving mechanism(s) remain unresolved. We study long-period (3.4 min) QPPs in the M3.7 flare on Feb 24, 2023, using SDO/AIA and Solar Orbiter/STIX to pinpoint their source and driver. We analyzed UV and HXR emissions from four subregions covering the flare ribbons and footpoints of the erupting filament. We find the QPP characteristics varied significantly across these regions. The strongest UV pulsations, which correlated strongly with HXR emissions, originated from a sequence of flare kernels at the expanding front of the southern flare ribbon. In contrast, another expanding ribbon front showed no pulsations. The spatial coincidence of UV and HXR sources points to non-thermal electrons as a common driver, with the HXR spectrum showing a soft-hard-soft evolution matching the pulsation timescale. We also observed UV pulsations from plasma injections into a separate filament channel, distinct from the main flare kernels. Our results suggest that the spatiotemporal evolution of the pulsations is driven by the propagation of magnetic reconnection in an asymmetric geometry. We propose that slipping reconnection along quasi-separatrix layers is key to generating and moving the UV kernels, potentially modulated by another time-varying process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03825v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Purkhart, Hannah Collier, Laura A. Hayes, Astrid M. Veronig, Miho Janvier, S\"am Krucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tale of Two Shocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It was the best of times, it was the worst of times, . . . - for the thermal/suprathermal particle populations in the vicinity of two traveling interplanetary shocks observed by Solar Orbiter on 2023-11-29 07:51:17 UTC and 2023-11-30 10:47:26 UTC at $\sim 0.83$ astronomical units from the Sun.
  We investigate these two very dissimilar shocks and elucidate their non-equilibrium features. We do not provide explanations of all observed features, our aim is to report them here for future reference.
  We use high-resolution data obtained with Solar Orbiter's Energetic Particle Detector (EPD), magnetometer (MAG), and Solar Wind Analyzer (SWA) to exhibit the very different natures of these two shocks and describe the detailed properties of suprathermal and energetic particles in their vicinity.
  We observe very different behavior of the energetic particle population because the two shocks are quite different. Solar wind protons and $\alpha$-particles are highly dynamic at the first, their beams appear to align well with rapid oscillations of the interplanetary magnetic field. Suprathermal particles associated with the second shock exhibit clear non-equilibrium and anisotropic features in their differential intensities at time scales comparable to the proton gyroperiod.
  The different geometries of the two shocks resulted in highly dissimilar populations of suprathermal and energetic particles in their vicinity. The first shock was associated with very interesting microphysics of the bulk plasma velocity distribution, the second resulted in similarly interesting microphysics of the accelerated particles. Both showed strong temporal variability of the particle populations at scales comparable to the proton gyroperiod.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03958v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert F. Wimmer-Schweingruber, Domenico Trotta, Rungployphan Kieokaew, Liu Yang, Alexander Kollhoff, Lars Berger, Patrick K\"uhl, Stephan I. B\"ottcher, Bernd Heber, Philippe Louarn, Andrey Fedorov, Javier Rodriguez-Pacheco, Ra\'ul G\'omez-Herrero, Francisco Espinosa Lara, Ignacio Cernuda, Yulia Kartavykh, Linghua Wang, George C. Ho, Robert C. Allen, Glenn M. Mason, Zheyi Ding, Andrea Larosa, G. Sindhuja, Sandra Eldrum, Sebastian Fleth, David Lario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamically derived morphology from the recurrence patterns of close binary stars using Kepler data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a novel method to classify close binary stars, derived from the dynamical structure inherent in their light curves. We apply the technique to light curves of binaries from the revised Kepler Eclipsing binary catalog, selecting close binaries which have the standard morphology parameter, $c$, $\gt 0.5$ corresponding to semi-detached, over-contact and ellipsoidal systems. Using the method of time delay embedding, we recreate the non-linear dynamics underlying the data and quantify the patterns of recurrences in them. Using two recurrence measures, Determinism and Entropy, we define a new Dynamically Derived Morphology (DDM) parameter and compute its values for the Kepler objects. While as expected, this metric is somewhat inversely correlated with the existing morphology parameter (Spearman $\rho= -0.32$), the method offers an alternate classification scheme for close binary stars that captures their nonlinear dynamics, an aspect often overlooked in conventional methods. Hence, the DDM parameter is expected to distinguish between stars with similar folded light curves, but are dynamically dissimilar due to nonlinear effects. Moreover, since the method can be easily automated and is computationally efficient it can be effectively used for future sensitive large data sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04111v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anisha R. V. Kashyap, D. Pawar, R. Misra, G. Ambika, Sandip V George</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Uniform Analysis of Debris Disks with the Gemini Planet Imager II: Constraints on Dust Density Distribution Using Empirically-Informed Scattering Phase Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00214v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spatially-resolved images of debris disks are necessary to determine disk morphological properties and the scattering phase function (SPF) which quantifies the brightness of scattered light as a function of phase angle. Current high-contrast imaging instruments have successfully resolved several dozens of debris disks around other stars, but few studies have investigated trends in the scattered-light, resolved population of debris disks in a uniform and consistent manner. We have combined Karhunen-Loeve Image Projection (KLIP) with radiative-transfer disk forward modeling in order to obtain the highest quality image reductions and constrain disk morphological properties of eight debris disks imaged by the Gemini Planet Imager at H-band with a consistent and uniformly-applied approach. In describing the scattering properties of our models, we assume a common SPF informed from solar system dust scattering measurements and apply it to all systems. We identify a diverse range of dust density properties among the sample, including critical radius, radial width, and vertical width. We also identify radially narrow and vertically extended disks that may have resulted from substellar companion perturbations, along with a tentative positive trend in disk eccentricity with relative disk width. We also find that using a common SPF can achieve reasonable model fits for disks that are axisymmetric and asymmetric when fitting models to each side of the disk independently, suggesting that scattering behavior from debris disks may be similar to Solar System dust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00214v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Hom, Jennifer Patience, Christine H. Chen, Gaspard Duch\^ene, Johan Mazoyer, Maxwell A. Millar-Blanchaer, Thomas M. Esposito, Paul Kalas, Katie A. Crotts, Eileen C. Gonzales, Ludmilla Kolokolova, Briley L. Lewis, Brenda C. Matthews, Malena Rice, Alycia J. Weinberger, David J. Wilner, Schuyler G. Wolff, Sebasti\'an Bruzzone, Elodie Choquet, John Debes, Robert J. De Rosa, Jessica Donaldson, Zachary Draper, Michael P. Fitzgerald, Dean C. Hines, Sasha Hinkley, A. Meredith Hughes, Ronald A. L\'opez, Franck Marchis, Stanimir Metchev, Amaya Moro-Martin, Erika Nesvold, Eric L. Nielsen, Rebecca Oppenheimer, Deborah Padgett, Marshall D. Perrin, Laurent Pueyo, Frederik Rantakyr\"o, Bin B. Ren, Glenn Schneider, Rem\'i Soummer, Inseok Song, Christopher C. Stark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The NASA Exoplanet Archive and Exoplanet Follow-up Observing Program: Data, Tools, and Usage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03299v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The NASA Exoplanet Archive and the Exoplanet Follow-up Observing Program service are two widely used resources for the exoplanet community. The NASA Exoplanet Archive provides a complete and accurate accounting of exoplanetary systems published by NASA missions and by the community in the refereed literature. In anticipation of continued exponential growth in the number of exoplanetary systems, and the increasing complexity in our characterization of these systems, the NASA Exoplanet Archive has restructured its primary tables and interfaces, as well as extending and standardizing their modes of access. The Exoplanet Follow-up Observing Program service provides the exoplanet community with a venue for coordinating and sharing follow-up and precursor data for exoplanets, their host stars, and stars that might eventually be targets for future planet searches, and recently reached one million files uploaded by the community. In this paper we describe the updates to our data holdings, functionality, accessibility, and tools, as well as future priorities for these two services.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03299v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessie L. Christiansen, Douglas L. McElroy, Marcy Harbut, David R. Ciardi, Megan Crane, John Good, Kevin K. Hardegree-Ullman, Aurora Y. Kesseli, Michael B. Lund, Meca Lynn, Ananda Muthiar, Ricky Nilsson, Toba Oluyide, Michael Papin, Amalia Rivera, Melanie Swain, Nicholas D. Susemiehl, Raymond Tam, Julian van Eyken, Charles Beichman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abundance Effects from Protoplanetary Disk Outflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04199v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Systematic abundance differences that depend on the condensation temperatures of elements have been observed, in particular for stars similar to the Sun; solar twins and solar analogs. Similar differences have also recently been shown to exist between solar abundances and abundances of refractory elements in primitive chondrites. Numerous mechanisms have been proposed to account for these effects, including also differences observed in binary systems. Rather than relying on specific mechanisms, this paper aims to show that the observed effects are a natural and unavoidable outcome of the star formation process itself, in which the associated outflows (winds and jets) carry away material, with efficiency varying with condensation temperature. By using analysis based on modeling results and scaling laws, the trends and magnitudes of the effects are investigated, in three contexts: 1) with respect to differences between the Sun and solar twins, 2) with respect to differences between the Sun and CI-chondrites, and 3) with respect to differences between members of binaries. It is shown that protoplanetary disk outflows indeed are expected to have differential abundance effects, with trends and magnitudes consistent with observed abundance effects. The qualitative as well as semi-quantitative character of the effects are reproduced, in all three contexts. The results demonstrate that the observed systematic differences are likely results of the disk outflows associated with the accretion process. In contrast to mechanisms relying on the tiny mass of planets leaving an observable signature, outflows carry away masses similar to the entire mass of the star, thus much more easily resulting in differential effects with the magnitudes observed, without for example having to assume that the abundance differences are limited to the convection zones of the stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04199v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>{\AA}ke Nordlund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YSO Jets Magnetocentrifugally Driven by Reconnecting Atmospheric Avalanche Accretion Streams Above Inner Circumstellar Disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10938v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fast, collimated jets are ubiquitous features of young stellar objects (YSOs). They are generally thought to be powered by disk accretion, but the details are debated. Through 2D (axisymmetric) MHD simulations, we find that a fast ($&gt;100$~km/s) collimated bipolar jet is continuously driven along the north and south poles of the circumstellar disk that is initially magnetized by a large-scale open poloidal field and contains a thermally ionized inner magnetically active zone surrounded by a dead zone. The fast jet is primarily driven magneto-centrifugally by the release of the gravitational binding energy of the so-called ``avalanche accretion streams" near the boundary of an evacuated poloidal field-dominated polar region and a thick disk atmosphere raised by a toroidal magnetic field. Specifically, the fast outflow is driven along the upper (open) branch of the highly pinched poloidal field lines threading the (strongly magnetically braked) accretion streams where the density is relatively low so that the lightly loaded material can be accelerated magneto-centrifugally along the open field line to a high speed. The highly pinched poloidal magnetic fields threading the avalanche accretion streams tend to reconnect, enabling mass to accrete to the center without dragging along the poloidal magnetic flux with it. The reconnection provides a potential heating source for producing chondrules and calcium- and aluminum-rich inclusions (CAIs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10938v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yisheng Tu, Zhi-Yun Li, Zhaohuan Zhu, Xiao Hu, Chun-Yen Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly Variable Magnetic Pressure-Driven YSO Jets in the Polar Cavity from Toroidal Fields Generated by Inner Disk Accretion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20495v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Jets and outflows are commonly observed in young stellar objects (YSOs), yet their origins remain debated. Using 3D non-ideal magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations of a circumstellar disk threaded by a large-scale open poloidal magnetic field, we identify three components in the disk-driven outflow: (1) a fast, collimated jet, (2) a less collimated, slower laminar disk wind, and (3) a magneto-rotational instability (MRI)-active turbulent disk wind that separates the former two. At high altitudes, the MRI-active wind merges with the laminar disk wind, leaving only the jet and disk wind as distinct components. The jet is powered by a novel mechanism in the star formation context: a lightly mass-loaded outflow driven by toroidal magnetic pressure in the low-density polar funnel near the system's rotation axis. A geometric analysis of the magnetic field structure confirms that magnetic tension does not contribute to the outflow acceleration, with magnetic pressure acting as the dominant driver. While the outflow in our model shares similarities with the magneto-centrifugal model-such as angular momentum extraction from the accreting disk-centrifugal forces play a negligible role in jet acceleration. In particular, the flow near the jet base does not satisfy the conditions for magneto-centrifugal wind launching. Additionally, the jet in our simulation exhibits strong spatial and temporal variability. These differences challenge the applicability of rotation-outflow velocity relations derived from steady-state, axisymmetric magneto-centrifugal jet models for estimating the jet's launching radius. For the slower disk wind, vertical motion is driven by toroidal magnetic pressure, while centrifugal forces widen the wind's opening angle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20495v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yisheng Tu, Zhi-Yun Li, Zhaohuan Zhu, Chun-Yen Hsu, Xiao Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deuterated water abundance in the young hot core RCW 120 S2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21945v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Since the emission of water molecules cannot be observed from Earth, less abundant isotopologues, such as H$_2^{18}$O and HDO, are used to trace water in star-forming regions. The main aim of this study is to determine HDO abundance in the hot core RCW 120 S2. We performed observations of the hot core in the 200-255~GHz range using the nFLASH230 receiver on the APEX telescope. Two HDO lines were detected toward RCW 120 S2. Their intensities are described by excitation temperature $286\pm2$~K and gas number density $\geq 10^9$~cm$^{-3}$. The emission originates from the hot core rather than the warm dense envelope surrounding a central young stellar object. The HDO column density ranges from $(3.9-7.9)\times10^{13}$~cm$^{-3}$ with a most probable value $5.6\times10^{13}$~cm$^{-3}$. The HDO abundance relative to hydrogen nuclei is $1.5\times10^{-9}$. This HDO abundance value is among the lowest reported for hot cores. Combined with the non-detection of the H$_2^{18}$O line, we conclude that protostellar heating in RCW 120 S2 is still in its early stages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21945v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria. S. Kirsanova, Anastasiia A. Farafontova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asteroseismology of the G8 subgiant beta Aquilae with SONG-Tenerife, SONG-Australia and TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00493v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present radial velocities of the G8 subgiant star beta Aql obtained in 2022 and 2023 using SONG-Tenerife and SONG-Australia. We also analysed a sector of TESS photometry that overlapped with the 2022 SONG data. We processed the time series to assign weights and to remove bad data points. The power spectrum clearly shows solar-like oscillations centred at 430 muHz. The TESS data show the oscillations at lower signal-to-noise because photometric measurements are much more affected by the granulation background than are radial velocities. The simultaneous observations in velocity and photometry represent the best such measurements for any star apart from the Sun. They allowed us to measure the ratio between the two to be 26.6+/-3.1 ppm/(m/s). We measured this ratio for the Sun from published SOHO data to be 19.5+/-0.7 ppm/(m/s) and, after accounting for the difference in effective temperatures of the beta Aql and the Sun, these values align with expectations. In both the Sun and beta Aql, the photometry-to-velocity ratio appears to be a function of frequency. We also measured the phase shift of the oscillations in beta Aql between SONG velocities and TESS photometry to be -113+/-7 deg, which agrees within uncertainties with the value for the Sun and also with a 3-D simulation of a star with similar properties to beta Aql. Importantly for exoplanet searches, we argue that simultaneous photometry can be used to predict the contribution of oscillations to radial velocities. We identified and measured frequencies for 22 oscillation modes in beta Aql with angular degrees of l=0, 1 and 2. Asteroseismic modelling yielded an excellent fit to the frequencies, giving accurate values for mass and age, placing quite strong constraints on the mixing-length parameter. Finally, the oscillation properties of beta Aql are very similar to subgiants and low-luminosity RGB stars in the open cluster M67.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00493v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Kjeldsen, Timothy R. Bedding, Yaguang Li, Frank Grundahl, Mads Fredslund Andersen, Duncan J. Wright, Jack Soutter, Robert Wittenmyer, Claudia Reyes, Dennis Stello, Courtney Crawford, Yixiao Zhou, Mathieu Clerte, Pere L. Palle, Sergio Simon-Diaz, Joergen Christensen-Dalsgaard, Rasmus Handberg, Hasse Hansen, Paul Heeren, Jens Jessen-Hansen, Mikkel Lund, Mia S. Lundkvist, Karsten Brogaard, Rene Tronsgaard, Jonatan Rudrasingam, Luca Casagrande, Jonathan Horner, Daniel Huber, John Lattanzio, Sarah L. Martell, Simon J. Murphy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of convective overshooting on the single-degenerate model of Type Ia supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The single-degenerate (SD) model is one of the principal models for the progenitors of Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia). However, it faces some challenges, the primary being its inability to account for the observed SN Ia birth rate. Many studies have attempted to address this issue by expanding the parameter space, defined by the initial donor star mass and orbital period, that can lead to SNe Ia, as well as by improving binary population synthesis. While these efforts have led to significant progress, many uncertainties in stellar physics persist, which influences the outcomes of such studies. Convective overshooting, which can significantly affect the internal structure of a star and subsequently its evolution within a binary system, is one of the most significant sources of uncertainty in stellar physics. We investigate the effect of convective overshooting on the parameter space and birth rate of SNe Ia within the SD model. We employed the common-envelope wind (CEW) model, a new version of the SD model, as our progenitor model. Using MESA, we obtained the parameter space that leads to SNe Ia for three different convective overshooting parameters and calculated the corresponding SN Ia birth rate. Convective overshooting expands the upper boundaries (corresponding to a larger initial donor mass) and right boundaries (corresponding to a longer initial orbital period) of the parameter space for systems with massive white dwarfs (WDs; &gt;= 0.75Msun). However, the minimum WD mass and the parameter space for low-mass WDs - and, consequently, the calculated SN Ia birth rate - vary non-monotonically with convective overshooting parameters. The CEW model may explain the SNe Ia that interact with the circumstellar medium (CSM), i.e., SNe Ia-CSM. We find that the parameter space for SNe Ia-CSM increases with convective overshooting parameters, as does their birth rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02551v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202554449</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xinghuan Wang, Xiangcun Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Systematic Transient Search of Single Observation Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08429v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We conduct a systematic search for astrophysical transients using data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT). The data were taken from 2017 to 2022 in three frequency bands spanning 77 GHz to 277 GHz. In this paper we present a pipeline for transient detection using single observation maps where each pixel of a map contains one observation with an integration time of approximately four minutes. We detect 34 transient events at 27 unique locations. All but two of the transients are associated with Galactic stars and exhibit a wide range of properties. We also detect an event coincident with the classical nova YZ Ret and one event consistent with a flaring active galactic nucleus. We notably do not detect any reverse shock emission from gamma ray bursts, a non-detection that may be in tension with current models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08429v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adce70</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 986 7 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Emily K. Biermann, Yaqiong Li, Sigurd Naess, Steve K. Choi, Susan E. Clark, Mark Devlin, Jo Dunkley, P. A. Gallardo, Yilun Guan, Allen Foster, Matthew Hasselfield, Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo, Matt Hilton, Adam D. Hincks, Anna Y. Q. Ho, John C. Hood II, Kevin M. Huffenberger, Arthur Kosowsky, Michael D. Niemack, John Orlowski-Scherer, Lyman Page, Bruce Partridge, Maria Salatino, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Suzanne T. Staggs, Cristian Vargas, Edward J. Wollack</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
