<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 02:43:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Lusztig $\mathbf{a}$-functions for quasiparabolic sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kazhdan and Lusztig introduce the $W$-graphs to describe the cells and molecules corresponding to the Coxeter groups. Building on this foundation, Lusztig defines the a-funtion to classify the cells, as well as the molecules. Marberg then generalizes Kazhdan and Lusztig's $W$-graphs, using fixed-point-free involutions as their indices. The molecules of the two new $S_n$-graphs are then classified via two correspondence similar to RSK correspondence by Marberg and me. In this paper, we define an analogue of the Lusztig a-function and finish the classification of cells by proving that every molecule in the $S_n$-graphs is indeed a cell.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07810v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifeng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetical Structures on Wheel Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An arithmetical structure on a finite and connected graph G is a pair (d, r) of positive integer vectors such that r is primitive (the gcd of its entries is 1) and (diag(d) - A)r = 0, where A is the adjacency matrix of G. In this article, we investigate arithmetical structures on the wheel graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07816v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bibhas Adhikari, Namita Behera, Dilli Ram Chhetri, Raj Bhawan Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lucky cars and lucky spots in parking functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parking functions correspond with preferences of $n$ cars which enter sequentially to park on a one-way street where (1) each car parks in the first available spot greater than or equal to its preference and (2) all cars successfully park. When a car parks in its preferred spot then the corresponding car and corresponding spot are deemed ``lucky.'' This paper looks briefly at lucky cars which have previously been studied and in simple cases can be understood by a generalization of a result due to Pollak. We also consider lucky spots where the situation is more complex and not previously studied. Probabilities and asymptotics for lucky spots are given for the first few spots on the one-way street. We close with an exploration of the special cases when cars enter the one-way street in either weakly-increasing or weakly-decreasing order of their preferences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07873v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve Butler, Kimberly Hadaway, Victoria Lenius, Preston Martens, Marshall Moats</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure of non-trivial intersecting families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We say that a family of $k$-subsets of an $n$-element set is {\it intersecting}, if any two of its sets intersect. In this paper, we study the structure of large intersecting families. Several years ago, Han and Kohayakawa (Proc. AMS, 2017), and then Kostochka and Mubayi (Proc. AMS, 2017) obtained certain structural results concerning large intersecting families. In this paper, we extend and generalize their results, giving them a conclusive form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07974v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Kupavskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When entropy meets Tur\'an: new proofs and hypergraph Tur\'an results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide a new proof of a density version of Tur\'an's theorem. We also rephrase both the theorem and the proof using entropy. With the entropic formulation, we show that some naturally defined entropic quantity is closely connected to other common quantities such as Lagrangian and spectral radius. In addition, we also determine the Tur\'an density for a new family of hypergraphs, which we call tents. Our result can be seen as a new generalization of Mubayi's result on the extended cliques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08075v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting-Wei Chao, Hung-Hsun Hans Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonicity of Transitive Graphs Whose Automorphism Group Has $\Z_{p}$ as Commutator Subgroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1982, Durnberger proved that every connected Cayley graph of a finite group with a commutator subgroup of prime order contains a hamiltonian cycle. In this paper, we extend this result to the infinite case. Additionally, we generalize this result to a broader class of infinite graphs $X$, where the automorphism group of $X$ contains a transitive subgroup $G$ with a cyclic commutator subgroup of prime order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08105v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Lehner, Farzad Maghsoudi, Babak Miraftab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commuting Pairs in Quasigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A quasigroup is a pair $(Q, *)$ where $Q$ is a non-empty set and $*$ is a binary operation on $Q$ such that for every $(a, b) \in Q^2$ there exists a unique $(x, y) \in Q^2$ such that $a*x=b=y*a$. Let $(Q, *)$ be a quasigroup. A pair $(x, y) \in Q^2$ is a commuting pair of $(Q, *)$ if $x * y = y * x$. Recently, it has been shown that every rational number in the interval $(0, 1]$ can be attained as the proportion of ordered pairs that are commuting in some quasigroup. For every positive integer $n$ we establish the set of all integers $k$ such that there is a quasigroup of order $n$ with exactly $k$ commuting pairs. This allows us to determine, for a given rational $q \in (0, 1]$, the spectrum of positive integers $n$ for which there is a quasigroup of order $n$ whose proportion of commuting pairs is equal to $q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08107v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Allsop, Ian M. Wanless</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to the linkage conjecture in tournaments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A digraph $D$ is $k$-linked if for every $2k$-tuple $ x_1,\ldots , x_k, y_1, \ldots , y_k$ of distinct vertices in $D$, there exist $k$ pairwise vertex-disjoint paths $P_1,\ldots, P_k$ such that $P_i$ starts at $x_i$ and ends at $y_i$, $i\in [k]$. In 2015, Pokrovskiy conjectured that there exists a function $g(k)$ such that every $2k$-connected tournament with minimum in-degree and minimum out-degree at least $g(k)$ is $k$-linked in [J. Comb. Theory, Ser. B 115 (2015) 339--347]. In this paper, we disprove this conjecture by constructing a family of counterexamples. The counterexamples also provide a negative answer to the question raised by Gir\~{a}o, Popielarz, Snyder in [Combinatorica 41 (2021) 815--837]. Further, we prove that every $(2k+1)$-connected semicomplete digraph $D$ with minimum out-degree at least $ 10^7k^{4}$ is $k$-linked, which refines and generalizes the early result of Gir\~{a}o, Popielarz, Snyder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08180v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia Zhou, Jin Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A special balancing game, Victor Grinberg's question</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a vector balancing game, on step $k$ player 1 chooses a unit vector $v_k$ and player 2 chooses a sign $\varepsilon_k\in \{-1,1\}$, and the position after $n$ steps is $z_n=\sum_1^n\varepsilon_k v_k$. Player 1's target is to make $\|z_n\|$ large and player 2's target is to make it small. We consider a special case of this game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08238v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imre B\'ar\'any</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$q$-deformation of chromatic polynomials and graphical arrangements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first observe a mysterious similarity between the braid arrangement and the arrangement of all hyperplanes in a vector space over the finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$. These two arrangements are defined by the determinants of the Vandermonde and the Moore matrix, respectively. These two matrices are transformed to each other by replacing a natural number $n$ with $q^n$ ($q$-deformation).
  In this paper, we introduce the notion of ``$q$-deformation of graphical arrangements'' as certain subarrangements of the arrangement of all hyperplanes over $\mathbb{F}_q$. This new class of arrangements extends the relationship between the Vandermonde and Moore matrices to graphical arrangements. We show that many invariants of the ``$q$-deformation'' behave as ``$q$-deformation'' of invariants of the graphical arrangements. Such invariants include the characteristic (chromatic) polynomial, the Stirling number of the second kind, freeness, exponents, basis of logarithmic vector fields, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08290v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tongyu Nian, Shuhei Tsujie, Ryo Uchiumi, Masahiko Yoshinaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge-graceful usual fan graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A graph $G$ with $p$ vertices and $q$ edges is said to be edge-graceful if its edges can be labeled from $1$ through $q$, in such a way that the labels induced on the vertices by adding over the labels of incident edges modulo $p$ are distinct. A known result under this topic is Lo's Theorem, which states that if a graph $G$ with $p$ vertices and $q$ edges is edge-graceful, then $p\Big|\Big(q^{2}+q-\dfrac{p(p-1)}{2}\Big)$.
  This paper presents novel results on the edge-gracefulness of the usual fan graphs. Using Lo's Theorem, the concepts of divisibility and Diophantine equations, and a computer program created, we determine all edge-graceful usual fan graphs $F_{1,n}$ with their corresponding edge-graceful labels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08338v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron D. C. Angel, John Rafael M. Antalan, John Loureynz F. Gamurot, Richard P. Tagle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A contribution to the characterization of minimal automorphic posets of width three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The characterization of the finite minimal automorphic posets of width three is still an open problem. Niederle has shown that this task can be reduced to the characterization of the nice sections of width three having a non-trivial tower of nice sections as retract. We solve this problem for a sub-class $\mathfrak{N}_2$ of the finite nice sections of width three. On the one hand, we characterize the posets in $\mathfrak{N}_2$ having a retract of width three being a non-trivial tower of nice sections, and on the other hand we characterize the posets in $\mathfrak{N}_2$ having a 4-crown stack as retract. The latter result yields a recursive approach for the determination of posets in $\mathfrak{N}_2$ having a 4-crown stack as retract. With this approach, we determine all posets in $\mathfrak{N}_2$ with height up to six having such a retract. For each integer $n \geq 2$, the class $\mathfrak{N}_2$ contains $2^{n-2}$ different isomorphism types of posets of height $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08363v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank A Campo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 dimensional Wythoff Nim</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new generalization of Wythoff Nim using three piles of stones. We show that its P-positions have finite difference properties and produce a partition of positive integers. Further, we give a conjecture that the P-positions approximate a semi-line whose slope is described by algebraic numbers of degree 5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08399v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shigeki Akiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence classes of lower and upper descent weak Bruhat intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathrm{Int}(n)$ denote the set of nonempty left weak Bruhat intervals in the symmetric group $\mathfrak{S}_n$. We investigate the equivalence relation $\overset{D}{\simeq}$ on $\mathrm{Int}(n)$, where $I \overset{D}{\simeq} J$ if and only if there exists a descent-preserving poset isomorphism between $I$ and $J$. For each equivalence class $C$ of $(\mathrm{Int}(n), \overset{D}{\simeq})$, a partial order $\preceq$ is defined by $[\sigma, \rho]_L \preceq [\sigma', \rho']_L$ if and only if $\sigma \preceq_R \sigma'$. Kim-Lee-Oh (2023) showed that the poset $(C, \preceq)$ is isomorphic to a right weak Bruhat interval.
  In this paper, we focus on lower and upper descent weak Bruhat intervals, specifically those of the form $[w_0(S), \sigma]_L$ or $[\sigma, w_1(S)]_L$, where $w_0(S)$ is the longest element in the parabolic subgroup $\mathfrak{S}_S$ of $\mathfrak{S}_n$, generated by $\{s_i \mid i \in S\}$ for a subset $S \subseteq [n-1]$, and $w_1(S)$ is the longest element among the minimal-length representatives of left $\mathfrak{S}_{[n-1] \setminus S}$-cosets in $\mathfrak{S}_n$. We begin by providing a poset-theoretic characterization of the equivalence relation $\overset{D}{\simeq}$. Using this characterization, the minimal and maximal elements within an equivalence class $C$ are identified when $C$ is a lower or upper descent interval. Under an additional condition, a detailed description of the structure of $(C, \preceq)$ is provided. Furthermore, for the equivalence class containing $[w_0(S), \sigma]_L$, an injective hull of ${\sf B}([w_0(S), \sigma]_L)$ is given, and for the equivalence class containing $[\sigma, w_1(S)]_L$, a projective cover of ${\sf B}([\sigma, w_1(S)]_L)$ is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08413v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Il Choi, Sun-Young Nam, Young-Tak Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximizing the signless Laplacian spectral radius of some theta graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08417v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $Q(G)=D(G)+A(G)$ be the signless Laplacian matrix of a simple graph $G$, where $D(G)$ and $A(G)$ are the degree diagonal matrix and the adjacency matrix of $G$, respectively. The largest eigenvalue of $Q(G)$, denoted by $q(G)$, is called the signless Laplacian spectral radius of $G$. Let $\theta(l_{1},l_{2},l_{3})$ denote the theta graph which consists of two vertices connected by three internally disjoint paths with length $l_{1}$, $l_{2}$ and $l_{3}$. Let $F_{n}$ be the friendship graph consisting of $\frac{n-1}{2}$ triangles which intersect in exactly one common vertex for odd $n\geq3$ and obtained by hanging an edge to the center of $F_{n-1}$ for even $n\geq4$. Let $S_{n,k}$ denote the graph obtained by joining each vertex of $K_{k}$ to $n-k$ isolated vertices. Let $S_{n,k}^{+}$ denote the graph obtained by adding an edge to the two isolated vertices of $S_{n,k}$. In this paper, firstly, we show that if $G$ is $\theta(1,2,2)$-free, then $q(G)\leq q(F_{n})$, unless $G\cong F_{n}$. Secondly, we show that if $G$ is $\theta(1,2,3)$-free, then $q(G)\leq q(S_{n,2})$, unless $G\cong S_{n,2}$. Finally, we show that if $G$ is $\{\theta(1,2,2),F_{5}\}$-free, then $q(G)\leq q(S_{n,1}^{+})$, unless $G\cong S_{n,1}^{+}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08417v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Liu, Ligong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tilings of the sphere by congruent pentagons IV: Edge combination $a^4b$ with general angles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We classify edge-to-edge tilings of the sphere by congruent pentagons with the edge combination $a^4b$ and with any irrational angle in degree: they are three $1$-parameter families of pentagonal subdivisions of the Platonic solids, with $12, 24$ and $60$ tiles; and a sequence of $1$-parameter families of pentagons admitting non-symmetric $3$-layer earth map tilings together with their various rearrangements under extra conditions. Their parameter moduli and geometric data are all computed in both exact and numerical form. The total numbers of different tilings for any fixed such pentagon are counted explicitly. As a byproduct, the degenerate pentagons produce naturally many new non-edge-to-edge quadrilateral tilings. A sequel of this paper will handle $a^4b$-pentagons with all angles being rational in degree by solving some trigonometric Diophantine equations, to complete our full classification of edge-to-edge tilings of the sphere by congruent pentagons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08492v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Shu, Yixi Liao, Erxiao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive co-degree densities and jumps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The minimum positive co-degree of a nonempty $r$-graph $H$, denoted by $\delta_{r-1}^+(H)$, is the largest integer $k$ such that for every $(r-1)$-set $S \subset V(H)$, if $S$ is contained in a hyperedge of $H$, then $S$ is contained in at least $k$ hyperedges of $H$. Given a family $\mathcal{F}$ of $r$-graphs, the positive co-degree Tur\'an function $\mathrm{co^+ex}(n,\mathcal{F})$ is the maximum of $\delta_{r-1}^+(H)$ over all $n$-vertex $r$-graphs $H$ containing no member of $\mathcal{F}$. The positive co-degree density of $\mathcal{F}$ is $\gamma^+(\mathcal{F}) = \underset{n \rightarrow \infty}{\lim} \frac{\mathrm{co^+ex}(n,\mathcal{F})}{n}.$ While the existence of $\gamma^+(\mathcal{F})$ is proved for all families $\mathcal{F}$, only few positive co-degree densities are known exactly.
  For a fixed $r \geq 2$, we call $\alpha \in [0,1]$ an achievable value if there exists a family of $r$-graphs $\mathcal{F}$ with $\gamma^+(\mathcal{F}) = \alpha$, and call $\alpha$ a jump if for some $\delta &gt; 0$, there is no family $\mathcal{F}$ with $\gamma^+(\mathcal{F}) \in (\alpha, \alpha + \delta)$. Halfpap, Lemons, and Palmer showed that every $\alpha \in [0, \frac{1}{r})$ is a jump. We extend this result by showing that every $\alpha \in [0, \frac{2}{2r -1})$ is a jump. We also show that for $r = 3$, the set of achievable values is infinite, more precisely, $\frac{k-2}{2k-3}$ for every $k \geq 4$ is achievable. Finally, we determine two additional achievable values for $r=3$ using flag algebra calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08597v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'ozsef Balogh, Anastasia Halfpap, Bernard Lidick\'y, Cory Palmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building monomial ideals with fixed betti numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07995v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the fact that as the number of generators of an ideal grows so does the complexity of calculating relations among the generators, this paper identifies collections of monomial ideals with a growing number of generators which have predictable free resolutions. We use elementary collapses from discrete homotopy theory to construct infinitely many monomial ideals, with an arbitrary number of generators, which have similar or the same betti numbers. We show that the Cohen-Macaulay property in each unmixed (pure) component of the ideal is preserved as the ideal is expanded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07995v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Faridi, Peilin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weak Lefschetz properties of artinian monomial algebras associated to certain tadpole graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08037v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a simple graph $G$, the artinian monomial algebra associated to $G$, denoted by $A(G)$, is defined by the edge ideal of $G$ and the squares of the variables. In this article, we classify some tadpole graphs $G$ for which $A(G)$ has or fails the weak Lefschetz property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08037v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phan Minh Hung, Nguyen Duy Phuoc, Tran Nguyen Thanh Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsically Correct Sorting in Cubical Agda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The paper "Sorting with Bialgebras and Distributive Laws" by Hinze et al. uses the framework of bialgebraic semantics to define sorting algorithms. From distributive laws between functors they construct pairs of sorting algorithms using both folds and unfolds. Pairs of sorting algorithms arising this way include insertion/selection sort and quick/tree sort.
  We extend this work to define intrinsically correct variants in cubical Agda. Our key idea is to index our data types by multisets, which concisely captures that a sorting algorithm terminates with an ordered permutation of its input list. By lifting bialgebraic semantics to the indexed setting, we obtain the correctness of sorting algorithms purely from the distributive law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08362v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3703595.3705873</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Cass Alexandru, Vikraman Choudhury, Jurriaan Rot, Niels van der Weide</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Poincar\'e polynomials for plane curves with quasi-homogeneous singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define a combinatorial object that can be associated with any conic-line arrangement with ordinary quasi-homogeneous singularities, which we call the combinatorial Poincar\'e polynomial. We prove a Terao-type factorization statement on the splitting of such a polynomial over the rationals under the assumption that our conic-line arrangements are free. Then we focus on the so-called $d$-arrangements in the plane. In particular, we provide a combinatorial constraint for free $d$-arrangements admitting ordinary quasi-homogeneous singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08436v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Pokora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primitive asymptotics in $\phi^4$ vector theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08617v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A longstanding conjecture in $\phi^4_4$ theory is that primitive graphs dominate the beta function asymptotically at large loop order in the minimal-subtraction scheme. Here we investigate this issue by exploiting additional combinatorial structure coming from an extension to vectors with $O(N)$ symmetry. For the 0-dimensional case, we calculate the $N$-dependent generating function of primitive graphs and its asymptotics, including arbitrarily many subleading corrections. We find that the leading asymptotic growth rate becomes visible only above $\approx 25$ loops, while data at lower order is suggestive of a wrong asymptotics. Our results also yield the exact asymptotics of Martin invariants.
  In 4D, each graph comes with a nontrivial Feynman integral, its period. We give bounds on the degree in $N$ for primitive and non-primitive graphs, and construct the primitive graphs of highest degree explicitly. We calculate the 4D primitive beta function numerically up to 17 loops. The qualitative behaviour is similar to the 0D series, with a small but systematic tendency for the 4D data to grow faster with $N$, indicating a correlation between periods and $O(N)$-symmetry factors. The zeros of the 4D primitive beta function approach their asymptotic locations quickly, but, like in 0D, the growth rate of the 4D primitive beta function does not match its asymptotics even at 17 loops.
  Our results improve on the knowledge of asymptotics in QFT by providing concrete analytic and numerical values, and putting individual observables into a broader context of $\phi^4_4$ theory in 0D and 4D. We demonstrate that even if certain quantities are in agreement with the asymptotics already below 10 loops, this must not be mistaken as evidence that overall an asymptotic regime has been reached.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08617v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul-Hermann Balduf, Johannes Th\"urigen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matroids, Feynman categories, and Koszul duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12370v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that various combinatorial invariants of matroids such as Chow rings and Orlik--Solomon algebras may be assembled into "operad-like" structures. Specifically, one obtains several operads over a certain Feynman category which we introduce and study in detail. In addition, we establish a Koszul-type duality between Chow rings and Orlik--Solomon algebras, vastly generalizing a celebrated result of Getzler. This provides a new interpretation of combinatorial Leray models of Orlik--Solomon algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12370v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basile Coron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Nearly Finitary Matroid that is not $k$-Nearly Finitary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04721v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The class of $k$-nearly finitary matroids for some natural number $k$ is a subclass of the class of nearly finitary matroids. A natural question is whether this inclusion is proper. We answer this question affirmatively by constructing a nearly finitary matroid that is not $k$-nearly finitary for any $k \in \mathbb{N}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04721v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.37236/10467</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Electronic Journal of Combinatorics, Volume 31, Issue 1, P1.32, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Tam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eulerian $k$-dominating reconfiguration graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10962v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a graph $G$, the vertices of the $k$-dominating graph, denoted $\mathcal{D}_k(G)$, correspond to the dominating sets of $G$ with cardinality at most $k$. Two vertices of $\mathcal{D}_k(G)$ are adjacent if and only if the corresponding dominating sets in $G$ can be obtained from one other by adding or removing a single vertex of $G$. Since $\mathcal{D}_k(G)$ is not necessarily connected when $k &lt; |V(G)|$, much research has focused on conditions under which $\mathcal{D}_k(G)$ is connected and recent work has explored the existence of Hamilton paths in the $k$-dominating graph. We consider the complementary problem of determining the conditions under which the $k$-dominating graph is Eulerian. In the case where $k = |V(G)|$, we characterize those graphs $G$ for which $\mathcal{D}_k(G)$ is Eulerian. In the case where $k$ is restricted, we determine for a number of graph classes, the conditions under which the $k$-dominating graph is Eulerian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10962v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. E. Messinger, A. Porter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S-Glued sums of lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10738v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For many equation-theoretical questions about modular lattices, Hall and Dilworth give a useful construction: Let $L_0$ be a lattice with largest element $u_0$, $L_1$ be a lattice disjoint from $L_0$ with smallest element $v_1$, and $a \in L_0$, $b \in L_1$ such that the intervals $[a, u_0]$ and $[v_1, b]$ are isomorphic. Then, after identifying those intervals you obtain $L_0 \cup L_1$, a lattice structure whose partial order is the transitive relation generated by the partial orders of $L_0$ and $L_1$. It is modular if $L_0$ and $L_1$ are modular. Since in this construction the index set $\{0, 1\}$ is essentially a chain, this work presents a method -- termed S-glued -- whereby a general family $L_x\ (x \in S)$ of lattices can specify a lattice with the small-scale lattice structure determined by the $L_x$ and the large-scale structure determined by $S$. A crucial application is representing finite-length modular lattices using projective geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10738v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Herrmann (Technische Universit\"at Darmstadt), Dale R. Worley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partition regularity of homogeneous quadratics: Current trends and challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17523v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Suppose we partition the integers into finitely many cells. Can we always find a solution of the equation $x^2+y^2=z^2$ with $x,y,z$ on the same cell? What about more general homogeneous quadratic equations in three variables? These are basic questions in arithmetic Ramsey theory, which have recently been partially answered using ideas inspired by ergodic theory and tools such as Gowers-uniformity properties and concentration estimates of bounded multiplicative functions. The aim of this article is to provide an introduction to this exciting research area, explaining the main ideas behind the recent progress and some of the important challenges that lie ahead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17523v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Frantzikinakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric Colorings of Disjoint Unions of Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00574v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The asymmetric coloring number of a graph is the minimum number of colors needed to color its vertices, so that no non-trivial automorphism preserves the color classes. We investigate the asymmetric coloring number of graphs that are disjoint unions of graphs. We will derive a general relationship between the asymmetric coloring number of disjoint copies of graphs and the number of ways to color a single copy asymmetrically, and then look at particular cases such as disjoint copies of paths, stars, cycles, and hypercubes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00574v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Aguilar, Daibik Barik, Jetharam Bhambhu, Evan Frankel, Nam Hung Tran Nguyen, Revathi Mandava, Aiden Marco, Kyle Pon, Tejas Shende, Yi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
