<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On constrained matchings, stable under random preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Colloquially, there are two groups, $n$ men and $n$ women, each man (woman) ranking women (men) as potential marriage partners. A complete matching is called stable if no unmatched pair prefer each other to their partners in the matching. If some pairs are not admissible, then such a matching may not exist, but a properly defined partial stable matching exists always, and all such matchings involve the same, equi-numerous, groups of men and women. Earlier we proved that, for the complete, random, preference lists, with high probability (whp) the total number of complete stable matchings is, roughly, of order $n^{1/2}$, at least. Here we consider the case that the preference lists are still complete, but a generic pair (man,woman) is admissible with probability $p$, independently of all other $n^2-1$ pairs. It is shown that the expected number of complete stable matchings tends to $0$ if, roughly, $p&lt;\tfrac{\log^2 n}{n}$ and to infinity if $p&gt;\tfrac{\log^2 n}{n}$. We show that whp: (a) there exists a complete stable matching if $p&gt;(9/4)\tfrac{\log^2 n}{n}$, (b) the number of unmatched men and women is bounded if $p&gt; \tfrac{\log^2n}{n}$, and (c) this number grows as a fractional power of $n$ for $p&lt;\tfrac{\log^2 n}{n}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10319v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Pittel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Over-Mahonian numbers: Basic properties and unimodality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose the number of permutations of length $n$ having $k$ overlined inversions, which we call over-Mahonian number. We study useful properties and some combinatorial interpretations by lattice paths/overpartitions and tilings. Furthermore, we prove combinatorially that these numbers form a log-concave sequence and therefore unimodal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10487v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Kessouri, Moussa Ahmia, Salim Mesbahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cayley graphs on finite groups generated by $p$-singular elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A singular graph is a finite graph $\Gamma$ whose adjacency matrix is singular. Let $G$ be a finite group and $p$ a prime divisor of the order of $G$. Also let $\Omega(G,p)$ be the set of all $p$-singular elements of $G$. In this paper, we show that the Cayley graph $\Gamma_p(G):=\mathrm{Cay}(G,\Omega(G,p))$ is a singular graph, if and only if the group $G$ has a non-principal $p$-block. We apply this result to obtain new classes of singular Cayley graphs (See Corollary 1.3). We also prove that if $G$ is $p$-solvable, then the diameter of $\Gamma_p(G)$ is at most the $p$-part of the order of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10497v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Ebrahimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The universal ${\mathfrak gl}$-weight system and the chromatic polynomial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent paper Zhuoke Yang, New approaches to ${\mathfrak gl}(N)$ weight system, Izvestiya Mathematics, 2023, vol. 77:6, 150--166; arXiv:2202.12225 (2022) a construction of a weight system, which unifies ${\mathfrak gl}(N)$ weight systems for $N=1,2,\dots$, has been suggested. The construction is based on an extension of the ${\mathfrak gl}(N)$ weight systems to permutations. This universal weight system takes values in the algebra of polynomials ${\mathbb C}[N;C_1,C_2,\dots]$ in infinitely many variables. We show that under the substitution $C_m=xN^{m-1}$, $m=1,2,\dots$, the leading term in $N$ of the value of the universal ${\mathfrak gl}$ weight system becomes the chromatic polynomial of the intersection graph of the chord diagram. Moreover, we show that under the substition $C_m=p_m N^{m-1}$, $m=1,2,\dots$, the leading term in $N$ of the value of the universal ${\mathfrak gl}$ weight system determines a flitered Hopf algebra homomorphism from the rotational Hopf algebra of permutations, which we construct in the present paper, to the Hopf algebra of polynomials ${\mathbb C}[p_1,p_2,\dots]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10562v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Kazarian (HSE University, Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology), N. Kodaneva (HSE University), S. Lando (HSE University, Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Brandt-Thomass\'e Theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving a long standing conjecture of Erd\H{o}s and Simonovits, Brandt and Thomass\'e proved that the chromatic number of each triangle-free graph $G$ such that $\delta(G)&gt;|V(G)|/3$ is at most four. In fact, they showed the much stronger result that every maximal triangle-free graph $G$ satisfying this minimum degree condition is a blow-up of either an Andr\'asfai or a Vega graph.
  Here we establish the same structural conclusion on $G$ under the weaker assumption that for $m\in\{2, 3, 4\}$ every sequence of $3m$ vertices has a subsequence of length $m+1$ with a common neighbour. In forthcoming work this will be used to solve an old problem of Andr\'asfai in Ramsey-Tur\'an theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10745v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomasz {\L}uczak, Joanna Polcyn, Christian Reiher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial properties of Circulant Hadamard matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe combinatorial properties of the defining row of a circulant Hadamard matrix by exploiting its orthogonality to subsequent rows, and show how to exclude several particular forms of these matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10748v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis H. Gallardo, Olivier Rahavandrainy, Reinhardt. Euler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colouring negative exact-distance graphs of signed graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $k$-th exact-distance graph, of a graph $G$ has $V(G)$ as its vertex set, and $xy$ as an edge if and only if the distance between $x$ and $y$ is (exactly) $k$ in $G$. We consider two possible extensions of this notion for signed graphs. Finding the chromatic number of a negative exact-distance square of a signed graph is a weakening of the problem of finding the smallest target graph to which the signed graph has a sign-preserving homomorphism. We study the chromatic number of negative exact-distance graphs of signed graphs that are planar, and also the relation of these chromatic numbers with the generalised colouring numbers of the underlying graphs. Our results are related to a theorem of Alon and Marshall about homomorphisms of signed graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10780v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Naserasr, Patrice Ossona de Mendez, Daniel A. Quiroz, Robert \v{S}\'amal, Weiqiang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signed projective cubes, a homomorphism point of view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The (signed) projective cubes, as a special class of graphs closely related to the hypercubes, are on the crossroad of geometry, algebra, discrete mathematics and linear algebra. Defined as Cayley graphs on binary groups, they represent basic linear dependencies. Capturing the four-color theorem as a homomorphism target they show how mapping of discrete objects, namely graphs, may relate to special mappings of plane to projective spaces of higher dimensions. In this work, viewed as a signed graph, first we present a number of equivalent definitions each of which leads to a different development. In particular, the new notion of common product of signed graphs is introduced which captures both Cartesian and tensor products of graphs. We then have a look at some of their homomorphism properties. We first introduce an inverse technique for the basic no-homomorphism lemma, using which we show that every signed projective cube is of circular chromatic number 4. Then observing that the 4-color theorem is about mapping planar graphs into signed projective cube of dimension 2, we study some conjectures in extension of 4CT. Toward a better understanding of these conjectures we present the notion of extended double cover as a key operation in formulating the conjectures. With a deeper look into connection between some of these graphs and algebraic geometry, we discover that projective cube of dimension 4, widely known as the Clebsh graph, but also known as Greenwood-Gleason graph, is the intersection graph of the 16 straight lines of an algebraic surface known as Segre surface, which is a Del Pezzo surface of degree 4. We note that an algebraic surface known as the Clebsch surface is one of the most symmetric presentations of a cubic surface. Recall that each smooth cubic surface contains 27 lines. Hence, from hereafter, we believe, a proper name for this graph should be Segre graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10814v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meirun Chen, Reza Naserasr, Alessandra Sarti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ungar Games on the Young-Fibonacci and the Shifted Staircase Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2023, Defant and Li introduced the Ungar move, which sends an element $v$ of a finite meet-semilattice $L$ to the meet of some subset of the elements covered by $v$. More recently, Defant, Kravitz, and Williams introduced the Ungar game on $L$, in which two players take turns making Ungar moves starting from an element of $L$ until the player that cannot make a nontrivial Ungar move loses. In this note, we settle two conjectures by Defant, Kravitz, and Williams on the Ungar games on the Young-Fibonacci lattice and the lattices of the order ideals of shifted staircases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10927v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunseo Choi, Katelyn Gan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing alphabet reduction pairs of arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In [1], we introduced a family of combinatorial designs, which we call "alphabet reduction pairs of arrays", ARPAs for short. These designs depend on three integer parameters $q, p \leq q, k\leq p$: $q$ is the size of the symbol set $\{0, 1 ,\ldots, q -1\}$ in which the coefficients of the arrays take their values; $p$ is the maximum number of distinct symbols allowed in a row of the second array of the pair; $k$ is the larger integer for which the two arrays of the pair coincide -- up to the order of their rows -- on any $k$-ary subset of their columns. The first array must contain at least one occurrence of the word $0\ 1\ \ldots\ q -1$. Intuitively, the idea is to cover "as many as possible" occurrences of this word of $q$ symbols with "as few as possible" words of at most $p$ different symbols.
  These designs are related to the approximability of "Constraint Satisfaction Problems with bounded constraint arity", known as $k\,$CSPs. In this context, we are particularly interested in ARPAs in which the frequency of the word $0\ 1\ \ldots\ q -1$ is maximal.
  We introduce a seemingly simpler family of combinatorial designs as "Cover pairs of arrays" (CPAs). The arrays of a CPA take Boolean coefficients, and must still coincide on any $k$-ary subset of their columns. The purpose is, as it were, to cover "as many as possible" occurrences of the word of $q$ ones using "as few as possible" $q$-length Boolean words of weight at most $p$. We show that, when it comes to maximizing the frequency of the words $0\ 1\ \ldots\ q -1$ in ARPAs and $1\ 1\ \ldots\ 1$ in CPAs, ARPAs and CPAs are equivalent. We prove the optimality of the ARPAs given in [1] for the case $p =k$. In addition, we provide optimal ARPAs for the cases $k =1$ and $k =2$. We emphasize the fact that both families of combinatorial designs are related to the approximability of $k\,$CSPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10930v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Culus, Sophie Toulouse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inequalities for $k$-regular partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build upon the work by Bessenrodt and Ono, as well as Beckwith and Bessenrodt concerning the combined additive and multiplicative behavior of the $k$-regular partition functions $p_k(n)$. Our focus is on addressing the solutions of the Bessenrodt--Ono inequality \begin{equation*} p_k(a) \, p_k(b) &gt; p_k(a+b). \end{equation*} We determine the sets $E_k$ and $F_k$ consisting of all pairs $(a,b)$, where we have equality or the opposite inequality. Bessenrodt and Ono previously determined the exception sets $E_{\infty}$ and $F_{\infty}$ for the partition function $p(n)$. We prove by induction that $E_k=E_{\infty}$ and $F_k=F_{\infty}$ if and only if $k \geq 10$. Beckwith and Bessenrodt used analytic methods to consider $2 \leq k \leq 6$, while Alanazi, Gagola, and Munagi studied the case $k=2$ using combinatorial methods. Finally, we present a precise and comprehensive conjecture on the log-concavity of the $k$-regular partition function extending previous speculations by Craig and Pun. The case $k=2$ was recently proven by Dong and Ji.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10987v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernhard Heim, Markus Neuhauser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotically Optimal Threshold Bias for the $(a : b)$ Maker-Breaker Minimum Degree, Connectivity and Hamiltonicity Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the $(a:b)$ Maker-Breaker subgraph game played on the edges of the complete graph $K_n$ on $n$ vertices, $n,a,b \in \mathbb{N}$ where the goal of Maker is to build a copy of a specific fixed subgraph $H$. In our work this is a spanning graph with minimum degree $k=k(n)$, a connected spanning subgraph or a Hamiltonian subgraph. In the $(a:b)$ game in each round Maker chooses $a$ unclaimed edges of $K_n$ and Breaker chooses $b$ unclaimed edges. Maker wins, if he succeeds to build a copy of the subgraph under consideration, otherwise Breaker wins. For the $k$-minimum-degree, we present a winning strategy for Maker leading to a bound that generalizes a bound of Gebauer and Szab{\'o} for the $(1:b)$ case. Moreover, we give an explicit strategy for Breaker for $b &gt;(1+o(1)) \frac{an}{a+\ln(n)}$ in case of $a=o\left(\sqrt{\frac{n}{\ln(n)}}\right)$ and $k=o(\ln(n))$. Note that this bound is the same as the Maker bound presented by Hefetz et al. (2012) for the $(a:b)$ connectivity game, which implies that the asymptotic optimal bias for this game is $\frac{an}{a+\ln(n)}$. This resolves the open problem stated by these authors. We also study the $(a:b)$ Hamiltonicity game in which Maker's goal is to create a Hamiltonian subgraph. For the $(1:b)$ variant Krivelevich proved that $\left(1+o(1) \right)\frac{n}{\ln n}$ is the exact threshold bias. Controlling Breaker's vertex degree in the $(a:b)$ Maker-Breaker minimum degree game enables us to the asymptotic optimal generalized threshold bias for the $(a:b)$-game, both for $a=o\left(\sqrt{\frac{n}{\ln n}} \right)$ and $a=\Omega\left(\sqrt{\frac{n}{\ln n}} \right)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11051v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adnane Fouadi, Mourad El Ouali, Anand Srivastav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix periods and competition periods of Boolean Toeplitz matrices II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is a follow-up to the paper [Matrix periods and competition periods of Boolean Toeplitz matrices, {\it Linear Algebra Appl.} 672:228--250, (2023)]. Given subsets $S$ and $T$ of $\{1,\ldots,n-1\}$, an $n\times n$ Toeplitz matrix $A=T_n\langle S ; T \rangle$ is defined to have $1$ as the $(i,j)$-entry if and only if $j-i \in S$ or $i-j \in T$. In the previous paper, we have shown that the matrix period and the competition period of Toeplitz matrices $A=T_n\langle S; T \rangle$ satisfying the condition ($\star$) $\max S+\min T \le n$ and $\min S+\max T \le n$ are $d^+/d$ and $1$, respectively, where $d^+= \gcd (s+t \mid s \in S, t \in T)$ and $d = \gcd(d, \min S)$. In this paper, we claim that even if ($\star$) is relaxed to the existence of elements $s \in S$ and $t \in T$ satisfying $s+t \le n$ and $\gcd(s,t)=1$, the same result holds. There are infinitely many Toeplitz matrices that do not satisfy ($\star$) but the relaxed condition. For example, for any positive integers $k, n$ with $2k+1 \le n$, it is easy to see that $T_n\langle k, n-k;k+1, n-k-1 \rangle$ does not satisfies ($\star$) but satisfies the relaxed condition. Furthermore, we show that the limit of the matrix sequence $\{A^m(A^T)^m\}_{m=1}^\infty$ is $T_n\langle d^+,2d^+, \ldots, \lfloor n/d^+\rfloor d^+\rangle$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11113v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gi-Sang Cheon, Bumtle Kang, Suh-Ryung Kim, Homoon Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetical Structures on Coconut Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11183v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If G is a finite connected graph, then an arithmetical structure on $G$ is a pair of vectors $(\mathbf{d}, \mathbf{r})$ with positive integer entries such that $(\diag(\mathbf{d}) - A)\cdot \mathbf{r} = \mathbf{0}$, where $A$ is the adjacency matrix of $G$ and the entries of $\mathbf{r}$ have no common factor other than $1$. In this paper, we generalize the result of Archer, Bishop, Diaz-Lopez, Garc\'ia Puente, Glass, and Louwsma on enumerating arithmetical structures on bidents (also called coconut tree graphs $\CT{p}{2}$) to all coconut tree graphs $\CT{p}{s}$ which consists of a path on $p&gt;0$ vertices to which we append $s&gt;0$ leaves to the right most vertex on the path. We also give a characterization of smooth arithmetical structures on coconut trees when given number assignments to the leaf nodes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11183v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Diaz-Lopez, Brian Ha, Pamela E. Harris, Jonathan Rogers, Theo Koss, Dorian Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Bounds on the Energy of Graphs with Self-Loops regarding $\lambda_{1}$ and $\lambda_{n}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G_{S}$ be a graph with $n$ vertices obtained from a simple graph $G$ by attaching one self-loop at each vertex in $S \subseteq V(G)$. The energy of $G_{S}$ is defined by Gutman et al. as $E(G_{S})=\sum_{i=1}^{n}\left| \lambda_{i} -\frac{\sigma}{n} \right|$, where $\lambda_{1},\dots,\lambda_{n}$ are the adjacency eigenvalues of $G_{S}$ and $\sigma$ is the number of self-loops of $G_{S}$. In this paper, several upper and lower bounds of $E(G_{S})$ regarding $\lambda_{1}$ and $\lambda_{n}$ are obtained. Especially, the upper bound $E(G_{S}) \leq \sqrt{n\left(2m+\sigma-\frac{\sigma^{2}}{n}\right)}$ $(\ast)$ given by Gutman et al. is improved to the following bound
  \begin{align*}
  E(G_{S})\leq \sqrt{n\left(2m+\sigma-\frac{\sigma^{2}}{n}\right)-\frac{n}{2}\left(\left |\lambda_{1}-\frac{\sigma}{n}\right |-\left |\lambda_{n}-\frac{\sigma}{n}\right |\right)^{2}},
  \end{align*} where $\left| \lambda_{1}-\frac{\sigma}{n}\right| \geq \dots \geq \left| \lambda_{n}-\frac{\sigma}{n}\right|$. Moreover, all graphs are characterized when the equality holds in Gutmans' bound $(\ast)$ by using this new bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11412v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghua Li, Yue Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of quasi-trees of bouquets with exactly one non-orientable loop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, Merino extended the classical relation between the $2n$-th Fibonacci number and the number of spanning trees of the $n$-fan graph to ribbon graphs, and established a relation between the $n$-associated Mersenne number and the number of quasi-trees of the $n$-wheel ribbon graph. Moreover, Merino posed a problem of finding the Lucas numbers as the number of spanning quasi-trees of a family of ribbon graphs. In this paper, we solve the problem and give the Matrix-Quasi-tree Theorem for a bouquet with exactly one non-orientable loop. Furthermore, this theorem is used to verify that the number of quasi-trees of some classes of bouquets is closely related to the Fibonacci and Lucas numbers. We also give alternative proofs of the number of quasi-trees of these bouquets by using the deletion-contraction relations of ribbon graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11648v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingying Deng, Xian'an Jin, Qi Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Independent [k]-Roman Domination on Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a function $f\colon V(G) \to \mathbb{Z}_{\geq 0}$ on a graph $G$, $AN(v)$ denotes the set of neighbors of $v \in V(G)$ that have positive labels under $f$. In 2021, Ahangar et al.~introduced the notion of $[k]$-Roman Dominating Function ([$k$]-RDF) of a graph $G$, which is a function $f\colon V(G) \to \{0,1,\ldots,k+1\}$ such that $\sum_{u \in N[v]}f(u) \geq k + |AN(v)|$ for all $v \in V(G)$ with $f(v)&lt;k$. The weight of $f$ is $\sum_{v \in V(G)}f(v)$. The $[k]$-Roman domination number, denoted by $\gamma_{[kR]}(G)$, is the minimum weight of a $[k]$-RDF of $G$. The notion of [$k$]-RDF for $k=1$ has been extensively investigated in the scientific literature since 2004, when introduced by Cockayne et al. as Roman Domination. An independent [$k$]-Roman dominating function ([$k$]-IRDF) $f\colon V(G) \to \{0,1,\ldots,k+1\}$ of a graph $G$ is a [$k$]-RDF of $G$ such that the set of vertices with positive labels is an independent set. The independent [$k$]-Roman domination number of $G$ is the minimum weight of a [$k$]-IRDF of $G$ and is denoted by $i_{[kR]}(G)$. In this paper, we propose the study of independent [$k$]-Roman domination on graphs for arbitrary $k \geq 1$. We prove that, for all $k\geq 3$, the decision problems associated with $i_{[kR]}(G)$ and $\gamma_{[kR]}(G)$ are NP-complete for planar bipartite graphs with maximum degree 3. We also present lower and upper bounds for $i_{[kR]}(G)$. Moreover, we present lower and upper bounds for the parameter $i_{[kR]}(G)$ for two families of 3-regular graphs called generalized Blanu\v{s}a snarks and Loupekine snarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11688v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>At\'ilio Gomes Luiz, Francisco Anderson Silva Vieira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domino tilings of three-dimensional cylinders: regularity of hamiltonian disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider tree-dimensional domino tilings of cylinders $\mathcal{D} \times [0,N] \subset \mathbb{R}^3$, where $\mathcal{D} \subset \mathbb{R}^2$ is a balanced quadriculated disk and $N \in \mathbb{N}$. A flip is a local move in the space of tilings: two adjacent and parallel dominoes are removed and then replaced in a different position. The twist is a flip invariant that associates an integer number to a domino tiling. A disk $\mathcal{D}$ is called regular if any two tilings of $\mathcal{D} \times [0,N]$ sharing the same twist can be connected trough a sequence of flips once extra vertical space is added to the cylinder. We prove that hamiltonian disks with narrow and small bottlenecks are regular. In particular, we show that the absence of a bottleneck in a hamiltonian disk implies regularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11777v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael de Marreiros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive generalization of the Friendship Paradox to weights and attributes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10423v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Friendship Paradox is a simple and powerful statement about node degrees in a graph (Feld 1991). However, it only applies to undirected graphs with no edge weights, and the only node characteristic it concerns is degree. Since many social networks are more complex than that, it is useful to generalize this phenomenon, if possible, and a number of papers have proposed different generalizations. Here, we unify these generalizations in a common framework, retaining the focus on undirected graphs and allowing for weighted edges and for numeric node attributes other than degree to be considered, since this extension allows for a clean characterization and links to the original concepts most naturally. While the original Friendship Paradox and the Weighted Friendship Paradox hold for all graphs, considering non-degree attributes actually makes the extensions fail around 50% of the time, given random attribute assignment. We provide simple correlation-based rules to see whether an attribute-based version of the paradox holds. In addition to theory, our simulation and data results show how all the concepts can be applied to synthetic and real networks. Where applicable, we draw connections to prior work to make this an accessible and comprehensive paper that lets one understand the math behind the Friendship Paradox and its basic extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10423v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-024-63167-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci Rep 14, 13730 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anna Evtushenko, Jon Kleinberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponentiable linear orders need not be transitive</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is well-known that every transitive linear order is exponentiable. However, is the converse true? This question was posed in Chapter 8 of the textbook titled "Linear Orderings" by Rosenstein. We define the class CTLO of cyclically transitive linear orders that properly contains the class of transitive linear orders, and show that all discrete unbounded orders in CTLO are exponentiable, thereby providing a negative answer to the question. The class CTLO is closely related to the class of transitive cyclic orders introduced by Droste, Giraudet and Macpherson. We also discuss the closure of subclasses of CTLO under products and iterated Hausdorff condensations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10532v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihir Mittal, Amit Kuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing Non-Repetitive Sequences with a Computable Lefthanded Local Lemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The lefthanded Lov\'asz local lemma (LLLL) is a generalization of the Lov\'asz local lemma (LLL), powerful technique from the probabilistic method. We prove a computable version of the LLLL and use it to effectivize a collection of results on the existence of certain types of non-repetitive sequences via the LLL and LLLL. This represents the first constructive proof of these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10564v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Mourad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Honeycomb Conjecture in normed planes and an alpha-convex variant of a theorem of Dowker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Honeycomb Conjecture states that among tilings with unit area cells in the Euclidean plane, the average perimeter of a cell is minimal for a regular hexagonal tiling. This conjecture was proved by L. Fejes T\'oth for convex tilings, and by Hales for not necessarily convex tilings. In this paper we investigate the same question for tilings of a given normed plane, and show that among normal, convex tilings in a normed plane, the average squared perimeter of a cell is minimal for a tiling whose cells are translates of a centrally symmetric hexagon. We also show that the question whether the same statement is true for the average perimeter of a cell is closely related to an $\alpha$-convex variant of a theorem of Dowker on the area of polygons circumscribed about a convex disk. Exploring this connection we find families of norms in which the average perimeter of a cell of a tiling is minimal for a hexagonal tiling, and prove some additonal related results. Finally, we apply our method to give a partial answer to a problem of Steinhaus about the isoperimetric ratios of cells of certain tilings in the Euclidean plane, appeared in an open problem book of Croft, Falconer and Guy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10622v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zsolt L\'angi, Shanshan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On entropy Marton-type inequalities and small symmetric differences with cosets of abelian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We recognise that an entropy inequality akin to the main intermediate goal of recent works (Gowers, Green, Manners, Tao [3],[2]) regarding a conjecture of Marton provides a black box from which we can also through a short deduction recover another description: if a finite subset $A$ of an abelian group $G$ is such that the distribution of the sums $a+b$ with $(a,b) \in A \times A$ is only slightly more spread out than the uniform distribution on $A$, then $A$ has small symmetric difference with some finite coset of $G$. The resulting bounds are necessarily sharp up to a logarithmic factor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10872v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Karam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbation-Resilient Sets for Dynamic Service Balancing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11075v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A combinatorial trade is a pair of sets of blocks of elements that can be exchanged while preserving relevant subset intersection constraints. The class of balanced and swap-robust minimal trades was proposed in [1] for exchanging blocks of data chunks stored on distributed storage systems in an access- and load-balanced manner. More precisely, data chunks in the trades of interest are labeled by popularity ranks and the blocks are required to have both balanced overall popularity and stability properties with respect to swaps in chunk popularities. The original construction of such trades relied on computer search and paired balanced sets obtained through iterative combining of smaller sets that have provable stability guarantees. To reduce the substantial gap between the results of prior approaches and the known theoretical lower bound, we present new analytical upper and lower bounds on the minimal disbalance of blocks introduced by limited-magnitude popularity ranking swaps. Our constructive and near-optimal approach relies on pairs of graphs whose vertices are two balanced sets with edges/arcs that capture the balance and potential balance changes induced by limited-magnitude popularity swaps. In particular, we show that if we start with carefully selected balanced trades and limit the magnitude of rank swaps to one, the new upper and lower bound on the maximum block disbalance caused by a swap only differ by a factor of $1.07$. We also extend these results for larger popularity swap magnitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11075v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Sima, Chao Pan, Olgica Milenkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Treewidth Inapproximability and Tight ETH Lower Bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a simple, self-contained, linear reduction from 3-SAT to Treewidth. Specifically, it shows that 1.00005-approximating Treewidth is NP-hard, and solving Treewidth exactly requires $2^{\Omega(n)}$ time, unless the Exponential-Time Hypothesis fails. We further derive, under the latter assumption, that there is some constant $\delta &gt; 1$ such that $\delta$-approximating Treewidth requires time $2^{n^{1-o(1)}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11628v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Edouard Bonnet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial proof for the rationality of the bivariate generating series of maps in positive genus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2007.07692v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we give the first combinatorial proof of a rationality scheme for the generating series of maps in positive genus enumerated by both vertices and faces, which was first obtained by Bender, Canfield and Richmond in 1993 by purely computational techniques. To do so, we rely on a bijection obtained by the second author in a previous work between those maps and a family of decorated unicellular maps. Our main contribution consists in a fine analysis of this family of maps. As a byproduct, we also obtain a new and simpler combinatorial proof of the rationality scheme for the generating series of maps enumerated by their number of edges, originally obtained computationally by Bender and Canfield in 1991 and combinatorially by the second author in 2019.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2007.07692v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marie Albenque, Mathias Lepoutre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variants of the Gy\`arf\`as-Sumner Conjecture: Oriented Trees and Rainbow Paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.13115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.13115v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a finite family $\mathcal{F}$ of graphs, we say that a graph $G$ is "$\mathcal{F}$-free" if $G$ does not contain any graph in $\mathcal{F}$ as a subgraph. A vertex-colored graph $H$ is called "rainbow" if no two vertices of $H$ have the same color. Given an integer $s$ and a finite family of graphs $\mathcal{F}$, let $\ell(s,\mathcal{F})$ denote the smallest integer such that any properly vertex-colored $\mathcal{F}$-free graph $G$ having $\chi(G)\geq\ell(s,\mathcal{F})$ contains an induced rainbow path on $s$ vertices. Scott and Seymour showed that $\ell(s,K)$ exists for every complete graph $K$. A conjecture of N. R. Aravind states that $\ell(s,C_3)=s$. The upper bound on $\ell(s,C_3)$ that can be obtained using the methods of Scott and Seymour setting $K=C_3$ are, however, super-exponential. Gy\'arf\'as and S\'ark\"ozy showed that $\ell(s,\{C_3,C_4\})=\mathcal{O}\big((2s)^{2s}\big)$. For $r\geq 2$, we show that $\ell(s,K_{2,r})\leq (r-1)(s-1)(s-2)/2+s$ and therefore, $\ell(s,C_4)\leq\frac{s^2-s+2}{2}$. This significantly improves Gy\'arf\'as and S\'ark\"ozy's bound and also covers a bigger class of graphs. We adapt our proof to achieve much stronger upper bounds for graphs of higher girth: we prove that $\ell(s,\{C_3,C_4,\ldots,C_{g-1}\})\leq s^{1+\frac{4}{g-4}}$, where $g\geq 5$. Moreover, in each case, our results imply the existence of at least $s!/2$ distinct induced rainbow paths on $s$ vertices. Along the way, we obtain some results on related problems on oriented graphs. For $r\geq 2$, let $\mathcal{B}_r$ denote the orientations of $K_{2,r}$ in which one vertex has out-degree or in-degree $r$. We show that every $\mathcal{B}_r$-free oriented graph $G$ having $\chi(G)\geq (r-1)(s-1)(s-2)+2s+1$ and every bikernel-perfect oriented graph $G$ with girth $g\geq 5$ having $\chi(G)\geq 2s^{1+\frac{4}{g-4}}$ contains every $s$ vertex oriented tree as an induced subgraph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.13115v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manu Basavaraju, L. Sunil Chandran, Mathew C. Francis, Karthik Murali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distribution of similar configurations in subsets of $\mathbb{F}_q^d$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.11579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.11579v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb{F}_q$ be a finite field of order $q$ and $E$ be a set in $\mathbb{F}_q^d$. The distance set of $E$ is defined by $\Delta(E):=\{\lVert x-y \rVert :x,y\in E\}$, where $\lVert \alpha \rVert=\alpha_1^2+\dots+\alpha_d^2$. Iosevich, Koh and Parshall (2018) proved that if $d\geq 2$ is even and $|E|\geq 9q^{d/2}$, then $$\mathbb{F}_q= \frac{\Delta(E)}{\Delta(E)}=\left\{\frac{a}{b}: a\in \Delta(E),\ b\in \Delta(E)\setminus\{0\} \right\}.$$ In other words, for each $r\in \mathbb{F}_q^*$ there exist $(x,y)\in E^2$ and $(x',y')\in E^2$ such that $\lVert x-y\rVert\neq0$ and $\lVert x'-y' \rVert=r\lVert x-y\rVert$.
  Geometrically, this means that if the size of $E$ is large, then for any given $r \in \mathbb{F}_q^*$ we can find a pair of edges in the complete graph $K_{|E|}$ with vertex set $E$ such that one of them is dilated by $r\in \mathbb{F}_q^*$ with respect to the other. A natural question arises whether it is possible to generalize this result to arbitrary subgraphs of $K_{|E|}$ with vertex set $E$ and this is the goal of this paper.
  In this paper, we solve this problem for $k$-paths $(k\geq 2)$, simplexes and 4-cycles. We are using a mix of tools from different areas such as enumerative combinatorics, group actions and Tur\'an type theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.11579v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.disc.2023.113571</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete Mathematics, Volume 346, Issue 10, October 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Firdavs Rakhmonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directed graphs with lower orientation Ramsey thresholds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the threshold $p_{\vec H}=p_{\vec H}(n)$ for the Ramsey-type property $G(n,p)\to \vec H$, where $G(n,p)$ is the binomial random graph and $G\to\vec H$ indicates that every orientation of the graph $G$ contains the oriented graph $\vec H$ as a subdigraph. Similarly to the classical Ramsey setting, the upper bound $p_{\vec H}\leq Cn^{-1/m_2(\vec H)}$ is known to hold for some constant $C=C(\vec H)$, where $m_2(\vec H)$ denotes the maximum $2$-density of the underlying graph $H$ of $\vec H$. While this upper bound is indeed the threshold for some $\vec H$, this is not always the case. We obtain examples arising from rooted products of orientations of sparse graphs (such as forests, cycles and, more generally, subcubic $\{K_3,K_{3,3}\}$-free graphs) and arbitrarily rooted transitive triangles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07033v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Ferreira Barros, Bruno Pasqualotto Cavalar, Yoshiharu Kohayakawa, Guilherme Oliveira Mota, T\'assio Naia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legendre theorems for a class of partitions with initial repetitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.10756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.10756v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Partitions with initial repetitions were introduced by George Andrews. We consider a subclass of these partitions and find Legendre theorems associated with their respective partition functions. The results in turn provide partition theoretic interpretations of some Rogers-Ramanujan identities due to Lucy J. Slater.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.10756v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darlison Nyirenda, Beaullah Mugwangwavari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterisation of the big Ramsey degrees of the generic partial order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10088v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As a result of 33 intercontinental Zoom calls, we characterise big Ramsey degrees of the generic partial order. This is an infinitary extension of the well known fact that finite partial orders endowed with linear extensions form a Ramsey class (this result was announced by Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il and R\"odl in 1984 with first published proof by Paoli, Trotter and Walker in 1985). Towards this, we refine earlier upper bounds obtained by Hubi\v{c}ka based on a new connection of big Ramsey degrees to the Carlson-Simpson theorem and we also introduce a new technique of giving lower bounds using an iterated application of the upper-bound theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10088v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Balko, David Chodounsk\'y, Natasha Dobrinen, Jan Hubi\v{c}ka, Mat\v{e}j Kone\v{c}n\'y, Lluis Vena, Andy Zucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A relation between the cube polynomials of partial cubes and the clique polynomials of their crossing graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14671v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Partial cubes are the graphs which can be embedded into hypercubes. The {\em cube polynomial} of a graph $G$ is a counting polynomial of induced hypercubes of $G$, which is defined as $C(G,x):=\sum_{i\geqslant 0}\alpha_i(G)x^i$, where $\alpha_i(G)$ is the number of induced $i$-cubes (hypercubes of dimension $i$) of $G$. The {\em clique polynomial} of $G$ is defined as $Cl(G,x):=\sum_{i\geqslant 0}a_i(G)x^i$, where $a_i(G)$ ($i\geqslant 1$) is the number of $i$-cliques in $G$ and $a_0(G)=1$. Equivalently, $Cl(G, x)$ is exactly the independence polynomial of the complement $\overline{G}$ of $G$. The {\em crossing graph} $G^{\#}$ of a partial cube $G$ is the graph whose vertices are corresponding to the $\Theta$-classes of $G$, and two $\Theta$-classes are adjacent in $G^{\#}$ if and only if they cross in $G$. In the present paper, we prove that for a partial cube $G$, $C(G,x)\leqslant Cl(G^{\#}, x+1)$ and the equality holds if and only if $G$ is a median graph. Since every graph can be represented as the crossing graph of a median graph [SIAM J. Discrete Math., 15 (2002) 235--251], the above necessary-and-sufficient result shows that the study on the cube polynomials of median graphs can be transformed to the one on the clique polynomials of general graphs (equivalently, on the independence polynomials of their complements). In addition, we disprove the conjecture that the cube polynomials of median graphs are unimodal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14671v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/jgt.23099</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Graph Theory, 106 (2024) 907-922</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Ting Xie, Yong-De Feng, Shou-Jun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of matching complexes of complete graphs via discrete Morse theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02973v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bouc first studied the topological properties of the matching complex of the complete graph of order $n$, denoted by $M_n$, in connection with Brown complexes and Quillen complexes. Later Bj\"{o}rner et al. showed that $M_n$ is homotopically $(\nu_n-1)$-connected, where $\nu_n=\lfloor{\frac{n+1}{3}}\rfloor-1$, and conjectured that this connectivity bound is sharp. Shareshian and Wachs settled the conjecture by inductively showing that the $\nu_n$-dimensional homology group of $M_n$ is nontrivial, with Bouc's calculation $H_1(M_7)$ serving as the pivotal base step. In general, the topology of $M_n$ is not very well-understood, even for a small $n$. In the present article, we look into the topology of $M_n$, and $M_7$ in particular, in the light of discrete Morse theory as developed by Forman. We first construct a gradient vector field on $M_n$ (for $n \ge 5$) that doesn't admit any critical simplices of dimension up to $\nu_n-1$, except one unavoidable $0$-simplex, which also leads to the aforementioned $(\nu_n-1)$-connectedness of $M_n$ in a purely combinatorial way. However, for an efficient homology computation by discrete Morse theoretic techniques, we are required to work with a gradient vector field that admits a low number of critical simplices, and also allows an efficient enumeration of gradient paths. An optimal gradient vector field is one with the least number of critical simplices, but the problem of finding an optimal gradient vector field, in general, is an NP-hard problem (even for $2$-dimensional complexes). We improve the gradient vector field constructed on $M_7$ in particular to a much more efficient (near-optimal) one, and then with the help of this improved gradient vector field, compute the homology groups of $M_7$ in an efficient and algorithmic manner. We also augment this near-optimal gradient vector field to one that we conjecture to be optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02973v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anupam Mondal, Sajal Mukherjee, Kuldeep Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A characterization of positroids, with applications to amalgams and excluded minors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.06694v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A matroid of rank $r$ on $n$ elements is a positroid if it has a representation by an $r$ by $n$ matrix over $\mathbb{R}$, each $r$ by $r$ submatrix of which has nonnegative determinant. Earlier characterizations of connected positroids and results about direct sums of positroids involve connected flats and non-crossing partitions. We prove another characterization of positroids of a similar flavor and give some applications of the characterization. We show that if $M$ and $N$ are positroids and $E(M)\cap E(N)$ is an independent set and a set of clones in both $M$ and $N$, then the free amalgam of $M$ and $N$ is a positroid, and we prove a second result of that type. Also, we identify several multi-parameter infinite families of excluded minors for the class of positroids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.06694v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph E. Bonin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying constraint programming to minimal lottery designs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12430v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop and deploy a set of constraints for the purpose of calculating minimal sizes of lottery designs. Specifically, we find the minimum number of tickets of size six which are needed to match at least two balls on any draw of size six, whenever there are at most 70 balls.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12430v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Cushing, David I. Stewart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demazure crystals for flagged key polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.17025v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One definition of key polynomials is as the weight generating functions of key tableaux. Assaf and Schilling introduced a crystal structure on key tableaux and related it to Morse--Schilling crystals on reduced factorizations for permutations via weak Edelman--Greene insertion. In this paper, we consider generalizations of both crystals depending on a flag. We extend weak EG insertion to a bijection between our flagged objects and show that the recording tableau gives a crystal isomorphism. As an application, we show that flagged key tableaux have a natural Demazure crystal structure, whose characters recover Reiner and Shimozono's flagged key polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.17025v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long increasing subsequences and non-algebraicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13649v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use a recent result of Alin Bostan to prove that the generating functions of two infinite sequences of permutation classes are not algebraic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13649v5</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miklos Bona</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect codes in 2-valent Cayley digraphs on abelian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19017v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a digraph $\Gamma$, a subset $C$ of $V(\Gamma)$ is a perfect code if $C$ is a dominating set such that every vertex of $\Gamma$ is dominated by exactly one vertex in $C$. In this paper, we classify strongly connected 2-valent Cayley digraphs on abelian groups admitting a perfect code, and determine completely all perfect codes of such digraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19017v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilong Yu, Yuefeng Yang, Yushuang Fan, Xuanlong Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heffter Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03940v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The notion of a Heffter array, which received much attention in the last decade, is equivalent to a pair of orthogonal Heffter systems. In this paper we study the existence problem of a set of $r$ mutually orthogonal Heffter systems for any $r$. Such a set is equivalent to a resolvable partial linear space of degree $r$ whose parallel classes are Heffter systems: this is a new combinatorial design that we call a Heffter space. We present a series of direct constructions of Heffter spaces with block size odd and arbitrarily large degree $r$ obtained with the crucial use of finite fields. Among the applications we establish, in particular, the existence of $r$ mutually orthogonal $k$-cycle systems of order a prime power $q=2kw+1$ whenever $kw$ is odd and $w&gt;4k^4\lceil{r\over k}\rceil$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03940v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Buratti, Anita Pasotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cartesian products of two $CR$ sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.09053v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The notions of CR set is intimately related with the generalized van der Waerden's theorem. In this article, we prove the product of two CR sets is again a CR set. This answers [Question 4.2., N. Hindman, H. Hosseini, D. Strauss, and M. Tootkaboni: Combinatorially rich sets in arbitrary semigroups, Semigroup Forum, 107 (2023), 127-143.] . We use combinatorial arguments to prove our result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.09053v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grid-drawings of graphs in three-dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02369v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using probabilistic methods, we obtain grid-drawings of graphs without crossings with low volume and small aspect ratio. We show that every $D$-degenerate graph on $n$ vertices can be drawn in $[m]^3$ where $m^3 = O(D^2 n\log n)$. In particular, every graph of bounded maximum degree can be drawn in a grid with volume $O(n \log n)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02369v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jozsef Balogh, Ethan Patrick White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caps and Wickets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $H_n^{(3)}$ be a 3-uniform linear hypergraph, i.e. any two edges have at most one vertex common. A special hypergraph, {\em wicket}, is formed by three rows and two columns of a $3 \times 3$ point matrix. In this note, we give a new lower bound on the Tur\'an number of wickets using estimates on cap sets. We also show that this problem is closely connected to important questions in additive combinatorics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00923v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jozsef Solymosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizers, Measures and IP-sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07252</link>
      <description>arXiv:1912.07252v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this simple note is to provide elementary model-theoretic proofs to some existing results on sumset phenomena and IP sets, motivated by Hrushovski's work on the stabilizer theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1912.07252v5</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amador Martin-Pizarro, Daniel Palac\'in</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vinogradov three prime theorem with Piatetski-Shapiro primes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.12572</link>
      <description>arXiv:1912.12572v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that, for any $c_1,c_2,c_3\in(1,41/35)$, every sufficiently large odd number $N$ can be represented as the sum of three primes $N = p_1 + p_2 +p_3$ such that $p_i = \lfloor n_{i}^{c_i}\rfloor$ for some $n_i \in{\mathbb N}$ for each $1 \leq i \leq 3$. Our arguments are based on a variant of Green's transference principle due to Matom\"aki, Maynard and Shao. We prove a necessary restriction estimate using Bourgain's strategy and employ Harman's sieve method to optimize our upper bound for $c_i$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1912.12572v4</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Chen Sun, Shanshan Du, Hao Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Standard Monomials for Positroid Varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.15384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.15384v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give an explicit characterization of the standard monomials for positroid varieties with respect to the Hodge degeneration and give a Gr\"obner basis. Furthermore, we show that promotion and evacuation biject standard monomials of a positroid variety with those of its cyclic shifts and $w_0$-reflection, respectively. The connection to promotion allows us to identify standard monomials of a positroid variety with Lam's cyclic Demazure crystal. Using a recurrence on the Hilbert series, we give an inductive formula for the character of cyclic Demazure modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.15384v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayah Almousa, Shiliang Gao, Daoji Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New and Faster Representation for Counting Integer Points in Parametric Polyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13788v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the counting function $E_P(y) = |P_{y} \cap Z^{n_x}|$ for a parametric polyhedron $P_{y} = \{x \in R^{n_x} \colon A x \leq b + B y\}$, where $y \in R^{n_y}$. We give a new representation of $E_P(y)$, called a \emph{piece-wise step-polynomial with periodic coefficients}, which is a generalization of piece-wise step-polynomials and integer/rational Ehrhart's quasi-polynomials. It gives the fastest way to calculate $E_P(y)$ in certain scenarios. The most important cases are the following:
  1) We show that, for the parametric polyhedron $P_y$ defined by a standard-form system $A x = y,\, x \geq 0$ with a fixed number of equalities, the function $E_P(y)$ can be represented by a polynomial-time computable function. In turn, such a representation of $E_P(y)$ can be constructed by an $poly\bigl(n, \|A\|_{\infty}\bigr)$-time algorithm;
  2) Assuming again that the number of equalities is fixed, we show that integer/rational Ehrhart's quasi-polynomials of a polytope can be computed by FPT-algorithms, parameterized by sub-determinants of $A$ or its elements;
  3) Our representation of $E_P$ is more efficient than other known approaches, if $A$ has bounded elements, especially if it is sparse in addition.
  Additionally, we provide a discussion about possible applications in the area of compiler optimization. In some "natural" assumptions on a program code, our approach has the fastest complexity bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13788v5</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Gribanov, D. Malyshev, P. Pardalos, N. Zolotykh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euler characteristics of affine ADE Nakajima quiver varieties via collapsing fibers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.14361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.14361v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a universal substitution formula that compares generating series of Euler characteristics of Nakajima quiver varieties associated with affine ADE diagrams at generic and at certain nongeneric stability conditions via a study of collapsing fibres in the associated variation of GIT map, unifying and generalising earlier results of the last two authors with N\'emethi and of Nakajima. As a special case, we compute generating series of Euler characteristics of noncommutative Quot schemes of Kleinian orbifolds. In type A and rank 1, we give a second, combinatorial proof of our substitution formula, using torus localisation and partition enumeration. This gives a combinatorial model of the fibers of the variation of GIT map, and also leads to relations between our results and the representation theory of the affine and finite Lie algebras in type A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.14361v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Bertsch, \'Ad\'am Gyenge, Bal\'azs Szendr\H{o}i, S{\o}ren Gammelgaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analytic version of stable arithmetic regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14363v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a structure theorem for stable functions on amenable groups, which extends the arithmetic regularity lemma for stable subsets of finite groups. Given a group $G$, a function $f\colon G\to [-1,1]$ is called stable if the binary function $f(x\cdot y)$ is stable in the sense of continuous logic. Roughly speaking, our main result says that if $G$ is amenable, then any stable function on $G$ is almost constant on all translates of a unitary Bohr neighborhood in $G$ of bounded complexity. The proof uses ingredients from topological dynamics and continuous model theory. We also prove several applications which generalize results in arithmetic combinatorics to nonabelian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14363v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Conant, Anand Pillay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local limits of random bipartite maps in high genus: the general case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04524v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the local convergence of uniform bipartite maps with prescribed face degrees in the high genus regime. Unlike in the previous work arxiv:2012.05813 on the subject, we do not make any assumption on the tail of the face degrees, except that they remain finite in the limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04524v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Budzinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Square-Root Law Does Not Hold in the Presence of Zero Divisors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13248v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $R$ be a finite ring and define the paraboloid $P = \{(x_1, \dots, x_d)\in R^d|x_d = x_1^2 + \dots + x_{d-1}^2\}.$ Suppose that for a sequence of finite rings of size tending to infinity, the Fourier transform of $P$ satisfies a square-root law for some fixed constant $C$. Then all but finitely many of the rings are fields. Most of our argument works in greater generality: let $f$ be a polynomial with integer coefficients in $d-1$ variables, with a fixed order of variable multiplications (so that it defines a function $R^{d-1}\rightarrow R$ even when $R$ is noncommutative), and set $V_f = \{(x_1, \dots, x_d)\in R^d|x_d = f(x_1, \dots, x_{d-1})\}$. If (for a sequence of finite rings of size tending to infinity) we have a square root law for the Fourier transform of $V_f$, then all but finitely many of the rings are fields or matrix rings of small dimension. We also describe how our techniques let us see that certain varieties do not satisfy a square root law even over finite fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13248v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Kingsbury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bottlenecking in graphs and a coarse Menger-type theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07802v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We expand upon the notion of bottlenecking introduced in our earlier work, characterizing a spectrum of graphs and showing that this naturally extends to a concept of coarse bottlenecking. We examine how bottlenecking differs from other notions of connectedness. We show how the notion of bottlenecking provides a different approach to coarsening measures of connectedness than the Coarse Menger Conjecture proposed independently by Georgakopoulos and Papasoglu as well as Albrechtsen, Huynh, Jacobs, Knappe, and Wollan, which was recently disproved by a counterexample. We give a proof of a coarse Menger-type theorem for the class of coarsely bottlenecked graphs, and provide a conjecture that would extend this to all graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07802v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Bruner, Atish Mitra, Heidi Steiger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large deviations for the largest singular value of sparse non-Hermitian matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09851v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a large deviation principle for the largest singular value of sparse non-Hermitian random matrices, or directed Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi networks in the constant average degree regime $p =\frac{d}{n}$ where $d$ is fixed. Entries are assumed to have Weibull distributions with tail decaying at rate $e^{-t^{\alpha}}$ for $\alpha &gt;0$. While the law of large number results agree with the largest eigenvalue of sparse Hermitian matrices given in (Ganguly and Nam, '22) and (Ganguly, Hiesmayr and Nam, '22), large deviation results are surprisingly simpler, exhibiting a single transition at $\alpha =2$. The rate function for undirected networks with $0&lt;\alpha \leq 2$ involved a transition at $\alpha =1$ and a complicated variational formula due to the emergence of cliques with large edge-weights (Ganguly, Hiesmayr and Nam, '22). For directed networks, we introduce a clique reduction technique which reformulates the problem for undirected networks with maximum clique size $2$, and the rate function is greatly simplified. For $\alpha &gt;2$, both the law of large numbers and large deviation results are identical to the sparse Hermitian case. Our results easily generalize to rectangular i.i.d. ensembles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09851v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyungwon Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
