<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal obstructions to $C_5$-coloring in hereditary graph classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For graphs $G$ and $H$, an $H$-coloring of $G$ is an edge-preserving mapping from $V(G)$ to $V(H)$. Note that if $H$ is the triangle, then $H$-colorings are equivalent to $3$-colorings. In this paper we are interested in the case that $H$ is the five-vertex cycle $C_5$.
  A minimal obstruction to $C_5$-coloring is a graph that does not have a $C_5$-coloring, but every proper induced subgraph thereof has a $C_5$-coloring. In this paper we are interested in minimal obstructions to $C_5$-coloring in $F$-free graphs, i.e., graphs that exclude some fixed graph $F$ as an induced subgraph. Let $P_t$ denote the path on $t$ vertices, and let $S_{a,b,c}$ denote the graph obtained from paths $P_{a+1},P_{b+1},P_{c+1}$ by identifying one of their endvertices.
  We show that there is only a finite number of minimal obstructions to $C_5$-coloring among $F$-free graphs, where $F \in \{ P_8, S_{2,2,1}, S_{3,1,1}\}$ and explicitly determine all such obstructions. This extends the results of Kami\'nski and Pstrucha [Discr. Appl. Math. 261, 2019] who proved that there is only a finite number of $P_7$-free minimal obstructions to $C_5$-coloring, and of D\k{e}bski et al. [ISAAC 2022 Proc.] who showed that the triangle is the unique $S_{2,1,1}$-free minimal obstruction to $C_5$-coloring.
  We complement our results with a construction of an infinite family of minimal obstructions to $C_5$-coloring, which are simultaneously $P_{13}$-free and $S_{2,2,2}$-free. We also discuss infinite families of $F$-free minimal obstructions to $H$-coloring for other graphs $H$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11704v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Goedgebeur, Jorik Jooken, Karolina Okrasa, Pawe{\l} Rz\k{a}\.zewski, Oliver Schaudt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Number of Spanning Trees in some Special Self-Similar Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce two families of planar and self-similar graphs which have small-world properties. The constructed models are based on an iterative process where each step of a certain formulation of modules results in a final graph with a self-similar structure. The number of spanning trees of a graph is one of the most graph-theoretical parameters, where its applications range from the theory of networks to theoretical chemistry. Two explicit formulas are introduced for the number of spanning trees for the two models. With explicit formulas for some of their topological parameters as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11806v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammed Alaa Morsy, Mohamed Anwar, Abdallah Aboutahoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed volumes of matroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our aim in this article is to compute the mixed volume of a matroid. We give two computations. The first one is based on the integration formula for complete fans given by Brion. The second computation is a step-by-step method using deletion of elements in the matroid as in Braden-Huh-Matherne-Proudfoot-Wang.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11837v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andy Hsiao, Kalle Karu, Jonathan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Generic Circular Triangle-Free Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the generic circular triangle-free graph $\mathbb C_3$ and propose a finite axiomatization of its first order theory. In particular, our main results show that a countable graph $G$ embeds into $\mathbb C_3$ if and only if it is a $\{K_3, K_1 + 2K_2, K_1+C_5, C_6\}$-free graph. As a byproduct of this result, we obtain a geometric characterization of finite $\{K_3, K_1 + 2K_2, K_1+C_5, C_6\}$-free graphs, and the (finite) list of minimal obstructions of unit Helly circular-arc graphs with independence number strictly less than three.
  The circular chromatic number $\chi_c(G)$ is a refinement of the classical chromatic number $\chi(G)$. We construct $\mathbb C_3$ so that a graph $G$ has circular chromatic number strictly less than three if and only if $G$ maps homomorphically to $\mathbb C_3$. We build on our main results to show that $\chi_c(G) &lt; 3$ if and only if $G$ can be extended to a $\{K_3, K_1 + 2K_2, K_1+C_5, C_6\}$-free graph, and in turn, we use this result to reprove an old characterization of $\chi_c(G) &lt; 3$ due to Brandt (1999). Finally, we answer a question recently asked by Guzm\'an-Pro, Hell, and Hern\'andez-Cruz by showing that the problem of deciding for a given finite graph $G$ whether $\chi_c(G) &lt; 3$ is NP-complete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12082v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Bodirsky, Santiago Guzm\'an-Pro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum saturated graphs for unions of cliques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $H$ be a fixed graph. A graph $G$ is called {\it $H$-saturated} if $H$ is not a subgraph of $G$ but the addition of any missing edge to $G$ results in an $H$-subgraph. The {\it saturation number} of $H$, denoted $sat(n,H)$, is the minimum number of edges over all $H$-saturated graphs of order $n$, and $Sat(n,H)$ denote the family of $H$-saturated graphs with $sat(n,H)$ edges and $n$ vertices. In this paper, we resolve a conjecture of Chen and Yuan in[Discrete Math. 347(2024)113868] by determining $Sat(n,K_p\cup (t-1)K_q)$ for every $2\le p\le q$ and $t\ge 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12204v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Han Zhu, Rong-Xia Hao, Zhen He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operad structures on the species composition of two operads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an explicit description of three operad structures on the species composition $p \circ q$, where $q$ is any given positive operad, and where $p$ is the NAP operad, or a shuffle version of the magmatic operad Mag. No distributive law between $p$ and $q$ is assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12326v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imen Rjaiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments of the free Jacobi process: a matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11708v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute the large size limit of the moment formula derived in \cite{DHS} for the Hermitian Jacobi process at fixed time. In particular, we identify the terms contributing to the limit and show they satisfy a double recurrence relation. We also determine explicitly some of them and revisit a special case relying on Carlitz summation identity for terminating $1$-balanced ${}_4F_3$ functions taken at unity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11708v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nizar Demni, Tarek Hamdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximal Mumford Curves from Planar Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A curve of genus g is maximal Mumford (MM) if it has g+1 ovals and g tropical cycles. We construct full-dimensional families of MM curves in the Hilbert scheme of canonical curves. This rests on first-order deformations of graph curves whose graph is planar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11838v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Kummer, Bernd Sturmfels, Raluca Vlad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Mathematical Formalisation of the {\gamma}-contraction Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12080v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Networks play an ubiquitous role in computer science and real-world applications, offering multiple kind of information that can be retrieved with adequate methods. With the continuous growing in the amount of data available, networks are becoming larger day by day. Consequently, the tasks that were easily achievable on smaller networks, often becomes impractical on huge amount of data, either due to the high computational cost or due to the impracticality to visualise corresponding data. Using distinctive node features to group large amount of connected data into a limited number of clusters, hence represented by a representative per cluster, proves to be a valuable approach. The resulting contracted graphs are more manageable in size and can reveal previously hidden characteristics of the original networks. Furthermore, in many real-world use cases, a definition of cluster is intrinsic with the data, eventually obtained with the injection of some expert knowledge represent by a categorical function. Clusters then results in set of connected vertices taking the same values in a finite set C. In the recent literature, Lombardi and Onofri proposed a novel, fast, and easily parallelisable approach under the name of $\gamma$-contraction to contract a graph given a categorical function. In this work, we formally define such approach by providing a rigorous mathematical definition of the problem, which, to the best of our knowledge, was missing in the existing literature. Specifically, we explore the variadic nature of the contraction operation and use it to introduce the weaker version of the colour contraction, under the name of $\beta$-contraction, that the algorithmic solution exploits. We finally dive into the details of the algorithm and we provide a full assesment on its convergence complexity relying on two constructive proofs that deeply unveil its mode of operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12080v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elia Onofri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continued-fraction characterization of Stieltjes moment sequences with support in $[\xi, \infty)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a continued-fraction characterization of Stieltjes moment sequences for which there exists a representing measure with support in $[\xi, \infty)$. The proof is elementary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12131v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan D. Sokal, James Walrad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite sumsets of the form $B+B$ in sets with large density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12201v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a set $A \subset \mathbb{N}$ we characterize in terms of its density when there exists an infinite set $B \subset \mathbb{N}$ and $t \in \{0,1\}$ such that $B+B \subset A-t$, where $B+B : =\{b_1+b_2\colon b_1,b_2 \in B\}$. Specifically, when the lower density $\underline{d}(A) &gt;1/2$ or the upper density $\overline{d}(A)&gt; 3/4$, the existence of such a set $B\subset \mathbb{N}$ and $t\in \{0,1\}$ is assured. Furthermore, whenever $\underline{d}(A) &gt; 3/4$ or $\overline{d}(A)&gt;5/6$, we show that the shift $t$ is unnecessary and we also provide examples to show that these bounds are sharp. Finally, we construct a syndetic three-coloring of the natural numbers that does not contain a monochromatic $B+B+t$ for any infinite set $B \subset \mathbb{N}$ and number $t \in \mathbb{N}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12201v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis Kousec, Trist\'an Radi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A higher-dimensional version of F\'ary's theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12265v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a generalization of Istvan F\'ary's celebrated theorem to higher dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12265v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karim Adiprasito, Zuzana Pat\'akov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting maps between graphs to embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12287v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study conditions for the existence of an embedding $\widetilde{f} \colon P \to Q \times \mathbb{R}$ such that $f = \mathrm{pr}_Q \circ \widetilde{f}$, where $f \colon P \to Q$ is a piecewise linear map between polyhedra. Our focus is on non-degenerate maps between graphs, where non-degeneracy means that the preimages of points are finite sets.
  We introduce combinatorial techniques and establish necessary and sufficient conditions for the general case. Using these results, we demonstrate that the problem of the existence of a lifting reduces to testing the satisfiability of a 3-CNF formula. Additionally, we construct a counterexample to a result by V. Po\'{e}naru on lifting of smooth immersions to embeddings.
  Furthermore, by establishing connections between the stated problem and the approximability by embeddings, we deduce that, in the case of generic maps from a tree to a segment, a weaker condition becomes sufficient for the existence of a lifting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12287v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Gorelov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-sum multisets mod p with an application to surface automorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.02147</link>
      <description>arXiv:1703.02147v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We solve a problem in enumerative combinatorics which is equivalent to counting topological types of certain group actions on compact Riemann surfaces. Let $V_2(F_p)$ be the two-dimensional vector space over $F_p$, the field with $p$ elements, $p$ an odd prime. We count orbits of the general linear group $GL_2(F_p)$ on certain multisets consisting of $R \geq 3$ non-zero columns from $V_2(F_p)$. The $R$-multisets are `zero-sum,' that is, the sum (mod $p$) over the columns in the multiset is $[\begin{smallmatrix} 0 \\ 0 \end{smallmatrix}]$. The orbit count yields the number of topological types of fully ramified actions of the elementary abelian $p$-group of rank $2$ on compact Riemann surfaces of genus $1+ Rp(p-1)/2-p^2.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1703.02147v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Weaver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli Spaces of Pentagonal Subdivision Tilings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.08776</link>
      <description>arXiv:1907.08776v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pentagonal subdivision gives three families of edge-to-edge tilings of the sphere by congruent pentagons. Each family forms a two dimensional moduli. We describe the moduli in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1907.08776v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinjin Liang, Erxiao Wang, Min Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A characterization of $g_2$-minimal normal 3-pseudomanifolds with at most four singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.06582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.06582v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Delta$ be a $g_2$-minimal normal 3-pseudomanifold. A vertex in $\Delta$ whose link is not a sphere is called a singular vertex. When $\Delta$ contains at most two singular vertices, its combinatorial characterization is known [9]. In this article, we present a combinatorial characterization of such a $\Delta$ when it has three singular vertices, including one $\mathbb{RP}^2$-singularity, or four singular vertices, including two $\mathbb{RP}^2$-singularities. In both cases, we prove that $\Delta$ is obtained from a one-vertex suspension of a surface, and some boundary complexes of $4$-simplices by applying the combinatorial operations of types connected sums, vertex foldings, and edge foldings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.06582v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biplab Basak, Raju Kumar Gupta, Sourav Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjacency and Broadcast Dimension of Grid and Directed Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.11001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.11001v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a simple undirected graph. A function $f : V(G) \to \mathbb{Z}_{\geq 0}$ is a $\textit{resolving broadcast}$ of $G$ if for any distinct $x, y \in V(G)$, there exists a vertex $z \in V(G)$ with $f(z) &gt; 0$ such that $\min \{ d(z, x), f(z)+1 \} \neq \min \{ d(z, y), f(z)+1 \}$. The $\textit{broadcast dimension}$ $\text{bdim}(G)$ of $G$ is the minimum of $\sum_{v \in V(G)} f(v)$ over all resolving broadcasts $f$ of $G$. Similarly, the $\textit{adjacency dimension}$ $\text{adim}(G)$ of $G$ is the minimum of $\sum_{v \in V(G)} f(v)$ over all resolving broadcasts $f$ of $G$ where $f$ takes values in $\{0,1\}$. These parameters are defined analogously for directed graphs by considering directed distances.
  We partially resolve a question of Zhang by obtaining precise bounds for the adjacency dimension of certain Cartesian products of path graphs, namely $\text{adim}(P_2 \square P_n)$ and $\text{adim}(P_3 \square P_n)$. Additionally, we study the behavior of adjacency and broadcast dimension on directed graphs. First, we explicitly calculate the adjacency dimension of a directed complete $k$-ary tree, where every edge is directed towards the leaves. Next, we prove that $\text{adim}(\vec{G}) = \text{bdim}(\vec{G})$ for some particular directed trees $\vec{G}$. Furthermore, we show that $\text{bdim}(G)$ can be as large as an exponential function of $\text{bdim}(\vec{G})$ or as small as a logarithmic function of $\text{bdim}(\vec{G})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.11001v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachana Madhukara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual-visibility in strong products of graphs via total mutual-visibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.07835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.07835v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a graph and $X\subseteq V(G)$. Then $X$ is a mutual-visibility set if each pair of vertices from $X$ is connected by a geodesic with no internal vertex in $X$. The mutual-visibility number $\mu(G)$ of $G$ is the cardinality of a largest mutual-visibility set. In this paper, the mutual-visibility number of strong product graphs is investigated. As a tool for this, total mutual-visibility sets are introduced. Along the way, basic properties of such sets are presented. The (total) mutual-visibility number of strong products is bounded from below in two ways, and determined exactly for strong grids of arbitrary dimension. Strong prisms are studied separately and a couple of tight bounds for their mutual-visibility number are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.07835v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serafino Cicerone, Gabriele Di Stefano, Sandi Klav\v{z}ar, Ismael G. Yero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of rings with planar, toroidal or projective planar prime ideal sum graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.15335v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $R$ be a commutative ring with unity. The prime ideal sum graph $\text{PIS}(R)$ of the ring $R$ is the simple undirected graph whose vertex set is the set of all nonzero proper ideals of $R$ and two distinct vertices $I$ and $J$ are adjacent if and only if $I + J$ is a prime ideal of $R$. In this paper, we study some interplay between algebraic properties of rings and graph-theoretic properties of their prime ideal sum graphs. In this connection, we classify non-local commutative Artinian rings $R$ such that $\text{PIS}(R)$ is of crosscap at most two. We prove that there does not exist a non-local commutative Artinian ring whose prime ideal sum graph is projective planar. Further, we classify non-local commutative Artinian rings of genus one prime ideal sum graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.15335v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Mathil, Barkha Baloda, Jitender Kumar, A. Somasundaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chip-firing and critical groups of signed graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09315v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study chip-firing on a signed graph $G_\phi$, employing a general theory of chip-firing on invertible matrices introduced by Guzm\'an and Klivans. Here a negative edge designates an adversarial relationship, so that firing a vertex incident to such an edge leads to a loss of chips at both endpoints. The chip-firing rule for $G_\phi$ is described by its reduced Laplacian matrix $L_{G_\phi}$, which also defines the critical group ${\mathcal K}(G_\phi)$. The valid chip configurations are given by the lattice points of a rational cone determined by $G_\phi$ and the underlying graph $G$. This gives rise to notions of critical as well as $z$-superstable configurations, both of which are counted by the determinant of $L_{G_\phi}$. We establish general results regarding these configurations, focusing on efficient methods of verifying the underlying properties. We then study the critical groups of signed graphs in the context of vertex switching and Smith normal forms. We use this to compute the critical groups of various classes of signed graphs including signed cycles, wheels, complete graphs, and fans, in the process generalizing results of Biggs and others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09315v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Cho, Anton Dochtermann, Ryota Inagaki, Suho Oh, Dylan Snustad, Bailee Zacovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A remark on continued fractions for permutations and D-permutations with a weight $-1$ per cycle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.11500v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that very simple continued fractions can be obtained for the ordinary generating functions enumerating permutations or D-permutations with a large number of independent statistics, when each cycle is given a weight $-1$. The proof is based on a simple lemma relating the number of cycles modulo 2 to the numbers of fixed points, cycle peaks (or cycle valleys), and crossings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.11500v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.37236/12149</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electronic Journal of Combinatorics 31(2), #P2.14 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bishal Deb, Alan D. Sokal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse of the Squared Distance Matrix of a Complete Multipartite Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a connected graph on $n$ vertices and $d_{ij}$ be the length of the shortest path between vertices $i$ and $j$ in $G$. We set $d_{ii}=0$ for every vertex $i$ in $G$. The squared distance matrix $\Delta(G)$ of $G$ is the $n\times n$ matrix with $(i,j)^{th}$ entry equal to $0$ if $i = j$ and equal to $d_{ij}^2$ if $i \neq j$. For a given complete $t$-partite graph $K_{n_1,n_2,\cdots,n_t}$ on $n=\sum_{i=1}^t n_i$ vertices, under some condition we find the inverse $\Delta(K_{n_1,n_2,\cdots,n_t})^{-1}$ as a rank-one perturbation of a symmetric Laplacian-like matrix $\mathcal{L}$ with $\textup{rank} (\mathcal{L})=n-1$. We also investigate the inertia of $\mathcal{L}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01069v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joyentanuj Das, Sumit Mohanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posets for $F$-polynomials in cluster algebras from surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06033v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a simple formula for arbitrary cluster variables in the marked surfaces model. As part of the formula, we associate a labeled poset to each tagged arc, such that the associated $F$-polynomial is a weighted sum of order ideals. Each element of the poset has a weight, and the weight of an ideal is the product of the weights of the elements of the ideal. In the unpunctured case, the weight on each element is a single $\hat{y}_i$, in the usual sense of principal coefficients. In the presence of punctures, some elements may have weights of the form $\hat{y}_i/\hat{y}_j$. Our search for such a formula was inspired by the Fundamental Theorem of Finite Distributive Lattices combined with work of Gregg Musiker, Ralf Schiffler, and Lauren Williams that, in some cases, organized the terms of the $F$-polynomial into a distributive lattice. The proof consists of a simple and poset-theoretically natural argument in a special case, followed by a hyperbolic geometry argument using a cover of the surface to prove the general case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06033v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Pilaud, Nathan Reading, Sibylle Schroll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial parametrisation of the canonical iterates to the solution of $-\gamma g'= g^{-1}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06618v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The iterates $h_0,h_1,h_2,\dotsc$ constructed in [8,5] and converging to the only solution $g=h\colon[0,1]\to[0,1]$ of the iterative differential equation $-\gamma g'= g^{-1}$, $\gamma&gt;0$, are parametrised by polynomials over $\Bbb Q$, and the corresponding constant $\gamma=\kappa\approx0.278877$ is estimated by rational numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06618v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Miyamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A construction of directed strongly regular graphs with parameters (63,11,8,1,2)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the existence of directed strongly regular graphs with parameters $(63,11,8,1,2)$. We construct a pair of nonisomorphic dsrg(63,11,8,1,2), where one is obtained from the other by reversing all arrows. Both directed strongly regular graphs have $L_2(8):3$ as the full automorphism group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03100v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andries E. Brouwer, Dean Crnkovi\'c, Andrea \v{S}vob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A structure theorem for homology 4-manifolds with $g_2\leq 5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.02355v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Numerous structural findings of homology manifolds have been derived in various ways in relation to $g_2$-values. The homology $4$-manifolds with $g_2\leq 5$ are characterized combinatorially in this article. It is well-known that all homology $4$-manifolds for $g_2\leq 2$ are polytopal spheres. We demonstrate that homology $4$-manifolds with $g_2\leq 5$ are triangulated spheres and are derived from triangulated 4-spheres with $g_2\leq 2$ by a series of connected sum, bistellar 1- and 2-moves, edge contraction, edge expansion, and edge flipping operations. We establish that the above inequality is optimally attainable, i.e., it cannot be extended to $g_2 = 6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.02355v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biplab Basak, Sourav Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
