<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pancyclicity in hypergraphs with large uniformity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Berge cycle of length $\ell$ in a hypergraph $\mathcal{H}$ is a sequence of alternating vertices and edges $v_0e_0v_1e_1...v_\ell e_\ell v_0$ such that $\{v_i,v_{i+1}\}\subseteq e_i$ for all $i$, with indices taken modulo $\ell$.
  For $n$ sufficiently large and $r\geq \lfloor\frac{n-1}{2}\rfloor-1$ we prove exact minimum degree conditions for an $n$-vertex, $r$-uniform hypergraph to contain Berge cycles of every length between $2$ and $n$. In conjunction with previous work, this provides sharp Dirac-type conditions for pancyclicity in $r$-uniform hypergraphs for all $3\leq r\leq n$ when $n$ is sufficiently large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00130v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teegan Bailey, Isaiah Hollars, Yupei Li, Ruth Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximal independent sets in the middle two layers of the Boolean lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $B(2d-1, d)$ be the subgraph of the hypercube $\mathcal{Q}_{2d-1}$ induced by its two largest layers. Duffus, Frankl and R\"odl proposed the problem of finding the asymptotics for the logarithm of the number of maximal independent sets in $B(2d-1, d)$. Ilinca and Kahn determined the logarithmic asymptotics and reiterated the question of what their order of magnitude is. We show that the number of maximal independent sets in $B(2d-1,d)$ is \[ \left(1+o(1)\right)(2d-1)\exp\left(\frac{(d-1)^2}{2^{2d-1}}\binom{2d-2}{d-1}\right)\cdot 2^{\binom{2d-2}{d-1}}, \] and describe their typical structure. The proof uses a new variation of Sapozhenko's Graph Container Lemma, a new isoperimetric lemma, a theorem of Hujter and Tuza on the number of maximal independent sets in triangle-free graphs and a stability version of their result by Kahn and Park, among other tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00132v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'ozsef Balogh, Ce Chen, Ramon I. Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tanglegrams with a Unique 1-Crossing-Critical Subtanglegram have Tangle Crossing Number 1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A tanglegram of size n is a graph formed from two rooted binary trees with n leaves each and a perfect matching between their leaf sets. Tanglegrams are used to model co-evolution in various settings. A tanglegram layout is a straight line drawing where the two trees are drawn as plane trees with their leaf-sets on two parallel lines, and only the edges of the matching may cross. The tangle crossing number of a tanglegram is the minimum crossing number among its layouts. It is known that tanglegrams have crossing number at least one precisely when they contain one of two size 4 subtanglegrams, which we refer to as cross-inducing subtanglegrams. We show here that a tanglegram with exactly one cross inducing subtanglegram must have tangle crossing number exactly one, and ask the question whether the tangle-crossing number of tanglegrams with exactly k cross-inducing subtanglegrams is bounded for every k.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00163v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Eva Czabarka, Alec Helm, L\'aszl\'o Sz\'ekely</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypergraph Characterization of Fusion Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a correspondence between multiplicity-free, self-dual,
  fusion rings and a digraph, hypergraph pair $(D,H)$. This
  correspondence is used to provide a complete characterization of all
  fusion rings corresponding to graphical properties of $D$. Further,
  we exploit this correspondence to provide a complete list of all
  non-isomorphic,
  self-dual, multiplicity-free fusion rings of rank at most 8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00180v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Bruillard, Kathleen Nowak, Stephen J. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On graphs without four-vertex induced subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a family F of graphs, a graph G is F-free if it does not contain any graph in F as an induced subgraph. The problem of determining the complexity of colouring (claw, 4K1)- free graphs is a well-known open problem. In this paper we solve the colouring problem for a subclass of (claw, 4K1)-free graphs. We design a polynomial-time algorithm to colour (claw, 4K1, bridge, C4-twin)-free graphs. This algorithm is derived from a structural theorem on (claw, 4K1, bridge, C4-twin)-free graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00202v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kathie Cameron, Ch\'inh T. Ho\`ang, Taite LaGrange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internally-disjoint Directed Pendant Steiner Trees in Digraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a digraph $D=(V(D),A(D))$ and a set $S\subseteq V(D)$ with $|S|\geq 2$ and $r\in S$, a directed pendant $(S,r)$-Steiner tree (or, simply, a pendant $(S,r)$-tree) is an out-tree $T$ rooted at $r$ such that $S\subseteq V(T)$ and each vertex of $S$ has degree one in $T$. Two pendant $(S,r)$-trees are called internally-disjoint if they are arc-disjoint and their common vertex set is exactly $S$. The goal of the {\sc Internally-disjoint Directed Pendant Steiner Tree Packing (IDPSTP)} problem is to find a largest collection of pairwise internally-disjoint pendant $(S,r)$-trees in $D$. We use $\tau_{S,r}(D)$ to denote the maximum number of pairwise internally-disjoint pendant $(S,r)$-trees in $D$ and define the directed pendant-tree $k$-connectivity of $D$ as
  \begin{align*}
  \tau_{k}(D)=\min\{\tau_{S,r}(D)\mid S\subseteq V(D),|S|=k,r\in S\}.
  \end{align*}
  IDPSTP is a restriction of the {\sc Internally-disjoint Directed Steiner Tree Packing} problem studied by Cheriyan and Salavatipour [Algorithmica, 2006] and Sun and Yeo [JGT, 2023]. The directed pendant-tree $k$-connectivity extends the concept of pendant-tree $k$-connectivity in undirected graphs studied by Hager [JCTB, 1985] and could be seen as a generalization of classical vertex-connectivity of digraphs.
  In this paper, we completely determine the computational complexity for the parameter $\tau_{S,r}(D)$ on Eulerian digraphs and symmetric digraphs. We also give sharp bounds and values for the parameter $\tau_{k}(D)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00298v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shanshan Yu, Yuefang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New kinds of block diagonal matching fields and toric degenerations of Grassmannians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Block diagonal matching field has many previous works. In general, a coherent matching field induces a monomial order to Pl\"{u}cker algebra, and block diagonal matching fields are a kind of coherent matching fields. In the present paper, we introduce a new kind of block diagonal matching fields and study the problem when they give a SAGBI basis. As a corollary, we provide a new family of toric degenerations of Grassmannians by using SAGBI bases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00388v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Higashitani, Nobukazu Kowaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum list $r$-colorable induced subgraphs in $kP_3$-free graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that, for every fixed positive integers $r$ and $k$, \textsc{Max-Weight List $r$-Colorable Induced Subgraph} admits a polynomial-time algorithm on $kP_3$-free graphs. This problem is a common generalization of \textsc{Max-Weight Independent Set}, \textsc{Odd Cycle Transversal} and \textsc{List $r$-Coloring}, among others. Our result has several consequences.
  First, it implies that, for every fixed $r \geq 5$, assuming $\mathsf{P}\neq \mathsf{NP}$, \textsc{Max-Weight List $r$-Colorable Induced Subgraph} is polynomial-time solvable on $H$-free graphs if and only if $H$ is an induced subgraph of either $kP_3$ or $P_5+kP_1$, for some $k \geq 1$. Second, it makes considerable progress toward a complexity dichotomy for \textsc{Odd Cycle Transversal} on $H$-free graphs, allowing to answer a question of Agrawal, Lima, Lokshtanov, Rz{\k{a}}{\.z}ewski, Saurabh, and Sharma [TALG 2024]. Third, it gives a short and self-contained proof of the known result of Chudnovsky, Hajebi, and Spirkl [Combinatorica 2024] that \textsc{List $r$-Coloring} on $kP_3$-free graphs is polynomial-time solvable for every fixed $r$ and $k$.
  We also consider two natural distance-$d$ generalizations of \textsc{Max-Weight Independent Set} and \textsc{List $r$-Coloring} and provide polynomial-time algorithms on $kP_3$-free graphs for every fixed integers $r$, $k$, and $d \geq 6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00412v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esther Galby, Paloma T. Lima, Andrea Munaro, Amir Nikabadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A census of face-transitive surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A face-transitive surface is a triangulated 2-dimensional manifold whose automorphism group acts transitively on its set of triangles. In this paper, we investigate this class of highly symmetric surface triangulations. We identify seven types of such face-transitive surfaces, splitting up further into a total of thirteen sub-types, distinguished by how their automorphism groups act on them. We use these theoretical results to compute a census of face-transitive surfaces with up to 1280 faces by constructing suitable cycle double covers of cubic node-transitive graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00425v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reymond Akpanya, Jonathan Spreer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumerations of 1-rotational Steiner systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00469v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper new $1$-rotational 2-Steiner systems for different admissible $v,k$ pairs are introduced. In particular, $1$-rotational unitals of order $4$ are enumerated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00469v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Hetman, Taras Banakh, Alex Ravsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumeration of idempotent-sum subsequences in finite cyclic semigroups and smooth sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The enumeration of zero-sum subsequences of a given sequence over finite cyclic groups is one classical topic, which starts from one question of P. Erd\H{o}s. In this paper, we consider this problem in a more general setting -- finite cyclic semigroups. Let $\mathcal{S}$ be a finite cyclic semigroup. By $\textbf{e}$ we denote the unique idempotent of the semigroup $\mathcal{S}$. Let $T$ be a sequence over the semigroup $\mathcal{S}$, and let $N(T; \textbf{e})$ be the number of distinct subsequences of $T$ with sum being the idempotent $\textbf{e}$. We obtain the lower bound for $N(T; \textbf{e})$ in terms of the length of $T$, and moreover, prove that $T$ contains subsequences with some smooth-structure in case that $N(T; \textbf{e})$ is not large. Our result generalizes the theorem obtained by W. Gao [Discrete Math., 1994] on the enumeration of zero-sum subsequences over finite cyclic groups to the setting of semigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00486v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoqing Wang, Yang Zhao, Xingliang Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equating three degrees of graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that, for every graph with at least 5 vertices, one can delete at most 3 vertices such that the subgraph obtained has at least three vertices with the same degree. This solves an open problem of Caro, Shapira and Yuster [Electron. J. Combin. 21 (2014) P1.24].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00504v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Liu, Qinghou Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A complement of the Erd\H{o}s-Hajnal problem on paths with equal-degree endpoints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Answering a question of Erd\H{o}s and Hajnal, Chen and Ma proved that for all $n\geq600$ every graph with $2n + 1$ vertices and at least $n^2 + n+1$ edges contains two vertices of equal degree connected by a path of length three, and the complete bipartite graph $K_{n,n+1}$ shows that this edge bound is sharp. In this paper, we obtain the above result for all $n\ge2$, and thus resolve the question of Erd\H{o}s and Hajnal completely.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00523v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Liu, Qinghou Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving through Cartesian products, coronas and joins in general position</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The general position problem asks for large sets of vertices such that no three vertices of the set lie on a common shortest path. Recently a dynamic version of this problem was defined, called the \emph{mobile general position problem}, in which a collection of robots must visit all the vertices of the graph whilst remaining in general position. In this paper we investigate this problem in the context of Cartesian products, corona products and joins, giving upper and lower bounds for general graphs and exact values for families including grids, cylinders, Hamming graphs and prisms of trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00535v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandi Klav\v{z}ar, Aditi Krishnakumar, Dorota Kuziak, Ethan Shallcross, James Tuite, Ismael G. Yero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing graphs into stable and ordered parts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Connections between structural graph theory and finite model theory recently gained a lot of attention. In this setting, many interesting question remain on the properties of hereditary dependent (NIP) classes of graphs, in particular related to first-order transductions.
  Motivated by Simon's decomposition theorem of dependent types into a stable part and a distal (order-like) part, we conjecture that every hereditary dependent class of graphs is transduction-equivalent to a hereditary dependent class of partially ordered graphs, where the cover graph of the partial order has bounded treewidth and the unordered graph is (edge) stable.
  In this paper, we consider the first non-trivial case (classes with bounded linear cliquewidth) and prove that the conjecture holds in a strong form, where the cover graph of the partial order has bounded pathwidth. Then, we extend our study to classes that admit bounded-size bounded linear cliquewidth covers, and prove that the conjecture holds for these classes, too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00594v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hector Buffi\`ere, Patrice Ossona de Mendez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irregularity and Topological Indices in Fibonacci Word Trees and Modified Fibonacci Word Index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces the concept of the Fibonacci Word Index $\operatorname{FWI}$, a novel topological index derived from the Albertson index, applied to trees constructed from Fibonacci words. Building upon the classical Fibonacci sequence and its generalizations, we explore the structural properties of Fibonacci word trees and their degree-based irregularity measures. We define the $\operatorname{FWI}$ and its variants, including the total irregularity and modified Fibonacci Word Index where it defined as \[ \operatorname{FWI}^*(T)=\sum_{n,m\in E(\mathscr{T})}[deg F_n^2-deg F_m^2], \] and establish foundational inequalities relating these indices to the maximum degree of the underlying trees. Our results extend known graph invariants to the combinatorial setting of Fibonacci words, providing new insights into their algebraic and topological characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00602v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasem Hamoud, Duaa Abdullah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite sums of combinatorial games (Dadaist games)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an interpretation of the infinite sum of combinatorial games. In such an interpretation, plays involve infinite runs, but without loops. The notion of a run is quite natural, but different possibilities arises for the notion of an alternating run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00614v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Lipparini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$k$-Homogeneous Equiangular Tight Frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Equiangular tight frames (ETFs) are optimal packings in projective space which also yield useful decompositions of signals. Paley ETFs are constructed using number theory. In this article, we present the doubly homogeneous automorphism groups of the Paley ETFs of prime order. We also prove some properties of doubly homogeneous frames, namely that they are always ETFs and that their short circuits -- i.e., dependent subsets of minimum size -- form a balanced incomplete block design. We additionally characterize all $k$-homogeneous ETFs for $3 \leq k \leq 5$. Finally, we revisit David Larson's AMS Memoirs \emph{Frames, Bases, and Group Representations} coauthored with Deguang Han and \emph{Wandering Vectors for Unitary Systems and Orthogonal Wavelets} coauthored with Xingde Dai with a modern eye and focus on finite-dimensional Hilbert spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00160v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily J. King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Littlewood correspondences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the 1940s Littlewood formulated three fundamental correspondences for the immanants and Schur symmetric functions on the general linear group, which establish deep connections between representation theory of the symmetric group and the general linear group parallel to the Schur-Weyl duality. In this paper, we introduce the notion of quantum immanants in the quantum coordinate algebra using primitive idempotents of the Hecke algebra. By employing $R$-matrix techniques, we establish the quantum analog of Littlewood correspondences between quantum immanants and Schur functions for the quantum coordinate algebra. In the setting of the Schur-Weyl-Jimbo duality, we construct an exact correspondence between the Gelfand-Tsetlin bases of the irreducible representations of the quantum enveloping algebra $U_q(\mathfrak{gl}(n))$ and Young's orthonormal basis of an irreducible representation of the Hecke algebra $\mathcal H_m$. This isomorphism leads to our trace formula for the quantum immanants, which settled the generalization problem
  of $q$-analog of Kostant's formular for $\lambda$-immanants. As applications, we also derive general $q$-Littlewood-Merris-Watkins identities and $q$-Goulden-Jackson identities as special cases of the quantum Littlewood correspondence III.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00406v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naihuan Jing, Yinlong Liu, Jian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ladders and Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00414v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1984, Ditor asked two questions: (1) For each $n\in\omega$ and infinite cardinal $\kappa$, is there a join-semilattice of breadth $n+1$ and cardinality $\kappa^{+n}$ whose principal ideals have cardinality $&lt; \kappa$? (2) For each $n \in \omega$, is there a lower-finite lattice of cardinality $\aleph_{n}$ whose elements have at most $n+1$ lower covers? We show that both questions have positive answers under the axiom of constructibility, and hence consistently with $\mathsf{ZFC}$. More specifically, we derive the positive answers from assuming that $\square_\kappa$ holds for enough $\kappa$'s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00414v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Notaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Minimal Generating Sets of Splitting Field and Cluster Towers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The concept of cluster towers was introduced by the second author and Krithika in [4] along with a question which was answered by the first author and Bhagwat in [1]. In this article we introduce the concept of minimal generating sets of splitting field and connect it to the concept of cluster towers. We establish that there exist infinitely many irreducible polynomials over rationals for which the splitting field has two extreme minimal generating sets (one of given cardinality and other of minimum cardinality) and for which we have two extreme cluster towers (one of given length and other of minimum length). We prove interesting properties of cluster tower associated with minimal generating set that we constructed in proof of the theorem and as a consequence get that degree sequence depends on the ordering even when we work with minimal generating set. We also establish an equivalent condition for a set to be minimum minimal generating set for a certain family of polynomials over rationals and count the total number of minimum minimal generating sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00672v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Jaiswal, P Vanchinathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The signed graphs with symmetric spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.06864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well known that a graph $G$ has a symmetric spectrum if and only if it is bipartite, a signed graph $\Gamma=(G,\sigma)$ has a symmetric spectrum if $G$ is bipartite. However, there exists a spectrally symmetric signed graph $\Gamma=(G,\sigma)$ such that $G$ is not bipartite. In this paper, we focus to characterize the signed graphs with symmetric spectra. Some necessary and (or) sufficient conditions for spectrally symmetric signed graphs are given. Moreover, some methods to construct signed graphs with symmetric spectra are found and infinite families of these signed graphs are produced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.06864v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deqiong Li, Qiongxiang Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotation-invariant web bases from hourglass plabic graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12501v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Webs give a diagrammatic calculus for spaces of tensor invariants. We introduce hourglass plabic graphs as a new avatar of webs, and use these to give the first rotation-invariant $U_q(\mathfrak{sl}_4)$-web basis, a long-sought object. The characterization of our basis webs relies on the combinatorics of these new plabic graphs and associated configurations of a symmetrized six-vertex model. We give growth rules, based on a novel crystal-theoretic technique, for generating our basis webs from tableaux and we use skein relations to give an algorithm for expressing arbitrary webs in the basis. We also discuss how previously known rotation-invariant web bases can be unified in our framework of hourglass plabic graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12501v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Gaetz, Oliver Pechenik, Stephan Pfannerer, Jessica Striker, Joshua P. Swanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promotion permutations for tableaux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12506v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In our companion paper, we develop a new $SL_4$-web basis. Basis elements are given by certain planar graphs and are constructed so that important algebraic operations can be performed diagrammatically. A guiding principle behind our construction is that the long cycle $(12\ldots n) \in \mathfrak{S}_n$ should act by rotation of webs. Moreover, the bijection between webs and tableaux should intertwine rotation with the promotion action on tableaux.
  In this paper, we develop necessary notions of promotion permutations and promotion matrices, which are new even for standard tableaux. To support inductive arguments in the companion paper, we must however work in the more general setting of fluctuating tableaux, which we introduce and which subsumes many classes of tableaux that have been previously studied, including (generalized) oscillating, vacillating, rational, alternating, and (semi)standard tableaux. Therefore, we also give here a full development of the basic combinatorics and representation theory of fluctuating tableaux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12506v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5070/C64264251</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Combinatorial Theory, Volume 4, Number 2 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christian Gaetz, Oliver Pechenik, Stephan Pfannerer, Jessica Striker, Joshua P. Swanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the free commutative monoid over a positive operad</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03808v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study algebraic structures on the free commutative twisted algebra generated by a positive operad $\mathbf q$, in the framework of vector species. Given a nonunital commutative twisted algebra structure $\mu$ on $\mathbf q$, we introduce the notion of $\mu$-compatible operad structure, leading to a nonunital operad structure on $\mathbf E \circ \mathbf q$, where $\mathbf E$ stands for the exponential species. Next, we define nested pre-Lie operads (NPL-operads), a weak form of the notion of operad, in which the nested associativity axiom is weakened down to a nested pre-Lie condition. This structure is new up to our knowledge. Several constructions of NPL-operads are presented. Finally, we define algebras over a NPL-operad, based on the notion of polynomial functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03808v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominique Manchon (LMBP), Hedi Regeiba (FSG), Imen Rjaiba (FSG), Yannic Vargas (TU Graz)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum number of edge colorings avoiding rainbow copies of $K_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we show that for $r\geq 12$ and any sufficiently large $n$-vertex graph $G$ the number of $r$-edge-colorings of $G$ with no rainbow $K_4$ is at most $r^{ex(n,K_4)}$, where $ex(n,K_4)$ denotes the Tur\'{a}n number of $K_4$. Moreover, $G$ attains equality if and only if it is the Tur\'{a}n graph $T_3(n)$.
  The bound on the number of colors $r\geq 12$ is best possible. It improves upon a result of H. Lefmann, D.A. Nolibos, and the second author who showed the same result for $r \geq 5434$ and it confirms a conjecture by Gupta, Pehova, Powierski and Staden.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19244v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hi\^ep H\`an, Carlos Hoppen, Nicolas Moro M\"uller, Dionatan Ricardo Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bull-free graphs and $\chi$-boundedness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A bull is a graph obtained from a four-vertex path by adding a vertex adjacent to the two middle vertices of the path. A graph $G$ is bull-free if no induced subgraph of $G$ is a bull. We prove that for all $k,t\in \mathbb{N}$, if $G$ is a bull-free graph of clique number at most $k$ and every triangle-free induced subgraph of $G$ has chromatic number at most $t$, then $G$ has chromatic number at most $k^{\mathcal{O}(\log t)}$. We further show that the bound $k^{\mathcal{O}(\log t)}$ is best possible up to a multiplicative constant in the exponent.
  The previously best known bound was of the form $2^{poly(k,t)\log poly(k,t)}$, due to Thomass\'{e}, Trotignon and Vu\v{s}kovi\'{c} (2017), whose proof uses Chudnovsky's decomposition theorem for bull-free graphs. Our result also implies that every $\chi$-bounded hereditary class of bull-free graphs is polynomially $\chi$-bounded. This was recently given a 10-page proof by Chudnovsky, Cook, Davies and Oum (2023) that relies heavily on Chudnovsky's structure theorem.
  Our proof is a single page long and completely avoids the structure theorem, using only one result of Chudnovsky and Safra (which itself has a short proof).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21093v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepehr Hajebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial zeta functions counting triangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11226v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we compute special values of certain combinatorial zeta functions counting geodesic paths in the (n-1)-skeleton of a triangulation of a n-dimensional manifold. We show that they carry a topological meaning. As such, we recover the first Betti number and L2-Betti number of compact manifolds, and the linking number of pairs of null-homologous knots in a 3-manifold. The tool to relate the two sides (counting geodesics/topological invariants) are random walks on higher dimensional skeleta of the triangulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11226v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'eo B\'enard (Aix-Marseille University), Yann Chaubet (University of Cambridge), Nguyen Viet Dang (Sorbonne Universit\'e), Thomas Schick (Universit\"at G\"ottingen)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variations of GIT quotients and dimer combinatorics for toric compound Du Val singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16112v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A dimer model is a bipartite graph described on the real two-torus, and it gives the quiver as the dual graph. It is known that for any three-dimensional Gorenstein toric singularity, there exists a dimer model such that a GIT quotient parametrizing stable representations of the associated quiver is a projective crepant resolution of this singularity for some stability parameter. It is also known that the space of stability parameters has the wall-and-chamber structure, and for any projective crepant resolution of a three-dimensional Gorenstein toric singularity can be realized as the GIT quotient associated to a stability parameter contained in some chamber. In this paper, we consider dimer models giving rise to projective crepant resolutions of a toric compound Du Val singularity. We show that sequences of zigzag paths, which are special paths on a dimer model, determine the wall-and-chamber structure of the space of stability parameters. Moreover, we can track the variations of stable representations under wall-crossing using the sequences of zigzag paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16112v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Nakajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
