<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Cops and Robbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a variant of Cops and Robbers in which both the cops and the robber are allowed to traverse up to $s$ edges on each of their turns, where $s \ge 2$. We give several general for this new model as well as establish bounds for the cop numbers for grids and hypercubes. We also determine the capture time of cop-win graphs when $s = 2$ up to a small additive constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20753v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William B. Kinnersley, Nikolas Townsend</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $k^{\text th}$ Upper Chromatic Number of the Line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $S \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$, and let $k\in\mathbb{N}$. Greenwell and Johnson define ${\hat\chi\ }^{(k)}(S)$ to be the smallest integer $m$ (if such an integer exists) such that for every $k\times m$ array $D=(d_{ij})$ of positive real numbers, $S$ can be colored with the colors $C_1,\ldots,C_m$ such that no two points of $S$ which are a (Euclidean) distance $d_{ij}$ apart are both colored $C_j$, for all $1\leq i \leq k$ and $1\leq j \leq m$. If no such integer exists then we say that ${\hat\chi\ }^{(k)}(S)=\infty$. In this paper we show that ${\hat\chi\ }^{(k)}(\mathbb{R})$ is finite for all $k$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20772v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete Mathematics, vol. 169 (1997), pp. 157-162</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Abrams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Richardson tableaux and components of Springer fibers equal to Richardson varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the study of Springer fibers and their totally nonnegative counterparts, we define a new subset of standard tableaux called Richardson tableaux. We characterize Richardson tableaux combinatorially using evacuation as well as in terms of a pair of associated reading words. We also characterize Richardson tableaux geometrically, proving that a tableau is Richardson if and only if the corresponding component of a Springer fiber is a Richardson variety, which in turn holds if and only if its positive part is a top-dimensional cell of the totally nonnegative Springer fiber studied by Lusztig (2021). We prove that each such component is smooth by leveraging a combinatorial description of the corresponding pair of reading words, generalizing a result of Graham-Zierau (2011). Another application is that the cohomology classes of these components can be computed in the Schubert basis using Schubert calculus. Finally, we show that the enumeration of Richardson tableaux is surprisingly elegant: the number of Richardson tableaux of fixed partition shape is a product of binomial coefficients, and the number of Richardson tableaux of size $n$ is the $n$th Motzkin number. As a result, we obtain a novel refinement for the Motzkin numbers, as well as a formula for the number of top-dimensional cells in the totally nonnegative Springer fiber.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20792v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven N. Karp, Martha E. Precup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenvalue bounds for distance-edge colorings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a fixed positive integer $t$, we consider the graph colouring problem in which edges at distance at most $t$ are given distinct colours. We obtain sharp lower bounds for the distance-$t$ chromatic index, the least number of colours necessary for such a colouring. Our bounds are of algebraic nature; they depend on the eigenvalues of the line graph and on a polynomial which can be found using integer linear programming methods. We show several graph classes that attain equality for our bounds, and also present some computational results which illustrate the bound's performance. Lastly, we investigate the implications the spectral approach has to the Erd\H{o}s-Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il conjecture, and derive some conditions which a graph must satisfy if we could use it to obtain a counter example through the proposed spectral methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20976v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aida Abiad, Luuk Reijnders</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signed Minkowski decompositions of convex polygons into minimum simplices and factorization of max-plus functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Signed Minkowski decomposition is an expression of a polytope as a Minkowski sum and difference of smaller polytopes. Signed Minkowski decompositions of a polytope can be interpreted as factorizations of a max-plus (tropical) function. We review two relations about Minkowski decompositions, and we prove that any 2-dimensional integral polytopes (polygons) have a signed Minkowski decomposition which consists of integral points, integral line segments of length 1, and integral triangles of area 1/2. From this result, we also obtain that any max-plus functions with two variables and integer coefficients can be expressed as a set of specified form of simpler max-plus functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20999v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soujun Kitagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cauchy identities for Grothendieck polynomials and a dual RSK correspondence through pipe dreams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Cauchy identity gives a recipe for decomposing a double Grothendieck polynomial $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}_w(x;y)$ as a sum of products $\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}_v(x)\mathfrak{G}^{(\beta)}_u(y)$ of single Grothendieck polynomials. Combinatorially, this identity suggests the existence of a weight-preserving bijection between certain families of diagrams called pipe dreams. In this paper, we provide such a bijection using an algorithm called pipe dream rectification. In turn, rectification is built from a new class of flow operators which themselves exhibit a surprising symmetry. Finally, we examine other applications of rectification including an insertion algorithm on pipe dreams which recovers a variant of the dual RSK correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21052v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugh Dennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to the Cohomology of the Flag Variety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One hundred years ago, Hilbert gave a list of important open problems in mathematics. His 15th problem asked for the development of a rigorous calculus explaining Schubert's enumerative results for intersecting varieties defined by rank conditions on vector spaces. Today by way of many contributions in algebraic topology, geometry, and combinatorics, we consider this solved. Yet, deep questions remain about the subtleties of actually carrying out the process. In this chapter, we hope to summarize the rigorous development of what has become known as Schubert calculus, with an eye toward computation. We discuss Grassmannians and flag varieties and their cohomology rings, following Monk's constructive algebraic approach. We derive formulas for Schur and Schubert polynomials, which represent cohomology classes of Schubert varieties. We hint at the vast literature in this area and point to the other references in the Handbook for more information. Finally, we identify open problems that remain a challenge even with modern tools at our fingertips in hopes of inspiring further contributions in this fascinating field.
  This is intended as the first chapter of a book entitled "Handbook of Combinatorial Algebraic Geometry: Subvarieties of the Flag Variety", a compendium of topics in the area. The book is being edited by Erik Insko, Martha Precup, and Ed Richmond. In addition to this introductory chapter, others will cover more advanced topics such as Kazhdan-Lusztig varieties, generalized smooth Schubert varieties, Richardson varieties and positroid varieties, spherical and torus orbit closures, spanning line configurations, different types of Hessenberg varieties, and generalizations to Kac-Moody flag varieties, each written by experts in those areas. We hope you enjoy this chapter enough to seek out the others, and that you send us any comments or corrections you find as you read this article!</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21064v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara C. Billey, Yibo Gao, Brendan Pawlowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lebesgue variant of the additive square problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The additive square problem is a relatively famous open problem in the area of combinatorics on words: Does there exist an infinite word over a finite alphabet, such that no two consecutive blocks of the same length have the same sum? In this note we solve a Lebesgue integral variant of the problem. The proof is based on Lebesgue's density theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21200v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ingrid Vukusic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grundy double domination number: bounds, graph operations, and efficient computation for $P_4$-tidy graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by graph domination games, various domination-type vertex sequences have been introduced, including the Grundy double dominating sequence (GDDS) of a graph and its associated parameter, the Grundy double domination number (GDDN). The decision version of the problem of computing the GDDN is known to be NP-complete, even when restricted to split graphs and bipartite graphs. In this paper, we establish general tight bounds for the GDDN. We also describe GDDSs for vertex-removed graphs and for the join of two graphs. Applying these results, we prove that computing the GDDN is linear for $P_4$-tidy graphs, thereby solving an open problem previously posed for cographs by B. Bre\v{s}ar et al. in [Bre\v{s}ar, B., Pandey, A., and Sharma, G. (2022). Computational aspects of some vertex sequences of grundy domination-type. Indian J. Discrete Math., 8:21-38].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21235v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinitely many counterexamples to a conjecture of Lov\'asz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the well-known conjecture of Ryser which relates maximum matchings to minimum vertex covers in $r$-partite $r$-uniform hypergraphs, Lov\'asz formulated a stronger conjecture. It states that one can always reduce the matching number by removing $r-1$ vertices. This conjecture was very recently disproven for $r=3$ by Clow, Haxell, and Mohar using the line graph of a $3$-regular graph of order $102$. Building on this, we describe a simple infinite family of counterexamples based on generalized Petersen graphs for the case $r=3$ and give specific counterexamples for $r=4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21286v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aida Abiad, Frederik Garbe, Xavier Povill, Christoph Spiegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RSB bounds on the maximum cut</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the context of random regular graphs, the size of the maximum cut is probably the second most studied graph parameter after the independence ratio. Zdeborov\'a and Boettcher used the cavity method, a non-rigorous statistical physics technique, to predict one-step replica symmetry breaking (1-RSB) formulas. Coja-Ohglan et al. confirmed these predictions as rigorous upper bounds using the interpolation method. While these upper bounds were not expected to be exact, they may be very close to the true values.
  In this paper, we establish 2-RSB upper bounds and fine-tune their parameters to beat the aforementioned 1-RSB bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21296v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Harangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear codes arising from the point-hyperplane geometry-Part I: the Segre embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $V$ be a vector space over the finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$ with $q$ elements and $\Lambda$ be the image of the Segre geometry $\mathrm{PG}(V)\otimes\mathrm{PG}(V^*)$ in $\mathrm{PG}(V\otimes V^*)$. Consider the subvariety $\Lambda_{1}$ of $\Lambda$ represented by the pure tensors $x\otimes \xi$ with $x\in V$ and $\xi\in V^*$ such that $\xi(x)=0$. Regarding $\Lambda_1$ as a projective system of $\mathrm{PG}(V\otimes V^*)$, we study the linear code $\mathcal{C}(\Lambda_1)$ arising from it. The code $\mathcal{C}(\Lambda_1)$ is minimal code and we determine its basic parameters, itsfull weight list and its linear automorphism group. We also give a geometrical characterization of its minimum and second lowest weight codewords as well as of some of the words of maximum weight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21309v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilaria Cardinali, Luca Giuzzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry classes of Hamiltonian cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We initiate the study of Hamiltonian cycles up to symmetries of the underlying graph. Our focus lies on the extremal case of Hamiltonian-transitive graphs, i.e., Hamiltonian graphs where, for every pair of Hamiltonian cycles, there is a graph automorphism mapping one cycle to the other. This generalizes the extensively studied uniquely Hamiltonian graphs. In this paper, we show that Cayley graphs of abelian groups are not Hamiltonian-transitive (under some mild conditions and some non-surprising exceptions), i.e., they contain at least two structurally different Hamiltonian cycles. To show this, we reduce Hamiltonian-transitivity to properties of the prime factors of a Cartesian product decomposition, which we believe is interesting in its own right. We complement our results by constructing infinite families of regular Hamiltonian-transitive graphs and take a look at the opposite extremal case by constructing a family with many different Hamiltonian cycles up to symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21337v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Baligacs (TU Darmstadt), Sofia Brenner (Universit\"at Kassel), Annette Lutz (TU Darmstadt), Lena Volk (TU Darmstadt)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On zero-sum subsequences in a finite abelian group of length not exceeding a given number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be an additive finite abelian group and let $k\in [\exp(G),\mathsf{D}(G)-1]$ be a positive integer. Denote by $\mathsf{s}_{\leq k}(G)$ the smallest positive integer $l\in \mathbb{N}\cup \{+\infty\}$ such that each sequence of length $l$ over $G$ has a non-empty zero-sum subsequence of length at most $k$. Let $k_G\in [\exp(G),\mathsf{D}(G)-1]$ be the smallest positive integer such that $\mathsf{s}_{\leq \mathsf{D}(G)-d}(G)\leq \mathsf{D}(G)+d$ for $\mathsf{D}(G)-d\geq k_G$. We conjecture that $k_G=\frac{\mathsf{D}(G)+1}{2}$ for finite abelian groups $G$ with $r(G)\geq 2$ and $\mathsf{D}(G)=\mathsf{D}^*(G)$.
  In this paper, we mainly study this conjecture for finite abelian $p$-groups and get some results to support this conjecture. We also prove that $k_G\leq \mathsf{D}(G)-2$ for all finite abelian groups $G$ with $r(G)\geq 2$ except $C_2^3$ and $C_2^4$. In addition, we also get some lower bounds for the invariant $\mathsf{s}_{\leq k}(G)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21383v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian laceability with a set of faulty edges in hypercubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Faulty networks are useful because link or node faults can occur in a network. This paper examines the Hamiltonian properties of hypercubes under certain conditional faulty edges. Let consider the hypercube \( Q_n \), for \( n \geq 5 \) and set of faulty edges \( F \) such that \( |F| \leq 4n - 17 \). We prove that a Hamiltonian path exists connecting any two vertices in \( Q_n - F \) from distinct partite sets if they verify the next two conditions: (i) in $Q_n - F$ any vertex has a degree at least 2, and (ii) in $Q_n - F$ at most one vertex has a degree exactly equal to 2. These findings provide an understanding of fault-tolerant properties in hypercube networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21391v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abid Ali, Weihua Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian paths extending a set of matchings in hypercubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The hypercube \( Q_n \) contains a Hamiltonian path joining \( x \) and \( y \) (where $x$ and $y$ from the opposite partite set) containing \( P \) if and only if the induced subgraph of \( P \) is a linear forest, where none of these paths have \( x \) or \( y \) as internal vertices nor both as endpoints. Dvo\v{r}\'ak and Gregor answered a problem posed by Caha and Koubek and proved that for every \( n \geq 5 \), there exist vertices \( x \) and \( y \) with a set of \( 2n - 4 \) edges in \( Q_n \) that extend to the Hamiltonian path joining \( x \) and \( y \). This paper examines the Hamiltonian properties of hypercubes with a matching set. Let consider the hypercube \( Q_n \), for \( n \geq 5 \) and a set of matching \( M \) such that \( |M| \leq 3n - 13 \). We prove a Hamiltonian path exists joining two vertices $x$ and $y$ in \( Q_n \) from opposite partite sets containing $M$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21432v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abid Ali, Lina Ba, Weihua Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric SICs over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20778v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Zauner's conjecture concerns the existence of $d^2$ equiangular lines in $\mathbb{C}^d$; such a system of lines is known as a SIC. In this paper, we construct infinitely many new SICs over finite fields. While all previously known SICs exhibit Weyl--Heisenberg symmetry, some of our new SICs exhibit trivial automorphism groups. We conjecture that such \textit{totally asymmetric} SICs exist in infinitely many dimensions in the finite field setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20778v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph W. Iverson, Dustin G. Mixon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic additive energy and entropy inequalities for sums and products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Following a growing number of studies that, over the past 15 years, have established entropy inequalities via ideas and tools from additive combinatorics, in this work we obtain a number of new bounds for the differential entropy of sums, products, and sum-product combinations of continuous random variables. Partly motivated by recent work by Goh on the discrete entropic version of the notion of "additive energy", we introduce the additive energy of pairs of continuous random variables and prove various versions of the statement that "the additive energy is large if and only if the entropy of the sum is small", along with a version of the Balog-Szemer\'edi-Gowers theorem for differential entropy. Then, motivated in part by recent work by M\'ath\'e and O'Regan, we establish a series of new differential entropy inequalities for products and sum-product combinations of continuous random variables. In particular, we prove a new, general, ring Pl\"unnecke-Ruzsa entropy inequality. We briefly return to the case of discrete entropy and provide a characterization of discrete random variables with "large doubling", analogous to Tao's Freiman-type inverse sumset theory for the case of small doubling. Finally, we consider the natural entropic analog of the Erd\"os-Szemer\'edi sum-product phenomenon for integer-valued random variables. We show that, if it does hold, then the range of parameters for which it does would necessarily be significantly more restricted than its anticipated combinatorial counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20813v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rupert Li, Lampros Gavalakis, Ioannis Kontoyiannis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Nathanson's Triangular Number Phenomenon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a finite set $A\subseteq \mathbb{Z}$, the $h$-fold sumset is $hA := \{x_1+\dots+x_h:x_i\in A\}$. We interpret the beginning of the sequence of sumset sizes $(|hA|)_{h=1}^\infty$ in terms of the successive $L^1$-minima of a lattice. Consequently, we explain (but not provably) the appearance of triangular numbers in a recent experiment of Nathanson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20836v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin O'Bryant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern Classes of Toric Variety Bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20848v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We resolve a conjecture of Khovanskii-Monin on the Chern classes of toric variety bundles. The main result is a formula for the total Chern class of the tangent bundle of a toric variety bundle in terms of the total Chern class of the base and the total Chern class of the toric fibre. The result serves as a simultaneous generalization of the description of the total Chern class of a projectivized vector bundle and of the formula for the total Chern class of a toric variety in terms of the Chern classes of the toric divisors. We also establish a topological version of this statement for stably complex quasitoric manifolds. As an immediate application, we obtain a formula for the total Chern class of a toroidal horospherical variety in terms of the Chern classes of the generalized flag variety and the total Chern class of the toric fibre, as well as a new proof of Masuda's formula for equivariant Chern classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20848v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Taroyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making Graphs Irregular through Irregularising Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The 1-2-3 Conjecture, introduced by Karo\'nski, {\L}uczak, and Thomason in 2004, was recently solved by Keusch. This implies that, for any connected graph $G$ different from $K_2$, we can turn $G$ into a locally irregular multigraph $M(G)$, i.e., in which no two adjacent vertices have the same degree, by replacing some of its edges with at most three parallel edges. In this work, we introduce and study a restriction of this problem under the additional constraint that edges added to $G$ to reach $M(G)$ must form a walk (i.e., a path with possibly repeated edges and vertices) of $G$. We investigate the general consequences of having this additional constraint, and provide several results of different natures (structural, combinatorial, algorithmic) on the length of the shortest irregularising walks, for general graphs and more restricted classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21254v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Bensmail, Romain Bourneuf, Paul Colinot, Samuel Humeau, Timoth\'ee Martinod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tropical linear systems and the realizability problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This thesis delves into the geometry of abstract tropical curves, exploring their complete linear system and associated tropical submodules. We establish a lower bound on the dimension of tropical submodules in terms of the Baker-Norine rank. Furthermore, the work provides a characterization of realizable canonical divisors, addressing a fundamental problem in connecting tropical geometry to its algebraic counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21268v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Dupraz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forbidden sparse intersections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16015v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $n$ be a positive integer, let $0&lt;p\leqslant p'\leqslant \frac{1}{2}$, and let $\ell \leqslant pn$ be a nonnegative integer. We prove that if $\mathcal{F},\mathcal{G}\subseteq \{0,1\}^n$ are two families whose cross intersections forbid $\ell$ -- that is, they satisfy $|A\cap B|\neq \ell$ for every $A\in\mathcal{F}$ and every $B\in\mathcal{G}$ -- then, setting $t:=\min\{\ell,pn-\ell\}$, we have the subgaussian bound \[ \mu_p(\mathcal{F})\, \mu_{p'}(\mathcal{G})\leqslant 2\exp\Big( - \frac{t^2}{58^2\,pn}\Big), \] where $\mu_p$ and $\mu_{p'}$ denote the $p$-biased and $p'$-biased measures on $\{0,1\}^n$ respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16015v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Forum of Mathematics, Sigma Vol. 13 (2025), e99, 1-29</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pandelis Dodos, Miltiadis Karamanlis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Christoffel words &amp; their lexicographic array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07974v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By a Christoffel matrix we mean a $n\times n$ matrix corresponding to the lexicographic array of a Christoffel word of length $n.$ In this note we show that if $R$ is an integral domain, then the product of two Christoffel matrices over $R$ is commutative and is a Christoffel matrix over $R.$ Furthermore, if a Christoffel matrix over $R$ is invertible, then its inverse is a Christoffel matrix over $R.$ Consequently, the set $GC_n(R)$ of all $n\times n$ invertible Christoffel matrices over $R$ forms an abelian subgroup of $GL_n(R).$ The subset of $GC_n(R)$ consisting all invertible Christoffel matrices having some element $a$ on the diagonal and $b$ elsewhere (with $a,b \in R$ distinct) forms a subgroup $H$ of $GC_n(R).$ If $R$ is a field, then the quotient $GC_n(R)/H$ is isomorphic to $(\Z/nZ)^\times,$ the multiplicative group of integers modulo $n.$ It follows that for each finite field $F$ and each finite abelian group $G,$ there exists $n\geq 2$ and a faithful representation $G\rightarrow GL_n(F)$ consisting entirely of $n\times n$ (invertible) Christoffel matrices over $F.$ We describe the structure of $GC_n(\Z/2\Z).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07974v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Q. Zamboni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Monochromatic Solutions of Linear Equations Using At Least Three Colors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17136v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the number of monochromatic solution to linear equation in $\{1,\dots,n\}$ when we color the set by at least three colors. We consider the $r$-commonness for $r\geq 3$ of linear equation with odd number of terms, and we also prove that any $2$-uncommon equation is $r$-uncommon for any $r\geq 3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17136v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurence P. Wijaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Substructure Analysis and Cycle Enumeration Methods for Directed Graphs Based on a Parameterized Hermitian Laplacian Matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17553v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the principal minors of a parameterized Hermitian Laplacian matrix for directed graphs, with a particular focus on the properties that appear when its complex parameter is a primitive $5$th root of unity. We demonstrate that under this condition, the principal minors yield values within the quadratic field $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{5})$. This algebraic property forms the basis for a method to enumerate non-vanishing unicyclic graphs of certain substructures by analyzing the rational and irrational components of the Hermitian Laplacian determinant. The study is situated within a general framework where a variable unit-modulus complex parameter is introduced into the Hermitian Laplacian matrix, which also facilitates an examination of relationships between determinants for different roots of unity. Our analysis adopts and investigates the concept of substructures, defined as vertex-edge pairs $(V',E')$ where edges in $E'$ are not restricted to connecting vertices within $V'$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17553v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding long cycles in a percolated expander graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12162v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a graph $G$, the percolated graph $G_p$ has each edge independently retained with probability $p$. Collares, Diskin, Erde, and Krivelevich initiated the study of large structures in percolated single-scale vertex expander graphs, wherein every set of exactly $k$ vertices of $G$ has at least $dk$ neighbours before percolation. We extend their result to a conjectured stronger form, proving that if $p = (1+\varepsilon)/d$ and $G$ is a graph on at least $k$ vertices which expands as above, then $G_p$ contains a cycle of length $\Omega_\varepsilon(kd)$ with probability at least $1-\exp(-\Omega_\varepsilon(k/d))$ as $k\rightarrow\infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12162v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lawrence Hollom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eulerian-type polynomials over Stirling permutations and box sorting algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well known that ascents, descents and plateaux are equidistributed over the set of classical Stirling permutations. Their common enumerative polynomials are the second-order Eulerian polynomials, which have been extensively studied by many researchers. This paper is divided into three parts. The first parts gives a convolution formula for the second-order Eulerian polynomials, which simplifies a result of Gessel. As an application, a determinantal expression for the second-order Eulerian polynomials is obtained. We then investigate the convolution formula of the trivariate second-order Eulerian polynomials. Among other things, by introducing three new statistics: proper ascent-plateau, improper ascent-plateau and trace, we discover that a six-variable Eulerian-type polynomial over a class of restricted Stirling permutations equals a six-variable Eulerian-type polynomial over signed permutations. By special parametrizations, we make use of Stirling permutations to give a unified interpretations of the $(p,q)$-Eulerian polynomials and derangement polynomials of types $A$ and $B$. The third part presents a box sorting algorithm which leads to a bijection between the terms in the expansion of $(cD)^nc$ and ordered weak set partitions, where $c$ is a smooth function in the indeterminate $x$ and $D$ is the derivative with respect to $x$. Using a map from ordered weak set partitions to standard Young tableaux, we find an expansion of $(cD)^nc$ in terms of standard Young tableaux. Combining this with grammars, we provide three interpretations of the second-order Eulerian polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16438v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Mei Ma, Jun-Ying Liu, Jean Yeh, Yeong-Nan Yeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some sharp bounds on the average Steiner (k, l)-eccentricity for trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17915v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce some transformations for trees that do not increase the average Steiner $(k,l)$-eccentricity for all $0\leq l\leq k\leq n$. Using these transformations, we obtain some sharp bounds on the average Steiner $(k,l)$-eccentricity for trees with some certain conditions, including given nodes, given diameter, given max degree and given leaves, and get the corresponding extremal trees as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17915v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Zeng, Gengji Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Row-wise Algorithm for Graph Realization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12869v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a $\{0,1\}$-matrix $M$, the graph realization problem for $M$ asks if there exists a spanning forest such that the columns of $M$ are incidence vectors of paths in the forest. The problem is closely related to the recognition of network matrices, which are a large subclass of totally unimodular matrices and have many applications in mixed-integer programming. Existing efficient algorithms for graph realization grow a submatrix in a column-wise fashion whilst maintaining a graphic realization. In the context of mixed-integer linear programming, this limits the set of submatrices of the constraint matrix that can efficiently be determined to be network matrices to network submatrices that span all rows and a subset of the columns. This paper complements the existing work by providing an algorithm that works in a row-wise fashion and uses similar data structures, and enables the detection of arbitrary graphic submatrices. The main challenge in designing efficient algorithms for the graph realization problem is ambiguity as there may exist many graphs realizing $M$. The key insight for designing an efficient row-wise algorithm is that a graphic matrix is uniquely represented by an SPQR-tree, a graph decomposition that stores all graphs with the same set of cycles. The developed row-wise algorithm uses data structures that are compatible with the column-wise algorithm and can be combined with the latter to detect maximal graphic submatrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12869v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rolf van der Hulst, Matthias Walter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The second class particle in the half-line open TASEP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00554v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the second class particle in half-line open TASEP under two different initial conditions with shock discontinuities. The exact formulas for the distribution of the second class particle can be derived by using the color-position symmetry theorem of colored half-space TASEP. We study the asymptotic distribution of second class particles under the constant scaling and KPZ-type scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00554v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kailun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anonymized Network Sensing Graph Challenge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The MIT/IEEE/Amazon GraphChallenge encourages community approaches to developing new solutions for analyzing graphs and sparse data derived from social media, sensor feeds, and scientific data to discover relationships between events as they unfold in the field. The anonymized network sensing Graph Challenge seeks to enable large, open, community-based approaches to protecting networks. Many large-scale networking problems can only be solved with community access to very broad data sets with the highest regard for privacy and strong community buy-in. Such approaches often require community-based data sharing. In the broader networking community (commercial, federal, and academia) anonymized source-to-destination traffic matrices with standard data sharing agreements have emerged as a data product that can meet many of these requirements. This challenge provides an opportunity to highlight novel approaches for optimizing the construction and analysis of anonymized traffic matrices using over 100 billion network packets derived from the largest Internet telescope in the world (CAIDA). This challenge specifies the anonymization, construction, and analysis of these traffic matrices. A GraphBLAS reference implementation is provided, but the use of GraphBLAS is not required in this Graph Challenge. As with prior Graph Challenges the goal is to provide a well-defined context for demonstrating innovation. Graph Challenge participants are free to select (with accompanying explanation) the Graph Challenge elements that are appropriate for highlighting their innovations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08115v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/HPEC62836.2024.10938508</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hayden Jananthan, Michael Jones, William Arcand, David Bestor, William Bergeron, Daniel Burrill, Aydin Buluc, Chansup Byun, Timothy Davis, Vijay Gadepally, Daniel Grant, Michael Houle, Matthew Hubbell, Piotr Luszczek, Peter Michaleas, Lauren Milechin, Chasen Milner, Guillermo Morales, Andrew Morris, Julie Mullen, Ritesh Patel, Alex Pentland, Sandeep Pisharody, Andrew Prout, Albert Reuther, Antonio Rosa, Gabriel Wachman, Charles Yee, Jeremy Kepner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A family of orthogonal functions on the unit circle and a new multilateral matrix inverse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03559v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using Bailey's very-well-poised $_6\psi_6$ summation, we show that a specific sequence of well-poised bilateral basic hypergeometric $_3\psi_3$ series form a family of orthogonal functions on the unit circle. We further extract a bilateral matrix inverse from Dougall's ${}_2H_2$ summation which we use, in combination with the Pfaff--Saalsch\"utz summation, to derive a summation for a particular bilateral hypergeometric $_3H_3$ series. We finally provide multivariate extensions of the bilateral matrix inverse and the $_3H_3$ summation in the setting of hypergeometric series associated to the root system $A_r$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03559v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Schlosser</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
