<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Maker-Breaker directed triangle game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate Maker-Breaker directed triangle games -- a directionally constrained variant of the classical Maker-Breaker triangle game. Our board of interest is a tournament, and the winning sets constitute all directed triangles ($3$-cycles) present in the tournament. We begin by studying the Maker-Breaker directed triangle game played on a specially defined tournament called the parity tournament, and we identify the board size threshold to be $n=7$, which is to say that if the size (i.e.\ the number of vertices) of the parity tournament equals $n$, Breaker has a winning strategy for $3\leq n&lt; 7$, while Maker can ensure a win for herself for $n\geq 7$. For the $(1:b)$ biased version of this game, we prove that the bias threshold $b^*(n)$ satisfies $\sqrt{\left(1/12+o(1)\right)\ n}\leq b^{*}(n) \leq\sqrt{\left(8/3+o(1)\right)\ n}$, which matches the order of magnitude (\ $\sqrt{n}$) of the bias threshold for the undirected counterpart of this game. Next, we consider the game on random tournaments $T(n,p)$ with labeled vertices $1,2,\ldots,n$, such that the edge between $i$ and $j$, for each $i&lt;j$, is directed from $i$ towards $j$ with probability $p$, independent of all else. We prove that Maker wins this game with probability approaching $1$ as $n \to \infty$ for any fixed $p \in (0,1)$. Extending the notion of `bias' from undirected games to our directed framework, we introduce the $(1: \kappa(n))$ flip-biased Maker-Breaker directed triangle game on the parity tournament, where we allow Breaker to strategically flip the directions of a fixed number of edges $\kappa(n)$ before the game begins. We show that the flip-bias threshold $\kappa^*(n)$ is asymptotically equal to $n^2/4$ as $n \to \infty$. This work opens up the possibility of studying a variety of directionally constrained Maker-Breaker positional games on tournaments (and more generally, on directed graphs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13919v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hrishikesh Jagtap, Moumanti Podder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-separable graphs meet Ledoux's polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the seminal article \cite{LED16}, an integral representation of the derivatives of entropy along the heat flow of a probability measure was established under suitable moment conditions. These integral representations have found significant applications in diverse domains - notably in information theory (e.g., entropy power inequalities, monotonicity of Fisher information) and in estimation theory (through the link between entropy derivatives and the minimum mean square error, MMSE, in Gaussian channels). The representations involve multivariate polynomials $(R_n)_n$, arising from a Lie algebra framework on multilinear operators. Despite their central role, the combinatorial structure of these polynomials remains only partially understood. In this note, we prove that the number of monomials in $R_n$ coincides with the number of degree sequences with degree sum $2n$ having a non-separable graph realization, thereby resolving a conjecture from \cite{MPS24}, and drawing an interesting link between these two domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14039v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mansanarez Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the quantum chromatic number of Hamming and generalized Hadamard graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum coloring finds applications in quantum cryptography and information. In this paper, we study the quantum chromatic numbers of Hamming graphs and a generalization of Hadamard graphs. We investigate the separation between the quantum and classical chromatic numbers of these graphs and determine the quantum chromatic numbers for some of them.
  For the upper bounds of the quantum chromatic numbers, we develop a linear programming approach over the Hamming scheme to construct modulus-one orthogonal representations. For the lower bounds, we determine the minimum eigenvalues for some of these graphs to derive corresponding spectral lower bounds on their quantum chromatic numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14209v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiwang Cao, Keqin Feng, Hexiang Huang, Yulin Yang, Zihao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The structure of sequences with zero-sum subsequences of the same length on finite abelian groups of rank two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be an additive finite abelian group, and let $\mathrm{disc}(G)$ denote the smallest positive integer $t$ with the property that every sequence $S$ over $G$ with length $|S|\geq t $ contains two nonempty zero-sum subsequences of distinct lengths. In recent years, Gao et al. established the exact value of $\mathrm{disc}(G)$ for all finite abelian groups of rank $2$ and resolved the corresponding inverse problem for the group $C_n \oplus C_n$. In this paper, we characterize the structure of sequences $S$ over $G = C_n \oplus C_{nm}$ (where $m\geq 2$) when $|S| = \mathrm{disc}(G)- 1$ and all nonempty zero-sum subsequences of $S$ have the same length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14215v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanzhen Hui, Xue Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Density Condition on Point Sets with Slowly-Scaling Distinct Dot Products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The distinct dot products problem, a variation on the Erd\H{o}s distinct distance problem, asks "Given a set $P_n$ of $n$ points in $\mathbb{R}^2$, what is the minimum number $|D(P_n)|$ of distinct dot products formed between them, asymptotically?" The best proven lower-bound is $|D(P_n)| \gtrsim n^{2/3+7/1425}$, due to work by Hanson$\unicode{x2013}$Roche-Newton$\unicode{x2013}$Senger, and a recent improvement by Kokkinos. However, the slowest-scaling known constructions have $|D(P_n)|\sim n$, leaving quite a large gap in the bound. Finding a sublinearly-scaling construction, or disproving its existence, would narrow this gap. We provide a condition that a sequence of point configurations $(P_n)_{n \in \mathbb{N}}$ must satisfy in order for $|D(P_n)|$ to scale 'slowly' i.e. $|D(P_n)| \ll n^{3/4}$. Namely, we prove that any such configuration must contain a point-rich line that gets arbitrarily 'dense' as the sequence progresses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14585v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anshula Gandhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excluding $K_{2,t}$ as a fat minor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for every $t \in \mathbb{N}$, the graph $K_{2,t}$ satisfies the fat minor conjecture of Georgakopoulos and Papasoglu: for every $K\in \mathbb{N}$ there exist $M,A\in \mathbb{N}$ such that every graph with no $K$-fat $K_{2,t}$ minor is $(M,A)$-quasi-isometric to a graph with no $K_{2,t}$ minor. We use this to obtain an efficient algorithm for approximating the minimal multiplicative distortion of any embedding of a finite graph into a $K_{2,t}$-minor-free graph, answering a question of Chepoi, Dragan, Newman, Rabinovich, and Vax\`es from 2012.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14644v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandra Albrechtsen, Marc Distel, Agelos Georgakopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homomorphisms of Partial Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14658v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A partial field is an algebraic object that allows one to simultaneously abstract several different representability properties of matroids. In this paper we study partial fields as algebraic objects in their own right. We characterize the weak and strong characteristic sets of partial fields and show that the class of partial fields is not well-quasi ordered. We provide a new proof that the lift operator of a partial field is idempotent. We also provide a relation between the fundamental elements of a partial field and its Dowling lift, and show that the Dowling lift operator is idempotent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14658v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Vaduthala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proof of the $\frac{3}{8}$-conjecture for independent domination in cubic graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A set $S$ of vertices in a graph $G$ is a dominating set of $G$ if every vertex not in $S$ is adjacent to a vertex in~$S$. An independent dominating set in $G$ is a dominating set of $G$ with the additional property that it is an independent set. The domination number, $\gamma(G)$, and the independent domination number, $i(G)$, are the minimum cardinalities among all dominating sets and independent dominating sets in $G$, respectively. By definition, $\gamma(G) \le i(G)$ for all graphs $G$. Let $G$ be a connected cubic graph of order~$n$. In 1996 Reed [Combin.\ Probab.\ Comput.\ 5 (1996), 277--295] proved a breakthrough result that $\gamma(G) \le \frac{3}{8}n$. We prove the stronger result that if $G$ is different from $K_{3,3}$ and the $5$-prism $C_5 \, \Box \, K_2$, then $i(G) \le \frac{3}{8}n$. This proves a known conjecture. The bound is tight in the sense that there are infinite families of connected cubic graphs that achieve equality in this bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14762v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo\v{s}tjan Bre\v{s}ar, Tanja Dravec, Michael A. Henning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cliques in hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that for any $k \ge 3$, every $k$-uniform hypergraph on $n$ vertices contains at most $n - o(n)$ different sizes of cliques (maximal complete subgraphs). In particular, the 3-uniform case answers a question of Erd\H{o}s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14804v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight bounds towards Zarankiewicz problem in hypergraph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The classical Zarankiewicz problem, which concerns the maximum number of edges in a bipartite graph without a forbidden complete bipartite subgraph, motivates a direct analogue for hypergraphs. Let $K_{s_1,\ldots, s_r}$ be the complete $r$-partite $r$-graph such that the $i$-th part has $s_i$ vertices. We say an $r$-partite $r$-graph $H=H(V_1,\ldots,V_r)$ contains an ordered $K_{s_1,\ldots, s_r}$ if $K_{s_1,\ldots, s_r}$ is a subgraph of $H$ and the set of size $s_i$ vertices is embedded in $V_i$. The Zarankiewicz number for $r$-graph, denoted by $z(m_1, \ldots, m_{r}; s_1,, \ldots,s_{r})$, is the maximum number of edges of the $r$-partite $r$-graph whose $i$-th part has $m_i$ vertices and does not contain an ordered $K_{s_1,\ldots, s_r}$. In this paper, we show that $$z(m_1,m_2, \cdots, m_{r-1},n ; s_1,s_2, \cdots,s_{r-1}, t)=\Theta\left(m_1m_2\cdots m_{r-1} n^{1-1 / s_1s_2\cdots s_{r-1}}\right)$$ for a range of parameters. This extends a result of Conlon [Math. Proc. Camb. Philos. Soc. (2022)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14869v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guorong Gao, Jianfeng Hou, Shuping Huang, Hezhi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Weighted and Bounded Multidimensional Catalan Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define a weighted analog for the multidimensional Catalan numbers, obtain matrix-based recurrences for some of them, and give conditions under which they are periodic. Building on this framework, we introduce two new sequences of triangular arrays: the first one enumerates the $k$-dimensional Balanced ballot paths of exact height $s$; the second one is a new multidimensional generalization of the Narayana numbers, which count the number of Balanced ballot paths with exactly $p$ peaks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14956v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Inagaki, Dimana Pramatarova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the expressivity of sparse maxout networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14068v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the expressivity of sparse maxout networks, where each neuron takes a fixed number of inputs from the previous layer and employs a, possibly multi-argument, maxout activation. This setting captures key characteristics of convolutional or graph neural networks. We establish a duality between functions computable by such networks and a class of virtual polytopes, linking their geometry to questions of network expressivity. In particular, we derive a tight bound on the dimension of the associated polytopes, which serves as the central tool for our analysis. Building on this, we construct a sequence of depth hierarchies. While sufficiently deep sparse maxout networks are universal, we prove that if the required depth is not reached, width alone cannot compensate for the sparsity of a fixed indegree constraint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14068v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moritz Grillo, Tobias Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Orthogonal View of Gau\ss ian Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14124v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish an alternative, ``perpendicular" collection of generating functions for the coefficients of Gaussian polynomials, $\begin{bmatrix}N+m\\m\end{bmatrix}_q$. We provide a general characterization of these perpendicular generating functions. For small values of $m$, unimodality of the coefficients of Gaussian polynomials is easily proved from these generating functions. Additionally, we uncover new and surprising identities for the differences of Gaussian polynomial coefficients, including a very unexpected infinite family of congruences for coefficients of $\begin{bmatrix}N+4\\4\end{bmatrix}_q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14124v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Krattenthaler (Universit\"at Wien), Brandt Kronholm (University of Texas Rio Grande Valley), Paul Marsh (University of Texas Rio Grande Valley)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic invariants of symbolic powers of binomial edge ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14272v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To a graph $G$ one associates the binomial edge ideal $J_G$ generated by a collection of binomials corresponding to the edges of $G$. In this paper, we study the asymptotic behavior of symbolic powers of $J_G$, its lexicographic initial ideal $\mathrm{in}_&lt;(J_G)$, and its multigraded generic initial ideal $\mathrm{gin}(J_G)$. We focus on the Waldschmidt constant, $\widehat{\alpha}$, and asymptotic regularity, $\widehat{\mathrm{reg}}$, which capture linear growth of minimal generator degrees and Castelnuovo--Mumford regularity. We explicitly compute $\widehat{\alpha}(J_G)$ and $\widehat{\alpha}(\mathrm{in}_&lt;(J_G))$, and compare the Betti numbers of the symbolic powers of $J_G$ and $J_H$, where $H$ is a subgraph of $G$. To analyze $\mathrm{in}_&lt;(J_G)$ and $\mathrm{gin}(J_G)$, we use the symbolic polyhedron, a convex polyhedron that encodes the elements of the symbolic powers of a monomial ideal. We determine its vertices via $G$'s induced connected subgraphs and show that $\widehat{\alpha}(\mathrm{gin}(J_G))=\widehat{\alpha}(I_G)$, where $I_G$ is the edge ideal of $G$. This yields an alternate proof of known bounds for $\widehat{\alpha}(I_G)$ in terms of $G$'s clique number and chromatic number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14272v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Belotserkovskiy, Mariana Land\'in, Charlie Ruppe, Lizzy Teryoshin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptotic number of equivalence classes of linear codes with given dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the asymptotic number of equivalence classes of linear codes with prescribed length and dimension. While the total number of inequivalent codes of a given length has been studied previously, the case where the dimension varies as a function of the length has not yet been considered. We derive explicit asymptotic formulas for the number of equivalence classes under three standard notions of equivalence, for a fixed alphabet size and increasing length. Our approach also yields an exact asymptotic expression for the sum of all q-binomial coefficients, which is of independent interest and answers an open question in this context. Finally, we establish a natural connection between these asymptotic quantities and certain discrete Gaussian distributions arising from Brownian motion, providing a probabilistic interpretation of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14424v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Di Giusto, Alberto Ravagnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An efficient algorithm for \textsc{$\mathcal{F}$-subgraph-free Edge Deletion} on graphs having a product structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14674v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a family $\mathcal{F}$ of graphs, a graph is \emph{$\mathcal{F}$-subgraph-free} if it has no subgraph isomorphic to a member of $\mathcal{F}$. We present a fixed-parameter linear-time algorithm that decides whether a planar graph can be made $\mathcal{F}$-subgraph-free by deleting at most $k$ vertices or $k$ edges, where the parameters are $k$, $\lvert \mathcal{F} \rvert$, and the maximum number of vertices in a member of $\mathcal{F}$. The running time of our algorithm is double-exponential in the parameters, which is faster than the algorithm obtained by applying the first-order model checking result for graphs of bounded twin-width.
  To obtain this result, we develop a unified framework for designing algorithms for this problem on graphs with a ``product structure.'' Using this framework, we also design algorithms for other graph classes that generalize planar graphs. Specifically, the problem admits a fixed-parameter linear time algorithm on disk graphs of bounded local radius, and a fixed-parameter almost-linear time algorithm on graphs of bounded genus.
  Finally, we show that our result gives a tight fixed-parameter algorithm in the following sense: Even when $\mathcal{F}$ consists of a single graph $F$ and the input is restricted to planar graphs, it is unlikely to drop any parameters $k$ and $\lvert V(F) \rvert$ while preserving fixed-parameter tractability, unless the Exponential-Time Hypothesis fails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14674v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinwoo An, Seonghyuk Im, Seokbeom Kim, Myounghwan Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order generalizations of stability and arithmetic regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.01739v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define a natural notion of higher order stability and show that subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$ that are tame in this sense can be approximately described by a union of low-complexity quadratic varieties, up to linear error. This generalizes the arithmetic regularity lemma for stable subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$, proved in earlier work of the authors, to the realm of higher-order Fourier analysis.
  This result is strictly stronger than the structure theorem for sets of bounded $\mathrm{VC}_2$-dimension, first proved by the authors in earlier versions of this paper and now available as a separate manuscript arXiv:2510.12867. Taken together, these results provide group theoretic analogues of results obtained for 3-uniform hypergraphs in arXiv:2111.01737.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.01739v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Terry, J. Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directed Acyclic Outerplanar Graphs Have Constant Stack Number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.04732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.04732v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The stack number of a directed acyclic graph $G$ is the minimum $k$ for which there is a topological ordering of $G$ and a $k$-coloring of the edges such that no two edges of the same color cross, i.e., have alternating endpoints along the topological ordering. We prove that the stack number of directed acyclic outerplanar graphs is bounded by a constant, which gives a positive answer to a conjecture by Heath, Pemmaraju and Trenk [SIAM J. Computing, 1999]. As an immediate consequence, this shows that all upward outerplanar graphs have constant stack number, answering a question by Bhore et al. [Eur. J. Comb., 2023] and thereby making significant progress towards the problem for general upward planar graphs originating from Nowakowski and Parker [Order, 1989]. As our main tool we develop the novel technique of directed $H$-partitions, which might be of independent interest. We complement the bounded stack number for directed acyclic outerplanar graphs by constructing a family of directed acyclic 2-trees that have unbounded stack number, thereby refuting a conjecture by N\"ollenburg and Pupyrev [GD 2023].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.04732v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/theoretics.25.25</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>TheoretiCS, Volume 4 (2025), Article 25, 1-33</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paul Jungeblut, Laura Merker, Torsten Ueckerdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An $(\aleph_0,k+2)$-Theorem for $k$-Transversals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.02181v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A family $\mathcal{F}$ of sets satisfies the $(p,q)$-property if among every $p$ members of $\mathcal{F}$, some $q$ can be pierced by a single point. The celebrated $(p,q)$-theorem of Alon and Kleitman asserts that for any $p \geq q \geq d+1$, any family $\mathcal{F}$ of compact convex sets in $\mathbb{R}^d$ that satisfies the $(p,q)$-property can be pierced by a finite number $c(p,q,d)$ of points. A similar theorem with respect to piercing by $(d-1)$-dimensional flats, called $(d-1)$-transversals, was obtained by Alon and Kalai.
  In this paper we prove the following result, which can be viewed as an $(\aleph_0,k+2)$-theorem with respect to $k$-transversals: Let $\mathcal{F}$ be an infinite family of closed balls in $\mathbb{R}^d$, and let $0 \leq k &lt; d$. If among every $\aleph_0$ elements of $\mathcal{F}$, some $k+2$ can be pierced by a $k$-dimensional flat, then $\mathcal{F}$ can be pierced by a finite number of $k$-dimensional flats. We derive this result as a corollary of a more general result which proves the same assertion for families of not necessarily convex objects called \emph{near-balls}, to be defined below.
  This is the first $(p,q)$-theorem in which the assumption is weakened to an $(\infty,\cdot)$ assumption. Our proofs combine geometric and topological tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.02181v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11856-025-2811-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chaya Keller, Micha A. Perles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origins of the Temperley-Lieb algebra: early history</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11929v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give an historical survey of some of the original basic algebraic and combinatorial results on Temperley-Lieb algebras, with a focus on certain results that have become folklore.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11929v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Doty, Anthony Giaquinto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>List colorings of $k$-partite $k$-graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03111v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A $k$-uniform hypergraph (or $k$-graph) $H = (V, E)$ is $k$-partite if $V$ can be partitioned into $k$ sets $V_1, \ldots, V_k$ such that each edge in $E$ contains precisely one vertex from each $V_i$. In this note, we consider list colorings for such hypergraphs. We show that for any $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ if each vertex $v \in V(H)$ is assigned a list of size $|L(v)| \geq \left((k-1+\varepsilon)\Delta/\log \Delta\right)^{1/(k-1)}$, then $H$ admits a proper $L$-coloring, provided $\Delta$ is sufficiently large. Up to a constant factor, this matches the bound on the chromatic number of simple $k$-graphs shown by Frieze and Mubayi, and that on the list chromatic number of triangle free $k$-graphs shown by Li and Postle. Our results hold in the more general setting of ``color-degree'' as has been considered for graphs. Furthermore, we establish a number of asymmetric statements matching results of Alon, Cambie, and Kang for bipartite graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03111v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.37236/12657</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Dhawan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant Hilbert and Ehrhart series under translative group actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14088v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study representations of finite groups on Stanley--Reisner rings of simplicial complexes and on lattice points in lattice polytopes. The framework of translative group actions allows us to use the theory of proper colorings of simplicial complexes without requiring an explicit coloring to be given. We prove that the equivariant Hilbert series of a Cohen--Macaulay simplicial complex under a translative group action admits a rational expression whose numerator is a positive integer combination of irreducible characters. This implies an analogous rational expression for the equivariant Ehrhart series of a lattice polytope with a unimodular triangulation that is invariant under a translative group action. As an application, we study the equivariant Ehrhart series of alcoved polytopes in the sense of Lam and Postnikov and derive explicit results in the case of order polytopes and of Lipschitz poset polytopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14088v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio D'Al\`i, Emanuele Delucchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smoothed analysis for graph isomorphism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06095v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There is no known polynomial-time algorithm for graph isomorphism testing, but elementary combinatorial "refinement" algorithms seem to be very efficient in practice. Some philosophical justification is provided by a classical theorem of Babai, Erd\H{o}s and Selkow: an extremely simple polynomial-time combinatorial algorithm (variously known as "na\"ive refinement", "na\"ive vertex classification", "colour refinement" or the "1-dimensional Weisfeiler-Leman algorithm") yields a so-called canonical labelling scheme for "almost all graphs". More precisely, for a typical outcome of a random graph $G(n,1/2)$, this simple combinatorial algorithm assigns labels to vertices in a way that easily permits isomorphism-testing against any other graph.
  We improve the Babai-Erd\H{o}s-Selkow theorem in two directions. First, we consider randomly perturbed graphs, in accordance with the smoothed analysis philosophy of Spielman and Teng: for any graph $G$, na\"ive refinement becomes effective after a tiny random perturbation to $G$ (specifically, the addition and removal of $O(n\log n)$ random edges). Actually, with a twist on na\"ive refinement, we show that $O(n)$ random additions and removals suffice. These results significantly improve on previous work of Gaudio-R\'acz-Sridhar, and are in certain senses best-possible.
  Second, we complete a long line of research on canonical labelling of random graphs: for any $p$ (possibly depending on $n$), we prove that a random graph $G(n,p)$ can typically be canonically labelled in polynomial time. This is most interesting in the extremely sparse regime where $p$ has order of magnitude $c/n$; denser regimes were previously handled by Bollob\'as, Czajka-Pandurangan, and Linial-Mosheiff. Our proof also provides a description of the automorphism group of a typical outcome of $G(n,p_n)$ (slightly correcting a prediction of Linial-Mosheiff).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06095v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Anastos, Matthew Kwan, Benjamin Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertices of the monotone path polytopes of hypersimplicies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14102v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The monotone path polytope of a polytope $P$ encapsulates the combinatorial behavior of the shadow vertex rule (a pivot rule used in linear programming) on $P$. Computing monotone path polytopes is the entry door to the larger subject of fiber polytopes, for which explicitly computing examples remains a challenge. We first give a detailed presentation on how to construct monotone path polytopes.
  Monotone path polytopes of cubes and simplices have been known since the seminal article of Billera and Sturmfels. We extend these results to hypersimplices by linking this problem to the combinatorics of lattice paths. Indeed, we give a combinatorial model which describes the vertices of the monotone path polytope of the hypersimplex $\Delta(n, 2)$ (for any generic direction). With this model, we give a precise count of these vertices, and furthermore count the number of coherent monotone paths on $\Delta(n, 2)$ according to their lengths.
  We prove that some of the results obtained also hold for hypersimplices $\Delta(n, k)$ for $k\geq 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14102v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Germain Poullot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pretty good fractional revival on abelian Cayley graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20367v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a graph with the adjacency matrix $A$. The transition matrix of $\Gamma$, denoted $H(t)$, is defined as $H(t) := \exp(-\textbf{i}tA)$, where $\textbf{i} := \sqrt{-1}$ and $t$ is a real variable. The graph $\Gamma$ is said to exhibit fractional revival (FR in short) between the vertices $a$ and $b$ if there exists a positive real number $t$ such that $H(t){\textbf{e}_{a}} = \alpha{\textbf{e}_{a}} + \beta{\textbf{e}_{b}}$, where $\alpha, \beta \in \mathbb{C}$ such that $\beta \neq 0$ and $|\alpha|^2 + |\beta|^2 = 1$. The graph $\Gamma$ is said to exhibit pretty good fractional revival (PGFR in short) between the vertices $a$ and $b$ if there exists a sequence of real numbers $\{t_k\}$ with $\lim_{k\to\infty} H(t_k){\textbf{e}_{a}} = \alpha{\textbf{e}_{a}} + \beta{\textbf{e}_{b}}$, where $\alpha, \beta \in \mathbb{C}$ such that $\beta \neq 0$ and $|\alpha|^2 + |\beta|^2 = 1$. In the definition of PGFR, if $\alpha=0$ then $\Gamma$ is said to exhibit pretty good state transfer (PGST in short) between $a$ and $b$. In this paper, we obtain some sufficient conditions for circulant graphs exhibiting PGFR. We also find some sufficient conditions for non-circulant abelian Cayley graphs exhibiting PGFR. From these sufficient conditions, we find infinite families of circulant graphs and non-circulant abelian Cayley graphs exhibiting PGFR that fail to exhibit FR and PGST. Finally, we obtain some necessary conditions for some families of circulant graphs exhibiting PGFR. Some of our results generalize the results of Chan et al. [Pretty good quantum fractional revival in paths and cycles. \textit {Algebr. Comb.} 4(6) (2021), 989-1004.] for cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20367v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kalita, Bikash Bhattacharjya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenspace embeddings of imprimitive association schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08733v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a given symmetric association scheme $\mathcal{A}$ and its eigenspace $S_j$ there exists a mapping of vertices of $\mathcal{A}$ to unit vectors of $S_j$, known as the spherical representation of $\mathcal{A}$ in $S_j$, such that the inner products of these vectors only depend on the relation between the corresponding vertices; furthermore, these inner products only depend on the parameters of $\mathcal{A}$. We consider parameters of imprimitive association schemes listed as open cases in the list of parameters for quotient-polynomial graphs recently published by Herman and Maleki, and study embeddings of their substructures into some eigenspaces consistent with spherical representations of the putative association schemes. Using this, we obtain nonexistence for two parameter sets for $4$-class association schemes and one parameter sets for a $5$-class association scheme passing all previously known feasibility conditions, as well as uniqueness for two parameter sets for $5$-class association schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08733v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jano\v{s} Vidali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rainbow triangles and the Erd\H{o}s-Hajnal problem in projective geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13781v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate a geometric version of the Erd\H{o}s-Hajnal conjecture that applies to finite projective geometries rather than graphs, in both its usual 'induced' form and the multicoloured form. The multicoloured conjecture states, roughly, that a colouring $c$ of the points of $\mathsf{PG}(n-1,q)$ containing no copy of a fixed colouring $c_0$ of $\mathsf{PG}(k-1,q)$ for small $k$ must contain a subspace of dimension polynomial in $n$ that avoids some colour.
  If $(k,q) = (2,2)$, then $c_0$ is a colouring of a three-element 'triangle', and there are three essentially different cases, all of which we resolve. We derive both the cases where $c_0$ assigns the same colour to two different elements from a recent breakthrough result in additive combinatorics due to Kelley and Meka. We handle the case that $c_0$ is a 'rainbow' colouring by proving that rainbow-triangle-free colourings of projective geometries are exactly those that admit a certain decomposition into two-coloured pieces. This is closely analogous to a theorem of Gallai on rainbow-triangle-free coloured complete graphs. We also show that existing structure theorems resolve certain two-coloured cases where $(k,q) = (2,3)$, and $(k,q) = (3,2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13781v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolyn Chun, James Dylan Douthitt, Wayne Ge, Tony Huynh, Matthew E. Kroeker, Peter Nelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the quadratic 8-edge case of the Brown-Erd\H{o}s-S\'os problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01739v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $f^{(r)}(n;s,k)$ be the maximum number of edges in an $n$-vertex $r$-uniform hypergraph containing no $k$ edges on at most $s$ vertices. Brown, Erd\H{o}s and S\'os conjectured in 1973 that the limit $\lim_{n\rightarrow \infty}n^{-2}f^{(3)}(n;k+2,k)$ exists for all $k$. Recently, Delcourt and Postle settled the conjecture and their approach was generalised by Shangguan to every uniformity $r\ge 4$: the limit $\lim_{n\rightarrow \infty}n^{-2}f^{(r)}(n;rk-2k+2,k)$ exists for all $r\ge 3$ and $k\ge 2$.
  The value of the limit is currently known for $k\in \{2,3,4,5,6,7\}$ due to various results authored by Glock, Joos, Kim, K\"{u}hn, Lichev, Pikhurko, R\"odl and Sun. In this paper we consider the case $k=8$, determining the value of the limit for each $r\ge 4$ and presenting a lower bound for $k=3$ that we conjecture to be sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01739v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Pikhurko, Shumin Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Composition-Based Approach to EKR Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{A}$ be a family of subsets of a finite set. A subfamily of $\mathcal{A}$ is said to be intersecting when any two of its members contain at least one common element. We say that $\mathcal{A}$ is an Erd{\H o}s-Ko-Rado (EKR) family if, for every element $x$ of the set, the subfamily consisting of all members of $\mathcal{A}$ that contain $x$ has the maximum cardinality among all intersecting subfamilies of $\mathcal{A}$.
  If these subfamilies are the only maximum intersecting subfamilies of $\mathcal{A}$, then $\mathcal{A}$ is called a strong EKR family. In this article, we introduce a compositional framework to establish the EKR and strong EKR properties in set systems when some subfamilies are known to satisfy the EKR or strong EKR properties. Our method is powerful enough to yield simpler proofs for several existing results, including those derived from Katona's cycle method (1968), Borg and Meagher's admissible ordering method (2016), related results on the family of permutations studied by Frankl and Deza (1977) and the family of perfect matchings of complete graphs of even order investigated by Meagher and Moura (2005). To demonstrate the applicability and effectiveness of our method when other existing methods have not been successful, we show that for every fixed $r$-uniform hypergraph $H$ and all sufficiently large integers $n$, the family of all subhypergraphs of the complete $r$-uniform hypergraph on $n$ vertices that are isomorphic to $H$ satisfies the strong EKR property, where two copies of $H$ are considered intersecting if they share at least one common hyperedge. Moreover, when the structural constraint $H$ is restricted to be a cycle, we establish a series of EKR results for families of cycles in the complete graph $K_n$ and the complete bipartite graph $K_{n,n}$ for a broad range of the parameter $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06207v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. B. Ebrahimi, A. Taherkhani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The lonely runner conjecture holds for eight runners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14111v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the lonely runner conjecture holds for eight runners. Our proof relies on a computer verification and on recent results that allow bounding the size of a minimal counterexample. We note that our approach also applies to the known cases with 4, 5, 6, and 7 runners. We expect that minor improvements to our approach could be enough to solve the cases of 9 or 10 runners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14111v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Rosenfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow polytopes for extensions of bipartite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The space of unit flows on a finite acyclic directed graph is a lattice polytope called the flow polytope of the graph. Given a bipartite graph $G$ with minimum degree at least two, we construct two associated acyclic directed graphs: the extension of $G$ and the almost-degree-whiskered graph of $G$. We prove that the normalized volume of the flow polytope for the extension of $G$ is equal to the number of matchings in the almost-degree-whiskered graph of $G$. Further, we refine this result by proving that the Ehrhart $h^*$-polynomial of the flow polytope for the extension of $G$ is equal to the unsigned matching polynomial of the almost-degree-whiskered graph of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26445v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Braun, Kaitlin Bruegge, Robert Davis, Derek Hanely</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the quadratic complexity of subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$ of bounded $\mathrm{VC_{2}}$-dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12767v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In prior work, we showed that subsets of $\mathbb{F}_{p}^{n}$ of $\mathrm{VC_{2}}$-dimension at most $k$ are well approximated by a union of atoms of a quadratic factor of complexity $(\ell,q)$, where the complexity $\ell$ of the linear part and the complexity $q$ of the quadratic part are both bounded in terms of $k$, $p$, and the desired level of approximation $\mu$. A key tool in the proof of this result was an arithmetic regularity lemma for the Gowers $U^3$-norm by Green and Tao, which resulted in tower-type bounds (in terms of $\mu^{-1}$) on both $\ell$ and $q$.
  In the present paper we show that for sets of bounded $\mathrm{VC}_2$-dimension, the bound on $q$ can be substantially improved. Specifically, we will prove that any set $A\subseteq G=\mathbb{F}_p^n$ of $\mathrm{VC}_2$-dimension at most $k$ is approximately equal (up to error $\mu |G|$) to a union of atoms of a quadratic factor whose quadratic complexity is at most $\log_p(\mu^{-k-o(1)})$, implying that the purely quadratic component of the factor partitions the group into $\mu^{-k-o(1)}$ many parts.
  We achieve this by using our earlier result to obtain an initial quadratic factor $\mathcal{B}$, and then applying a generalization of an argument of Alon, Fox and Zhao for subsets of $\mathbb{F}_{p}^{n}$ of bounded $\mathrm{VC}$-dimension to the label space (also known as "configuration space") of $\mathcal{B}$. A related strategy was employed in earlier work of the authors on $\mathrm{NFOP}_2$ subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$, and in work of the first author in the context of 3-uniform hypergraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12767v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Terry, J. Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The structure of subsets of $\mathbb{F}_p^n$ of bounded $\mathrm{VC}_2$-dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12867v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that a subset of $\mathbb{F}_{p}^{n}$ of $\mathrm{VC_{2}}$-dimension at most $k$ is well approximated by a union of atoms of a quadratic factor of complexity $(\ell,q)$ (denoting the complexities of the linear and quadratic part, respectively), where $\ell$ and $q$ are bounded by a constant depending only on $k$ and the desired level of approximation. This generalises a result of Alon, Fox and Zhao on the structure of sets of bounded $\mathrm{VC}$-dimension, and is analogous to contemporaneous work of the authors arXiv:2111.01737 in the setting of 3-uniform hypergraphs.
  The main result originally appeared--albeit with a different proof--in a 2021 preprint arXiv:2111.01739, which has since been split into two: the present work, which focuses on higher arity NIP and develops a theory of local uniformity semi-norms of possibly independent interest, and its companion arXiv:2111.01739, which strengthens these results under a generalized notion of stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12867v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Terry, J. Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VC-Dimension vs Degree: An Uncertainty Principle for Boolean Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13705v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we uncover a new uncertainty principle that governs the complexity of Boolean functions. This principle manifests as a fundamental trade-off between two central measures of complexity: a combinatorial complexity of its supported set, captured by its Vapnik-Chervonenkis dimension ($\mathrm{VC}(f)$), and its algebraic structure, captured by its polynomial degree over various fields. We establish two primary inequalities that formalize this trade-off: $\mathrm{VC}(f)+\mathrm{deg}(f)\ge n,$ and $\mathrm{VC}(f)+\mathrm{deg}_{\mathbb{F}_2}(f)\ge n$. In particular, these results recover the classical uncertainty principle on the discrete hypercube, as well as the Sziklai--Weiner's bound in the case of $\mathbb{F}_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13705v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Chang, Yijia Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monogamy of entanglement between cones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.11805v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A separable quantum state shared between parties $A$ and $B$ can be symmetrically extended to a quantum state shared between party $A$ and parties $B_1,\ldots ,B_k$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Quantum states that are not separable, i.e., entangled, do not have this property. This phenomenon is known as "monogamy of entanglement". We show that monogamy is not only a feature of quantum theory, but that it characterizes the minimal tensor product of general pairs of convex cones $\mathsf{C}_A$ and $\mathsf{C}_B$: The elements of the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ are precisely the tensors that can be symmetrically extended to elements in the maximal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\max} \mathsf{C}^{\otimes_{\max} k}_B$ for every $k\in\mathbf{N}$. Equivalently, the minimal tensor product of two cones is the intersection of the nested sets of $k$-extendible tensors. It is a natural question when the minimal tensor product $\mathsf{C}_A\otimes_{\min} \mathsf{C}_B$ coincides with the set of $k$-extendible tensors for some finite $k$. We show that this is universally the case for every cone $\mathsf{C}_A$ if and only if $\mathsf{C}_B$ is a polyhedral cone with a base given by a product of simplices. Our proof makes use of a new characterization of products of simplices up to affine equivalence that we believe is of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.11805v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00208-024-02935-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Math. Ann. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Aubrun, Alexander M\"uller-Hermes, Martin Pl\'avala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphon Quantum Filtering Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12249v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a non-exchangeable system of interacting quantum particles with mean-field type interactions, subject to continuous measurement on dense graphs. In the mean-field limit, we derive a graphon-based quantum filtering system, establish its well-posedness, and prove propagation of chaos for multi-class bosonic systems with blockwise interactions. We then discuss applications to quantum state preparation and quantum graphon games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12249v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Amini, Nina H. Amini, Sofiane Chalal, Gaoyue Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admissible set and squarefree-power-like function with applications to squarefree symbolic powers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01366v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the abstract notion of squarefree-power-like functions, which unify the sequences of squarefree ordinary and symbolic powers of squarefree monomial ideals. By employing the Tor-vanishing criteria for mixed sums of ideals, we establish sharp lower bounds for their Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity in terms of what we call the admissible set of the associated hypergraph. As an application, we derive the first general combinatorial lower bound for the regularity of squarefree symbolic powers of monomial ideals. In the setting of edge ideals, by exploiting the special combinatorial structures of block graphs and Cohen-Macaulay chordal graphs, we show that this bound turns into an exact formula for all squarefree symbolic powers of block graphs, as well as for the second squarefree symbolic powers of edge ideals of Cohen-Macaulay chordal graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01366v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trung Chau, Kanoy Kumar Das, Amit Roy, Kamalesh Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skeletons and Spectra: Bernoulli graphings are relatively Ramanujan</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13323v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to investigate the spectral theory of unimodular random graphs and graphings representing them. We prove that Bernoulli graphings are relatively Ramanujan with respect to their skeleton Markov chain. That is, the part of their spectrum that comes from the random labels falls within the appropriate Alon-Boppana bound. This result complements an example due to Fr\k{a}czyk of an ergodic unimodular random graph with almost sure spectral gap but non-expanding Bernoulli graphing.
  We also highlight connections of our work with the theory of finite random graphs. Exploiting the result of Bordenave and Collins on random lifts being relatively almost Ramanujan, we prove a strengthening of our main theorem for unimodular quasi-transitive quasi-trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13323v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'ector Jard\'on-S\'anchez, L\'aszl\'o M\'arton T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
