<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 10:06:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Tripodal structure in undersaturated random graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We numerically investigate typical graphs in a region of the Strauss model of random graphs with constraints on the densities of edges and triangles. This region, where typical graphs had been expected to be bipodal but turned out to be tripodal, involves edge densities $e$ below $e_0 = (3-\sqrt{3})/6 \approx 0.2113$ and triangle densities $t$ slightly below $e^3$. We determine the extent of this region in $(e,t)$ space and show that there is a discontinuous phase transition at the boundary between this region and a bipodal phase. We further show that there is at least one phase transition within this region, where the parameters describing typical graphs change discontinuously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16797v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William DiCarlo, Lorenzo Sadun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Vu's conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2002, Vu conjectured that graphs of maximum degree $\Delta$ and maximum codegree at most $\zeta \Delta$ have chromatic number at most $(\zeta+o(1))\Delta$. Despite its importance, the conjecture has remained widely open. The only direct progress so far has been obtained in the ``dense regime,'' when $\zeta$ is close to $1$, by Hurley, de Verclos, and Kang.
  In this paper we provide the first progress in the sparse regime $\zeta \ll 1$, the case of primary interest to Vu. We show that there exists $\zeta_0 &gt; 0$ such that for all $\zeta \in [\log^{-32}\Delta,\zeta_0]$, the following holds: if $G$ is a graph with maximum degree $\Delta$ and maximum codegree at most $\zeta \Delta$, then $\chi(G) \leq (\zeta^{1/32} + o(1))\Delta$. We derive this from a more general result that assumes only that the common neighborhood of any $s$ vertices is bounded rather than the codegrees of pairs of vertices. Our more general result also extends to the list coloring setting, which is of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16818v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Bradshaw, Abhishek Dhawan, Abhishek Methuku, Michael C. Wigal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity and recurrence in infinite words and related structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the asymptotics and fine-scale behavior of quantitative combinatorial measures of infinite words and related dynamical and algebraic structures.
  We construct infinite recurrent words $w$ whose complexity functions $p_w(n)$ are arbitrarily close to linear, but whose discrete derivatives are not bounded from above by $p_w(n)/n$. Moreover, we construct words of polynomially bounded complexity whose discrete derivatives exceed $p_w(n)/n^\varepsilon$ infinitely often, for every given $\varepsilon&gt;0$. These provide negative answers in a strong sense to an open question of Cassaigne from 1997, showing that his theorem on words of linear complexity is best possible.
  Next, we characterize, up to a linear multiplicative error, the complexity functions of strictly ergodic subshifts, showing that every non-decreasing, submultiplicative function arises in this setting. This gives the first `industrial' construction of strictly ergodic subshifts of prescribed subexponential complexity.
  We then investigate quantitative recurrence in uniformly recurrent words and, as an application, address a question of Bavula from 2006 related to holonomic inequalities on the spectrum of possible filter dimensions of simple associative algebras: we construct simple algebras of prescribed filter dimension in $[1,\infty)$ and essentially settling the problem entirely in the graded case. Throughout, we construct uniformly recurrent words of linear complexity and with arbitrary polynomial recurrence growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16840v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Be'eri Greenfeld, Carlos Gustavo Moreira, Efim Zelmanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tail bound for cumulant series for complex functions of independent random variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We obtain explicit bounds on the truncation error of the cumulant series of a bounded complex function of a random vector with independent components. The bounds are based on multidimensional differences. This extends the theory of the author with Brendan McKay and Rui-Ray Zhang (J. Combin. Th., Ser. B, 2025) from real functions to complex functions. We demonstrate some initial applications including a Berry--Esseen bound, an Edgeworth expansion for triangles in random graphs, and enumeration of regular graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16952v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Isaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric $(2^k-1,2^{k-1},2^{k-2})$-designs which are $(2^{k-1}-1)$-pyramidal over abelian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A design is called $t$-pyramidal when it has an automorphism group which fixes $t$ points and acts sharply transitively on the remaining points. We determine all symmetric $(2^k-1,2^{k-1},2^{k-2})$-designs which are $(2^{k-1}-1)$-pyramidal over abelian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16963v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Pankov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumeration of Cayley graphs over a nonabelian group of order $8p$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $T_{8p} = \left\langle a,b\mid a^{2p}=b^8=e,a^p=b^4,b^{-1}ab=a^{-1} \right\rangle$ be a nonabelian group of order $8p$, where $p$ is an odd prime number. In this paper, we give the formula to calculate the number of Cayley graphs over $T_{8p}$ up to isomorphism by using the P\'olya Enumeration Theorem. Moreover, we get the formula to calculate the number of connected Cayley graphs over $T_{8p}$ by deleting the disconnected graphs. By applying the results, we list the exact number of (connected) Cayley graphs for $3\leq p \leq 13$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17035v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bei Ye, Xiaogang Liu, Jing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal designs and symmetric Hadamard matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our main result is the construction of symmetric Hadamard matrices of order q(1 + q) where q is a prime power congruent to 3 mod 8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17141v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dragomir \v{Z}. Djokovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossing and non-crossing families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a finite set $P$ of points in the plane in general position, a \emph{crossing family} of size $k$ in $P$ is a collection of $k$ line segments with endpoints in $P$ that are pairwise crossing. It is a long-standing open problem to determine the largest size of a crossing family in any set of $n$ points in the plane in general position. It is widely believed that this size should be linear in $n$.
  Motivated by results from the theory of partitioning complete geometric graphs, we study a variant of this problem for point sets $P$ that do not contain a \emph{non-crossing family} of size $m$, which is a collection of 4 disjoint subsets $P_1$, $P_2$, $P_3$, and $P_4$ of $P$, each containing $m$ points of $P$, such that for every choice of 4 points $p_i \in P_i$, the set $\{p_1,p_2,p_3,p_4\}$ is such that $p_4$ is in the interior of the triangle formed by $p_1,p_2,p_3$. We prove that, for every $m \in \mathbb{N}$, each set $P$ of $n$ points in the plane in general position contains either a crossing family of size $n/2^{O(\sqrt{\log{m}})}$ or a non-crossing family of size $m$, by this strengthening a recent breakthrough result by Pach, Rubin, and Tardos (2021). Our proof is constructive and we show that these families can be obtained in expected time $O(nm^{1+o(1)})$. We also prove that a crossing family of size $\Omega(n/m)$ or a non-crossing family of size $m$ in $P$ can be found in expected time $O(n)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17277v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Todor Anti\'c, Martin Balko, Birgit Vogtenhuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An eigenvalue interlacing approach to Garland's method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a pure $d$-dimensional simplicial complex. For $0\le k\le d$, let $X(k)$ be the set of $k$-dimensional faces of $X$, let $\tilde{L}_k(X)$ be the $k$-dimensional weighted total Laplacian operator on $X$, and let $\tilde{H}_k(X;\mathbb{R})$ be its $k$-dimensional reduced homology group with real coefficients. For $\sigma\in X$, let $\text{lk}(X,\sigma)$ be the link of $\sigma$ in $X$. For a matrix $M$, we denote by $\text{Spec}(M)$ the multi-set containing all the eigenvalues of $M$. We show that, for every $0\le \ell&lt;k \le d$, \[
  \text{dim}(\tilde{H}_k(X;\mathbb{R}))\le \sum_{\eta\in X(\ell)}\left| \left\{ \lambda\in \text{Spec}(\tilde{L}_{k-\ell-1}(\text{lk}(X,\eta))) :\, \lambda\le \frac{(\ell+1)(d-k)}{k+1}\right\}\right|. \] This extends the classical vanishing theorem of Garland, corresponding to the special case when the right hand side of the inequality is equal to zero, and a more recent result by Hino and Kanazawa, corresponding to the case $\ell=k-1$. A main new ingredient in our proof is an abstract version of Garland's local to global principle, which follows as a simple consequence of the eigenvalue interlacing theorem, and may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17279v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan Lew</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Additive systems for $\mathbb{Z}$ are undecidable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: What are the collections of sets ${A}_i\subset\mathbb{Z}$ such that any $n\in\mathbb{Z}$ has exactly one representation as $n=a_0+a_1+\dotsb$ with $a_i\in{A}_i$? The answer for $\mathbb{N}_0$ instead of $\mathbb{Z}$ is given by a theorem of de Bruijn. We describe a family of natural candidate collections for $\mathbb{Z}$, which we call canonical collections. Translating the problem into the language of dynamical systems, we show that the question of whether the sumset of a canonical collection covers the entire $\mathbb{Z}$ is difficult: specifically, there is a collection for which this question is equivalent to the Collatz conjecture, and there is a well-behaved family of collections for which this question is equivalent to the universal halting problem for Fractran and is therefore undecidable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17285v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Zabolotskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intersections of longest cycles in vertex-transitive and highly connected graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the classical conjectures of Lov\'asz, Thomassen, and Smith, recent work has renewed interest in the study of longest cycles in important graph families, such as vertex-transitive and highly connected graphs. In particular, Groenland et al.\ proved that if two longest cycles and in a graph share $m$ vertices, then there exists a vertex cut of size $O(m^{8/5})$ separating them, yielding improved bounds toward these conjectures. Their proof combines Tur\'an-type arguments with computer-assisted search.
  We prove two results addressing problems of Babai (1979) and Smith (1984) on intersections of longest cycles in vertex-transitive and highly connected graphs. First, we strengthen the bound of Groenland et al.\ by showing that if two longest cycles and in a graph share $m$ vertices, then there exists a vertex cut of size $O(m^{3/2})$ separating them. As a consequence, we show that in every \(k\)-connected graph, any two longest cycles intersect in at least \(\Omega(k^{2/3})\) vertices, improving the best known bound toward Smith's conjecture. Our proof is purely combinatorial, employing supersaturation-type estimates beyond the existing Tur\'an-type approach. Second, we prove that in every connected vertex-transitive graph on \(n\) vertices, any two longest cycles intersect in at least \(f(n)\) vertices for some function \(f(n)\to\infty\) as \(n\to\infty\), thereby resolving a problem of Babai (1979) for the class of vertex-transitive graphs central to his original motivation. In doing so, we introduce a new method for constructing longer cycles in vertex-transitive graphs based on a given cycle, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17438v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Ma, Ziyuan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial Extensions on Andrews and El Bachraoui's Almost-Distinct Partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Andrews and El Bachraoui recently studied integer partitions where the smallest part is repeated a specified number of times and any other parts are distinct. Their results included two ``surprising identities'' for which they requested combinatorial proofs. We provide combinatorial proofs for an infinite family of related identities and also consider the analogous partitions where only the largest part can be repeated. The results give rise to infinite families of inequalities for the number of partitions with distinct parts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17459v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Refinement of the Crank-Mex Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is proved that the number of partitions of n with odd mex and k parts that aren't ones equals the number of partitions of n with nonnegative crank and k parts that aren't ones..</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17491v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George E Andrews, Moshe Newman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Values Versus Expansion in Directed and Undirected Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We relate the nontrivial singular values $\sigma_2,\ldots,\sigma_n$ of the normalized adjacency matrix of an Eulerian directed graph to combinatorial measures of graph expansion: \\ 1. We introduce a new directed analogue of conductance $\phi_{dir}$, and prove a Cheeger-like inequality showing that $\phi_{dir}$ is bounded away from 0 iff $\sigma_2$ is bounded away from 1. In undirected graphs, this can be viewed as a unification of the standard Cheeger Inequality and Trevisan's Cheeger Inequality for the smallest eigenvalue.\\ 2. We prove a singular-value analogue of the Higher-Order Cheeger Inequalities, giving a combinatorial characterization of when $\sigma_k$ is bounded away from 1. \\ 3. We tighten the relationship between $\sigma_2$ and vertex expansion, proving that if a $d$-regular graph $G$ with the property that all sets $S$ of size at most $n/2$ have at least $(1+\delta)\cdot |S|$ out-neighbors, then $1-\sigma_2=\Omega(\delta^2/d)$. This bound is tight and saves a factor of $d$ over the previously known relationship.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17539v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jake Ruotolo, Salil Vadhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Burning numbers via eigenpolytopes -- Hamming graphs, Johnson graphs, and halved cubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give lower and upper bounds on the burning number of Hamming graphs, Johnson graphs, and halved cube graphs. For the lower bounds, we use the fact that $1$-skeletons of the eigenpolytopes of these graphs are isomorphic to the original graphs. Then, we present a dynamic search algorithm performed on the eigenpolytope to find an unburned vertex. This idea was originally used by Alon (Discrete Appl.\ Math.,\ 1992), who determined the burning number of the hypercube graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17559v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Tanaka, Norihide Tokushige</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Size Condition for Small Diameter Orientable Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 2002, Koh and Tay conjectured that every bridgeless graph of order $n\geq 5$ and size at least ${n\choose 2}-n+5$ has an orientation of diameter two. Later, Cochran, Czabarka, Dankelmann and Sz\'{e}kely proved this conjecture and asked what is the minimum number of edges required in a bridgeless graph of order $n$ to guarantee the existence of an orientation of diameter at most $d$? We conjecture that the answer is ${n-d \choose 2}+n+2$. We prove this conjecture for the case $d=n-2$ and prove the lower bound of this conjecture for the case $5\leq d\leq n-2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17569v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sopon Boriboon, Teeradej Kittipassorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On graphs with equal and different Kromatic symmetric functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kromatic symmetric function (KSF) $\overline{X}_G$ of a graph $G$ is a $K$-analogue introduced by Crew, Pechenik, and Spirkl in arXiv:2301.02177 of Stanley's chromatic symmetric function (CSF) $X_G$. The KSF is known to distinguish some pairs of graphs with the same CSF. The first author showed in arXiv:2403.15929 and arXiv:2502.21285 that the number of copies in $G$ of certain induced subgraphs can be determined given $\overline{X}_G$, and conjectured that $\overline{X}_G$ distinguishes all graphs. We disprove that conjecture by finding four pairs of 8-vertex graphs with equal KSF, as well as giving several ways to use existing graph pairs with equal KSF to construct larger graph pairs that also have equal KSF. On the other hand, we show that many of the graph pairs from the constructions of Orellana and Scott in arXiv:1308.6005 and of Aliste-Prieto, Crew, Spirkl, and Zamora in arXiv:2007.11042 of graphs with the same CSF are distinguished by the KSF, thus also giving some new examples of cases where the KSF is a stronger invariant than the CSF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17682v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Pierson, Soham Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analogue of the Erd{\H o}s Matching Conjecture for permutations with fixed number of cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $S_{n}$ denote the set of permutations of $[n]=\{1,2,\dots, n\}$. For each integer $k\geq 1$, let $S_{n,k}$ be the set of all permutations of $[n]$ with exactly $k$ disjoint cycles.
  A subset $H\subseteq S_{n,k}$ is to be a matching if $\pi_1$ and $\pi_2$ do not have any common cycles for all distinct $\pi_1,\pi_2\in H$. The matching number of a family $\mathcal A\subseteq S_{n,k}$ is denoted by $\nu_{p}(\mathcal A)$ and is defined to be the size of the largest matching in $\mathcal A$. In this paper, we determine the maximum size of a family $\mathcal A\subseteq S_{n,k}$ subject to the condition $\nu_p(\mathcal A)\leq s$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17683v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Yeaw Ku, Kok Bin Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hook immanantal equalities for linear combination matrices of (di)graphs and their applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\chi_\lambda$ be an irreducible character of the symmetric group $S_n$. For an $n \times n$ matrix $M = (m_{ij})$, define the immanant of $M$ corresponding to $\chi_\lambda$ by \begin{eqnarray*} d_\lambda(M) = \sum_{\sigma \in S_n} \chi_\lambda(\sigma) \prod_{i=1}^n m_{i\sigma(i)}. \end{eqnarray*} For $\lambda = (k, 1^{n-k})$, the immanant $d_{(k, 1^{n-k})}(M)$ is called the hook immanant and denoted by $d_k(M)$. The hook immanant polynomial of matrix $M$ is defined as $d_{k}(xI_n - M)$, where $I_n$ is the $n \times n$ identity matrix. Let $G$ and $\overrightarrow{G}$ be a graph and a digraph, respectively. Suppose that $D(G)$ and $A(G)$ (resp. $D(\overrightarrow{G})$ and $A(\overrightarrow{G})$) are the degree matrix and adjacency matrix of $G$ (resp. $\overrightarrow{G}$), respectively. In this paper, we characterize two hook immanantal equalities for the linear combination of matrices $\beta D(G)+\gamma A(G)$ and $\beta D(\overrightarrow{G})+\gamma A(\overrightarrow{G})$, where $\beta$ and $\gamma$ are real numbers. As applications, we derive recursive formulas for the hook immanantal polynomials and hook immanants of graph matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17743v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangshuai Dong, Tingzeng Wu, HongJian Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero blocking numbers of graphs with complexity results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a graph $G$ in which vertices are either black or white, a zero forcing process is an iterative vertex color changing process such that the only white neighbor of a black vertex becomes black in the next time step. A zero forcing set is an initial subset of black vertices in a zero forcing process ultimately expands to include all vertices of the graph; otherwise we call its complement a zero blocking set. The zero blocking number $B(G)$ of $G$ is the minimum size of a zero blocking set. This paper determines zero blocking numbers of the union and the join of two graphs. It also determines all minimum zero blocking sets of hypercubes. Finally, a linear-time algorithm for the zero blocking numbers of trees is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17785v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hau-Yi Lin, Wu-Hsiung Lin, Gerard Jennhwa Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper bounds on the odd graceful chromatic number of graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We obtain several new upper bounds of the odd graceful chromatic number of a graph $G$, which must be bipartite. Some of our bounds depend only on the number of the vertices of $G$ or the chromatic number of some graphs related to the bipartition of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17799v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Afifurrahman, Fawwaz Fakhrurrozi Hadiputra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On nut graphs with two vertex and three edge orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nut graphs are graphs whose adjacency matrix is singular with one-dimensional null space spanned by a vector with no zero entries. In a recent paper, Ba\v{s}i\'c, Fowler and Pisanski proved that the automorphism group of a nut graph has more orbits on the edge set than on the vertex set. They classified all orders for which a vertex-transitive nut graph with precisely two edge orbits exists, and conjectured that a nut graph with two vertex and three edge orbits exists for each non-prime order $n \ge 9$. Motivated by this conjecture, we introduce a very general construction that provides graphs with the desired symmetry properties, and we determine some sufficient spectral and structural conditions under which they are nut graphs. The construction yields infinite families of examples and confirms the above conjecture for all odd non-prime orders up to $2\,500$ and for at least $99.8$ percent of all odd non-prime orders up to a million. Finally, we present some additional interesting examples of nut graphs with two vertex and three edge orbits that do not arise from this construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17842v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ksenija Rozman, Primo\v{z} \v{S}parl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterisations and Structural Properties of Pure n-Simplicial Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper extends the concept of trees in graphs to the context of pure n-simplicial complexes by generalising the notion of paths and cycles (in graphs). We introduce and study these higher-dimensional analogues of trees known as pure n-simplicial trees. Our main result is to establish the equivalence between pure n-simplicial trees and the (m, n)-trees introduced by Dewdney in 1974 when m = n - 1, thereby extending and improving his original characterisation. We also disprove two conjectures proposed by Dewdney in 1974 by providing counterexamples, and we present a refined version of the conjecture with an added condition, along with a rigorous proof. Our results contribute to the theoretical knowledge of higher-dimensional trees and their structural properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17854v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Kottari, Niteesh Sahni, Qazi J. Azhad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic properties of $t$-Schur overpartitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent work, Nadji and Ahmia introduced the $t$-Schur overpartitions as an overpartition analogue for $t$-Schur partitions, which generalizes the classical Schur's partitions into parts congruent to $1$ or $5$ modulo $6$. We continue the study of this new class of overpartitions and prove several arithmetic results for the cases $t=3,9$ and $t$ being a power of $2$ or a power of $3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17928v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed L. Nadji, Manjil P. Saikia, James A. Sellers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbation of dense graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the past two decades, various properties of randomly perturbed/augmented (hyper)graphs have been intensively studied, since the model was introduced by Bohman, Frieze and Martin in 2003. The model usually considers a deterministic graph $G$ with minimum degree condition, perturbed/augmented by a binomial random graph $G(n,p)$ on the same vertex set. In this paper, we show that for many problems of finding spanning subgraphs, one can indeed relax the minimum degree condition to a density condition. This includes the embedding problem for $F$-factors when $F$ is not a forest, graphs with bounded maximum degree, $r$-th power of $k$-uniform tight Hamilton cycles for $r,k\ge 2$, and $k$-uniform Hamilton $\ell$-cycles for $\ell\in[2,k-1]$. These results strengthen the results of Balogh, Treglown, and Wagner, of B\"{o}ttcher, Montgomery, Parczyk, and Person, and of Chang, Han and Thoma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18042v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Han, Seonghyuk Im, Bin Wang, Junxue Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Transfer on Unitary Cayley Graphs and Quadratic Unitary Cayley Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The unitary Cayley graph, denoted $X_n$, is the graph with vertex set ${\mathbb{Z}}_n$ such that two distinct vertices $a$ and $b$ are adjacent if $a-b=u$ for some $u$ with $1 \leq u \leq n-1$ and $\gcd(u,n) = 1$. The quadratic unitary Cayley graph, denoted $G_n$, is the graph with vertex set ${\mathbb{Z}}_n$ such that two distinct vertices $a$ and $b$ are adjacent if $a-b=u^2$ or $a-b=-u^2$ for some $u$ with $1 \leq u \leq n-1$ and $\gcd(u,n) = 1$. In this paper, we classify all $X_n$ admitting pretty good fractional. We also classify all $X_n$ that admit fractional revival. It turns out that $X_n$ admits fractional revival if and only if it admits pretty good fractional revival. Further, we classify all $G_n$ admitting periodicity. As a consequence, we obtain all $G_n$ admitting perfect state transfer. We also classify $G_n$ admitting pretty good state transfer, pretty good fractional revival and fractional revival.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18068v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kalita, Bikash Bhattacharjya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Graham's rearrangement conjecture over $\mathbb{F}_2^n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A sequence $s_1,s_2,\ldots, s_k$ of elements of a group $G$ is called a valid ordering if the partial products $s_1, s_1 s_2, \ldots, s_1\cdots s_k$ are all distinct. A long-standing problem in combinatorial group theory asks whether, for a given group $G$, every subset $S \subseteq G\setminus \{\mathrm{id}\}$ admits a valid ordering; the instance of the additive group $\mathbb{F}_p$ is the content of a well-known 1971 conjecture of Graham. Most partial progress to date has concerned the edge cases where either $S$ or $G \setminus S$ is quite small. Our main result is an essentially complete resolution of the problem for $G=\mathbb{F}_2^n$: we show that there is an absolute constant $C&gt;0$ such that every subset $S\subseteq \mathbb{F}_2^n \setminus \{0\}$ of size at least $C$ admits a valid ordering. Our proof combines techniques from additive and probabilistic combinatorics, including the Freiman--Ruzsa theorem and the absorption method.
  Along the way, we also solve the general problem for moderately large subsets: there is a constant $c&gt;0$ such that for every group $G$ (not necessarily abelian), every subset $S \subseteq G\setminus \{\mathrm{id}\}$ of size at least $|G|^{1-c}$ admits a valid ordering. Previous work in this direction concerned only sets of size at least $(1-o(1))|G|$. A main ingredient in our proof is a structural result, similar in spirit to the Arithmetic Regularity Lemma, showing that every Cayley graph can be efficiently decomposed into mildly quasirandom components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18254v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Bedert, Matija Buci\'c, Noah Kravitz, Richard Montgomery, Alp M\"uyesser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proving it is impossible; on Erd\H{o}s problem $\# 278$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Erd\H{o}s asked many mathematical questions. Some lead to exciting research, others turned out to be easily solved. In this article, we provide evidence that one of his questions, Erd\H{o}s problem \#278 , has no general answer. We do so by relating it with a hard knapsack problem instance,and by demonstrating that different, non-equivalent formulas arise depending on the structure of the moduli.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18270v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stijn Cambie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random-projector quantum diagnostics of Ramsey numbers and a prime-factor heuristic for $R(5,5)=45$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16699v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a statistical framework for estimating Ramsey numbers by embedding two-color Ramsey instances into a $Z_2 \times Z_2$-graded Majorana algebra. This approach replaces brute-force enumeration with two randomized spectral diagnostics applied to operators of a given dimension d associated with Ramsey numbers: a linear projector $P_{lin}$ and an exponential map $P_{exp}(\alpha)$, suitable for both classical and quantum computation. In the diagonal case, both diagnostics identify R(5,5) at n=45. The quantum realizations act on a reduced module and therefore require only five data qubits plus a few ancillas via block-encoding/qubitization for R(5,5)=45, in stark contrast to the $\binom{n}{2} \approx 10^3$ logical qubits demanded by direct edge encodings. We also provide few-qubit estimates for R(6,6) and R(7,7), and propose a simple "prime-sequence" consistency heuristic that connects R(5,5)=45 to constrained diagonal growth. Our method echoes Erd\H{o}s's probabilistic paradigm, emphasizing randomized arguments rather than explicit colorings, and parallels the classical coin-flip approach to Ramsey bounds. Finally, we discuss potential applications of this framework to machine learning with a limited number of qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16699v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Tamburini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Property Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Property testers are fast, randomized "election polling"-type algorithms that determine if an input (e.g., graph or hypergraph) has a certain property or is $\varepsilon$-far from the property. In the dense graph model of property testing, it is known that many properties can be tested with query complexity that depends only on the error parameter $\varepsilon$ (and not on the size of the input), but the current bounds on the query complexity grow extremely quickly as a function of $1/\varepsilon$. Which properties can be tested efficiently, i.e., with $\mathrm{poly}(1/\varepsilon)$ queries? This survey presents the state of knowledge on this general question, as well as some key open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16878v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lior Gishboliner, Asaf Shapira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative selection theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The point selection theorem says that the convex hull of any finite point set contains a point that lies in a positive proportion of the simplices determined by that set. This paper proves several new volumetric versions of this theorem which replace the points by sets of large volume, including the first volumetric selection theorem for $(d+1)$-tuples. As consequences, we significantly decrease the upper bound for the number of sets necessary in a volumetric weak $\epsilon$-net, from $O_d(\epsilon^{-d^2(d+3)^2/4})$ to $O_d(\epsilon^{-(d+1)})$, and substantially reduce the the piercing number for volumetric $(p,q)$-theorems.
  We also prove a volumetric version of the homogeneous point selection theorem. To do so, we introduce a volumetric same-type lemma and a new volumetric colorful Tverberg theorem.
  We prove all of our results for diameter as well as volume.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16965v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Travis Dillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphs arising from the dual Steenrod algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17041v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend Wood's graph theoretic interpretation of certain quotients of the mod $2$ dual Steenrod algebra to quotients of the mod $p$ dual Steenrod algebra where $p$ is an odd prime and to quotients of the $C_2$-equivariant dual Steenrod algebra. We establish connectedness criteria for graphs associated to monomials in these algebra quotients and investigate questions about trees and Hamilton cycles in these settings. We also give graph theoretic interpretations of algebraic structures such as the coproduct and antipode arising from the Hopf algebra structure on the mod $p$ dual Steenrod algebra and the Hopf algebroid structure of the $C_2$-equivariant dual Steenrod algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17041v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Elliott, Courtney Hauf, Kai Morton, Sarah Petersen, Leticia Schow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Friezes and continued fractions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore basic properties of number friezes, due to Conway and Coxeter, and their relations to decompositions of rational numbers into continued fractions, Farey sequences, and the modular group acting on the hyperbolic plane. These are notes from a mini-course for undergraduate students given at the 19th Summer School ``Modern Mathematics'', Dubna, Russia, July 18-29, 2019.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17074v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgeny Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenvalues of Maximal Abelian Covers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We fully characterize the eigenvalues (flat bands) of the maximal abelian cover of a finite multi-graph in terms of the combinatorics of the base graph. This solves a problem of Higuchi and Nomura (2009, Problem 6.11). We use our new criterion to prove that the maximal abelian cover of any regular multi-graph has no eigenvalues, thereby proving a conjecture of (ibid., Conjecture 6.12). In an appendix, we relate our criterion for eigenvalues of the maximal abelian cover to an existing criterion for eigenvalues of the universal cover.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17332v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenbo Li, Michael Magee, Mostafa Sabri, Joe Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A subbase property for describing edge-end spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a previous joint work with Aurichi and Magalh\~aes Jr., we showed that the topological spaces arising from the edge-end structure of infinite graphs define a proper subfamily of those obtained through the well-known (vertex-)ends. This result was later recovered by a more general approach due to Pitz, who also stated the problem of finding a purely topological characterization for the class of edge-end spaces. His question reads as an edge-related version of a similar conjecture posed by Diestel in 1992, but there regarding the usual end structure of infinite graphs and which was recently answered also by Pitz via the existence of a suitable clopen subbase. This paper shows how an extra intersection property can be combined with his solution in order to restrict it to the edge-end spaces, hence stating a topological description for this later family as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17424v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Real</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relatively closed subgroups of permutation groups with a cyclic regular normal subgroup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by some known problems concerning combinatorial structures associated with finite one-dimensional affine permutation groups, we study subgroups which are closed in $\operatorname{\Gamma{L}}_1(q)$. This brings us to a description of the relatively closed subgroups of permutation groups with a cyclic regular normal subgroup. Our results, in particular, provide a classification of the minimal nontrivial one-dimensional affine association schemes which generalizes the recent Muzychuk classification of the one-dimensional affine rank 3 graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17664v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Buturlakin, Andrey V. Vasil'ev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Smallest Singular Value of Log-Concave Random Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17745v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $A$ be an $N\times n$ random matrix whose entries are coordinates of an isotropic log-concave random vector in $\mathbb{R}^{Nn}$. We prove sharp lower tail estimates for the smallest singular value of $A$ in the following cases: (1) when $N=n$ and $A$ is drawn from an unconditional distribution, with no independence assumption; (2) when the columns of $A$ are independent and $N\geq n$; (3) when $A$ is sufficiently tall, that is $N\geq (1+\lambda)n$ for any positive constant $\lambda$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17745v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Fernandez V, Galyna V. Livshyts, Stephanie Mui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the recursive computation of the bracket polynomial for closed 4-tangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17904v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a 4-tangle shadow, we concatenate it with itself n times and form a knot by applying a closure operation that connects each top endpoint to the corresponding bottom endpoint on the same side without introducing any crossings. We then compute the Kauffman bracket polynomial for the resulting knot using a states matrix defined with respect to the basis of the Kauffman 4-strand diagram monoid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17904v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franck Ramaharo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity of quadrics via Ehrhart theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity of the d-dimensional non-degenerate quadric hypersurface of characteristic p &gt; 2 is a rational function of p composed from the Ehrhart polynomials of integer polytopes. In consequence, we explain and recover a result of Gessel and Monsky and prove that the Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity of quadrics of fixed characteristic is a decreasing function of dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17915v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Pak, Boris Shapiro, Ilya Smirnov, Ken-ichi Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Parameterized Complexity of Grundy Domination and Zero Forcing Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18104v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider two different problem families that deal with domination in graphs. On the one hand, we focus on dominating sequences. In such a sequence, every vertex dominates some vertex of the graph that was not dominated by any earlier vertex in the sequence. The problem of finding the longest dominating sequence is known as $\mathsf{Grundy~Domination}$. Depending on whether the closed or the open neighborhoods are used for domination, there are three other versions of this problem. We show that all four problem variants are $\mathsf{W[1]}$-hard when parameterized by the solution size. On the other hand, we consider the family of Zero forcing problems which form the parameterized duals of the Grundy domination problems. In these problems, one looks for the smallest set of vertices initially colored blue such that certain color change rules are able to color all other vertices blue. Bhyravarapu et al. [IWOCA 2025] showed that one of these problems, known as $\mathsf{Zero~Forcing~Set}$, is in $\mathsf{FPT}$ when parameterized by the treewidth or the solution size. We extend their treewidth result to the other three variants of zero forcing and their respective Grundy domination problems. Our algorithm also implies an $\mathsf{FPT}$ algorithm for $\mathsf{Grundy~Domination}$ when parameterized by the number of vertices that are not in the dominating sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18104v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Scheffler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimates on the number of rational solutions of Markoff-Hurwitz equations over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $N$ denote the number of solutions to the generalized Markoff-Hurwitz-type equation \[(a_1X_1^m+\cdots + a_nX_n^m+a)^k=bX_1\cdots X_n \] over the finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$, where $m,k$ are positive integers, and $a,b,a_i\in \mathbb{F}_q^*$ for $i=1,\dots, n$, with $k,m\ge 2$ and $n\ge 3$. Using techniques from algebraic geometry, we provide an estimate for $N$ and establish conditions under which the equation admits solutions where all $X_i$ are nonzero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18191v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miriam Abdon, Daniela Alves de Oliveira, Juliane Capaverde, Mariana P\'erez, Melina Privitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploratory Notes on Symbolic Constraints in Polyhedral Enclosure and Tetrahedral Decomposition in Genus-0 Polyhedra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I present a coordinate-free, symbolic framework for deciding whether a given set of polygonal faces can form a closed, genus-zero polyhedral surface and for predicting how such a surface could be decomposed into internal tetrahedra. The method uses only discrete incidence variables, such as the number of internal tetrahedra $T$, internal gluing triangles $N_i$, and internal triangulation segments $S_i$, and applies combinatorial feasibility checks before any geometric embedding is attempted. For polyhedra in \emph{normal form}, I record exact incidence identities linking $V,E,F$ to a flatness parameter $S:=\sum_f(\deg f-3)$, and I identify parity-sensitive effects in $E$, $F$, and $S$. The external identities and parity-sensitive bounds hold universally for genus-0 polyhedral graphs. For internal quantities, I prove exact relations $N_i=2T-V+2$ and $T-N_i+S_i=1$ (with $S_i$ taken to be the number of interior edges) and obtain restricted linear ranges within a \emph{shell--aligned ladder} subclass (SALT), where at most one interior edge is introduced per layer. Consequently, I propose a symbolic workflow that yields rapid pre-checks for structural impossibility, reducing the need for costly geometric validation in computational geometry, graphics, and automated modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moustapha Itani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On some explicit integrals related to "fractal foothills"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.02741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.02741v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the previous papers, we tried to analyze the complete loop counting functions that count all the loops in an infinite random walk represented by digits of a real number. In this paper, the consideration will be restricted to the partial loop counting functions $V$ that count the returns to the origin only. This simplification allows us to find closed-form expressions for various integrals related to $V$. Some applications to the complete loop counting functions, in particular, their connections with Bernoulli polynomials, are also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.02741v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton A Kutsenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and growth of $\mathbb{R}$-bonacci words</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01213v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A binary word is called $q$-decreasing, for $q&gt;0$, if inside this word each of length-maximal (in the local sense) occurrences of a factor of the form $0^a1^b$, $a&gt;0$, satisfies $q \cdot a &gt; b$. We bijectively link $q$-decreasing words with certain prefixes of the cutting sequence of the line $y=qx$. We show that for any real positive $q$ the number of $q$-decreasing words of length $n$ grows as $C_q \cdot \Phi(q)^n$ for some constant $C_q$ which depends on $q$ but not on $n$. From previous works, it is already known that $\Phi(1)$ is the golden ratio, $\Phi(2)$ is equal to the tribonacci constant, $\Phi(k)$ is $(k+1)$-bonacci constant. We prove that the function $\Phi(q)$ is strictly increasing, discontinuous at every positive rational point, and exhibits a fractal structure related to the Stern-Brocot tree and Minkowski's question mark function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01213v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.37236/12705</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>S. Dovgal and S.Kirgizov, Structure and growth of $\mathbb{R}$-bonacci words, The Electronic Journal of Combinatorics, 32(3), Article P3.32, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Dovgal, Sergey Kirgizov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confluent Vandermonde matrix and related topics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01474v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we explore the connections between the confluent Vandermonde matrix over an arbitrary field and several mathematical topics, including interpolation polynomials, Hasse derivatives, LU factorization, companion matrices and their Jordan forms, and the partial fraction decomposition. Using a unified approach based on polynomial evaluations and derivative computations at selected points, we provide accessible proofs that not only clarify key results but also offer insights for both experienced researchers and those new to the subject.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01474v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi-Kwong Li, Jephian C. -H. Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect Matching in Product Graphs and in their Random Subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14020v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $t \in \mathbb{N}$ and every $i\in[t]$, let $H_i$ be a $d_i$-regular connected graph, with $1&lt;|V(H_i)|\le C$ for some integer $C\ge 2$. Let $G=\square_{i=1}^tH_i$ be the Cartesian product of $H_1, \ldots, H_t$. We show that if $t\ge 5C$ then $G$ contains a (nearly-)perfect matching.
  Then, considering the random graph process on $G$, we generalise the result of Bollob\'as on the binary hypercube $Q^t$, showing that with high probability, the hitting times for minimum degree one, connectivity, and the existence of a (nearly-)perfect matching in the random graph process on $G$ are the same. As a byproduct, we develop several tools which may be of independent interest in a more general setting when one seeks to establish the typical existence of a perfect matching under percolation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14020v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahar Diskin, Anna Geisler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tree independence number II. Three-path-configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00265v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A three-path-configuration is a graph consisting of three pairwise internally-disjoint paths the union of every two of which is an induced cycle of length at least four. A graph is 3PC-free if no induced subgraph of it is a three-path-configuration. We prove that 3PC-free graphs have poly-logarithmic tree-independence number. More explicitly, we show that there exists a constant $c$ such that every $n$-vertex 3PC-free graph graph has a tree decomposition in which every bag has stability number at most $c (\log n)^2$. This implies that the Maximum Weight Independent Set problem, as well as several other natural algorithmic problems, that are known to be NP-hard in general, can be solved in quasi-polynomial time if the input graph is 3PC-free.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00265v5</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Chudnovsky, Sepehr Hajebi, Daniel Lokshtanov, Sophie Spirkl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncrossing arithmetic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher-order notions of Kreweras complementation have appeared in the literature in the works of Krawczyk, Speicher, Mastnak, Nica, Arizmendi, Vargas, and others. While the theory has been developed primarily for specific applications in free probability, it also possesses an elegant, purely combinatorial core that is of independent interest. The present article aims at offering a simple account of various aspects of higher-order Kreweras complementation on the basis of elementary arithmetic, (co)algebraic, categorical and simplicial properties of noncrossing partitions. The main idea is to consider noncrossing partitions as providing an interesting noncommutative analogue of the interplay between the divisibility poset and the multiplicative monoid of positive integers. Just as the divisibility poset can be regarded as the decalage of the multiplicative monoid, we exhibit the lattice of noncrossing partitions as the decalage of a partial monoid structure on noncrossing partitions encoding higher-order Kreweras complements. While our results may be considered familiar, several of the viewpoints can be regarded as novel, offering an efficient approach both conceptually and computationally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17660v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kurusch Ebrahimi-Fard, Lo\"ic Foissy, Joachim Kock, Fr\'ed\'eric Patras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A closed formula for linear recurrences with constant coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a linear recurrence of the form $c_n=a_1c_{n-1}+\cdots+a_j c_{n-j}$, it is well-known that $c_n=\sum_{r}p_r(n)r^n$, where the sum is taken over the set of characteristic roots and each $p_r(n)$ is some polynomial. We give a closed formula for the coefficients of each polynomial $p_r(n)$ for any linear recurrence of this form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12660v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Glenn Bruda, Bruce Fang, Pico Gilman, Raul Marquez, Steven J. Miller, Beni Prapashtica, Daeyoung Son, Saad Waheed, Janine Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A characterization of unimodular hypergraphs with disjoint hyperedges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The incidence matrix of a graph is totally unimodular if and only if the graph is bipartite, i.e., it contains no odd cycles. We extend the characterization of total unimodularity to hypergraphs whose hyperedges of size at least four are pairwise disjoint, which we call disjoint hypergraphs. Disjoint hypergraphs have been used to model problems with fairness constraints that ensure balanced representation. We prove that total unimodularity for disjoint hypergraphs is equivalent to forbidding both odd cycles and structures that we call odd tree houses. Our result extends to disjoint mixed hypergraphs, whose incidence matrices have $\{0, \pm1\}$-entries. As a corollary, we resolve a special case of a conjecture on almost totally unimodular matrices, originally posed by Padberg and later modified by Cornu\'ejols and Zuluaga.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10593v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Caoduro, Meike Neuwohner, Joseph Paat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Murnaghan--Nakayama rules for symplectic, orthogonal and orthosymplectic Schur functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish new Murnaghan--Nakayama rules for symplectic, orthogonal and orthosymplectic Schur functions. The classical Murnaghan--Nakayama rule expresses the product of a power sum symmetric function with a Schur function as a linear combination of Schur functions. Symplectic and orthogonal Schur functions correspond to characters of irreducible representations of symplectic and orthogonal groups. Orthosymplectic Schur functions arise as characters of orthosymplectic Lie superalgebras and are hybrids of symplectic and ordinary Schur functions. We derive explicit formulas for the product of the relevant power-sum function with each of these functions, which can partly be described combinatorially using border strip manipulations. Our Murnaghan--Nakayama rules each include three distinct terms: a classical term corresponding to the addition of border strips to the relevant Young diagram, a term involving the removal of border strips, and a third term, which we describe both algebraically and combinatorially.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11447v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete Mathematics, Volume 349, Issue 2, February 2026, 114741</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nishu Kumari, Anna Stokke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite graphs with the double Hall property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The super-neighborhood of a vertex set $A$ in a graph $G$, denoted by $\Lambda^2(A)$, is the set of vertices adjacent to at least two vertices in $A$. We say that a bipartite graph $G=(X, Y)$ with $|X| \geq 2$ satisfies the double Hall property (with respect to $X$) if $|\Lambda^2(A)| \geq |A|$ for any subset $A \subseteq X$ with $|A| \geq 2$. Kostochka et al. first conjectured that if a bipartite graph $G=(X, Y)$ satisfies a slightly weaker version of the double Hall property, then $G$ contains a cycle that covers all vertices of $X$. They verified their conjecture for $|X| \leq 6$. In this paper, we extend their result to $|X| = 7$. Later, Salia conjectured that every bipartite graph satisfying the double Hall property has a cycle covering all vertices of $X$. We show that Salia's conjecture is almost equivalent to a much weaker conjecture requiring vertices in $Y$ to have high degrees. By extending a result of Bar\'at et al., we also show that Salia's conjecture holds for some graphs where the vertices of $Y$ have degree either $2$ or very high. Finally, we establish a lower bound for the maximum degree of graphs satisfying the double Hall property and present deterministic and probabilistic constructions of such graphs that approach this bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10903v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guantao Chen, Mikhail Lavrov, Yuying Ma, Yimo Su, Jennifer Vandenbussche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On posets and polytopes attached to arbors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Starting from the data of an arbor, which is a rooted tree with vertices decorated by disjoint sets, we introduce a lattice polytope and a partial order on its lattice points. We give recursive algorithms for various classical invariants of these polytopes and posets, using the tree structure. For linear arbors, we propose a conjecture exchanging the Ehrhart polynomial of the polytope with the Zeta polynomial of the poset for the reverse arbor. The general motivation comes from the action of a transmutation operator acting on M -triangles, which should link the posets considered here with some kinds of generalized noncrossing partitions and generalized associahedra. We give some evidence for this relationship in several cases, including notably some polytopes, namely halohedra and Hochschild polytopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04247v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fr\'ed\'eric Chapoton (IRMA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disperse Hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21052v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $\ell \geq 3$, an $\ell$-uniform hypergraph is disperse if the number of edges induced by any set of $\ell+1$ vertices is 0, 1, $\ell$ or $\ell+1$. We show that every disperse $\ell$-uniform hypergraph on $n$ vertices contains a clique or independent set of size $n^{\Omega_{\ell}(1)}$, answering a question of the first author and Tomon. To this end, we prove several structural properties of disperse hypergraphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21052v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lior Gishboliner, Ethan Honest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spanning tree spectrum: improved bounds and simple proofs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23648v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The number of spanning trees of a graph $G$, denoted $\tau(G)$, is a well studied graph parameter with numerous connections to other areas of mathematics. In a recent remarkable paper, answering a question of Sedl\'a\v{c}ek from 1969, Chan, Kontorovich and Pak showed that $\tau(G)$ takes at least $1.1103^n$ different values across simple (and planar) $n$-vertex graphs $G$, for large enough $n$. We give a very short, purely combinatorial proof that at least $1.55^n$ values are attained. We also prove that exponential growth can be achieved with regular graphs, determining the growth rate in another problem first raised by Sedl\'a\v{c}ek in the late 1960's. We further show that the following modular dual version of the result holds. For any integer $N$ and any $u &lt; N$ there exists a planar graph on $O(\log N)$ vertices whose number of spanning trees is $u$ modulo $N$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23648v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noga Alon, Matija Buci\'c, Lior Gishboliner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faithful universal graphs for minor-closed classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19582v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It was proved by Huynh, Mohar, \v{S}\'amal, Thomassen and Wood in 2021 that any countable graph containing every countable planar graph as a subgraph has an infinite clique minor. We prove a finite, quantitative version of this result: for fixed $t$, if a graph $G$ is $K_t$-minor-free and contains every $n$-vertex planar graph as a subgraph, then $G$ has $2^{\Omega(n)}$ vertices. On the other hand, we construct a polynomial size $K_4$-minor-free graph containing every $n$-vertex tree as an induced subgraph, and a polynomial size $K_7$-minor-free graph containing every $n$-vertex $K_4$-minor-free graph as induced subgraph. This answers several problems raised recently by Bergold, Ir\v{s}i\v{c}, Lauff, Orthaber, Scheucher and Wesolek.
  We study more generally the order of universal graphs for various classes (of graphs of bounded degree, treedepth, pathwidth, or treewidth), if the universal graphs retain some of the structure of the original class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19582v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Bastide, Louis Esperet, Carla Groenland, Claire Hilaire, Cl\'ement Rambaud, Alexandra Wesolek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonic normalized heat diffusion for distance-regular graphs with classical parameters of diameter $3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the monotonic normalized heat diffusion property on distance-regular graphs with classical parameters of diameter $3$. Regev and Shinkar found a Cayley graph for which this property fails. On the other hand, this property has been proved on abelian Cayley graphs, graphs with $3$ distinct eigenvalues and regular bipartite graphs with $4$ distinct eigenvalues by Price, Nica and Kubo-Namba, respectively. A distance regular graph with classical parameters of diameter $3$ has $4$ distinct eigenvalues and is not necessarily bipartite or vertex transitive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04314v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiping Liu, Heng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Domination Exponents for Pairs of Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12151v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding graph density profiles is notoriously challenging. Even for pairs of graphs, complete characterizations are known only in very limited cases, such as edges versus cliques. This paper explores a relaxation of the graph density profile problem by examining the homomorphism density domination exponent $C(H_1, H_2)$. This is the smallest real number $c \geq 0$ such that $t(H_1, T) \geq t(H_2, T)^c$ for all target graphs $T$ (if such a $c$ exists) where $t(H,T)$ is the homomorphism density from $H$ to $T$. We demonstrate that infinitely many families of graphs are required to realize $C(H_1, H_2)$ for all connected graphs $H_1$, $H_2$. We derive the homomorphism density domination exponent for a variety of graph pairs, including paths and cycles. As a couple of typical examples, we obtain exact values when $H_1$ is an even cycle and $H_2$ contains a Hamiltonian cycle, and provide asymptotically sharp bounds when both $H_1$ and $H_2$ are odd cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12151v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigoriy Blekherman, Annie Raymond, Alexander Razborov, Fan Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamilton cycles in regular graphs perturbed by a random 2-factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21756v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that for each $d \geq 2$, the union of a $d$-regular graph with a uniformly random $2$-factor on the same vertex set is Hamiltonian with high probability. This resolves a conjecture by Dragani\'c and Keevash for all values of $d$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21756v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Cicely (Cece),  Henderson, Sean Longbrake, Dingjia Mao, Patryk Morawski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binomial Transforms and the Binomial Convolution of Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04179v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given any two sequences of complex numbers, we establish simple relations between their binomial convolution and the binomial convolution of their individual binomial transforms. We employ these relations to derive new identities involving Fibonacci numbers, Bernoulli numbers, Catalan numbers, harmonic numbers, odd harmonic numbers, and binomial coefficients. In addition, we present several results which allow the construction of new binomial-transform pairs from existing ones. Many new relations concerning self-inverse sequences are also derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04179v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunle Adegoke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identically vanishing $k$-generalized Fibonacci polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11596v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recurrence for the $k$-generalized Fibonacci polynomials is usually iterated upwards to positive values of $n$ only. When the recurrence is iterated downwards to $n&lt;0$, there are indices where the polynomials vanish identically. This fact does not seem to have been noted in the literature. We derive the set of such indices. We present the left-justified generalized Pascal triangle for $n&lt;0$. For $k\ge3$ and $n&lt;0$, we show the degree of the polynomial does not increase monotonically with $|n|$. We derive expressions for the individual polynomial coefficients (the elementary symmetric polynomials of the roots). We present results for the properties of the polynomials, for both $n&gt;0$ and $n&lt;0$, including factorization of the polynomials and properties of the roots (including bounds on the amplitudes of the nonzero roots). Results are also derived for real roots. The nonzero roots have a $k$-fold rotational symmetry around the origin in the complex plane. We employ generating functions to derive combinatorial sums for the polynomials. (Separate treatments are required for $n&gt;0$ and $n&lt;0$.) This includes new sums which are more concise and computationally more efficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11596v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. R. Mane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Steiner systems $S(2,6,v)$ with block length 6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper various Steiner systems $S(2,k,v)$ for $k = 6$ are collected and enumerated for specific constructions. In particular, two earlier unknown types of $1$-rotational designs are found for the groups $SL(2,5)$ and $((\mathbb Z_3 \times \mathbb Z_3) \rtimes \mathbb Z_3) \times \mathbb Z_5$. Also new Steiner systems $S(2,6,96), S(2,6,106), S(2,6,111)$ are listed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16009v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Banakh, Ivan Hetman, Alex Ravsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cycle-factors of regular graphs via entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is a classical result that a random permutation of $n$ elements has, on average, about $\log n$ cycles. We generalise this fact to all directed $d$-regular graphs on $n$ vertices by showing that, on average, a random cycle-factor of such a graph has $\mathcal{O}((n\log d)/d)$ cycles. This is tight up to the constant factor and improves the best previous bound of the form $\mathcal{O}(n/\sqrt{\log d})$ due to Vishnoi. Our results also yield randomised polynomial-time algorithms for finding such a cycle-factor and for finding a tour of length $(1+\mathcal{O}((\log d)/d)) \cdot n$ if the graph is connected. This makes progress on a conjecture of Magnant and Martin and on a problem studied by Vishnoi and by Feige, Ravi, and Singh. Our proof uses the language of entropy to exploit the fact that the upper and lower bounds on the number of perfect matchings in regular bipartite graphs are extremely close.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19417v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha Christoph, Nemanja Dragani\'c, Ant\'onio Gir\~ao, Eoin Hurley, Lukas Michel, Alp M\"uyesser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partitioning set $[n] = \{1, \dots, n\}$ into subsets of size at most $m$ such that all sums are powers of $m$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00946v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given integer $n &gt; 0$ and $m &gt; 1$, we call a partition of set $[n] = \{1, \dots, n\}$ {\em $m$-good} if each of the partitioning sets is of size at most $m$ and the sum of numbers in it is a power of $m$, that is, $m^t$ for some $t \geq 0$. It is easily seen that a unique 2-good partition exists for each $n$ and, in contrast, for each fixed $m&gt;3$, for infinitely many $n$, no $m$-good partition exists.
  Case $m=3$ is more difficult. We conjecture that 3-good partitions exist for each $n$ and prove that a minimal counter-example, if any, is at least 101 and must belong to the set
  {\centering $N_o = \{n \equiv 2 \pmod 3\} \cap \{3^t+1 &lt; n &lt; (3^{t+1}+1)/2 \mid t \geq 4\}.$ }
  For this case we provide some partial results. We also show that a 3-good partition is unique if $n \in N_u = \{1, 2, 3, 4, 3^t-4, 3^t-2, 3^t-1, 3^t, 3^t+1, 3^t+2, 3^t+3 \mid t &gt; 1\}$ and conjecture that the inverse holds too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00946v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Gurvich, Mariya Naumova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On finiteness of spectral radius order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09947v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The concept of spectral radius order plays an crucial role in the breakthrough work on equiangular lines due to Jiang, Tidor, Yao, Zhang, and Zhao [Ann. of Math. (2) 194 (2021), no. 3, 729-743]. However, it is difficult to calculate the spectral radius order explicitly in general, or even to characterize numbers with finite spectral radius order. In this paper, we characterize numbers with finite spectral radius orders in two special classes: quadratic algebraic integers and the numbers no larger than 2. Additionally, we derive precise values of the spectral radius order of two infinite families of quadratic algebraic integers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09947v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanlong Ding, Chuanyuan Ge, Shiping Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A lower bound on the number of bent squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14605v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bent functions are Boolean functions that are maximally nonlinear. They can be represented as bent squares, i.e., square matrices for which each row and each column is the Walsh spectrum of a Boolean function. Using this representation, it is shown in this note that the number of bent functions in $n$ variables is at least $2^{n \cdot 2^{\frac{n}{2}} \left(1 + O\left(\frac{1}{n}\right)\right)}$ for even integers $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14605v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Kristian Haugland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization with pattern-avoiding input</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04236v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Permutation pattern-avoidance is a central concept of both enumerative and extremal combinatorics. In this paper we study the effect of permutation pattern-avoidance on the complexity of optimization problems.
  In the context of the dynamic optimality conjecture (Sleator, Tarjan, STOC 1983), Chalermsook, Goswami, Kozma, Mehlhorn, and Saranurak (FOCS 2015) conjectured that the amortized search cost of an optimal binary search tree (BST) is constant whenever the search sequence is pattern-avoiding. The best known bound to date is $2^{\alpha{(n)}(1+o(1))}$ recently obtained by Chalermsook, Pettie, and Yingchareonthawornchai (SODA 2024); here $n$ is the BST size and $\alpha(\cdot)$ the inverse-Ackermann function. In this paper we resolve the conjecture, showing a tight $O(1)$ bound. This indicates a barrier to dynamic optimality: any candidate online BST (e.g., splay trees or greedy trees) must match this optimum, but current analysis techniques only give superconstant bounds.
  More broadly, we argue that the easiness of pattern-avoiding input is a general phenomenon, not limited to BSTs or even to data structures. To illustrate this, we show that when the input avoids an arbitrary, fixed, a priori unknown pattern, one can efficiently compute a $k$-server solution of $n$ requests from a unit interval, with total cost $n^{O(1/\log k)}$, in contrast to the worst-case $\Theta(n/k)$ bound; and a traveling salesman tour of $n$ points from a unit box, of length $O(\log{n})$, in contrast to the worst-case $\Theta(\sqrt{n})$ bound; similar results hold for the euclidean minimum spanning tree, Steiner tree, and nearest-neighbor graphs.
  We show both results to be tight. Our techniques build on the Marcus-Tardos proof of the Stanley-Wilf conjecture, and on the recently emerging concept of twin-width.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04236v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Aram Berendsohn, L\'aszl\'o Kozma, Michal Opler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On integer distance sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10821v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a new approach to address some classical questions concerning the size and structure of integer distance sets. Our main result is that any integer distance set in the Euclidean plane is either very sparse or has all but an exceedingly small proportion of its points lying on a single line or circle. From this, we deduce a near-optimal lower bound on the diameter of any non-collinear integer distance set of size $n$ and a strong upper bound on the size of any integer distance set in $[-N,N]^2$ with no three points on a line and no four points on a circle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10821v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Greenfeld, Marina Iliopoulou, Sarah Peluse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B_{n-1}$-orbits on the flag variety and the Bruhat graph of the symmetric group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10122v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $G=G_{n}=GL(n)$ be the $n\times n$ complex general linear group and embed $G_{n-1}=GL(n-1)$ in the top left hand corner of $G$. The standard Borel subgroup of upper triangular matrices $B_{n-1}$ of $G_{n-1}$ acts on the flag variety of $G$ with finitely many orbits. In this paper, we show that each $B_{n-1}$-orbit is the intersection of orbits of two Borel subgroups of $G$ acting on the flag variety of $G$. This allows us to give a new combinatorial description of the $B_{n-1}$-orbits by associating to each orbit a pair of Weyl group elements. The closure relations for the $B_{n-1}$-orbits can then be understood in terms of the Bruhat order on the Weyl group, and the Richardson-Springer monoid action on the orbits can be understood in terms of the classical monoid action of the Weyl group on itself. This approach makes the closure relation more transparent than in earlier work of Magyar and the monoid action significantly more computable than in our earlier papers, and also allows us to obtain new information about the orbits including a simple formula for the dimension of an orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10122v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Colarusso, Sam Evens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified FPT Framework for Crossing Number Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00206v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The basic (and traditional) crossing number problem is to determine the minimum number of crossings in a topological drawing of an input graph in the plane. We develop a unified framework that smoothly captures many generalized crossing number problems, and that yields fixed-parameter tractable (FPT) algorithms for them not only in the plane but also on surfaces. Our framework takes the following form. We fix a surface S, an integer r, and a map \k{appa} from the set of topological drawings of graphs in S to Z+\cup{\infty}, satisfying some natural monotonicity conditions, but essentially describing the allowed drawings and how we want to count the crossings in them. Then deciding whether an input graph G has an allowed drawing D on S with \k{appa}(D)&lt;=r can be done in time quadratic in the size of G (and exponential in other parameters). More generally, we may take as input an edge-colored graph, and distinguish crossings by the colors of the involved edges; and we may allow to perform a bounded number of edge removals and vertex splits to G before drawing it. The proof is a reduction to the embeddability of a graph on a two-dimensional simplicial complex. This framework implies, in a unified way, quadratic FPT algorithms for many topological crossing number variants established in the graph drawing community. Some of these variants already had previously published FPT algorithms, mostly relying on Courcelle's metatheorem, but for many of those, we obtain an algorithm with a better runtime. Moreover, our framework extends, at no cost, to these crossing number variants in any fixed surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00206v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Eric Colin de Verdi\`ere, Petr Hlin\v{e}n\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some $q$-hypergeometric identities associated with partition theorems of Lebesgue, Schur and Capparelli</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04712v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Here, we establish a polynomial identity in three variables $a, b, c$, and with the degree of the polynomial given in terms of two integers $L, M$. By letting $L$ and $M$ tend to infinity, we get the 1993 Alladi-Gordon $q$-hypergeometric key-identity for the generalized Schur Theorem as well as the fundamental Lebesgue identity by two different choices of the variables. This polynomial identity provides a generalization and a unified approach to the Schur and Lebesgue theorems. We discuss other analytic identities for the Lebesgue and Schur theorems and also provide a key identity ($q$-hypergeometric) for Andrews' deep refinement of the Alladi-Schur theorem. Finally, we discuss a new infinite hierarchy of identities, the first three of which relate to the partition theorems of Euler, Lebesgue, and Capparelli, and provide their polynomial versions as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04712v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yazan Alamoudi, Krishnaswami Alladi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On an entropy inequality for quadratic forms and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15196v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce Frostman conditions for bivariate random variables and study discretized entropy sum-product phenomena in both independent and dependent regimes.
  In the independent setting, we show that for any non-degenerate rational quadratic form $\phi(x,y)$ and $0&lt;s&lt;1$, there exists some positive constant $\epsilon = \epsilon(\phi,s)$ such that any independent marginally $(s,C;s,C)$-Frostman random variable $(X,Y)$ satisfies
  $$\max\left\{H_n(X+Y),\,H_n(\phi(X,Y))\right\} \ge n(s+\epsilon)$$ for sufficiently large $n$. The proof introduces a novel multi-step entropy framework, combining the submodularity formula, the discretized entropy Balog-Szemer\'{e}di-Gowers theorem, and state-of-the-art results on the Falconer distance problem, to reduce general forms to a diagonal core case.
  In the dependent setting, we obtain analogous bounds for special polynomials. As an application, we derive that there exists $\epsilon=\epsilon(s)&gt;0$ such that, for any $\delta$-separated set $A\subset [0, 1]$ of cardinality $\delta^{-s}$ satisfying some non-concentration condition and any subset $G\subseteq A\times A$ with $|G|\geq \delta^\epsilon |A|^2$, the $\delta$-covering numbers satisfy $$ E_\delta(A+_GA) + E_\delta(\alpha \cdot A^{\wedge 2}+_G \beta\cdot A^{\wedge 2}) \gg_{\alpha,\beta,s} C^{-O_s(1)}\delta^{-\epsilon}|A|, $$ whenever $\delta$ is small enough.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15196v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Iosevich, Thang Pham, Nguyen Dac Quan, Steven Senger, Boqing Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On pairs of triangular numbers whose product is a perfect square and pairs of intervals of successive integers with equal sums of squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06598v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A number $N$ is a triangular number if it can be written as $N = t(t + 1)/2$ for some nonnegative integer number $t$. A triangular number $N$ is called square if it is a perfect square, that is, $N = d^2$ for some integer number $d$. Square triangular numbers were characterized by Euler in 1778 and are in one-to-one correspondence with the so-called near-isosceles Pythagorean triples $(k,k+1,l)$, where $k^2 + (k+1)^2 = l^2$. A quadratic number is the product $\Pi = \Pi(k,j) = k(k+1)(k+j)(k+j+1)$ for some nonnegative integer numbers $k$ and $j$. By definition, it is the product of two triangular numbers and 4. Quadratic number $\Pi$ and the corresponding pair $(k,j)$ are called square if $\Pi$ is a perfect square. Clearly, $(k,j)$ is square if both triangular numbers $k(k+1)/2$ and $(k+j)(k+j+1)/2$ are perfect squares. Yet, there exist infinitely many other square quadratic numbers. We construct polynomials $j_i(k)$ of degree $i$ with positive integer coefficients satisfying equations: $k + j_{2 \ell}(k) + 1 = k [a_\ell k^\ell + \dots + a_1 k + a_0]^2 +1 = (k+1) [b_\ell k^\ell + \dots + b_1 k + b_0]^2$ and \newline $k + j_{2\ell+1}(k) + 1 = k(k+1) [a_\ell k^\ell + \dots + a_1 k + a_0]^2 + 1 = [b_{\ell+1} k^{\ell+1}+b_\ell k^\ell + \dots + b_1 k + b_0]^2$ for some positive integer $\ell$ and some coefficients $a_i, b_j$, $i=0, \ldots, \ell, j=0, \ldots, \ell+1$. All the obtained pairs $(k, j_i(k))$ are square. We conjecture that the products of square triangular numbers and pairs $(k, j_i(k))$ cover all quadratic squares. Additionally, we identify pairs of intervals of successive integers with equal sums of squares.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06598v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Gurvich, Mariya Naumova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrence for pretentious systems along generalized Pythagorean triples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09778v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish multiple recurrence results for pretentious measure-preserving multiplicative actions along generalized Pythagorean triples, that is, solutions to the equation $ax^2 + b y^2 = c z^2$. This confirms the ergodic-theoretic form of the generalized Pythagorean partition regularity conjecture in this critical case of structured measure-preserving actions. As a consequence of our main theorem, any finite coloring of $\mathbb{N}$ generated by the level sets of finitely many pretentious completely multiplicative functions, must contain a monochromatic generalized Pythagorean triple.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09778v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Frantzikinakis, Andreas Mountakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
