<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Type C $K$-Stanley symmetric functions and Kra\'skiewicz-Hecke insertion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Type C $K$-Stanley symmetric functions, which are $K$-theoretic extensions of the Type C Stanley symmetric functions. They are indexed by signed permutations and can be used to enumerate reduced words via their expansion into Schur $Q$-functions, which are indexed by strict partitions. A combinatorial description of the Schur $Q$- coefficients is given by Kra\'skiewicz insertion. Similarly, their $K$-Stanley analogues are conjectured to expand positively into $GQ$'s, which are $K$-theory representatives for the Lagrangian Grassmannian introduced by Ikeda and Naruse also indexed by strict partitions. We introduce a $K$-theoretic analogue of Kra\'skiewicz insertion, which can be used to enumerate 0-Hecke expressions for signed permutations and gives a conjectural combinatorial rule for computing this $GQ$ expansion.
  We show the Type C $K$-Stanleys for certain fully commutative signed permutations are skew $GQ$'s. Combined with a Pfaffian formula of Anderson's, this allows us to prove Lewis and Marberg's conjecture that $GQ$'s of (skew) rectangle shape are $GQ$'s of trapezoid shape. Combined with our previous conjecture, this also gives an explicit combinatorial description of the skew $GQ$ expansion into $GQ$'s. As a consequence, we obtain a conjecture for the product of two $GQ$ functions where one has trapezoid shape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16641v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Arroyo, Zachary Hamaker, Graham Hawkes, Jianping Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Improved Upper Bound on the Threshold Bias of the Oriented-cycle game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the $b$-biased Oriented-cycle game where two players, OMaker and OBreaker, take turns directing the edges of $K_n$ (the complete graph on $n$ vertices). In each round, OMaker directs one previously undirected edge followed by OBreaker directing between one and $b$ previously undirected edges. The game ends once all edges have been directed, and OMaker wins if and only if the resulting tournament contains a directed cycle. Bollob\'as and Szab\'o asked the following question: what is the largest value of the bias $b$ for which OMaker has a winning strategy? Ben-Eliezer, Krivelevich and Sudakov proved that OMaker has a winning strategy for $b \leq n/2 - 2$. In the other direction, Clemens and Liebenau proved that OBreaker has a winning strategy for $b \geq 5n/6+2$. Inspired by their approach, we propose a significantly stronger strategy for OBreaker which we prove to be winning for $b \geq 0.7845n + O(1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16770v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anita Liebenau, Abdallah Saffidine, Jeffrey Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The graph zeta functions with respect to the group matrix of a finite group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present formulas for the edge zeta function and the second weighted zeta function with respect to the group matrix of a finite abelian group $\Gamma $. Furthermore, we give another proof of Dedekind Theorem for the group determinant of $\Gamma $ by the decomposition formula for a matrix of a group covering of a digraph. Finally, we treat the weighted complexity of the complete graph with entries of the group matrix of $\Gamma $ as arc weights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16821v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsuyoshi Miezaki, Iwao Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum saturated graphs without $4$-cycles and $5$-cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a family of graphs $\mathcal{F}$, a graph $G$ is said to be $\mathcal{F}$-saturated if $G$ does not contain a copy of $F$ as a subgraph for any $F\in\mathcal{F}$, but the addition of any edge $e\notin E(G)$ creates at least one copy of some $F\in\mathcal{F}$ within $G$. The minimum size of an $\mathcal{F}$-saturated graph on $n$ vertices is called the saturation number, denoted by $\mbox{sat}(n, \mathcal{F})$. Let $C_r$ be the cycle of length $r$. In this paper, we study on $\mbox{sat}(n, \mathcal{F})$ when $\mathcal{F}$ is a family of cycles. In particular, we determine that $\mbox{sat}(n, \{C_4,C_5\})=\lceil\frac{5n}{4}-\frac{3}{2}\rceil$ for any positive integer $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16839v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex Partitioning and $p$-Energy of Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a Hermitian matrix $A$ of order $n$ with eigenvalues $\lambda_1(A)\ge \cdots\ge \lambda_n(A)$, define \[ \mathcal{E}_p^+(A)=\sum_{\lambda_i &gt; 0} \lambda_i^p(A), \quad \mathcal{E}_p^-(A)=\sum_{\lambda_i&lt;0} |\lambda_i(A)|^p,\] to be the positive and the negative $p$-energy of $A$, respectively. In this note, first we show that if $A=[A_{ij}]_{i,j=1}^k$, where $A_{ii}$ are square matrices, then \[ \mathcal{E}_p^+(A)\geq \sum_{i=1}^{k} \mathcal{E}_p^+(A_{ii}), \quad \mathcal{E}_p^-(A)\geq \sum_{i=1}^{k} \mathcal{E}_p^-(A_{ii}),\] for any real number $p\geq 1$. We then apply the previous inequality to establish lower bounds for $p$-energy of the adjacency matrix of graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16882v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saieed Akbari, Hitesh Kumar, Bojan Mohar, Shivaramakrishna Pragada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separation Number and Treewidth, Revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a constructive proof of the fact that the treewidth of a graph $G$ is bounded by a linear function of the separation number of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17112v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hussein Houdrouge, Babak Miraftab, Pat Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on Mixed Cages of Girth 5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A mixed regular graph is a graph where every vertex has $z$ incoming arcs, $z$ outgoing arcs, and $r$ edges; furthermore, if it has girth $g$, we say that the graph is a \emph{$[z,r;g]$-mixed graph}. A \emph{$[z,r;g]$-mixed cage} is a $[z,r;g]$-mixed graph with the smallest possible order. In this note, we give a family of $[z,q;5]$-mixed graphs for $q\geq 7$ power of prime and $q-1\leq 4z+R$ with $z\geq 1$ and $R \in \{1,\ldots,5\}$. This provides better upper bounds on the order of mixed cages until this moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17152v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriela Araujo-Pardo, Lydia Mirabel Mendoza-Cadena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing simplex graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The simplex graph $S(G)$ of a graph $G$ is defined as the graph whose vertices are the cliques of $G$ (including the empty set), with two vertices being adjacent if, as cliques of $G$, they differ in exactly one vertex. Simplex graphs form a subclass of median graphs and include many well-known families of graphs, such as gear graphs, Fibonacci cubes and Lucas cubes.
  In this paper, we characterize simplex graphs from four different perspectives: the first focuses on a graph class associated with downwards-closed sets -- namely, the daisy cubes; the second identifies all forbidden partial cube-minors of simplex graphs; the third is from the perspective of the $\Theta$ equivalent classes; and the fourth explores the relationship between the maximum degree and the isometric dimension. Furthermore, very recently, Betre et al.\ [K. H. Betre, Y. X. Zhang, C. Edmond, Pure simplicial and clique complexes with a fixed number of facets, 2024, arXiv: 2411.12945v1] proved that an abstract simplicial complex (i.e., an independence system) of a finite set can be represented to a clique complex of a graph if and only if it satisfies the Weak Median Property. As a corollary, we rederive this result by using the graph-theoretical method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17160v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Ting Xie, Shou-Jun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On high discrepancy $1$-factorizations of complete graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17176v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We proved that for every sufficiently large $n$, the complete graph $K_{2n}$ with an arbitrary edge signing $\sigma: E(K_{2n}) \to \{-1, +1\}$ admits a high discrepancy $1$-factor decomposition. That is, there exists a universal constant $c &gt; 0$ such that every edge-signed $K_{2n}$ has a perfect matching decomposition $\{\psi_1, \ldots, \psi_{2n-1}\}$, where for each perfect matching $\psi_i$, the discrepancy $\lvert \frac{1}{n} \sum_{e\in E(\psi_i)} \sigma(e) \rvert$ is at least $c$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17176v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangdong Ai, Fankang He, Seonghyuk Im, Hyunwoo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hankel Determinants for Convolution of Power Series: An Extension of Cigler's Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cigler considered certain shifted Hankel determinants of convolution powers of Catalan numbers and conjectured identities for these determinants. Recently, Fulmek gave a bijective proof of Cigler's conjecture. Cigler then provided a computational proof. We extend Cigler's determinant identities to the convolution of general power series $F(x)$, where $F(x)$ satisfies a certain type of quadratic equation. As an application, we present the Hankel determinant identities of convolution powers of Motzkin numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17187v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feihu Liu, Ying Wang, Yingrui Zhang, Zihao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pullback parking functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a generalization of parking functions in which cars are limited in their movement backwards and forwards by two nonnegative integer parameters $k$ and $\ell$, respectively. In this setting, there are $n$ spots on a one-way street and $m$ cars attempting to park in those spots, and $1\leq m\leq n$. We let $\alpha=(a_1,a_2,\ldots,a_m)\in[n]^m$ denote the parking preferences for the cars, which enter the street sequentially. Car $i$ drives to their preference $a_i$ and parks there if the spot is available. Otherwise, car $i$ checks up to $k$ spots behind their preference, parking in the first available spot it encounters if any. If no spots are available, or the car reaches the start of the street, then the car returns to its preference and attempts to park in the first spot it encounters among spots $a_i+1,a_i+2,\ldots,a_i+\ell$. If car $i$ fails to park, then parking ceases. If all cars are able to park given the preferences in $\alpha$, then $\alpha$ is called a $(k,\ell)$-pullback $(m,n)$-parking function. Our main result establishes counts for these parking functions in two ways: counting them based on their final parking outcome (the order in which the cars park on the street), and via a recursive formula. Specializing $\ell=n-1$, our result gives a new formula for the number of $k$-Naples $(m,n)$-parking functions and further specializing $m=n$ recovers a formula for the number of $k$-Naples parking functions given by Christensen et al. The specialization of $k=\ell=1$, gives a formula for the number of vacillating $(m,n)$-parking functions, a generalization of vacillating parking functions studied by Fang et al., and the $m=n$ result answers a problem posed by the authors. We conclude with a few directions for further study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17256v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.63151/amjc.v4i.21</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>American Journal of Combinatorics Vol. 4 (2025) 1--22</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Elder, Pamela E. Harris, Lybitina Koene, Ilana Lavene, Lucy Martinez, Molly Oldham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On almost Gallai colourings in complete graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For $t \in \mathbb{N}$, we say that a colouring of $E(K_n)$ is $\textit{almost}$ $t$-$\textit{Gallai}$ if no two rainbow $t$-cliques share an edge. Motivated by a lemma of Berkowitz on bounding the modulus of the characteristic function of clique counts in random graphs, we study the maximum number $\tau_t(n)$ of rainbow $t$-cliques in an almost $t$-Gallai colouring of $E(K_n)$. For every $t \ge 4$, we show that $n^{2-o(1)} \leq \tau_t(n) = o(n^2)$. For $t=3$, surprisingly, the behaviour is substantially different. Our main result establishes that $$\left ( \frac{1}{2}-o(1) \right ) n\log n \le \tau_3(n) = O\big (n^{\sqrt{2}\log n} \big ),$$ which gives the first non-trivial improvements over the simple lower and upper bounds. Our proof combines various applications of the probabilistic method and a generalisation of the edge-isoperimetric inequality for the hypercube.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17334v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandr Grebennikov, Let\'icia Mattos, Tibor Szab\'o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality for catalytic equations and fully parked trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that critical parking trees conditioned to be fully parked converge in the scaling limits towards the Brownian growth-fragmentation tree, a self-similar Markov tree different from Aldous' Brownian tree recently introduced and studied by Bertoin, Curien and Riera. As a by-product of our study, we prove that positive non-linear polynomial equations involving a catalytic variable display a universal polynomial exponent $5/2$ at their singularity, confirming a conjecture by Chapuy, Schaeffer and Drmota &amp; Hainzl. Compared to previous analytical works on the subject, our approach is probabilistic and exploits an underlying random walk hidden in the random tree model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17348v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Contat, Nicolas Curien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumerating partial linear transformations in a similarity class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.06222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2005.06222v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $V$ be a finite-dimensional vector space over the finite field ${\mathbb F}_q$ and suppose $W$ and $\widetilde{W}$ are subspaces of $V$. Two linear transformations $T:W\to V$ and $\widetilde{T}:\widetilde{W}\to V$ are said to be similar if there exists a linear isomorphism $S:V\to V$ with $SW=\widetilde{W}$ such that $S\circ T=\widetilde{T}\circ S $. Given a linear map $T$ defined on a subspace $W$ of $V$, we give an explicit formula for the number of linear maps that are similar to $T$. Our results extend a theorem of Philip Hall that settles the case $W=V$ where the above problem is equivalent to counting the number of square matrices over ${\mathbb F}_q$ in a conjugacy class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2005.06222v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akansha Arora, Samrith Ram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the broken tetrahedron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Here we consider the hypergraph Tur\'an problem in uniformly dense hypergraphs as was suggested by Erd\H{o}s and S\'os. Given a $3$-graph $F$, the uniform Tur\'an density $\pi_u(F)$ of $F$ is defined as the supremum over all $d\in[0,1]$ for which there is an $F$-free uniformly $d$-dense $3$-graph, where uniformly $d$-dense means that every linearly sized subhypergraph has density at least $d$. Recently, Glebov, Kr\'al', and Volec and, independently, Reiher, R\"odl, and Schacht proved that $\pi_u(K_4^{(3)-})=\frac{1}{4}$, solving a conjecture by Erd\H{o}s and S\'os. Despite substantial attention, the uniform Tur\'an density is still only known for very few hypergraphs. In particular, the problem due to Erd\H{o}s and S\'os to determine $\pi_u(K_4^{(3)})$ remains wide open.
  In this work, we determine the uniform Tur\'an density of the $3$-graph on five vertices that is obtained from $K_4^{(3)-}$ by adding an additional vertex whose link forms a matching on the vertices of $K_4^{(3)-}$. Further, we point to two natural intermediate problems on the way to determining $\pi_u(K_4^{(3)})$, and solve the first of these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12747v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>August Y. Chen, Bjarne Sch\"ulke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On extended perfect codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10992v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider extended $1$-perfect codes in Hamming graphs $H(n,q)$. Such nontrivial codes are known only when $n=2^k$, $k\geq 1$, $q=2$, or $n=q+2$, $q=2^m$, $m\geq 1$. Recently, Bespalov proved nonexistence of extended $1$-perfect codes for $q=3$, $4$, $n&gt;q+2$. In this work, we characterize all positive integers $n$, $r$ and prime $p$, for which there exist such a code in $H(n,p^r)$. We also consider $2$-perfect codes in Hamming $H(n,q)$ and Johnson graphs $J(n,w)$ and find new necessary conditions on there existence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10992v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Vorob'ev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A star-comb lemma for infinite digraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The star-comb lemma is a standard tool in infinite graph theory, which states that for every infinite set $U$ of vertices in a connected graph $G$ there exists either a subdivided infinite star in $G$ with all leaves in $U$, or an infinite comb in $G$ with all teeth in $U$.
  In this paper, we elaborate a counterpart of the star-comb lemma for directed graphs. More precisely, we prove that for every infinite set $U$ of vertices in a strongly connected directed graph $D$, there exists a strongly connected butterfly minor of $D$ with infinitely many teeth in $U$ that is either shaped by a star or shaped by a comb, or is a chain of triangles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04877v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Reich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Normal Play of the Domination Game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13118v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 2010, Bre\v{s}ar, Klav\v{z}ar and Rall introduced the optimization variant of the graph domination game and the game domination number. In 2024, Leo Versteegen obtained the celebrated proof of the Conjecture $\frac{3}{5}$ on this variant of the domination game, proposed by Kinnersley, West and Zamani in 2013. In this paper, we investigate for the first time the normal play of the domination game, which we call \textsc{Normal Domination Game}, that is an impartial game where the last to play wins. We use the Sprague-Grundy theory to prove that Alice (the first player) wins in the path $P_n$ if and only if $n$ is not a multiple of $4$, and wins in the cycle $C_n$ if and only if $n=4k+3$ for some integer $k$. Finally, we obtain a polynomial time algorithm to decide the winner for any disjoint union of paths and cycles in the \textsc{Normal Domination Game} and its natural partizan variant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13118v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Marcos Brito, Nicolas Martins, Rudini Sampaio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integral Ricci Curvature for Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16465v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of integral Ricci curvature $I_{\kappa_0}$ for graphs, which measures the amount of Ricci curvature below a given threshold $\kappa_0$. We focus our attention on the Lin-Lu-Yau Ricci curvature. As applications, we prove a Bonnet-Myers-type diameter estimate, a Moore-type estimate on the number of vertices of a graph in terms of the maximum degree $d_M$ and diameter $D$, and a Lichnerowicz-type estimate for the first eigenvalue $\lambda_1$ of the Graph Laplacian, generalizing the results obtained by Lin, Lu, and Yau. All estimates are uniform, depending only on geometric parameters like $\kappa_0$, $I_{\kappa_0}$, $d_M$, or $D$, and do not require the graphs to be positively curved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16465v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Ramos Oliv\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star decompositions and independent sets in random regular graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09458v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A $k$-star decomposition of a graph is a partition of its edges into $k$-stars (i.e., $k$ edges with a common vertex). The paper studies the following problem: for what values of $k&gt;d/2$ does the random $d$-regular graph have a $k$-star decomposition (asymptotically almost surely, provided that the number of edges is divisible by $k$)?
  Delcourt, Greenhill, Isaev, Lidick\'y, and Postle proposed the following conjecture. It is easy to see that a $k$-star decomposition necessitates the existence of an independent set of density $1-d/(2k)$. So let $k^{\mathrm{ind}}_d$ be the largest $k$ for which the random $d$-regular graph a.a.s. contains an independent set of this density. Clearly, $k$-star decompositions cannot exist for $k&gt;k^{\mathrm{ind}}_d$. The conjecture suggests that this is essentially the only restriction: there is a threshold $k^\star_d$ such that $k$-star decompositions exist if and only if $k \leq k^\star_d$, and it (basically) coincides with the other threshold, i.e., $k^\star_d \approx k^{\mathrm{ind}}_d$.
  We confirm this conjecture for sufficiently large $d$ by showing that a $k$-star decomposition exists if $d/2&lt; k &lt; k^{\mathrm{ind}}_d$. In fact, we prove the existence even if $k=k^{\mathrm{ind}}_d$ for degrees $d$ with asymptotic density $1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09458v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Harangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex degree sums for rainbow matchings in 3-uniform hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14968v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $n \in 3\mathbb{Z}$ be sufficiently large. Zhang, Zhao and Lu proved that if $H$ is a 3-uniform hypergraph with $n$ vertices and no isolated vertices, and if $deg(u)+deg(v) &gt; \frac{2}{3}n^2 - \frac{8}{3}n + 2$ for any two vertices $u$ and $v$ that are contained in some edge of $H$, then $ H $ admits a perfect matching. In this paper, we prove that the rainbow version of Zhang, Zhao and Lu's result is asymptotically true. More specifically, let $\delta &gt; 0$ and $ F_1, F_2, \dots, F_{n/3} $ be 3-uniform hypergraphs on a common set of $n$ vertices. For each $ i \in [n/3] $, suppose that $F_i$ has no isolated vertices and $deg_{F_i}(u)+deg_{F_i}(v) &gt; \left( \frac{2}{3} + \delta \right)n^2$ holds for any two vertices $u$ and $v$ that are contained in some edge of $F_i$. Then $ \{ F_1, F_2, \dots, F_{n/3} \} $ admits a rainbow matching. Note that this result is asymptotically tight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14968v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haorui Liu, Mei Lu, Yan Wang, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomials with Lorentzian Signature, and Computing Permanents via Hyperbolic Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.02759v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the class of polynomials whose Hessians evaluated at any point of a closed convex cone have Lorentzian signature. This class is a generalization to the remarkable class of Lorentzian polynomials. We prove that hyperbolic polynomials and conic stable polynomials belong to this class, and the set of polynomials with Lorentzian signature is closed. Finally, we develop a method for computing permanents of nonsingular matrices which belong to a class that includes nonsingular $k$-locally singular matrices via hyperbolic programming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.02759v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Papri Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Watson-Crick conjugates of words and languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.03123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.03123v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the concept of Watson-Crick conjugates, also known as $\theta$-conjugates (where $\theta$ is an antimorphic involution), of words and languages. This concept extends the classical idea of conjugates by incorporating the Watson-Crick complementarity of DNA sequences. Our investigation initially focuses on the properties of $\theta$-conjugates of words. We then define $\theta$-conjugates of a language and study closure properties of certain families of languages under the $\theta$-conjugate operation. Furthermore, we analyze the iterated $\theta$-conjugate of both words and languages. Finally, we discuss the idea of $\theta$-conjugate-free languages and examine some decidability problems related to it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.03123v3</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kalpana Mahalingam, Anuran Maity</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorics of Castelnuovo-Mumford Regularity of Binomial Edge Ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09179v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Since the introduction of binomial edge ideals $J_{G}$ by Herzog et al. and independently Ohtani, there has been significant interest in relating algebraic invariants of the binomial edge ideal with combinatorial invariants of the underlying graph $G$. Here, we take up a question considered by Herzog and Rinaldo regarding Castelnuovo--Mumford regularity of block graphs. To this end, we introduce a new invariant $\nu(G)$ associated to any simple graph $G$, defined as the maximal total length of a certain collection of induced paths within $G$ subject to conditions on the induced subgraph. We prove that for any graph $G$, $\nu(G) \leq \text{reg}(J_{G})-1$, and that the length of a longest induced path of $G$ is less than or equal to $\nu(G)$; this refines an inequality of Matsuda and Murai. We then investigate the question: when is $\nu(G) = \text{reg}(J_{G})-1$? We prove that equality holds when $G$ is closed; this gives a new characterization of a result of Ene and Zarojanu, and when $G$ is bipartite and $J_{G}$ is Cohen-Macaulay; this gives a new characterization of a result of Jayanathan and Kumar. For a block graph $G$, we prove that $\nu(G)$ admits a combinatorial characterization independent of any auxiliary choices, and we prove that $\nu(G) = \text{reg}(J_{G})-1$. This gives $\text{reg}(J_{G})$ a combinatorial interpretation for block graphs, and thus answers the question of Herzog and Rinaldo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09179v3</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam LaClair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting Equilibria of the Electrostatic Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1873, James C. Maxwell conjectured that the electric field generated by $n$ point charges in generic position has at most $(n-1)^2$ isolated zeroes. The first (non-optimal) upper bound was only obtained in 2007 by Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro, who also posed two additional interesting conjectures.
  In this article, we give the best upper bound known to date on the number of zeroes of the electric field, and construct a counterexample to a conjecture of Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro that the number of equilibria cannot exceed those of the distance function defined by the unit point charges.
  Finally, we note that it is quite possible that Maxwell's quadratic upper bound is not tight, so it is prudent to find smaller bounds. Hence, we also explore examples and construct configurations of charges achieving the highest ratios of the number of electric field zeroes by point charges found to this day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05315v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herbert Edelsbrunner, Christopher Fillmore, Gon\c{c}alo Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transductions of Graph Classes Admitting Product Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18326v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In a quest to thoroughly understand the first-order transduction hierarchy of hereditary graph classes, some questions in particular stand out; such as, what properties hold for graph classes that are first-order transductions of planar graphs (and of similar classes)? When addressing this (so-far wide open) question, we turn to the concept of a product structure - being a subgraph of the strong product of a path and a graph of bounded tree-width, introduced by Dujmovic et al. [JACM 2020]. Namely, we prove that any graph class which is a first-order transduction of a class admitting such product structure, up to perturbations also meets a structural description generalizing the concept of a product structure in a dense hereditary way - the latter concept being introduced just recently by Hlineny and Jedelsky under the name of H-clique-width [MFCS 2024]. Using this characterization, we show that the class of the 3D grids, as well as a class of certain modifications of 2D grids, are not first-order transducible from classes admitting a product structure, and in particular not from the class of planar graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18326v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Hlin\v{e}n\'y, Jan Jedelsk\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the module of derivations of a line arrangement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01624v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To each multiple point $p$ in a line arrangement $\mathcal A$ in the complex projective plane we associate a derivation $\tilde D_p \in D_0( \mathcal A)$. We show first that these derivations span a large subspace of $D_0(\mathcal A)$. To each such derivation $\tilde D_p \in D_0(\mathcal A)$ we associate a polynomial $g_p$ which seems to play a key role in the characterization of the freeness of $\mathcal A$, as well as in the study of the position of the multiple points of $\mathcal A$ with respect to unions of lines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01624v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Dimca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Scarf complex of squarefree powers, symbolic powers of edge ideals, and cover ideals of graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13337v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Every monomial ideal $I$ has a Scarf complex, which is a subcomplex of its minimal free resolution. We say that $I$ is Scarf if its Scarf complex is also its minimal free resolution. In this paper, we fully characterize all pairs $(G,n)$ of a graph $G$ and an integer $n$ such that the squarefree power $I(G)^{[n]}$ or the symbolic power $I(G)^{(n)}$ of the edge ideal $I(G)$ is Scarf. We also determine all graphs $G$ such that its cover ideal $J(G)$ is Scarf, with an explicit description when $G$ is either chordal or bipartite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13337v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trung Chau, Nursel Erey, Aryaman Maithani</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
