<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 05:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the numbers of subforests and subgraph-degree-tuples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We enumerate the row-column-sums of all square tridiagonal $(0,1)$-matrices and prove that their count coincides with OEIS A022026 $-$ the number of acyclic subgraphs of the complete $2\times n$ grid graph. We then extend this correspondence in two independent directions: 1. admitting larger sets of matrix entries, and 2. relaxing the tridiagonal support to broader prescribed sparsity patterns. The latter leads us to conjecture that, for any bipartite graph $G$, the number of its acyclic subgraphs equals the number of degree sequences realized by subgraphs of $G$. Moreover, for any non-bipartite graph, the former should be strictly smaller than the latter. We discuss several general approaches and prove these hypotheses for cactus graphs and generalized book graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26936v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Shteiner, Pavel Shteyner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pattern Forcing (0,1)-Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce two related notions of pattern enforcement in $(0,1)$-matrices: $Q$-forcing and strongly $Q$-forcing, which formalize distinct ways a fixed pattern $Q$ must appear within a larger matrix. A matrix is $Q$-forcing if every submatrix can realize $Q$ after turning any number of $1$-entries into $0$-entries, and strongly $Q$-forcing if every $1$-entry belongs to a copy of $Q$.
  For $Q$-forcing matrices, we establish the existence and uniqueness of extremal constructions minimizing the number of $1$-entries, characterize them using Young diagrams and corner functions, and derive explicit formulas and monotonicity results. For strongly $Q$-forcing matrices, we show that the minimum possible number of $0$-entries of an $m\times n$ strongly $Q$-forcing matrix is always $O(m+n)$, determine the maximum possible number of $1$-entries of an $n\times n$ strongly $P$-forcing matrix for every $2\times2$ and $3\times3$ permutation matrix, and identify symmetry classes with identical extremal behavior.
  We further propose a conjectural formula for the maximum possible number of $1$-entries of an $n\times n$ strongly $I_k$-forcing matrix, supported by results for $k=2,3$. These findings reveal contrasting extremal structures between forcing and strongly forcing, extending the combinatorial understanding of pattern embedding in $(0,1)$-matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27076v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Cao, Shen-Fu Tsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labeled Chip-Firing on Star Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the stable configurations of the labeled chip-firing game on an infinitely subdivided $k$-star graph starting with $km$ chips on the center vertex. We prove a sorting property of this game and analyze special stable configurations corresponding to standard Young tableaux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27082v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annika Gonzalez-Zugasti, Ryan Lynch, Dylan Snustad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A decomposition formula for the Bartholdi zeta function of a hypergraph covering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown by Mizuno and Sato that the Bartholdi zeta function of a covering graph is decomposed as a product of Bartholdi zeta functions of a base graph that are associated with representations. In this paper, we extend their result to the case of a hypergraph covering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27134v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kosei Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rooted $C_5$-Minors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27161v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a graph and $x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_k$ be distinct vertices of $G$. We say $(G,x_1x_2\ldots x_k)$ has a $C_k$-minor or $G$ has a $C_k$-minor rooted at $x_1x_2\ldots x_k$, if there exist pairwise disjoint sets $X_1, X_2, \ldots, X_k\subseteq V(G)$, such that for all $i\in [k]$, $G[X_i]$ is connected, $x_i\in X_i$, and $G$ has an edge between $X_i$ and $X_{i+1}$, where $X_{k+1}=X_k$. When $k=3$ it is easy to determine when $(G,x_1x_2x_3)$ contains a $C_3$-minor. For $k=4$, Robertson, Seymour and Thomas gave a characterization of $(G,x_1x_2x_3x_4)$ with no $C_4$-minor, which, in particular, implies that such $G$ has connectivity at most 5. In this paper, we apply a method of Thomas and Wollan to prove a result, which implies that if $G$ is $10$-connected then, for all distinct vertices $x_1,x_2,x_3,x_4,x_5$ of $G$, $(G,x_1x_2x_3x_4x_5)$ has a $C_5$-minor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27161v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiying Du, Yanjia Li, Xingxing Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of a conjecture of Fomichev and Karev</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture of Fomichev and Karev [{European J. Combin.} 127 (2025) 104160] by showing the equality of two graph invariants: $\varphi$, defined via graph colorings, and $\psi$, derived from the $\mathfrak{sl}(2)$-weight system of its 2-dimensional irreducible representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27279v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Yan, Qingying Deng, Xian'an Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Borel Combinatorics of Schreier Graphs of $\mathbb{Z}$-actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the Borel combinatorics of Schreier graphs of $\mathbb{Z}$-actions with arbitrary finite generating sets. We formulate the Borel combinatorics in terms of existence of Borel equivariant maps from $F(2^{\mathbb{Z}})$ to subshifts of finite type. We then show that the Borel combinatorics and the continuous combinatorics coincide, and both are decidable. This is in contrast with the case of $\mathbb{Z}^2$-actions. We then turn to the problem of computing Borel chromatic numbers for such graphs. We give an algorithm for this problem which runs in exponential time. We then prove some bounds for the Borel chromatic numbers and give a formula for the case where the generating set has size 4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27290v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Su Gao, Yingying Jiang, Tianhao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropy and completeness indices of multilinear maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structures of multilinear maps are characterized by invariants. In this paper we introduce two invariants, named the isotropy index and the completeness index. These invariants capture the tensorial structure of the kernel of a multilinear map. We establish bounds on both indices in terms of the partition rank, geometric rank, analytic rank and height, and present three applications: 1) Using the completeness index as an interpolator, we establish upper bounds on the aforementioned tensor ranks in terms of the subrank. This settles an open problem raised by Kopparty, Moshkovitz and Zuiddam, and consequently answers a question of Derksen, Makam and Zuiddam. 2) We prove a Ramsey-type theorem for the two indices, generalizing a recent result of Qiao and confirming a conjecture of his. 3) By computing the completeness index, we obtain a polynomial-time probabilistic algorithm to estimate the height of a polynomial ideal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27387v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyuan Chen, Ke Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lucky Cars in Fubini Rankings and Unit Fubini Rankings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study lucky cars in subsets of parking functions, called Fubini rankings and unit Fubini rankings. A Fubini ranking is a sequence of nonnegative integers that encodes a valid ranking of competitors, where ties are allowed. A car (or competitor) is said to be lucky if it is the first instance of that rank appearing in the sequence. We present combinatorial characterizations and enumeration formulas for lucky cars in both Fubini rankings and unit Fubini rankings, and establish connections between these objects and ordered set partitions, as well as integer compositions. To obtain our results, we use several techniques to enumerate statistics over these families of objects.
  In particular, we employ generating functions, bijective and combinatorial arguments, recurrence relations, and Zeilberger's creative telescoping method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27574v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camilo Barreto, Melissa Beerbower, Jennifer Elder, Pamela E. Harris, Lucy Martinez, Jos\'e L. Ram\'irez, Samuel Ram\'irez, Grant Shirley, Julio C. V\'asquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lov\'asz-Kneser theorem for triangulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the Kneser graph of triangulations of a convex $n$-gon has chromatic number $n-2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27689v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Molnar, Cosmin Pohoata, Michael Zheng, Daniel G. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyTIE: A Python Program for the Evaluation of Degree-Based Topological Descriptors and Molecular Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have developed PyTIE (Python Topological Indices Expressions) which is defined as the collections of Python packages such as PyTIE D, PyTIE DS, PyTIE SMS DE, and PyTIE SMS DSE, which are open-source software packages and cross-platform Python package designed to expedite the retrieval of results for mathematics, chemistry and chemical engineering researchers within constant time. This open-source tool extends its utility to chemistry and chemical engineering researchers with limited mathematical proficiency. PyTIE facilitates the loading of molecular graphs, specifying parameters such as minimum degree, maximum degree, and the number of vertex pairs (edge partitions). The edge partitions of a molecular graph based on degree sum also plays a crucial role in predicting heat of formation and enthalpy of formation along with DFT techniques. It systematically computes expressions and numerical values for various topological indices, including degree-based and neighborhood degree-based indices, as well as Shannon's entropy, providing visual representations of the results. Emphasizing topological indices for Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship and Quantitative Structure-Property Relationship analyses, PyTIE proves particularly relevant in these studies. Serving as a Python package, it seamlessly integrates with libraries such as NumPy, math and SymPy offering extensive options for data analysis. The efficiency of PyTIE is demonstrated through illustrative examples in various contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26813v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahaya Vijay Jeyaraj, Roy S, Govardhan S, Tony Augustine, Jyothish K</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-algebraic Guessing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given finitely many consecutive terms of an infinite sequence, we discuss the construction of a polynomial difference equation that the sequence may satisfy. We also present a method to seek a candidate polynomial differential equation for its generating function. It appears that these methods often lead to effective D-algebraic operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26869v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bertrand Teguia Tabuguia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructive Characterization and Recognition Algorithm for Grafts with a Connected Minimum Join</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26975v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Minimum joins in a graft $(G, T)$, also known as minimum $T$-joins of a graph $G$, are said to be connected if they determine a connected subgraph of $G$. Grafts with a connected minimum join have gained interest ever since Middendorf and Pfeiffer showed that they satisfy Seymour's min-max formula for joins and $T$-cut packings; that is, in such grafts, the size of a minimum join is equal to the size of a maximum packing of $T$-cuts. In this paper, we provide a constructive characterization of grafts with a connected minimum join. We also obtain a polynomial time algorithm that decides whether a given graft has a connected minimum join and, if so, outputs one. Our algorithm has two bottlenecks; one is the time required to compute a minimum join of a graft, and the other is the time required to solve the single-source all-sink shortest path problem in a graph with conservative $\pm 1$-valued edge weights. Thus, our algorithm runs in $O(n(m + n\log n) )$ time. In the nondense case, it improves upon the time bound for this problem due to Seb\H{o} and Tannier that was introduced as an application of their results on metrics on graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26975v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nanano Kita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing matrix representations to fully heterochronous ranked tree shapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Phylogenetic tree shapes capture fundamental signatures of evolution. We consider ``ranked'' tree shapes, which are equipped with a total order on the internal nodes compatible the tree graph. Recent work has established an elegant bijection of ranked tree shapes and a class of integer matrices, called \textbf{F}-matrices, defined by simple inequalities. This formulation is for isochronous ranked tree shapes, where all leaves share the same sampling time, such as in the study of ancient human demography from present-day individuals. Another important style of phylogenetics concerns trees where the ``timing'' of events is by branch length rather than calendar time. This style of tree, called a rooted phylogram, is output by popular maximum-likelihood methods. These trees are broadly relevant, such as to study the affinity maturation of B cells in the immune system. Discretizing time in a rooted phylogram gives a fully heterochronous ranked tree shape, where leaves are part of the total order.
  Here we extend the \textbf{F}-matrix framework to such fully heterochronous ranked tree shapes. We establish an explicit bijection between a class of \textbf{F}-matrices and the space of such tree shapes. The matrix representation has the key feature that values at any entry are highly constrained via four previous entries, enabling straightforward enumeration of all valid tree shapes. We also use this framework to develop probabilistic models on ranked tree shapes. Our work extends understanding of combinatorial objects that have a rich history in the literature: isochronous ranked tree shapes are related to alternating permutations that Andr\'e studied over 130 years ago, and Poupard found (nearly 40 years ago) that fully heterochronous ranked tree shapes are counted by the reduced tangent numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27030v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Jennings-Shaffer, Cherith Chen, Julia A Palacios, Frederick A Matsen IV</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S\'ark\"ozy's theorem in $\mathbf{F}_2[x]$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Green showed that, conditional on GRH, a subset $A \subseteq [N]$ with $\mid A \mid \gg_{\epsilon} N^{\frac{11}{12}+\epsilon}$ must contain two elements whose difference is $p-1$ for $p$ a prime. We prove an analogous unconditional result for $\mathbf{F}_2[x]$, improving the exponent to $\frac{7}{8}+\epsilon$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27573v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Kowalska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ergodic averages for sparse corners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27627v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a framework for the study of the limiting behavior of multiple ergodic averages with commuting transformations when all iterates are given by the same sparse sequence; this enables us to partially resolve several longstanding problems. First, we address a special case of the joint intersectivity question of Bergelson, Leibman, and Lesigne by giving necessary and sufficient conditions under which the multidimensional polynomial Szemer\'edi theorem holds for length-three patterns. Second, we show that for two commuting transformations, the Furstenberg averages remain unchanged when the iterates are taken along sparse sequences such as $[n^c]$ for a positive noninteger $c$, advancing a conjecture of the first author. Lastly, we extend Chu's result on popular common differences in linear corners to polynomial and Hardy corners. Our toolbox includes recent degree lowering and seminorm smoothing techniques, the machinery of magic extensions of Host, and novel structured extensions motivated by works of Tao and Leng. Combined, these techniques reduce the analysis to settings where the Host-Kra theory of characteristic factors and equidistribution on nilmanifolds yield a family of striking identities from which our main results follow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27627v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Frantzikinakis, Borys Kuca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forbidden cycles in metrically homogeneous graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.05177</link>
      <description>arXiv:1808.05177v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a recent paper by a superset of the authors it was proved that for every primitive 3-constrained space $\Gamma$ of finite diameter $\delta$ from Cherlin's catalogue of metrically homogeneous graphs, there exists a finite family $\mathcal F$ of $\{1,\ldots, \delta\}$-edge-labelled cycles such that a $\{1,\ldots, \delta\}$-edge-labelled graph is a subgraph of $\Gamma$ if and only if it contains no homomorphic images of cycles from $\mathcal F$. However, the cycles in the families $\mathcal F$ were not described explicitly as it was not necessary for the analysis of Ramsey expansions and the extension property for partial automorphisms.
  This paper fills this gap by providing an explicit description of the cycles in the families $\mathcal F$, heavily using the previous result in the process. Additionally, we explore the potential applications of this result, such as interpreting the graphs as semigroup-valued metric spaces or homogenizations of $\omega$-categorical $\{1,\delta\}$-edge-labelled graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1808.05177v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ejc.2025.104262</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Journal of Combinatorics (132), 2026 European Journal of Combinatorics (132), 2026 European Journal of Combinatorics (132), 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hubi\v{c}ka, Michael Kompatscher, Mat\v{e}j Kone\v{c}n\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horospherical random graphs and lockdown strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.03535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.03535v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Expanders are sparse graph that are strongly connected, where {\it connectivity} is quantified using eigenvalues of the adjacency matrix, and {\it sparsity} in terms of vertex valency. We give a model of random graphs and study their connectivity and sparsity. This model is a particular case of soft geometric random graphs, and allows to construct sparse graphs with good expansion properties, as well as highly clustered ones. On those graphs, we study the speed at which random walks spread in the graph, and visit all vertices. As an illustration, we build a model for mainland France and study the spread of random walks under several types of lockdown. Our experiments show that completely closing medium and long distance travel to slow down the spread of a random walk is more efficient than than local restrictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.03535v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indira Chatterji, Austin Lawson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorization structures, cones, and polytopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07328v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Factorization structures occur in toric differential and discrete geometry, and can be viewed in multiple ways, e.g., as objects determining substantial classes of explicit toric Sasaki and K\"ahler geometries, as special coordinates on such, or as an apex generalisation of cyclic polytopes featuring a generalised Gale's evenness condition. This article presents a comprehensive study of factorization structures. It establishes their structure theory and introduces their use in the geometry of cones and polytopes. The article explains the construction of polytopes and cones compatible with a given factorization structure, and exemplifies it for product Segre-Veronese and Veronese factorization structures, where the latter case includes cyclic polytopes. Further, it derives the generalised Gale's evenness condition for compatible cones, polytopes and their duals, and explicitly describes faces of these. Factorization structures naturally provide generalised Vandermonde identities, which relate normals of any compatible polytope, and which are used for Veronese factorization structure to find examples of Delzant and rational Delzant compatible polytopes. The article offers a myriad of factorization structure examples, which are later characterised to be precisely factorization structures with decomposable curves, and raises the question if these encompass all factorization structures, i.e., the existence of an indecomposable factorization curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07328v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/prm.2025.10046</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Roland P\'u\v{c}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moderate Deviations of Triangle Counts in the Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi Random Graph $G(n,m)$: The Lower Tail</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $N_{\triangle}(G)$ be the number of triangles in a graph $G$. In [14] and [25] (respectively) the following bounds were proved on the lower tail behaviour of triangle counts in the dense Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi random graphs $G_m\sim G(n,m)$:
  \[ \mathbb{P}\big(N_{\triangle}(G_m) \, &lt; \, (1-\delta)\mathbb{E}[N_{\triangle}(G_m)]\big) \,=\,
  \exp\left(-\Theta\left(\delta^2n^3\right)\right) \qquad \text{if $n^{-3/2}\ll \delta\ll n^{-1}$} \] and \[
  \mathbb{P}\big(N_{\triangle}(G_m) \, &lt; \, (1-\delta)\mathbb{E}[N_{\triangle}(G_m)]\big) \,=\,
  \exp\left(-\Theta(\delta^{2/3}n^2) \right) \qquad \text{if $n^{-3/4} \ll \delta \ll 1$.}
  \]
  Neeman, Radin and Sadun [25] also conjectured that the probability should be of the form $\exp\left(-\Theta\left(\delta^2n^3\right)\right)$ in the "missing interval" $n^{-1}\ll \delta\ll n^{-3/4}$. We prove this conjecture.
  As part of our proof we also prove that some random graph statistics, related to degrees and codegrees, are normally distributed with high probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13792v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ejc.2025.104189</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European J. Combin. Volume 129, October 2025, 104189</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Alvarado, Gabriel Dias, Simon Griffiths</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the Bierbrauer-Friedman bound for orthogonal arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16559v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We characterize mixed-level orthogonal arrays in terms of algebraic designs in a special multigraph. We prove a mixed-level analog of the Bierbrauer-Friedman (BF) bound for pure-level orthogonal arrays and show that arrays attaining it are radius-1 completely regular codes (equivalently, intriguing sets, equitable 2-partitions, perfect 2-colorings) in the corresponding multigraph. For the case when the numbers of levels are powers of the same prime number, we characterize, in terms of multispreads, additive mixed-level orthogonal arrays attaining the BF bound. For pure-level orthogonal arrays, we consider versions of the BF bound obtained by replacing the Hamming graph by its polynomial generalization and show that in some cases this gives a new bound.
  Keywords: orthogonal array, algebraic t-design, completely regular code, equitable partition, intriguing set, Hamming graph, Bierbrauer-Friedman bound, additive codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16559v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10623-025-01711-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Des. Codes Cryptogr. 93(11) 2025, 4937-4950</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Denis S. Krotov, Ferruh \"Ozbudak, Vladimir N. Potapov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twenty years of Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il's classification programme of Ramsey classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17293v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the 1970s, structural Ramsey theory emerged as a new branch of combinatorics. This development came with the isolation of the concepts of the $\mathbf{A}$-Ramsey property and Ramsey class. Following the influential Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il-R\"odl theorem, several Ramsey classes have been identified. In the 1980s, Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il, inspired by a seminar of Lachlan, discovered a crucial connection between Ramsey classes and Fra\"iss\'e classes, and, in his 1989 paper, connected the classification programme of homogeneous structures to structural Ramsey theory. In 2005, Kechris, Pestov, and Todor\v{c}evi\'c revitalized the field by connecting Ramsey classes to topological dynamics. This breakthrough motivated Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il to propose a program for classifying Ramsey classes. We review the progress made on this program in the past two decades, list open problems, and discuss recent extensions to new areas, namely the extension property for partial automorphisms (EPPA), and big Ramsey structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17293v5</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cosrev.2025.100814</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computer Science Review 59 (2026), 100814</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hubi\v{c}ka, Mat\v{e}j Kone\v{c}n\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Indices With Degree Sequence $\mathscr{D}$ of Tree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12909v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we refer to a asymptotic degree sequence as $\mathscr{D}=(d_1,d_2,\dots,d_n)$. The examination of topological indices on trees gives us a general overview through bounds to find the maximum and minimum bounds which reflect the maximum and minimum number of edges incident to every vertex in the graph, Albertson index known as $\sum_{uv\in E(G)}\lvert d_u(G)-d_v(G) \rvert$, Sigma index $\sigma(G)$ among $\mathscr{D}$ of tree $T$ when $d_n\geqslant \dots \geqslant d_1$. According to the first zegrb we show for a degree sequence of order $n=4$, $\operatorname{irr}(T)=M_1(T)^2-2\sqrt{M_1(T)}+\sum_{i=1}^4\left|x_i-x_{i+1}\right|-(b+c)-1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12909v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasem Hamoud, Duaa Abdullah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationships between minimum rank problem parameters for cobipartite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02977v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a simple graph, the minimum rank problem is to determine the smallest rank among the symmetric matrices whose off-diagonal nonzero entries occur in positions corresponding to the edges of the graph. Bounds on this minimum rank (and on an equivalent value, the maximum nullity) are given by various graph parameters, most notably the zero forcing number and its variants. For a matrix, replacing each nonzero entry with the symbol \(\ast\) gives its zero-nonzero pattern. The associated minimum rank problem is to determine, given only this pattern, the smallest possible rank of the matrix. The most fundamental lower bound on this minimum rank is the triangle number of the pattern. A cobipartite graph is the complement of a bipartite graph; its vertices can be partitioned into two cliques. Such a graph corresponds to a zero-nonzero pattern in a natural way. Over an infinite field, the minimum rank of the graph and that of the pattern obey a simple relationship. We show that this same relationship is followed by the zero forcing number of the graph and the triangle number of the pattern. This has implications for the relationship between the two minimum rank problems. We also explore how, for cobipartite graphs, variants of the zero forcing number and other parameters important to the minimum rank problem are related, as well as how, for graphs in general, these parameters can be interpreted in terms of the zero-nonzero patterns of the symmetric matrices associated with the graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02977v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Deaett, Derek Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Finite Sumsets and Product Sets in Subsets of the Natural Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01301v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the occurrence of additive and multiplicative structures in random subsets of the natural numbers. Specifically, for a Bernoulli random subset of $\mathbb{N}$ where each integer is included independently with probability $p\in (0,1)$, we prove that almost surely such a set contains finite sumsets (FS-sets) and finite product sets (FP-sets) of every finite length. In addition, we establish a novel connection between Hindman's partition theorem and the central limit theorem, providing a probabilistic perspective on the asymptotic Gaussian behavior of monochromatic finite sums and products. These results can be interpreted as probabilistic analogues of finite-dimensional versions of Hindman's theorem. Applications, implications, and open questions related to infinite FS-sets and FP-sets are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01301v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sukrit Chakraborty, Sayan Goswami, Sourav Kanti Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Intersection Distribution: New Results and Perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04675v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Intersection distribution and non-hitting index are concepts introduced recently by Li and Pott as a new way to view the behaviour of a collection of finite field polynomials. With both an algebraic interpretation via the intersection of a polynomial with a set of lines, and a geometric interpretation via a $(q+1)$-set possessing an internal nucleus, the concepts have proved their usefulness as a new way to view various long-standing problems, and have applications in areas such as Kakeya sets. In this paper, by exploiting connections with diverse areas including the theory of algebraic curves, cyclotomy and the enumeration of irreducible polynomials, we establish new results and resolve various Open Problems of Li and Pott. We prove geometric results which shed new light on the relationship between intersection distribution and projective equivalence of polynomials, and algebraic results which describe and characterise the degree of $S_f$ - the index of the largest non-zero entry in the intersection distribution of $f$. We provide new insights into the non-hitting spectrum, and show the limitations of the non-hitting index as a tool for characterisation. Finally, the benefits provided by the connections to other areas are evidenced in two short new proofs of the cubic case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04675v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophie Huczynska, Lukas Klawuhn, Maura B. Paterson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divergent Infinite Series -- Ramanujan's Initial Intuition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08652v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates Srinivasa Ramanujan's initial intuitive methodology for assigning the finite value -1/12 to the sum of the divergent infinite series of all positive integers. We systematically examine Ramanujan's initial method, originally sketched in his notebooks, and set the methodology into an algebraic framework. The methodology has limited applicability to other classes of divergent series. The methodology is extended to assign a Ramanujan smoothed sum to the infinite sequences of integers raised to a positive integer power and to figurate binomial number sequences, including triangular numbers, tetrahedral numbers, and higher-dimensional analogues, avoiding analytical continuation. A key finding establishes that the Ramanujan smoothed sums of figurate binomial sequences are intrinsically connected to logarithmic numbers (Gregory coefficients), providing a novel perspective on Ramanujan summation through the lens of classical combinatorial functions. The paper applies asymptotic expansions of associated rational generating functions to demonstrate consistency with established results from analytic continuation methods. The results illuminate the deeper mathematical structures underlying Ramanujan's intuitive insights and suggest new avenues for research in divergent series summation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08652v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario M. Attard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cliques in hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14804v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that for any $k \ge 3$, every $k$-uniform hypergraph on $n$ vertices contains at most $n - \omega(1)$ different sizes of cliques (maximal complete subgraphs). In particular, the 3-uniform case answers a question of Erd\H{o}s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14804v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An extension of Viennot's shadow to rook placements via orbit harmonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23735v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For fixed positive integers $n,m,r$, let $\mathrm{Mat}_{n \times m}(\mathbb{C})$ be the affine space of $n \times m$ complex matrices with coordinate ring $\mathbb{C}[\mathbf{x}_{n \times m}]$. We define a homogeneous ideal $I_{n,m,r}$, where the graded quotient $\mathbb{C}[\mathbf{x}_{n \times m}]/I_{n,m,r}$ is obtained from the orbit harmonics deformation of the matrix loci corresponding to all rook placements of size at least $r$. By extending rook placements to elements in $\mathfrak{S}_{n+m-r}$ and applying Viennot's shadow line avatar of the Schensted correspondence, we compute the standard monomial basis of the quotient $\mathbb{C}[\mathbf{x}_{n \times m}]/I_{n,m,r}$ with respect to diagonal monomial orders. We also determine the graded $\mathfrak{S}_n\times\mathfrak{S}_m$-module structure of $\mathbb{C}[\mathbf{x}_{n \times m}]/I_{n,m,r}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23735v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jasper M. Liu, Hai Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elekes-Szab\'o for collinearity on cubic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.14059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.14059v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the orchard problem on cubic surfaces. We classify possibly reducible cubic surfaces $X\subseteq \mathbb{P}^3(\C)$ with smooth components on which there exist families of finite sets (of unbounded size) with quadratically many 3-rich lines which do not concentrate (in a natural sense) on any projective plane. Namely, we prove that such a family exists precisely when $X$ is a union of three planes sharing a common line.
  Along the way, we obtain a general result about nilpotency of groups admitting an algebraic action satisfying an Elekes-Szab\'o condition, and we prove the following purely algebrogeometric statement: if the composition of four Geiser involutions through sufficiently generic points $a,b,c,d$ on a smooth irreducible cubic surface has infinitely many fixed points, then a single plane contains $a,b,c,d$ and all but finitely many of the fixed points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.14059v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bays, Jan Dobrowolski, Tingxiang Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The barrier Ramsey theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02544v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study a very general finite Ramsey theorem, where both the sets being colored and the homogeneous set must satisfy some largeness notion. For the homogeneous set this has already been done using the notion of $\alpha$-largeness, where $\alpha$ is a countable ordinal equipped with a system of fundamental sequences. To extend this approach the more appropriate notion is barrier largeness. Since the complexity of barriers can be measured by countable ordinals, we define Ramsey ordinals and, using appropriate iterations of the Veblen functions, we are able to compute them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02544v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Marcone, Antonio Montalb\'an, Andrea Volpi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum $K$-theoretic divisor axiom for flag manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove an identity for (torus-equivariant) 3-point, genus 0, $K$-theoretic Gromov-Witten invariants of flag manifolds $G/P$, which can be thought of as a replacement for the ``divisor axiom'' in their (torus-equivariant) quantum $K$-theory. This identity enables us to compute these invariants when two insertions are Schubert classes and the other a Schubert divisor class. Our type-independent proof utilizes the Chevalley formula for the (torus-equivariant) quantum $K$-theory ring of flag manifolds, which computes multiplications by Schubert divisor classes in terms of the quantum Bruhat graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16150v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Lenart, Satoshi Naito, Daisuke Sagaki, Leonardo C. Mihalcea, Weihong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite $N$ precursors of the free cumulants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21483v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study $\mathrm{U}(N)$ invariant polynomials on the space of $N\times N$ matrices first introduced by Capitaine and Casalis, that are precursors of free cumulants in various respects. First, they are polynomials of deterministic matrices, that are not yet evaluated over some probability law, contrary to what is usually meant by cumulants. Secondly, they converge towards the algebraic expression of free cumulants in terms of moments as $N\to \infty$, with $1/N^2$ corrections expressed in terms of monotone Hurwitz numbers. Their most crucial property is their additivity with respect to averaging over sums of $\mathrm{U}(N)$ conjugacy orbits, providing a finite $N$ version of the well-known additivity of free cumulants in free probability. Finally, they extend several properties of free cumulants at finite $N$, including a Wick rule for their average over a Gaussian weight and their appearance in various matrix integrals. Building on the additivity property of these precursors, we also define and compute a coproduct describing the behaviour of general invariant polynomials with respect to the addition of $\mathrm{U}(N)$ conjugacy orbits, as well as their expectation values on sums of $\mathrm{U}(N)$-invariant random matrices. In our construction, a central role is played by the so-called HCIZ integral, both for the definition of the precursors and for the derivation of their properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21483v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sylvain Lacroix, Jean-Bernard Zuber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
