<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO</link>
    <description>math.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 04:03:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hamilton Cycles In Vertex-Transitive Graphs of Order 10p</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After a long term efforts, the Hamiltonian problem of connected vertex-transitive graphs of order $pq$ (where $p$ and $q$ are primes) was finally finshed in 2021, see [10]. Fifteen years ago, mathematicians began to challenge this problem for graphs of order $2pq$. Among of them, it was proved in 2012 (see [21]) that every connected vertex-transitive graph of order $10p$ (where $p\neq7$ is a prime) contains a Hamilton path, with the exception of a family of graphs which was recently confirmed in [11]. In this paper, a further conclusion will be achieved: every connected vertex-transitive graph of order $10p$ (where $p$ is a prime) contains a Hamilton cycle, except for the truncation of the Petersen graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19888v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huye Chen, Jingjian Li, Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New upper bounds on the order of mixed cages of girth 6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20003v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A $[z,r;g]$-mixed cage is a mixed graph of minimum order such that each vertex has $z$ in-arcs, $z$ out-arcs, $r$ edges, and it has girth $g$, and the minimum order for $[z,r;g]$-mixed graphs is denoted by $n[z,r;g]$. In this paper, we present an infinite family of mixed graphs with girth $6$, that improves, in some cases, the families that we give in G. Araujo-Pardo and L. Mendoza-Cadena. \textit{On Mixed Cages of girth 6}, arXiv:2401.14768v2. In particular, if $q$ is an even prime power we construct a family of graphs that satisfies $n[\frac{q}{4},q;6]\leq 4q^2-4$, and if $q$ is an odd prime power, and $\frac{q-3}{2}$ is odd then our family satisfies that $n[\frac{q-1}{4},q;6]\leq 4q^2-4$, otherwise $n[\frac{q-3}{4},q;6]\leq 4q^2-4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20003v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriela Araujo-Pardo, Lydia Mirabel Mendoza-Cadena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster structures in mixed Grassmanianns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20038v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generalizing the results by Fomin-Pylyavskyy and Carde, we construct a family of natural cluster structures in the coordinate ring of a mixed Grassmannian, the configuration space of tuples of several vectors and covectors in a finite-dimensional complex vector space. We describe and explore these cluster structures using the machinery of weaves introduced by Casals and Zaslow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20038v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zenan Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of possibilities for random dating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a regular graph and $H$ a subgraph on the same vertex set. We give surprisingly compact formulas for the number of copies of $H$ one expects to find in a random subgraph of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20072v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Combinatorial Theory, Series A, vol. 115 (2008), pp. 1265-1271</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Abrams, Rod Canfield, Andrew Granville</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minors of non-hamiltonian polyhedra and the Herschel family</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that every non-hamiltonian polyhedron contains the Herschel graph as a minor. As an application, we provide a characterization of non-hamiltonian polyhedra without $K_{2,6}$ minors, thereby resolving a conjecture by Ellingham, Marshall, Ozeki, Royle, and Tsuchiya.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20086v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>On-Hei Solomon Lo, Kenta Ozeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On minors of non-hamiltonian graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A theorem of Tutte states that every 4-connected non-hamiltonian graph contains $K_{3,3}$ as a minor. We strengthen this result by proving that such a graph must contain $K_{3,4}$ as a minor, thereby confirming a special case of a conjecture posed by Chen, Yu, and Zang in a strong form. This result may be viewed as a step toward characterizing the minor-minimal 4-connected non-hamiltonian graphs. As a 3-connected analog, Ding and Marshall conjectured that every 3-connected non-hamiltonian graph has a minor of $K_{3,4}$, $\mathfrak{Q}^+$, or the Herschel graph, where $\mathfrak{Q}^+$ is obtained from the cube by adding a new vertex adjacent to three independent vertices. We confirm this conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20087v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>On-Hei Solomon Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalization of Deodhar's defect statistic for Iwahori--Hecke algebras of type $BC$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $H$ be the Iwahori--Hecke algebra corresponding to any Coxeter group. Deodhar's defect statistic [Geom. Dedicata 36, (1990) pp.95--119] allows one to expand products of simple Kazhdan--Lusztig basis elements of $H$ in the natural basis of $H$. Clearwater and the third author gave a type-$A$ extension [Ann. Comb. 25, no. 3 (2021) pp.757--787] of this formula which combinatorially describes the natural expansion of products of Kazhdan--Lusztig basis elements indexed by smooth elements of the symmetric group. We similarly give a type-$BC$ extension of Deodhar's result which combinatorially describes the natural expansion of Kazhdan--Lusztig basis elements indexed by hyperoctahedral group elements which are simultaneously smooth in types $B$ and $C$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20099v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gavin Hobbs, Tommy Parisi, Mark Skandera, Jiayuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the homogeneity problem of the Kazhdan-Lusztig ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20153v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we identify some sufficient conditions for a Kazhdan-Lusztig ideal to be inhomogeneous. Also, we attempt to approach the problem of giving some necessary and sufficient conditions for a Kazhdan-Lusztig ideal to be "standard homogeneous".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20153v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adhip Ganguly, Shyamashree Upadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjacency spectral radius and H-factors in 1-binding graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a graph, and let $H:V(G)\longrightarrow\{\{1\},\{0,2\}\}$ be a set-valued function. Hence, $H(v)$ equals $\{1\}$ or $\{0,2\}$ for any $v\in V(G)$. We let $$ H^{-1}(1)=\{v: v\in V(G) \ \mbox{and} \ H(v)=1\}. $$ An $H$-factor of $G$ is a spanning subgraph $F$ of $G$ such that $d_F(v)\in H(v)$ for each $v\in V(G)$. Lu and Kano showed a characterization for the existence of an $H$-factor in a graph [Characterization of 1-tough graphs using factors, Discrete Math. 343 (2020) 111901]. Let $A(G)$ and $\rho(G)$ denote the adjacency matrix and the adjacency spectral radius of $G$, respectively. By using Lu and Kano's result, we pose a sufficient condition with respect to the adjacency spectral radius to guarantee the existence of an $H$-factor in a 1-binding graph. In this paper, we prove that if a connected 1-binding graph $G$ of order $n\geq11$ satisfies $\rho(G)\geq\rho(K_1\vee(K_{n-4}\cup K_2\cup K_1))$, then $G$ has an $H$-factor for each $H:V(G)\longrightarrow\{\{1\},\{0,2\}\}$ with $H^{-1}(1)$ even, unless $G=K_1\vee(K_{n-4}\cup K_2\cup K_1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20273v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sizhong Zhou, Tao Zhang, Zhiren Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Base, Normal and Near-normal Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The base sequences BS(n+1,n) are four sequences of $\pm1$ and lengths n+1,n+1,n,n with zero auto correlation. The base sequence conjecture states that BS(n+1,n) exists for all integers $n&gt;0$ and has been verified for $n\le40$. We present our algorithm and gives construction of BS(n+1,n) for $n=41,42,43$.
  The Normal sequences NS (n) and the Near-normal sequences NNS (n) are subclasses of BS(n+1,n). Yang conjecture asserts that there is a NNS(n) for each even integer n and has been verified for $n\le40$. We found that there is no NNS(n) for n=42 and 44 by exhaustive search, which gives the first counter case of Yang conjecture. We also show that there is no NS(n) for n=41,42,43,44,45 by exhaustive search and proves that no NS(n) exist for $n=8k-2,k \in Z_+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20296v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Wang, Jiayi Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumeration of subsets with closedness in finite fields of characteristic 2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The additive closedness in the subset of an additive group is termed as r-value. The nature of closedness in different subsets of fixed size is observed as a spectrum of r-values. We enumerate r-values of subsets in finite fields of characteristic 2 and represent them as the spectrum of values. Based on these values the subsets can be further studied as partial Steiner triple systems, sum-free sets, Sidon sets, and Schure triples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20351v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nithish Kumar R, Vadiraja Bhatta G. R., Prasanna Poojary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Rigidity and Spectral Embeddings of Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the structure of conformally rigid graphs. Graphs are conformally rigid if introducing edge weights cannot increase (decrease) the second (last) eigenvalue of the Graph Laplacian. Edge-transitive graphs and distance-regular graphs are known to be conformally rigid. We establish new results using the connection between conformal rigidity and edge-isometric spectral embeddings of the graph. All $1$-walk regular graphs are conformally rigid, a consequence of a stronger property of their embeddings. Using symmetries of the graph, we establish two related characterizations of when a vertex-transitive graph is conformally rigid. This provides a necessary and sufficient condition for a Cayley graph on an abelian group to be conformally rigid. As an application we exhibit an infinite family of conformally rigid circulants. Our symmetry technique can be interpreted in the language of semidefinite programming which provides another criterion for conformal rigidity in terms of edge orbits. The paper also describes a number of explicit conformally rigid graphs whose conformal rigidity is not yet explained by the existing theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20541v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Gouveia, Stefan Steinerberger, Rekha R. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Erd\H{o}s-Ko-Rado problem of flags with type $\{1, n-3 \}$ of finite sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A flag of a finite set $S$ is a set $f$ of non-empty, proper subsets of $S$, such that $X\subseteq Y$ or $Y\subseteq X$ for all $X,Y\in f$. Two flags $f_1$ and $f_2$ of $S$ are opposite if $X_1\cap X_2=\emptyset$, or $X_1\cup X_2=S$ for all $X_1\in f_1$ and $X_2\in f_2$. The set $\{|X| \mid X\in f \}$ is the type of a flag $f$. A set of pairwise non-opposite flags is an Erd\H{o}s-Ko-Rado set. In 2022 Metsch posed the problem of determining the maximum size of all Erd\H{o}s-Ko-Rado sets of flags of type $T$ with $|T|=2$. We contribute towards this by determining the maximum size for flags of type $\{ 1,n-3\}$ for finite sets with $n$ elements. Furthermore we answer an open questions of Metsch regarding a small case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20556v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Heering</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On likelihood of a Condorcet winner for uniformly random and independent voter preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a mathematical model of voting contest with $m$ voters and $n$ candidates, with each voter ranking the candidates in order of preference, without ties. A Condorcet winner is a candidate who gets more than $m/2$ votes in pairwise contest with every other candidate. An ``impartial culture'' setting is the case when each voter chooses his/her candidate preference list uniformly at random from all $n!$ preferences, and does it independently of all other voters. For impartial culture case, Robert May and Lisa Sauermann showed that when $m=2k-1$ is fixed ($k=2$ and $k&gt;2$ respectively), and $n$ grows indefinitely, the probability of a Condorcet winner is small, of order $n^{-(k-1)/k}$. We show that when $m$ grows indefinitely and $m\gg n^4$, the probability of a Condercet winner is $1-O(n^2/m^{1/2})\to 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20613v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Pittel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labeled Chip-Firing on Directed $k$-ary Trees and Where Chips Land</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chip-firing is a combinatorial game played on a graph, in which chips are placed and dispersed on the vertices until a stable configuration is achieved. We study a chip-firing variant on an infinite, rooted directed $k$-ary tree, where we place $k^n$ chips labeled $1,2,3,\dots, k^n$ on the root for some nonnegative integer $n$. A vertex $v$ can fire if it has at least $k$ chips; when it fires, $k$ chips are selected, and the chip with the $i$th smallest label is sent to the $i$th leftmost child of $v$. A stable configuration is reached when no vertices can fire. In this paper, we prove numerous properties of the stable configuration, such as that chips land on vertices in ranges and the lengths of those ranges. We also describe where each chip can land. This helps us describe possible stable configurations of the game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20656v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Inagaki, Tanya Khovanova, Austin Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On graph automorphisms related to Snort</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20669v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the outcomes of various positions of the game Snort. When played on graphs admitting an automorphism of order two that maps vertices outside of their closed neighbourhoods (called opposable graphs), the second player has a winning strategy. We give a necessary and sufficient condition for a graph to be opposable, and prove that the property of being opposable is preserved by several graph products. We show examples that a graph being second-player win does not imply that the graph is opposable, which answers Kakihara's conjecture. We give an analogous definition to opposability, which gives a first-player winning strategy; we prove a necessary condition for this property to be preserved by the Cartesian and strong products. As an application of our results, we determine the outcome of Snort when played on various $n\times m$ chess graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20669v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rylo Ashmore, Beth Ann Austin, Alfie M. Davies, Danny Dyer, William Kellough</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Cores of Higher Graphs Using Geometric and Topological Means: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this survey, we explore recent literature on finding the cores of higher graphs using geometric and topological means. We study graphs, hypergraphs, and simplicial complexes, all of which are models of higher graphs. We study the notion of a core, which is a minimalist representation of a higher graph that retains its geometric or topological information. We focus on geometric and topological methods based on discrete curvatures, effective resistance, and persistent homology. We aim to connect tools from graph theory, discrete geometry, and computational topology to inspire new research on the simplification of higher graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19857v1</guid>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>In\'es Garc\'ia-Redondo, Claudia Landi, Sarah Percival, Anda Skeja, Bei Wang, Ling Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlator Polytopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, "cosmohedra" have been introduced as polytopes underlying the cosmological wavefunction for conformally coupled Tr($\Phi^3$) theory in FRW cosmologies, generalizing associahedra for flat space scattering amplitudes. In this letter we show that correlation functions are also directly captured by a new polytope - the "Correlatron". The combinatorics of correlation functions is an interesting blend of flat space scattering amplitudes and wavefunctions. This is reflected in the correlatron geometry, which is a one-higher dimensional polytope sandwiched between cosmohedron and associahedron facets. We provide an explicit embedding for the correlatron, which is a natural extension of the "shaving" picture for cosmohedra to one higher dimension. As a byproduct, we also define "graph correlahedra" as polytopes for the contribution to correlators from any fixed graph. We show how the canonical form of these polytopes directly computes the graph correlator, without the power of two weights seen in previous geometric formulations. Finally, we give a prescription for extracting the full correlator from the canonical form of the correlatron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19907v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina Figueiredo, Francisco Vaz\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Strange) gamma evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review "creative" strategies of closed-form evaluations of hypergeometric functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20289v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wadim Zudilin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On plane cycles in geometric multipartite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A geometric graph is a drawing of a graph in the plane where the vertices are drawn as points in general position and the edges as straight-line segments connecting their endpoints. It is plane if it contains no crossing edges. We study plane cycles in geometric complete multipartite graphs. We prove that if a geometric complete multipartite graph contains a plane cycle of length $t$, with $t \geq 6$, it also contains a smaller plane cycle of length at least $\lfloor t/2\rfloor + 1$. We further give a characterization of geometric complete multipartite graphs that contain plane cycles with a color class appearing at least twice. For geometric drawings of $K_{n,n}$, we give a sufficient condition under which they have, for each $s \leq n$, a plane cycle of length 2s. We also provide an algorithm to decide whether a given geometric drawing of $K_{n,n}$ contains a plane Hamiltonian cycle in time $O(n \log n + nk^2) + O(k^{5k})$, where k is the number of vertices inside the convex hull of all vertices. Finally, we prove that it is NP-complete to decide if a subset of edges of a geometric complete bipartite graph H is contained in a plane Hamiltonian cycle in H.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20421v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Ricci, Jonathan Rollin, Andr\'e Schulz, Alexandra Weinberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Graph Odd Edge-Colorings and Odd Edge-Coverings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10192v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An odd $k$-edge-coloring of a graph $G$ is a (not necessarily proper) edge-coloring with at most $k$ colors such that each non-empty color class induces a graph in which every vertex is of odd degree; similarly, if more than one color per edge is allowed, we speak of an odd $k$-edge-covering of $G$. In this paper, we fully resolve two major conjectures on odd edge-colorings and odd edge-coverings of graphs, proposed by Petru{\v{s}}evski and {\v{S}}krekovski ({\it European Journal of Combinatorics,} 91:103225, 2021). The first conjecture states that, apart from two particular exceptions which are respectively odd $5$- and odd-$6$-edge-colorable, for any other loopless and connected graph $G$ there exists an edge $e$ such that $G\backslash \{e\}$ is odd $3$-edge-colorable. The second conjecture states that any simple graph $G$ admits an odd $3$-edge-covering in which at most one edge receives more than one color. In addition, we strongly confirm the second conjecture by demonstrating that there exists an odd $3$-edge-covering in which at most one edge receives two colors and the rest of the edges receive unique colors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10192v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Chuan Liu, Mirko Petru\v{s}evski, Xu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partition subcubic planar graphs into independent sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12189v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A packing $(1^{\ell}, 2^k)$-coloring of a graph $G$ is a partition of $V(G)$ into $\ell$ independent sets and $k$ $2$-packings (whose pairwise vertex distance is at least $3$). The square coloring of planar graphs was first studied by Wegner in 1977. Thomassen and independently Hartke et al. proved one can always square color a cubic planar graph with $7$ colors, i.e., every subcubic planar graph is packing $(2^7)$-colorable. We focus on packing $(1^{\ell}, 2^k)$-colorings, which lie between proper coloring and square coloring. Gastineau and Togni proved every subcubic graph is packing $(1,2^6)$-colorable and asked whether every subcubic graph except the Petersen graph is packing $(1,2^5)$-colorable.
  In this paper, we prove an analogue result of Thomassen and Hartke et al. on packing coloring that every subcubic planar graph is packing $(1,2^5)$-colorable. This also answers the question of Gastineau and Togni affirmatively for subcubic planar graphs. Moreover, we prove that there exists an infinite family of subcubic planar graphs that are not packing $(1,2^4)$-colorable, which shows that our result is the best possible. Besides, our result is also sharp in the sense that the disjoint union of Petersen graphs is subcubic and non-planar, but not packing $(1,2^5)$-colorable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12189v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xujun Liu, Yan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of Cubic Graphs and Simplicial Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22137v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simplicial surfaces describe the incidence relations between vertices, edges and faces of triangulated 2-dimensional manifolds in a purely combinatorial way. By considering only the incidences of edges and faces, simplicial surfaces are closely related to cubic graphs. In this paper we investigate how properties of simplicial surfaces and cubic graphs can be transferred to each other. Furthermore, we study embeddings of cubic graphs on simplicial surfaces and how they are connected to strong graph embeddings. For instance, 3-connected cubic planar graphs are uniquely embeddable on simplicial spheres, which is a direct consequence of Whitney's embedding theorem. Moreover, 3-connected cubic planar graphs can also be embedded on simplicial surfaces of higher genus. We characterise the properties that a simplicial sphere must possess such that the cubic graph describing its edge-face incidence relation can be embedded on a simplicial surface of non-negative Euler characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22137v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meike Wei{\ss}, Alice C. Niemeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp thresholds for spanning regular subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14794v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that $(1+o(1))\sqrt{e/n}$ is the sharp threshold for the appearance of the square of a Hamilton cycle in $G(n,p)$, confirming the conjecture of Kahn, Narayanan, and Park. We also find the exact asymptotics of the threshold for the emergence of a spanning subgraph isomorphic to a fixed graph $F$ for a wide family of $d$-regular graphs $F$. This family includes almost all $d$-regular graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14794v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksim Zhukovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some sharp bounds on the average Steiner (k, l)-eccentricity for trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17915v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce some transformations for trees that do not increase the average Steiner $(k,l)$-eccentricity for all $0\leq l\leq k\leq n$. Using these transformations, we obtain some sharp bounds on the average Steiner $(k,l)$-eccentricity for trees with some certain conditions, including given nodes, given diameter, given max degree and given leaves, and get the corresponding extremal trees as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17915v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Zeng, Gengji Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proportion of blocking curves in a pencil</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.06019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.06019v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{L}$ be a pencil of plane curves defined over $\mathbb{F}_q$ with no $\mathbb{F}_q$-points in its base locus. We investigate the number of curves in $\mathcal{L}$ whose $\mathbb{F}_q$-points form a blocking set. When the degree of the pencil is allowed to grow with respect to $q$, we show that the geometric problem can be translated into a purely combinatorial problem about disjoint blocking sets. We also study the same problem when the degree of the pencil is fixed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.06019v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shamil Asgarli, Dragos Ghioca, Chi Hoi Yip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taut smoothings of arcs and curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06623v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the geometric and combinatorial effect of smoothing an intersection point in a collection of arcs or curves on a surface. We prove that all taut arcs with fixed endpoints and all taut 1-manifolds with at least two non-disjoint components on an orientable surface with negative Euler characteristic admit a taut smoothing, and also that all taut arcs with free endpoints admit a smoothing that is either taut or becomes taut after removing at most one intersection. We deduce that for every Riemannian metric on a surface, the shortest properly immersed arcs with at least $k$ self-intersections have exactly $k$ self-intersections when the endpoints of the arc are fixed, and at most $k+1$ self-intersections otherwise, and that the arc length spectrum is "coarsely ordered" by self-intersection number. Along the way, we obtain partial analogous results in the case of curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06623v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Macarena Arenas, Max Neumann-Coto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A fixed-point theorem for face maps, or deletion-tolerant random finite sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21484v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish a fixed-point theorem for the face maps that consist in deleting the $i$th entry of an ordered set. Furthermore, we show that there exists random finite sets of integers that are almost invariant under such deletions. Consequences for various monoids of order-preserving transformations of $\mathbf{N}$ are discussed in an appendix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21484v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Hutchcroft, Nicolas Monod, Omer Tamuz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on congruences for the difference between even cranks and odd cranks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16267v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, Amdeberhan and Merca proved some arithmetic properties of the crank parity function $C(n)$ defined as the difference between the number of partitions of $n$ with even cranks and those with odd cranks and the sequence $a(n)$ whose generating function is the reciprocal of that of $C(n)$. The function $C(n)$ was first studied by Choi, Kang, and Lovejoy. In this note, we give new elementary proofs of some of their main results and extend them. In particular, we establish Ramanujan-type congruences modulo $5$ and $25$ for certain finite sums involving $C(n)$ and $a(n)$. Our proofs employ the results of Cooper, Hirschhorn, and Lewis, and certain identities involving the Rogers-Ramanujan continued fraction $R(q)$ due to Chern and Tang.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16267v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Russelle Guadalupe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex addition to a ball graph with application to reliability and area coverage in autonomous swarms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19197v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A unit ball graph consists of a set of vertices, labeled by points in Euclidean space, and edges joining all pairs of points within distance $1$. These geometric graphs are used to model a variety of spatial networks, including communication networks between agents in an autonomous swarm. In such an application, vertices and/or edges of the graph may not be perfectly reliable; an agent may experience failure or a communication link rendered inoperable. With the goal of designing robust swarm formations, or unit ball graphs with high reliability (probability of connectedness), in a preliminary conference paper we provided an algorithm with cubic time complexity to determine all possible changes to a unit ball graph by repositioning a single vertex. Using this algorithm and Monte Carlo simulations, one obtains an efficient method to modify a unit ball graph by moving a single vertex to a location which maximizes the reliability. Another important consideration in many swarm missions is area coverage, yet highly reliable ball graphs often contain clusters of vertices. Here, we generalize our previous algorithm to improve area coverage as well as reliability. Our algorithm determines a location to add or move a vertex within a unit ball graph which maximizes the reliability, under the constraint that no other vertices of the graph be within some fixed distance. We compare this method of obtaining graphs with high reliability and evenly distributed area coverage to another method which uses a modified Fruchterman-Reingold algorithm for ball graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19197v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Calum Buchanan, Puck Rombach, James Bagrow, Hamid R. Ossareh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Search Improvements for Soft Happy Colouring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19284v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For $0\leq \rho\leq 1$ and a coloured graph $G$, a vertex $v$ is $\rho$-happy if at least $\rho \mathrm{deg}(v)$ of its neighbours have the same colour as $v$. Soft happy colouring of a partially coloured graph $G$ is the problem of finding a vertex colouring $\sigma$ that preserves the precolouring and has the maximum number of $\rho$-happy vertices. It is already known that this problem is NP-hard and directly relates to the community structure of the graphs; under a certain condition on the proportion of happiness $\rho$ and for graphs with community structures, the induced colouring by communities can make all the vertices $\rho$-happy. We show that when $0\leq \rho_1&lt;\rho_2\leq 1$, a complete $\rho_2$-happy colouring has a higher accuracy of community detection than a complete $\rho_1$-happy colouring. Moreover, when $\rho$ is greater than a threshold, it is unlikely for an algorithm to find a complete $\rho$-happy colouring with colour classes of almost equal sizes. Three local search algorithms for soft happy colouring are proposed, and their performances are compared with one another and other known algorithms. Among them, the linear-time local search is shown to be not only very fast, but also a reliable algorithm that can dramatically improve the number of $\rho$-happy vertices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19284v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Hadi Shekarriz, Dhananjay Thiruvady, Asef Nazari, Wilfried Imrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
