<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Exploration of the Pythagorean Theorem Using HOBO Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel method for finding integer sets that satisfy the Pythagorean theorem by leveraging the Higher-Order Binary Optimization (HOBO) formulation. Unlike the Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) formulation, which struggles to express complex mathematical equations, HOBO's ability to model higher-order interactions between binary variables makes it well-suited for addressing more complex and expressive problem settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11076v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoya Yasuda, Naoaki Mochida, Shunsuke Sotobayashi, Devanshu Garg, Yuichiro Minato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-level Monte-Carlo Gradient Methods for Stochastic Optimization with Biased Oracles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider stochastic optimization when one only has access to biased stochastic oracles of the objective and the gradient, and obtaining stochastic gradients with low biases comes at high costs. This setting captures various optimization paradigms, such as conditional stochastic optimization, distributionally robust optimization, shortfall risk optimization, and machine learning paradigms, such as contrastive learning. We examine a family of multi-level Monte Carlo (MLMC) gradient methods that exploit a delicate tradeoff among bias, variance, and oracle cost. We systematically study their total sample and computational complexities for strongly convex, convex, and nonconvex objectives and demonstrate their superiority over the widely used biased stochastic gradient method. When combined with the variance reduction techniques like SPIDER, these MLMC gradient methods can further reduce the complexity in the nonconvex regime. Our results imply that a series of stochastic optimization problems with biased oracles, previously considered to be more challenging, is fundamentally no harder than the classical stochastic optimization with unbiased oracles. We also delineate the boundary conditions under which these problems become more difficult. Moreover, MLMC gradient methods significantly improve the best-known complexities in the literature for conditional stochastic optimization and shortfall risk optimization. Our extensive numerical experiments on distributionally robust optimization, pricing and staffing scheduling problems, and contrastive learning demonstrate the superior performance of MLMC gradient methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11084v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Hu, Jie Wang, Xin Chen, Niao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality of Geometric Tests for Forward-Flatness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently it has been shown that the property of forward-flatness for discrete-time systems, which is a generalization of static feedback linearizability and a special case of a more general concept of flatness, can be checked by two different geometric tests. One is based on unique sequences of involutive distributions, while the other is based on a unique sequence of integrable codistributions. In this paper, the relation between these sequences is discussed and it is shown that the tests are in fact dual. The presented results are illustrated by an academic example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11143v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Schrotshamer, Bernd Kolar, Markus Sch\"oberl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Hosting Capacity Assessment for Electric Vehicles: A Sequential Forecast-then-Optimize Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hosting capacity (HC) assessment for electric vehicles (EVs) is of great significance to ensure the safe integration of EVs and the reliable operation of power systems. Existing HC assessment methods mainly focus on a long-term perspective (e.g., system planning), and model the EV charging demands as scalar values. However, HC estimated from a long-term perspective may be inaccurate and unreliable for real-time operation, since long-term peak estimation differs from the real-time stochasticity of EV charging demands. In this regard, this paper proposes a real-time HC assessment method for EVs through a three-step process of real-time probabilistic forecasting, real-time risk analysis and probabilistic optimization. Specifically, we first conduct real-time probabilistic forecasting through an adaptive spatio-temporal graph convolutional network to describe the stochasticity in EV charging demands across multiple charging stations. This model leverages adaptive spatial feature extraction, attention-based temporal feature extraction, and second-order graph representation to capture the spatio-temporal features of EV charging demands. Subsequently, based on the probabilistic forecasting, we propose a real-time risk analysis method, which is achieved by calculating the probabilistic power flow based on an improved Gaussian mixture model. Furthermore, we provide a real-time formulation of the HC of EVs and propose an optimization model to assess it. Numerical experiments on a real-world dataset demonstrate that the proposed forecasting model outperforms state-of-the-art forecasting methods by achieving the lowest RMSE value of 0.0442, the proposed real-time risk analysis method maintains over 96.6% accuracy with 99.99% reduction in computational complexity, and the real-time HC is improved by 66.3% compared to long-term assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11269v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingrui Zhuang, Lin Cheng, Ning Qi, Xinyi Wang, Yue Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Length-minimizing LED Trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a specific type of Euclidean tree called LED (Leaves of Equal Depth) tree. LED trees can be used in computational phylogeny, since they are a natural representative of the time evolution of a set of species in a feature space. This work is focused on LED trees that are length minimizers for a given set of leaves (species) and a given isomorphism type (the hierarchical structure of ancestors). The underlying minimization problem can be seen as a variant of the classical Euclidean Steiner tree problem. Even though it has a convex objective function, it is rather non-trivial, since it has a non-convex feasible set. The main contribution of this paper is that we provide a uniqueness result for this problem. Moreover, we explore some geometrical and topological properties of the feasible set and we prove several geometrical characteristics of the length minimizers that are analogical to the properties of Steiner trees. At the end, we show a simple example of an application in historical linguistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11385v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana Sarkociov\'a Reme\v{s}\'ikov\'a, Peter Sarkoci, M\'aria Trnovsk\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flatness-based control revisited: The HEOL setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the algebraic foundations of the HEOL setting, which combines flatness-based control and intelligent controllers, two advances in automatic control that have been proven in practice, including in industry. The result provides a solution to many pending questions on feedback loops concerning flatness-based control and model-free control (MFC). Elementary module theory, ordinary differential fields and the generalization of K\"ahler differentials to differential fields provide an intrinsic definition of the tangent linear system. The algebraic manipulations associated with the operational calculus lead to homeostat and intelligent controllers. They are illustrated via some computer simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11580v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Join, Emmanuel Delaleau, Michel Fliess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ensemble Epanechnikov Mixture Filter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the high-dimensional setting, Gaussian mixture kernel density estimates become increasingly suboptimal. In this work we aim to show that it is practical to instead use the optimal multivariate Epanechnikov kernel. We make use of this optimal Epanechnikov mixture kernel density estimate for the sequential filtering scenario through what we term the ensemble Epanechnikov mixture filter (EnEMF). We provide a practical implementation of the EnEMF that is as cost efficient as the comparable ensemble Gaussian mixture filter. We show on a static example that the EnEMF is robust to growth in dimension, and also that the EnEMF has a significant reduction in error per particle on the 40-variable Lorenz '96 system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11164v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey A. Popov, Renato Zanetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Negotiation Using Comparison-Based Gradient Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Negotiation is useful for resolving conflicts in multi-agent systems. We explore autonomous negotiation in a setting where two self-interested rational agents sequentially trade items from a finite set of categories. Each agent has a utility function that depends on the amount of items it possesses in each category. The offering agent makes trade offers to improve its utility without knowing the responding agent's utility function, and the responding agent accepts offers that improve its utility. We present a comparison-based algorithm for the offering agent that generates offers through previous acceptance or rejection responses without extensive information sharing. The algorithm estimates the responding agent's gradient by leveraging the rationality assumption and rejected offers to prune the space of potential gradients. After the algorithm makes a finite number of consecutively rejected offers, the responding agent is at a near-optimal state, or the agents' preferences are closely aligned. Additionally, we facilitate negotiations with humans by representing natural language feedback as comparisons that can be integrated into the proposed algorithm. We compare the proposed algorithm against random search baselines in integer and fractional trading scenarios and show that it improves the societal benefit with fewer offers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surya Murthy, Mustafa O. Karabag, Ufuk Topcu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Guarantees for Online Selection Over Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Prophet inequalities are a cornerstone in optimal stopping and online decision-making. Traditionally, they involve the sequential observation of $n$ non-negative independent random variables and face irrevocable accept-or-reject choices. The goal is to provide policies that provide a good approximation ratio against the optimal offline solution that can access all the values upfront -- the so-called prophet value. In the prophet inequality over time problem (POT), the decision-maker can commit to an accepted value for $\tau$ units of time, during which no new values can be accepted. This creates a trade-off between the duration of commitment and the opportunity to capture potentially higher future values.
  In this work, we provide best possible worst-case approximation ratios in the IID setting of POT for single-threshold algorithms and the optimal dynamic programming policy. We show a single-threshold algorithm that achieves an approximation ratio of $(1+e^{-2})/2\approx 0.567$, and we prove that no single-threshold algorithm can surpass this guarantee. With our techniques, we can analyze simple algorithms using $k$ thresholds and show that with $k=3$ it is possible to get an approximation ratio larger than $\approx 0.602$. Then, for each $n$, we prove it is possible to compute the tight worst-case approximation ratio of the optimal dynamic programming policy for instances with $n$ values by solving a convex optimization program. A limit analysis of the first-order optimality conditions yields a nonlinear differential equation showing that the optimal dynamic programming policy's asymptotic worst-case approximation ratio is $\approx 0.618$. Finally, we extend the discussion to adversarial settings and show an optimal worst-case approximation ratio of $\approx 0.162$ when the values are streamed in random order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11224v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Perez-Salazar, Victor Verdugo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vizier Gaussian Process Bandit Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Google Vizier has performed millions of optimizations and accelerated numerous research and production systems at Google, demonstrating the success of Bayesian optimization as a large-scale service. Over multiple years, its algorithm has been improved considerably, through the collective experiences of numerous research efforts and user feedback. In this technical report, we discuss the implementation details and design choices of the current default algorithm provided by Open Source Vizier. Our experiments on standardized benchmarks reveal its robustness and versatility against well-established industry baselines on multiple practical modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11527v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyou Song, Qiuyi Zhang, Chansoo Lee, Emily Fertig, Tzu-Kuo Huang, Lior Belenki, Greg Kochanski, Setareh Ariafar, Srinivas Vasudevan, Sagi Perel, Daniel Golovin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annealed Sinkhorn for Optimal Transport: convergence, regularization path and debiasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11620v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sinkhorn's algorithm is a method of choice to solve large-scale optimal transport (OT) problems. In this context, it involves an inverse temperature parameter $\beta$ that determines the speed-accuracy trade-off. To improve this trade-off, practitioners often use a variant of this algorithm, Annealed Sinkhorn, that uses an nondecreasing sequence $(\beta_t)_{t\in \mathbb{N}}$ where $t$ is the iteration count. However, besides for the schedule $\beta_t=\Theta(\log t)$ which is impractically slow, it is not known whether this variant is guaranteed to actually solve OT. Our first contribution answers this question: we show that a concave annealing schedule asymptotically solves OT if and only if $\beta_t\to+\infty$ and $\beta_t-\beta_{t-1}\to 0$. The proof is based on an equivalence with Online Mirror Descent and further suggests that the iterates of Annealed Sinkhorn follow the solutions of a sequence of relaxed, entropic OT problems, the regularization path. An analysis of this path reveals that, in addition to the well-known "entropic" error in $\Theta(\beta^{-1}_t)$, the annealing procedure induces a "relaxation" error in $\Theta(\beta_{t}-\beta_{t-1})$. The best error trade-off is achieved with the schedule $\beta_t = \Theta(\sqrt{t})$ which, albeit slow, is a universal limitation of this method. Going beyond this limitation, we propose a simple modification of Annealed Sinkhorn that reduces the relaxation error, and therefore enables faster annealing schedules. In toy experiments, we observe the effectiveness of our Debiased Annealed Sinkhorn's algorithm: a single run of this algorithm spans the whole speed-accuracy Pareto front of the standard Sinkhorn's algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11620v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'ena\"ic Chizat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plug-in estimation of Schr\"odinger bridges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11686v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a procedure for estimating the Schr\"odinger bridge between two probability distributions. Unlike existing approaches, our method does not require iteratively simulating forward and backward diffusions or training neural networks to fit unknown drifts. Instead, we show that the potentials obtained from solving the static entropic optimal transport problem between the source and target samples can be modified to yield a natural plug-in estimator of the time-dependent drift that defines the bridge between two measures. Under minimal assumptions, we show that our proposal, which we call the \emph{Sinkhorn bridge}, provably estimates the Schr\"odinger bridge with a rate of convergence that depends on the intrinsic dimensionality of the target measure. Our approach combines results from the areas of sampling, and theoretical and statistical entropic optimal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11686v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aram-Alexandre Pooladian, Jonathan Niles-Weed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superlinear Convergence of an Interior Point Algorithm on Linear Semi-definite Feasibility Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.08215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.08215v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the literature, besides the assumption of strict complementarity, superlinear convergence of implementable polynomial-time interior point algorithms using known search directions, namely, the HKM direction, its dual or the NT direction, to solve semi-definite programs (SDPs) is shown by (i) assuming that the given SDP is nondegenerate and making modifications to these algorithms [10], or (ii) considering special classes of SDPs, such as the class of linear semi-definite feasibility problems (LSDFPs) and requiring the initial iterate to the algorithm to satisfy certain conditions [26, 27]. Otherwise, these algorithms are not easy to implement even though they are shown to have polynomial iteration complexities and superlinear convergence [14]. The conditions in [26, 27] that the initial iterate to the algorithm is required to satisfy to have superlinear convergence when solving LSDFPs however are not practical. In this paper, we propose a practical initial iterate to an implementable infeasible interior point algorithm that guarantees superlinear convergence when the algorithm is used to solve the homogeneous feasibility model of an LSDFP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.08215v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chee-Khian Sim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of individual compensation and acceptance decisions in crowdsourced delivery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01317v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the recent innovations in urban distribution is crowdsourced delivery, where deliveries are made by occasional drivers who wish to utilize their surplus resources (unused transport capacity) by making deliveries in exchange for some compensation. The potential benefits of crowdsourced delivery include reduced delivery costs and increased flexibility (by scaling delivery capacity up and down as needed). The use of occasional drivers poses new challenges because (unlike traditional couriers) neither their availability nor their behavior in accepting delivery offers is certain. The relationship between the compensation offered to occasional drivers and the probability that they will accept a task has been largely neglected in the scientific literature. Therefore, we consider a setting in which compensation-dependent acceptance probabilities are explicitly considered in the process of assigning delivery tasks to occasional drivers. We propose a mixed-integer nonlinear model that minimizes the expected delivery costs while identifying optimal assignments of tasks to a mix of professional and occasional drivers and their compensation. We propose an exact two-stage solution algorithm that allows to decompose compensation and assignment decisions for generic acceptance probability functions and show that the runtime of this algorithm is polynomial under mild conditions. Finally, we also study a more general case of the considered problem setting, show that it is NP-hard and propose an approximate linearization scheme of our mixed-integer nonlinear model. The results of our computational study show clear advantages of our new approach over existing ones. They also indicate that these advantages remain in dynamic settings when tasks and drivers are revealed over time and in which case our method constitutes a fast, yet powerful heuristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01317v5</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alim Bu\u{g}ra \c{C}{\i}nar, Wout Dullaert, Markus Leitner, Rosario Paradiso, Stefan Waldherr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turnpike and dissipativity in generalized discrete-time stochastic linear-quadratic optimal control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05422v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate different turnpike phenomena of generalized discrete-time stochastic linear-quadratic optimal control problems. Our analysis is based on a novel strict dissipativity notion for such problems, in which a stationary stochastic process replaces the optimal steady state of the deterministic setting. We show that from this time-varying dissipativity notion, we can conclude turnpike behaviors concerning different objects like distributions, moments, or sample paths of the stochastic system and that the distributions of the stationary pair can be characterized by a stationary optimization problem. The analytical findings are illustrated by numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05422v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Schie{\ss}l, Ruchuan Ou, Timm Faulwasser, Michael Heinrich Baumann, Lars Gr\"une</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the relationship between stochastic turnpike and dissipativity notions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07281v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and study different dissipativity notions and different turnpike properties for discrete-time stochastic nonlinear optimal control problems. The proposed stochastic dissipativity notions extend the classic notion of Jan C. Willems to $L^r$ random variables and to probability measures. Our stochastic turnpike properties range from a formulation for random variables via turnpike phenomena in probability and in probability measures to the turnpike property for the moments. Moreover, we investigate how different metrics (such as Wasserstein or L\'evy-Prokhorov) can be leveraged in the analysis. Our results are built upon stationarity concepts in distribution and in random variables and on the formulation of the stochastic optimal control problem as a finite-horizon Markov decision process. We investigate how the proposed dissipativity notions connect to the various stochastic turnpike properties and we work out the link between different forms of dissipativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07281v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Schie{\ss}l, Michael H. Baumann, Timm Faulwasser, Lars Gr\"une</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SubRiemannian cut time and cut locus in Reiter-Heisenberg groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14771v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the subRiemannian cut time and cut locus of a given point in a class of step-2 Carnot groups of Reiter-Heisenberg type. Following the Hamiltonian point of view, we write and analyze extremal curves, getting the cut time of any of them, and a precise description of the set of cut points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14771v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annamaria Montanari, Daniele Morbidelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proximal observers for secure state estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper discusses a general framework for designing robust state estimators for a class of discrete-time nonlinear systems. We consider systems that may be impacted by impulsive (sparse but otherwise arbitrary) measurement noise sequences. We show that a family of state estimators, robust to this type of undesired signal, can be obtained by minimizing a class of nonsmooth convex functions at each time step. The resulting state observers are defined through proximal operators. We obtain a nonlinear implicit dynamical system in term of estimation error and prove, in the noise-free setting, that it vanishes asymptotically when the minimized loss function and the to-be-observed system enjoy appropriate properties. From a computational perspective, even though the proposed observers can be implemented via efficient numerical procedures, they do not admit closed-form expressions. The paper argues that by adopting appropriate relaxations, simple and fast analytic expressions can be derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06098v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent Bako, Madiha Nadri, Vincent Andrieu, Qinghua Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-optimal performance of stochastic economic MPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15159v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents first results for near optimality in expectation of the closed-loop solutions for stochastic economic MPC. The approach relies on a recently developed turnpike property for stochastic optimal control problems at an optimal stationary process, combined with techniques for analyzing time-varying economic MPC schemes. We obtain near optimality in finite time as well as overtaking and average near optimality on infinite time horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15159v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Schie{\ss}l, Ruchuan Ou, Timm Faulwasser, Michael H. Baumann, Lars Gr\"une</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Discretization for Continuous-State MDPs in Infectious Disease Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12540v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Repeated decision-making problems under uncertainty may arise in the health policy context, such as infectious disease control for COVID-19 and other epidemics. These problems may sometimes be effectively solved using Markov decision processes (MDPs). However, the continuous or large state space of such problems for capturing infectious disease prevalence renders it difficult to implement tractable MDPs to identify the optimal disease control policy over time. We therefore develop an algorithm for discretizing continuous states for approximate MDP solutions in this context. We benchmark performance against a uniform discretization using both a synthetic example and an example of COVID-19 in Los Angeles County.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12540v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suyanpeng Zhang, Sze-chuan Suen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assortment Optimization Under History-Dependent Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10967v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper examines how to plan multi-period assortments when customer utility depends on historical assortments. We formulate this problem as a nonlinear integer programming problem and propose solution methodologies for different regimes of this problem. First, we present a sequential revenue-ordered policy and show that it is optimal when historical assortments positively affect customer utility. Second, we show that the problem is NP-hard under the presence of a negative history-dependent effect (such as a satiation effect). In this case, we propose using a lifting-based framework to reformulate the problem as a mixed-integer exponential cone program that state-of-the-art solvers can solve. Additionally, we identify an optimal cyclic policy for an asymptotic regime, and we also relate its length to the customer's memory length. Finally, we present a case study using a catering service dataset that shows that our model demonstrates good fitness and can effectively balance variety and revenue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10967v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taotao He, Yating Zhang, Huan Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expanding the reach of quantum optimization with fermionic embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.01778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.01778v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quadratic programming over orthogonal matrices encompasses a broad class of hard optimization problems that do not have an efficient quantum representation. Such problems are instances of the little noncommutative Grothendieck problem (LNCG), a generalization of binary quadratic programs to continuous, noncommutative variables. In this work, we establish a natural embedding for this class of LNCG problems onto a fermionic Hamiltonian, thereby enabling the study of this classical problem with the tools of quantum information. This embedding is accomplished by a new representation of orthogonal matrices as fermionic quantum states, which we achieve through the well-known double covering of the orthogonal group. Correspondingly, the embedded LNCG Hamiltonian is a two-body fermion model. Determining extremal states of this Hamiltonian provides an outer approximation to the original problem, a quantum analogue to classical semidefinite relaxations. In particular, when optimizing over the \emph{special} orthogonal group our quantum relaxation obeys additional, powerful constraints based on the convex hull of rotation matrices. The classical size of this convex-hull representation is exponential in matrix dimension, whereas our quantum representation requires only a linear number of qubits. Finally, to project the relaxed solution back into the feasible space, we propose rounding procedures which return orthogonal matrices from appropriate measurements of the quantum state. Through numerical experiments we provide evidence that this rounded quantum relaxation can produce high-quality approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.01778v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Zhao, Nicholas C. Rubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unfolded proximal neural networks for robust image Gaussian denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03139v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A common approach to solve inverse imaging problems relies on finding a maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimate of the original unknown image, by solving a minimization problem. In thiscontext, iterative proximal algorithms are widely used, enabling to handle non-smooth functions and linear operators. Recently, these algorithms have been paired with deep learning strategies, to further improve the estimate quality. In particular, proximal neural networks (PNNs) have been introduced, obtained by unrolling a proximal algorithm as for finding a MAP estimate, but over a fixed number of iterations, with learned linear operators and parameters. As PNNs are based on optimization theory, they are very flexible, and can be adapted to any image restoration task, as soon as a proximal algorithm can solve it. They further have much lighter architectures than traditional networks. In this article we propose a unified framework to build PNNs for the Gaussian denoising task, based on both the dual-FB and the primal-dual Chambolle-Pock algorithms. We further show that accelerated inertial versions of these algorithms enable skip connections in the associated NN layers. We propose different learning strategies for our PNN framework, and investigate their robustness (Lipschitz property) and denoising efficiency. Finally, we assess the robustness of our PNNs when plugged in a forward-backward algorithm for an image deblurring problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03139v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Trieu Vy Le, Audrey Repetti, Nelly Pustelnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical method for nonlinear Kolmogorov PDEs via sensitivity analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11910v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine nonlinear Kolmogorov partial differential equations (PDEs). Here the nonlinear part of the PDE comes from its Hamiltonian where one maximizes over all possible drift and diffusion coefficients which fall within a $\varepsilon$-neighborhood of pre-specified baseline coefficients. Our goal is to quantify and compute how sensitive those PDEs are to such a small nonlinearity, and then use the results to develop an efficient numerical method for their approximation. We show that as $\varepsilon\downarrow 0$, the nonlinear Kolmogorov PDE equals the linear Kolmogorov PDE defined with respect to the corresponding baseline coefficients plus $\varepsilon$ times a correction term which can be also characterized by the solution of another linear Kolmogorov PDE involving the baseline coefficients. As these linear Kolmogorov PDEs can be efficiently solved in high-dimensions by exploiting their Feynman-Kac representation, our derived sensitivity analysis then provides a Monte Carlo based numerical method which can efficiently solve these nonlinear Kolmogorov equations. We establish an error and complexity analysis for our numerical method. Moreover, we provide numerical examples in up to 100 dimensions to empirically demonstrate the applicability of our numerical method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11910v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Bartl, Ariel Neufeld, Kyunghyun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Generalization and Convergence by Enhancing Implicit Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20763v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we propose an Implicit Regularization Enhancement (IRE) framework to accelerate the discovery of flat solutions in deep learning, thereby improving generalization and convergence. Specifically, IRE decouples the dynamics of flat and sharp directions, which boosts the sharpness reduction along flat directions while maintaining the training stability in sharp directions. We show that IRE can be practically incorporated with {\em generic base optimizers} without introducing significant computational overload. Experiments show that IRE consistently improves the generalization performance for image classification tasks across a variety of benchmark datasets (CIFAR-10/100, ImageNet) and models (ResNets and ViTs). Surprisingly, IRE also achieves a $2\times$ {\em speed-up} compared to AdamW in the pre-training of Llama models (of sizes ranging from 60M to 229M) on datasets including Wikitext-103, Minipile, and Openwebtext. Moreover, we provide theoretical guarantees, showing that IRE can substantially accelerate the convergence towards flat minima in Sharpness-aware Minimization (SAM).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20763v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingze Wang, Jinbo Wang, Haotian He, Zilin Wang, Guanhua Huang, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li, Weinan E, Lei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
