<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 01:41:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An interdisciplinary data-science approach to managing natural hazards risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Natural hazard risk management is a demanding interdisciplinary task. It requires domain knowledge, integration of robust computational methods, and effective use of complex datasets. However, existing solutions tend to focus on specific aspects, data, or methods, limiting their impact and applicability. Here, we present a general data-driven framework to support risk assessment and policy making illustrating its usage in the context of fire hazard by integrating three unique datasets of fire behavior, street network, and census data for the whole state of California. We show that integrating spatial complexity by including a fire behavior layer and a socio-demographic layer changes the universal function observed in previous optimization frameworks that only work with the accessibility of facilities. These results open avenues for the future development of flexible interdisciplinary frameworks in natural hazards management using complex large-scale data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07270v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristobal Pais, Minho Kim, John Radke, Marta C. Gonzalez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Droop-based Finite-Control-Set Model Predictive Control of Inverter-based Resources in Islanded AC Microgrid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an improved droop control method to ensure effective power sharing, voltage regulation, and frequency stabilization of inverter-based resources (IBRs) connected in parallel in an islanded AC microgrid. In the contemporary droop control algorithm, the distance between connected inverters affects the effectiveness of the active power-frequency and the reactive power-voltage droop characteristics which results in poor power sharing at the primary level of the microgrid. That is, high impedance emanating from long transmission lines results in instability, poor voltage tracking, and ineffective frequency regulation. Hence, in this work, we use a finite-control-set model predictive controller (FCS-MPC) in the inner loop, which gives efficient voltage tracking, good frequency regulation, and faster performance response. FCS-MPC is easy to implement in fast switching converters and does not suffer from computational burden unlike the continuous-set MPC and is also devoid of issues of multiple-loop, parameter variation, and slow response associated with conventional droop control methods. We derived the condition for bounded stability for the FCS-MPC and the proposed method is tested via a numerical simulation on three IBRs. The results show effective power sharing, capacitor voltage tracking, and efficient frequency regulation with reduced oscillations to changes in load.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07281v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayobami Olajube, Koto Omiloli, Satish Vedula, Olugbenga Anubi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Precision, Fair University Course Scheduling During a Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07355v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scheduling university courses is extra challenging when classroom capacities are reduced because of social distancing requirements that are implemented in response to a pandemic such as COVID-19. In this work, we propose an expanded taxonomy of course delivery modes, present an integer program, and develop a course scheduling algorithm to enable all course sections -- even the largest -- to have a significant classroom learning component during a pandemic. Our approach is fair by ensuring that a certain fraction of the instruction in every course section occurs in the classroom. Unlike previous studies, we do not allow rotating attendance and instead require simultaneous attendance in which all students in a section meet in 1-5 rooms at the same time but less often than in a normal semester. These mass meetings, which create opportunities for in-person midterm exams and group activities, are scheduled at high precision across all days of the semester rather than a single, repeating week. A fast heuristic algorithm makes the schedule in an hour. Results: We consider the 1834 in-person course sections, 172 classrooms, and 96 days in the fall 2022 semester at [UniversityXYZ]. If average classroom capacity is reduced by 75% due to a pandemic, our approach still allows at least 25% of the instruction in every section, and more than 49% of all instruction across the entire campus, to be in the classroom. Our method also produces excellent results for regular classroom assignment. Managerial implications: An algorithm based on the principles of fairness and simultaneous attendance can significantly improve university course schedules during a pandemic and in normal times. High-precision schedules that prepare a campus for various pandemic possibilities can be created with minimal administrative effort and activated at a moment's notice before or during a semester if an outbreak occurs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07355v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew E. H. Petering, Mohammad Khamechian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small-Time Local Controllability of the multi-input bilinear Schr\"odinger equation thanks to a quadratic term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this article is to contribute to a better understanding of the relations between the exact controllability of nonlinear PDEs and the control theory for ODEs based on Lie brackets, through a study of the Schr{\"o}dinger PDE with bilinear control.We focus on the small-time local controllability (STLC) around an equilibrium, when the linearized system is not controllable. We study the second order order term in the Taylor expansion of the state, with respect to the control.For scalar input ODEs, quadratic terms never recover controllability: they induce signed drifts in the dynamics. Thus proving STLC requires to go at least to the third order. Similar results were proved for the bilinear Schr{\"o}dinger PDE with scalar input controls.In this article, we study the case of multi-input systems. We clarify among the quadratic Lie brackets, those that allow to recover STLC: they are bilinear with respect to 2 different controls. For ODEs, our result is a consequence of Sussman's sufficient condition S($\theta$) (when focused on quadratic terms), but we propose a new proof, designed to prepare an easier transfer to PDEs. This proof relies on a representation formula of the state inspired by the Magnus formula. By adapting it, we prove a new STLC result for the bilinear Schr{\"o}dinger PDE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07446v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Gherdaoui (IRMAR, ENS Rennes)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An implementable proximal-type method for computing critical points to minimization problems with a nonsmooth and nonconvex constraint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work proposes an implementable proximal-type method for a broad class of optimization problems involving nonsmooth and nonconvex objective and constraint functions. In contrast to existing methods that rely on an ad hoc model approximating the nonconvex functions, our approach can work with a nonconvex model constructed by the pointwise minimum of finitely many convex models. The latter can be chosen with reasonable flexibility to better fit the underlying functions' structure. We provide a unifying framework and analysis covering several subclasses of composite optimization problems and show that our method computes points satisfying certain necessary optimality conditions, which we will call model criticality. Depending on the specific model being used, our general concept of criticality boils down to standard necessary optimality conditions. Numerical experiments on some stochastic reliability-based optimization problems illustrate the practical performance of the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07471v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio M. Sempere, Welington de Oliveira, Johannes O. Royset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bilinear optimal control for chemotaxis model: The case of two-sidedly degenerate diffusion with Volume-Filling Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study an optimal control problem for a coupled non-linear system of reaction-diffusion equations with degenerate diffusion, consisting of two partial differential equations representing the density of cells and the concentration of the chemotactic agent. By controlling the concentration of the chemical substrates, this study can guide the optimal growth of cells. The novelty of this work lies on the direct and dual models that remain in a weak setting, which is uncommon in the recent literature for solving optimal control systems. Moreover, it is known that the adjoint problems offer a powerful approach to quantifying the uncertainty associated with model inputs. However, these systems typically lack closed-form solutions, making it challenging to obtain weak solutions. For that, the well-posedness of the direct problem is first well guaranteed. Then, the existence of an optimal control and the first-order optimality conditions are established. Finally, weak solutions for the adjoint system to the non-linear degenerate direct model, are introduced and investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07519v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georges Chamoun, Mazen Saad, Toni Sayah, Sarah Serhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mini-batch descent in semiflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the application of mini-batch gradient descent to semiflows. Given a loss function, we introduce a continuous version of mini-batch gradient descent by randomly selecting sub-loss functions over time, defining a piecewise flow. We prove that, under suitable assumptions on the gradient flow, the mini-batch descent flow trajectory closely approximates the original gradient flow trajectory on average. Additionally, we propose a randomized minimizing movement scheme that also approximates the gradient flow of the loss function. We illustrate the versatility of this approach across various problems, including constrained optimization, sparse inversion, and domain decomposition. Finally, we validate our results with several numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07556v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Dom\'inguez Corella, Mart\'in Hern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Control Set Model Predictive Control with Limit Cycle Stability Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper considers the design of finite control set model predictive control (FCS-MPC) for discrete-time switched affine systems. Existing FCS-MPC methods typically pursue practical stability guarantees, which ensure convergence to a bounded invariant set that contains a desired steady state. As such, current FCS-MPC methods result in unpredictable steady-state behavior due to arbitrary switching among the available finite control inputs. Motivated by this, we present a FCS-MPC design that aims to stabilize a steady-state limit cycle compatible with a desired output reference via a suitable cost function. We provide conditions in terms of periodic terminal costs and finite control set control laws that guarantee asymptotic stability of the developed limit cycle FCS-MPC algorithm. Moreover, we develop conditions for recursive feasibility of limit cycle FCS-MPC in terms of periodic terminal sets and we provide systematic methods for computing ellipsoidal and polytopic periodically invariant sets that contain a desired steady-state limit cycle. Compared to existing periodic terminal ingredients for tracking MPC with a continuous control set, we design and compute terminal ingredients using a finite control set. The developed methodology is validated on switched systems and power electronics benchmark examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07615v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duo Xu, Mircea Lazar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S2MPJ and CUTEst optimization problems for Matlab, Python and Julia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new decoder for the SIF test problems of the CUTEst collection is described, which produces problem files allowing the computation of values and derivatives of the objective function and constraints of most \cutest\ problems directly within ``native'' Matlab, Python or Julia, without any additional installation or interfacing with MEX files or Fortran programs. When used with Matlab, the new problem files optionally support reduced-precision computations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07812v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serge Gratton, Philippe L. Toint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllability problems of a neutral integro-differential equation with memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The current study addresses the control problems posed by a semilinear neutral integro-differential equation with memory. The primary objectives of this study are to investigate the existence of a mild solution and approximate controllability of both linear and semilinear control systems in Banach spaces. To accomplish this, we begin by introducing the concept of a resolvent family associated with the homogeneous neutral integro-differential equation without memory. In the process, we establish some important properties of the resolvent family. Subsequently, we develop approximate controllability results for a linear control problem by constructing a linear-quadratic regulator problem. This involves establishing the existence of an optimal pair and determining the expression of the optimal control that produces the approximate controllability of the linear system. Furthermore, we deduce sufficient conditions for the existence of a mild solution and approximate controllability of a semilinear system in a reflexive Banach space with a uniformly convex dual. Additionally, we delve into the discussion of approximate controllability for a semilinear problem in general Banach space, assuming a Lipschitz type condition on the nonlinear term. Finally, we implement our findings to examine the approximate controllability of certain partial differential equations, demonstrating their practical relevance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07886v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumit Arora, Akambadath Nandakumaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian anti-de Sitter plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a two-dimensional Lorentzian problem on the anti-de Sitter plane. Using methods of geometric control theory and differential geometry, it was possible to construct an orthonormal frame, calculate extremal trajectories, describe the reachable set, construct an optimal synthesis, and describe the Lorentzian distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07172v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Z. Ali, Yu. L. Sachkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliced Wasserstein Geodesics and Equivalence Wasserstein and Sliced Wasserstein metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper will introduce a family of sliced Wasserstein geodesics which are not standard Wasserstein geodesics, objects yet to be discovered in the literature. These objects exhibit how the geometric structure of the Sliced Wasserstein space differs from the Wasserstein space, and provides a simple example of how solving the barycenter and gradient flow problems change when moving between these metrics. Some of these geodesics will only be H\"older continuous with respect to the Wasserstein metric and thus will provide a direct proof that Sliced-Wasserstein and regular Wasserstein metrics are not equivalent. Previous proofs of this were done for various cases in [2] and [5]. This paper, not only provides a direct proof, but also fills in gaps showing these metrics not equivalent in dimensions greater than 2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07219v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Seale Hopper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Sensor and Actuator Selection for Factored Markov Decision Processes: Complexity, Approximability and Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Factored Markov Decision Processes (fMDPs) are a class of Markov Decision Processes (MDPs) in which the states (and actions) can be factored into a set of state (and action) variables. The state space, action space and reward function of a fMDP can be encoded compactly using a factored representation. In this paper, we consider the setting where we have a set of potential sensors to select for the fMDP (at design-time), where each sensor measures a certain state variable and has a selection cost. We formulate the problem of selecting an optimal set of sensors for fMDPs (subject to certain budget constraints) to maximize the expected infinite-horizon discounted return provided by the optimal control policy. We show the fundamental result that it is NP-hard to approximate this optimization problem to within any non-trivial factor. We then study the dual problem of budgeted actuator selection (at design-time) to maximize the expected return under the optimal policy. Again, we show that it is NP-hard to approximate this optimization problem to within any non-trivial factor. Furthermore, with explicit examples, we show the failure of greedy algorithms for both the sensor and actuator selection problems and provide insights into the factors that cause these problems to be challenging. Despite the inapproximability results, through extensive simulations, we show that the greedy algorithm may provide near-optimal performance for actuator and sensor selection in many real-world and randomly generated fMDP instances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07310v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jayanth Bhargav, Mahsa Ghasemi, Shreyas Sundaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Revenue Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a data-driven problem pricing problem in which a seller offers a price for a single item based on demand observed at a small finite number of historical prices. Our goal is to derive precise evaluation procedures of the value of the historical information gathered by the seller, along with prescriptions for more efficient price experimentation. Our main methodological result is an exact characterization of the maximin ratio (defined as the worst-case revenue garnered by a seller who only relies on past data divided by the optimal revenue achievable with full knowledge of the distribution of values). This result allows to measure the value of any historical data consisting of prices and corresponding conversion rates. We leverage this central reduction to provide new insights about price experimentation. Motivated by practical constraints that impede the seller from changing prices abruptly, we first illustrate our framework by evaluating the value of local information and show that the mere sign of the gradient may sometimes provide significant information to the seller. We then showcase how our framework can be used to run efficient price experiments. On the one hand, we develop a method to select the next price experiment that the seller should use to maximize the information obtained. On the other hand, we demonstrate that our result allows to considerably reduce the price experimentation needed to reach preset revenue guarantees through dynamic pricing algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07316v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achraf Bahamou, Omar Besbes, Omar Mouchtaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Note on the Basic Properties of Subgaussian Random Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This note provides a basic description of subgaussianity, by defining $(\sigma, \rho)$-subgaussian random variables $X$ ($\sigma&gt;0, \rho&gt;0$) as those satisfying $\mathbb{E}(\exp(\lambda X))\leq \rho\exp(\frac{1}{2}\sigma^2\lambda^2)$ for any $\lambda\in\mathbb{R}$. The introduction of the parameter $\rho$ may be particularly useful for those seeking to refine bounds, or align results from different sources, in the analysis of stochastic processes and concentration inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07348v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian problems on the Heisenberg group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07379v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two left-invariant Lorentzian problems on the Heisenberg group are considered. The Pontryagin maximum principle was applied to both problems and a parameterization of abnormal and normal extremal trajectories was obtained. Reachability sets and the existence of optimal trajectories are investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07379v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. A. Galyaev, Yu. L. Sachkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alternating Subspace Approximate Message Passing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Numerous renowned algorithms for tackling the compressed sensing problem employ an alternating strategy, which typically involves data matching in one module and denoising in another. Based on an in-depth analysis of the connection between the message passing and operator splitting, we present a novel approach, the Alternating Subspace Method (ASM), which intuitively combines the principles of the greedy methods (e.g., the orthogonal matching pursuit type methods) and the splitting methods (e.g., the approximate message passing type methods). Essentially, ASM modifies the splitting method by achieving fidelity in a subspace-restricted fashion. We reveal that such confining strategy still yields a consistent fixed point iteration and establish its local geometric convergence on the lasso problem. Numerical experiments on both the lasso and channel estimation problems demonstrate its high convergence rate and its capacity to incorporate different prior distributions. Further theoretical analysis also demonstrates the advantage of the motivated message-passing splitting by incorporating quasi-variance degree of freedom even for the classical lasso optimization problem. Overall, the proposed method is promising in efficiency, accuracy and flexibility, which has the potential to be competitive in different sparse recovery applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07436v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Zhu, Yufei Ma, Xiaoguang Li, Tiejun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pessimism Meets Risk: Risk-Sensitive Offline Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07631v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study risk-sensitive reinforcement learning (RL), a crucial field due to its ability to enhance decision-making in scenarios where it is essential to manage uncertainty and minimize potential adverse outcomes. Particularly, our work focuses on applying the entropic risk measure to RL problems. While existing literature primarily investigates the online setting, there remains a large gap in understanding how to efficiently derive a near-optimal policy based on this risk measure using only a pre-collected dataset. We center on the linear Markov Decision Process (MDP) setting, a well-regarded theoretical framework that has yet to be examined from a risk-sensitive standpoint. In response, we introduce two provably sample-efficient algorithms. We begin by presenting a risk-sensitive pessimistic value iteration algorithm, offering a tight analysis by leveraging the structure of the risk-sensitive performance measure. To further improve the obtained bounds, we propose another pessimistic algorithm that utilizes variance information and reference-advantage decomposition, effectively improving both the dependence on the space dimension $d$ and the risk-sensitivity factor. To the best of our knowledge, we obtain the first provably efficient risk-sensitive offline RL algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07631v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dake Zhang, Boxiang Lyu, Shuang Qiu, Mladen Kolar, Tong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APTAS for bin packing with general cost structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the following generalization of the bin packing problem. We are given a set of items each of which is associated with a rational size in the interval [0,1], and a monotone non-decreasing non-negative cost function f defined over the cardinalities of the subsets of items. A feasible solution is a partition of the set of items into bins subject to the constraint that the total size of items in every bin is at most 1. Unlike bin packing, the goal function is to minimize the total cost of the bins where the cost of a bin is the value of f applied on the cardinality of the subset of items packed into the bin. We present an APTAS for this strongly NP-hard problem. We also provide a complete complexity classification of the problem with respect to the choice of f.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07677v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Jaykrishnan, Asaf Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Projected Subspace Pursuit for Block Sparse Signal Reconstruction: Convergence Analysis and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07707v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a convergence analysis of the Group Projected Subspace Pursuit (GPSP) algorithm proposed by He et al. [HKL+23] (Group Projected subspace pursuit for IDENTification of variable coefficient differential equations (GP-IDENT), Journal of Computational Physics, 494, 112526) and extend its application to general tasks of block sparse signal recovery. We prove that when the sampling matrix satisfies the Block Restricted Isometry Property (BRIP) with a sufficiently small Block Restricted Isometry Constant (BRIC), GPSP exactly recovers the true block sparse signals. When the observations are noisy, this convergence property of GPSP remains valid if the magnitude of true signal is sufficiently large. GPSP selects the features by subspace projection criterion (SPC) for candidate inclusion and response magnitude criterion (RMC) for candidate exclusion. We compare these criteria with counterparts of other state-of-the-art greedy algorithms. Our theoretical analysis and numerical ablation studies reveal that SPC is critical to the superior performances of GPSP, and that RMC can enhance the robustness of feature identification when observations contain noises. We test and compare GPSP with other methods in diverse settings, including heterogeneous random block matrices, inexact observations, face recognition, and PDE identification. We find that GPSP outperforms the other algorithms in most cases for various levels of block sparsity and block sizes, justifying its effectiveness for general applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07707v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roy Y. He, Haixia Liu, Hao L\'iu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Measure Transport and Neural PDE Solvers for Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The task of sampling from a probability density can be approached as transporting a tractable density function to the target, known as dynamical measure transport. In this work, we tackle it through a principled unified framework using deterministic or stochastic evolutions described by partial differential equations (PDEs). This framework incorporates prior trajectory-based sampling methods, such as diffusion models or Schr\"odinger bridges, without relying on the concept of time-reversals. Moreover, it allows us to propose novel numerical methods for solving the transport task and thus sampling from complicated targets without the need for the normalization constant or data samples. We employ physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) to approximate the respective PDE solutions, implying both conceptional and computational advantages. In particular, PINNs allow for simulation- and discretization-free optimization and can be trained very efficiently, leading to significantly better mode coverage in the sampling task compared to alternative methods. Moreover, they can readily be fine-tuned with Gauss-Newton methods to achieve high accuracy in sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07873v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingtong Sun, Julius Berner, Lorenz Richter, Marius Zeinhofer, Johannes M\"uller, Kamyar Azizzadenesheli, Anima Anandkumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Computing Budget Allocation for Data-driven Ranking and Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.11809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.11809v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a fixed budget ranking and Selection (R&amp;S) problem, one aims to identify the best design among a finite number of candidates by efficiently allocating the given computing budget to evaluate design performance. Classical methods for R&amp;S usually assume the distribution of the randomness in the system is exactly known. In this paper, we consider the practical scenario where the true distribution is unknown but can be estimated from streaming input data that arrive in batches over time. We formulate the R&amp;S problem in this dynamic setting as a multi-stage problem, where we adopt the Bayesian approach to estimate the distribution and formulate a stage-wise optimization problem to allocate the computing budget. We characterize the optimality conditions for the stage-wise problem by applying the large deviations theory to maximize the decay rate of probability of false selection. Based on the optimality conditions and combined with the updating of distribution estimates, we design two sequential budget allocation procedures for R&amp;S under streaming input data. We theoretically guarantee the consistency and asymptotic optimality of the proposed procedures. We demonstrate the practical efficiency through numerical experiments in comparison with the equal allocation policy and an extension of the Optimal Computing Budget Allocation algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.11809v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Wang, Enlu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generalization of the Riccati Recursion for Equality-Constrained Linear Quadratic Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.14836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.14836v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a generalization of the well-known Riccati recursion for solving the discrete-time equality-constrained linear quadratic optimal control problem. The recursion can be used to compute the solutions as well as optimal feedback control policies. Unlike other tailored approaches for this problem class, the proposed method does not require restrictive regularity conditions on the problem. This allows its use in nonlinear optimal control problem solvers that use exact Lagrangian Hessian information. We demonstrate that our approach can be implemented in a highly efficient algorithm that scales linearly with the horizon length. Numerical tests show a significant speed-up of up to two orders of magnitude with respect to state-of-the-art general-purpose sparse linear solvers. Based on the proposed approach, faster nonlinear optimal control problem solvers can be developed that are suitable for more complex applications or for implementations on low-cost or low-power computational platforms. The implementation of the proposed algorithm is made available as open-source software.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.14836v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lander Vanroye, Joris De Schutter, Wilm Decr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear-quadratic optimal control for abstract differential-algebraic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend a classical approach to linear quadratic (LQ) optimal control via Popov operators to abstract linear differential-algebraic equations (ADAEs) in Hilbert spaces. To ensure existence of solutions, we assume that the underlying differential-algebraic equation has index one in the pseudo-resolvent sense. This leads to the existence of a degenerate semigroup that can be used to define a Popov operator for our system. It is shown that under a suitable coercivity assumption for the Popov operator the optimal costs can be described by a bounded Riccati operator and that the optimal control input is of feedback form. Furthermore, we characterize exponential stability of ADAEs which is required to solve the infinite horizon LQ problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08762v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannes Gernandt, Timo Reis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence analysis of a regularized Newton method with generalized regularization terms for convex optimization problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09786v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a regularized Newton method (RNM) with generalized regularization terms for unconstrained convex optimization problems. The generalized regularization includes quadratic, cubic, and elastic net regularizations as special cases. Therefore, the proposed method serves as a general framework that includes not only the classical and cubic RNMs but also a novel RNM with elastic net regularization. We show that the proposed RNM has the global $\mathcal{O}(k^{-2})$ and local superlinear convergence, which are the same as those of the cubic RNM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09786v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuya Yamakawa, Nobuo Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation of shape optimization problems with non-smooth PDE constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with a shape optimization problem governed by a non-smooth PDE, i.e., the nonlinearity in the state equation is not necessarily differentiable. We follow the functional variational approach of [36] where the set of admissible shapes is parametrized by a large class of continuous mappings. This methodology allows for both boundary and topological variations. It has the advantage that one can rewrite the shape optimization problem as a control problem in a function space. To overcome the lack of convexity of the set of admissible controls, we provide an essential density property. This permits us to show that each parametrization associated to the optimal shape is the limit of global optima of non-smooth distributed optimal control problems. The admissible set of the approximating minimization problems is a convex subset of a Hilbert space of functions. Moreover, its structure is such that one can derive strong stationary optimality conditions [5]. This opens the door to future research concerning sharp first-order necessary optimality conditions in form of a qualified optimality system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15146v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Livia Betz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abide by the Law and Follow the Flow: Conservation Laws for Gradient Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00144v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the geometric properties of gradient descent dynamics is a key ingredient in deciphering the recent success of very large machine learning models. A striking observation is that trained over-parameterized models retain some properties of the optimization initialization. This "implicit bias" is believed to be responsible for some favorable properties of the trained models and could explain their good generalization properties. The purpose of this article is threefold. First, we rigorously expose the definition and basic properties of "conservation laws", that define quantities conserved during gradient flows of a given model (e.g. of a ReLU network with a given architecture) with any training data and any loss. Then we explain how to find the maximal number of independent conservation laws by performing finite-dimensional algebraic manipulations on the Lie algebra generated by the Jacobian of the model. Finally, we provide algorithms to: a) compute a family of polynomial laws; b) compute the maximal number of (not necessarily polynomial) independent conservation laws. We provide showcase examples that we fully work out theoretically. Besides, applying the two algorithms confirms for a number of ReLU network architectures that all known laws are recovered by the algorithm, and that there are no other independent laws. Such computational tools pave the way to understanding desirable properties of optimization initialization in large machine learning models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00144v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sibylle Marcotte, R\'emi Gribonval, Gabriel Peyr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IRKA is a Riemannian Gradient Descent Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02031v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The iterative rational Krylov algorithm (IRKA) is a commonly used fixed-point iteration developed to minimize the $\mathcal{H}_2$ model order reduction error. In this work, IRKA is recast as a Riemannian gradient descent method with a fixed step size over the manifold of rational functions having fixed degree. This interpretation motivates the development of a Riemannian gradient descent method utilizing as a natural extension variable step size and line search. Comparisons made between IRKA and this extension on a few examples demonstrate significant benefits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02031v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petar Mlinari\'c, Christopher A. Beattie, Zlatko Drma\v{c}, Serkan Gugercin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Decentralized Market Mechanism for Energy Communities under Operating Envelopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17201v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an operating envelopes (OEs) aware energy community market mechanism that dynamically charges/rewards its members based on two-part pricing. The OEs are imposed exogenously by a regulated distribution system operator (DSO) on the energy community's revenue meter and is subject to a generalized net energy metering (NEM) tariff design. By formulating the interaction of the community operator and its members as a Stackelberg game, we show that the proposed two-part pricing achieves a Nash equilibrium and maximizes the community's social welfare in a decentralized fashion while ensuring that the community's operation abides by the OEs. The market mechanism conforms with the cost-causation principle and guarantees community members a surplus level no less than their maximum surplus when they autonomously face the DSO. The dynamic and uniform community price is a monotonically decreasing function of the community's aggregate renewable generation. We also analyze the impact of exogenous parameters such as NEM rates and OEs on the value of joining the community. Lastly, through numerical studies, we showcase the community's welfare, and pricing, and compare its members' surplus to customers under the DSO's regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17201v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed S. Alahmed, Guido Cavraro, Andrey Bernstein, Lang Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
