<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative results on a generalized viscosity approximation method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study, in a nonlinear setting, the asymptotic behaviour of a generalized viscosity approximation method associated with a countable family of nonexpansive mappings satisfying resolvent-like conditions. We apply proof mining methods to obtain quantitative results on asymptotic regularity in W-hyperbolic spaces and rates of metastability in CAT(0) spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09968v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo Firmino, Laurentiu Leustean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast projection onto the top-k-sum constraint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops an efficient algorithm for computing the Euclidean projection onto the top-k-sum constraint, a key operation in financial risk management and matrix optimization problems. Existing projection methods rely on sorting and therefore incur an initial O(nlogn) complexity, which limits their scalability in high-dimensional settings. To address this difficulty, we revisit the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions of the projection problem and introduce relaxed conditions that remain sufficient for characterizing the solution. These conditions lead to a simple geometric interpretation: finding the solutions is equivalent to locating the intersection of two monotone piecewise linear functions. Building on this insight, we propose an iterative and highly efficient algorithm that searches directly for the intersection point and completely avoids all sorting procedures. We prove that the algorithm converges globally and reaches the exact solution in a finite number of iterations. Extensive numerical experiments further demonstrate that the proposed algorithm substantially outperforms existing algorithms and exhibits empirical O(n) complexity across a broad range of problem instances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10255v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianting Pan, Ming Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimality Deviation using the Koopman Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the impact of approximation error in data-driven optimal control problem of nonlinear systems while using the Koopman operator. While the Koopman operator enables a simplified representation of nonlinear dynamics through a lifted state space, the presence of approximation error inevitably leads to deviations in the computed optimal controller and the resulting value function. We derive explicit upper bounds for these optimality deviations, which characterize the worst-case effect of approximation error. Supported by numerical examples, these theoretical findings provide a quantitative foundation for improving the robustness of data-driven optimal controller design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10270v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Lin, Bingxian Wu, Nan Bai, Yunxiao Ren, Zhisheng Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual subspace evolution strategies for nonlinear inverse problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonlinear inverse problems often feature noisy, non-differentiable, or expensive residual evaluations that make Jacobian-based solvers unreliable. Popular derivative-free optimizers such as natural evolution strategies (NES) or Powell's NEWUOA still assume smoothness or expend many evaluations to maintain stability. Ensemble Kalman inversion (EKI) relies on empirical covariances that require preconditioning and scale poorly with residual dimension.
  We introduce residual subspace evolution strategies (RSES), a derivative-free solver that samples Gaussian probes around the current iterate, builds a residual-only surrogate from their differences, and recombines the probes through a least-squares solve yielding an optimal update without forming Jacobians or covariances. Each iteration costs $k+1$ residual evaluations, where $k \ll n$ for $n$-dimensional problems, with $O(k^3)$ linear algebra overhead.
  Benchmarks on calibration, regression, and deconvolution problems demonstrate consistent misfit reduction in both deterministic and stochastic settings. RSES matches or surpasses xNES and NEWUOA while staying competitive with EKI under matched evaluation budgets, particularly when smoothness or covariance assumptions fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10325v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Alemanno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primal-dual splitting for structured composite monotone inclusions with or without cocoercivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a primal-dual splitting algorithm for a broad class of structured composite monotone inclusions that involve finitely many set-valued operators, compositions of set-valued operators with bounded linear operators, and single-valued operators possibly without cocoercivity. The proposed algorithm is not only a unification for several contemporary algorithms but also a blueprint to generate new algorithms with graph-based structures. Our approach reduces dimensionality compared with the standard product space technique, which typically reformulates the original problem as the sum of two maximally monotone operators in order to apply splitting methods. It accommodates different cocoercive or Lipschitz constants as well as different resolvent parameters, and yields a larger allowable step-size range than in product space reformulations. We demonstrate the practicality of the approach by a numerical experiment on the decentralized fused lasso problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10366v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minh N. Dao, Hung M. Phan, Matthew K. Tam, Thang D. Truong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Objective Coefficient Rounding and Almost Symmetries in Binary Programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article investigates the interplay of rounding objective coefficients in binary programs and almost symmetries. Empirically, reducing the number of significant bits through rounding often leads to instances that are easier to solve. One reason can be that the amount of symmetries increases, which enables solvers to be more effective when they are exploited. This can signify that the original instance contains 'almost symmetries'. Furthermore, solving the rounded problems provides approximations to the original objective values. We empirically investigate these relations on instances of the capacitated facility location problem, the knapsack problem and a diverse collection of additional instances, using the solvers SCIP and CP-SAT. For all investigated problem classes, we show empirically that this yields faster algorithms with guaranteed solution quality. The influence of symmetry depends on the instance type and solver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10507v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Kuzinowicz, Pawe{\l} Lichocki, Gioni Mexi, Marc E. Pfetsch, Sebastian Pokutta, Max Zimmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Quadratic Regulators: A New Look</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linear time-invariant control systems can be considered as finitely generated modules over the commutative principal ideal ring $\mathbb{R}[\frac{d}{dt}]$ of linear differential operators with respect to the time derivative. The Kalman controllability in this algebraic language is translated as the freeness of the system module. Linear quadratic regulators rely on quadratic Lagrangians, or cost functions. Any flat output, i.e., any basis of the corresponding free module leads to an open-loop control strategy via an Euler-Lagrange equation, which becomes here a linear ordinary differential equation with constant coefficients. In this approach, the two-point boundary value problem, including the control variables, becomes tractable. It yields notions of optimal time horizon, optimal parameter design and optimal rest-to-rest trajectories. The loop is closed via an intelligent controller derived from model-free control, which is known to exhibit excellent performance concerning model mismatches and disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10641v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'eEdric Join, Emmanuel Delaveau, Michel Fliess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Global Convergence of the Consensus-Based Optimization Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consensus-based optimization (CBO) is a multi-agent metaheuristic derivative-free optimization algorithm that has proven to be capable of globally minimizing nonconvex nonsmooth functions across a diverse range of applications while being amenable to theoretical analysis. The method leverages an interplay between exploration of the energy landscape of the objective function through a system of interacting particles subject to stochasticity and exploitation of the particles' positions through the computation of a global consensus about the location of the minimizer based on the Laplace principle. In this paper, we prove strong mean square convergence of the practical numerical time-discrete CBO algorithm to the global minimizer for a rich class of objective functions. For CBO with both isotropic and anisotropic diffusion, our convergence result features conditions on the choice of the hyperparameters as well as explicit rates of convergence in the time discretization step size $\Delta t$ and the number of particles $N$. By interpreting the time-discrete algorithm at the continuous-time level through a system of stochastic differential equations (SDEs), our proof strategy combines traditional finite-time convergence theory for numerical methods applied to SDEs with careful considerations due to the fact that the CBO coefficients do not satisfy a global Lipschitz condition. To accomodate the latter, we adopt a recently proposed generalization of Sznitman's classical argument, which allows to discard an event of small probability, controllable through fine moment estimates for the particle systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10654v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabrina Bonandin, Konstantin Riedl, Sara Veneruso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Convergence Analysis of an Inexact Preconditioned Stochastic Model-Based Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on investigating an inexact stochastic model-based optimization algorithm that integrates preconditioning techniques for solving stochastic composite optimization problems. The proposed framework unifies and extends the fixed-metric stochastic model-based algorithm to its preconditioned and inexact variants. Convergence guarantees are established under mild assumptions for both weakly convex and convex settings, without requiring smoothness or global Lipschitz continuity of the objective function. By assuming a local Lipschitz condition, we derive nonasymptotic and asymptotic convergence rates measured by the gradient of the Moreau envelope. Furthermore, convergence rates in terms of the distance to the optimal solution set are obtained under an additional quadratic growth condition on the objective function. Numerical experiment results demonstrate the theoretical findings for the proposed algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10826v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenglong Bao, Yancheng Yuan, Shulan Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indirect methods in optimal control on Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work focuses on indirect descent methods for optimal control problems governed by nonlinear ordinary differential equations in Banach spaces, viewed as abstract models of distributed dynamics. As a reference line, we revisit the classical schemes, rooted in Pontryagin's maximum principle, and highlight their sensitivity to local convexity and lack of monotone convergence. We then develop an alternative method based on exact cost-increment formulas and finite-difference probes of the terminal cost. We show that our method exhibits stable monotone convergence in numerical analysis of an Amari-type neural field control problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10831v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Chertovskih, Nikolay Pogodaev, Maxim Staritsyn, A. Pedro Aguiar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Decompositions of Controllability Gramian and Its Inverse based on System Eigenvalues in Companion Form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controllability and observability Gramians, along with their inverses, are widely used to solve various problems in control theory. This paper proposes spectral decompositions of the controllability Gramian and its inverse based on system eigenvalues for a continuous LTI dynamical system in the controllability canonical (companion) form. The Gramian and its inverse are represented as sums of Hermitian matrices, each corresponding to individual system eigenvalues or their pairwise combinations. These decompositions are obtained for the solutions of both algebraic and differential Lyapunov and Riccati equations with arbitrary initial conditions, allowing for the estimation of system spectral properties over an arbitrary time interval and their prediction at future moments. The derived decompositions are also generalized to the case of multiple eigenvalues in the dynamics matrix spectrum, enabling a closed-form estimation of the effects of resonant interactions with the system's eigenmodes. The spectral components are interpreted as measurable quantities in the minimum energy control problem. Therefore, they are unambiguously defined and can quantitatively characterize the influence of individual eigenmodes and associated system devices on controllability, observability, and the asymptotic dynamics of perturbation energy. The additional information obtained from these decompositions can improve the accuracy of algorithms in solving various practical problems, such as stability analysis, minimum energy control, structural design, tuning regulators, optimal placement of actuators and sensors, network analysis, and model order reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10851v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Iskakov, Igor Yadykin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Regret Optimal Control Under Moment-Based Ambiguity Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a class of finite-horizon, linear-quadratic stochastic control problems, where the probability distribution governing the noise process is unknown but assumed to belong to an ambiguity set consisting of all distributions whose mean and covariance lie within norm balls centered at given nominal values. To address the distributional ambiguity, we explore the design of causal affine control policies to minimize the worst-case expected regret over all distributions in the given ambiguity set. The resulting minimax optimal control problem is shown to admit an equivalent reformulation as a tractable convex program that corresponds to a regularized version of the nominal linear-quadratic stochastic control problem. While this convex program can be recast as a semidefinite program, semidefinite programs are typically solved using primal-dual interior point methods that scale poorly with the problem size in practice. To address this limitation, we propose a scalable dual projected subgradient method to compute optimal controllers to an arbitrary accuracy. Numerical experiments are presented to benchmark the proposed method against state-of-the-art data-driven and distributionally robust control design approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10906v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feras Al Taha, Eilyan Bitar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient projection method and stochastic search for some optimal control models with spin chains. I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article (I) considers the known optimal control model of a quantum information transfer along a spin chain with controlled external parabolic magnetic field, with an arbitrary length. The article adds certain lower and upper pointwise constraints on controls, adds the problem of keeping the signal at the last spin, considers various classes of controls. For these problems under piecewise continuous controls, the projection-type linearized Pontryagin maximum principle, gradient projection method's constructions in its one- and two- and three-step forms were adapted by analogy with [Morzhin O.V., Pechen A.N. J. Phys. A: Math. Theor., 2025]. Moreover, an example with a genetic algorithm's successful use under a special class of controls is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10093v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg V. Morzhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Moroccan Public Procurement Game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the public procurement market through the lens of game theory by modeling it as a strategic game with discontinuous and non-quasiconcave payoffs. We first show that the game admits no Nash equilibrium in pure strategies. We then analyze the two-player case and derive two explicit mixed-strategy equilibria for the symmetric game and for the weighted $(p,1-p)$ formulation. Finally, we establish the existence of a symmetric Nash equilibrium in the general $N$-player case by applying the diagonal disjoint payoff matching condition, which allows us to extend equilibrium existence to the mixed-strategy setting despite payoff discontinuities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10109v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nizar Riane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit Control Barrier Function-based Safety Filters and their Resource-Aware Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10118v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the efficient implementation of safety filters that are designed using control barrier functions (CBFs), which minimally modify a nominal controller to render it safe with respect to a prescribed set of states. Although CBF-based safety filters are often implemented by solving a quadratic program (QP) in real time, the use of off-the-shelf solvers for such optimization problems poses a challenge in applications where control actions need to be computed efficiently at very high frequencies. In this paper, we introduce a closed-form expression for controllers obtained through CBF-based safety filters. This expression is obtained by partitioning the state-space into different regions, with a different closed-form solution in each region. We leverage this formula to introduce a resource-aware implementation of CBF-based safety filters that detects changes in the partition region and uses the closed-form expression between changes. We showcase the applicability of our approach in examples ranging from aerospace control to safe reinforcement learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10118v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pol Mestres, Shima Sadat Mousavi, Pio Ong, Lizhi Yang, Ersin Das, Joel W. Burdick, Aaron D. Ames</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient projection method and stochastic search for some optimal control models with spin chains. II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article (II) continues the research described in [Morzhin O.V. Gradient projection method and stochastic search for some optimal control models with spin chains. I (submitted)] (Article I), derives the needed finite-dimensional gradients corresponding to the infinite-dimensional gradients obtained in Article I, both for transfer and keeping problems at a certain $N$-dimensional spin chain, and correspondingly adapts a projection-type condition for optimality, gradient projection method (GPM). For the case $N=3$, the given in this article examples together with Example 3 in Article I show that: a) the adapted GPM and genetic algorithm (GA) successfully solved numerically the considered transfer and keeping problems; b) the two- and three-step GPM forms significantly surpass the one-step GPM. Moreover, GA and a special class of controls were successfully used in such the transfer problem that $N=20$ and the final time is not assigned.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10290v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg V. Morzhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certifying Concavity and Monotonicity in Games via Sum-of-Squares Hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Concavity and its refinements underpin tractability in multiplayer games, where players independently choose actions to maximize their own payoffs which depend on other players' actions. In concave games, where players' strategy sets are compact and convex, and their payoffs are concave in their own actions, strong guarantees follow: Nash equilibria always exist and decentralized algorithms converge to equilibria. If the game is furthermore monotone, an even stronger guarantee holds: Nash equilibria are unique under strictness assumptions. Unfortunately, we show that certifying concavity or monotonicity is NP-hard, already for games where utilities are multivariate polynomials and compact, convex basic semialgebraic strategy sets -- an expressive class that captures extensive-form games with imperfect recall. On the positive side, we develop two hierarchies of sum-of-squares programs that certify concavity and monotonicity of a given game, and each level of the hierarchies can be solved in polynomial time. We show that almost all concave/monotone games are certified at some finite level of the hierarchies. Subsequently, we introduce SOS-concave/monotone games, which globally approximate concave/monotone games, and show that for any given game we can compute the closest SOS-concave/monotone game in polynomial time. Finally, we apply our techniques to canonical examples of imperfect recall extensive-form games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10292v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Leon, Iosif Sakos, Ryann Sim, Antonios Varvitsiotis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-SKM-Net: Trainable Neural Network Framework for Linear Constraint Satisfaction via Sampling Kaczmarz-Motzkin Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural network constraint satisfaction is crucial for safety-critical applications such as power system optimization, robotic path planning, and autonomous driving. However, existing constraint satisfaction methods face efficiency-applicability trade-offs, with hard constraint methods suffering from either high computational complexity or restrictive assumptions on constraint structures. The Sampling Kaczmarz-Motzkin (SKM) method is a randomized iterative algorithm for solving large-scale linear inequality systems with favorable convergence properties, but its argmax operations introduce non-differentiability, posing challenges for neural network applications. This work proposes the Trainable Sampling Kaczmarz-Motzkin Network (T-SKM-Net) framework and, for the first time, systematically integrates SKM-type methods into neural network constraint satisfaction. The framework transforms mixed constraint problems into pure inequality problems through null space transformation, employs SKM for iterative solving, and maps solutions back to the original constraint space, efficiently handling both equality and inequality constraints. We provide theoretical proof of post-processing effectiveness in expectation and end-to-end trainability guarantees based on unbiased gradient estimators, demonstrating that despite non-differentiable operations, the framework supports standard backpropagation. On the DCOPF case118 benchmark, our method achieves 4.27ms/item GPU serial forward inference with 0.0025% max optimality gap with post-processing mode and 5.25ms/item with 0.0008% max optimality gap with joint training mode, delivering over 25$\times$ speedup compared to the pandapower solver while maintaining zero constraint violations under given tolerance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10461v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Zhu, Yao Zhang, Jiashen Ren, Qingchun Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of multidimensional Simple Clock Auctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10614v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simple Clock Auctions (SCA) are a mechanism commonly used in spectrum auctions to sell lots of frequency bandwidths. We study such an auction with one player having access to perfect information against straightforward bidders. When the opponents' valuations satisfy the ordinary substitutes condition, we show that it is optimal to bid on a fixed lot overtime. In this setting, we consider a continuous-time version of the SCA auction in which the prices follow a differential inclusion with a piecewise-constant dynamics. We show that there exists a unique solution in the sense of Filippov. This guarantees that the continuous-time model coincides with the limit of the discrete-time auction when price increments tend to zero. Moreover, we show that the value function of this limit auction is piecewise linear (though possibly discontinuous). Finally, we illustrate these results by analyzing a simplified version of the multiband Australian spectrum auction of 2017.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10614v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jad Zeroual, Marianne Akian, Aur\'elien Bechler, Matthieu Chardy, St\'ephane Gaubert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Elementary Proof of the Near Optimality of LogSumExp Smoothing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10825v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the design of smoothings of the (coordinate-wise) max function in $\mathbb{R}^d$ in the infinity norm. The LogSumExp function $f(x)=\ln(\sum^d_i\exp(x_i))$ provides a classical smoothing, differing from the max function in value by at most $\ln(d)$. We provide an elementary construction of a lower bound, establishing that every overestimating smoothing of the max function must differ by at least $\sim 0.8145\ln(d)$. Hence, LogSumExp is optimal up to constant factors. However, in small dimensions, we provide stronger, exactly optimal smoothings attaining our lower bound, showing that the entropy-based LogSumExp approach to smoothing is not exactly optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10825v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thabo Samakhoana, Benjamin Grimmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multidimensional Sorting: Comparative Statics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10853v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In sorting literature, comparative statics for multidimensional assignment models with general output functions and input distributions is an important open question. We provide a complete theory of comparative statics for technological change in general multidimensional assignment models. Our main result is that any technological change is uniquely decomposed into two distinct components. The first component (gradient) gives a characterization of changes in marginal earnings through a Poisson equation. The second component (divergence-free) gives a characterization of labor reallocation. For U.S. data, we quantify equilibrium responses in sorting and earnings with respect to cognitive skill-biased technological change.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10853v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Job Boerma, Andrea Ottolini, Aleh Tsyvinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Representations and $H_{\infty}$-Optimal Control of Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.13104v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider $\hinf$-optimal state-feedback control of the class of linear Partial Differential Equations (PDEs) which admit a Partial Integral Equation (PIE) representation. While linear matrix inequalities are commonly used for optimal control of Ordinary Differential Equations (ODEs), the absence of a universal state-space representation and suitable dual form prevents such methods from being applied to optimal control of PDEs. Specifically, for ODEs, the controller synthesis problem is defined in state-space, and duality is used to resolve the bilinearity of that synthesis problem. Recently, the PIE representation was proposed as a universal state-space representation for linear PDE systems. In this paper, we show that any PDE system represented by a PIE admits a dual PIE with identical stability and I/O properties. This result allows us to reformulate the stabilizing and optimal state-feedback control problems as convex optimization over the cone of positive Partial Integral (PI) operators. Operator inversion formulae then allow us to construct feedback gains for the original PDE system. The results are verified through application to several canonical problems in optimal control of PDEs and indicate the resulting bounds on $\hinf$ norm are not conservative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.13104v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachin Shivakumar, Amritam Das, Matthew Peet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A global Barzilai and Borwein's gradient normalization descent method for multiobjective optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05070v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the unconstrained multiobjective optimization problem. In recent years, researchers pointed out that the steepest decent method may generate small stepsize which leads to slow convergence rates. To address the issue, we propose a global Barzilai and Borwein's gradient normalization descent method for multiobjective optimization (GBBN). In our method, we propose a new normalization technique to generate new descent direction. We demonstrate that line search can achieve better stepsize along the descent direction. Furthermore, we prove the global convergence of accumulation points generated by GBBN as Pareto critical points and establish a linear rate of convergence under reasonable assumptions. Finally, we evaluated the effectiveness of the proposed GBBN method based on the quality of the approximated Pareto frontier and computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05070v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingxue Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the risk levels of distributionally robust chance constrained problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01177v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss the utilization of perturbed risk levels (PRLs) for the solution of chance-constrained problems via sampling-based approaches. PRLs allow the consideration of distributional ambiguity by rescaling the risk level of the nominal chance constraint. Explicit expressions of the PRL exist for some discrepancy-based ambiguity sets.
  We propose a discrepancy functional not included in previous comparisons of different PRLs based on the likelihood ratio, which we term ,,relative variation distance" (RVD). If the ambiguity set can be described by the RVD, the rescaling of the risk level with the PRL is in contrast to other discrepancy functionals possible even for very low risk levels. We derive distributionally robust one- and two-level guarantees for the solution of chance-constrained problems with randomized methods. We demonstrate the viability of the derived guarantees for a randomized MPC under distributional ambiguity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01177v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moritz Heinlein, Teodoro Alamo, Sergio Lucia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non Null-Controllability Properties of the Grushin-Like Heat Equation on 2D-Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the internal non null-controllability properties of the heat equation on 2-dimensional almost-Riemannian manifolds with an interior singularity, and under the assumption that the closure of the control zone does not contain the whole singularity. We show that if locally, around the singularity, the sub-Riemannian metric can be written in a Grushin form, or equivalently the sub-Laplacian writes as a generalized Grushin operator, then, achieving null-controllability requires at least a minimal amount of time. As locally the manifold looks like a rectangular domain, we consequently focus ourselves on the non null-controllability properties of the generalized Grushin-like heat equation on various Euclidean domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00997v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Vanlaere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moreau envelope and proximal-point methods under the lens of high-order regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to investigating the fundamental properties of the high-order proximal operator (HOPE) and the high-order Moreau envelope (HOME) in the nonconvex setting, where the quadratic regularization ($p=2$) is replaced by a $p$-order regularizer with $p &gt; 1$. After establishing several basic properties of HOPE and HOME, we study the differentiability and weak smoothness of HOME under $q$-prox-regularity with $q \geq 2$ and $p$-calmness for $p \in (1,2]$ and $2 \leq p \leq q$. Furthermore, we propose a high-order proximal-point algorithm (HiPPA) and analyze the convergence of the generated sequence to proximal fixed points. Our results pave the way for the development of a high-order smoothing theory with $p&gt;1$ that can lead to new algorithmic advances in the nonconvex setting. To illustrate this potential for nonsmooth and nonconvex optimization, we apply HiPPA to the Nesterov-Chebyshev-Rosenbrock functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04577v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alireza Kabgani, Masoud Ahookhosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average Optimal Control of Uncertain Control-Affine Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06204v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work studies optimal control problems of systems with uncertain, probabilistically distributed parameters to optimize average performance. Known as Riemann-Stieltjes, average, or ensemble optimal control, this kind of problem is crucial when parameter uncertainty matters. We derive necessary optimality conditions and characterize feedback controls for control-affine systems. Two scenarios are examined: known initial conditions (finite-dimensional case) and uncertain initial conditions (infinite-dimensional framework). The Pontryagin Maximum Principle is extended using a Hilbert space formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06204v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11228-025-00784-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Set-Valued Variational Analysis 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Soledad Aronna, Gabriel de Lima Monteiro, Oscar Sierra Fonseca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-Duration Station-Keeping Strategy for Cislunar Spacecraft Formations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19620v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates a novel guidance and control strategy for cislunar near-rectilinear halo orbit formation-keeping applied to high-fidelity dynamics. Bounded relative motion is constructed about long-duration ephemeris trajectories with osculating invariant circles to form quasi-periodic relative orbits. State-of-the-art absolute control strategies are paired with a simple and effective relative control feedback law. Finally, a control barrier function is implemented to ensure recursively passively-safe bounded relative motion under feedback in the presence of possible missed maneuver events for the duration of the formation flight. The strategy is verified in high-fidelity simulation environments through Monte Carlo trials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19620v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Foss, Yuji Takubo, Simone D'Amico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bellman Optimality of Average-Reward Robust Markov Decision Processes with a Constant Gain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14203v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Learning and optimal control under robust Markov decision processes (MDPs) have received increasing attention, yet most existing theory, algorithms, and applications focus on finite-horizon or discounted models. Long-run average-reward formulations, while natural in many operations research and management contexts, remain underexplored. This is primarily because the dynamic programming foundations are technically challenging and only partially understood, with several fundamental questions remaining open. This paper steps toward a general framework for average-reward robust MDPs by analyzing the constant-gain setting. We study the average-reward robust control problem with possible information asymmetries between the controller and an S-rectangular adversary. Our analysis centers on the constant-gain robust Bellman equation, examining both the existence of solutions and their relationship to the optimal average reward. Specifically, we identify when solutions to the robust Bellman equation characterize the optimal average reward and stationary policies, and we provide one-sided weak communication conditions ensuring solutions' existence. These findings expand the dynamic programming theory for average-reward robust MDPs and lay a foundation for robust dynamic decision making under long-run average criteria in operational environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14203v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengbo Wang, Nian Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending Douglas-Rachford Splitting for Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19637v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Douglas-Rachford splitting method is a classical and widely used algorithm for solving monotone inclusions involving the sum of two maximally monotone operators. It was recently shown to be the unique frugal, no-lifting resolvent-splitting method that is unconditionally convergent in the general two-operator setting. In this work, we show that this uniqueness does not hold in the convex optimization case: when the operators are subdifferentials of proper, closed, convex functions, a strictly larger class of frugal, no-lifting resolvent-splitting methods is unconditionally convergent. We provide a complete characterization of all such methods in the convex optimization setting and prove that this characterization is sharp: unconditional convergence holds exactly on the identified parameter regions. These results immediately yield new families of convergent ADMM-type and Chambolle-Pock-type methods obtained through their Douglas-Rachford reformulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19637v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Nilsson, Anton {\AA}kerman, Pontus Giselsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational analysis of determinantal varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22613v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Determinantal varieties -- the sets of bounded-rank matrices or tensors -- have attracted growing interest in low-rank optimization. The tangent cone to low-rank sets is widely studied and underpins a range of geometric methods. The second-order geometry, which encodes curvature information, is more intricate. In this work, we develop a unified framework to derive explicit formulas for both first- and second-order tangent sets to various low-rank sets, including low-rank matrices, tensors, symmetric matrices, and positive semidefinite matrices. The framework also accommodates the intersection of a low-rank set and another set satisfying mild assumptions, thereby yielding a tangent intersection rule. Through the lens of tangent sets, we establish a necessary and sufficient condition under which a nonsmooth problem and its smooth parameterization share equivalent second-order stationary points. Moreover, we exploit tangent sets to characterize optimality conditions for low-rank optimization and prove that verifying second-order optimality is NP-hard. In a separate line of analysis, we investigate variational geometry of the graph of the normal cone to matrix varieties, deriving the explicit Bouligand tangent cone, Fr\'echet and Mordukhovich normal cones to the graph. These results are further applied to develop optimality conditions for low-rank bilevel programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22613v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Yang, Bin Gao, Ya-xiang Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Communication-Efficient Distributed Optimization Algorithm with Coupled Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02634v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper designs a communication-efficient distributed optimization algorithm for optimization problems subject to coupled equality constraints. By means of duality theory, the original problem is reformulated to tackle the coupled equality constraints. Furthermore, compressed communication is employed to enhance efficiency whereas introducing compression errors that degrade the performance. To address this, differential compression techniques with dynamic scaling factors are incorporated into the algorithm design. It is shown that the proposed distributed compressed algorithm achieves linear convergence under different compressors. Numerical results further demonstrate its robust performance under different types of compressors while satisfying the equality constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02634v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhu Duan, Ziwen Yang, Xiaoming Duan, Shanying Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sum of Squares Decompositions for Structured Biquadratic Forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02734v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies sum-of-squares (SOS) representations for structured biquadratic forms. We prove that diagonally dominated symmetric biquadratic tensors are always SOS. For the special case of symmetric biquadratic forms, we establish necessary and sufficient conditions for positive semi-definiteness of monic symmetric biquadratic forms, characterize the geometry of the corresponding PSD cone as a convex polyhedron, and prove that every such PSD form is SOS for any dimensions $m$ and $n$. We also formulate conjectures regarding SOS representations for symmetric M-biquadratic tensors and symmetric $\mathrm{B}_{0}$-biquadratic tensors, discussing their likelihood and potential proof strategies. Our results advance the understanding of when positive semi-definiteness implies sum-of-squares decompositions for structured biquadratic forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02734v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Xu, Chunfeng Cui, Liqun Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Smooth Approximation Framework for Weakly Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Standard complexity analyses for weakly convex optimization rely on the Moreau envelope technique proposed by Davis and Drusvyatskiy (2019). The main insight is that nonsmooth algorithms, such as proximal subgradient, proximal point, and their stochastic variants, implicitly minimize a smooth surrogate function induced by the Moreau envelope. Meanwhile, explicit smoothing, which directly minimizes a smooth approximation of the objective, has long been recognized as an efficient strategy for nonsmooth optimization. In this paper, we generalize the notion of smoothable functions, which was proposed by Beck and Teboulle (2012) for nonsmooth convex optimization. This generalization provides a unified viewpoint on several important smoothing techniques for weakly convex optimization, including Nesterov-type smoothing and Moreau envelope smoothing. Our theory yields a framework for designing smooth approximation algorithms for both deterministic and stochastic weakly convex problems with provable complexity guarantees. Furthermore, our theory extends to the smooth approximation of non-Lipschitz functions, allowing for complexity analysis even when global Lipschitz continuity does not hold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09720v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Deng, Wenzhi Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational structures for the Fokker--Planck equation with general Dirichlet boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07803v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the convergence of a modified Jordan--Kinderlehrer--Otto scheme to a solution to the Fokker--Planck equation in $\Omega \Subset \mathbb R^d$ with general -- strictly positive and temporally constant -- Dirichlet boundary conditions. We work under mild assumptions on the domain, the drift, and the initial datum.
  In the special case where $\Omega$ is an interval in $\mathbb R^1$, we prove that such a solution is a gradient flow -- curve of maximal slope -- within a suitable space of measures, endowed with a modified Wasserstein distance.
  Our discrete scheme and modified distance draw inspiration from contributions by A. Figalli and N. Gigli [J. Math. Pures Appl. 94, (2010), pp. 107--130], and J. Morales [J. Math. Pures Appl. 112, (2018), pp. 41--88] on an optimal-transport approach to evolution equations with Dirichlet boundary conditions. Similarly to these works, we allow the mass to flow from/to the boundary $\partial \Omega$ throughout the evolution. However, our leading idea is to also keep track of the mass at the boundary by working with measures defined on the whole closure $\overline \Omega$.
  The driving functional is a modification of the classical relative entropy that also makes use of the information at the boundary. As an intermediate result, when $\Omega$ is an interval in $\mathbb R^1$, we find a formula for the descending slope of this geodesically nonconvex functional.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07803v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00526-025-03193-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Calc. Var. 65, 23 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Quattrocchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant Test-Time Training with Operator Sketching for Imaging Inverse Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05771v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Equivariant Imaging (EI) regularization has become the de-facto technique for unsupervised training of deep imaging networks, without any need of ground-truth data. Observing that the EI-based unsupervised training paradigm currently has significant computational redundancy leading to inefficiency in high-dimensional applications, we propose a sketched EI regularization which leverages the randomized sketching techniques for acceleration. We apply our sketched EI regularization to develop an accelerated deep internal learning framework, which can be efficiently applied for test-time network adaptation. Additionally, for network adaptation tasks, we propose a parameter-efficient approach to accelerate both EI and Sketched-EI via optimizing only the normalization layers. Our numerical study on X-ray CT and multicoil magnetic resonance image reconstruction tasks demonstrate that our approach can achieve significant computational acceleration over the standard EI counterpart, especially in test-time training tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05771v5</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guixian Xu, Jinglai Li, Junqi Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uniform convexity of the squared distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03442v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1983, Z\u{a}linescu showed that the squared norm of a uniformly convex normed space is uniformly convex on bounded subsets. We extend this result to the metric setting of uniformly convex hyperbolic spaces. We derive applications to the convergence of shadow sequences and to proximal minimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03442v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Sipos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Outer Optimizers in Local SGD: Learning Rates, Momentum, and Acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10439v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern machine learning often requires training with large batch size, distributed data, and massively parallel compute hardware (like mobile and other edge devices or distributed data centers). Communication becomes a major bottleneck in such settings but methods like Local Stochastic Gradient Descent (Local SGD) show great promise in reducing this additional communication overhead. Local SGD consists of three parts: a local optimization process, an aggregation mechanism, and an outer optimizer that uses the aggregated updates from the nodes to produce a new model. While there exists an extensive literature on understanding the impact of hyperparameters in the local optimization process, the choice of outer optimizer and its hyperparameters is less clear. We study the role of the outer optimizer in Local SGD, and prove new convergence guarantees for the algorithm. In particular, we show that tuning the outer learning rate allows us to (a) trade off between optimization error and stochastic gradient noise variance, and (b) make up for ill-tuning of the inner learning rate. Our theory suggests that the outer learning rate should sometimes be set to values greater than $1$. We extend our results to settings where we use momentum in the outer optimizer, and we show a similar role for the momentum-adjusted outer learning rate. We also study acceleration in the outer optimizer and show that it improves the convergence rate as a function of the number of communication rounds, improving upon the convergence rate of prior algorithms that apply acceleration locally. Finally, we also introduce a novel data-dependent analysis of Local SGD that yields further insights on outer learning rate tuning. We conduct comprehensive experiments with standard language models and various outer optimizers to validate our theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10439v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Khaled, Satyen Kale, Arthur Douillard, Chi Jin, Rob Fergus, Manzil Zaheer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold Graphs Are Globally Synchronizing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12646v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Kuramoto model describes phase oscillators on the unit circle whose interactions are encoded by a graph. Each edge acts like a spring that pulls the two adjacent oscillators toward each other whenever their phases differ. A central question is to determine which graphs are globally synchronizing, meaning that trajectories of the Kuramoto dynamics converge to the fully synchronized state from almost all initial conditions, except for a set of measure zero. This property is tightly linked to the benign nonconvexity of the model's energy landscape. Existing guarantees for global synchronization rely on minimum-degree thresholds, which require the graph to be highly dense. In this work, we show that connected threshold graphs, whose density may vary from $2/n$ to $1$, are globally synchronizing. Our proof relies on a phasor-geometric analysis of the stationary points of the associated energy landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12646v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongjin Wu, Ulrik Brandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal cost for the null controllability of the Stokes system with controls having $n-1$ components and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04721v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the optimal cost of null controllability for the $n$-dimensional Stokes system when the control acts on $n-1$ scalar components. We establish a novel spectral estimate for low frequencies of the Stokes operator, involving solely $n-1$ components, and use it to show that the cost of controllability with controls having $n-1$ components remains of the same order in time as in the case of controls with $n$ components, namely $O(e^{C/T})$, i.e. the cost of null controllability is not affected by the absence of one component of the control. We also give several applications of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04721v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe W. Chaves-Silva, Marcos G. Ferreira-Silva, Diego A. Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Trajectory Generation for Goal-Oriented Spacecraft Rendezvous</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09111v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reliable real-time trajectory generation is essential for future autonomous spacecraft. While recent progress in nonconvex guidance and control is paving the way for onboard autonomous trajectory optimization, these methods still rely on extensive expert input (e.g., waypoints, constraints, mission timelines, etc.), which limits the operational scalability in real rendezvous missions. This paper introduces SAGES (Semantic Autonomous Guidance Engine for Space), a trajectory-generation framework that translates natural-language commands into spacecraft trajectories that reflect high-level intent while respecting nonconvex constraints. Experiments in two settings -- fault-tolerant proximity operations with continuous-time constraint enforcement and a free-flying robotic platform -- demonstrate that SAGES reliably produces trajectories aligned with human commands, achieving over 90% semantic-behavioral consistency across diverse behavior modes. Ultimately, this work marks an initial step toward language-conditioned, constraint-aware spacecraft trajectory generation, enabling operators to interactively guide both safety and behavior through intuitive natural-language commands with reduced expert burden.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09111v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Takubo, Arpit Dwivedi, Sukeerth Ramkumar, Luis A. Pabon, Daniele Gammelli, Marco Pavone, Simone D'Amico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Mathematical Research via Human-AI Interactive Theorem Proving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09443v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate how large language models can be used as research tools in scientific computing while preserving mathematical rigor. We propose a human-in-the-loop workflow for interactive theorem proving and discovery with LLMs. Human experts retain control over problem formulation and admissible assumptions, while the model searches for proofs or contradictions, proposes candidate properties and theorems, and helps construct structures and parameters that satisfy explicit constraints, supported by numerical experiments and simple verification checks. Experts treat these outputs as raw material, further refine them, and organize the results into precise statements and rigorous proofs. We instantiate this workflow in a case study on the connection between manifold optimization and Grover's quantum search algorithm, where the pipeline helps identify invariant subspaces, explore Grover-compatible retractions, and obtain convergence guarantees for the retraction-based gradient method. The framework provides a practical template for integrating large language models into frontier mathematical research, enabling faster exploration of proof space and algorithm design while maintaining transparent reasoning responsibilities. Although illustrated on manifold optimization problems in quantum computing, the principles extend to other core areas of scientific computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09443v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyi Li, Zhijian Lai, Dong An, Jiang Hu, Zaiwen Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
