<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 01:43:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Recommend-to-Match with Random Supply Rejections: Formulation, Approximation, and Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19122v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Matching demand with supply in crowd-sourcing logistics platforms must contend with uncertain worker participation. Motivated by this challenge, we study a two-stage ``recommend-to-match" problem under stochastic supplier rejections, where each demand is initially recommended to multiple potential suppliers prior to final matching decisions. We formulate a stochastic optimization model that explicitly captures uncertain supplier acceptance behavior. We show that an exact mixed-integer linear formulation is obtainable for the special case with homogeneous and independent acceptance responses, but the general problem does not admit an efficient formulation. Particularly, our analysis reveals that deterministic linear approximation methods can perform arbitrarily poorly in such settings. To overcome this limitation, we propose a new approximation approach based on mixed-integer exponential cone programming (MIECP) and establish its parametric performance guarantees. Extensive experiments on synthetic data and real-world freight data validate the effectiveness of our approach. Our MIECP-based solution achieves near-optimal matching performance while reducing computation time by over 90% compared to benchmark methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19122v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyue Liu, Sheng Liu, Mingyao Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy Gradient Method for LQG Control via Input-Output-History Representation: Convergence to $O(\epsilon)$-Stationary Points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the policy gradient method (PGM) for the linear quadratic Gaussian (LQG) dynamic output-feedback control problem using an input-output-history (IOH) representation of the closed-loop system. First, we show that any dynamic output-feedback controller is equivalent to a static partial-state feedback gain for a new system representation characterized by a finite-length IOH. Leveraging this equivalence, we reformulate the search for an optimal dynamic output feedback controller as an optimization problem over the corresponding partial-state feedback gain. Next, we introduce a relaxed version of the IOH-based LQG problem by incorporating a small process noise with covariance $\epsilon I$ into the new system to ensure coerciveness, a key condition for establishing gradient-based convergence guarantees. Consequently, we show that a vanilla PGM for the relaxed problem converges to an $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon)$-stationary point, i.e., $\overline{K}$ satisfying $\|\nabla J(\overline{K})\|_F \leq \mathcal{O}(\epsilon)$, where $J$ denotes the original LQG cost. Numerical experiments empirically indicate convergence to the vicinity of the globally optimal LQG controller.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19141v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonori Sadamoto, Takashi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query-Efficient Zeroth-Order Algorithms for Nonconvex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Zeroth-order optimization (ZO) has been a powerful framework for solving black-box problems, which estimates gradients using zeroth-order data to update variables iteratively. The practical applicability of ZO critically depends on the efficiency of single-step gradient estimation and the overall query complexity. However, existing ZO algorithms cannot achieve efficiency on both simultaneously. In this work, we consider a general constrained optimization model with black-box objective and constraint functions. To solve it, we propose novel algorithms that can achieve the state-of-the-art overall query complexity bound of $\mathcal{O}(d/\epsilon^4)$ to find an $\epsilon$-stationary solution ($d$ is the dimension of variable space), while reducing the queries for estimating a single-step gradient from $\mathcal{O}(d)$ to $\mathcal{O}(1)$. Specifically, we integrate block updates with gradient descent ascent and a block gradient estimator, which leads to two algorithms, ZOB-GDA and ZOB-SGDA, respectively. Instead of constructing full gradients, they estimate only partial gradients along random blocks of dimensions, where the adjustable block sizes enable high single-step efficiency without sacrificing convergence guarantees. Our theoretical results establish the finite-sample convergence of the proposed algorithms for nonconvex optimization. Finally, numerical experiments on a practical problem demonstrate that our algorithms require over ten times fewer queries than existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19165v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyang Jin, Yuke Zhou, Yujie Tang, Jie Song, Siyang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supermodular Maximization with Cardinality Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $V$ be a finite set of $n$ elements, $f: 2^V \rightarrow \mathbb{R}_+$ be a nonnegative monotone supermodular function, and $k$ be a positive integer no greater than $n$. This paper addresses the problem of maximizing $f(S)$ over all subsets $S \subseteq V$ subject to the cardinality constraint $|S| = k$ or $|S|\le k$.
  Let $r$ be a constant integer. The function $f$ is assumed to be {\em $r$-decomposable}, meaning there exist $m\,(\ge1)$ subsets $V_1, \dots, V_m$ of $V$, each with a cardinality at most $r$, and a corresponding set of nonnegative supermodular functions $f_i : 2^{V_i} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}_+$, $i=1,\ldots,m$ such that $f(S) =\sum_{i=1}^m f_i(S \cap V_i)$ holds for each $S \subseteq V$. Given $r$ as an input, we present a polynomial-time $O(n^{(r-1)/2})$-approximation algorithm for this maximization problem, which does not require prior knowledge of the specific decomposition.
  When the decomposition $(V_i,f_i)_{i=1}^m$ is known, an additional connectivity requirement is introduced to the problem. Let $G$ be the graph with vertex set $V$ and edge set $\cup_{i=1}^m \{uv:u,v\in V_i,u\neq v\}$. The cardinality constrained solution set $S$ is required to induce a connected subgraph in $G$. This model generalizes the well-known problem of finding the densest connected $k$-subgraph. We propose a polynomial time $O(n^{(r-1)/2})$-approximation algorithm for this generalization. Notably, this algorithm gives an $O(n^{1/2})$-approximation for the densest connected $k$-subgraph problem, improving upon the previous best-known approximation ratio of $O(n^{2/3})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19191v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xujin Chen, Xiaodong Hu, Changjun Wang, Qingjie Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology optimization for microfluidic mixers by a phase field method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate multi-physical topology optimization for microfluidic mixers employing the phase-field model. The optimization problem is formulated using a modified Ginzburg-Landau free energy functional. To eliminate fluid blockage in microfluidic mixers, we incorporate the coupled Navier-Stokes, convection-diffusion and Poisson-Boltzmann equations. An Allen-Cahn type gradient flow method is proposed based on sensitivity analysis. The algorithm is validated for its computational effectiveness through numerical simulations of benchmark problems in 2D and 3D.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19192v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongyuan Liu, Jiajie Li, Shengfeng Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonmonotone subgradient methods based on a local descent lemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to extend the context of nonmonotone descent methods to the class of nonsmooth and nonconvex functions called upper-$\mathcal{C}^2$, which satisfy a nonsmooth and local version of the descent lemma. Under this assumption, we propose a general subgradient method that performs a nonmonotone linesearch, and we prove subsequential convergence to a stationary point of the optimization problem. Our approach allows us to cover the setting of various subgradient algorithms, including Newton and quasi-Newton methods. In addition, we propose a specification of the general scheme, named Self-adaptive Nonmonotone Subgradient Method (SNSM), which automatically updates the parameters of the linesearch. Particular attention is paid to the minimum sum-of-squares clustering problem, for which we provide a concrete implementation of SNSM. We conclude with some numerical experiments where we exhibit the advantages of SNSM in comparison with some known algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19341v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco J. Arag\'on-Artacho, Rub\'en Campoy, Pedro P\'erez-Aros, David Torregrosa-Bel\'en</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Radius of Robust Feasibility Approach to Directional Sensors in Uncertain Terrain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A sensor has the ability to probe its surroundings. However, uncertainties in its exact location can significantly compromise its sensing performance. The radius of robust feasibility defines the maximum range within which robust feasibility is ensured. This work introduces a novel approach integrating it with the directional sensor networks to enhance coverage using a distributed greedy algorithm. In particular, we provide an exact formula for the radius of robust feasibility of sensors in a directional sensor network. The proposed model strategically orients the sensors in regions with high coverage potential, accounting for robustness in the face of uncertainty. We analyze the algorithm's adaptability in dynamic environments, demonstrating its ability to enhance efficiency and robustness. Experimental results validate its efficacy in maximizing coverage and optimizing sensor orientations, highlighting its practical advantages for real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19407v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanshika Datta, C. Nahak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proximal algorithm incorporating difference of convex functions optimization for solving a class of single-ratio fractional programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a class of single-ratio fractional minimization problems, where both the numerator and denominator of the objective are convex functions satisfying positive homogeneity. Many nonsmooth optimization problems on the sphere that are commonly encountered in application scenarios across different scientific fields can be converted into this equivalent fractional programming. We derive local and global optimality conditions of the problem and subsequently propose a proximal-subgradient-difference of convex functions algorithm (PS-DCA) to compute its critical points. When the DCA step is removed, PS-DCA reduces to the proximal-subgradient algorithm (PSA). Under mild assumptions regarding the algorithm parameters, it is shown that any accumulation point of the sequence produced by PS-DCA or PSA is a critical point of the problem. Moreover, for a typical class of generalized graph Fourier mode problems, we establish global convergence of the entire sequence generated by PS-DCA or PSA. Numerical experiments conducted on computing the generalized graph Fourier modes demonstrate that, compared to proximal gradient-type algorithms, PS-DCA integrates difference of convex functions (d.c.) optimization, rendering it less sensitive to initial points and preventing the sequence it generates from being trapped in low-quality local minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19408v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Qi, Jianfeng Huang, Lihua Yang, Chao Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and performance of stochastic economic MPC - Stochastic characterization of the closed-loop asymptotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19416v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Model Predictive Control (MPC) is well understood in the deterministic setting, yet rigorous stability and performance guarantees for stochastic MPC remain limited to the consideration of terminal constraints and penalties. In contrast, this work analyzes stochastic economic MPC with an expected cost criterion and establishes closed-loop guarantees without terminal conditions. Relying on stochastic dissipativity and turnpike properties, we construct closed-loop Lyapunov functions that ensure $P$-practical asymptotic stability of a particular optimal stationary process under different notions of stochastic convergence, such as in distribution or in the $p$-th mean. In addition, we derive tight near-optimal bounds for both averaged and non-averaged performance, thereby extending classical deterministic results to the stochastic domain. Finally, we show that the abstract stochastic MPC scheme requiring distributional knowledge shares the same closed-loop properties as a practically implementable algorithm based only on sampled state information, ensuring applicability of our findings. Our findings are illustrated by a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19416v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Schie{\ss}l, Hannah Selder, Ruchuan Ou, Michael Heinrich Baumann, Timm Faulwasser, Lars Gr\"une</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential stability of finite-$N$ consensus-based optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the finite-agent behavior of Consensus-Based Optimization (CBO), a recent metaheuristic for the global minimization of a function, that combines drift toward a consensus estimate with stochastic exploration. While previous analyses focus on asymptotic mean-field limits, we investigate the stability properties of CBO for finite population size \( N \). Following a hierarchical approach, we first analyze a deterministic formulation of the algorithm and then extend our results to the fully stochastic setting governed by a system of stochastic differential equations. Our analysis reveals that essential stability properties, including almost sure and mean square exponential convergence, persist in both regimes and provides sharp quantitative estimates on the rates of convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19565v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone G\"ottlich, Jacob Heieck, Andreas Neuenkirch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On an adjoint-based numerical approach for time-dependent optimal control problems of biomedical interest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work develops a rigorous numerical framework for solving time-dependent Optimal Control Problems (OCPs) governed by partial differential equations, with a particular focus on biomedical applications. The approach deals with adjoint-based Lagrangian methodology, which enables efficient gradient computation and systematic derivation of optimality conditions for both distributed and concentrated control formulations. The proposed framework is first verified using a time-dependent advection-diffusion problem endowed with a manufactured solution to assess accuracy and convergence properties. Subsequently, two representative applications involving drug delivery are investigated: (i) a light-triggered drug delivery system for targeted cancer therapy and (ii) a catheter-based drug delivery system in a patient-specific coronary artery. Numerical experiments not only demonstrate the accuracy of the approach, but also its flexibility and robustness in handling complex geometries, heterogeneous parameters, and realistic boundary conditions, highlighting its potential for the optimal design and control of complex biomedical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19576v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Mirzaiyan, Pierfrancesco Siena, Pasquale Claudio Africa, Michele Girfoglio, Gianluigi Rozza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers for Utility-based Shortfall Risk Portfolio Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Utility-based shortfall risk (UBSR), a convex risk measure sensitive to tail losses, has gained popularity in recent years. However, research on computational methods for UBSR optimization remains relatively scarce. In this paper, we propose a fast and scalable algorithm for the UBSR-based portfolio optimization problem. Leveraging the Sample Average Approximation (SAA) framework, we reformulate the problem as a block-separable convex program and solve it efficiently via the alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM). In the high-dimensional setting, a key challenge arises in one of the subproblems -- a projection onto a nonlinear feasibility set defined by the shortfall-risk constraint. We propose two semismooth Newton algorithms to solve this projection subproblem. The first algorithm directly applies a semismooth Newton iteration to the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) system of the projection problem. The second algorithm employs an implicit function transformation of semismooth functions to reduce the problem to a univariate equation involving the Lagrange multiplier and achieves global superlinear convergence with enhanced numerical stability under mild regularity conditions. Theoretical convergence guarantees of the proposed algorithms are established, and numerical experiments demonstrate a substantial speedup over state-of-the-art solvers, particularly in high-dimensional regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19614v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rufeng Xiao, Zhiping Li, Rujun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse identification of epidemiological compartment models with conserved quantities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19762v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the application of a framework for sparse model identification of differential equations from timeseries data in the context of compartmental models in epidemiology. Such frameworks often seek a sparse representation from a polynomial basis in the state variables which reproduces the timeseries. Out-of-the-box approaches for the underlying sparse regression problem have moderate success reproducing the provided timeseries, but typically fail at producing a consistent, interpretable compartment model and conserving the total population, which are common properties in principled compartment modeling. Additionally, the conserved polynomial quantities, such as the sum of state variables, add algebraic nuances to a polynomial design matrix. We propose a linear program formulation to solve these issues by posing a pure one-norm objective, sampling from the nullspace of the design matrix, and imposing a set of linear constraints for between-compartment flows. We conduct several numerical experiments on synthetic data and succeed in ensuring model sparsity, accurately capturing system dynamics, and preserving conservation of population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19762v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuchehr Aminian, Kristin M. Kurianski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nodal Capacity Expansion Planning with Flexible Large-Scale Load Siting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose explicitly incorporating large-scale load siting into a stochastic nodal power system capacity expansion planning model that concurrently co-optimizes generation, transmission and storage expansion. The potential operational flexibility of some of these large loads is also taken into account by considering them as consisting of a set of tranches with different reliability requirements, which are modeled as a constraint on expected served energy across operational scenarios. We implement our model as a two-stage stochastic mixed-integer optimization problem with cross-scenario expectation constraints. To overcome the challenge of scalability, we build upon existing work to implement this model on a high performance computing platform and exploit scenario parallelization using an augmented Progressive Hedging Algorithm. The algorithm is implemented using the bounding features of mpisppy, which have shown to provide satisfactory provable optimality gaps despite the absence of theoretical guarantees of convergence. We test our approach to assess the value of this proactive planning framework on total system cost and reliability metrics using realistic testcases geographically assigned to San Diego and South Carolina, with datacenter and direct air capture facilities as large loads.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19781v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomas Valencia Zuluaga, Simon Pang, Jean-Paul Watson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Production and Just Distribution in Diverse Society</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18896v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we want to investigate dynamics of productivity in a society which is diverse when it comes to both the productivity and the perception of justice in distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18896v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Roginskaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impartial Selection with Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the selection of agents based on mutual nominations, a theoretical problem with many applications from committee selection to AI alignment. As agents both select and are selected, they may be incentivized to misrepresent their true opinion about the eligibility of others to influence their own chances of selection. Impartial mechanisms circumvent this issue by guaranteeing that the selection of an agent is independent of the nominations cast by that agent. Previous research has established strong bounds on the performance of impartial mechanisms, measured by their ability to approximate the number of nominations for the most highly nominated agents. We study to what extent the performance of impartial mechanisms can be improved if they are given a prediction of a set of agents receiving a maximum number of nominations. Specifically, we provide bounds on the consistency and robustness of such mechanisms, where consistency measures the performance of the mechanisms when the prediction is accurate and robustness its performance when the prediction is inaccurate. For the general setting where up to $k$ agents are to be selected and agents nominate any number of other agents, we give a mechanism with consistency $1-O\big(\frac{1}{k}\big)$ and robustness $1-\frac{1}{e}-O\big(\frac{1}{k}\big)$. For the special case of selecting a single agent based on a single nomination per agent, we prove that $1$-consistency can be achieved while guaranteeing $\frac{1}{2}$-robustness. A close comparison with previous results shows that (asymptotically) optimal consistency can be achieved with little to no sacrifice in terms of robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19002v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Cembrano, Felix Fischer, Max Klimm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Natural Gradient VI: Guarantees for Non-Conjugate Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stochastic Natural Gradient Variational Inference (NGVI) is a widely used method for approximating posterior distribution in probabilistic models. Despite its empirical success and foundational role in variational inference, its theoretical underpinnings remain limited, particularly in the case of non-conjugate likelihoods. While NGVI has been shown to be a special instance of Stochastic Mirror Descent, and recent work has provided convergence guarantees using relative smoothness and strong convexity for conjugate models, these results do not extend to the non-conjugate setting, where the variational loss becomes non-convex and harder to analyze. In this work, we focus on mean-field parameterization and advance the theoretical understanding of NGVI in three key directions. First, we derive sufficient conditions under which the variational loss satisfies relative smoothness with respect to a suitable mirror map. Second, leveraging this structure, we propose a modified NGVI algorithm incorporating non-Euclidean projections and prove its global non-asymptotic convergence to a stationary point. Finally, under additional structural assumptions about the likelihood, we uncover hidden convexity properties of the variational loss and establish fast global convergence of NGVI to a global optimum. These results provide new insights into the geometry and convergence behavior of NGVI in challenging inference settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19163v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangyuan Sun, Ilyas Fatkhullin, Niao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Communication-Efficient Decentralized Actor-Critic Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19199v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the problem of reinforcement learning in multi-agent systems where communication among agents is limited. We develop a decentralized actor-critic learning framework in which each agent performs several local updates of its policy and value function, where the latter is approximated by a multi-layer neural network, before exchanging information with its neighbors. This local training strategy substantially reduces the communication burden while maintaining coordination across the network. We establish finite-time convergence analysis for the algorithm under Markov-sampling. Specifically, to attain the $\varepsilon$-accurate stationary point, the sample complexity is of order $\mathcal{O}(\varepsilon^{-3})$ and the communication complexity is of order $\mathcal{O}(\varepsilon^{-1}\tau^{-1})$, where tau denotes the number of local training steps. We also show how the final error bound depends on the neural network's approximation quality. Numerical experiments in a cooperative control setting illustrate and validate the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19199v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxing Ren, Nicola Bastianello, Thomas Parisini, Andreas A. Malikopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle system approximation of Nash equilibria in large games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19211v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a probabilistic framework to approximate Nash equilibria in symmetric $N$-player games in the large population regime, via the analysis of associated mean field games (MFGs). The approximation is achieved through the analysis of a McKean-Vlasov type Langevin dynamics and their associated particle systems, with convergence to the MFG solution established in the limit of vanishing temperature parameter. Relying on displacement monotonicity or Lasry-Lions monotonicity of the cost function, we prove contractility of the McKean-Vlasov process and uniform-in-time propagation of chaos for the particle system. Our results contribute to the general theory of interacting diffusions by showing that monotonicity can ensure convergence without requiring small interaction assumptions or functional inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19211v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovic Tangpi, Nizar Touzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllable Machine Unlearning via Gradient Pivoting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine unlearning (MU) aims to remove the influence of specific data from a trained model. However, approximate unlearning methods, often formulated as a single-objective optimization (SOO) problem, face a critical trade-off between unlearning efficacy and model fidelity. This leads to three primary challenges: the risk of over-forgetting, a lack of fine-grained control over the unlearning process, and the absence of metrics to holistically evaluate the trade-off. To address these issues, we reframe MU as a multi-objective optimization (MOO) problem. We then introduce a novel algorithm, Controllable Unlearning by Pivoting Gradient (CUP), which features a unique pivoting mechanism. Unlike traditional MOO methods that converge to a single solution, CUP's mechanism is designed to controllably navigate the entire Pareto frontier. This navigation is governed by a single intuitive hyperparameter, the `unlearning intensity', which allows for precise selection of a desired trade-off. To evaluate this capability, we adopt the hypervolume indicator, a metric that captures both the quality and diversity of the entire set of solutions an algorithm can generate. Our experimental results demonstrate that CUP produces a superior set of Pareto-optimal solutions, consistently outperforming existing methods across various vision tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19226v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngsik Hwang, Dong-Young Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error Analysis of Triangular Optimal Transport Maps for Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19283v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic analysis of estimation errors for a class of optimal transport based algorithms for filtering and data assimilation. Along the way, we extend previous error analyses of Brenier maps to the case of conditional Brenier maps that arise in the context of simulation based inference. We then apply these results in a filtering scenario to analyze the optimal transport filtering algorithm of Al-Jarrah et al. (2024, ICML). An extension of that algorithm along with numerical benchmarks on various non-Gaussian and high-dimensional examples are provided to demonstrate its effectiveness and practical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19283v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Al-Jarrah, Bamdad Hosseini, Niyizhen Jin, Michele Martino, Amirhossein Taghvaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization Benchmark for Diffusion Models on Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The training of diffusion models is often absent in the evaluation of new optimization techniques. In this work, we benchmark recent optimization algorithms for training a diffusion model for denoising flow trajectories. We observe that Muon and SOAP are highly efficient alternatives to AdamW (18% lower final loss). We also revisit several recent phenomena related to the training of models for text or image applications in the context of diffusion model training. This includes the impact of the learning-rate schedule on the training dynamics, and the performance gap between Adam and SGD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19376v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Schaipp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Probabilistic Computing Approach to the Closest Vector Problem for Lattice-Based Factoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19390v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The closest vector problem (CVP) is a fundamental optimization problem in lattice-based cryptography and its conjectured hardness underpins the security of lattice-based cryptosystems. Furthermore, Schnorr's lattice-based factoring algorithm reduces integer factoring (the foundation of current cryptosystems, including RSA) to the CVP. Recent work has investigated the inclusion of a heuristic CVP approximation `refinement' step in the lattice-based factoring algorithm, using quantum variational algorithms to perform the heuristic optimization. This coincides with the emergence of probabilistic computing as a hardware accelerator for randomized algorithms including tasks in combinatorial optimization. In this work we investigate the application of probabilistic computing to the heuristic optimization task of CVP approximation refinement in lattice-based factoring. We present the design of a probabilistic computing algorithm for this task, a discussion of `prime lattice' parameters, and experimental results showing the efficacy of probabilistic computing for solving the CVP as well as its efficacy as a subroutine for lattice-based factoring. The main results found that (a) this approach is capable of finding the maximal available CVP approximation refinement in time linear in problem size and (b) probabilistic computing used in conjunction with the lattice parameters presented can find the composite prime factors of a semiprime number using up to 100x fewer lattice instances than similar quantum and classical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19390v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max O. Al-Hasso, Marko von der Leyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring LLM-based Multi-Agent Systems Against Corruptions via Node Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Model (LLM)-based Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) have become a popular paradigm of AI applications. However, trustworthiness issues in MAS remain a critical concern. Unlike challenges in single-agent systems, MAS involve more complex communication processes, making them susceptible to corruption attacks. To mitigate this issue, several defense mechanisms have been developed based on the graph representation of MAS, where agents represent nodes and communications form edges. Nevertheless, these methods predominantly focus on static graph defense, attempting to either detect attacks in a fixed graph structure or optimize a static topology with certain defensive capabilities. To address this limitation, we propose a dynamic defense paradigm for MAS graph structures, which continuously monitors communication within the MAS graph, then dynamically adjusts the graph topology, accurately disrupts malicious communications, and effectively defends against evolving and diverse dynamic attacks. Experimental results in increasingly complex and dynamic MAS environments demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms existing MAS defense mechanisms, contributing an effective guardrail for their trustworthy applications. Our code is available at https://github.com/ChengcanWu/Monitoring-LLM-Based-Multi-Agent-Systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19420v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengcan Wu, Zhixin Zhang, Mingqian Xu, Zeming Wei, Meng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning of Off-Grid Renewable Power to Ammonia Systems with Heterogeneous Flexibility: A Multistakeholder Equilibrium Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09113v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Off-grid renewable power to ammonia (ReP2A) systems present a promising pathway toward carbon neutrality in both the energy and chemical industries. However, due to chemical safety requirements, the limited flexibility of ammonia synthesis poses a challenge when attempting to align with the variable hydrogen flow produced from renewable power. This necessitates the optimal sizing of equipment capacity for effective and coordinated production across the system. Additionally, an ReP2A system may involve multiple stakeholders with varying degrees of operational flexibility, complicating the planning problem. This paper first examines the multistakeholder sizing equilibrium (MSSE) of the ReP2A system. First, we propose an MSSE model that accounts for individual planning decisions and the competing economic interests of the stakeholders of power generation, hydrogen production, and ammonia synthesis. We then construct an equivalent optimization problem based on Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions to determine the equilibrium. Following this, we decompose the problem in the temporal dimension and solve it via multicut generalized Benders decomposition (GBD) to address long-term balancing issues. Case studies based on a realistic project reveal that the equilibrium does not naturally balance the interests of all stakeholders due to their heterogeneous characteristics. Our findings suggest that benefit transfer or re-arrangement ensure mutual benefits and the successful implementation of ReP2A projects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09113v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TPWRS.2025.3561674</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yangjun Zeng (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Yiwei Qiu (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Jie Zhu (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Shi Chen (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Tianlei Zang (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Buxiang Zhou (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Ge He (School of Chemical Engineering, Sichuan University), Xu Ji (School of Chemical Engineering, Sichuan University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Investment Portfolio of Thyristor- and IGBT-based Electrolysis Rectifiers in Utility-scale Renewable P2H Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17092v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Renewable power-to-hydrogen (ReP2H) systems require rectifiers to supply power to electrolyzers (ELZs). Two main types of rectifiers, insulated-gate bipolar transistor rectifiers (IGBT-Rs) and thyristor rectifiers (TRs), offer distinct tradeoffs. IGBT-Rs provide flexible reactive power control but are costly, whereas TRs are more affordable with lower power loss but consume a large amount of uncontrollable reactive power. A mixed configuration of rectifiers in utility-scale ReP2H systems could achieve a decent tradeoff and increase overall profitability. To explore this potential, this paper proposes an optimal investment portfolio model. First, we model and compare the active and reactive power characteristics of ELZs powered by TRs and IGBT-Rs. Second, we consider the investment of ELZs, rectifiers, and var resources and coordinate the operation of renewables, energy storage, var resources, and the on-off switching and load allocation of multiple ELZs. Subsequently, a two-stage stochastic programming (SP) model based on weighted information gap decision theory (W-IGDT) is developed to address the uncertainties of the renewable power and hydrogen price, and we apply the progressive hedging (PH) algorithm to accelerate its solution. Case studies demonstrate that optimal rectifier configurations increase revenue by at most 13.78% compared with configurations using only TRs or IGBT-Rs, existing project setups, or intuitive designs. Under the optimal portfolio, reactive power compensation investment is nearly eliminated, with a preferred TR-to-IGBT-R ratio of 3:1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17092v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TSTE.2025.3595150</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yangjun Zeng (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Yiwei Qiu (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Liuchao Xu (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Chenjia Gu (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Yi Zhou (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Jiarong Li (Harvard John A. Paulson School of Engineering and Applied Sciences), Shi Chen (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University), Buxiang Zhou (College of Electrical Engineering, Sichuan University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending Exact Convex Relaxations of Quadratically Constrained Quadratic Programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03204v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A convex relaxation of a quadratically constrained quadratic program (QCQP) is called exact if it has a rank-$1$ optimal solution that corresponds to an optimal solution of the QCQP. Given a QCQP whose convex relaxation is exact, this paper investigates the incorporation of additional quadratic inequality constraints under a non-intersecting quadratic constraint condition while maintaining the exactness of the convex relaxation of the resulting QCQP. Specifically, we extend existing exact semidefinite programming relaxation, completely positive programming relaxation and doubly nonnegative programming relaxation of various classes of QCQPs in a unified manner. Illustrative examples are included to demonstrate the applicability of the established result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03204v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masakazu Kojima, Sunyoung Kim, Naohiko Arima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-optimality of the Separation Principle for Quadratic Control from Bilinear Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11555v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of controlling a linear dynamical system from bilinear observations with minimal quadratic cost. Despite the similarity of this problem to standard linear quadratic Gaussian (LQG) control, we show that when the observation model is bilinear, neither does the Separation Principle hold, nor is the optimal controller affine in the estimated state. Moreover, the cost-to-go is non-convex in the control input. Hence, finding an analytical expression for the optimal feedback controller is difficult in general. Under certain settings, we show that the standard LQG controller locally maximizes the cost instead of minimizing it. Furthermore, the optimal controllers (derived analytically) are not unique and are nonlinear in the estimated state. We also introduce a notion of input-dependent observability and derive conditions under which the Kalman filter covariance remains bounded. We illustrate our theoretical results through numerical experiments in multiple synthetic settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11555v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yahya Sattar, Sunmook Choi, Yassir Jedra, Maryam Fazel, Sarah Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rank-One Modified Value Iteration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01828v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we provide a novel algorithm for solving planning and learning problems of Markov decision processes. The proposed algorithm follows a policy iteration-type update by using a rank-one approximation of the transition probability matrix in the policy evaluation step. This rank-one approximation is closely related to the stationary distribution of the corresponding transition probability matrix, which is approximated using the power method. We provide theoretical guarantees for the convergence of the proposed algorithm to optimal (action-)value function with the same rate and computational complexity as the value iteration algorithm in the planning problem and as the Q-learning algorithm in the learning problem. Through our extensive numerical simulations, however, we show that the proposed algorithm consistently outperforms first-order algorithms and their accelerated versions for both planning and learning problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01828v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arman Sharifi Kolarijani, Tolga Ok, Peyman Mohajerin Esfahani, Mohamad Amin Sharif Kolarijani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pattern-preserving optimal control problems with increasing time horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09970v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a general framework that guarantees the preservation of optimal control patterns as the time horizon $[0,T]$ increases and becomes unbounded. A concept of pattern-preserving family of optimal control problems is introduced and the goal is achieved by analyzing the $\Gamma$-convergence of the corresponding variational formulations as $T\to\infty$. Special attention is given to scenarios involving state constraints. To illustrate the results, examples and applications are provided, with particular focus on switched systems and epidemic control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09970v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Della Rossa, Lorenzo Freddi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary controllability of the Korteweg-de Vries equation: The Neumann case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04977v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article gives a necessary first step to understanding the critical set phenomenon for the Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) equation posed on interval $[0,L]$ considering the Neumann boundary conditions with only one control input. We showed that the KdV equation is controllable in the critical case, i.e., when the spatial domain $L$ belongs to the set $\mathcal{R}_c$, where $c\neq-1$ and $$
  \mathcal{R}_c:=\left\{\frac{2\pi}{\sqrt{3(c+1)}}\sqrt{m^2+ml+m^2};\ m,l\in \mathbb{N}^*\right\}\cup\left\{\frac{m\pi}{\sqrt{c+1}};\ m\in \mathbb{N}^*\right\}, $$ the KdV equation is exactly controllable in $L^2(0,L)$. The result is achieved using the return method together with a fixed point argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04977v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. de A. Capistrano-Filho, J. S. da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness and propagation of chaos for McKean-Vlasov stochastic variational inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11053v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a broad class of McKean-Vlasov stochastic variational inequalities (MVSVIs), where both the drift coefficient $b$ and the diffusion coefficient $\sigma$ depend on time $t$, the state $X_t$ and its distribution $\mu_t$. We establish the strong well-posedness, when $b$ is superlinear growth and locally Lipschitz continuous, and $\sigma$ is locally H\"older continuous, both with respect to $X_t$ and $\mu_t$. Additionally, we present the first propagation of chaos result for MVSVIs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11053v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Ning, Jing Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Sample Identification of Partially Observed Bilinear Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07652v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of learning a realization of a partially observed bilinear dynamical system (BLDS) from noisy input-output data. Given a single trajectory of input-output samples, we provide a finite time analysis for learning the system's Markov-like parameters, from which a balanced realization of the bilinear system can be obtained. Our bilinear system identification algorithm learns the system's Markov-like parameters by regressing the outputs to highly correlated, nonlinear, and heavy-tailed covariates. Moreover, the stability of BLDS depends on the sequence of inputs used to excite the system. These properties, unique to partially observed bilinear dynamical systems, pose significant challenges to the analysis of our algorithm for learning the unknown dynamics. We address these challenges and provide high probability error bounds on our identification algorithm under a uniform stability assumption. Our analysis provides insights into system theoretic quantities that affect learning accuracy and sample complexity. Lastly, we perform numerical experiments with synthetic data to reinforce these insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07652v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yahya Sattar, Yassir Jedra, Maryam Fazel, Sarah Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Asynchronous Federated Learning: A Delicate Trade-Off Between Model-Parameter Staleness and Update Frequency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08206v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Synchronous federated learning (FL) scales poorly with the number of clients due to the straggler effect. Algorithms like FedAsync and GeneralizedFedAsync address this limitation by enabling asynchronous communication between clients and the central server. In this work, we rely on stochastic modeling and analysis to better understand the impact of design choices in asynchronous FL algorithms, such as the concurrency level and routing probabilities, and we leverage this knowledge to optimize loss. Compared to most existing studies, we account for the joint impact of heterogeneous and variable service speeds and heterogeneous datasets at the clients. We characterize in particular a fundamental trade-off for optimizing asynchronous FL: minimizing gradient estimation errors by avoiding model parameter staleness, while also speeding up the system by increasing the throughput of model updates. Our two main contributions can be summarized as follows. First, we prove a discrete variant of Little's law to derive a closed-form expression for relative delay, a metric that quantifies staleness. This allows us to efficiently minimize the average loss per model update, which has been the gold standard in literature to date, using the upper-bound of Leconte et al. as a proxy. Second, we observe that naively optimizing this metric drastically slows down the system by overemphasizing staleness at the expense of throughput. This motivates us to introduce an alternative metric that also accounts for speed, for which we derive a tractable upper-bound that can be minimized numerically. Extensive numerical results show these optimizations enhance accuracy by 10% to 30%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08206v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI), Oct 2025, Bologna, Italy</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abdelkrim Alahyane (LAAS-SARA, LAAS), C\'eline Comte (CNRS, LAAS-SARA, LAAS), Matthieu Jonckheere (CNRS, LAAS-SARA, LAAS), \'Eric Moulines (X)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CISSIR: Beam Codebooks with Self-Interference Reduction Guarantees for Integrated Sensing and Communication Beyond 5G</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10371v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a beam codebook design for integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) that reduces self-interference (SI) to alleviate analog distortion. Our optimization framework, which considers either tapered beamforming or phased arrays for both analog and hybrid schemes, modifies given reference codebooks such that a certain SI power level is achieved. In contrast to other low-SI codebooks, which often rely on hardly interpretable optimization parameters, we provide design guidelines to obtain sensing performance guarantees by deriving analytical bounds on saturation and analog-to-digital quantization in relation to the multipath SI level. By selecting standard reference codebooks in our simulations, we show how our method substantially improves the signal-to-noise ratio for sensing with little impact on 5G-NR communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10371v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Hernang\'omez, Jochen Fink, Renato L. G. Cavalcante, S{\l}awomir Sta\'nczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Spatially Adaptive $\ell_1$-Norms Weights for Convolutional Synthesis Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09483v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an unrolled algorithm approach for learning spatially adaptive parameter maps in the framework of convolutional synthesis-based $\ell_1$ regularization. More precisely, we consider a family of pre-trained convolutional filters and estimate deeply parametrized spatially varying parameters applied to the sparse feature maps by means of unrolling a FISTA algorithm to solve the underlying sparse estimation problem. The proposed approach is evaluated for image reconstruction of low-field MRI and compared to spatially adaptive and non-adaptive analysis-type procedures relying on Total Variation regularization and to a well-established model-based deep learning approach. We show that the proposed approach produces visually and quantitatively comparable results with the latter approaches and at the same time remains highly interpretable. In particular, the inferred parameter maps quantify the local contribution of each filter in the reconstruction, which provides valuable insight into the algorithm mechanism and could potentially be used to discard unsuited filters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09483v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Kofler, Luca Calatroni, Christoph Kolbitsch, Kostas Papafitsoros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fair Supervised Learning Through Constraints on Smooth Nonconvex Unfairness-Measure Surrogates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15788v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new strategy for fair supervised machine learning is proposed. The main advantages of the proposed strategy as compared to others in the literature are as follows. (a) We introduce a new smooth nonconvex surrogate to approximate the Heaviside functions involved in discontinuous unfairness measures. The surrogate is based on smoothing methods from the optimization literature, and is new for the fair supervised learning literature. The surrogate is a tight approximation which ensures the trained prediction models are fair, as opposed to other (e.g., convex) surrogates that can fail to lead to a fair prediction model in practice. (b) Rather than rely on regularizers (that lead to optimization problems that are difficult to solve) and corresponding regularization parameters (that can be expensive to tune), we propose a strategy that employs hard constraints so that specific tolerances for unfairness can be enforced without the complications associated with the use of regularization. (c) Our proposed strategy readily allows for constraints on multiple (potentially conflicting) unfairness measures at the same time. Multiple measures can be considered with a regularization approach, but at the cost of having even more difficult optimization problems to solve and further expense for tuning. By contrast, through hard constraints, our strategy leads to optimization models that can be solved tractably with minimal tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15788v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Khatti, Daniel P. Robinson, Frank E. Curtis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second domain variation for the $p$ - capacity and the $q$ - torsional rigidity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20307v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The second domain variation of the $p$-capacity and the $q$ - torsional rigidity for compact sets in $R^d, d\geq3$ with $1&lt;p&lt;d$ is computed. Conditions on $p$ and $q&gt;1$ are given such that the ball is a local minimzer or maximizer of the product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20307v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfred Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to measure the uncertainty of a tournament draw: The case of European football's Champions League</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15320v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to recent empirical studies, the group draw of major sports tournaments can imply a high level of uncertainty, and some lucky teams enjoy an unfair advantage over the other teams. We propose a novel technique to quantify this draw uncertainty, which, arguably, has an optimal level of zero. Our simulation-based approach requires generating a high number of random draws to compute the variance of qualifying probabilities for each team. The method is applied to compare draw uncertainty in the former group stage and the current incomplete round-robin league phase of the UEFA Champions League. We also break down the impact of the 2024/25 reform into various components. The new format is found to decrease draw uncertainty; the reduction can mainly be attributed to the inaccurate seeding system used by UEFA. Our results reveal that the primary benefit of an incomplete round-robin tournament compared to the standard group stage lies in the robustness of its draw uncertainty to the seeding of the teams, which is a crucial aspect of fairness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15320v4</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'aszl\'o Csat\'o, Andr\'as Gyimesi, Dries Goossens, Karel Devriesere, Roel Lambers, Frits Spieksma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observability of Schr\"odinger propagators on tori in rough settings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23965v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: On tori of arbitrary dimensions, Schr\"odinger propagators with bounded potentials are conjectured to be observable from space-time domains of positive Lebesgue measure. We reduce this conjecture to certain integrability bounds for free Schr\"odinger waves, thereby proving the conjecture on the one-dimensional torus and producing new examples of observation domains. These bounds are far weaker than Bourgain's conjectured periodic Strichartz estimates, yet remain highly nontrivial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23965v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Burq, Hui Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preconditioned Norms: A Unified Framework for Steepest Descent, Quasi-Newton and Adaptive Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10777v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Optimization lies at the core of modern deep learning, yet existing methods often face a fundamental trade-off between adapting to problem geometry and leveraging curvature utilization. Steepest descent algorithms adapt to different geometries through norm choices but remain strictly first-order, whereas quasi-Newton and adaptive optimizers incorporate curvature information but are restricted to Frobenius geometry, limiting their applicability across diverse architectures. In this work, we propose a unified framework generalizing steepest descent, quasi-Newton methods, and adaptive methods through the novel notion of preconditioned matrix norms. This abstraction reveals that widely used optimizers such as SGD and Adam, as well as more advanced approaches like Muon and KL-Shampoo, and recent hybrids including SOAP and SPlus, all emerge as special cases of the same principle. Within this framework, we provide the first systematic treatment of affine and scale invariance in the matrix-parameterized setting, establishing necessary and sufficient conditions under generalized norms. Building on this foundation, we introduce two new methods, $\texttt{MuAdam}$ and $\texttt{MuAdam-SANIA}$, which combine the spectral geometry of Muon with Adam-style preconditioning. Our experiments demonstrate that these optimizers are competitive with, and in some cases outperform, existing state-of-the-art methods. Our code is available at https://github.com/brain-lab-research/LIB/tree/quasi_descent</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10777v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Veprikov, Arman Bolatov, Samuel Horv\'ath, Aleksandr Beznosikov, Martin Tak\'a\v{c}, Slavomir Hanzely</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
