<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 04:00:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Extremum Seeking Control for Multivariable Maps under Actuator Saturation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper deals with the gradient-based extremum seeking control for multivariable maps under actuator saturation. By exploiting a polytopic embedding of the unknown Hessian, we derive a LMI-based synthesis condition to ensure that the origin of the average closed-loop error system is exponentially stable. Then, the convergence of the extremum seeking control system under actuator saturation to the unknown optimal point is proved by employing Lyapunov stability and averaging theories. Numerical simulations illustrate the efficacy of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08005v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enzo Ferreira Tomaz Silva, Pedro Henrique Silva Coutinho, Tiago Roux Oliveira, Miroslav Krsti\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On iteratively regularized first-order methods for simple bilevel optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider simple bilevel optimization problems where the goal is to compute among the optimal solutions of a composite convex optimization problem, one that minimizes a secondary objective function. Our main contribution is threefold. (i) When the upper-level objective is a composite strongly convex function, we propose an iteratively regularized proximal gradient method in that the regularization parameter is updated at each iteration under a prescribed rule. We establish the asymptotic convergence of the generated iterate to the unique optimal solution. Further, we derive simultaneous sublinear convergence rates for suitably defined infeasibility and suboptimality error metrics. When the optimal solution set of the lower-level problem admits a weak sharp minimality condition, utilizing a constant regularization parameter, we show that this method achieves simultaneous linear convergence rates. (ii) For addressing the setting in (i), we also propose a regularized accelerated proximal gradient method. We derive quadratically decaying sublinear convergence rates for both infeasibility and suboptimality error metrics. When weak sharp minimality holds, a linear convergence rate with an improved dependence on the condition number is achieved. (iii) When the upper-level objective is a smooth nonconvex function, we propose an inexactly projected iteratively regularized gradient method. Under suitable assumptions, we derive new convergence rate statements for computing a stationary point of the simple bilevel problem. We present preliminary numerical experiments for resolving three instances of ill-posed linear inverse problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08079v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepideh Samadi, Daniel Burbano, Farzad Yousefian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Compression for Fast Online Stochastic Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an online data compression approach for efficiently solving distributionally robust optimization (DRO) problems with streaming data while maintaining out-of-sample performance guarantees. Our method dynamically constructs ambiguity sets using online clustering, allowing the clustered configuration to evolve over time for an accurate representation of the underlying distribution. We establish theoretical conditions for clustering algorithms to ensure robustness, and show that the performance gap between our online solution and the nominal DRO solution is controlled by the Wasserstein distance between the true and compressed distributions, which is approximated using empirical measures. We provide a regret analysis, proving that the upper bound on this performance gap converges sublinearly to a fixed clustering-dependent distance, even when nominal DRO has access, in hindsight, to the subsequent realization of the uncertainty. Numerical experiments in mixed-integer portfolio optimization demonstrate significant computational savings, with minimal loss in solution quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08097v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irina Wang, Marta Fochesato, Bartolomeo Stellato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Robust Energy Systems Considering Weather Uncertainty and Nuclear Power Failures: A Case Study in Northern Europe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Capacity expansion models used for policy support have increasingly represented both the variability and uncertainty of weather-dependent generation (wind and solar). However, although also uncertain, as demonstrated by the performance of the French nuclear power fleet in 2022, uncertainty arising from nuclear power outages has been largely neglected in the literature. This paper presents the first capacity expansion model that considers uncertainty in nuclear power availability caused by unplanned outages. We propose a mathematical model that combines a scenario-based stochastic optimization approach (to deal with weather-related uncertainties) with a data-driven adjustable robust optimization approach (to deal with nuclear failure-related uncertainties). The robust model represents the bulky behavior of nuclear power plants, with large (1 GW) units that are either on or off, while at the same time letting the model decide on the optimal amount of nuclear capacity. We tested the model in a case for Northern Europe (seven nodes) with a time resolution of 1250 time steps. Our findings show that nuclear power outages do, in fact, impose a vulnerability on the energy system if not considered in the planning phase. Our proposed model performs well and finds solutions that prevent Loss-of-Load (at a price of robustness of 0.6%), even in more extreme weather conditions. Robust solutions are characterized by a higher capacity of gas plants, but, perhaps surprisingly, nuclear power capacity is barely affected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08145v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamran Forghani, Xiaoming Kan, Lina Reichenberg, Fredrik Hedenus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal protection and vaccination against epidemics with reinfection risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of optimal allocation of vaccination and protection measures for the Susceptible-Infected-Recovered-Infected (SIRI) epidemiological model, which generalizes the classical Susceptible-Infected-Recovered (SIR) and Susceptible-Infected-Susceptible (SIS) epidemiological models by allowing for reinfection. We first introduce the controlled SIRI dynamics, and discuss the existence and stability of the equilibrium points. We then formulate a finite-horizon optimal control problem where the cost of vaccination and protection is proportional to the mass of population that adopts it. Our main contribution in this work arises from a detailed investigation into the existence/non-existence of singular control inputs, and establishing optimality of bang-bang controls, obtained by solving an optimal control problem considering a running cost that is linear with respect to the input variables of limited non-pharmaceutical and medical resources, in an epidemic model with reinfection risk and compromised immunity. In contrast to most prior works, we rigorously establish the non-existence of singular controls, i.e., the optimality of bang-bang control. Under some reasonable conditions, we characterize the structure of both the optimal control inputs, and also that vaccination control input admits a bang-bang structure. Numerical results provide valuable insights into the evolution of the disease spread under optimal control inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08191v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Urmee Maitra (Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur), Ashish R. Hota (Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur), Rohit Gupta (Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay), Alfred O. Hero (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Momentum ADMM for nonconvex and nonsmooth optimization with application to PnP algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a single-loop Stochastic Momentum Alternating Direction Method of Multipliers (SMADMM) for tackling a class of nonconvex and nonsmooth optimization problems. We establish that SMADMM achieves an optimal oracle complexity of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-\frac{3}{2}})$ in the online setting, where only stochastic first-order oracle, is available. In particular, SMADMM requires only $\mathcal{O}(1)$ stochastic gradient evaluations per iteration and avoids the need for restarting with large batch gradient estimates. This is the first stochastic ADMM method achieving optimal oracle complexity for nonconvex and nonsmooth problems, requiring $\mathcal{O}(1)$ batch size. Furthermore, we extend our method by integrating it with plug-and-play (PnP) priors, resulting in the PnP-SMADMM algorithm. Numerical experiments on classification, CT image reconstruction and phase retrieve demonstrate the practical effectiveness of our approach and validate the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08223v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangkang Deng, Shuchang Zhang, Boyu Wang, Jiachen Jin, Juan Zhou, Hongxia Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qualitative properties of solutions to a fractional pseudo-parabolic equation with singular potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the initial boundary value problem for a fractional pseudo-parabolic equation with singular potential. The global existence and blow-up of solutions to the initial boundary value problem are obtained at low initial energy. Moreover, the exponential decay estimates for global solutions and energy functional are further derived, and the upper and lower bounds of both blow-up time and blow-up rate for blow-up solutions are respectively estimated. Specifically, we extend the method for proving blow-up of solutions with negative initial energy in previous literatures to cases involving nonnegative initial energy, which broadens the applicability of this method. Finally, for the corresponding stationary problem, the existence of ground-state solutions is established, and it is proved that the global solutions strongly converge to the solutions of stationary problem as time tends to infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08265v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-kun Shao, Nan-jing Huang, Xue-song Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interior Point Differential Dynamic Programming, Redux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08278v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present IPDDP2, a structure-exploiting algorithm for solving discrete-time, finite horizon optimal control problems with nonlinear constraints. Inequality constraints are handled using a primal-dual interior point formulation and step acceptance for equality constraints follows a line-search filter approach. The iterates of the algorithm are derived under the Differential Dynamic Programming (DDP) framework. Our numerical experiments evaluate IPDDP2 on four robotic motion planning problems. IPDDP2 reliably converges to low optimality error and exhibits local quadratic and global convergence from remote starting points. Notably, we showcase the robustness of IPDDP2 by using it to solve a contact-implicit, joint limited acrobot swing-up problem involving complementarity constraints from a range of initial conditions. We provide a full implementation of IPDDP2 in the Julia programming language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08278v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Xu, Stephen Gould, Iman Shames</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annealed Mean Field Descent Is Highly Effective for Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, formulating various combinatorial optimization problems as Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) has gained significant attention as a promising approach for efficiently obtaining optimal or near-optimal solutions. While QUBO offers a general-purpose framework, existing solvers often struggle with performance variability across different problems.
  This paper (i) theoretically analyzes Mean Field Annealing (MFA) and its variants--which are representative QUBO solvers, and reveals that their underlying self-consistent equations do not necessarily represent the minimum condition of the Kullback-Leibler divergence between the mean-field approximated distribution and the exact distribution, and (ii) proposes a novel method, the Annealed Mean Field Descent (AMFD), which is designed to address this limitation by directly minimizing the divergence.
  Through extensive experiments on five benchmark combinatorial optimization problems (Maximum Cut Problem, Maximum Independent Set Problem, Traveling Salesman Problem, Quadratic Assignment Problem, and Graph Coloring Problem), we demonstrate that AMFD exhibits superior performance in many cases and reduced problem dependence compared to state-of-the-art QUBO solvers and Gurobi--a state-of-the-art versatile mathematical optimization solver not limited to QUBO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08315v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyo Kuroki, Thiem Van Chu, Masato Motomura, Kazushi Kawamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sectoral and spatial decomposition methods for multi-sector capacity expansion models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-sector capacity expansion models play a crucial role in energy planning by providing decision support for policymaking in technology development. To ensure reliable support, these models require high technological, spatial, and temporal resolution, leading to large-scale linear programming problems that are often computationally intractable. To address this challenge, conventional approaches rely on simplifying abstractions that trade accuracy for computational efficiency. Benders decomposition has been widely explored to improve computational efficiency in electricity capacity expansion models. Specifically, state-of-the-art methods have primarily focused on improving performance through temporal decomposition. However, multi-sector models introduce additional complexity, requiring new decomposition strategies. In this work, we propose a budget-based formulation to extend decomposition to the sectoral and spatial domains. We test the developed sectoral and spatial Benders decomposition algorithms on case studies of the continental United States, considering different configurations in terms of spatial and temporal resolution. Results show that our algorithms achieve substantial performance improvement compared to existing decomposition algorithms, with runtime reductions within 15%-70%. The proposed methods leverage the generic structure of multi-sector capacity expansion models, and can thus be applied to most existing energy planning models, ensuring computational tractability without sacrificing resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08503v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Parolin, Yu Weng, Paolo Colbertaldo, Ruaridh Macdonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlled stochastic processes for simulated annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulated annealing solves global optimization problems by means of a random walk in a cooling energy landscape based on the objective function and a temperature parameter. However, if the temperature is decreased too quickly, this procedure often gets stuck in suboptimal local minima. In this work, we consider the cooling landscape as a curve of probability measures. We prove the existence of a minimal norm velocity field which solves the continuity equation, a differential equation that governs the evolution of the aforementioned curve. The solution is the weak gradient of an integrable function, which is in line with the interpretation of the velocity field as a derivative of optimal transport maps. We show that controlling stochastic annealing processes by superimposing this velocity field would allow them to follow arbitrarily fast cooling schedules. Here we consider annealing processes based on diffusions and piecewise deterministic Markov processes. Based on convergent optimal transport-based approximations to this control, we design a novel interacting particle--based optimization method that accelerates annealing. We validate this accelerating behaviour in numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08506v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Molin, Axel Ringh, Moritz Schauer, Akash Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Mode Decomposition for Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an extension of optimal mode decomposition (OMD) for autonomous systems to systems with controls. The extension is developed along the same lines as the extension of dynamic mode decomposition (DMD) to DMD with control (DMDc).
  DMD identifies a linear dynamic system from high-dimensional snapshot data. DMD is often combined with a subsequent reduction by a projection to a truncated basis for the space spanned by the snapshots. In OMD, the identification and reduction are essentially integrated into a single optimization step, thus avoiding the somewhat adhoc decoupled, a posteriori reduction that is necessary if DMD is to be used for model reduction. DMD was devised for autonomous systems and later extended to DMD for systems with control inputs (DMDc). We present the analogous extension of OMD to OMDc, i.e. OMD for systems with control inputs. We illustrate the proposed method with an application to coupled diffusion-equations that model the drying of a wood chip. Reduced models of this type are required for the efficient simulation of industrial drying processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08545v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Mieg, Martin M\"onnigmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal selection of the most informative nodes for a noisy DeGroot model with stubborn agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Finding the optimal subset of individuals to observe in order to obtain the best estimate of the average opinion of a society is a crucial problem in a wide range of applications, including policy-making, strategic business decisions, and the analysis of sociological trends. We consider the opinion vector X to be updated according to a DeGroot opinion dynamical model with stubborn agents, subject to perturbations from external random noise, which can be interpreted as transmission errors. The objective function of the optimization problem is the variance reduction achieved by observing the equilibrium opinions of a subset K of agents. We demonstrate that, under this specific setting, the objective function exhibits the property of submodularity. This allows us to effectively design a Greedy Algorithm to solve the problem, significantly reducing its computational complexity. Simple examples are provided to validate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08622v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberta Raineri, Giacomo Como, Fabio Fagnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deriving the Gradients of Some Popular Optimal Transport Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note, I review entropy-regularized Monge-Kantorovich problem in Optimal Transport, and derive the gradients of several popular algorithms popular in Computational Optimal Transport, including the Sinkhorn algorithms, Wasserstein Barycenter algorithms, and the Wasserstein Dictionary Learning algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08722v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangzhou Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Piecewise Lyapunov Analysis of sub--quadratic SGD: Applications to Robust and Quantile Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08178v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by robust and quantile regression problems, {we investigate the stochastic gradient descent (SGD) algorithm} for minimizing an objective function $f$ that is locally strongly convex with a sub--quadratic tail. This setting covers many widely used online statistical methods. We introduce a novel piecewise Lyapunov function that enables us to handle functions $f$ with only first-order differentiability, which includes a wide range of popular loss functions such as Huber loss. Leveraging our proposed Lyapunov function, we derive finite-time moment bounds under general diminishing stepsizes, as well as constant stepsizes. We further establish the weak convergence, central limit theorem and bias characterization under constant stepsize, providing the first geometrical convergence result for sub--quadratic SGD. Our results have wide applications, especially in online statistical methods. In particular, we discuss two applications of our results. 1) Online robust regression: We consider a corrupted linear model with sub--exponential covariates and heavy--tailed noise. Our analysis provides convergence rates comparable to those for corrupted models with Gaussian covariates and noise. 2) Online quantile regression: Importantly, our results relax the common assumption in prior work that the conditional density is continuous and provide a more fine-grained analysis for the moment bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08178v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixuan Zhang (Lucy),  Dongyan (Lucy),  Huo, Yudong Chen, Qiaomin Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network-assisted Interval Reachability for Systems with Control Barrier Function-Based Safe Controllers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08249v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) have been widely utilized in the design of optimization-based controllers and filters for dynamical systems to ensure forward invariance of a given set of safe states. While CBF-based controllers offer safety guarantees, they can compromise the performance of the system, leading to undesirable behaviors such as unbounded trajectories and emergence of locally stable spurious equilibria. Computing reachable sets for systems with CBF-based controllers is an effective approach for runtime performance and stability verification, and can potentially serve as a tool for trajectory re-planning. In this paper, we propose a computationally efficient interval reachability method for performance verification of systems with optimization-based controllers by: (i) approximating the optimization-based controller by a pre-trained neural network to avoid solving optimization problems repeatedly, and (ii) using mixed monotone theory to construct an embedding system that leverages state-of-the-art neural network verification algorithms for bounding the output of the neural network. Results in terms of closeness of solutions of trajectories of the system with the optimization-based controller and the neural network are derived. Using a single trajectory of the embedding system along with our closeness of solutions result, we obtain an over-approximation of the reachable set of the system with optimization-based controllers. Numerical results are presented to corroborate the technical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08249v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damola Ajeyemi, Saber Jafarpour, Emiliano Dall'Anese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed data-driven control without persistence of excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that data that is not sufficiently informative to allow for system re-identification can still provide meaningful information when combined with external or physical knowledge of the system, such as bounded system matrix norms. We then illustrate how this information can be leveraged for safety and energy minimization problems and to enhance predictions in unmodelled dynamics. This preliminary work outlines key ideas toward using limited data for effective control by integrating physical knowledge of the system and exploiting interpolation conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08484v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martina Vanelli, Julien M. Hendrickx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SME Gender-Related Innovation: A Non-Numerical Trend Analysis Using Positive, Zero, and Negative Quantities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08493v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses gender-related aspects of innovation processes in Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs). Classical analytical and statistical approaches often struggle with the high complexity and insufficient data typical of gender-related innovation studies. We propose a trend-based modelling framework that requires minimal information and uses non-numerical quantifiers: increasing, constant, and decreasing. This approach enables the analysis of ten-dimensional models including variables such as Gender, Product Innovation, Process Innovation, and High-Risk Tolerance. Using trend-based artificial intelligence methods, we identify 13 distinct scenarios and all possible transitions between them. This allows for the evaluation of queries like: Can exports increase while gender parameters remain constant? Two versions of the GASI trend model are presented: the original and an expert-modified version addressing critiques related to scenario transitions. The final model confirms stability and supports the assumption that "no tree grows to heaven." Trend-based modelling offers a practical, interpretable alternative for complex, data-scarce systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08493v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nina Bo\v{c}kov\'a, Barbora Voln\'a, Mirko Dohnal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian optimization for mixed variables using an adaptive dimension reduction process: applications to aircraft design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08682v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multidisciplinary design optimization methods aim at adapting numerical optimization techniques to the design of engineering systems involving multiple disciplines. In this context, a large number of mixed continuous, integer and categorical variables might arise during the optimization process and practical applications involve a large number of design variables. Recently, there has been a growing interest in mixed variables constrained Bayesian optimization but most existing approaches severely increase the number of the hyperparameters related to the surrogate model. In this paper, we address this issue by constructing surrogate models using less hyperparameters. The reduction process is based on the partial least squares method. An adaptive procedure for choosing the number of hyperparameters is proposed. The performance of the proposed approach is confirmed on analytical tests as well as two real applications related to aircraft design. A significant improvement is obtained compared to genetic algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08682v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2514/6.2022-0082</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Paul Saves, Nathalie Bartoli, Youssef Diouane, Thierry Lefebvre, Joseph Morlier, Christophe David, Eric Nguyen Van, S\'ebastien Defoort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surrogate-based optimization of system architectures subject to hidden constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exploration of novel architectures requires physics-based simulation due to a lack of prior experience to start from, which introduces two specific challenges for optimization algorithms: evaluations become more expensive (in time) and evaluations might fail. The former challenge is addressed by Surrogate-Based Optimization (SBO) algorithms, in particular Bayesian Optimization (BO) using Gaussian Process (GP) models. An overview is provided of how BO can deal with challenges specific to architecture optimization, such as design variable hierarchy and multiple objectives: specific measures include ensemble infills and a hierarchical sampling algorithm. Evaluations might fail due to non-convergence of underlying solvers or infeasible geometry in certain areas of the design space. Such failed evaluations, also known as hidden constraints, pose a particular challenge to SBO/BO, as the surrogate model cannot be trained on empty results. This work investigates various strategies for satisfying hidden constraints in BO algorithms. Three high-level strategies are identified: rejection of failed points from the training set, replacing failed points based on viable (non-failed) points, and predicting the failure region. Through investigations on a set of test problems including a jet engine architecture optimization problem, it is shown that best performance is achieved with a mixed-discrete GP to predict the Probability of Viability (PoV), and by ensuring selected infill points satisfy some minimum PoV threshold. This strategy is demonstrated by solving a jet engine architecture problem that features at 50% failure rate and could not previously be solved by a BO algorithm. The developed BO algorithm and used test problems are available in the open-source Python library SBArchOpt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08721v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2514/6.2024-4401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In AIAA Aviation Forum and Ascend 2024 (p. 4401)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jasper Bussemaker, Paul Saves, Nathalie Bartoli, Thierry Lefebvre, Bj\"orn Nagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Budget-Adaptive Allocation Rule for Optimal Computing Budget Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.02377v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simulation-based ranking and selection (R&amp;S) is a popular technique for optimizing discrete-event systems (DESs). It evaluates the mean performance of system designs by simulation outputs and aims to identify the best system design from a set of alternatives by intelligently allocating a limited simulation budget. In R&amp;S, the optimal computing budget allocation (OCBA) is an efficient budget allocation rule that asymptotically maximizes the probability of correct selection (PCS). In this paper, we first show the asymptotic OCBA rule can be recovered by considering a large-scale problem with a specific large budget. Considering a sufficiently large budget can greatly simplify computations, but it also causes the asymptotic OCBA rule ignoring the impact of budget. To address this, we then derive a budget-adaptive rule under the setting where budget is not large enough to simplify computations. The proposed budget-adaptive rule determines the ratio of total budget allocated to designs based on the budget size, and its budget-adaptive property highlights the significant impact of budget on allocation strategy. Based on the proposed budget-adaptive rule, two heuristic algorithms are developed. In the numerical experiments, the superior efficiency of our proposed allocation rule is shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.02377v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zirui Cao, Haowei Wang, Ek Peng Chew, Haobin Li, Kok Choon Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bregman firmly nonexpansive proximal operator for baryconvex optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00928v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a generalization of the proximal operator defined through a convex combination of convex objectives, where the coefficients are updated in a minimax fashion. We prove that this new operator is Bregman firmly nonexpansive with respect to a Bregman divergence that combines Euclidean and information geometries; and that its fixed points are given by the critical points of a certain nonconvex function. Finally, we derive the associated continuous flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00928v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mastane Achab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Methods with Local Steps and Random Reshuffling for Generally Smooth Non-Convex Federated Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02781v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-convex Machine Learning problems typically do not adhere to the standard smoothness assumption. Based on empirical findings, Zhang et al. (2020b) proposed a more realistic generalized $(L_0, L_1)$-smoothness assumption, though it remains largely unexplored. Many existing algorithms designed for standard smooth problems need to be revised. However, in the context of Federated Learning, only a few works address this problem but rely on additional limiting assumptions. In this paper, we address this gap in the literature: we propose and analyze new methods with local steps, partial participation of clients, and Random Reshuffling without extra restrictive assumptions beyond generalized smoothness. The proposed methods are based on the proper interplay between clients' and server's stepsizes and gradient clipping. Furthermore, we perform the first analysis of these methods under the Polyak-{\L} ojasiewicz condition. Our theory is consistent with the known results for standard smooth problems, and our experimental results support the theoretical insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02781v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yury Demidovich, Petr Ostroukhov, Grigory Malinovsky, Samuel Horv\'ath, Martin Tak\'a\v{c}, Peter Richt\'arik, Eduard Gorbunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Fault Detection Trade-off Design with Prior Fault Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20237v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The robustness of fault detection algorithms against uncertainty is crucial in the real-world industrial environment. Recently, a new probabilistic design scheme called distributionally robust fault detection (DRFD) has emerged and received immense interest. Despite its robustness against unknown distributions in practice, current DRFD focuses on the overall detectability of all possible faults rather than the detectability of critical faults that are a priori known. Henceforth, a new DRFD trade-off design scheme is put forward in this work by utilizing prior fault information. The key contribution includes a novel distributional robustness metric of detecting a known fault and a new soft distributionally robust chance constraint that ensures robust detectability. Then a new trade-off design scheme of fault detection under unknown probability distributions is proposed, and this offers a flexible balance between the robustness of detecting known critical faults and the overall detectability against all possible faults. To solve the resulting problem, an exact reformulation is derived and a customized solution algorithm is developed, which includes a sequential optimization procedure and an initialization strategy. Finally, case studies on a simulated three-tank system and a real-world battery cell are carried out to showcase the usefulness of our DRFD method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20237v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulin Feng, Hailang Jin, Steven X. Ding, Hao Ye, Chao Shang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential convergence of general iterative proportional fitting procedures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20264v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the success of Sinkhorn's algorithm for entropic optimal transport, we study convergence properties of iterative proportional fitting procedures (IPFP) used to solve more general information projection problems. We establish exponential convergence guarantees for the IPFP whenever the set of probability measures which is projected onto is defined through constraints arising from linear function spaces. This unifies and extends recent results from multi-marginal, adapted and martingale optimal transport. The proofs are based on strong convexity arguments for the dual problem, and the key contribution is to illuminate the role of the geometric interplay between the subspaces defining the constraints. In this regard, we show that the larger the angle (in the sense of Friedrichs) between the linear function spaces, the better the rate of contraction of the IPFP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20264v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Eckstein, Aziz Lakhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Quadratic Optimization for Solving Expectation Equality Constrained Stochastic Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A sequential quadratic programming method is designed for solving general smooth nonlinear stochastic optimization problems subject to expectation equality constraints. We consider the setting where the objective and constraint function values, as well as their derivatives, are not directly available. The algorithm applies an adaptive step size policy and only relies on objective gradient estimates, constraint function estimates, and constraint derivative estimates to update iterates. Both asymptotic and non-asymptotic convergence properties of the algorithm are analyzed. Under reasonable assumptions, the algorithm generates a sequence of iterates whose first-order stationary measure diminishes in expectation. In addition, we identify the iteration and sample complexity for obtaining a first-order $\varepsilon$-stationary iterate in expectation. The results of numerical experiments demonstrate the efficiency and efficacy of our proposed algorithm compared to a penalty method and an augmented Lagrangian method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09490v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoming Shen, Yang Zeng, Baoyu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Schr\"odinger bridges and Sinkhorn semigroups for log-concave models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15963v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we obtain several new results and developments in the study of entropic optimal transport problems (a.k.a. Schr\"odinger problems) with general reference distributions and log-concave target marginal measures. Our approach combines transportation cost inequalities
  with the theory of Riccati matrix difference equations arising in filtering and optimal control theory. This methodology is partly based on a novel entropic stability of Schr\"odinger bridges and closed form expressions of a class of discrete time algebraic Riccati equations. In the context of regularized entropic transport these techniques provide new sharp entropic map estimates. When applied to the stability of Sinkhorn semigroups, they also yield
  a series of novel contraction estimates in terms of the fixed point of Riccati equations.
  The strength of our approach is that it is applicable to a large class of models arising in machine learning and artificial intelligence algorithms. We illustrate the impact of our results in the context of regularized entropic transport, proximal samplers and diffusion generative models as well as diffusion flow matching models</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15963v5</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Del Moral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasserstein Gradient Flows for Moreau Envelopes of f-Divergences in Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04613v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Commonly used $f$-divergences of measures, e.g., the Kullback-Leibler divergence, are subject to limitations regarding the support of the involved measures. A remedy is regularizing the $f$-divergence by a squared maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) associated with a characteristic kernel $K$. We use the kernel mean embedding to show that this regularization can be rewritten as the Moreau envelope of some function on the associated reproducing kernel Hilbert space. Then, we exploit well-known results on Moreau envelopes in Hilbert spaces to analyze the MMD-regularized $f$-divergences, particularly their gradients. Subsequently, we use our findings to analyze Wasserstein gradient flows of MMD-regularized $f$-divergences. We provide proof-of-the-concept numerical examples for flows starting from empirical measures. Here, we cover $f$-divergences with infinite and finite recession constants. Lastly, we extend our results to the tight variational formulation of $f$-divergences and numerically compare the resulting flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04613v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Stein, Sebastian Neumayer, Nicolaj Rux, Gabriele Steidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonparametric Steady-state Learning for Robust Output Regulation of Nonlinear Output Feedback Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16170v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article addresses the nonadaptive and robust output regulation problem of the general nonlinear output feedback system with error output. The global robust output regulation problem for a class of general output feedback nonlinear systems with an uncertain exosystem and high relative degree can be tackled by constructing a linear generic internal model provided that a continuous nonlinear mapping exists. Leveraging the presented nonadaptive framework facilitates the conversion of the nonlinear robust output regulation problem into a robust nonadaptive stabilization endeavour for the augmented system endowed with Input-to-State Stable dynamics, removing the need for constructing a specific Lyapunov function with positive semidefinite derivatives and the commmonly employed assumption that the nonlinear system should be linear-in-parameter(parameterized) condition. The nonadaptive approach is extended by incorporating the nonparametric learning framework to ensure the feasibility of the nonlinear mapping, which can be classified into a data-driven method. Moreover, the introduced nonparametric learning framework allows the controlled system to learn the dynamics of the steady-state/input behaviour from the signal generated from the internal model with the output error as the feedback. As a result, the nonadaptive/nonparametric approach can be advantageous by guaranteeing convergence of the estimation and tracking error even when the underlying controlled system dynamics are complex or poorly understood. The effectiveness of the theoretical results is illustrated for a benchmark example: a controlled duffing system and two practical examples: a continuously stirred tank reactor and a continuous bioreactor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16170v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shimin Wang, Martin Guay, Richard D. Braatz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Linear Systems and Matrix Norm Approximation via Multi-level Sketched Preconditioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05865v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new class of preconditioned iterative methods for solving linear systems of the form $Ax = b$. Our methods are based on constructing a low-rank Nystr\"om approximation to $A$ using sparse random matrix sketching. This approximation is used to construct a preconditioner, which itself is inverted quickly using additional levels of random sketching and preconditioning. We prove that the convergence of our methods depends on a natural average condition number of $A$, which improves as the rank of the Nystr\"om approximation increases. Concretely, this allows us to obtain faster runtimes for a number of fundamental linear algebraic problems:
  1. We show how to solve any $n\times n$ linear system that is well-conditioned except for $k$ outlying large singular values in $\tilde{O}(n^{2.065} + k^\omega)$ time, improving on a recent result of [Derezi\'nski, Yang, STOC 2024] for all $k \gtrsim n^{0.78}$.
  2. We give the first $\tilde{O}(n^2 + {d_\lambda}^{\omega}$) time algorithm for solving a regularized linear system $(A + \lambda I)x = b$, where $A$ is positive semidefinite with effective dimension $d_\lambda=\mathrm{tr}(A(A+\lambda I)^{-1})$. This problem arises in applications like Gaussian process regression.
  3. We give faster algorithms for approximating Schatten $p$-norms and other matrix norms. For example, for the Schatten 1-norm (nuclear norm), we give an algorithm that runs in $\tilde{O}(n^{2.11})$ time, improving on an $\tilde{O}(n^{2.18})$ method of [Musco et al., ITCS 2018]. All results are proven in the real RAM model of computation. Interestingly, previous state-of-the-art algorithms for most of the problems above relied on stochastic iterative methods, like stochastic coordinate and gradient descent. Our work takes a completely different approach, instead leveraging tools from matrix sketching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05865v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Derezi\'nski, Christopher Musco, Jiaming Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaled Relative Graph Analysis of Lur'e Systems and the Generalized Circle Criterion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18318v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scaled Relative Graphs (SRGs) provide a novel graphical frequency-domain method for the analysis of nonlinear systems. However, we show that the current SRG analysis suffers from a pitfall that limit its applicability in analyzing practical nonlinear systems. We overcome this pitfall by modifying the SRG of a linear time invariant operator, combining the SRG with the Nyquist criterion, and apply our result to Lur'e systems. We thereby obtain a generalization of the celebrated circle criterion, which deals with a broader class of nonlinearities, and provides (incremental) $L_2$-gain performance bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18318v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julius P. J. Krebbekx, Roland T\'oth, Amritam Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Regularity Estimates for Optimal Transport via Entropic Regularisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11382v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a general approach to prove global regularity estimates for quadratic optimal transport using the entropic regularisation of the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11382v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathael Gozlan (MAP5 - UMR 8145), Maxime Sylvestre (CEREMADE)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
