<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC</link>
    <description>math.OC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 05:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical shape and topology optimization of regions supporting the boundary conditions of a physical problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article deals with a particular class of shape and topology optimization problems: the optimized design is a region $G$ of the boundary $\partial \Omega$ of a given domain $\Omega$, which supports a particular type of boundary conditions in the considered physical problem. In our analyses, we develop adapted versions of the notions of shape and topological derivatives, which are classically tailored to functions of a ``bulk'' domain. This leads to two complementary notions of derivatives for a quantity of interest $J(G)$ depending on a region $G \subset \partial \Omega$: on the one hand, we elaborate on the boundary variation method of Hadamard for evaluating the sensitivity of $J(G)$ with respect to ``small'' perturbations of the boundary of $G$ within $\partial \Omega$. On the other hand, we use techniques from asymptotic analysis to appraise the sensitivity of $J(G)$ with respect to the addition of a new connected component to the region $G$, shaped as a ``small'' surface disk. The calculation of both types of derivatives raises original difficulties, which are carefully detailed in a simple mathematical setting based on the conductivity equation. We notably propose formal arguments to calculate our derivatives with a minimum amount of technicality, and show how they can be generalized to handle more intricate problems, arising for instance in the contexts of acoustics and structural mechanics, respectively governed by the Helmholtz and linear elasticity equations. In numerical applications, our derivatives are incorporated into a recent algorithmic framework for tracking arbitrarily dramatic motions of a region $G$ within a fixed ambient surface, which combines the level set method with remeshing techniques to offer a clear, body-fitted discretization of the evolving region. Finally, various 3d numerical examples are presented to illustrate the salient features of our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19510v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Bonnetier, Carlos Brito-Pacheco, Charles Dapogny, Rafael Estevez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cost-optimal Management of a Residential Heating System With a Geothermal Energy Storage Under Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a residential heating system with renewable and non-renewable heat generation and different consumption units and investigate a stochastic optimal control problem for its cost-optimal management. As a special feature, the heating system is equipped with a geothermal storage that enables the intertemporal transfer of thermal energy by storing surplus heat for later use. In addition to the numerous technical challenges, economic issues such as cost-optimal control also play a central role in the design and operation of such systems. The latter leads to challenging mathematical optimization problems, as the response of the storage to charging and discharging decisions depends on the spatial temperature distribution in the storage. We take into account uncertainties regarding randomly fluctuating heat generation from renewable energies and the environmental conditions that determine heat demand and supply. The dynamics of the multidimensional controlled state processes is governed by a partial, a random ordinary and two stochastic differential equations. We first apply a spatial discretization to the partial differential equation and use model reduction techniques to reduce the dimension of the associated system of ordinary differential equations. Finally, a time-discretization leads to a Markov decision process for which we apply a state discretization to determine approximations of the cost-optimal control and the associated value function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19619v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pual Honore Takam, Ralf Wunderlich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum stochastic linear quadratic control theory: Closed-loop solvability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the closed-loop solvability of the quantum stochastic linear quadratic optimal control problem. We derive the Pontryagin maximum principle for the linear quadratic control problem of infinite-dimensional quantum stochastic systems. The equivalence between unique closed-loop solvability for quantum stochastic linear quadratic optimal control problems and the well-posedness of the corresponding quantum Riccati equations is established. Notably, although the quantum Riccati equation is an infinite-dimensional deterministic operator-valued ordinary differential equation, classical methods are not applicable. Inspired by L\"{u} and Zhang's approach [Q. L\"{u} and X. Zhang, Probability Theory and Stochastic Modelling, 101. Springer, Cham, (2021) \&amp; Mem. Amer. Math. Soc. 294 (2024)] to stochastic Riccati equations, we prove the existence and uniqueness of its solutions. The results provide a theoretical foundation for the optimal design of quantum control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19666v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Penghui, Wang Shan, Zhao Shengkai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Linear Consensus Algorithm on Strongly Connected Graph Using Effective Resistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the performance of the linear consensus algorithm on strongly connected graphs using the linear quadratic (LQ) cost as a performance measure.
  In particular, we derive bounds on the LQ cost by leveraging effective resistance. Our results extend previous analyses -- which were limited to reversible cases -- to the nonreversible setting. To facilitate this generalization, we introduce novel concepts, termed the back-and-forth path and the pivot node, which serve as effective alternatives to traditional techniques that require reversibility. Moreover, we apply our approach to geometric graphs to estimate the LQ cost without the reversibility assumption. The proposed approach provides a framework that can be adapted to other contexts where reversibility is typically assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19720v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takumi Yonaiyama, Kazuhiro Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inexact Moreau Envelope Lagrangian Method for Non-Convex Constrained Optimization under Local Error Bound Conditions on Constraint Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the inexact Moreau envelope Lagrangian (iMELa) method for solving smooth non-convex optimization problems over a simple polytope with additional convex inequality constraints. By incorporating a proximal term into the traditional Lagrangian function, the iMELa method approximately solves a convex optimization subproblem over the polyhedral set at each main iteration. Under the assumption of a local error bound condition for subsets of the feasible set defined by subsets of the constraints, we establish that the iMELa method can find an $\epsilon$-Karush-Kuhn-Tucker point with $\tilde O(\epsilon^{-2})$ gradient oracle complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19764v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yankun Huang, Qihang Lin, Yangyang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing Stochastic Matrices for Weighted Averaging in Gossip Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The convergence of the gossip process has been extensively studied; however, algorithms that generate a set of stochastic matrices, the infinite product of which converges to a rank-one matrix determined by a given weight vector, have been less explored. In this work, we propose an algorithm for constructing (local) stochastic matrices based on a given gossip network topology and a set of weights for averaging across different consensus clusters, ensuring that the gossip process converges to a finite limit set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19821v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erkan Bayram, Mohamed-Ali Belabbas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Extremal Principle and Necessary Conditions for Minimizing Sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The conventional definition of extremality of a finite collection of sets is extended by replacing a fixed point (extremal point) in the intersection of the sets by a collection of sequences of points in the individual sets with the distances between the corresponding points tending to zero. This allows one to consider collections of unbounded sets with empty intersection. Exploiting the ideas behind the conventional extremal principle, we derive an extended sequential version of the latter result in terms of Fr\'echet and Clarke normals. Sequential versions of the related concepts of stationarity, approximate stationarity and transversality of collections of sets are also studied. As an application, we establish sequential necessary conditions for minimizing (and more general firmly stationary, stationary and approximately stationary) sequences in a constrained optimization problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19884v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Duy Cuong, Alexander Y. Kruger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Optimal Vaccination Plan in SIR Epidemic Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work focuses on understanding the minimum eradication time for the controlled Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (SIR) model in the time-homogeneous setting, where the infection and recovery rates are constant. The eradication time is defined as the earliest time the infectious population drops below a given threshold and remains below it. For time-homogeneous models, the eradication time is well-defined due to the predictable dynamics of the infectious population, and optimal control strategies can be systematically studied. We utilize Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) to solve the partial differential equation (PDE) governing the eradication time and derive the corresponding optimal vaccination control. The PINN framework enables a mesh-free solution to the PDE by embedding the dynamics directly into the loss function of a deep neural network. We use a variable scaling method to ensure stable training of PINN and mathematically analyze that this method is effective in our setting. This approach provides an efficient computational alternative to traditional numerical methods, allowing for an approximation of the eradication time and the optimal control strategy. Through numerical experiments, we validate the effectiveness of the proposed method in computing the minimum eradication time and achieving optimal control. This work offers a novel application of PINNs to epidemic modeling, bridging mathematical theory and computational practice for time-homogeneous SIR models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19890v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minseok Kim, Yeongjong Kim, Yeoneung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open Problem: Two Riddles in Heavy-Ball Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This short paper presents two open problems on the widely used Polyak's Heavy-Ball algorithm. The first problem is the method's ability to exactly \textit{accelerate} in dimension one exactly. The second question regards the behavior of the method for parameters for which it seems that neither a Lyapunov nor a cycle exists.
  For both problems, we provide a detailed description of the problem and elements of an answer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19916v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Goujaud, Adrien Taylor, Aymeric Dieuleveut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Steepest Descent Methods on Riemannian Manifolds and Hilbert Spaces: Convergence Analysis and Stochastic Extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimization techniques are at the core of many scientific and engineering disciplines. The steepest descent methods play a foundational role in this area. In this paper we studied a generalized steepest descent method on Riemannian manifolds, leveraging the geometric structure of manifolds to extend optimization techniques beyond Euclidean spaces. The convergence analysis under generalized smoothness conditions of the steepest descent method is studied along with an illustrative example. We also explore adaptive steepest descent with momentum in infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces, focusing on the interplay of step size adaptation, momentum decay, and weak convergence properties. Also, we arrived at a convergence accuracy of $O(\frac{1}{k^2})$. Finally, studied some stochastic steepest descent under non-Gaussian noise, where bounded higher-order moments replace Gaussian assumptions, leading to a guaranteed convergence, which is illustrated by an example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19929v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rashid A., Amal A Samad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A differential game approach to intrinsic encirclement control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19933v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the encirclement control problem involving two groups using a non-cooperative differential game approach. The active group seeks to chase and encircle the passive group, while the passive group responds by fleeing cooperatively and simultaneously encircling the active group. Instead of prescribing an expected radius or a predefined path for encirclement, we focus on the whole formation manifold of the desired relative configuration, two concentric circles, by allowing permutation, rotation, and translation of players. The desired relative configurations arise as the steady state resulting from Nash equilibrium strategies and are achieved in an intrinsic way by designing the interaction graphs and weight function of each edge. Furthermore, the asymptotic convergence to the desired manifold is guaranteed. Finally, numerical simulations demonstrate encirclement and counter-encirclement scenarios, verifying the effectiveness of our strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19933v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panpan Zhou, Yueyue Xu, Yibei Li, Bo Wahlberg, Xiaoming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative games defined by multi-objective optimization in competition for subsurface resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel decision making framework for forming potential collaboration among otherwise competing agents in subsurface systems. The agents can be, e.g., groundwater, CO$_2$, or hydrogen injectors and extractors with conflicting goals on a geophysically connected system. The operations of a given agent affect the other agents by induced pressure buildup that may jeopardize system integrity. In this work, such a situation is modeled as a cooperative game where the set of agents is partitioned into disjoint coalitions that define the collaborations. The games are in partition function form with externalities, i.e., the value of a coalition depends on both the coalition itself and on the actions of external agents.
  We investigate the class of cooperative games where the coalition values are the total injection volumes as given by Pareto optimal solutions to multi-objective optimization problems subject to arbitrary physical constraints. For this class of games, we prove that the Pareto set of any coalition structure is a subset of any other coalition structure obtained by splitting coalitions of the first coalition structure. Furthermore, the hierarchical structure of the Pareto sets is used to reduce the computational cost in an algorithm to hierarchically compute the entire Pareto fronts of all possible coalition structures.
  We demonstrate the framework on a pumping wells groundwater example, and nonlinear and realistic CO$_2$ injection cases, displaying a wide range of possible outcomes. Numerical cost reduction is demonstrated for the proposed algorithm with hierarchically computed Pareto fronts compared to independently solving the multi-objective optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19987v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Per Pettersson, Sebastian Krumscheid, Sarah Gasda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified recursive identification algorithm with quantized observations based on weighted least-squares type criteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates system identification problems with Gaussian inputs and quantized observations under fixed thresholds. A new formulation for the predictor of quantized observations is introduced, establishing a linear correlation with the parameter estimations through a probabilistic relationship among quantized observations, Gaussian inputs, and system parameters. Subsequently, a novel weighted least-squares criterion is proposed, and a two-step recursive identification algorithm is constructed, which is capable of addressing both noisy and noise-free linear systems. Convergence analysis of this identification algorithm is conducted, demonstrating convergence in both almost sure and $L^{p}$ senses under mild conditions, with respective rates of $O(\sqrt{ \log \log k/k})$ and $O(1/k^{p/2})$, where $k$ denotes the time step. In particular, this algorithm offers an asymptotically efficient estimation of the variance of Gaussian variables using quantized observations. Additionally, asymptotic normality is established, and an expression for the asymptotic variance is provided when the weight coefficients are properly selected. Furthermore, extensions to output-error systems are discussed, enhancing the applicability and relevance of the proposed methods. Two numerical examples are provided to validate these theoretical advancements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20085v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingrui Liu, Ying Wang, Yanlong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace accelerated measure transport methods for fast and scalable sequential experimental design, with application to photoacoustic imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel approach for sequential optimal experimental design (sOED) for Bayesian inverse problems involving expensive models with large-dimensional unknown parameters. The focus of this work is on designs that maximize the expected information gain (EIG) from prior to posterior, which is a computationally challenging task in the non-Gaussian setting. This challenge is amplified in sOED, as the incremental expected information gain (iEIG) must be approximated multiple times in distinct stages, with both prior and posterior distributions often being intractable. To address this, we derive a derivative-based upper bound for the iEIG, which not only guides design placement but also enables the construction of projectors onto likelihood-informed subspaces, facilitating parameter dimension reduction. By combining this approach with conditional measure transport maps for the sequence of posteriors, we develop a unified framework for sOED, together with amortized inference, scalable to high- and infinite-dimensional problems. Numerical experiments for two inverse problems governed by partial differential equations (PDEs) demonstrate the effectiveness of designs that maximize our proposed upper bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20086v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiangang Cui, Karina Koval, Roland Herzog, Robert Scheichl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential convergence of general iterative proportional fitting procedures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the success of Sinkhorn's algorithm for entropic optimal transport, we study convergence properties of iterative proportional fitting procedures (IPFP) used to solve more general information projection problems. We establish exponential convergence guarantees for the IPFP whenever the set of probability measures which is projected onto is defined through constraints arising from linear function spaces. This unifies and extends recent results from multi-marginal, adapted and martingale optimal transport. The proofs are based on strong convexity arguments for the dual problem, and the key contribution is to illuminate the role of the geometric interplay between the subspaces defining the constraints. In this regard, we show that the larger the angle (in the sense of Friedrichs) between the linear function spaces, the better the rate of contraction of the IPFP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20264v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Eckstein, Aziz Lakhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pontryagin-Bellman Differential Dynamic Programming for Low-Thrust Trajectory Optimization with Path Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new algorithm to solve constrained nonlinear optimal control problem, with an emphasis on low-thrust trajectory in highly nonlinear dynamics. The algorithm, dubbed Pontryagin-Bellman Differential Dynamic Programming (PDDP), is the result of the incorporation of Pontryagin Minimum Principle (PMP) into the Differential Dynamic Programming (DDP) formulation. Unlike traditional indirect methods that rely on first-order shooting techniques to determine the optimal costate, PDDP optimizes the costates using a null-space trust-region method, solving a series of quadratic subproblems derived from first- and second-order sensitivities. Terminal equality constraints are handled via a general augmented Lagrangian method, while state-path constraints are enforced using a quadratic penalty approach. The resulting solution method represents a significant improvement over classical indirect methods, which are known to be ineffective for state-constrained problems. The use of DDP to optimize the costate partially reduces the inherent sensitivities of indirect methods, thereby improving the robustness to poor initial guess. Finally, the incorporation of PMP within the DDP formulation enables the design of long-duration, multi-spiral low-thrust trajectories with fewer optimization variables compared to classical DDP formulations. Although the paper emphasizes the spacecraft low-thrust trajectory optimization problem, the theoretical foundations are general and applicable to any control-affine optimal control problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20291v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanis Sidhoum, Kenshiro Oguri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A systematic literature review on the application of analytical approaches and mathematical programming in public bus transit network design and operations planning: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19430v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Among all public transit modes, bus transit systems stand out as the most prevalent and popular. This prominence has spurred a significant body of research addressing various aspects of bus systems. In the literature, analytical approaches and mathematical programming are predominantly used to explore the Public Bus Transit Network Design Problem and Operations Planning (PBTNDP&amp;OP). Part I of our study presented statistical analyses of literature applying these methodologies to PBTNDP&amp;OP, along with a comprehensive review of analytical papers, highlighting the strengths and weaknesses of each approach. In Part II, we delve into the applications of mathematical programming within PBTNDP&amp;OP, building upon the 15 major sub-categories identified in Part I. We have critically analyzed the identified papers within these sub-categories from various perspectives, including the problems investigated, modeling methods employed, decision variables, network structures, and key findings. This critical review highlights selected papers in each category. Finally, acknowledging existing research gaps, we propose potential extensions for future research. Despite the extensive array of publications, numerous topics still warrant further exploration. Notably, sustainable PBTNDP&amp;OP and challenges associated with integrating emerging technologies are poised to dominate future research agendas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19430v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Mahmoudi, Saeid Saidi, S. Chan Wirasinghe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Interpolation Effect of Score Smoothing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19499v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Score-based diffusion models have achieved remarkable progress in various domains with the ability to generate new data samples that do not exist in the training set. In this work, we examine the hypothesis that their generalization ability arises from an interpolation effect caused by a smoothing of the empirical score function. Focusing on settings where the training set lies uniformly in a one-dimensional linear subspace, we study the interplay between score smoothing and the denoising dynamics with mathematically solvable models. In particular, we demonstrate how a smoothed score function can lead to the generation of samples that interpolate among the training data within their subspace while avoiding full memorization. We also present evidence that learning score functions with regularized neural networks can have a similar effect on the denoising dynamics as score smoothing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19499v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengdao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LORENZA: Enhancing Generalization in Low-Rank Gradient LLM Training via Efficient Zeroth-Order Adaptive SAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19571v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study robust parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) techniques designed to improve accuracy and generalization while operating within strict computational and memory hardware constraints, specifically focusing on large-language models (LLMs). Existing PEFT methods often lack robustness and fail to generalize effectively across diverse tasks, leading to suboptimal performance in real-world scenarios. To address this, we present a new highly computationally efficient framework called AdaZo-SAM, combining Adam and Sharpness-Aware Minimization (SAM) while requiring only a single-gradient computation in every iteration. This is achieved using a stochastic zeroth-order estimation to find SAM's ascent perturbation. We provide a convergence guarantee for AdaZo-SAM and show that it improves the generalization ability of state-of-the-art PEFT methods. Additionally, we design a low-rank gradient optimization method named LORENZA, which is a memory-efficient version of AdaZo-SAM. LORENZA utilizes a randomized SVD scheme to efficiently compute the subspace projection matrix and apply optimization steps onto the selected subspace. This technique enables full-parameter fine-tuning with adaptive low-rank gradient updates, achieving the same reduced memory consumption as gradient-low-rank-projection methods. We provide a convergence analysis of LORENZA and demonstrate its merits for pre-training and fine-tuning LLMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19571v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yehonathan Refael, Iftach Arbel, Ofir Lindenbaum, Tom Tirer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified FOX Optimizer for Solving optimization problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20027v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The FOX optimizer, inspired by red fox hunting behavior, is a powerful algorithm for solving real-world and engineering problems. However, despite balancing exploration and exploitation, it can prematurely converge to local optima, as agent positions are updated solely based on the current best-known position, causing all agents to converge on one location. This study proposes the modified FOX optimizer (mFOX) to enhance exploration and balance exploration and exploitation in three steps. First, the Oppositional-Based Learning (OBL) strategy is used to improve the initial population. Second, control parameters are refined to achieve a better balance between exploration and exploitation. Third, a new update equation is introduced, allowing agents to adjust their positions relative to one another rather than relying solely on the best-known position. This approach improves exploration efficiency without adding complexity. The mFOX algorithm's performance is evaluated against 12 well-known algorithms on 23 classical benchmark functions, 10 CEC2019 functions, and 12 CEC2022 functions. It outperforms competitors in 74% of the classical benchmarks, 60% of the CEC2019 benchmarks, and 58% of the CEC2022 benchmarks. Additionally, mFOX effectively addresses four engineering problems. These results demonstrate mFOX's strong competitiveness in solving complex optimization tasks, including unimodal, constrained, and high-dimensional problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20027v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dler O. Hasan, Hardi M. Mohammed, Zrar Khalid Abdul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Offline Reinforcement Learning via Inverse Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inspired by the recent successes of Inverse Optimization (IO) across various application domains, we propose a novel offline Reinforcement Learning (ORL) algorithm for continuous state and action spaces, leveraging the convex loss function called ``sub-optimality loss" from the IO literature. To mitigate the distribution shift commonly observed in ORL problems, we further employ a robust and non-causal Model Predictive Control (MPC) expert steering a nominal model of the dynamics using in-hindsight information stemming from the model mismatch. Unlike the existing literature, our robust MPC expert enjoys an exact and tractable convex reformulation. In the second part of this study, we show that the IO hypothesis class, trained by the proposed convex loss function, enjoys ample expressiveness and achieves competitive performance comparing with the state-of-the-art (SOTA) methods in the low-data regime of the MuJoCo benchmark while utilizing three orders of magnitude fewer parameters, thereby requiring significantly fewer computational resources. To facilitate the reproducibility of our results, we provide an open-source package implementing the proposed algorithms and the experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20030v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis Dimanidis, Tolga Ok, Peyman Mohajerin Esfahani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast and Robust Reformulation of the UVN-Flash Problem via Direct Entropy Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20173v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the phase equilibrium problem for multicomponent mixtures under specified internal energy (U), volume (V), and mole numbers (N1,N2, . . . ,Nn), commonly known as the UVN-flash problem. While conventional phase equilibrium calculations typically use pressure-temperature-mole number (PTN) specifications, the UVN formulation is essential for dynamic simulations of closed systems and energy balance computations. Existing approaches, including those based on iterative pressure-temperature updates and direct entropy maximization, suffer from computational inefficiencies due to nested iterations and reliance on inner Newton solvers. In this work, we present a novel reformulation of the UVN-flash problem as a direct entropy maximization problem that eliminates the need for inner Newton iterations, addressing key computational bottlenecks. We derive two new novel formulations: 1) a formulation based on entropy and internal energy and (2) an alternative formulation based on Helmholtz free energy. We begin with a stability analysis framework, followed by a reformulation of the UVN flash problem in natural variables. We then introduce our novel approach and discuss the numerical methods used, including gradient and Hessian computations. The proposed method is validated against benchmark cases, demonstrating improved efficiency and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20173v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.13140/RG.2.2.19629.40168</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pardeep Kumar, Patricio I. Rosen Esquivel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform-in-Time Convergence Rates to a Nonlinear Markov Chain for Mean-Field Interacting Jump Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a system of $N$ particles interacting through their empirical distribution on a finite state space in continuous time. In the formal limit as $N\to\infty$, the system takes the form of a nonlinear (McKean--Vlasov) Markov chain. This paper rigorously establishes this limit. Specifically, under the assumption that the mean field system has a unique, exponentially stable stationary distribution, we show that the weak error between the empirical measures of the $N$-particle system and the law of the mean field system is of order $1/N$ uniformly in time. Our analysis makes use of a master equation for test functions evaluated along the measure flow of the mean field system, and we demonstrate that the solutions of this master equation are sufficiently regular. We then show that exponential stability of the mean field system is implied by exponential stability for solutions of the linearized Kolmogorov equation with a source term. Finally, we show that our results can be applied to the study of mean field games and give a new condition for the existence of a unique stationary distribution for a nonlinear Markov chain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20262v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asaf Cohen, Ethan Huffman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Driver Behavior in Speed Advisory Systems: Koopman-based Approach with Online Update</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20347v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate driver behavior modeling is essential for improving the interaction and cooperation of the human driver with the driver assistance system. This paper presents a novel approach for modeling the response of human drivers to visual cues provided by a speed advisory system using a Koopman-based method with online updates. The proposed method utilizes the Koopman operator to transform the nonlinear dynamics of driver-speed advisory system interactions into a linear framework, allowing for efficient real-time prediction. An online update mechanism based on Recursive Least Squares (RLS) is integrated into the Koopman-based model to ensure continuous adaptation to changes in driver behavior over time. The model is validated using data collected from a human-in-the-loop driving simulator, capturing diverse driver-specific trajectories. The results demonstrate that the offline learned Koopman-based model can closely predict driver behavior and its accuracy is further enhanced through an online update mechanism with the RLS method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20347v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehmet Fatih Ozkan, Jeff Chrstos, Marcello Canova, Stephanie Stockar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pontryagin maximum principle for the deterministic mean field type optimal control problem via the Lagrangian approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.01892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.01892v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study necessary optimality conditions for the deterministic mean field type free-endpoint optimal control problem. Our study relies on the Lagrangian approach that treats the mean field type control system as a crowd of infinitely many agents who are labeled by elements of some probability space. First, we derive the Pontryagin maximum principle in the Lagrangian form. Furthermore, we consider the Kantorovich and Eulerian formalizations which describe mean field type control systems via distributions on the set of trajectories and nonlocal continuity equation respectively. We prove that local minimizers in the Kantorovich or Eulerian formulations determine local minimizers within the Lagrangian approach. Using this, we deduce the Pontryagin maximum principle in the Kantorovich and Eulerian forms. To illustrate the general theory, we examine a model system of mean field type linear quadratic regulator. We show that the optimal strategy in this case is determined by a linear feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.01892v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yurii Averboukh, Dmitry Khlopin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quickest detection problem with false negatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.01844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.01844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate and solve a variant of the quickest detection problem which features false negatives. A standard Brownian motion acquires a drift at an independent exponential random time which is not directly observable. Based on the observation in continuous time of the sample path of the process, an optimizer must detect the drift as quickly as possible after it has appeared. The optimizer can inspect the system multiple times upon payment of a fixed cost per inspection. If a test is performed on the system before the drift has appeared then, naturally, the test will return a negative outcome. However, if a test is performed after the drift has appeared, then the test may fail to detect it and return a false negative with probability $\epsilon\in(0,1)$. The optimisation ends when the drift is eventually detected. The problem is formulated mathematically as an optimal multiple stopping problem, and it is shown to be equivalent to a recursive optimal stopping problem. Exploiting such connection and free boundary methods we find explicit formulae for the expected cost and the optimal strategy. We also show that when $\epsilon = 0$ our expected cost is an affine transformation of the one in Shiryaev's classical optimal detection problem with a rescaled model parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.01844v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiziano De Angelis, Jhanvi Garg, Quan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A single player and a mass of agents: a pursuit evasion-like game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.05742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.05742v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a finite-horizon differential game of pursuit-evasion like, between a single player and a mass of agents. The player and the mass directly control their own evolution, which for the mass is given by a first order PDE of transport equation type. Using also an adapted concept of non-anticipating strategies, we derive an infinite dimensional Isaacs equation, and by dynamic programming techniques we prove that the value function is the unique viscosity solution on a suitable invariant subset of a Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.05742v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/cocv/2024009</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ESAIM: Control, Optimisation and Calculus of Variations, 30, 17 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Bagagiolo, Rossana Capuani, Luciano Marzufero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Dimension Reduction Using Semi-Relaxed Gromov-Wasserstein Distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15959v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dimension reduction techniques typically seek an embedding of a high-dimensional point cloud into a low-dimensional Euclidean space which optimally preserves the geometry of the input data. Based on expert knowledge, one may instead wish to embed the data into some other manifold or metric space in order to better reflect the geometry or topology of the point cloud. We propose a general method for manifold-valued multidimensional scaling based on concepts from optimal transport. In particular, we establish theoretical connections between the recently introduced semi-relaxed Gromov-Wasserstein (srGW) framework and multidimensional scaling by solving the Monge problem in this setting. We also derive novel connections between srGW distance and Gromov-Hausdorff distance. We apply our computational framework to analyze ensembles of political redistricting plans for states with two Congressional districts, achieving an effective visualization of the ensemble as a distribution on a circle which can be used to characterize typical neutral plans, and to flag outliers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15959v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranthony A. Clark, Tom Needham, Thomas Weighill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bilevel reinforcement learning via the development of hyper-gradient without lower-level convexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19697v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bilevel reinforcement learning (RL), which features intertwined two-level problems, has attracted growing interest recently. The inherent non-convexity of the lower-level RL problem is, however, to be an impediment to developing bilevel optimization methods. By employing the fixed point equation associated with the regularized RL, we characterize the hyper-gradient via fully first-order information, thus circumventing the assumption of lower-level convexity. This, remarkably, distinguishes our development of hyper-gradient from the general AID-based bilevel frameworks since we take advantage of the specific structure of RL problems. Moreover, we design both model-based and model-free bilevel reinforcement learning algorithms, facilitated by access to the fully first-order hyper-gradient. Both algorithms enjoy the convergence rate $O(\epsilon^{-1})$. To extend the applicability, a stochastic version of the model-free algorithm is proposed, along with results on its iteration and sample complexity. In addition, numerical experiments demonstrate that the hyper-gradient indeed serves as an integration of exploitation and exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19697v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Yang, Bin Gao, Ya-xiang Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremality of families of sets and set-valued optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20473v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper explores a new extremality model involving collections of arbitrary families of sets. We demonstrate its applicability to set-valued optimization problems with general preferences, weakening the assumptions of the known results and streamlining their proofs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20473v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Duy Cuong, Alexander Y. Kruger, Nguyen Hieu Thao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A zero-sum differential game for two opponent masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03860v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate an infinite dimensional partial differential equation of Isaacs' type, which arises from a zero-sum differential game between two masses. The evolution of the two masses is described by a controlled transport/continuity equation, where the control is given by the vector velocity field. Our study is set in the framework of the viscosity solutions theory in Hilbert spaces, and we prove the uniqueness of the value functions as solutions of the Isaacs equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03860v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Bagagiolo, Rossana Capuani, Luciano Marzufero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prevailing against Adversarial Noncentral Disturbances: Exact Recovery of Linear Systems with the $l_1$-norm Estimator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03218v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies the linear system identification problem in the general case where the disturbance is sub-Gaussian, correlated, and possibly adversarial. First, we consider the case with noncentral (nonzero-mean) disturbances for which the ordinary least-squares (OLS) method fails to correctly identify the system. We prove that the $l_1$-norm estimator accurately identifies the system under the condition that each disturbance has equal probabilities of being positive or negative. This condition restricts the sign of each disturbance but allows its magnitude to be arbitrary. Second, we consider the case where each disturbance is adversarial with the model that the attack times happen occasionally but the distributions of the attack values are arbitrary. We show that when the probability of having an attack at a given time is less than 0.5 and each attack spans the entire space in expectation, the $l_1$-norm estimator prevails against any adversarial noncentral disturbances and the exact recovery is achieved within a finite time. These results pave the way to effectively defend against arbitrarily large noncentral attacks in safety-critical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03218v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihun Kim, Javad Lavaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonsmooth rank-one symmetric matrix factorization landscape</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17487v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider nonsmooth rank-one symmetric matrix factorization. It has no spurious second-order stationary points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17487v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Josz, Lexiao Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Physics-informed neural networks loss function regularization with a variance-based term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13993v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In machine learning and statistical modeling, the mean square or absolute error is commonly used as an error metric, also called a "loss function." While effective in reducing the average error, this approach may fail to address localized outliers, leading to significant inaccuracies in regions with sharp gradients or discontinuities. This issue is particularly evident in physics-informed neural networks (PINNs), where such localized errors are expected and affect the overall solution. To overcome this limitation, we propose a novel loss function that combines the mean and the standard deviation of the chosen error metric. By minimizing this combined loss function, the method ensures a more uniform error distribution and reduces the impact of localized high-error regions. The proposed loss function is easy to implement and tested on problems of varying complexity: the 1D Poisson equation, the unsteady Burgers' equation, 2D linear elastic solid mechanics, and 2D steady Navier-Stokes equations. Results demonstrate improved solution quality and lower maximum error compared to the standard mean-based loss, with minimal impact on computational time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13993v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John M. Hanna, Hugues Talbot, Irene E. Vignon-Clementel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic first-order method with multi-extrapolated momentum for highly smooth unconstrained optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14488v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider an unconstrained stochastic optimization problem where the objective function exhibits high-order smoothness. Specifically, we propose a new stochastic first-order method (SFOM) with multi-extrapolated momentum, in which multiple extrapolations are performed in each iteration, followed by a momentum update based on these extrapolations. We demonstrate that the proposed SFOM can accelerate optimization by exploiting the high-order smoothness of the objective function $f$. Assuming that the $p$th-order derivative of $f$ is Lipschitz continuous for some $p\ge2$, and under additional mild assumptions, we establish that our method achieves a sample complexity of $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(\epsilon^{-(3p+1)/p})$ for finding a point $x$ such that $\mathbb{E}[\|\nabla f(x)\|]\le\epsilon$. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first SFOM to leverage arbitrary-order smoothness of the objective function for acceleration, resulting in a sample complexity that improves upon the best-known results without assuming the mean-squared smoothness condition. Preliminary numerical experiments validate the practical performance of our method and support our theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14488v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prescribed-Time and Hyperexponential Concurrent Learning with Partially Corrupted Datasets: A Hybrid Dynamical Systems Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11303v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a class of concurrent learning (CL) algorithms designed to solve parameter estimation problems with convergence rates ranging from hyperexponential to prescribed-time while utilizing alternating datasets during the learning process. The proposed algorithm employs a broad class of dynamic gains, from exponentially growing to finite-time blow-up gains, enabling either enhanced convergence rates or user-prescribed convergence time independent of the dataset's richness. The CL algorithm can handle applications involving switching between multiple datasets that may have varying degrees of richness and potential corruption. The main result establishes convergence rates faster than any exponential while guaranteeing uniform global ultimate boundedness in the presence of disturbances, with an ultimate bound that shrinks to zero as the magnitude of measurement disturbances and corrupted data decreases. The stability analysis leverages tools from hybrid dynamical systems theory, along with a dilation/contraction argument on the hybrid time domains of the solutions. The algorithm and main results are illustrated via a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11303v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel E. Ochoa, Jorge I. Poveda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Multi-Level Optimization for Sequentially Cleared Energy Markets with a Case Study on Gas and Carbon Aware Unit Commitment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper examines Mixed-Integer Multi-Level problems with Sequential Followers (MIMLSF), a specialized optimization model aimed at enhancing upper-level decision-making by incorporating anticipated outcomes from lower-level sequential market-clearing processes. We introduce a novel approach that combines lexicographic optimization with a weighted-sum method to asymptotically approximate the MIMLSF as a single-level problem, capable of managing multi-level problems exceeding three levels. To enhance computational efficiency and scalability, we propose a dedicated Benders decomposition method with multi-level subproblem separability. To demonstrate the practical application of our MIMLSF solution technique, we tackle a unit commitment problem (UC) within an integrated electricity, gas, and carbon market clearing framework in the Northeastern United States, enabling the incorporation of anticipated costs and revenues from gas and carbon markets into UC decisions. This ensures that only profitable gas-fired power plants (GFPPs) are committed, allowing system operators to make informed decisions that prevent GFPP economic losses and reduce total operational costs under stressed electricity and gas systems. The case study not only demonstrates the applicability of the MIMLSF model but also highlights the computational benefits of the dedicated Benders decomposition technique, achieving average reductions of 32.23% in computing time and 94.23% in optimality gaps compared to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13643v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Xia, Iacopo Savelli, Thomas Morstyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Linear Time Projection onto the $\ell_{1,\infty}$ Ball; Application to Sparse Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09836v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Looking for sparsity is nowadays crucial to speed up the training of large-scale neural networks. Projections onto the $\ell_{1,2}$ and $\ell_{1,\infty}$ are among the most efficient techniques to sparsify and reduce the overall cost of neural networks. In this paper, we introduce a new projection algorithm for the $\ell_{1,\infty}$ norm ball. The worst-case time complexity of this algorithm is $\mathcal{O}\big(nm+J\log(nm)\big)$ for a matrix in $\mathbb{R}^{n\times m}$. $J$ is a term that tends to 0 when the sparsity is high, and to $nm$ when the sparsity is low. Its implementation is easy and it is guaranteed to converge to the exact solution in a finite time. Moreover, we propose to incorporate the $\ell_{1,\infty}$ ball projection while training an autoencoder to enforce feature selection and sparsity of the weights. Sparsification appears in the encoder to primarily do feature selection due to our application in biology, where only a very small part ($&lt;2\%$) of the data is relevant. We show that both in the biological case and in the general case of sparsity that our method is the fastest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09836v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Perez, Laurent Condat, Michel Barlaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De Finetti's Control for Refracted Skew Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11471v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we propose a refracted skew Brownian motion as a risk model with endogenous regime switching, which generalizes the refracted diffusion risk process introduced by Gerber and Shiu. We consider an optimal dividend problem for the refracted skew Brownian risk model and identify sufficient conditions, respectively, for barrier strategy, band strategy and their variants to be optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11471v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongqin Gao, Yan Lv, Xiaowen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control of an Impulsive VS-EIAR Epidemic Model with Application to COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00864v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate a VS-EIAR epidemiological model that incorporates vaccinated individuals $\{V_i : i = 1, \ldots, n\}$, where $n \in \mathbb{N}^{*}$. The dynamics of the VS-EIAR model are governed by a system of ordinary differential equations describing the evolution of vaccinated, susceptible, exposed, infected, asymptomatic, and deceased population groups. Our primary objective is to minimize the number of susceptible, exposed, infected, and asymptomatic individuals by administering vaccination doses to susceptible individuals and providing treatment to the infected population. To achieve this, we employ optimal control theory to regulate the epidemic dynamics within an optimal terminal time $\tau^{*}$. Using Pontryagin's Maximum Principle (PMP), we establish the existence of an optimal control pair $(v^{*}(t), u^{*}(t))$. Additionally, we extend the model to an impulsive VS-EIAR framework, with particular emphasis on the impact of immigration and population movement. Finally, we present numerical simulations to validate the theoretical results and demonstrate their practical applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00864v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mamadou Abdoul Diop, Mohammed Elghandouri, Khalil Ezzinbi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cubic regularized subspace Newton for non-convex optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16666v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the optimization problem of minimizing non-convex continuous functions, which is relevant in the context of high-dimensional machine learning applications characterized by over-parametrization. We analyze a randomized coordinate second-order method named SSCN which can be interpreted as applying cubic regularization in random subspaces. This approach effectively reduces the computational complexity associated with utilizing second-order information, rendering it applicable in higher-dimensional scenarios. Theoretically, we establish convergence guarantees for non-convex functions, with interpolating rates for arbitrary subspace sizes and allowing inexact curvature estimation. When increasing subspace size, our complexity matches $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-3/2})$ of the cubic regularization (CR) rate. Additionally, we propose an adaptive sampling scheme ensuring exact convergence rate of $\mathcal{O}(\epsilon^{-3/2}, \epsilon^{-3})$ to a second-order stationary point, even without sampling all coordinates. Experimental results demonstrate substantial speed-ups achieved by SSCN compared to conventional first-order methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16666v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jim Zhao, Aurelien Lucchi, Nikita Doikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training-free Diffusion Model Alignment with Sampling Demons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05760v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aligning diffusion models with user preferences has been a key challenge. Existing methods for aligning diffusion models either require retraining or are limited to differentiable reward functions. To address these limitations, we propose a stochastic optimization approach, dubbed Demon, to guide the denoising process at inference time without backpropagation through reward functions or model retraining. Our approach works by controlling noise distribution in denoising steps to concentrate density on regions corresponding to high rewards through stochastic optimization. We provide comprehensive theoretical and empirical evidence to support and validate our approach, including experiments that use non-differentiable sources of rewards such as Visual-Language Model (VLM) APIs and human judgements. To the best of our knowledge, the proposed approach is the first inference-time, backpropagation-free preference alignment method for diffusion models. Our method can be easily integrated with existing diffusion models without further training. Our experiments show that the proposed approach significantly improves the average aesthetics scores for text-to-image generation. Implementation is available at https://github.com/aiiu-lab/DemonSampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05760v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the Thirteenth International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Po-Hung Yeh, Kuang-Huei Lee, Jun-Cheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
