<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>SAGAbg II: the Low-Mass Star-Forming Sequence Evolves Significantly Between 0.05&lt;z&lt;0.21</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The redshift-dependent relation between galaxy stellar mass and star formation rate (the Star-Forming Sequence, or SFS) is a key observational yardstick for galaxy assembly. We use the SAGAbg-A sample of background galaxies from the Satellites Around Galactic Analogs (SAGA) Survey to model the low-redshift evolution of the low-mass SFS. The sample is comprised of 23258 galaxies with H$\alpha$-based star formation rates (SFRs) spanning $6&lt;\log_{10}(\rm M_\star/[M_\odot])&lt;10$ and $z&lt;0.21$ ($t&lt;2.5$ Gyr). Although it is common to bin or stack galaxies at $z \lesssim 0.2$ for galaxy population studies, the difference in lookback time between $z=0$ and $z=0.21$ is comparable to the time between $z=1$ to $z=2$. We develop a model to account for both the physical evolution of low-mass SFS and the selection function of the SAGA survey, allowing us to disentangle redshift evolution from redshift-dependent selection effects across the SAGAbg-A redshift range. Our findings indicate significant evolution in the SFS over the last 2.5 Gyr, with a rising normalization: $\langle {\rm SFR}({\rm M_\star=10^{8.5} M_\odot)}\rangle(z)=1.24^{+0.25}_{-0.23}\ {\rm z} -1.47^{+0.03}_{-0.03}$. We also identify the redshift limit at which a static SFS is ruled out at the 95% confidence level, which is $z=0.05$ based on the precision of the SAGAbg-A sample. Comparison with cosmological hydrodynamic simulations reveals that some contemporary simulations under-predict the recent evolution of the low-mass SFS. This demonstrates that the recent evolution of the low-mass SFS can provide new constraints on the assembly of the low-mass Universe and highlights the need for improved models in this regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12221v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin Kado-Fong, Marla Geha, Yao-Yuan Mao, Mithi A. C. de los Reyes, Risa H. Wechsler, Benjamin Weiner, Yasmeen Asali, Nitya Kallivayalil, Ethan O. Nadler, Erik J. Tollerud, Yunchong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization of active galactic nuclei with significant VLBI-Gaia displacements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerous studies have reported significant displacements in the coordinates of active galactic nuclei between measurements using radio interferometry techniques and those obtained by the Gaia space observatory. There is a consensus that these discrepancies do indeed manifest astrometrically resolved sub-components of AGN rather than random measurement noise. Among other evidence, it has been reported that AGN with VLBI-to-Gaia displacements (VGD) pointing downstream their parsec-scale radio jets exhibit higher optical polarization compared to sources with the opposite VGD orientation. We aim to verify this previously reported connection between optical polarization and VGD-jet angle using a larger dataset of polarimetric measurements and updated Gaia DR3 positions. We also seek additional evidence supporting the disc-jet dichotomy as an explanation of such a connection by using mm-wave polarization and multi-band optical polarization measurements. We performed optical polarimetric observations of 157 AGN using three telescopes. We cross-match public astrometric data from VLBI and Gaia experiments, obtain corresponding positional displacements, and join this catalog with the polarimetric and jet directions data. AGN with downstream VGD are confirmed to have significantly higher optical fractional polarization than the upstream sample. At the same time, the mm-wavelength polarization of the two samples demonstrates very similar distributions. Our results support the hypothesis that the VLBI-to-Gaia displacements pointing down the radio jet are likely caused by a component in the jet emitting highly polarized synchrotron radiation and dominating in the overall optical emission. The upstream-oriented VGD are likely to be produced by the low-polarized emission of the central engine sub-components dominating in the optical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12226v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry Blinov, Arina Arshinova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SDSS-V Black Hole Mapper Reverberation Mapping Project: A Kinematically Variable Broad-Line Region and Consequences for Masses of Luminous Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12229v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a velocity-resolved reverberation mapping analysis of the hypervariable quasar RM160 (SDSS J141041.25+531849.0) at z = 0.359 with 153 spectroscopic epochs of data representing a ten-year baseline (2013-2023). We split the baseline into two regimes based on the 3x flux increase in the light curve: a 'low state' phase during the years 2013-2019 and a 'high state' phase during the years 2022-2023. The velocity-resolved lag profiles (VRLP) indicate that gas with different kinematics dominates the line emission in different states. The H\b{eta} VRLP begins with a signature of inflow onto the BLR in the 'low state', while in the 'high state' it is flatter with less signature of inflow. The H{\alpha} VRLP begins consistent with a virialized BLR in the 'low state', while in the 'high state' shows a signature of inflow. The differences in the kinematics between the Balmer lines and between the 'low state' and the 'high state' suggests complex BLR dynamics. We find that the BLR radius and velocity (both FWHM and {\sigma}) do not obey a constant virial product throughout the monitoring period. We find that BLR lags and continuum luminosity are correlated, consistent with rapid response of the BLR gas to the illuminating continuum. The BLR kinematic profile changes in unpredictable ways that are not related to continuum changes and reverberation lag. Our observations indicate that non-virial kinematics can significantly contribute to observed line profiles, suggesting caution for black-hole mass estimation in luminous and highly varying quasars like RM160.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12229v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Logan B. Fries, Jonathan R. Trump, Keith Horne, Megan C. Davis, Catherine J. Grier, Yue Shen, Scott F. Anderson, Tom Dwelly, Y. Homayouni, Sean Morrison, Jessie C. Runnoe, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Roberto J. Assef, Dmitry Bizyaev, W. N. Brandt, Peter Breiding, Joel Browstein, Priyanka Chakraborty, P. B. Hall, Anton M. Koekemoer, H\'ector J. Ibarra-Medel, Mary Loli Mart\'inez-Aldama, C. Alenka Negrete, Kaike Pan, Claudio Ricci, Donald P. Scheider, Hugh W. Sharp, Theodore B. Smith, Zachary Stone, Matthew J. Temple</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UNCOVERing the High-Redshift AGN Population Among Extreme UV Line Emitters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: JWST has revealed diverse new populations of high-redshift ($z\sim4-11$) AGN and extreme star-forming galaxies that challenge current models. In this paper, we use rest-frame UV emission-line diagnostics to identify AGN candidates and other exceptional ionizing sources, complementing previous studies predominantly focused on broad-line AGN. In this paper, we use rest-frame UV emission-line diagnostics to identify AGN candidates and other exceptional ionizing sources, complementing previous studies predominantly focused on broad-line AGN. From a parent sample of 205 $\mathrm{z_{spec}}&gt;3$ UNCOVER galaxies with NIRSpec/PRISM follow-up, we identify 12 C IV, He II, and C III] emitters. Leveraging the combined rest-optical and UV coverage of PRISM, we limit the emission-line model space using the sample's [O III]/H$\beta$ distribution, significantly decreasing the overlap between AGN and star-formation models in the UV diagnostics. We then find that the five He II emitters are the strongest AGN candidates, with further support from two [Ne V] detections and one X-ray detection from Chandra. We cannot robustly quantify the AGN fraction in this sample, but we note that close to 20% of $\mathrm{M_{*}&gt;2\times10^{9}\,M_{\odot}}$ parent sample galaxies are AGN candidates. The lower-mass line emitters, which are consistent with both AGN and star-forming photoionization models, have more compact sizes and higher specific star formation rates than the parent sample. Higher-resolution and deeper data on these UV line emitters should provide much stronger constraints on the obscured AGN fraction at $z &gt; 3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12232v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helena Treiber, Jenny Greene, John R. Weaver, Tim B. Miller, Lukas J. Furtak, David J. Setton, Bingjie Wang, Anna de Graaff, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Sam E. Cutler, Pratika Dayal, Robert Feldmann, Seiji Fujimoto, Andy D. Goulding, Vasily Kokorev, Ivo Labbe, Joel Leja, Danilo Marchesini, Themiya Nanayakkara, Erica Nelson, Richard Pan, Sedona H. Price, Jared Siegel, Katherine Suess, Katherine Whitaker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NH3 (1,1) hyperfine intensity anomalies in infall sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identifying infall motions is crucial for our understanding of accretion processes in regions of star formation. The NH3 (1,1) hyperfine intensity anomaly (HIA) has been proposed to be a readily usable tracer for such infall motions in star-forming regions harboring young stellar objects at very early evolutionary stages. In this paper, we seek to study the HIA toward fifteen infall candidate regions to assess its reliability as an infall tracer. By using deep observations of the NH3 (1,1) transition with the Effelsberg 100 m telescope, HIAs have been identified toward all the targets. Fourteen out of fifteen sources exhibit anomalous intensities either in the inner or outer satellite lines. All the derived HIAs conform to the framework of the existing two models, namely, hyperfine selective trapping (HST) and systematic contraction or expansion motion (CE) models. In our sample of infall candidates, a majority of the HIAs remain consistent with the HST model. Only in three targets, the HIAs are consistent with infall motions under the CE model. Thus HIAs could be used as an infall tracer but seem not highly sensitive to infall motions in our single-dish data. Nevertheless, the emission could be blended with emission from outflow activities. HIAs consistent with the HST model show stronger anomalies with increasing kinetic temperatures (Tk), which is expected by the HST model. On the other hand, HIAs consistent with infall motions show little dependence on Tk. Therefore, HIAs may preferably trace infall of cold gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12233v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Wu, Christian Henkel, Dongdong Zhou, Friedrich Wyrowski, Karl M. Menten, Jarken Esimbek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BASS. XLIII: Optical, UV, and X-ray emission properties of unobscured Swift/BAT active galactic nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present one of the largest multiwavelength studies of simultaneous optical-to-X-ray spectral energy distributions (SEDs) of unobscured active galactic nuclei (AGN) in the local Universe. Using a representative sample of hard-X-ray-selected AGN from the 70-month Swift/BAT catalog, with optical/UV photometric data from Swift/UVOT and X-ray spectral data from Swift/XRT, we constructed broadband SEDs of 236 nearby AGN (0.001&lt;z&lt;0.3). We employed GALFIT to estimate host galaxy contamination in the optical/UV and determine the intrinsic AGN fluxes. We used an absorbed power law with a reflection component to model the X-ray spectra and a dust-reddened multi-temperature blackbody to fit the optical/UV SED. We calculated total bolometric luminosities ($L_{bol}$), optical-to-X-ray spectral indices ($\alpha_{ox}$), and multiple bolometric corrections (BCs) in the optical, UV, and X-rays. We used black hole masses obtained by reverberation mapping and the virial method to estimate Eddington ratios ($\lambda_{Edd}$) for all our AGN. We confirm the tight correlation between UV and X-ray luminosity for our sample. We observe a significant decrease in $\alpha_{ox}$ with $L_{bol}$ and $\lambda_{Edd}$, suggesting that brighter sources emit more UV photons per X-rays. We report a second-order regression relation between the 2-10 keV BC and $\alpha_{ox}$, which is useful to compute $L_{bol}$ in the absence of multiband SEDs. We also investigate the dependence of optical/UV BCs on the physical properties of AGN and obtain a significant increase in the UV BCs with $L_{bol}$ and $\lambda_{Edd}$, unlike those in the optical, which are constant across five orders of $L_{bol}$ and $\lambda_{Edd}$. We obtain significant dispersions (~0.1-1 dex) in all BCs, and hence recommend using appropriate relations with observed quantities while including the reported scatter, instead of their median values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12239v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kriti K. Gupta, Claudio Ricci, Matthew J. Temple, Alessia Tortosa, Michael J. Koss, Roberto J. Assef, Franz E. Bauer, Richard Mushotzy, Federica Ricci, Yoshihiro Ueda, Alejandra F. Rojas, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Chin-Shin Chang, Kyuseok Oh, Ruancun Li, Taiki Kawamuro, Yaherlyn Diaz, Meredith C. Powell, Daniel Stern, C. Megan Urry, Fiona Harrison, Brad Cenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving constraints on the extended mass distribution in the Galactic Center with stellar orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studying the orbital motion of stars around Sagittarius A* in the Galactic Center provides a unique opportunity to probe the gravitational potential near the supermassive black hole at the heart of our Galaxy. Interferometric data obtained with the GRAVITY instrument at the Very Large Telescope Interferometer (VLTI) since 2016 has allowed us to achieve unprecedented precision in tracking the orbits of these stars. GRAVITY data have been key to detecting the in-plane, prograde Schwarzschild precession of the orbit of the star S2, as predicted by General Relativity. By combining astrometric and spectroscopic data from multiple stars, including S2, S29, S38, and S55 - for which we have data around their time of pericenter passage with GRAVITY - we can now strengthen the significance of this detection to an approximately $10 \sigma$ confidence level. The prograde precession of S2's orbit provides valuable insights into the potential presence of an extended mass distribution surrounding Sagittarius A*, which could consist of a dynamically relaxed stellar cusp comprised of old stars and stellar remnants, along with a possible dark matter spike. Our analysis, based on two plausible density profiles - a power-law and a Plummer profile - constrains the enclosed mass within the orbit of S2 to be consistent with zero, establishing an upper limit of approximately $1200 \, M_\odot$ with a $1 \sigma$ confidence level. This significantly improves our constraints on the mass distribution in the Galactic Center. Our upper limit is very close to the expected value from numerical simulations for a stellar cusp in the Galactic Center, leaving little room for a significant enhancement of dark matter density near Sagittarius A*.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12261v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The GRAVITY Collaboration, Karim Abd El Dayem, Roberto Abuter, Nicolas Aimar, Pau Amaro Seoane, Antonio Amorim, Julie Beck, Jean Philippe Berger, Henri Bonnet, Guillaume Bourdarot, Wolfgang Brandner, Vitor Cardoso, Roberto Capuzzo Dolcetta, Yann Cl\'enet, Ric Davies, Tim de Zeeuw, Antonia Drescher, Andreas Eckart, Frank Eisenhauer, Helmut Feuchtgruber, Gert Finger, Natascha M. F\"orster Schreiber, Arianna Foschi, Feng Gao, Paulo Garcia, Eric Gendron, Reinhard Genzel, Stefan Gillessen, Michael Hartl, Xavier Haubois, Frank Haussman, Gernot Hei{\ss}el, Thomas Hennig, Stefan Hippler, Matthew Horrobin, Lieselotte Jochum, Laurent Jocou, Andreas Kaufer, Pierre Kervella, Sylvestre Lacour, Vincent Lapeyr\`ere, Jean B. Le Bouquin, Pierre L\'ena, Dieter Lutz, Felix Mang, Nikhil More, Thomas Ott, Thibaut Paumard, Karine Perraut, Guy Perrin, Oliver Pfuhl, Sebastien Rabien, Diogo C. Ribeiro, Matteo Sadun Bordoni, Silvia Scheithauer, Jinyi Shangguan, Taro Shimizu, Julia Stadler, Odele Straub, Christian Straubmeier, Eckhard Sturm, Linda J. Tacconi, Irene Urso, Frederic Vincent, Sebastiano D. Von Fellenberg, Felix Widmann, Ekkehard Wieprecht, Julien Woillez, Fupeng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INSPIRE: INvestigating Stellar Population In RElics -- VII. The local environment of ultra-compact massive galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Relic galaxies, the oldest ultra-compact massive galaxies (UCMGs), contain almost exclusively "pristine" stars formed during an intense star formation (SF) burst at high redshift. As such, they allow us to study in detail the early mechanism of galaxy assembly in the Universe. Using the largest catalogue of spectroscopically confirmed UCMGs for which a degree of relicness (DoR) had been estimated, the INSPIRE catalogue, we investigate whether or not relics prefer dense environments. The objective of this study is to determine if the DoR, which measures how extreme the SF history was, and the surrounding environment are correlated. In order to achieve this goal, we employ the AMICO galaxy cluster catalogue to compute the probability for a galaxy to be a member of a cluster, and measure the local density around each UCMG using machine learning-based photometric redshifts. We find that UCMGs can reside both in clusters and in the field, but objects with very low DoR (&lt; 0.3, i.e., a relatively extended SF history) prefer under-dense environments. We additionally report a correlation between the DoR and the distance from the cluster centre: more extreme relics, when located in clusters, tend to occupy the more central regions of them. We finally outline potential evolution scenarios for UCMGs at different DoR to reconcile their presence in both clusters and field environments</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12288v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diana Scognamiglio, Chiara Spiniello, Mario Radovich, Crescenzo Tortora, Nicola R. Napolitano, Rui Li, Matteo Maturi, Michalina Maksymowicz-Maciata, Michele Cappellari, Magda Arnaboldi, Davide Bevacqua, Lodovico Coccato, Giuseppe D'Ago, Hai-Cheng Feng, Anna Ferr\'e-Mateu, Johanna Hartke, Ignacio Mart\'in-Navarro, Claudia Pulsoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Background Interstellar Medium as Observed from Off-Order Low-Resolution Spitzer-IRS Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spitzer 'hidden' observations of the background are used to construct a catalog of 4,090 spectra and examine the signature of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) molecules and their connection to extinction by dust. A strong positive correlation is recovered between WISE12, E(B-V), and the 11.2 $\mu$m PAH band. For 0.06 $\leq$ E(B-V) $\leq$ 5.0, correlations of the 6.2, 11.2, and 12.7 $\mu$m PAH band are positive with E(B-V). Three dust temperature regimes are revealed. Correlations with WISE12 are well-constrained and that with 12.7/11.2 is flat. Decomposition with the NASA Ames PAH IR Spectroscopic Database reveals a tentative positive correlation between the 6.2/11.2 and the PAH ionization fraction, while that with 12.7/11.2 is slightly negative, suggesting PAH structural changes. The relation with PAH size and 6.2/11.2 is negative, while that with 12.7/11.2 is positive. Averaging spectra into five E(B-V) and three T$_{\rm dust}$ bins shows an evolution in PAH emission and variations in 12.7/11.2. Database-fits show an increase in $f_{\rm i}$ and the PAH ionization parameter $\gamma$, but a more stable large PAH fraction. While the largest $\gamma$s are associated with the highest T$_{\rm dust}$, there is no one-to-one correlation. The analysis is hampered by low-quality data at short wavelengths. There are indications that PAHs in the more-diffuse backgrounds behave differently from those in the general interstellar medium. However, they are often still associated with larger scale filamentary cloud-like structures. The spectra and auxiliary data have been made available through the Ames Background Interstellar Medium Spectral Catalog and may guide JWST programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12324v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christiaan Boersma, Jesse D. Bregman, Louis J. Allamandola, Pasquale Temi, Alexandros Maragkoudakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star cluster formation from turbulent clumps. IV. Protoplanetary disc evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most stars are born in the crowded environments of gradually forming star clusters. Dynamical interactions between close-passing stars and the evolving UV radiation fields from proximate massive stars are expected to sculpt the protoplanetary discs in these clusters, potentially contributing to the diversity of planetary systems that we observe. Here, we investigate the impact of cluster environment on disc demographics by implementing simple protoplanetary disc evolution models within $N$-body simulations of gradual star cluster formation. We consider a range of star formation efficiency per free-fall time, $\epsilon_{\rm ff}$, and mass surface density of the natal cloud environment, $\Sigma_{\rm cl}$, both of which affect the overall duration of cluster formation. We track the interaction history of all stars to estimate the dynamical truncation of the discs around stars involved in close encounters. We also track external photoevaporation of the discs due to the ionizing radiation field of the nearby high- and intermediate-mass ($&gt; 5 M_\odot$) stars. We find that $\epsilon_{\rm ff}$, $\Sigma_{\rm cl}$, and the degree of primordial binarity have major influences on the masses and radii of the disc population. In particular, external photo-evaporation has a greater impact than dynamical interactions in determining the fate of discs in our clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12378v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aayush Gautam, Juan P. Farias, Jonathan C. Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DIISC Survey: Deciphering the Interplay Between the Interstellar Medium, Stars, and the Circumgalactic Medium Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Deciphering the Interplay between the Interstellar medium, Stars, and the Circumgalactic medium (DIISC) Survey. This survey is designed to investigate the correlations in properties between the circumgalactic medium (CGM), the interstellar medium (ISM), stellar distributions, and young star-forming regions. The galaxies were chosen to have a QSO sightline within 3.5 times the HI radii probing the disk-CGM interface. The sample contains 34 low-redshift galaxies with a median stellar mass of 10$^{10.45}~\rm M_{\odot}$ probed at a median impact parameter of $\rho=55~kpc$. The survey combines ultraviolet spectroscopic data from the Cosmic Origins Spectrograph aboard the Hubble Space Telescope with HI 21 cm hyperfine transition imaging with the Very Large Array (VLA), ultraviolet imaging from Galaxy Evolution Explorer (GALEX), and optical imaging and spectroscopy with the MMT and Vatican Advanced Technology Telescope. We describe the specific goals of the survey, data reduction, high-level data products, and some early results. We present the discovery of a strong inverse correlation, at a confidence level of 99.99%, between Lyman $\alpha$ equivalent width, $\rm W_{Ly\alpha}$, and impact parameter normalized by the HI radius ($\rho/R_{HI}$). We find $\rho/R_{HI}$ to be a better empirical predictor of Lyman $\alpha$ equivalent width than virial radius normalized impact parameter ($\rho/R_{vir}$) or parameterizations combining $\rho,~R_{vir}$, stellar mass, and star formation rate. We conclude that the strong anticorrelation between the Lyman $\alpha$ equivalent width and $\rho/R_{HI}$ indicates that the neutral gas distribution of the CGM is more closely connected to the galaxy's gas disk rather than its stellar and dark matter content.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12554v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanchayeeta Borthakur, Mansi Padave, Timothy Heckman, Hansung B. Gim, Alejandro J. Olvera, Brad Koplitz, Emmanuel Momjian, Rolf A. Jansen, David Thilker, Guinevere Kauffman, Andrew J. Fox, Jason Tumlinson, Robert C. Kennicutt, Dylan Nelson, Jacqueline Monckiewicz, Thorsten Naab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemical evolution of a young super star cluster at the Sunburst Arc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observations of high-redshift galaxies have revealed starburst galaxies with excessive amounts of nitrogen, well above that expected in standard evolutionary models. The Sunburst Arc galaxy, particularly its young and massive star cluster, represents the closest ($z=2.4$) and brightest of these as a strongly lensed object. In this work, we study the chemical history of this star cluster to determine the origin of the elevated gas-phase nitrogen using a chemical evolution model. Our model includes the enrichment of OB stars through stellar winds and core-collapse supernovae assuming that massive stars ($M&gt;25$ $M_\odot$) collapse directly into black holes at the end of their lives. We fit the model parameters to the observed chemical abundances of the Sunburst Arc cluster: O/H, C/O, and N/O. We find that the observed chemical abundances can be explained by models featuring intense star formation events, characterized by rapid gas accretion and high star formation efficiencies. Additionally, the stellar population contributing to the gas enrichment must exclude Wolf-Rayet stars. These conditions might be present in other nitrogen-rich objects as their similar chemical abundances suggest a common history. As previous studies have proposed the presence of Wolf-Rayet stars in the new nitrogen-rich objects, further research using chemodynamic modeling is necessary to ascertain the true nature of these objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12605v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Truman Tapia, Kenji Bekki, Brent Groves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Formaldehyde Masers II: Effects of an HII region and Beaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present new results of a numerical study of the pumping of 4.8 GHz and 14.5 GHz maser of o-Formaldehyde in the presence of a free-free radiation field. It is shown that in the presence of a free-free radiation field inversion of not only the 4.8 GHz transition, but also the 14.5 GHz transition and other doublet state transitions occur. Further results are presented to illustrate how, as a consequence of the pumping scheme, the inversion of the 4.8 GHz and 14.5 GHz transitions respond to the free-free radiation fields associated with HII regions with different emission measures and levels of geometric dilution with respect to the masing region. We also discuss the criticism raised in the past by various authors against the pumping of the 4.8 GHz Formaldehyde masers by a free-free radiation field. It is argued that the rarity of the Formaldehyde masers is not to be ascribed to the pumping scheme but to other factors such as, e.g., the evolution of the associated HII region or the chemical evolution of the star forming region which determines the Formaldehyde abundance or a combination of both.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12637v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>DJ van der Walt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotationally inelastic rate coefficients for C$_7$N$^{-}$ and C$_{10}$H$^{-}$ anions in collision with H$_2$ at interstellar conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The anions C$_7$N$^-$ and C$_{10}$H$^-$ are the two longest of the linear (C,N)-bearing and (C,H)-bearing chains which have so far been detected in the Interstellar Medium. In order to glean information on their collision-induced rotational state-changing processes, we analyse the general features of new ab initio potentials describing the interaction of both linear anions with H$_2$, one of the most abundant partners in their ISM environment. We employ an artificial neural network fit of the reduced-dimensionality potential energy surface for C$_7$N$^-$...H$_2$ interaction and discuss in detail the spatial features in terms of multipolar radial coefficients. For the C$_{10}$H$^-$...H$_2$ interaction we use the initial grid of two dimensional raw points to generate by quadrature the Legendre expansion directly, further including the long-range terms as discussed in the main text. Quantum scattering calculations are employed to obtain rotationally inelastic cross sections, for collision energies in the range of 10$^{-4}$ to 400 cm$^{-1}$. From them we generate the corresponding inelastic rate coefficients as a function of temperature covering the range from 10 to 50 K. The results for the rate coefficients for the longest cyanopolyyne are compared with the earlier results obtained for the smaller terms of the same series, also in collision with H$_2$. We obtain that the inelastic rate coefficients for the long linear anions are all fairly large compared with the earlier systems. The consequences of such findings on their non-equilibrium rotational populations in interstellar environments are illustrated in our conclusions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12685v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Giri, L. Gonz\'alez-S\'anchez, F. A. Gianturco, U. Lourderaj, A. Mart\'in Santa Mar\'ia, S. Rana, N. Sathyamurthy, E. Yurtsever, R. Wester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conference Summary: Stellar Feedback in the ISM: Celebrating the Life and Work of You-Hua Chu</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this conference summary I first provide some historical notes on my own collaboration with You-Hua Chu and on the discovery of X-rays from superbubbles by Margarita Rosado S. I then consider the central subject of the conference, stellar feedback, and how interactions between stellar winds and the interstellar medium can limit or enhance the effects of feedback compared to models including only supernova explosions. Finally, I review results in other areas covered by the conference, including planet and star formation, nova and supernova remnants, different topics in stellar evolution and interaction with the interstellar medium, star clusters, observational surveys, and observational and numerical techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12838v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mordecai-Mark Mac Low (American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confirmation of interstellar phosphine towards asymptotic giant branch star IRC+10216</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phosphorus (P) is an important element for the chemical evolution of galaxies and many kinds of biochemical reactions. Phosphorus is one of the crucial chemical compounds in the formation of life on our planet. In an interstellar medium, phosphine (PH$_{3}$) is a crucial biomolecule that plays a major role in understanding the chemistry of phosphorus-bearing molecules, particularly phosphorus nitride (PN) and phosphorus monoxide (PO), in the gas phase or interstellar grains. We present the first confirmed detection of phosphine (PH$_{3}$) in the asymptotic giant branch (AGB) carbon-rich star IRC+10216 using the Atacama Large Millimeter/Submillimeter Array (ALMA) band 6. We detect the $J$ = 1$_{0}$$-$0$_{0}$ rotational transition line of PH$_{3}$ with a signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of $\geq$3.5$\sigma$. This is the first confirmed detection of phosphine (PH$_{3}$) in the ISM. Based on LTE spectral modelling, the column density of PH$_{3}$ is (3.15$\pm$0.20)$\times$10$^{15}$ cm$^{-2}$ at an excitation temperature of 52$\pm$5 K. The fractional abundance of PH$_{3}$ with respect to H$_{2}$ is (8.29$\pm$1.37)$\times$10$^{-8}$. We also discuss the possible formation pathways of PH$_{3}$ and we claim that PH$_{3}$ may be created via the hydrogenation of PH$_{2}$ on the grain surface of IRC+10216.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12907v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arijit Manna, Sabyasachi Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Broadband Spectral State in the Ultraluminous X-ray Source Holmberg IX X-1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a series of five new broadband X-ray observations of the ultraluminous X-ray source Holmberg IX X-1, performed by $XMM$-$Newton$ and $NuSTAR$ in coordination. The first three of these show high soft X-ray fluxes but a near total collapse of the high-energy ($\gtrsim$15 keV) emission, previously seen to be surprisingly stable across all prior broadband observations of the source. The latter two show a recovery in hard X-rays, remarkably once again respecting the same stable high-energy flux exhibited by all of the archival observations. We also present a joint analysis of all broadband observations of Holmberg IX X-1 to date (encompassing 11 epochs in total) in order to investigate whether it shows the same luminosity-temperature behaviour as NGC 1313 X-1 (which also shows a stable high-energy flux), whereby the hotter disc component in the spectrum exhibits two distinct, positively-correlated tracks in the luminosity-temperature plane. Holmberg IX X-1 may show similar behaviour, but the results depend on whether the highest energy emission is assumed to be an up-scattering corona or an accretion column. The strongest evidence for this behaviour is found in the former case, while in the latter the new 'soft' epochs appear distinct from the other high-flux epochs. We discuss possible explanations for these new 'soft' spectra in the context of the expected structure of super-Eddington accretion flows around black holes and neutron stars, and highlight a potentially interesting analogy with the recent destruction and re-creation of the corona seen in the AGN 1ES 1927+654.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12241v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. J. Walton, M. Bachetti, P. Kosec, F. Furst, C. Pinto, T. P. Roberts, R. Soria, D. Stern, W. N. Alston, M. Brightman, H. P. Earnshaw, A. C. Fabian, F. A. Harrison, M. J. Middleton, R. Sathyaprakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-regulation of high-redshift black hole accretion via jets: challenges for SMBH formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12250v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The early growth of black holes (BHs) in atomic-cooling halos is likely influenced by feedback on the surrounding gas. While the effects of radiative feedback are well-documented, mechanical feedback, particularly from AGN jets, has been comparatively less explored. Building on our previous work that examined the growth of a 100 ${M_\odot}$ BH in a constant density environment regulated by AGN jets, we expand the initial BH mass range from 1 to $10^4$ ${M_\odot}$ and adopt a more realistic density profile for atomic-cooling halos. We reaffirm the validity of our analytic models for jet cocoon propagation and feedback regulation. We identify several critical radii-namely, the terminal radius of jet cocoon propagation, the isotropization radius of the jet cocoon, and the core radius of the atomic-cooling halo-that are crucial in determining BH growth given specific gas properties and jet feedback parameters. In a significant portion of the parameter space, our findings show that jet feedback substantially disrupts the halo's core during the initial feedback episode, preventing BH growth beyond $10^4$ ${M_\odot}$. Conversely, conditions characterized by low jet velocities and high gas densities enable sustained BH growth over extended periods. We provide a prediction for the black hole mass growth as a function of time and feedback parameters. We found that, to form a supermassive BH ($&gt;10^6 {M_\odot}$) within 1 Gyr entirely by accreting gas from an atomic-cooling halo, the jet energy feedback efficiency must be $\lesssim 10^{-4} \dot{M}_{BH} c^2$ even if the seed BH mass is $10^4 {M_\odot}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12250v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kung-Yi Su, Greg Bryan, Zolt\'an Haiman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parsec-scale jet direction evolution in AGNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12309v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the variability of the parsec-scale jet directions in active galactic nuclei (AGNs). Our analysis involves 317 AGNs at frequencies ranging from 2 to 43 GHz, and is made possible by developing an automatic inner jet direction measurement procedure. We find strong significant variations in a one quarter of these AGNs; the effect is likely ubiquitous, and not detected in the rest due to a limited sensitivity and observations epoch coverage. Average apparent jet rotation speeds range from 0.21 deg/yr at 2 GHz to 1.04 deg/yr at 43 GHz. This strong frequency dependence indicates that the variability cannot be explained by jet components propagating ballistically without acceleration: more complex jet shapes or patterns are required. Still, we demonstrate that the apparent direction changes are predominantly caused by the jet nozzle rotations, and not by individual components propagating transversely to the jet. In this work, we focus on variability scales much longer than the times of observations, that is &gt; 50 years. Using our measurements, we bound potential periods to less than 1000 years in the source rest frame for 90% AGNs in the sample. This allows us to constrain mechanisms causing these variations if they are periodic, such as instabilities, disk-driven precession, or binary black hole effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12309v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Kostrichkin, Alexander Plavin, Alexander Pushkarev, Marina Butuzova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Self-Lensing and Eclipsing Signals due to Detached Compact Objects in the TESS Light Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A fraction of Galactic stars have compact companions which could be white dwarfs (WDs), neutron stars (NSs) or stellar-mass black holes (SBHs). In a detached and edge-on binary system including a main-sequence star and a compact object (denoted by WDMS, NSMS, and BHMS systems), the stellar brightness can change periodically due to self-lensing or eclipsing features. The shape of a self-lensing signals is a degenerate function of stellar radius and compact object's mass because the self-lensing peak strongly depends on the projected source radius normalized to Einstein radius. Increasing the inclination angle $i$ changes the self-lensing shape from a strict top-hat model to one with slow-increasing edges. We simulate stellar light curves due to these binary systems which are observed by NASA's Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) telescope and evaluate the efficiencies to detect their periodic signatures using two sets of criteria (i)SNR$&gt;3$ and $N_{\rm{tran}}&gt;1$ (Low-Confidence, LC), and (ii) SNR$&gt;5$ and $N_{\rm{tran}}&gt;2$ (High-Confidence, HC). The HC efficiencies for detecting WDMS, NSMS, and BHMS systems with the inclination angle $i&lt;20^{\circ}$ during different time spans are $5$-$7\%$, $4.5$-$6\%$, and $4$-$5\%$, respectively. Detecting lensing-induced features is possible in only $\lesssim3\%$ and $\lesssim33\%$ of detectable WDMS and NSMS events. The detection efficiencies for closer source stars with higher priorities are higher and drop to zero for $b\gtrsim R_{\star}$, where $b\simeq \tan(i) a$ is the impact parameter($a$ is the semi-major axis). We predict the numbers of WDs, NSs, and SBHs that are discovered from the TESS Candidate Target List stars are $15$-$18$, $6$-$7$, and $&lt;1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12441v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sedighe Sajadian, Niayesh Afshordi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study examines the possibility of starting the process of collapsing and forming stars from a fractional molecular cloud. Although the Verlinde's approach is employed to derive the corresponding gravitational potential, the results are easily generalizable to other gravitational potential proposals for fractional systems. It is due to the fact that the different methods, despite the difference in the details of results, all obtain power forms for the potential in terms of radius. An essential result of this analysis is the derivation of the corresponding Jeans mass limit, which is a crucial parameter in understanding the formation of stars. The study shows that the Jeans mass of a cloud in fractional gravity is much smaller than the traditional value. In addition, the study also determines the burning temperature of the resulting star using the Gamow theory. This calculation provides insight into the complex processes that govern the evolution of these celestial bodies. Finally, the study briefly discusses the investigation of hydrostatic equilibrium, a crucial condition that ensures the stability of these fractional stars. It also addresses the corresponding Lane--Emden equation, which is pivotal in understanding this equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12869v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Moradpour, S. Jalalzadeh, M. Javaherian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into the origins and growth of seeds of supermassive black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.06338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.06338v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a well-tested, theoretically supported empirical relation that helps decipher the origins, growth, and properties of SMBHs (supermassive black holes). Based on theoretical considerations and analysis of mass (MBH) versus age (t) distribution of 93 high-redshift (z&gt;5.6) SMBHs, we get MBH = Ms exp [14.6(t-100)/t (Myr)], which gives the SMBH's seed mass Ms and its derivative gives the instantaneous mass-accretion rate. It yields seeds of ~ 20-420 Msun (solar masses) for the recently discovered SMBHs GNz11, CEERS-19, and UHZ1 and (~ 3E+04 Msun) for the largest (1.24E+10 Msun) high-z SMBH. It is applied to 132446 SMBHs at z &lt;2.4, cataloged by Kozlowski. The resultant seeds are classified based on size and likely formation mechanism: ~ 58% are light (&lt;400 Msun) and deemed to t~58% are light (&lt;400Msun) and considered to be Pop III remnants; ~ 39% are intermediate size (400 -3000 Msun) and &lt; 3% are heavier seeds (3E+03 -3E+04 Msun), both of which may have formed by mergers of Pop III remnants. The direct collapse black hole (DCBH) mechanism is not required but is not excluded. Furthermore, the results show the following. The mass-accretion rate increases exponentially from the seed's inception at z ~30, reaches a broad plateau at z ~ 8.5 to 6 coincident with the epoch of reionization, and decreases monotonically towards z=0. Sub-Eddington accretion is the norm, except during the first ~150 Myr, SMBHs experienced super-Eddington accretion, or the radiative efficiency was &lt;0.1. The largest seed can potentially grow via luminous accretion up to (6.6+/-2.2)E+10 Msun, consistent with a theoretical limit of ~ 5+10 Msun proposed by King. The Eddington ratio decreases, and the radiative efficiency increases as z decreases, consistent with recent findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.06338v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yash Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep extragalactic HI survey of the COSMOS field with FAST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16597v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a deep HI survey at L-band conducted with the Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical radio Telescope (FAST) over the COSMOS field. This survey is strategically designed to overlap with the MIGHTEE COSMOS field, aiming to combine the sensitivity of the FAST and high-resolution of the MeerKAT. We observed the field with FAST for approximately 11 hours covering $\sim$2 square degrees, and reduced the raw data to HI spectral cubes over the frequency range 1310-1420 MHz. The FAST-HI data reach a median 3$\sigma$ column density of $N_{\rm HI}\sim2\times10^{17}$ cm$^{-2}$ over a 5 km s$^{-1}$ channel width, allowing for studies of the distribution of HI gas in various environments, such as in galaxies, the Circum-Galactic Medium (CGM) and Intergalactic Medium (IGM). We visually searched the spectral cubes for HI sources, and found a total of 80 HI detections, of which 56 have been cross-matched with the MIGHTEE-HI catalogue. With the cross-matched sources, we compare their HI masses and find that the total HI mass fraction in the IGM and CGM surrounding the galaxy pairs is statistically higher than the HI fraction surrounding the isolated galaxies by a difference of 13$\pm$4%, indicating that the CGM and IGM associated with interacting systems are richer in neutral hydrogen compared to those around isolated galaxies in the local Universe. We also describe several FAST-MeerKAT synergy projects, highlighting the full potential of exploiting both single-dish and interferometric observations to study the distribution and evolution of the diffuse HI gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16597v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengxing Pan, Matt J. Jarvis, Ming Zhu, Yin-Zhe Ma, Mario G. Santos, Anastasia A. Ponomareva, Ian Heywood, Yingjie Jing, Chen Xu, Ziming Liu, Yogesh Chandola, Yipeng Jing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WALLABY Pilot Survey: HI source-finding with a machine learning framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11668v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The data volumes generated by the WALLABY atomic Hydrogen (HI) survey using the Australiian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder (ASKAP) necessitate greater automation and reliable automation in the task of source-finding and cataloguing. To this end, we introduce and explore a novel deep learning framework for detecting low Signal-to-Noise Ratio (SNR) HI sources in an automated fashion. Specfically, our proposed method provides an automated process for separating true HI detections from false positives when used in combination with the Source Finding Application (SoFiA) output candidate catalogues. Leveraging the spatial and depth capabilities of 3D Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs), our method is specifically designed to recognise patterns and features in three-dimensional space, making it uniquely suited for rejecting false positive sources in low SNR scenarios generated by conventional linear methods. As a result, our approach is significantly more accurate in source detection and results in considerably fewer false detections compared to previous linear statistics-based source finding algorithms. Performance tests using mock galaxies injected into real ASKAP data cubes reveal our method's capability to achieve near-100% completeness and reliability at a relatively low integrated SNR~3-5. An at-scale version of this tool will greatly maximise the science output from the upcoming widefield HI surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11668v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Wang, O. Ivy Wong, Tobias Westmeier, Chandrashekar Murugeshan, Karen Lee-Waddell, Yuanzhi. Cai, Xiu. Liu, Austin Xiaofan Shen, Jonghwan Rhee, Helga D\'enes, Nathan Deg, Peter Kamphuis, Barbara Catinella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic effects cannot explain galactic dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12302v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been suggested in recent literature that nonlinear and/or gravitomagnetic general relativistic effects can play a leading role in galactic dynamics, partially or totally replacing dark matter. Using the 1+3 "quasi-Maxwell" formalism, we show, on general grounds, such hypothesis to be impossible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12302v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.064056</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 064056 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. Filipe O. Costa, Jos\'e Nat\'ario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YOLO-CIANNA: Galaxy detection with deep learning in radio data. I. A new YOLO-inspired source detection method applied to the SKAO SDC1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05925v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The upcoming Square Kilometer Array (SKA) will set a new standard regarding data volume generated by an astronomical instrument, which is likely to challenge widely adopted data-analysis tools that scale inadequately with the data size. The aim of this study is to develop a new source detection and characterization method for massive radio astronomical datasets based on modern deep-learning object detection techniques. For this, we seek to identify the specific strengths and weaknesses of this type of approach when applied to astronomical data. We introduce YOLO-CIANNA, a highly customized deep-learning object detector designed specifically for astronomical datasets. In this paper, we present the method and describe all the elements introduced to address the specific challenges of radio astronomical images. We then demonstrate the capabilities of this method by applying it to simulated 2D continuum images from the SKA observatory Science Data Challenge 1 (SDC1) dataset. Using the SDC1 metric, we improve the challenge-winning score by +139% and the score of the only other post-challenge participation by +61%. Our catalog has a detection purity of 94% while detecting 40 to 60% more sources than previous top-score results, and exhibits strong characterization accuracy. The trained model can also be forced to reach 99% purity in post-process and still detect 10 to 30% more sources than the other top-score methods. It is also computationally efficient, with a peak prediction speed of 500 images of 512x512 pixels per second on a single GPU. YOLO-CIANNA achieves state-of-the-art detection and characterization results on the simulated SDC1 dataset and is expected to transfer well to observational data from SKA precursors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05925v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202449548</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>D. Cornu, P. Salom\'e, B. Semelin, A. Marchal, J. Freundlich, S. Aicardi, X. Lu, G. Sainton, F. Mertens, F. Combes, C. Tasse</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
