<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel high-z submm Galaxy Efficient Line Survey in ALMA bands 3 through 8 -- An ANGELS Pilot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use the Atacama Large sub/Millimetre Array (ALMA) to efficiently observe spectral lines across Bands 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8 at high-resolution (0.5" - 0.1") for 16 bright southern Herschel sources at $1.5 &lt; z &lt; 4.2$. With only six and a half hours of observations, we reveal 66 spectral lines in 17 galaxies. These observations detect emission from CO (3-2) to CO(18-17), as well as atomic ([CI](1-0), (2-1), [OI] 145 $\mu$m and [NII] 205 $\mu$m) lines. Additional molecular lines are seen in emission (${\rm H_2O}$ and ${\rm H_2O^+}$) and absorption (OH$^+$ and CH$^+$). The morphologies based on dust continuum ranges from extended sources to strong lensed galaxies with magnifications between 2 and 30. CO line transitions indicate a diverse set of excitation conditions with a fraction of the sources ($\sim 35$%) showcasing dense, warm gas. The resolved gas to star-formation surface densities vary strongly per source, and suggest that the observed diversity of dusty star-forming galaxies could be a combination of lensed, compact dusty starbursts and extended, potentially-merging galaxies. The predicted gas depletion timescales are consistent with 100 Myr to 1 Gyr, but require efficient fueling from the extended gas reservoirs onto the more central starbursts, in line with the Doppler-shifted absorption lines that indicate inflowing gas for two out of six sources. This pilot paper explores a successful new method of observing spectral lines in large samples of galaxies, supports future studies of larger samples, and finds that the efficiency of this new observational method will be further improved with the planned ALMA Wideband Sensitivity Upgrade.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16351v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. J. L. C. Bakx, A. Amvrosiadis, G. J. Bendo, H. S. B. Algera, S. Serjeant, L. Bonavera, E. Borsato, X. Chen, P. Cox, J. Gonz\'alez-Nuevo, M. Hagimoto, K. C. Harrington, R. J. Ivison, P. Kamieneski, L. Marchetti, D. A. Riechers, T. Tsukui, P. P. van der Werf, C. Yang, J. A. Zavala, P. Andreani, S. Berta, A. R. Cooray, G. De Zotti, S. Eales, R. Ikeda, K. K. Knudsen, I. Mitsuhashi, M. Negrello, R. Neri, A. Omont, D. Scott, Y. Tamura, P. Temi, S. A. Urquhart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy Size and Mass Build-up in the First 2 Gyrs of Cosmic History from Multi-Wavelength JWST NIRCam Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The evolution of galaxy sizes in different wavelengths provides unique insights on galaxy build-up across cosmic epochs. Such measurements can now finally be done at $z&gt;3$ thanks to the exquisite spatial resolution and multi-wavelength capability of the JWST. With the public data from the CEERS, PRIMER-UDS, and PRIMER-COSMOS surveys, we measure the sizes of $\sim 3500$ star-forming galaxies at $3 \leqslant z&lt;9$, in 7 NIRCam bands using the multi-wavelength model fitting code GalfitM. The size-mass relation is measured in four redshift bins, across all NIRCam bands. We find that, the slope and intrinsic scatter of the rest-optical size-mass relation are constant across this redshift range and consistent with previous HST-based studies at low-z. When comparing the relations across different wavelengths, the average rest-optical and rest-UV relations are consistent with each other up to $z=6$, but the intrinsic scatter is largest in rest-UV wavelengths compared to rest-optical and redder bands. This behaviour is independent of redshift and we speculate that it is driven by bursty star-formation in $z&gt;4$ galaxies. Additionally, for $3\leqslant z&lt;4$ star-forming galaxies at $\rm M_* &gt; 10^{10} M_{\odot}$, we find smaller rest-$\rm 1\rm\,\mu m$ sizes in comparison to rest-optical (and rest-UV) sizes, suggestive of colour gradients. When comparing to simulations, we find agreement over $\rm M_* \approx 10^{9} - 10^{10} M_{\odot}$ but beyond this mass, the observed size-mass relation is significantly steeper. Our results show the power of JWST/NIRCam to provide new constraints on galaxy formation models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16354v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalie Allen, Pascal A. Oesch, Sune Toft, Jasleen Matharu, Conor J. R. McPartland, Andrea Weibel, Gabe Brammer, Rebecca A. A. Bowler, Kei Ito, Rashmi Gottumukkala, Francesca Rizzo, Francesco Valentino, Rohan G. Varadaraj, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooling Flows as a Reference Solution for the Hot Circumgalactic Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The circumgalactic medium (CGM) in $\gtrsim 10^{12}$ $\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ halos is dominated by a hot phase ($T \gtrsim 10^{6}$ K). While many models exist for the hot gas structure, there is as yet no consensus. We compare cooling flow models, in which the hot CGM flows inward due to radiative cooling, to the CGM of $\sim 10^{12}-10^{13}$ $\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ halos in galaxy formation simulations from the FIRE project at $z\sim0$. The simulations include realistic cosmological evolution and feedback from stars but neglect AGN feedback. At both mass scales, CGM inflows are typically dominated by the hot phase rather than by the `precipitation' of cold gas. Despite being highly idealized, we find that cooling flows describe $\sim 10^{13}$ $\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ halos very well, with median agreement in the density and temperature profiles of $\sim 20\%$ and $\sim 10\%$, respectively. This indicates that stellar feedback has little impact on CGM scales in those halos. For $\sim 10^{12}$ $\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ halos, the thermodynamic profiles are also accurately reproduced in the outer CGM. For some of these lower-mass halos, cooling flows significantly overpredict the hot gas density in the inner CGM. This could be due to multidimensional angular momentum effects not well captured by our 1D cooling flow models and/or to the larger cold gas fractions in these regions. Turbulence, which contributes $\sim 10-40\%$ of the total pressure, must be included to accurately reproduce the temperature profiles. Overall, cooling flows predict entropy profiles in better agreement with the FIRE simulations than other idealized models in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16359v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imran Sultan, Claude-Andr\'e Faucher-Gigu\`ere, Jonathan Stern, Shaked Rotshtein, Lindsey Byrne, Nastasha Wijers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Baryonic Feedback on Warm-Hot Circumgalactic Medium in CAMELS Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The baryonic physics shaping galaxy formation and evolution are complex, spanning a vast range of scales and making them challenging to model. Cosmological simulations rely on subgrid models that produce significantly different predictions. Understanding how models of stellar and active galactic nuclei (AGN) feedback affect baryon behavior across different halo masses and redshifts is essential. Using the SIMBA and IllustrisTNG suites from the Cosmology and Astrophysics with MachinE Learning Simulations (CAMELS) project, we explore the effect of parameters governing the subgrid implementation of stellar and AGN feedback. We find that while IllustrisTNG shows higher cumulative feedback energy across all halos, SIMBA demonstrates a greater spread of baryons, quantified by the closure radius and circumgalactic medium (CGM) gas fraction. This suggests that feedback in SIMBA couples more effectively to baryons and drives them more efficiently within the host halo. There is evidence that different feedback modes are highly interrelated in these subgrid models. Parameters controlling stellar feedback efficiency significantly impact AGN feedback, as seen in the suppression of black hole mass growth and delayed activation of AGN feedback to higher mass halos with increasing stellar feedback efficiency in both simulations. Additionally, AGN feedback efficiency parameters affect the CGM gas fraction at low halo masses in SIMBA, hinting at complex, non-linear interactions between AGN and SNe feedback modes. Overall, we demonstrate that stellar and AGN feedback are intimately interwoven, especially at low redshift, due to subgrid implementation, resulting in halo property effects that might initially seem counterintuitive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16361v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabel Medlock (Department of Astronomy Yale University), Chloe Neufeld (Department of Astronomy Yale University), Daisuke Nagai (Department of Astronomy Yale University, Department of Physics Yale University), Daniel Angl\'es Alc\'azar (Department of Physics University of Connecticut, Center for Computational Astrophysics Flatiron Institute), Shy Genel (CASA Department of Astrophysical and Planetary Sciences University of Colorado), Benjamin Oppenheimer (Center for Computational Astrophysics Flatiron Institute), Priyanka Singh (Department of Physics Yale University, Department of Astronomy Astrophysics and Space Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Indore), Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro (Center for Computational Astrophysics Flatiron Institute, Department of Astrophysical Sciences Princeton University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AEOS: Star-by-Star Cosmological Simulations of Early Chemical Enrichment and Galaxy Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The AEOS project introduces a series of high-resolution cosmological simulations that model star-by-star chemical enrichment and galaxy formation in the early Universe, achieving 1 pc resolution. These simulations capture the complexities of galaxy evolution within the first ~300 Myr by modeling individual stars and their feedback processes. By incorporating chemical yields from individual stars, AEOS generates galaxies with diverse stellar chemical abundances, linking them to hierarchical galaxy formation and early nucleosynthetic events. These simulations underscore the importance of chemical abundance patterns in ancient stars as vital probes of early nucleosynthesis, star formation histories, and galaxy formation. We examine the metallicity floors of various elements resulting from Pop III enrichment, providing best-fit values for eight different metals (e.g., [O/H] = -4.0) to guide simulations without Pop III models. Additionally, we identify galaxies that begin star formation with Pop II after external enrichment and investigate the frequency of CEMP stars at varying metallicities. The AEOS simulations offer detailed insights into the relationship between star formation, feedback, and chemical enrichment. Future work will extend these simulations to later epochs to interpret the diverse stellar populations of the Milky Way and its satellites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16366v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaley Brauer, Andrew Emerick, Jennifer Mead, Alexander P. Ji, John H. Wise, Greg L. Bryan, Mordecai-Mark Mac Low, Benoit Cote, Eric P. Andersson, Anna Frebel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-learning the gap between real and simulated nebulae: A domain-adaptation approach to classify ionised nebulae in nearby galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classifying ionised nebulae in nearby galaxies is crucial to studying stellar feedback mechanisms and understanding the physical conditions of the interstellar medium. This classification task is generally performed by comparing observed line ratios with photoionisation simulations of different types of nebulae (HII regions, planetary nebulae, and supernova remnants). However, due to simplifying assumptions, such simulations are generally unable to fully reproduce the line ratios in observed nebulae. This discrepancy limits the performance of the classical machine-learning approach, where a model is trained on the simulated data and then used to classify real nebulae. In this study, we use a domain-adversarial neural network (DANN) to bridge the gap between photoionisation models (source domain) and observed ionised nebulae from the PHANGS-MUSE survey (target domain). The DANN is an example of a domain-adaptation algorithm, whose goal is to maximise the performance of a model trained on labelled data in the source domain on an unlabelled target domain by extracting domain-invariant features. Our results indicate a significant improvement in classification performance in the target domain when employing the DANN framework compared to a classical neural network (NN) classifier. Additionally, we investigate the impact of adding noise to the source dataset, finding that noise injection acts as a form of regularisation, further enhancing the performances of both the NN and DANN models on the observational data. The combined use of domain adaptation and noise injection improves the classification accuracy in the target domain by 24%. This study highlights the potential of domain adaptation methods in tackling the domain-shift challenge when using theoretical models to train machine-learning pipelines in astronomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16370v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Belfiore, Michele Ginolfi, Guillermo Blanc, Mederic Boquien, Melanie Chevance, Enrico Congiu, Simon C. O. Glover, Brent Groves, Ralf S. Klessen, Eduardo M\'endez-Delgado, Thomas G. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filament Accretion and Fragmentation in the Perseus Molecular Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observations suggest that filaments in molecular clouds can grow by mass accretion while forming cores via fragmentation. Here we present one of the first large sample studies of filament accretion using velocity gradient measurements of star-forming filaments on the $\sim 0.05$ pc scale with NH$_3$ observations of the Perseus Molecular Cloud, primarily obtained as a part of the GBT Ammonia Survey (GAS). In this study, we find significant correlations between velocity gradient, velocity dispersion, mass per unit length, and the number of cores per unit length of the Perseus filaments. Our results suggest a scenario in which filaments not only grow through mass accretion but also form new cores continuously in the process well into the thermally supercritical regime. Such behavior is contrary to that expected from isolated filament models but consistent with how filaments form within a more realistic cloud environment, suggesting that the cloud environment plays a crucial role in shaping core formation and evolution in filaments. Furthermore, even though velocity gradients within filaments are not oriented randomly, we find no correlation between velocity gradient orientation and the filament properties we analyzed. This result suggests that gravity is unlikely the dominant mechanism imposing order on the $\sim 0.05$ pc scale for dense star-forming gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16372v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Chun-Yuan Chen, James Di Francesco, Rachel K. Friesen, Jaime E. Pineda, Paola Caselli, Adam Ginsburg, Helen Kirk, Anna Punanova, the GAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling the density and mass of the Milky Way's proto-galaxy components with $APOGEE$-$Gaia$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unravelling galaxy formation theory requires understanding galaxies both at high and low redshifts. A possible way to connect both realms is by studying the oldest stars in the Milky Way (i.e., the proto-Galaxy). We use the $APOGEE$-$Gaia$ surveys to perform a purely chemical dissection of Milky Way (MW) stellar populations, and identify samples of stars likely belonging to proto-Galactic fragments. The metallicity dependence of the distribution of old MW stars in the [Mg/Mn]-[Al/Fe] enables the distinction of at least two populations in terms of their star formation histories: a rapidly evolved population likely associated with the main progenitor system of the proto-MW; and populations characterised by less efficient, slower, star formation. In the Solar neighbourhood these populations are dominated by the $Gaia-Enceladus/Sausage$ accretion debris. In the inner Galaxy, they are largely associated with the $Heracles$ structure. We model the density of chemically defined proto-Galaxy populations, finding that they are well represented by a Plummer model with a scale radius of $a$ ~3.5 kpc, and an oblate ellipsoid with flattening parameters [$p$ ~0.8; $q$ ~0.6]; this finding indicates that the MW plausibly hosts a low-mass, metal-poor, bulge component. We integrate this density for $chemically$ $unevolved$ stars between $-2$ &lt; [Fe/H] &lt; $-0.5$ to obtain a minimum stellar mass for the proto-Galaxy of $M_{*}$ ($r$ &lt; 10 kpc) = $9.1\pm0.2\times10^{8}$ M$_{\odot}$. Our results suggest the proto-Milky Way is at least comprised of two significant fragments: the main $in$ $situ$ progenitor and the $Heracles$ structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16374v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danny Horta, Ricardo P. Schiavon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A systematic analysis of star cluster disruption by tidal shocks -- II. Predicting star cluster dissolution rates from a time-series analysis of their tidal histories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most of the dynamical mass loss from star clusters is thought to be caused by the time-variability of the tidal field (``tidal shocks''). Systematic studies of tidal shocks have been hampered by the fact that each tidal history is unique, implying both a reproducibility and a generalisation problem. Here we address these issues by investigating how star cluster evolution depends on the statistical properties of its tidal history. We run a large suite of direct N-body simulations of clusters with tidal histories generated from power spectra of a given slope and with different normalisations, which determine the time-scales and amplitudes of the shocks, respectively. At fixed normalisation (i.e. the same median tidal field strength), the dissolution time-scale is nearly independent of the power spectrum slope. However, the dispersion in dissolution time-scales, obtained by repeating simulations for different realisations of statistically identical tidal histories, increases with the power spectrum slope. This result means that clusters experiencing high-frequency shocks have more similar mass loss histories than clusters experiencing low-frequency shocks. The density-mass relationship of the simulated clusters follows a power-law with slope between 1.08 and 1.45, except for the lowest normalisations (for which clusters effectively evolve in a static tidal field). Our findings suggest that star cluster evolution can be described statistically from a time-series analysis of its tidal history, which is an important simplification for describing the evolution of the star cluster population during galaxy formation and evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16389v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad7a7b</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy J. Webb, Marta Reina-Campos, J. M. Diederik Kruijssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UVCANDELS: Catalogs of photometric redshifts and galaxy physical properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The UltraViolet imaging of the Cosmic Assembly Near-infrared Deep Extragalactic Legacy Survey Fields (UVCANDELS) program provides deep HST F275W and F435W imaging over four CANDELS fields (GOODS-N, GOODS-S, COSMOS, and EGS). We combine this newly acquired UV imaging with existing HST imaging from CANDELS as well as existing ancillary data to obtain robust photometric redshifts and reliable estimates for galaxy physical properties for over 150,000 galaxies in the $\sim$430 arcmin$^2$ UVCANDELS area. Here, we leverage the power of the new UV photometry to not only improve the photometric redshift measurements in these fields, but also constrain the full redshift probability distribution combining multiple redshift fitting tools. Furthermore, using the full UV-to-IR photometric dataset, we measure the galaxy physical properties by fitting templates from population synthesis models with two different parameterizations (flexible and fixed-form) of the star-formation histories (SFHs). Compared to the flexible SFH parametrization, we find that the fixed-form SFHs systematically underestimate the galaxy stellar masses, both at the low- ($\lesssim10^9 M_\odot$) and high- ($\gtrsim10^{10} M_\odot$) mass end, by as much as $\sim0.5$ dex. This underestimation is primarily due the limited ability of fixed-form SFH parameterization to simultaneously capture the chaotic nature of star-formation in these galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16404v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vihang Mehta, Marc Rafelski, Ben Sunnquist, Harry I. Teplitz, Claudia Scarlata, Xin Wang, Adriano Fontana, Nimish P. Hathi, Kartheik G. Iyer, Anahita Alavi, James Colbert, Norman Grogin, Anton Koekemoer, Kalina V. Nedkova, Matthew Hayes, Laura Prichard, Brian Siana, Brent M. Smith, Rogier Windhorst, Teresa Ashcraft, Micaela Bagley, Ivano Baronchelli, Guillermo Barro, Alex Blanche, Adam Broussard, Timothy Carleton, Nima Chartab, Alex Codoreanu, Seth Cohen, Christopher Conselice, Y. Sophia Dai, Behnam Darvish, Romeel Dave, Laura DeGroot, Duilia De Mello, Mark Dickinson, Najmeh Emami, Henry Ferguson, Leonardo Ferreira, Keely Finkelstein, Steven Finkelstein, Jonathan P. Gardner, Eric Gawiser, Timothy Gburek, Mauro Giavalisco, Andrea Grazian, Caryl Gronwall, Yicheng Guo, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Shoubaneh Hemmati, Justin Howell, Rolf A. Jansen, Zhiyuan Ji, Sugata Kaviraj, Keunho J. Kim, Peter Kurczynski, Ilin Lazar, Ray A. Lucas, John MacKenty, Kameswara Bharadwaj Mantha, Alec Martin, Garreth Martin, Tyler McCabe, Bahram Mobasher, Alexa M. Morales, Robert O'Connell, Charlotte Olsen, Lillian Otteson, Swara Ravindranath, Caleb Redshaw, Michael Rutkowski, Brant Robertson, Zahra Sattari, Emmaris Soto, Lei Sun, Sina Taamoli, Eros Vanzella, L. Y. Aaron Yung, Bonnabelle Zabelle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multiwavelength overview of the giant spiral UGC 2885</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: UGC 2885 (z = 0.01935) is one of the largest and most massive galaxies in the local Universe, yet its undisturbed spiral structure is unexpected for such an object and unpredicted in cosmological simulations. Understanding the detailed properties of extreme systems such as UGC 2885 can provide insight on the limits of scaling relations and physical processes driving galaxy evolution. Our goal is to understand whether UGC 2885 has followed a similar evolutionary path to other high-mass galaxies by examining its place on the fundamental metallicity relation and the star-forming main sequence. We present new observations of UGC 2885 with the CFHT and IRAM 30-m telescopes. These novel data are used to respectively calculate metallicity and molecular hydrogen mass values. We estimate stellar mass (M*) and star formation rate (SFR) based on mid-infrared observations with the Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer. We find global metallicities Z = 9.28, 9.08 and 8.74 at the 25 kpc ellipsoid from N2O2, R23 and O3N2 indices, respectively. This puts UGC 2885 at the high end of the galaxy metallicity distribution. The molecular hydrogen mass is calculated as M(H2)=(1.89+/-0.24)e11 Msun, the SFR as 1.63+/-0.72 Msun/yr and the stellar mass as (4.83 +/- 1.52)e11 Msun, which gives a star formation efficiency (SFE = SFR/M(H2)) of (8.67+/-4.20)e12/yr. This indicates that UGC 2885 has an extremely high molecular gas content when compared to known samples of star forming galaxies (~100 times more) and a relatively low SFR for its current gas content. We conclude that UGC 2885 has gone through cycles of star formation periods, which increased its stellar mass and metallicity to its current state. The mechanisms that are fueling the current molecular gas reservoir and keeping the galaxy from producing stars remain uncertain. We discuss the possibility that a molecular bar is quenching star forming activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16467v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus C. Carvalho, Bavithra Naguleswaran, Pauline Barmby, Mark Gorski, Sabine K\"oenig, Benne Holwerda, Jason E. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The power spectrum of galaxies from large to small scales: a line-intensity mapping perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We model the power spectrum of galaxies in the IllustrisTNG simulation when they are weighted by their star formation rate. Such a weighting is relevant in the context of line-intensity mapping (LIM). On intermediate to large scales, the model accounts for non-linear bias of star-forming galaxies and halo exclusion (a 2-halo term). On small scales, it incorporates the weighted distribution of satellite galaxies within haloes (a 1-halo term). The random sampling of satellite galaxies adds a shot noise term to the power spectrum on small scales, and their confinement to haloes introduces a halo shot noise term on large scales. The full model reproduces the measured power spectrum to within a few per cent on all scales, and the fitting parameters have a clear physical meaning. Omitting satellite galaxies from the analysis leads to an underestimation of both the large-scale bias and the mean LIM intensity by approximately 30 per cent each at redshift 1.5. Assigning the LIM intensity of satellites to the centre of their respective haloes affects the power spectrum on scales $k &gt; 0.3$ h Mpc$^{-1}$. We discuss how the LIM power spectrum can be used to constrain cosmology on large scales, and galaxy formation on smaller scales, with our fitting function providing an accurate and well-motivated parametrisation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16588v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Lan Jun (UTokyo), Tom Theuns (ICC, Durham), Kana Moriwaki (UTokyo), Sownak Bose (ICC, Durham)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the quiescent galaxy population in the Spiderweb protocluster at z=2.16 with deep HST/WFC3 slitless spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the HST WFC3 G141 grism slitless spectroscopy observation of the core region of the Spiderweb protocluster at $z=2.16$. We analyzed the spectra of all objects in a $\sim 2 \times 2 \text{ arcmin}^2$ field of view and identified 40 protocluster members, recovering 19 previously identified H$\alpha$-emitters in addition to revealing 21 new members. The spectra allowed us to identify 11 galaxies with quiescent spectra. Three galaxies with quiescent spectra are possibly still star-forming according to SED fitting, indicating a possible left-over or dust-obscured star formation. We estimate a quiescent fraction of $\sim 50\%$ for $M_\star &gt; 10^{11} M_\odot$. About half of the quiescent galaxies possibly host AGN, hinting at AGN's key role in quenching galaxies in the protocluster environment. These quiescent galaxies have relatively more compact and concentrated light profiles than the star-forming members, but they are not yet as bulge-dominated as local ellipticals. These results are consistent with previous studies that indicate the Spiderweb protocluster is in the maturing stage, with a red sequence that has begun forming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16643v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdurrahman Naufal, Yusei Koyama, Chiara D'Eugenio, Helmut Dannerbauer, Rhythm Shimakawa, Jose Manuel P\'erez-Mart\'inez, Tadayuki Kodama, Yuheng Zhang, Kazuki Daikuhara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial Profiles of $\Sigma_{\ast}$, $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$, Gas Metallicity and Their Correlations Across the Galactic Mass-Size Plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyzed the global and resolved properties of approximately 1,240 nearby star-forming galaxies from the MaNGA survey, comparing compact and extended galaxies -- those with smaller and larger radii ($R_{\rm e}$), respectively -- at a fixed stellar mass ($M_{\ast}$). Compact galaxies typically exhibit lower HI gas fractions, higher dust extinction, higher metallicity, greater mass concentration, and lower angular momentum on a global scale. Radial profiles of stellar mass surface density ($\Sigma_{\ast}$) and star formation rate surface density ($\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$), as functions of the effective radius ($R/$$R_{\rm e}$), reveal that compact galaxies display steeper gradients and higher values, resulting in elevated specific star formation rates (sSFR) in their inner regions compared to their outskirts. At a given $\Sigma_{\ast}$, compact galaxies have higher sSFR than extended galaxies, particularly in low-mass galaxies (log($M_{\ast}$/$M_{\odot}$)$\,\leq\,$10$^{10}$). Additionally, their metallicity profiles differ significantly: extended galaxies have steeper metallicity gradients, while compact galaxies exhibit flatter slopes and higher metallicity at a given $R/$$R_{\rm e}$. After accounting for the dependence of metallicity on $M_{\ast}$ and $\Sigma_{\ast}$, no further correlation with SFR is observed. The combination of higher sSFR and potentially higher star formation efficiency in compact galaxies suggests that their central gas is being rapidly consumed, leading to older stellar populations, as indicated by D$_{n}$(4000) and EW(H$\delta_A$), and resulting in faster central growth. Our results reveal that radial SFR profiles cannot be fully determined by $M_{\ast}$ and $\Sigma_{\ast}$ alone; other factors, such as galaxy size or angular momentum, must be considered to fully understand the observed trends.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16651v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Lin, Shiyin Shen, Hassen M. Yesuf, Ye-Wei Mao, Lei Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joining the Dots: High Redshift Black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A recent paper (King, 2024) suggested that emission from the central supermassive black holes in high-redshift galaxies must be tightly collimated by the effects of partly expelling a super-Eddington mass supply. I show here that this idea predicts that these galaxies should produce very little detectable rest-frame X-ray emission, appear Compton thick, and show no easily detectable sign of outflows. All of these properties agree with current observations. To produce these effects, the mass supply to the black holes should exceed the Eddington rate by factors 50 - 100, which appears in line with conditions during the early growth of the holes. I note that theoretical derivations of the ratio of black hole mass to host galaxy stellar mass already predict that this should increase significantly at high redshift, in line with recent observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16970v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The star formation history of the first bulge fossil fragment candidate Terzan 5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16971v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Terzan 5 and Liller 1 are the only bulge stellar clusters hosting multi-iron and multi-age stellar populations. They are therefore claimed to constitute a novel class of astrophysical objects: the fossils of massive star-forming clumps that possibly sank to the center of the Milky Way and contributed to the formation of the bulge. This is based on the hypothesis that the ancient clumps were able to retain iron-enriched supernova ejecta, later giving rise to younger and more metal-rich populations. Aims. A way to investigate this scenario is reconstructing their star formation histories (SFHs) and proving a prolonged and multi-episode star formation activity. Methods. Leveraging ground- and space-based high-resolution images, we derived the SFH of Terzan 5 by employing the color-magnitude diagram fitting routine SFERA. Results. The best-fit solution predicts an old, main peak occurred between 12 and 13 Gyr ago that generated 70 % of the current stellar mass, followed by a lower-rate star formation activity with two main additional bursts. Conclusions. These results indicate that Terzan 5, similarly to Liller 1, experienced a prolonged, multiepisode star formation activity, fueled by metal-enriched gas deposited in its central regions, in agreement with the expectations of a self-enrichment scenario in a primordial massive clump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16971v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Crociati, Michele Cignoni, Emanuele Dalessandro, Cristina Pallanca, Davide Massari, Francesco R. Ferraro, Barbara Lanzoni, Livia Origlia, Elena Valenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Massive Star Formation: Radio Flux Variability in UCHII Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context:
  Theoretical models of early accretion during the formation process of massive stars have predicted that HII regions exhibit radio variability on timescales of decades. However, large-scale searches for such temporal variations with sufficient sensitivity have not yet been carried out.
  Aims:
  We aim to identify HII regions with variable radio wavelength fluxes and to investigate the properties of the identified objects, especially those with the highest level of variability.
  Methods:
  We compared the peak flux densities of 86 ultracompact HII (UCHII) regions measured by the GLOSTAR and CORNISH surveys and identified variables that show flux variations higher than 30% over ~8 yr timespan between these surveys.
  Results:
  We found a sample of 38 variable UCHII regions, which is the largest sample identified to date. The overall occurrence of variability is 44$\pm$5%, suggesting that variation in UCHII regions is significantly more common than prediction.
  The variable UCHII regions are found to be younger than non-variable UCHII regions, all of them meeting the size criterion of hypercompact (HC) HII regions. We studied the 7 UCHII regions (the ``Top7'') that show the highest variability with variations &gt; 100%.
  The Top7 variable UCHII regions are optically thick at 4--8 GHz and compact, suggesting they are in a very early evolutionary stage of HCHII or UCHII regions. There is a significant correlation between variability and the spectral index of the radio emission. No dependence is observed between the variations and the properties of the sources' natal clumps traced by submillimeter continuum emission from dust, although variable HII regions are found in clumps at an earlier evolutionary stage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17117v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Y. Yang, M. A. Thompson, J. S. Urquhart, A. Brunthaler, K. M. Menten, Y. Gong, Chao-Wei Tsai, A. L. Patel, D. Li, W. D. Cotton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A recent confirmation of the wide binary gravitational anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Concerning recent published studies exploring the presence or otherwise of a gravitational anomaly at low accelerations in wide binary stars
  as observed by the {\it Gaia} satellite, Cookson (2024) presents an interesting case. In that study, RMS values of binned relative internal
  velocities in 1D for wide binaries are compared to Newtonian predictions for that quantity, with the author concluding that the data presented
  show no indication of any inconsistency with Newtonian expectations. However, the comparison presented is critically
  flawed, as the Newtonian predictions used refer to wide binaries with mean total masses of 2.0 $M_{\odot}$. This is larger than the 1.56 $M_{\odot}$
  value which applies to the data used in said paper. In this short note we correct the error mentioned above and show that the data and error bars
  as given in Cookson (2024) are in fact inconsistent with Newtonian expectations. Contrary to the assertion by Cookson, the data presented in Cookson
  (2024) actually show a clear anomaly in the low acceleration gravitational regime, this being consistent with a number of independent studies yielding
  this same result. Based on the analysis by Cookson (2024), wide binary systems show a clear Milgromian deviation from Newtonian dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17178v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Hernandez, Pavel Kroupa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Unobscured QSOs in the Southern Hemisphere with KS4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a catalog of unobscured QSO candidates in the southern hemisphere from the early interim data of the KMTNet Synoptic Survey of Southern Sky (KS4). The KS4 data covers $\sim2500\,{\rm deg}^{2}$ sky area, reaching 5$\sigma$ detection limits of $\sim$22.1-22.7 AB mag in the $BVRI$ bands. Combining this with available infrared photometric data from the surveys covering the southern sky, we select the unobscured QSO candidates based on their colors and spectral energy distributions (SEDs) fitting results. The final catalog contains 72,964 unobscured QSO candidates, of which only 0.4% are previously identified as QSOs based on spectroscopic observations. Our selection method achieves an 87% recovery rate for spectroscopically confirmed bright QSOs at $z&lt;2$ within the KS4 survey area. In addition, the number count of our candidates is comparable to that of spectroscopically confirmed QSOs from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey in the northern sky. These demonstrate that our approach is effective in searching for unobscured QSOs in the southern sky. Future spectro-photometric surveys covering the southern sky will enable us to discern their true nature and enhance our understanding of QSO populations in the southern hemisphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17187v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongjung Kim, Minjin Kim, Myungshin Im, Seo-Won Chang, Mankeun Jeong, Woowon Byun, Joonho Kim, Dohyeong Kim, Hyunjin Shim, Hyunmi Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain-Adaptive Neural Posterior Estimation for Strong Gravitational Lens Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16347v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling strong gravitational lenses is prohibitively expensive for modern and next-generation cosmic survey data. Neural posterior estimation (NPE), a simulation-based inference (SBI) approach, has been studied as an avenue for efficient analysis of strong lensing data. However, NPE has not been demonstrated to perform well on out-of-domain target data -- e.g., when trained on simulated data and then applied to real, observational data. In this work, we perform the first study of the efficacy of NPE in combination with unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA). The source domain is noiseless, and the target domain has noise mimicking modern cosmology surveys. We find that combining UDA and NPE improves the accuracy of the inference by 1-2 orders of magnitude and significantly improves the posterior coverage over an NPE model without UDA. We anticipate that this combination of approaches will help enable future applications of NPE models to real observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16347v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paxson Swierc, Marcos Tamargo-Arizmendi, Aleksandra \'Ciprijanovi\'c, Brian D. Nord</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The radiative-convective gap: fact or fiction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gaia characterizes the stellar populations of nearby open clusters with unprecedented precision. We investigate the B\"ohm-Vitense gap, which has been found as a prominent feature in the stellar sequence of open clusters. Using PARSEC isochrone fitting, we derive astrophysical parameters for more than 1100 stars in Praesepe, identify more than 1100 bona fide single stars in the alpha Persei (Melotte 20) open cluster, and confirm their approximate match in terms of age (approx. 710 Myr and 45 Myr) and metallicity ([M/H] approx. +0.15 dex and +0.13 dex) to the Hyades and Pleiades, respectively. By merging data of the cluster pairs, we improve number statistics. We do not find a clear gap in the combined observational G_abs vs. BP-RP color-magnitude diagram (CMD) in the stellar mass range corresponding to the location of the B\"ohm-Vitense gap. We reproduce gaps in simulated Hyades-type CMDs randomly drawn from an initial mass function. There is no strong evidence for a discontinuity originating in the transition from radiative to convective energy transport in the stellar photosphere. We conclude that the observed gaps in the stellar sequences of open clusters could be explained by small number statistics and the uneven mass-color relation at the transition from spectral type A to F.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16369v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Brandner, Artur Sorg, Siegfried R\"oser, Elena Schilbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Low Metallicity Massive Contact Binary Star System Candidate in WLM identified by Hubble and James Webb Space Telescope imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16393v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present archival HST and JWST ultraviolet through near infrared time series photometric observations of a massive minimal-contact binary candidate in the metal-poor galaxy WLM ($Z = 0.14 Z_{\odot}$). This discovery marks the lowest metallicity contact binary candidate observed to date. We determine the nature of the two stars in the binary by using the eclipsing binary modeling software (PHysics Of Eclipsing BinariEs; PHOEBE) to train a neural network to fit our observed panchromatic multi-epoch photometry. The best fit model consists of two hot MS stars ($T_1=29800^{+2300}_{-1700}$ K, $M_1=16^{+2}_{-3}~M_{\odot}$, and $T_2=18000^{+5000}_{-5000}$ K, $M_2=7^{+5}_{-3}~M_{\odot}$). We discuss plausible evolutionary paths for the system, and suggest the system is likely to be currently in a contact phase before ultimately ending in a merger. Future spectroscopy will help to further narrow down evolutionary pathways. This work showcases a novel use of data of JWST and HST imaging originally taken to characterize RR Lyrae. We expect time series imaging from LSST, BlackGEM, etc. to uncover similar types of objects in nearby galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16393v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maude Gull, Daniel R. Weisz, Kareem El-Badry, Jan Henneco, Alessandro Savino, Meredith Durbin, Yumi Choi, Roger E. Cohen, Andrew A. Cole, Matteo Correnti, Julianne J. Dalcanton, Karoline M. Gilbert, Steven R. Goldman, Puragra Guhathakurta, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Max J. B. Newman, Evan D. Skillman, Benjamin F. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A study of sixty-one massive over-contact binary candidates from the OGLE survey of the Magellanic Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive contact binaries are fundamental test-beds to study properties of close binaries en route to stellar mergers. Progress in their understanding has been largely impeded due to a dearth in their observed counterparts. We accumulate 61 over-contact binary candidates from the OGLE survey of the Magellanic Clouds and form the largest known sample of such systems. We mine the OGLE-IV catalogue for B-type and earlier systems which match our synthetic light curves, and thereafter examine their properties in comparison with our binary populations. Simultaneously, we also investigate the degeneracy in the light curves between over-contact and near-contact binaries and attempt to distinguish these populations. We construct new synthetic populations of such systems from detailed $\texttt{MESA}$ models with initial parameters of M$_\textrm{total,i}=14-80\,\textrm{M}_{\odot}$ and P$_\textrm{i}=0.6-23\,$days, and compute analogous $\texttt{PHOEBE}$ light curves. We then extract OGLE systems that match our synthetic light curves and compare their numbers, and distributions in periods, absolute V-band magnitudes and colours (V-I) with our population predictions. We expect massive over-contact binaries to have smooth equal-depth light curves due to their equal-mass ($q\approx1$) and consequently, equal-temperature components. We mine 47 and 14 predominantly B-type over-contact OGLE binaries from the Large and Small Magellanic Clouds respectively, with periods of $\approx0.6-1\,$d, along with a few wider O-type systems. This sample is consistent with our theoretically expected numbers and colour-magnitude and period distributions. Additionally, we find that binaries nearing contact have periods as large as $4.5\,$d and mass ratios of $q\approx0.4-0.95$, some of which may masquerade as over-contact binaries and thereby lead to potential observational misclassifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16427v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athira Menon, Michal Pawlak, Daniel J. Lennon, Koushik Sen, Norbert Langer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McFACTS I: Testing the LVK AGN channel with Monte Carlo For AGN Channel Testing &amp; Simulation (McFACTS)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Active galactic nuclei (AGN) are a promising source of the binary black hole (BBH) mergers observed in gravitational waves with LIGO-Virgo-Kagra (LVK). Constraining the AGN channel allows us to limit AGN parameter space (disk density, size, average lifetime) and nuclear star cluster (NSC) parameter space. Constraints on AGN and NSCs have implications for $\Lambda$CDM models of AGN feedback and models of AGN-driven SMBH merger and growth. Here we present several qualitative studies of the AGN channel using new public, open-source, fast, reproducible code \texttt{McFACTS}\footnote{https://github.com/mcfacts}:Monte Carlo for AGN channel Testing \&amp; Simulation. We demonstrate several important features for testing the AGN channel, including: i) growth to large mass IMBH is helped by the presence of migration traps or disk boundaries, ii) flat BH initial mass functions highlight hierarchical merger features in the mass spectrum, iii) high rates of dynamical encounters strongly inhibit BBH formation and merger at migration traps, iv) the ($q,\chi_{\rm eff}$) anti-correlation is a strong test of the bias to prograde mergers in the AGN channel, v) spheroid encounters can drive a fraction of mergers with high in-plane spin components ($\chi_{\rm p}$), vi) a high rate of extreme mass ratio inspirals (EMRIs) are driven by an initial population of embedded retrograde BH, vii) Both LVK and LISA are powerful probes of models of AGN disks and their embedded populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16515v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barry McKernan, K. E. Saavik Ford, Harry E. Cook, Vera Delfavero, Kaila Nathaniel, Jake Postiglione, Shawn Ray, Richard O'Shaughnessy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Dimensional Particle-In-Cell Simulations of Two-Dimensional Bernstein-Greene-Kruskal Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16585v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present three-dimensional (3D) Particle-In-Cell (PIC) simulations to study the stability of 2D Bernstein-Greene-Kruskal (BGK) modes in a magnetized plasma with a finite background magnetic field. The simulations were performed using the Plasma Simulation Code (PSC) [Germaschewski et al., J. of Comp. Phys. 318, 305 (2016)], as in our recent study using 2D PIC simulations [McClung et al., Phys. Plasmas 31, 042302 (2024)], in order to see if and how the previous results would change with 3D effects. We found that solutions that are stable (unstable) in 2D simulations are still stable (unstable) in the new 3D simulations. However, the instability develops slower in 3D than in 2D and forms an unstable spiral wave structure that is in-phase along the axial direction. We have also simulated cases with an electron density bump (EDB) at the center, in addition to cases with an electron density hole (EDH) considered in our previous study, and found differences in the unstable spiral wave structures between the two cases. Additionally, we have generalized our simulations to have an increased electron thermal velocity, as well as using initial conditions solved from the complete Vlasov-Maxwell system of equations. We found that these generalizations did not change the overall behavior of the simulations and the instability that evolves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16585v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. T. Franciscovich, J. McClung, K. Germaschewski, C. S. Ng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Initial Composition on Massive Star Evolution and Nucleosynthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the sensitivity of presupernova evolution and supernova nucleosynthesis yields of massive stars to variations of the initial composition. We use the solar abundances from Lodders (2009), and compute two different initial stellar compositions: i) scaled solar abundances, and ii) the isotopic galactic chemical history model (GCH) developed by West and Heger (2013b). We run a grid of models using the KEPLER stellar evolution code, with 7 initial stellar masses, 12 initial metallicities, and two for each scaling method to explore the effects on nucleosynthesis over a metallicity range of $-4.0\leq[Z]\leq+0.3$. We find that the compositions from the GCH model better reproduce the weak \emph{s}-process peak than the scaled solar models. The model yields are then used in the OMEGA Galactic Chemical Evolution (GCE) code to assess this result further. We find that initial abundances used in computing stellar structure have more of an impact on GCE results than initial abundances used in the burn network, with the GCH model again being favored when compared to observations. Lastly, a machine learning algorithm was used to verify the free parameter values of the GCH model, which were previously found by West and Heger (2013b) using a stochastic fitting process. The updated model is provided as an accessible tool for further nucleosynthesis studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher West, Alexander Heger, Benoit Cote, Lev Serxner, Haoxuan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Empirical Sample of Spectra of M-type Stars with Homogeneous Atmospheric-Parameter Labels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discrepancies between theoretical and observed spectra, and the systematic differences between various spectroscopic parameter estimates, complicate the determination of atmospheric parameters of M-type stars. In this work, we present an empirical sample of 5105 M-type star spectra with homogeneous atmospheric parameter labels through stellar-label transfer and sample cleaning. We addressed systematic discrepancies in spectroscopic parameter estimates by adopting recent results for Gaia EDR3 stars as a reference standard. Then, we used a density-based spatial clustering of applications with noise to remove unreliable samples in each subgrid of parameters. To confirm the reliability of the stellar labels, a 5-layer neural network was utilized, randomly partitioning the samples into training and testing sets. The standard deviations between the predicted and actual values in the testing set are 14 K for Teff , 0.06 dex for log g, and 0.05 dex for [M/H], respectively. In addition, we conducted an internal cross-validation to enhance validation and obtained precisions of 11 K, 0.05 dex, and 0.05 dex for Teff , log g, and [M/H], respectively. A grid of 1365 high Signal-to-Noise ratio (S/N) spectra and their labels, selected from the empirical sample, was utilized in the stellar parameter pipeline for M-Type stars (LASPM) of the Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST), producing an almost seamless Kiel distribution diagram for LAMOST DR10 and DR11 data. The atmospheric parameters for M-type stars from LAMOST DR11 show improved precision compared to the data from DR9, with improvements (for spectra with S/N higher than 10) from 118 to 67 K in Teff , 0.2 to 0.07 dex in log g, and 0.29 to 0.14 dex in [M/H].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16730v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing Du, A-Li Luo, Song Wang, Yinbi Li, Cai-Xia Qu, Xiao Kong, Yan-xin Guo, Yi-han Song, Fang Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooling rate and turbulence in the intracluster medium of the cool-core cluster Abell 2667</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a detailed analysis of the thermal X-ray emission from the intracluster medium (ICM) in the cool-core galaxy cluster Abell 2667 ($z=0.23$). Our goal is to detect low-temperature ($&lt;2$ keV) X-ray emitting gas, potentially associated to a cooling flow that connects the hot ICM reservoir to the cold gas phase responsible for star formation and supermassive black hole feeding. We use new deep XMM-Newton EPIC and RGS data, combined with archival Chandra data, to perform a spectral analysis for the core region. We find 1$\sigma$ upper limits to the cooling gas fraction of $\sim$40 $\rm M_{\odot}yr^{-1}$ and $\sim$50-60 $\rm M_{\odot}yr^{-1}$ in the temperature ranges 0.5-1 keV and 1-2 keV, respectively. The lack of OVII, FeXXI-FeXXII, and FeXVII emission lines in the RGS spectra suggest that the fraction of gas cooling below 1 keV is limited to a few tens of $\rm M_{\odot}yr^{-1}$ at most. However, we detect several lines (e.g. SiXIV, MgXII, FeXXIII/FeXXIV, NeX, OVIII$\alpha$) that allow us to estimate a 1$\sigma$ upper limit for turbulent broadening of $\sim$320 km $\rm s^{-1}$, higher that other cool-core clusters such as Abell 1835, implying mechanisms that boost turbulence in Abell 2667's atmosphere. Imaging analysis of Chandra data suggests the presence of a cold front, possibly lined to sloshing or ICM cavities. However, current data do not clearly identify the physical mechanism driving turbulence. These finding indicate that Abell 2667 is similar to other low-redshift cool-core clusters, though the large upper limit on turbulence hints at significant ICM heating, which may suppress cooling for extended periods and contribute to future condensation events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16831v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Lepore, C. Pinto, P. Tozzi, M. Gaspari, F. Gastaldello, A. Liu, P. Rosati, R. van Weeren, G. Cresci, E. Iani, G. Rodighiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Repeating Fast Radio Burst Source in a Low-Luminosity Dwarf Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17044v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the localization and host galaxy of FRB 20190208A, a repeating source of fast radio bursts (FRBs) discovered using CHIME/FRB. As part of the PRECISE repeater localization program on the EVN, we monitored FRB 20190208A for 65.6 hours at $\sim1.4$ GHz and detected a single burst, which led to its VLBI localization with 260 mas uncertainty (2$\sigma$). Follow-up optical observations with the MMT Observatory ($i\gtrsim 25.7$ mag (AB)) found no visible host at the FRB position. Subsequent deeper observations with the GTC, however, revealed an extremely faint galaxy ($r=27.32 \pm0.16$ mag), very likely ($99.95 \%$) associated with FRB 20190208A. Given the dispersion measure of the FRB ($\sim580$ pc cm$^{-3}$), even the most conservative redshift estimate ($z_{\mathrm{max}}\sim0.83$) implies that this is the lowest-luminosity FRB host to date ($\lesssim10^8L_{\odot}$), even less luminous than the dwarf host of FRB 20121102A. We investigate how localization precision and the depth of optical imaging affect host association, and discuss the implications of such a low-luminosity dwarf galaxy. Unlike the other repeaters with low-luminosity hosts, FRB 20190208A has a modest Faraday rotation measure of a few tens of rad m$^{-2}$, and EVN plus VLA observations reveal no associated compact persistent radio source. We also monitored FRB 20190208A for 40.4 hours over 2 years as part of the \'ECLAT repeating FRB monitoring campaign on the Nan\c{c}ay Radio Telescope, and detected one burst. Our results demonstrate that, in some cases, the robust association of an FRB with a host galaxy will require both high localization precision, as well as deep optical follow-up.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17044v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dant\'e M. Hewitt, Mohit Bhardwaj, Alexa C. Gordon, Aida Kirichenko, Kenzie Nimmo, Shivani Bhandari, Isma\"el Cognard, Wen-fai Fong, Armando Gil de Paz, Akshatha Gopinath, Jason W. T. Hessels, Franz Kirsten, Benito Marcote, Vladislavs Bezrukovs, Richard Blaauw, Justin D. Bray, Salvatore Buttaccio, Tomas Cassanelli, Pragya Chawla, Alessandro Corongiu, William Deng, Hannah N. Didehbani, Yuxin Dong, Marcin P. Gawro\'nski, Marcello Giroletti, Lucas Guillemot, Jeff Huang, Ronniy C. Joseph, Victoria M. Kaspi, Mattias Lazda, Michael Lindqvist, Maccaferri Giuseppe, Lluis Mas-Ribas, Kiyoshi W. Masui, Ryan Mckinven, Daniele Michilli, Anya E. Nugent, Omar S. Ould-Boukattine, Zsolt Paragi, Aaron B. Pearlman, Ue-Li Pen, Ziggy Pleunis, Ketan R. Sand, Vishwangi Shah, Kaitlyn Shin, Mark P. Snelders, Tiziana Venturi, Na Wang, David R. A. Williams-Baldwin, Jun Yang, Jianping P. Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a unified injection model of short-lived radioisotopes in N-body simulations of star-forming regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent research provides compelling evidence that the decay of short-lived radioisotopes (SLRs), such as 26Al, provided the bulk of energy for heating and desiccation of volatile-rich planetesimals in the early Solar System. However, it remains unclear whether the early Solar System was highly enriched relative to other planetary systems with similar formation characteristics. While the Solar System possesses an elevated level of SLR enrichment compared to the interstellar medium, determining SLR enrichment of individual protoplanetary disks observationally has not been performed and is markedly more difficult. We use N-body simulations to estimate enrichment of SLRs in star-forming regions through two likely important SLR sources, stellar winds from massive stars and supernovae. We vary the number of stars and the radii of the star-forming regions and implement two models of stellar wind SLR propagation for the radioisotopes 26Al and 60Fe. We find that for 26Al enrichment the Solar System is at the upper end of the expected distribution, while for the more supernovae dependent isotope 60Fe we find that the Solar System is comparatively very highly enriched. Furthermore, combined with our previous research, these results suggest that the statistical role of 26Al-driven desiccation on exoplanet bulk composition may be underestimated in typical interpretations of the low-mass exoplanet census, and that 60Fe is even less influential as a source of heating than previously assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17163v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Eatson, R. J. Parker, T. Lichtenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Ray Mediated Thermal Fronts in the Warm-Hot Circumgalactic Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the 1D plane-parallel front connecting the warm ($10^4$ K) and hot ($10^6$ K) phases of the circumgalactic medium (CGM), focusing on the influence of cosmic rays (CRs) in shaping these transition layers. We find that cosmic rays dictate the thermal balance while other fluxes (thermal conduction, radiative cooling, and gas flow) adjust to compensate. We compute column density ratios for selected transition temperature ions and compare them with observational data. While most of our models fail to reproduce the observations, a few are successful, although we make no claims for their uniqueness. Some of the discrepancies may indicate challenges in capturing the profiles in cooler, photoionized regions, as has been suggested for by previous efforts to model thermal transition layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17252v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanjue Zhu, Ellen G. Zweibel, Nickolay Y. Gnedin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPICE: the connection between cosmic reionisation and stellar feedback in the first galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16895v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present SPICE, a new suite of RHD cosmological simulations targeting the epoch of reionisation. The goal of these simulations is to systematically probe a variety of stellar feedback models, including "bursty" and "smooth" forms of supernova energy injection, as well as poorly-explored scenarios such as hypernova explosions and radiation pressure. Subtle differences in the behaviour of supernova feedback drive profound differences in reionisation histories, with burstier forms of feedback causing earlier reionisation. We also find that some global galaxy properties, such as the dust-attenuated luminosity functions and star formation main sequence, remain degenerate between models. Stellar feedback and its strength determine the morphological mix of galaxies emerging by z = 5 and that the reionisation history is inextricably connected to intrinsic properties such as galaxy kinematics and morphology. While star-forming, massive disks are prevalent if supernova feedback is "smooth", "bursty" feedback preferentially generates dispersion-dominated systems. Different modes of feedback produce different strengths of outflows, altering the ISM/CGM in different ways, and in turn strongly affecting the escape of LyC photons. We establish a correlation between galaxy morphology and LyC escape fraction, revealing that dispersion-dominated systems have escape fractions 10-50 times higher than their rotation-dominated counterparts at all redshifts. Dispersion-dominated systems should thus preferentially generate large HII regions as compared to their rotation-dominated counterparts. Since dispersion-dominated systems are more prevalent if stellar feedback is more explosive, reionisation occurs earlier in our simulation with burstier feedback. Statistical samples of post-reionisation galaxy morphologies probed with JWST, ALMA and MUSE can constrain stellar feedback and models of cosmic reionisation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16895v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1125</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aniket Bhagwat, Tiago Costa, Benedetta Ciardi, R\"udiger Pakmor, Enrico Garaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Heavy Metal Survey: The Evolution of Stellar Metallicities, Abundance Ratios, and Ages of Massive Quiescent Galaxies Since z~2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05307v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the elemental abundances and ages of 19 massive quiescent galaxies at $z\sim1.4$ and $z\sim2.1$ from the Keck Heavy Metal Survey. The ultra-deep LRIS and MOSFIRE spectra were modeled using a full-spectrum stellar population fitting code with variable abundance patterns. The galaxies have iron abundances between [Fe/H] = -0.5 and -0.1 dex, with typical values of $-0.2$ [$-0.3$] at $z\sim1.4$ [$z\sim2.1$]. We also find a tentative $\log\sigma_v$-[Fe/H] relation at $z\sim1.4$. The magnesium-to-iron ratios span [Mg/Fe]$\,=0.1$\,--\,$0.6$ dex, with typical values of $0.3$ [$0.5$] dex at $z\sim1.4$ [$z\sim2.1$]. The ages imply formation redshifts of $z_{\rm form}=2-8$. Compared to quiescent galaxies at lower redshifts, we find [Fe/H] was $\sim0.2$ dex lower at $z=1.4-2.1$. We find no evolution in [Mg/Fe] out to $z\sim1.4$, though the $z\sim2.1$ galaxies are $0.2$ dex enhanced compared to $z=0-0.7$. A comparison of these results to a chemical evolution model indicates that galaxies at higher redshift form at progressively earlier epochs and over shorter star-formation timescales, with the $z\sim2.1$ galaxies forming the bulk of their stars over 150 Myr at $z_{\rm form}\sim4$. This evolution cannot be solely attributed to an increased number of quiescent galaxies at later times; several Heavy Metal galaxies have extreme chemical properties not found in massive galaxies at $z\sim0.0-0.7$. Thus, the chemical properties of individual galaxies must evolve over time. Minor mergers also cannot fully account for this evolution as they cannot increase [Fe/H], particularly in galaxy centers. Consequently, the build-up of massive quiescent galaxies since $z\sim2.1$ may require further mechanisms such as major mergers and/or central star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05307v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aliza G. Beverage, Mariska Kriek, Katherine A. Suess, Charlie Conroy, Sedona H. Price, Guillermo Barro, Rachel Bezanson, Marijn Franx, Brian Lorenz, Yilun Ma, Lamiya Mowla, Imad Pasha, Pieter van Dokkum, Daniel Weisz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rate and contribution of mergers to mass assembly from NIRCam observations of galaxy candidates up to 13.3 billion years ago</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11428v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an analysis of the galaxy merger rate in the redshift range $4.0&lt;z&lt;9.0$ (i.e. about 1.5 to 0.5 Gyr after the Big Bang) based on visually identified galaxy mergers from morphological parameter analysis. Our dataset is based on high-resolution NIRCam JWST data (a combination of F150W and F200W broad-band filters) in the low-to-moderate magnification ($\mu&lt;2$) regions of the Abell 2744 cluster field. From a parent set of 675 galaxies $(M_{U}\in[-26.6,-17.9])$, we identify 64 merger candidates from the Gini, $M_{20}$ and Asymmetry morphological parameters, leading to a merger fraction $f_m=0.11\pm0.04$. There is no evidence of redshift evolution of $f_m$ even at the highest redshift considered, thus extending well into the epoch of reionization the constant trend seen previously at $z\lesssim 6$. Furthermore, we investigate any potential redshift dependent differences in the specific star formation rates between mergers and non-mergers. Our analysis reveals no significant correlation in this regard, with deviations in the studied redshift range typically falling within $(1-1.5)\sigma$ from the null hypotesis that can be attributed to sample variance and measurement errors. Finally, we also demonstrate that the classification of a merging system is robust with respect to the observed (and equivalently rest-frame) wavelength of the high-quality JWST broad-band images used. This preliminary study highlights the potential for progress in quantifying galaxy assembly through mergers during the epoch of reionization, with significant sample size growth expected from upcoming large JWST infrared imaging datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11428v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\`o Dalmasso, Antonello Calabr\`o, Nicha Leethochawalit, Benedetta Vulcani, Kristan Boyett, Michele Trenti, Tommaso Treu, Marco Castellano, Maru\v{s}a Brada\v{c}, Benjamin Metha, Paola Santini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus star formation history as revealed by detailed elemental abundances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13641v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus merger was a major event in the history of the Milky Way. Studies on Milky Way satellite dwarf galaxies show that key elemental abundance patterns, which probe different nucleosynthetic channels, reflect the host galaxy's star formation history.
  We gather Mg, Fe, Ba, and Eu abundance measurements for Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus stars from the SAGA database and use [Fe/Mg], [Ba/Mg], [Eu/Mg], and [Eu/Ba], as a function of [Fe/H] to constrain the star formation history of Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus. We use the known star formation histories and elemental abundance patterns of the Sculptor and Fornax dwarf spheroidal galaxies as comparison.
  The elemental abundance ratios of [Fe/Mg], [Ba/Mg], [Eu/Mg], and [Eu/Ba] all increase with [Fe/H] in Gaia-Sausage- Enceladus. The [Eu/Mg] begins to increase at [Fe/H]= -2.0 and continues steadily, contrasting with the Sculptor dSph galaxy. The [Eu/Ba] increases and remains high across the [Fe/H] range, contrasting with that of the Sculptor dSph galaxy and deviating from the Fornax dSph galaxy at high [Fe/H]. The [Ba/Mg] is higher than those of the Sculptor dSph galaxy at the lowest [Fe/H] and gradually increases, similar to the Fornax dSph galaxy. We constrain three main properties of the Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus star formation history: 1) star formation started gradually, 2) it extended for over 2 Gyr, and 3) it was quenched around [Fe/H] of -0.5, likely when it fell into the Milky Way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13641v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Ernandes, D. Feuillet, S. Feltzing, \'A. Sk\'ulad\'ottir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon and Iron Deficiencies in Quiescent Galaxies at z=1-3 from JWST-SUSPENSE: Implications for the Formation Histories of Massive Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02556v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the stellar metallicities and multi-element abundances (C, Mg, Si, Ca, Ti, Cr, and Fe) of 15 massive (log $M/M_\odot=10.2-11.2$) quiescent galaxies at z=1-3, derived from ultradeep JWST-SUSPENSE spectra. Compared to quiescent galaxies at z~0, these galaxies exhibit a deficiency of 0.26$\pm0.04$ dex in [C/H], 0.16$\pm0.03$ dex in [Fe/H], and 0.07$\pm0.04$ dex in [Mg/H], implying rapid formation and quenching before significant enrichment from asymptotic giant branch stars and Type Ia supernovae. Additionally, we find that galaxies forming at higher redshift consistently show higher [Mg/Fe] and lower [Fe/H] and [Mg/H], regardless of their observed redshift. The evolution in [Fe/H] and [C/H] is therefore primarily driven by lower-redshift samples naturally including galaxies with longer star-formation timescales. In contrast, the lower [Mg/H] likely reflects earlier-forming galaxies expelling larger gas reservoirs during their quenching phase. Consequently, the mass-metallicity relation, primarily reflecting [Mg/H], is somewhat lower at z=1-3 compared to the lower redshift relation. Finally, we compare our results to standard stellar population modeling approaches employing solar abundance patterns and non-parametric star-formation histories (using Prospector). Our SSP-equivalent ages agree with the mass-weighted ages from Prospector, while the metallicities disagree significantly. Nonetheless, the metallicities better reflect [Fe/H] than total [Z/H]. We also find that star-formation timescales inferred from elemental abundances are significantly shorter than those from Prospector, and we discuss the resulting implications for the early formation of massive galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02556v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aliza G. Beverage, Martje Slob, Mariska Kriek, Charlie Conroy, Guillermo Barro, Rachel Bezanson, Gabriel Brammer, Chloe M. Cheng, Anna de Graaff, Natascha M. F\"orster Schreiber, Marijn Franx, Brian Lorenz, Pavel E. Mancera Pi\~na, Danilo Marchesini, Adam Muzzin, Andrew B. Newman, Sedona H. Price, Alice E. Shapley, Mauro Stefanon, Katherine A. Suess, Pieter van Dokkum, David Weinberg, Daniel R. Weisz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASTRODEEP-JWST: NIRCam-HST multiband photometry and redshifts for half a million sources in six extragalactic deep fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00169v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a set of photometric catalogs primarily aimed at providing the community with a comprehensive database for the study of galaxy populations in the high redshift Universe. The set gathers data from eight JWST NIRCam observational programs, targeting the Abell 2744 (GLASS-JWST, UNCOVER, DDT2756 and GO3990), EGS (CEERS), COSMOS and UDS (PRIMER), and GOODS North and South (JADES and NGDEEP) deep fields, for a total area of $\sim$0.2 sq. degrees. Photometric estimates are obtained by means of well-established techniques, including tailored improvements designed to enhance the performance on the specific dataset. We also include new measurements from HST archival data, thus collecting 16 bands spanning from 0.44 to 4.44 $\mu$m. A grand total of $\sim$530 thousand sources is detected on stacks of NIRCam 3.56 and 4.44 $\mu$m mosaics. We assess the photometric accuracy by comparing fluxes and colors against archival catalogs. We also provide photometric redshift estimates, statistically validated against a large set of robust spectroscopic data. The catalogs are publicly available on the Astrodeep website.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00169v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451409</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>E. Merlin, P. Santini, D. Paris, M. Castellano, A. Fontana, T. Treu, S. L. Finkelstein, J. S. Dunlop, P. Arrabal Haro, M. Bagley, K. Boyett, A. Calabr\`o, M. Correnti, K. Davis, M. Dickinson, C. T. Donnan, H. C. Ferguson, F. Fortuni, M. Giavalisco, K. Glazebrook, A. Grazian, N. A. Grogin, N. Hathi, M. Hirschmann, J. S. Kartaltepe, L. J. Kewley, A. Kirkpatrick, D. D. Kocevski, A. M. Koekemoer, G. Leung, J. M. Lotz, R. A. Lucas, D. K. Magee, D. Marchesini, S. Mascia, D. J. McLeod, R. J. McLure, T. Nanayakkara, L. Napolitano, M. Nonino, C. Papovich, L. Pentericci, P. G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, N. Pirzkal, S. Ravindranath, G. Roberts-Borsani, R. S. Somerville, M. Trenti, J. R. Trump, B. Vulcani, X. Wang, P. J. Watson, S. M. Wilkins, G. Yang, L. Y. A. Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helical randomization of magnetized Galactic and galactic clusters plasmas: from magnetorotational disc dynamo to the Faraday rotation sky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07399v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is shown, using results of numerical simulations and Galactic and galactic clusters observations that the transition from deterministic chaos to hard turbulence in the Galactic and galactic clusters magnetized plasmas occurs through a randomization process. The notion of distributed chaos has been used to describe the randomization process. The randomization can be quantified with the main parameter of the distributed chaos which in turn can be related to magnetic helicity or its dissipation rate. Spontaneous breaking of local reflectional symmetry (an inherent property of chaotic/turbulent motions) generates local helicity even when the global helicity is negligible. It is shown that the magnetic fields can impose their level of randomization on the electron density and the Faraday rotation maps. Results of the numerical simulations of the Galactic and galactic clusters dynamos: the inner disk's ones (based on the magnetorotational instability) and global ones, are in good agreement with this approach, as well as with the results obtained using observations of the Faraday rotation sky.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07399v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Bershadskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Candidate ram-pressure stripped galaxies in six low-redshift clusters revealed from ultraviolet imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10586v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The assembly of galaxy clusters is understood to be a hierarchical process with a continuous accretion of galaxies over time, which increases the cluster size and mass. Late-type galaxies that fall into clusters can undergo ram-pressure stripping, forming extended gas tails within which star formation can happen. The number, location, and tail orientations of such galaxies provide clues about the galaxy infall process, the assembly of the cluster over time, and the consequences of infall for galaxy evolution. Here, we utilise the $\sim$ 0.5 degree diameter circular field of the Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope to image six galaxy clusters at z &lt; 0.06 that are known to contain jellyfish galaxies. We searched for stripping candidates in the ultraviolet images of these clusters, which revealed 54 candidates showing signs of unilateral extra-planar emission, due to ram-pressure stripping. Seven candidates had already been identified as likely stripping based on optical B-band imaging. We identified 47 new candidates through UV imaging. Spectroscopic redshift information is available for 39 of these candidate galaxies, of which 19 are associated with six clusters. The galaxies with spectroscopic redshifts that are not part of the clusters appear to be within structures at different redshifts identified as additional peaks in the redshift distribution of galaxies, indicating that they might be ram-pressure stripped or disturbed galaxies in other structures along the line of sight. We examine the orbital history of these galaxies based on their location in the position-velocity phase-space diagram and explore a possible connection to the orientation of the tail direction among cluster member candidates. The tails of confirmed cluster member galaxies are found to be oriented away from the cluster centre.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10586v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koshy George, B. M. Poggianti, A. Omizzolo, B. Vulcani, P. C\^ot\'e, J. Postma, R. Smith, Y. L. Jaffe, M. Gullieuszik, A. Moretti, A. Subramaniam, P. Sreekumar, S. K. Ghosh, S. N. Tandon, J. B. Hutchings</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Radcliffe Wave as traced by young open clusters: Stellar parameters, activity indicators, and abundances of solar-type members of eight young clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Radcliffe Wave has only recently been recognised as a about 3 kpc long coherent gas structure encompassing most of the star forming regions in the solar vicinity. Since its discovery, it has been mainly studied from the perspective of dynamics, but a detailed chemical study is necessary to understand its nature and the composition of the natal clouds that gave rise to it. In this paper we used some of the connected young open clusters (age $\lesssim$ 100 Myr) as tracers of the molecular clouds. We performed high-resolution spectroscopy with GIARPS at the TNG of 53 stars that are bona fide members of seven clusters located at different positions along the Radcliffe Wave. We provide radial velocities and atmospheric parameters for all of them. For a subsample consisting of 41 FGK stars we also studied the chromospheric activity and the content of Li, from which we inferred the age of the parent clusters. These values agree with the evolutionary ages reported in the literature. For these FGK stars we determined the chemical abundances for 25 species. Pleiades, ASCC 16 and NGC 7058 exhibit a solar metallicity while Melotte 20, ASCC 19, NGC 2232, and Roslund 6 show a slightly subsolar value ($\approx-$0.1 dex). On average, the clusters show a chemical composition compatible with that of the Sun, especially for $\alpha$- and Fe-peak elements. Neutron-capture elements, on the other hand, present a slight overabundance of about 0.2 dex, specially barium. Finally, considering also ASCC 123, studied by our group in a previous research, we infer a correlation between the chemical composition and the age or position of the clusters along the Wave, demonstrating their physical connection within an inhomogeneous mixing scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14373v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Alonso-Santiago, A. Frasca, A. Bragaglia, G. Catanzaro, X. Fu, G. Andreuzzi, L. Magrini, S. Lucatello, A. Vallenari, M. Jian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ALMA-QUARKS Survey: Fibers' role in star formation unveiled in an intermediate-mass protocluster region of the Vela D cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15333v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a detailed analysis of the IRS 17 filament within the intermediate-mass protocluster IRAS 08448-4343 (of $\sim\,10^3\,\rm L_{\odot}$), using ALMA data from the ATOMS 3-mm and QUARKS 1.3-mm surveys. The IRS 17 filament, which spans $\sim$54000 au ($0.26\,\rm pc$) in length and $\sim$4000 au ($0.02\,\rm pc$) in width, exhibits a complex, multi-component velocity field, and harbours hierarchical substructures. These substructures include three bundles of seven velocity-coherent fibers, and 29 dense ($n\sim 10^8\,\rm cm^{-3}$) condensations. The fibers have a median length of $\sim 4500\,\rm au$ and a median width of $\sim 1400\,\rm au$. Among these fibers, four are identified as ``fertile", each hosting at least three dense condensations, which are regarded as the ``seeds" of star formation. While the detected cores are randomly spaced within the IRS\,17 filament based on the 3-mm dust continuum image, periodic spacing ($\sim1600\,\rm au$) of condensations is observed in the fertile fibers according to the 1.3-mm dust map, consistent with the predictions of linear isothermal cylinder fragmentation models. These findings underscore the crucial role of fibers in star formation and suggest a hierarchical fragmentation process that extends from the filament to the fibers, and ultimately, to the smallest-scale condensations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15333v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongting Yang, HongLi Liu, Tie Liu, Anandmayee Tej, Xunchuan Liu, Jinhua He, Guido Garay, Amelia Stutz, Lei Zhu, Sheng-Li Qin, Fengwei Xu, Pak-Shing Li, Mika Juvela, Pablo Garcia, Paul F. Goldsmith, Siju Zhang, Xindi Tang, Patricio Sanhueza, Shanghuo Li, Chang Won Lee, Swagat Ranjan Das, Wenyu Jiao, Xiaofeng Mai, Prasanta Gorai, Yichen Zhang, Zhiyuan Ren, L. Viktor Toth, Jihye Hwang, Leonardo Bronfman, Kenichi Tatematsu, Lokesh Dewangan, James O. Chibueze, Suinan Zhang, Gang Wu, Jinjin Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YOLO-CL: Galaxy cluster detection in the SDSS with deep machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.09657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.09657v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: (Abridged) Galaxy clusters are a powerful probe of cosmological models. Next generation large-scale optical and infrared surveys will reach unprecedented depths over large areas and require highly complete and pure cluster catalogs, with a well defined selection function. We have developed a new cluster detection algorithm YOLO-CL, which is a modified version of the state-of-the-art object detection deep convolutional network YOLO, optimized for the detection of galaxy clusters. We trained YOLO-CL on color images of the redMaPPer cluster detections in the SDSS. We find that YOLO-CL detects $95-98\%$ of the redMaPPer clusters, with a purity of $95-98\%$ calculated by applying the network to SDSS blank fields. When compared to the MCXC2021 X-ray catalog in the SDSS footprint,YOLO-CL is more complete then redMaPPer, which means that the neural network improved the cluster detection efficiency of its training sample. The YOLO-CL selection function is approximately constant with redshift, with respect to the MCXC2021 cluster mean X-ray surface brightness. YOLO-CL shows high performance when compared to traditional detection algorithms applied to SDSS. Deep learning networks benefit from a strong advantage over traditional galaxy cluster detection techniques because they do not need galaxy photometric and photometric redshift catalogs. This eliminates systematic uncertainties that can be introduced during source detection, and photometry and photometric redshift measurements. Our results show that YOLO-CL is an efficient alternative to traditional cluster detection methods. In general, this work shows that it is worth exploring the performance of deep convolution networks for future cosmological cluster surveys, such as the Rubin/LSST, Euclid or the Roman Space Telescope surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.09657v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202345976</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 677, A101 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Grishin, Simona Mei, St\'ephane Ilic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple model of dust extinction in gamma-ray burst host galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03570v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gamma-ray burst (GRB) afterglows are powerful probes for studying the different properties of their host galaxies (e.g., the interstellar dust) at all redshifts. By fitting their spectral energy distribution (SED) over a large range of wavelengths, we can gain direct insights into the properties of the interstellar dust by studying the extinction curves. Unlike the dust extinction templates, such as the average Milky Way (MW) or the Small and Large Magellanic Cloud (SMC and LMC), the extinction curves of galaxies outside the Local Group exhibit deviation from these laws. Altogether, X-ray and gamma-ray satellites as well as ground-based telescopes, such as Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory (Swift) and Gamma-Ray Optical and Near-Infrared Detector (GROND), provide measurements of the afterglows from the X-ray to the NIR, which can be used to extract information on dust extinction curves along their lines of sight. The study presented in this paper undertakes such a photometric study, comprising a preparatory work for the SVOM mission and its ground-based follow-up telescope COLIBRI. We propose a simple parameterization of the dust extinction curve of GRB host galaxies. Our model is based on a power law form with the addition of a Loretzian-like Drude profile with two parameters: the extinction slope, $\gamma$, and the 2175 $\AA$ bump amplitude, $E_\rm{b}$. Using the seven GROND filter bands, we tested our dust extinction model and explored the parameter space in extinction and redshift by fitting SEDs of simplified simulations of GRB afterglow spectra based on different extinction curve templates. From a final sample of 10 real Swift/GROND extinguished GRBs, we determined the quantities of the dust extinction in their host and measured their extinction curves. The measured average extinction curve is equivalent to a quasi-featureless in-between SMC-LMC template.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03570v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202450601</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>N. A. Rakotondrainibe, V. Buat, D. Turpin, D. Dornic, E. LeFloc'h, S. D. Vergani, S. Basa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling absorption and emission profiles from accretion disc winds with WINE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13933v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fast, massive winds are ubiquitously observed in the UV and X-ray spectra of Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) and other accreting sources. Theoretical and observational evidences suggest they are launched at accretion disc scales, carrying significant mass and angular momentum. Thanks to such high energy output, they may play an important role in transferring the accretion energy to the surrounding environment. In the case of AGNs, this process can help setting the so-called coevolution between the AGN and its host galaxy. To precisely assess the effective role of these winds, it is necessary to accurately measure their properties, including mass and energy rates. We aim to maximise the scientific return of current and future observations by improving the theoretical modelling of these winds through our Winds in the Ionised Nuclear Environment (WINE) model. WINE is a spectroscopic model designed for disc winds in AGNs and compact accreting sources, which couples photoionisation and radiative transfer with special relativistic effects and a three-dimensional model of the emission profiles. We explore with WINE the main spectral features associated to AGN disc winds, with particular emphasis on the detectability of the wind emission. We simulate observations with the X-ray microcalorimeters Resolve on board the XRISM satellite and the future Athena's X-IFU for the typical properties and exposure times of the sources in the XRISM Performance Verification phase. The wind kinematic, geometry, ionisation and column density deeply affect shape and strength of the spectral features. Thanks to this, both Resolve and X-IFU will be able to accurately constrain the main properties of disc winds in a broad range of parameters. We also find a dramatic difference in the gas opacity when using a soft, Narrow Line Seyfert 1-like SED compared to a canonical powerlaw SED with spectral index Gamma=2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13933v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfredo Luminari, Enrico Piconcelli, Francesco Tombesi, Fabrizio Nicastro, Fabrizio Fiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
