<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 01:31:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Simulations of Stellar Halos with Gaia Sausage-Enceladus Analogues: Two Sausages, One Bun?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observations of the Milky Way's stellar halo find that it is predominantly comprised of a radially-biased population of stars, dubbed the Gaia Sausage--Enceladus, or GSE. These stars are thought to be debris from dwarf galaxy accretion early in the Milky Way's history. Though typically considered to be from a single merger, it is possible that the GSE debris has multiple sources. To investigate this possibility, we use the IllustrisTNG50 simulation to identify stellar accretion histories in 98 Milky Way analogues -- the largest sample for which such an identification has been performed -- and find GSE-like debris in 32, with two-merger GSEs accounting for a third of these cases. Distinguishing single-merger GSEs from two-merger GSEs is difficult in common kinematic spaces, but differences are more evident through chemical abundances and star formation histories. This is because single-merger GSEs are typically accreted more recently than the galaxies in two-merger GSEs: the median infall times (with 16th and 84th percentiles) are $5.9^{+3.3}_{-2.0}$ and $10.7^{+1.2}_{-3.7}$ Gyr ago for these scenarios, respectively. The systematic shifts in abundances and ages which occur as a result suggest that efforts in modeling these aspects of the stellar halo prove ever-important in understanding its assembly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02723v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Folsom, Mariangela Lisanti, Lina Necib, Danny Horta, Mark Vogelsberger, Lars Hernquist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peculiar dark matter halos inferred from gravitational lensing as a manifestation of modified gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If modified gravity holds, but the weak lensing analysis is done in the standard way, one finds that dark matter halos have peculiar shapes, not following the standard Navarro-Frenk-White profiles, and are fully predictable from the distribution of baryons. Here we study in detail the distribution of the apparent dark matter around point masses, which approximate galaxies and galaxy clusters, and their pairs for the QUMOND MOND gravity, taking an external gravitational acceleration $g_e$ into account. At large radii, the apparent halo of a point mass $M$ is shifted against the direction of the external field. When averaged over all lines-of-sight, the halo has a hollow center, and denoting the by $a_0$ the MOND acceleration constant, its density behaves like $\rho(r)=\sqrt{Ma_0/G}/(4\pi r^2)$ between the galacticentric radii $\sqrt{GM/a_0}$ and $\sqrt{GMa_0}/g_e$, and like $\rho\propto r^{-7}G^2M^3a_0^3/g_e^5$ further away. Between a pair of point masses, there is a region of a negative apparent dark matter density, whose mass can exceed the baryonic mass of the system. The density of the combined dark matter halo is not a sum of the densities of the halos of the individual points. The density has a singularity near the zero-acceleration point, but remains finite in projection. We compute maps of the surface density and the lensing shear for several configurations of the problem, and derive formulas to scale them to further configurations. In general, for a large subset of MOND theories in their weak field regime, for any configuration of the baryonic mass $M$ with the characteristic size of $d$, the total lensing density scales as $\rho({\vec{x}})=\sqrt{Ma_0/G}d^{-2}f\left(\vec{\alpha},\vec{x}/d,g_ed/\sqrt{GMa_0}\right)$, where the vector $\vec{\alpha}$ describes the geometry of the system. Distinguishing between QUMOND and cold dark matter seems possible with the existing instruments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02725v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal B\'ilek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JADES Ultra-red Flattened Objects: Morphologies and Spatial Gradients in Color and Stellar Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the more surprising findings after the first year of JWST observations is the large number of spatially extended galaxies (ultra-red flattened objects, or UFOs) among the optically-faint galaxy population otherwise thought to be compact. Leveraging the depth and survey area of the JADES survey, we extend observations of the optically-faint galaxy population to an additional 112 objects, 56 of which are well-resolved in F444W with effective sizes, $R_e &gt; 0.25''$, more than tripling previous UFO counts. These galaxies have redshifts around $2 &lt; z &lt; 4$, high stellar masses ($\mathrm{log(M_*/M_{\odot})} \sim 10-11$), and star-formation rates around $\sim 100-1000 \mathrm{M_{\odot}/yr}$. Surprisingly, UFOs are red across their entire extents which spatially resolved analysis of their stellar populations shows is due to large values of dust attenuation (typically $A_V &gt; 2$ mag even at large radii). Morphologically, the majority of our UFO sample tends to have low S\'ersic indices ($n \sim 1$) suggesting these large, massive, optically faint galaxies have little contribution from a bulge in F444W. Further, a majority have axis-ratios between $0.2 &lt; q &lt; 0.4$, which Bayesian modeling suggests that their intrinsic shapes are consistent with being a mixture of inclined disks and prolate objects with little to no contribution from spheroids. While kinematic constraints will be needed to determine the true intrinsic shapes of UFOs, it is clear that an unexpected population of large, disky or prolate objects contributes significantly to the population of optically faint galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02726v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad64c2</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Justus L. Gibson, Erica Nelson, Christina C. Williams, Sedona H. Price, Katherine E. Whitaker, Katherine A. Suess, Anna de Graaff, Benjamin D. Johnson, Andrew J. Bunker, William M. Baker, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Kristan Boyett, Stephane Charlot, Emma Curtis-Lake, Daniel J. Eisenstein, Kevin Hainline, Ryan Hausen, Roberto Maiolino, George Rieke, Marcia Rieke, Brant Robertson, Sandro Tacchella, Chris Willott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disk Turbulence and Star Formation Regulation in High$-z$ Main Sequence Analogue Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The gas-phase velocity dispersions in disk galaxies, which trace turbulence in the interstellar medium, are observed to increase with lookback time. However, the mechanisms that set this rise in turbulence are observationally poorly constrained. To address this, we combine kiloparsec-scale ALMA observations of CO(3-2) and CO(4-3) with HST observations of H$\alpha$ to characterize the molecular gas and star formation properties of seven local analogues of main sequence galaxies at $z \sim 1-2$, drawn from the DYNAMO sample. Investigating the ''molecular gas main sequence'' on kpc-scales, we find that galaxies in our sample are more gas-rich than local star-forming galaxies at all disk positions. We measure beam smearing corrected molecular gas velocity dispersions and relate them to the molecular gas and star formation rate surface densities. Despite being relatively nearby ($z \sim 0.1$), DYNAMO galaxies exhibit high velocity dispersions and gas and star formation rate surface densities throughout their disks, when compared to local star forming samples. Comparing these measurements to predictions from star formation theory, we find very good agreements with the latest feedback-regulated star formation models. However, we find that theories which combine gravitational energy dissipation from radial gas transport with feedback over-estimate the observed molecular gas velocity dispersions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02730v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Lenki\'c, Deanne B. Fisher, Alberto D. Bolatto, Peter J. Teuben, Rebecca C. Levy, Jiayi Sun, Rodrigo Herrera-Camus, Karl Glazebrook, Danail Obreschkow, Roberto Abraham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galactic Orbits of Interstellar Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02739v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. The first interstellar objects, such as 'Oumuamua, Borisov and IM1, were discovered over the past decade. Aims. We follow the trajectories of known interstellar objects in the gravitational potential of the Milky Way galaxy to constrain their possible origin. Methods. We initiate the trajectories based on the measured velocities of the interstellar objects relative to the Local Standard of Rest. Since the scale-height of stars in the Milky-Way disk increases with age, we use the vertical excursion of each interstellar object from the Milky-Way disk mid-plane to constrain their likely age. Results. The small vertical extent of 'Oumuamua's past trajectory suggests that it originated near the mid-plane of the thin disk, implying a likely age younger than 1-2 Gyr. The maximal excursion of the comet Borisov is similar to that of the Sun, suggesting a similar age. The meteor IM1 exhibits yet larger vertical excursions, suggesting an older source. Finally, we show that human-made interstellar probes, like Voyager 1 or Pioneer 10 will arrive at the opposite side of the Milky Way disk relative to the Sun in $\sim$ 2 Gyr and return to the vicinity of the Sun before it becomes a red giant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02739v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shokhruz Kakharov, Abraham Loeb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Enrichment Population Theory at High Redshift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An Early Enrichment Population (EEP) has been theorized to produce the observed metallicity in the intracluster medium (ICM) of galaxy clusters. This population likely existed at high redshifts (z$\sim$10), relics of which we posit exist today as dwarf galaxies. Previous work argues that the initial mass function (IMF) of the EEP must be flatter than those found at lower redshifts, but with considerable uncertainties. In this work, we present a more quantitative model for the EEP and demonstrate how observational constraints can be applied to the IMF using supernova Type Ia (SNIa) rates, delay time distribution (DTD), and the luminosity function (LF) of galaxy clusters. We determine best-fit values for the slope and mass break of the IMF by comparing IMFs from literature with observed DTDs and the low-luminosity component ($M(R)&lt; -12$) of the Coma LF. We derive two best-fit IMFs: (1) $\alpha_{lo} = -0.13 \pm 0.24$ for $0.07 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 1.75$ and $\alpha_{hi} = 0.53 \pm 0.01$ for $1.75 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 150$, and (2) $\alpha_{lo} = 1.06 \pm 0.11$ for $0.07 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 6$ and $\alpha_{hi} = 0.53 \pm 0.01$ for $6 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 150$. We also compare these with sl-5 from Loewenstein (2013) with $\alpha=0.5$ for $0.07 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 8$ and $\alpha=0.3$ for $8 &lt; M/M_\odot &lt; 150$. This EEP model, along with stars formed at later times, can produce the observed metallicity, is consistent with other observations, and predicts a significant rise in the SNIa rate at increasing redshift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02781v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne E. Blackwell, Joel N. Bregman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rich interstellar reservoir of dinitriles: Detection of malononitrile and maleonitrile in TMC-1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While the nitrile group is by far the most prevalent one among interstellar molecules, the existence of interstellar dinitriles (molecules containing two -CN groups) has recently been proven. Here we report the discovery of two new dinitriles in the cold dense cloud TMC-1. These newly identified species are malononitrile, CH2(CN)2, and maleonitrile, the Z isomer of NC-CH=CH-CN, which can be seen as the result of substituting two H atoms with two -CN groups in methane and ethylene, respectively. These two molecules were detected using data from the ongoing QUIJOTE line survey of TMC-1 that is being carried out with the Yebes 40m telescope. We derive column densities of 1.8e11 cm-2 and 5.1e10 cm-2 for malononitrile and maleonitrile, respectively. This means that they are eight and three times less abundant than HCC-CH2-CN and (E)-HCC-CH=CH-CN, respectively, which are analog molecules detected in TMC-1 in which one -CN group is converted into a -CCH group. This is in line with previous findings in which -CCH derivatives are more abundant than the -CN counterparts in TMC-1. We examined the potential chemical pathways to these two dinitriles, and we find that while maleonitrile can be efficiently formed through the reaction of CN with CH2CHCN, the formation of malononitrile is not clear because the neutral-neutral reactions that could potentially form it are not feasible under the physical conditions of TMC-1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02843v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Agundez, C. Bermudez, C. Cabezas, G. Molpeceres, Y. Endo, N. Marcelino, B. Tercero, J. -C. Guillemin, P. de Vicente, J. Cernicharo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A framework for incorporating binding energy distribution in gas-ice astrochemical models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the most serious limitations of current astrochemical models with the rate equation (RE) approach is that only a single type of binding site is considered in grain surface chemistry, although laboratory and quantum chemical studies have found that surfaces contain various binding sites with different potential energy depths. When various sites exist, adsorbed species can be trapped in deep potential sites, increasing the resident time on the surface. On the other hand, adsorbed species can be populated in shallow sites, activating thermal hopping and thus two-body reactions even at low temperatures, where the thermal hopping from deeper sites is not activated. Such behavior cannot be described by the conventional RE approach. In this work, I present a framework for incorporating various binding sites (i.e., binding energy distribution) in gas-ice astrochemical models as an extension of the conventional RE approach. I propose a simple method to estimate the probability density function for the occupation of various sites by adsorbed species, assuming a quasi-steady state. By using thermal desorption and hopping rates weighted by the probability density functions, the effect of binding energy distribution is incorporated into the RE approach without increasing the number of ordinary differential equations to be solved. This method is found to be accurate and computationally efficient and enables us to consider binding energy distribution even for a large gas-ice chemical network, which contains hundreds of icy species. The impact of the binding energy distribution on interstellar ice composition is discussed quantitatively for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02958v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenji Furuya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAST detection of OH emission in the carbon-rich planetary nebula NGC 7027</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first detection of the ground-state OH emission line at 1612 MHz toward the prototypical carbon-rich planetary nebula (PN) NGC 7027, utilizing the newly installed ultra-wideband (UWB) receiver of the Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical radio Telescope (FAST). This emission is likely to originate from the interface of the neutral shell and the ionized region. The other three ground-state OH lines at 1665, 1667, and 1721 MHz are observed in absorption and have velocities well matched with that of HCO$^+$ absorption. We infer that the OH absorption is from the outer shell of NGC 7027, although the possibility that they are associated with a foreground cloud cannot be completely ruled out. All the OH lines exhibit a single blue-shifted component with respect to the central star. The formation of OH in carbon-rich environments might be via photodissociation-induced chemical processes. Our observations offer significant constraints for chemical simulations, and they underscore the potent capability of the UWB receiver of FAST to search for nascent PNe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02962v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu-Jia Ouyang, Yong Zhang, Chuan-Peng Zhang, Peng Jiang, Jun-ichi Nakashima, Xi Chen, Hai-Hua Qiao, Xu-Ying Zhang, Hao-Min Sun, Xiao-Hu Li, Albert Zijlstra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Star Cluster Within Galaxy using Self-consistent Hybrid Hydro/N-body Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a GPU-accelerated hybrid hydro/N-body code (Enzo-N) designed to address the challenges of concurrently simulating star clusters and their parent galaxies. This task has been exceedingly challenging, primarily due to the considerable computational time required, which stems from the substantial scale difference between galaxies (~ 0.1 Mpc) and star clusters (~ pc). Yet, this significant scale separation means that particles within star clusters perceive those outside the star cluster in a semi-stationary state. By leveraging this aspect, we integrate the direct N-body code (Nbody6++GPU) into the cosmological (magneto-)hydrodynamic code (Enzo) through the utilization of the semi-stationary background acceleration approximation. We solve the dynamics of particles within star clusters using the direct N-body solver with regularization for few-body interactions, while evolving particles outside -- dark matter, gas, and stars -- using the particle-mesh gravity solver and hydrodynamic methods. We demonstrate that Enzo-N successfully simulates the co-evolution of star clusters and their parent galaxies, capturing phenomena such as core collapse of the star cluster and tidal stripping due to galactic tides. This comprehensive framework opens up new possibilities for studying the evolution of star clusters within galaxies, offering insights that were previously inaccessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03128v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad6b16</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yongseok Jo, Seoyoung Kim, Ji-hoon Kim, Greg L. Bryan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of the high-mass star-forming region S255IR at various scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The S255IR-SMA1 core contains the protostar NIRS3 with a mass of $\sim$20 M$_\odot$. Several years ago, the first burst of luminosity for massive protostars, caused by an episodic accretion event, was recorded here. We have been studying this object for a long time using various instruments, including ALMA. The general morphology and kinematics of this area have been investigated. Disk-shaped structures, jets and outflows have been identified and studied in detail. We recently observed this object with ALMA with a resolution an order of magnitude higher than previously achieved - about 15 milliarcseconds, which corresponds to about 25 AU. This paper presents new results from the analysis of these data together with observations in other bands. The new data show an inhomogeneous disk structure, an ionized region around the protostar, and the presence of a jet observed in the submillimeter continuum, consisting of individual knots, the orientation of which differs markedly from that on large scales. The submillimeter emission from the jet most likely represents bremsstrahlung from ionized gas. Based on observations of the lines of some molecules, the kinematics and physical characteristics of this region are discussed. Methanol maser emission associated with the jet is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03133v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. I. Zinchenko (Institute of Applied Physics of the Russian Academy of Sciences), S. -Y. Liu (Institute of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Academia Sinica, Taiwan), D. K. Ojha (Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai, India), Y. -N. Su (Institute of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Academia Sinica, Taiwan), P. M. Zemlyanukha (Institute of Applied Physics of the Russian Academy of Sciences)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Balmer Jump Street: The Nebular Continuum at High Redshift and Implications for the Bright Galaxy Problem, UV Continuum Slopes, and Early Stellar Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03189v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study, from both a theoretical and observational perspective, the physical origin and spectroscopic impact of extreme nebular emission in high-redshift galaxies. The nebular continuum, which can appear during extreme starbursts, is of particular importance as it tends to redden UV slopes and has a significant contribution to the UV luminosities of galaxies. Furthermore, its shape can be used to infer the gas density and temperature of the ISM. First, we provide a theoretical background, showing how different stellar populations (SPS models, IMFs, and stellar temperatures) and nebular conditions impact observed galaxy spectra. We demonstrate that, for systems with strong nebular continuum emission, 1) UV fluxes can increase by up to 0.7~magnitudes (or more in the case of hot/massive stars) above the stellar continuum, which may help reconcile the surprising abundance of bright high-redshift galaxies and the elevated UV luminosity density at $z&gt;10$, 2) at high gas densities, UV slopes can redden from $\beta\lesssim-2.5$ to $\beta\sim-1$, 3) observational measurements of $\xi_{ion}$ are grossly underestimated, and 4) UV downturns from two-photon emission can masquerade as DLAs. Second, we present a dataset of 58 galaxies observed with NIRSpec on JWST at $2.5&lt;z&lt;9.0$ that are selected to have strong nebular continuum emission via the detection of the Balmer jump. Five of the 58 spectra are consistent with being dominated by nebular emission, exhibiting both a Balmer jump and a UV downturn consistent with two-photon emission. For some galaxies, this may imply the presence of hot massive stars and a top-heavy IMF. We conclude by exploring the properties of spectroscopically confirmed $z&gt;10$ galaxies, finding that UV slopes and UV downturns are in some cases redder or steeper than expected from SPS models, which may hint at more exotic (e.g. hotter/more massive stars or AGN) ionizing sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03189v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harley Katz, Alex J. Cameron, Aayush Saxena, Laia Barrufet, Nicholas Choustikov, Nikko J. Cleri, Anna de Graaff, Richard S. Ellis, Robert A. E. Fosbury, Kasper E. Heintz, Michael Maseda, Jorryt Matthee, Ian McConchie, Pascal A. Oesch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Red Type-1 Quasars after Cosmic Noon and Impact on $L_{\rm UV}$-related Quasar Statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03228v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past decades, nearly a million quasars have been explored to shed light on the evolution of supermassive black holes and galaxies. The ultraviolet-to-optical spectra of type-1 quasars particularly offer insights into their black hole activities. Recent findings, however, raise questions about the prevalence of red type-1 quasars of which colors might be due to dust-obscuration and their potential influence on luminosity-related properties of quasars. We examine the fraction of red type-1 quasars within the redshift range of $0.68\leq z &lt; 2.20$, applying spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting using optical-to-MIR photometric data of Sloan Digital Sky Survey Data Release 14 quasars. Approximately 10\,\% of the type-1 quasars exhibit red colors suggestive of dust obscuration. There is an association between the brightness of the MIR luminosity and a higher fraction of red type-1 quasars, albeit with negligible redshift evolution. By employing $E(B-V)$ values from the SED fitting, we obtained dereddened luminosity of the red type-1 quasars and reassess the quasar luminosity function (QLF) and black hole mass ($M_{\rm BH}$) estimates. Result shows a modest increase in the number density of bright quasars, linking to more flatten bright-end slope of QLFs, while $M_{\rm BH}$ adjustments are minimal. Current SDSS selections in optical could miss a significant population of heavily dust-obscured quasars. As future MIR surveys like SPHEREx expand, they may reveal enough obscured quasars to prompt a more profound revision of fundamental quasar properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03228v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongjung Kim, Dohyeong Kim, Myungshin Im, Minjin Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of the physical and chemical properties of dense clumps in several high-mass star-forming regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive stars play an important role in the Universe. Unlike low-mass stars, the formation of these objects located at great distances is still unclear. It is expected to be governed by some combination of self-gravity, turbulence, and magnetic fields. Our aim is to study of the chemical and physical conditions of dense clumps in several high-mass star-forming regions. We performed observations towards 5 high-mass star-forming regions (L1287, S187, S231, DR21(OH), NGC7538) with the IRAM 30 m telescope. We covered the 2-3 and 4 mm wavelength band and analyzed the lines of HCN, HNC, HCO$^+$, HC$_3$N, HNCO, OCS, CS, SiO, SO$_2$ and SO. Using astrodendro algorithm on the 850 $\mu$m dust emission data from the SCUBA Legacy catalogue, we identified dense gas clumps and determined their masses, H$_2$ column densities and sizes. Furthermore, the kinetic temperatures, molecular abundances and dynamical state were obtained. The Red Midcourse Space Experiment Source survey (RMS) was used to determine the clump types. We identified $\sim$20 clumps. We found no significant correlation between line width and size, but the linewidth-mass and mass-size relationships are strongly correlated. Virial analysis indicated that the clumps with HII regions and young stellar objects (YSOs) are gravitationally bound. Furthermore, it was suggested that significant magnetic fields provide additional support for clump stability. The molecular abundances decrease from YSOs to submm and HII regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03271v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Pazukhin, I. I. Zinchenko, E. A. Trofimova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dwarf Galaxies in the MATLAS Survey: Hubble Space Telescope Observations of the Globular Cluster Systems of 74 Ultra Diffuse Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra diffuse galaxies, characterized by their low surface brightness and large physical size, constitute a subclass of dwarf galaxies that challenge our current understanding of galaxy formation and evolution. In this paper, we probe the properties of 74 UDGs, identified in the MATLAS survey, based on a comprehensive study of their globular cluster (GC) populations. We obtained high resolution HST imaging of these galaxies using the ACS F606W and F814W filters, allowing us to select GCs based on color and concentration index. After background subtraction and completeness correction, we calculate an overall total of 387 GCs. The number of GCs per galaxy ranges from 0 to 38, with the majority (64%) having low counts (0-2 GCs). On average, the more massive UDGs host a larger number of GCs. We find that our UDGs have specific frequencies (S_N) ranging from 0 to 91, with a small population (9%) with S_N &gt; 30. The median S_N of our sample is similar to the one for the Perseus cluster UDGs, despite the fact that our UDGs are found in lower density environments. The S_N measurements for individual galaxies can extend beyond those found in Perseus, but remain below the values found for UDGs in the Virgo and Coma cluster. Based on a trending analysis of the S_N values with the host galaxy properties, we find trends with host galaxy size, roundness, color, and local density. For the UDGs with sufficiently high statistics, we study 2D density maps of the GC distributions, which show a variety of appearances: symmetric, asymmetric, off-center, and elongated. The UDGs with disturbed density maps also show disturbed stellar light morphologies. We further quantify the distribution by modeling it with a Sersic profile, finding R_{e,GC}/R_{e,gal} ~ 1.0, which indicates that the GCs follow the stellar light of the host galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03311v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francine R. Marleau, Pierre-Alain Duc, Melina Poulain, Oliver Mueller, Sungsoon Lim, Patrick R. Durrell, Rebecca Habas, Ruben Sanchez-Janssen, Sanjaya Paudel, Jeremy Fensch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eddington Ratios of Dust-obscured Quasars at $z \lesssim 1$: Evidence Supporting Dust-obscured Quasars as Young Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03324v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dust-obscured quasars have been suspected as the intermediate stage galaxies between merger-driven star-forming galaxies and unobscured quasars. This merger-driven galaxy evolution scenario suggests that dust-obscured quasars exhibit higher Eddington ratios ($\lambda_{\rm Edd}$) than those of unobscured quasars. However, their high dust obscuration poses challenges to accurately measuring their $\lambda_{\rm Edd}$ using commonly employed bolometric luminosity ($L_{\rm bol}$) and black hole (BH) mass ($M_{\rm BH}$) estimators based on the ultraviolet (UV) or optical luminosity. Recently, Kim et al. (2023) established new estimators for $L_{\rm bol}$ and $M_{\rm BH}$ based on mid-infrared (MIR) continuum luminosity ($L_{\rm MIR}$), which are less affected by dust obscuration. These estimators enable the study of a large number of dust-obscured quasars across a wide redshift range. In this study, we measure the $\lambda_{\rm Edd}$ values of 30 dust-obscured quasars at $z \lesssim 1$, the largest sample size to date, using the $L_{\rm MIR}$-based $L_{\rm bol}$ and $M_{\rm BH}$ estimators. Our findings reveal that dust-obscured quasars exhibit significantly higher $\lambda_{\rm Edd}$ values compared to unobscured quasars. Moreover, we confirm that the enhanced $\lambda_{\rm Edd}$ values of dust-obscured quasars maintain consistency across the redshift span of 0 to 1. Our results strongly support the picture that dust-obscured quasars are in the earlier stage than unobscured quasars in the merger-driven galaxy evolutionary track.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03324v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dohyeong Kim, Yongjung Kim, Myungshin Im, Eilat Glikman, Minjin Kim, Tanya Urrutia, Gu Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Emission Regions in Jets of Low Luminosity Active Galactic Nucleus in NGC 4278</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15657v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO) has detected very high energy gamma rays from the LINER galaxy NGC 4278, which has a low luminosity active galactic nucleus, and symmetric mildly relativistic S-shaped twin jets detected by radio observations. Few low-luminosity active galactic nuclei are detected in gamma rays due to their faintness. Earlier, several radio-emitting components were detected in the jets of NGC 4278. We model their radio emission with synchrotron emission of ultra-relativistic electrons to estimate the strength of the magnetic field inside these components within a time-dependent framework after including the ages of the different components. We show that the synchrotron and synchrotron self-Compton emission by these components cannot explain the Swift X-ray data and the LHAASO gamma-ray data from NGC 4278. We suggest that a separate component in one of the jets is responsible for the high energy emission whose age, size, magnetic field and the spectrum of the ultra-relativistic electrons inside it have been estimated after fitting the multi-wavelength data of NGC 4278 with the sum of the spectral energy distributions from the radio components and the high energy component. We note that the radio components of NGC 4278 are larger than the high-energy component which has also been observed in several high-luminosity active galactic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15657v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samik Dutta, Nayantara Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turbulent Pressure Support in Galaxy Clusters -- Impact of the Hydrodynamical Solver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02719v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The amount of turbulent pressure in galaxy clusters is still debated, especially as for the impact of the dynamical state and the hydro-method used for simulations. We study the turbulent pressure fraction in the intra cluster medium of massive galaxy clusters. We aim to understand the impact of the hydrodynamical scheme, analysis method, and dynamical state on the final properties of galaxy clusters from cosmological simulations. We perform non-radiative simulations of a set of zoom-in regions of seven galaxy clusters with Meshless Finite Mass (MFM) and Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics (SPH). We use three different analysis methods based on: $(i)$ the deviation from hydrostatic equilibrium, $(ii)$ the solenoidal velocity component obtained by a Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition, and $(iii)$ the small-scale velocity obtained through a multi-scale filtering approach. We split the sample of simulated clusters into active and relaxed clusters. Our simulations predict an increased turbulent pressure fraction for active compared to relaxed clusters. This is especially visible for the velocity-based methods. For these, we also find increased turbulence for the MFM simulations compared to SPH, consistent with findings from more idealized simulations. The predicted non-thermal pressure fraction varies between a few percent for relaxed clusters and $\approx13\%$ for active ones within the cluster center and increases towards the outskirts. No clear trend with redshift is visible. Our analysis quantitatively assesses the importance played by the hydrodynamical scheme and the analysis method to determine the non-thermal/turbulent pressure fraction. While our setup is relatively simple (non-radiative runs), our simulations show agreement with previous, more idealized simulations, and make a step further toward the understanding of turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02719v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederick Groth, Milena Valentini, Ulrich P. Steinwandel, David Vall\'es-P\'erez, Klaus Dolag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Argon X-ray absorption in the local ISM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first comprehensive analysis of the argon K-edge absorption region (3.1-4.2 \AA) using high-resolution HETGS {\it Chandra} spectra of 33 low-mas X-ray binaries. Utilizing R-matrix theory, we computed new K photoabsorption cross-sections for {\rm Ar}~{\sc i}--{\rm Ar}~{\sc xvi} species. For each X-ray source, we estimated column densities for the {\rm Ar}~{\sc i}, {\rm Ar}~{\sc ii}, {\rm Ar}~{\sc iii}, {\rm Ar}~{\sc xvi}, {\rm Ar}~{\sc xvii} and {\rm Ar}~{\sc xviii} ions, which trace the neutral, warm and hot components of the gaseous Galactic interstellar medium. We examined their distribution as a function of Galactic latitude, longitude, and distances to the sources. However, no significant correlations were discerned among distances, Galactic latitude, or longitude. Future X-ray observatories will allow us to benchmark the atomic data as the main resonance lines will be resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02734v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Gatuzz, T. W. Gorczyca, M. F. Hasoglu, J. A. Garc\'ia, T. R. Kallman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical properties of filaments in the cosmic web</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03083v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the context of the cosmological and constrained ELUCID simulation, this study explores the statistical characteristics of filaments within the cosmic web, focussing on aspects such as the distribution of filament lengths and their radial density profiles. Using the classification of the cosmic web environment through the Hessian matrix of the density field, our primary focus is on how cosmic structures react to the two variables $R_{\rm s}$ and $\lambda_{\rm th}$. The findings show that the volume fractions of knots, filaments, sheets, and voids are highly influenced by the threshold parameter $\lambda_{\rm th}$, with only a slight influence from the smoothing length $R_{\rm s}$. The central axis of the cylindrical filament is pinpointed using the medial-axis thinning algorithm of the COWS method. It is observed that median filament lengths tend to increase as the smoothing lengths increase. Analysis of filament length functions at different values of $R_{\rm s}$ indicates a reduction in shorter filaments and an increase in longer filaments as $R_{\rm s}$ increases, peaking around $2.5R_{\rm s}$. The study also shows that the radial density profiles of filaments are markedly affected by the parameters $R_{\rm s}$ and $\lambda_{\rm th}$, showing a valley at approximately $2R_{\rm s}$, with increases in the threshold leading to higher amplitudes of the density profile. Moreover, shorter filaments tend to have denser profiles than their longer counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03083v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youcai Zhang, Hong Guo, Xiaohu Yang, Peng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galactic-Field Metal-Rich RR~Lyrae Variables: Features of Kinematics and Abundances of Selected Chemical Elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03107v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an analysis of the relative abundance features of a number of chemical elements in the atmospheres of metal-rich ($\rm{[Fe/H]} &gt; -1.0$) Galactic-field RR~Lyrae variable stars and the kinematic characteristics of these stars. We have previously shown that the relative abundances of some $\alpha$-elements: magnesium, silicon, calcium, and to a greater extent of titanium, as well as yttrium and scandium in such stars are lower than in most of other types of stars, bearing similar metallicity. It is found here that some of these metal-rich RR~Lyrae stars also have very low relative abundances of sodium, aluminum and nickel. The orbital parameters of all the metal-rich RR~Lyrae variables studied in this paper are typical of the Galactic thin or thick disk objects, however, unusual chemical composition let us to suggests a possible extragalactic origin for some of them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03107v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024, Astrophysical Bulletin, Vol. 79, No. 3</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. L. Gozha, V. A. Marsakov, V. V. Koval'</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Dust-Scattering Model for M1-92: A Revised Estimate of the Mass Distribution and Inclination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03136v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Preplanetary nebulae (PPNe) are formed from mass-ejecting late-stage AGB stars. Much of the light from the star gets scattered or absorbed by dust particles, giving rise to the observed reflection nebula seen at visible and near-IR wavelengths. Precursors to planetary nebulae (PNe), PPNe generally have not yet undergone any ionization by UV radiation from the still-buried stellar core. Bipolar PPNe are a common form of observed PPNe. This study lays the groundwork for future dynamical studies by reconstructing the dust density distribution of a particularly symmetric bipolar PPN, M1-92 (Minkowski's Footprint, IRAS 19343$+$2926). For this purpose, we develop an efficient single-scattering radiative transfer model with corrections for double-scattering. Using a V-band image from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST), we infer the dust density profile and orientation of M1-92. These results indicate that M1-92's slowly expanding equatorial torus exhibits an outer radial cutoff in its density, which implicates the influence of a binary companion during the formation of the nebula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03136v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/galaxies12040044</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Galaxies 2024, 12(4), 44</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yun Qi Li, Mark R. Morris, Raghvendra Sahai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redshift dependence of FRB host dispersion measures across cosmic epochs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03163v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We constrain the redshift dependence of (rest frame) host galaxy dispersion measures of localized FRBs by assuming it to vary as a simple power law ($\propto (1+z)^{\alpha}$). We simultaneously fit $\alpha$ as well as the host dispersion measure to the data of FRBs with known redshifts. We find that $\alpha\approx 0$ is preferred over higher values of $\alpha$ with either a positive or negative sign. Such constraints have implications for our understanding of galaxy formation and can be used to inform galaxy and large scale simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03163v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandeep Kumar Acharya, Paz Beniamini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brightest Cluster Galaxy Offsets in Cold Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00928v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The distribution of offsets between the brightest cluster galaxies of galaxy clusters and the centroid of their dark matter distributions is a promising probe of the underlying dark matter physics. In particular, since this distribution is sensitive to the shape of the potential in galaxy cluster cores, it constitutes a test of dark matter self-interaction on the largest mass scales in the universe. We examine these offsets in three suites of modern cosmological simulations; IllustrisTNG, MillenniumTNG and BAHAMAS. For clusters above $10^{14}\rm{M_\odot}$, we examine the dependence of the offset distribution on gravitational softening length, the method used to identify centroids, redshift, mass, baryonic physics, and establish the stability of our results with respect to various nuisance parameter choices. We find that offsets are overwhelmingly measured to be smaller than the minimum converged length scale in each simulation, with a median offset of $\sim1\rm{kpc}$ in the highest resolution simulation considered, TNG300-1, which uses a gravitational softening length of $1.48\rm{kpc}$. We also find that centroids identified via source extraction on smoothed dark matter and stellar particle data are consistent with the potential minimum, but that observationally relevant methods sensitive to cluster strong gravitational lensing scales, or those using gas as a tracer for the potential can overestimate offsets by factors of $\sim10$ and $\sim30$, respectively. This has the potential to reduce tensions with existing offset measurements which have served as evidence for a nonzero dark matter self-interaction cross section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00928v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cian Roche (MIT), Michael McDonald (MIT), Josh Borrow (MIT, UPenn), Mark Vogelsberger (MIT, IAIFI), Xuejian Shen (MIT), Volker Springel (MPA), Lars Hernquist (Harvard), Ruediger Pakmor (MPA), Sownak Bose (Durham), Rahul Kannan (York)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong asymptotic giant branch stars' spectral features in distant quiescent galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07414v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Age-dating and weighting stellar populations in galaxies are essential steps to study galaxy formation through cosmic times. Evolutionary population synthesis models with different input physics are used towards this aim. In particular, the contribution from the thermally pulsing asymptotic giant branch (TP-AGB) stellar phase, which peaks for intermediate-age 0.6-2 Gyr systems, has been debated upon for decades. Here we report the detection of strong cool-star signatures in the rest-frame near-infrared spectra of three young (~1 Gyr), massive (~10^10 Msun) quiescent galaxies at large look-back time, z=1-2, using JWST/NIRSpec. The co-existence of oxygen- and carbon-type absorption features, spectral edges and features from rare species such as Vanadium, and possibly Zirconium, reveal a strong contribution from TP-AGB stars. Population synthesis models with significant TP-AGB contribution reproduce the observations better than those with weak TP-AGB, which are commonly used. These findings call for revisions of published stellar population fitting results, pointing to lower masses and younger ages, with additional implications on cosmic dust production and chemical enrichment. New generations of improved models are needed, informed by these and future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07414v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiying Lu, Emanuele Daddi, Claudia Maraston, Mark Dickinson, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Raphael Gobat, Alvio Renzini, Mauro Giavalisco, Micaela B. Bagley, Antonello Calabr\`o, Yingjie Cheng, Alexander de la Vega, Chiara D'Eugenio, David Elbaz, Steven L. Finkelstein, Carlos G\'omez-Guijarro, Qiusheng Gu, Nimish P. Hathi, Marc Huertas-Company, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Anton M. Koekemoer, Aur\'elien Le Bail, Yipeng Lyu, Benjamin Magnelli, Bahram Mobasher, Casey Papovich, Nor Pirzkal, R. Michael Rich, Sandro Tacchella, L. Y. Aaron Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Baryonic Tully-Fisher Relation of HI-bearing Low Surface Brightness Galaxies Implies Their Formation Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16754v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the baryonic Tully-Fisher relation in low surface brightness galaxies selected from the Arecibo Legacy Fast ALFA survey. We find that the $\rm HI$-bearing low surface brightness galaxies still follow the baryonic Tully-Fisher relation of typical late-type galaxies, with a slope of approximately 4 in the baryonic mass versus rotational velocity diagram on the logarithmic scale, i.e., $M_{\rm{b}}\propto v_{\rm{rot}}^4$. Our findings suggest that the matter distributions in low surface brightness galaxies may resemble that of general late-type galaxies, and hint that low surface brightness galaxies may not originate from dark matter halos of low densities or stronger/weaker feedback processes, but may emerge from dark matter halos with high spin values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16754v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zichen Hua, Yu Rong, Hui-jie Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Galaxy Cluster HI Mass Recovery with CHIME at Redshifts z = 1 and 2 via the IllustrisTNG Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01382v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Canadian Hydrogen Intensity Mapping Experiment (CHIME) is a drift-scan interferometer designed to map the entire northern sky every 24 hours. The all-sky coverage and sensitivity to neutral hydrogen flux at intermediate redshifts makes the instrument a resource for other exciting science in addition to cosmology for which it was originally designed. Characterizing the contents of CHIME's beam-smoothed maps will aid in planning novel use-cases for the instrument, particularly those pertaining to galaxy evolution studies. Here, we demonstrate its utility for the study of the HI content of stacked galaxy populations across environments. Focusing first on galaxy clusters, we use simulated data from the IllustrisTNG project to understand the relative contribution of objects that fall into CHIME's synthesized beam to the observed HI flux using stacking analyses at a couple of representative redshifts. We find that there is an appreciable difference in the estimated stacked flux when galaxy clusters or cluster member galaxies are used as tracers compared to stacking on a general galaxy catalog. Stacking on galaxy clusters, we report that it is possible to recover an average $M_\mathrm{HI}$ for clusters as a function of redshift and selection criteria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01382v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ava Polzin, Laura Newburgh, Priyamvada Natarajan, Hsiao-Wen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dust beyond the torus: Revealing the mid-infrared heart of local Seyfert ESO 428-G14 with JWST/MIRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polar dust has been discovered in a number of local Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN), with radiation-driven torus models predicting a wind to be its main driver. However, little is known about its characteristics, spatial extent, or connection to the larger scale outflows. We present the first JWST/MIRI study aimed at imaging polar dust by zooming onto the centre of ESO 428-G14, part of the Galaxy Activity, Torus, and Outflow Survey (GATOS) survey of local AGN. We detect extended mid-infrared (MIR) emission within 200 pc from the nucleus. This polar structure is co-linear with a radio jet and lies perpendicular to a molecular gas lane that feeds and obscures the nucleus. Its morphology bears a striking resemblance to that of gas ionised by the AGN in the narrow-line region. We demonstrate that part of this spatial correspondence is due to contamination within the JWST filter bands from strong emission lines. Correcting for the contamination, we find the morphology of the dust continuum to be more compact, though still clearly extended out to ~ 100 pc. We estimate the emitting dust has a temperature of ~ 120 K. Using simple models, we find that the heating of small dust grains by the radiation from the central AGN and/or radiative jet-induced shocks is responsible for the extended MIR emission. Radiation-driven dusty winds from the torus is unlikely to be important. This has important implications for scales to which AGN winds can carry dust and dense gas out into their host galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16100v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1596</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 532, Issue 4, Pages 4645-4660, August 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Houda Haidar, David J. Rosario, Almudena Alonso-Herrero, Miguel Pereira-Santaella, Ismael Garc\'ia-Bernete, Stephanie Campbell, Sebastian F. H\"onig, Cristina Ramos Almeida, Erin Hicks, Daniel Delaney, Richard Davies, Claudio Ricci, Chris M. Harrison, Mason Leist, Enrique Lopez-Rodriguez, Santiago Garcia-Burillo, Lulu Zhang, Chris Packham, Poshak Gandhi, Anelise Audibert, Enrica Bellocchi, Peter Boorman, Andrew Bunker, Fran\c{c}oise Combes, Tanio Diaz Santos, Fergus R. Donnan, Omaira Gonzalez Martin, Laura Hermosa Mu\~noz, Matthaios Charidis, Alvaro Labiano, Nancy A. Levenson, Daniel May, Dimitra Rigopoulou, Alberto Rodriguez Ardila, T. Taro Shimizu, Marko Stalevski, Martin Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST/NIRSpec Observations of Ly$\alpha$ Emission in Star Forming Galaxies at $6.5\lesssim z\lesssim13$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an analysis of JWST Ly$\alpha$ spectroscopy of $z\gtrsim6.5$ galaxies, using observations in the public archive covering galaxies in four independent fields (GOODS-N, GOODS-S, Abell 2744, EGS). We measure Ly$\alpha$ emission line properties for a sample of $210$ $z\simeq6.5-13$ galaxies, with redshifts confirmed independently of Ly$\alpha$ in all cases. We present $3$ new detections of Ly$\alpha$ emission in JWST spectra, including a large equivalent width (EW $=143\ \r{A}$) Ly$\alpha$ emitter with strong CIV emission (EW $=21\ \r{A}$) at $z=7.1$ in GOODS-N. We measure the redshift-dependent Ly$\alpha$ EW distribution across our sample. We find that strong Ly$\alpha$ emission (EW $&gt;25\ \r{A}$) becomes increasingly rare at earlier epochs, suggesting that the transmission of Ly$\alpha$ photons decreases by $4\times$ between $z\simeq5$ and $z\simeq9$. We describe potential implications for the IGM neutral fraction. There is significant field to field variance in the Ly$\alpha$ emitter fraction. In contrast to the three other fields, the EGS shows no evidence for reduced transmission of Ly$\alpha$ photons at $z\simeq7-8$, suggesting a significantly ionized sightline may be present in the field. We use available NIRCam grism observations from the FRESCO survey to characterize overdensities on large scales around known Ly$\alpha$ emitters in the GOODS fields. The strongest overdensities appear linked with extremely strong Ly$\alpha$ detections (EW $&gt;50\ \r{A}$) in most cases. Future Ly$\alpha$ spectroscopy with JWST has the potential to constrain the size of ionized regions around early galaxy overdensities, providing a new probe of the reionization process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01507v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengtao Tang, Daniel P. Stark, Michael W. Topping, Charlotte Mason, Richard S. Ellis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selection bias obfuscates the discovery of fast radio burst sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01876v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: FRBs are a newly discovered class of extragalactic radio transients characterised by their high energy and short-duration (~$\mu$s-ms)[1]. Their elusive physical origin remains a subject of ongoing research, with magnetars emerging as leading candidates[2],[3]. Previous studies have employed various methodologies to address the FRB origin problem, including demographic analyses of FRB host galaxies and their local environments[4]-[6], assessments of FRB rate evolution with redshift[7]-[9], and searches for proposed multi-messenger FRB counterparts[10]. However, these studies are susceptible to significant biases stemming from unaccounted radio and optical selection effects. Here we present empirical evidence for a substantial selection bias against detecting FRBs in galaxies with large inclination angles (edge-on) using a sample of hosts identified for FRBs discovered by untargeted surveys. This inclination-related bias likely leads to a significant underestimation (by about a factor of two) of the FRB rates reported in the literature and disfavours globular clusters as the dominant origin of FRB sources, as previously speculated[6]. These conclusions have important implications for FRB progenitor models and targeted FRB follow-up strategies. We further investigate the impact of this bias on the relative rate of FRBs in different host environments. Our analysis suggests that scattering in FRB hosts is likely responsible for the observed bias[11],[12]. However, a larger sample of localised FRBs is required to robustly quantify its contribution in the inclination-related selection bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01876v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohit Bhardwaj, Jimin Lee, Kevin Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
