<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>ALMA detection of Masers and Dasars in the Hydrogen Recombination Lines of the Planetary Nebula Mz3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The hydrogen recombination lines H30$\alpha$, H40$\alpha$, H42$\alpha$, H50$\beta$ and H57$\gamma$ and the underlying bremsstrahlung continuum emission were detected with ALMA in the bipolar nebula Mz3. The source was not spatially resolved, but the velocity profile of the H30$\alpha$ line shows clear indication of maser amplification, confirming previous reports of laser amplification in the far infrared H recombination lines observed with Herschel Space Observatory. Comparison between the flux densities of the H50$\beta$, H40$\alpha$ and H42$\alpha$ lines show overcooling, or darkness amplification by stimulated absorption (dasar effect) at the LSR velocity of about $-25$ km s$^{-1}$, which constrains the density of the absorbing region to about 10$^3$ cm$^{-3}$. The H30$\alpha$ line, on the other hand, presents maser lines at LSR velocities of $-69$ and $-98$ km s$^{-1}$, which indicates ionized gas with densities close to 10$^7$ cm$^{-3}$. Although the source of emission was not resolved, it was possible to find the central position of the images for each velocity interval, which resulted in a well defined position-velocity distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11901v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Abraham, P. P. B. Beaklini, I. Aleman, R. Sahai, A. Zijlstra, S. Akras, D. R. Gon\c{c}alves, T. Ueta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $R$-process Alliance: Enrichment of $R$-process Elements in a Simulated Milky Way-like Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the formation of stars with varying amounts of heavy elements synthesized by the rapid neutron-capture process ($r$-process) based on our detailed cosmological zoom-in simulation of a Milky Way-like galaxy with an $N$-body/smoothed particle hydrodynamics code, ASURA. Most stars with no overabundance in $r$-process elements, as well as the strongly $r$-process enhanced $r$-II stars ([Eu/Fe] $&gt;+0.7$), are formed in dwarf galaxies accreted by the Milky Way within the 6 Gyr after the Big Bang. In contrast, over half of the moderately enhanced $r$-I stars ($+0.3 &lt;$ [Eu/Fe] $\leq +0.7$) are formed in the main in-situ disk after 6 Gyr. Our results suggest that the fraction of $r$-I and $r$-II stars formed in disrupted dwarf galaxies is larger the higher their [Eu/Fe] is. Accordingly, the most strongly enhanced $r$-III stars ([Eu/Fe] $&gt; +2.0$) are formed in accreted components. These results suggest that non-$r$-process-enhanced stars and $r$-II stars are mainly formed in low-mass dwarf galaxies that hosted either none or a single neutron star merger, while the $r$-I stars tend to form in the well-mixed in-situ disk. We compare our findings with high-resolution spectroscopic observations of $r$-process-enhanced metal-poor stars in the halo and dwarf galaxies, including those collected by the R-Process Alliance. We conclude that observed [Eu/Fe] and [Eu/Mg] ratios can be employed in chemical tagging of the Milky Way's accretion history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11943v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutaka Hirai, Timothy C. Beers, Young Sun Lee, Shinya Wanajo, Ian U. Roederer, Masaomi Tanaka, Masashi Chiba, Takayuki R. Saitoh, Vinicius M. Placco, Terese T. Hansen, Rana Ezzeddine, Anna Frebel, Erika M. Holmbeck, Charli M. Sakari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cracking the relation between mass and 1P-star fraction of globular clusters: II. The masses in 1P and 2P stars as a second tool</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galactic globular clusters contain two main groups of stars, the pristine or 1P stars, and the polluted or 2P stars. The pristine-star fraction in clusters, $F_{1P}$, is a decreasing function of the cluster present-day mass, $m_{prst}$. Paper~I has introduced a model mapping the region of the $(m_{prst},F_{1P})$ space occupied by clusters, with the cluster mass threshold for 2P-star formation a key building-block. We now expand this model to the pristine-star fraction in dependence of the pristine- and polluted-population masses. Milone et al.(2020) found that $F_{1P}$ anticorrelates more tightly with the polluted-population present-day mass, $m_{2P,prst}$, than with the cluster total mass, $m_{prst}$. In contrast, $F_{1P}$ anticorrelates poorly with the pristine-population current mass, $m_{1P,prst}$. We show the loose anticorrelation between $F_{1P}$ and $m_{1P,prst}$ to result from a roughly constant pristine-population mass among clusters as they start their long-term evolution in the Galactic tidal field. As for the tight anticorrelation between $m_{2P,prst}$ and $F_{1P}$, it stems from the initially shallow relation between $m_{2P}$ and $F_{1P}$ (Fig.4). Clusters of the Large and Small Magellanic Clouds (LMC and SMC, respectively) appear to behave unexpectedly with respect to each other. For a given $F_{1P}$, LMC clusters are more massive than SMC clusters despite their enduring a stronger tidal field (Fig.6). This is opposite to how the Galactic outer- and inner-halo clusters behave (bottom panels of Figs 1-3). The explanation may lie in cluster formation conditions. Finally, we wonder whether the single-population clusters NGC~419 and Rup~106 formed as multiple-populations clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11950v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genevi\`eve Parmentier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Truncated Circumgalactic Medium of the Large Magellanic Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) is the nearest massive galaxy to the Milky Way. Its circumgalactic medium is complex and multi-phase, containing both stripped HI structures like the Magellanic Stream and Bridge, and a diffuse warm corona seen in high-ion absorption. We analyze 28 AGN sightlines passing within 35 kpc of the LMC with archival HST/COS spectra to characterize the cool (T\approx10^4$ K) gas in the LMC CGM, via new measurements of UV absorption in six low ions (OI, FeII, SiII, AlII, SII, and NiII) and one intermediate ion (SiIII). We show that a declining column-density profile is present in all seven ions, with the low-ion profiles having a steeper slope than the high-ion profiles in CIV and SiIV reported by Krishnarao et al. 2022. Crucially, absorption at the LMC systemic velocity is only detected (in all ions) out to 17 kpc. Beyond this distance, the gas has a lower velocity and is associated with the Magellanic Stream. These results demonstrate that the LMC's CGM is composed of two distinct components: a compact inner halo extending to 17 kpc, and a more extended stripped region associated with the Stream. The compactness and truncation of the LMC's inner CGM agree with recent simulations of ram-pressure stripping of the LMC by the Milky Way's extended corona.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11960v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sapna Mishra, Andrew J. Fox, Dhanesh Krishnarao, Scott Lucchini, Elena D'Onghia, Frances H. Cashman, Kathleen A. Barger, Nicolas Lehner, Jason Tumlinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting stars from the integrated spectra of galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last decades, evolutionary population synthesis models have powered an unmatched leap forward in our understanding of galaxies. From dating the age of the first galaxies in the Universe to detailed measurements of the chemical composition of nearby galaxies, the success of this approach built upon simple stellar population (SSP) spectro-photometric models is unquestionable. However, the internal constraints inherent to the construction of SSP models may hinder our ability to analyze the integrated spectra of galaxies in situations where the SSP assumption does not sufficiently hold. Thus, here we revisit the possibilities of fitting galaxy spectra as a linear combination of stellar templates without assuming any a priori knowledge on stellar evolution. We showcase the sensitivity of this alternative approach to changes in the stellar population properties, in particular the direct connection to variations in the stellar initial mass function, as well as its advantages when dealing with non-canonical integrated populations and semi-resolved observations. Furthermore, our analysis demonstrates that the absorption spectra of galaxies can be used to independently constrain tellar evolution theory beyond the limited conditions of the solar neighborhood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11961v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Mart\'in-Navarro, A. Vazdekis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra Long Period Cepheids as standard candles from Gaia to Rubin-LSST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An analysis of the Ultra Long Period Cepheids (ULPs) properties could significantly contribute to understanding the Hubble constant tension, e.g. the current discrepancy between determinations based on local distance indicators and those relying on cosmic microwave background measurements. These highly luminous variables are observable beyond 100 Mpc, so if they were confirmed to behave as standard candles, they would allow us a direct measurement of cosmological distances without any secondary distance indicator, thus reducing potential systematic errors in the calibration of the cosmic distance scale. This paper presents an analysis of the largest known sample of 73 ULPs, including 15 objects in nearby galaxies, with new accurate and homogeneous photometry obtained by Gaia DR3, and a new object, in our Galaxy, identified as Long Period Variable in Gaia DR3, but recently reclassified as ULP. The obtained results suggest that, by improving photometric accuracy, the ULP Period-Wesenheit relation shows a smaller dispersion than that obtained in literature and is in better agreement with the Classical Cepheid (CC) one, supporting the hypothesis that ULPs are the extension of the CCs at higher period, mass and luminosity. However, to reach this aim, it is necessary to enrich the sample with high-quality data. The Rubin-LSST survey offers the possibility to achieve this thanks to its photometric characteristics and time extension. In particular, we will explore the capabilities of the Rubin-LSST survey to recover ULP theoretical light-curves by using a new tool called PulsationStarRecovery, built by our group for this type of analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12017v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/ad863c</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>I. Musella, S. Leccia, R. Molinaro, M. Marconi, F. Cusano, M. Di Criscienzo, G. Fiorentino, V. Braga, V. Ripepi, G. De Somma, M. Gatto, E. Luongo, T. Sicignano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Search for 3-mm Molecular Absorption Line Transitions in the Magellanic Stream</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12102v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Magellanic Stream, a tidal tail of diffuse gas falling onto the Milky Way, formed by interactions between the Small and Large Magellanic Clouds, is primarily composed of neutral atomic hydrogen (HI). The deficiency of dust and the diffuse nature of the present gas make molecular formation rare and difficult, but if present, could lead to regions potentially suitable for star formation, thereby allowing us to probe conditions of star formation similar to those at high redshifts. We search for HCO$^+$, HCN, HNC, and C$_2$H using the highest sensitivity observations of molecular absorption data from the Atacama Large Millimeter Array to trace these regions, comparing with HI archival data to compare these environments in the Magellanic Stream to the HI column density threshold for molecular formation in the Milky Way. We also compare the line of sight locations with confirmed locations of stars, molecular hydrogen, and OI detections, though at higher sensitivities than the observations presented here. We find no detections to a 3$\sigma$ significance, despite four sightlines having column densities surpassing the threshold for molecular formation in the diffuse regions of the Milky Way. Here we present our calculations for the upper limits of the column densities of each of these molecular absorption lines, ranging from $3 \times 10^{10}$ to $1 \times 10^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$. The non-detection of HCO$^+$ suggests that at least one of the following is true: (i) $X_{HCO^+, \mathrm{MS}}$ is significantly lower than the Milky Way value; (ii) that the widespread diffuse molecular gas observed in the Milky Way's diffuse ISM does not have a direct analog in the MS; (iii) the HI-to-H$_2$ transition occurs in the MS at a higher surface density in the MS than in the LMC or SMC; or (iv) molecular gas exists in the MS, but only in small, dense clumps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12102v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucille Steffes, Daniel R. Rybarczyk, Sne\v{z}ana Stanimirovi\'c, J. R. Dawson, Mary Putman, Philipp Richter, John Gallagher III, Harvey Liszt, Claire Murray, John Dickey, Carl Heiles, Audra Hernandez, Robert Lindner, Yangyang Liu, Naomi McClure-Griffiths, Tony Wong, Blair Savage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Physical Origin of Extreme Emission Line Galaxies at High redshifts: Strong {\sc [Oiii]} Emission Lines Produced by Obscured AGNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present deep Subaru/FOCAS spectra for two extreme emission line galaxies (EELGs) at $z\sim 1$ with strong {\sc[Oiii]}$\lambda$5007 emission lines, exhibiting equivalent widths (EWs) of $2905^{+946}_{-578}$ \AA\ and $2000^{+188}_{-159}$ \AA, comparable to those of EELGs at high redshifts that are now routinely identified with JWST spectroscopy. Adding a similarly large {\sc [Oiii]} EW ($2508^{+1487}_{-689}$ \AA) EELG found at $z\sim 2$ in the JWST CEERS survey to our sample, we explore for the physical origins of the large {\sc [Oiii]} EWs of these three galaxies with the Subaru spectra and various public data including JWST/NIRSpec, NIRCam, and MIRI data. While there are no clear signatures of AGN identified by the optical line diagnostics, we find that two out of two galaxies covered by the MIRI data show strong near-infrared excess in the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) indicating obscured AGN. Because none of the three galaxies show clear broad H$\beta$ lines, the upper limits on the flux ratios of broad-H$\beta$ to {\sc [Oiii]} lines are small, $\lesssim 0.15$ that are comparable with Seyfert $1.8-2.0$ galaxies. We conduct \texttt{Cloudy} modeling with the stellar and AGN incident spectra, allowing a wide range of parameters including metallicities and ionization parameters. We find that the large {\sc [Oiii]} EWs are not self-consistently reproduced by the spectra of stars or unobscured AGN, but obscured AGN that efficiently produces O$^{++}$ ionizing photons with weak nuclear and stellar continua that are consistent with the SED shapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12198v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenghao Zhu, Yuichi Harikane, Masami Ouchi, Yoshiaki Ono, Masato Onodera, Shenli Tang, Yuki Isobe, Yoshiki Matsuoka, Toshihiro Kawaguchi, Hiroya Umeda, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yongming Liang, Yi Xu, Yechi Zhang, Dongsheng Sun, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Jenny Greene, Kazushi Iwasawa, Kotaro Kohno, Tohru Nagao, Andreas Schulze, Takatoshi Shibuya, Miftahul Hilmi, Malte Schramm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Milky Way atlas for linear filaments II. clump rotation versus filament orientation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dense clumps distributed along filaments are the immediate medium for star formation. Kinematic properties of the clumps, such as velocity gradient and angular momentum, combined with filament orientation, provide important clues to the formation mechanism of filament-clump configurations and the role of filaments in star formation. By cross-matching the Milky Way atlas for linear filaments and the Structure, Excitation and Dynamics of the Inner Galactic Interstellar Medium (SEDIGISM) 13CO (2-1) data, we aim to derive the velocity gradient and its direction, the specific angular momentum (J/M), and the ratio (\beta) between the rotational energy and gravitational energy of clumps, as well as to investigate the alignment between clump rotation and filament orientation. We found a monotonic increase in J/M as a function of clump size (R), following a power-law relation J/M~\propto~R^{1.5\pm0.2}. The ratio \beta ranges from 1.1~\times~10^{-5} to 0.1, with a median value 1.0~\times~10^{-3}, suggesting that clump rotation provides insignificant support against gravitational collapse. The distribution of the angle between clump rotation and natal filament orientation is random, indicating that the clumps' rotational axes have no discernible correlation with the orientation of their hosting filaments. Counting only the most massive clump in each filament also finds no alignment between clump rotation and filament orientation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12215v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuefang Xu, Ke Wang, Qian Gou, Tapas Baug, Di Li, Chunguo Duan, Juncheng Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrared Spectra of Solid-State Ethanolamine: Laboratory Data in Support of JWST Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ethanolamine (NH$_2$CH$_2$CH$_2$OH, EA) has been identified in the gas phase of the ISM within molecular clouds. Although EA has not been directly observed in the molecular ice phase, a solid state formation mechanism has been proposed. However, the current literature lacks an estimation of the infrared band strengths of EA ices. We conducted an experimental investigation of solid EA ice at low temperatures to ascertain its infrared band strengths, phase transition temperature, and multilayer binding energy. The commonly used laser interferometry method was not applied. Infrared band strengths were determined using three distinct methods. The obtained lab spectrum of EA was compared with the publicly available MIRI MRS James Webb Space Telescope observations toward a low mass protostar. The phase transition temperature for EA ice falls within the range of 175 to 185 K. Among the discussed methods, the simple pressure gauge method provides a reasonable estimate of band strength. We derive a band strength value of about $1\times10^{-17}$ cm molecule$^{-1}$ for the NH$_2$ bending mode in the EA molecules. Additionally, temperature-programmed desorption analysis yielded a multilayer desorption energy of 0.61$\pm$0.01 eV. By comparing the laboratory data documented in this study with the JWST spectrum of the low mass protostar IRAS 2A, an upper-limit for the EA ice abundances was derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12235v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Suhasaria, S. M. Wee, R. Basalg\`ete, S. A. Krasnokutski, C. J\"ager, G. Perotti, Th. Henning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Star Formation History of Nearby Galaxies: A Machine Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reproducing color-magnitude diagrams (CMDs) of star-resolved galaxies is one of the most precise methods for measuring the star formation history (SFH) of nearby galaxies back to the earliest time. The upcoming big data era poses challenges to the traditional numerical technique in its capacity to deal with vast amounts of data, which motivates us to explore the feasibility of employing machine learning networks in this field. In this study, we refine the synthetic CMD method with a state-of-the-art theoretical stellar evolution model to simulate the properties of stellar populations, incorporate the convolutional neural network (CNN) in the fitting process to enhance the efficiency, and innovate the initial stellar mass estimation to improve the flexibility. The fine-tuned deep learning network, named \texttt{SFHNet}, has been tested with synthetic data and further validated with photometric data collected from the Hubble Space Telescope (\textit{HST}). The derived SFHs are largely in accordance with those reported in the literature. Furthermore, the network provides detailed insights into the distribution of stellar density, initial stellar mass, and star formation rate (SFR) over the age-metallicity map. The application of the deep learning network not only measures the SFH accurately but also enhances the synthetic CMD method's efficiency and flexibility, thereby facilitating a more comprehensive and in-depth understanding of nearby galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12253v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujiao Yang, Chao Liu, Ming Yang, Yun Zheng, Hao Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The GALAH Survey: Stellar parameters and abundances for 800,000 Gaia RVS spectra using GALAH DR4 and The Cannon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Analysing stellar parameters and abundances from nearly one million Gaia DR3 Radial Velocity Spectrometer (RVS) spectra poses challenges due to the limited spectral coverage (restricted to the infrared Ca II triplet) and variable signal-to-noise ratios of the data. To address this, we use The Cannon, a data-driven method, to transfer stellar parameters and abundances from the GALAH Data Release 4 (DR4; R ~ 28,000) catalogue to the lower resolution Gaia DR3 RVS spectra (R ~ 11,500). Our model, trained on 14,484 common targets, predicts parameters such as Teff, log g, and [Fe/H], along with several other elements across approximately 800,000 Gaia RVS spectra. We utilise stars from open and globular clusters present in the Gaia RVS catalogue to validate our predicted mean [Fe/H] with high precision (~0.02-0.10 dex). Additionally, we recover the bimodal distribution of [Ti/Fe] versus [Fe/H], reflecting the high and low alpha-components of Milky Way disk stars, demonstrating The Cannon's capability for accurate stellar abundance determination from medium-resolution Gaia RVS spectra. The methodologies and resultant catalogue presented in this work highlight the remarkable potential of the RVS dataset, which by the end of the Gaia mission will comprise spectra of over 200 million stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12272v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradosh Barun Das, Daniel B. Zucker, Gayandhi M. De Silva, Nicholas W. Borsato, Aldo Mura-Guzm\'an, Sven Buder, Melissa Ness, Thomas Nordlander, Andrew R. Casey, Sarah L. Martell, Joss Bland-Hawthorn, Richard de Grijs, Ken C. Freeman, Janez Kos, Dennis Stello, Geraint F. Lewis, Michael R. Hayden, Sanjib Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Give to Ursa Minor what is Ursa Minor's: an updated census of the RR Lyrae population in the Ursa Minor dwarf galaxy based on Gaia DR3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use RR Lyrae stars identified by the Gaia third data release (DR3) to explore the outskirts of the Ursa Minor (UMi) dwarf spheroidal galaxy (dSph) and update the census of its variable star population. We adopted different tools based on the Gaia DR3 astrometric and photometric data (proper motions, Period-Wesenheit-Metallicity relations, spatial distribution, colour-magnitude diagram and stellar isochrone fitting) to discriminate between different types of variable stars, and to identify UMi members. We find a total of 129 RR Lyrae stars and Anomalous Cepheids (ACs) that belong to UMi. We report 47 new RR Lyrae stars (46 bona fide and 1 candidate) and 5 new ACs (4 bona fide and 1 candidate), including new possible members in the extreme periphery of the galaxy at a distance of $\sim$ 12 half-light radii. We reclassified 13 RR Lyrae stars identified by the Gaia DR3 Specific Object Study pipeline for Cepheids and RR Lyrae stars (SOS Cep$\&amp;$RRL), using data from the literature and Gaia astrometry and photometry. Specifically, we assigned these 13 DR3 RR Lyrae stars to 10 Anomalous Cepheids and 3 double-mode RR Lyrae (RRd), respectively. From the average luminosity of the RR Lyrae stars we derive for UMi a distance modulus of $(m-M)_{0}=$ 19.23 $\pm$ 0.09 mag in excellent agreement with the literature. Finally, we investigated whether some of UMi's variable stars might be members of the ultra-faint stellar cluster Mu{\~n}oz~1, that lies at a projected distance of 45 arcmin from UMi's centre. Based on the properties of the variable stars (distances, colours and metallicities), we find unlikely that they belong to the cluster.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12433v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Garofalo, G. Clementini, F. Cusano, T. Muraveva, L. Monti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Icarus revisited: An Ancient, Metal-poor Accreted Stellar Stream in the Disk of the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The search for accreted satellites in the Galactic disk is a challenging task, to which Gaia plays a crucial role in synergy with ground-based spectroscopic surveys. In 2021, Re Fiorentin et al. discovered five substructures with disk kinematics including Icarus. To gain more insight into the origin of Icarus as a remnant of a dwarf galaxy rather than a signature of secular processes of disk formation, we complement astrometric Gaia DR3 data with spectroscopy from APOGEE DR17 and GALAH DR3, and explore the chemo-dynamical distributions within 3 kpc of the Sun. We select 622 stars in the accreted/unevolved regions of [Mg/Mn]-[Al/Fe] and [Mg/Fe]-[Fe/H], where we identify 81 and 376 stars with $-2&lt;{\rm[Fe/H]}&lt;-0.7$ belonging to Icarus and Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus (GSE), respectively. The revised properties of Icarus are: $\langle V+V_{\rm LSR}\rangle\simeq171~\rm{km~s}^{-1}$, $\sigma_{V}\simeq37\rm{km~s}^{-1}$, $\langle e\rangle\simeq0.36$, $\langle{\rm[Fe/H]}\rangle\simeq-1.35$, $\langle{\rm[Mg/Fe]}\rangle\simeq+0.27$, $\langle{\rm[Al/Fe]}\rangle\simeq-0.13$, and $\langle{\rm[Mn/Fe]}\rangle\simeq-0.39$. From the CMD of its members, Icarus appears older than 12 Gyr. Such age and dynamical properties are reminiscent of the metal-weak thick disk. However, detailed chemical analysis in the diagnostic spaces [Ni/Fe]-[(C+N)/O], [Y/Eu]-[Fe/H], [Eu/Mg]-[Fe/H], [Ba/Y]-[Fe/H], and [Ba/Mg]-[Mg/H] evidences that Icarus and GSE occupy the accreted region, well separated from the bulk of in situ disk stars. Updated comparisons with N-body simulations confirm that Icarus' stars are consistent with the debris of a dwarf galaxy with a stellar mass of $\sim~10^9~M_\odot$ accreted onto a primordial disk on an initial prograde low-inclination orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12581v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paola Re Fiorentin, Alessandro Spagna, Mario G. Lattanzi, Michele Cignoni, Sara Vitali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HYPERION. Shedding light on the first luminous quasars: A correlation between UV disc winds and X-ray continuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the main open questions in the field of luminous ($L_{\rm bol}&gt;10^{47}\,\rm erg\,s^{-1}$) quasars (QSOs) at $z \gtrsim 6$ is the rapid formation ($&lt; 1\,$Gyr) of their supermassive black holes (SMBHs). For this work we analysed the relation between the X-ray properties and other properties describing the physics and growth of both the accretion disc and the SMBH in QSOs at the Epoch of Reionization (EoR). The sample consists of 21 $z&gt;6$ QSOs, which includes 16 sources from the rapidly grown QSOs from the HYPERION sample and five other luminous QSOs with available high-quality archival X-ray data. We discovered a strong and statistically significant ($&gt;3\sigma$) relation between the X-ray continuum photon index ($\Gamma$) and the $\rm C\,IV$ disc wind velocity ($v_{\rm C\,IV}$) in $z&gt;6$ luminous QSOs, whereby the higher the $v_{\rm C\,IV}$, the steeper the $\Gamma$. This relation suggests a link between the disc-corona configuration and the kinematics of disc winds. Furthermore, we find evidence at $&gt;2-3\sigma$ level that $\Gamma$ and $v_{\rm C\,IV}$ are correlated to the growth rate history of the SMBH. Although additional data are needed to confirm it, this result may suggest that, in luminous $z&gt;6$ QSOs, the SMBH predominantly grows via fast accretion rather than via initial high seed BH mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12786v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Tortosa, L. Zappacosta, E. Piconcelli, M. Bischetti, C. Done, G. Miniutti, I. Saccheo, G. Vietri, A. Bongiorno, M. Brusa, S. Carniani, I. V. Chilingarian, F. Civano, S. Cristiani, V. D'Odorico, M. Elvis, X. Fan, C. Feruglio, F. Fiore, S. Gallerani, E. Giallongo, R. Gilli, A. Grazian, M. Guainazzi, F. Haardt, A. Luminari, R. Maiolino, N. Menci, F. Nicastro, P. O. Petrucci, S. Puccetti, F. Salvestrini, R. Schneider, V. Testa, F. Tombesi, R. Tripodi, R. Valiante, L. Vallini, E. Vanzella, A. Vasylenko, C. Vignali, F. Vito, M. Volonteri, F. La Franca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on the article "Non-local gravitational corrections in black hole shadow images" by S. O. Alexeyev et al</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently Alexeyev et al. published paper (J. Theor. Exper. Phys. v. 165, N 4, p. 508 in Russian; arXiv:2404.16079 [gr-qc], the reference is given also in [1]). In the paper the authors discussed an opportunity of estimating spins from the analysis of the shadow reconstruction of black holes, theoretically considered using the nonlocal gravity model proposed earlier for the description of "quantum" black holes. However, in essence, this paper considered circular photon orbits, and the fact that the corresponding motion parameters determine the shape and size of shadows, similarly to Kerr black holes, remained unproven. It is also remained unproven the statement that for an equatorial observer the shadow size in the direction of rotation of quantum black holes remains independent of spin. A long time ago the shadow property was established for the Kerr black hole case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11898v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander F. Zakharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HOLESOM: Constraining the Properties of Slowly-Accreting Massive Black Holes with Self-Organizing Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accreting massive black holes (MBHs, with M$_\bullet &gt; 10^3$ M$_{\odot}$) are known for their panchromatic emission, spanning from radio to gamma rays. While MBHs accreting at significant fractions of their Eddington rate are readily detectable, those accreting at much lower rates in radiatively inefficient modes often go unnoticed, blending in with other astrophysical sources. This challenge is particularly relevant for gas-starved MBHs in external galaxies and those possibly wandering in the Milky Way. We present HOLESOM, a machine learning-powered tool based on the Self-Organizing Maps (SOMs) algorithm, specifically designed to identify slowly-accreting MBHs using sparse photometric data. Trained on a comprehensive set of $\sim$ 20, 000 spectral energy distributions (SEDs), HOLESOM can (i) determine if the photometry of a source is consistent with slowly-accreting MBHs and (ii) estimate its black hole mass and Eddington ratio, including uncertainties. We validate HOLESOM through extensive tests on synthetic data and real-world cases, including Sagittarius A* (Sgr A*), demonstrating its effectiveness in identifying slowly-accreting MBHs. Additionally, we derive analytical relations between radio and X-ray luminosities to further constrain physical parameters. The primary strength of HOLESOM lies in its ability to accurately identify MBH candidates, which can then be targeted for follow-up photometric and spectroscopic observations. Fast and scalable, HOLESOM offers a robust framework for automatically scanning large multi-wavelength datasets, making it a valuable tool for unveiling hidden MBH populations in the local Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11951v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina La Torre, Fabio Pacucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superradiance of charged black holes embedded in dark matter halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11952v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrophysical environments are ubiquitous in the Universe; from accretion disks around black holes to galactic dark matter halos, distributions of astrophysical material veil the vast majority of Cosmos. Including environmental effects in strong-field gravity and astrophysics is, therefore, a rather tantalizing task in the quest for novel gravitational-wave phenomena. Here, we examine how environments affect the high-energy process of superradiance. In particular, we study the amplification of charged scalar waves under the expense of the electrostatic energy contained in a charged black hole that is embedded in an observationally-motivated, and qualitatively generic, dark matter halo. We find that the superradiant amplification of massless charged scalar fields scattering off environmentally-enriched charged black holes can be equally efficient to those occurring in vacuum charged black holes. This occurs due to the fact that the sole interplay between the scalar wave and the black hole is the electromagnetic interaction. The addition of mass on the charged scalar waves leads to a rapid suppression of superradiant amplification. This transpires to a great extent due to the `friction' that the mass introduces to the black hole potential. Nevertheless, for sufficiently large scalar masses, the amplification factors can be also subdominantly affected by the compactness of the halo. This occurs because the gravitational interaction between the dense halo and the wave's mass grows, thus further suppressing the superradiant amplification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11952v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Mollicone, Kyriakos Destounis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing EMRI/IMRI candidates with quasiperiodic ultrafast outflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The first detection of the quasiperiodic ultrafast outflow in the ASASSN-20qc system was reported by Pasham et al. (2024). The outflow is revealed in the soft X-ray spectra as an absorption feature, which is periodically enhanced every $ \sim 8.3$ days. The periodic nature of the ultrafast outflow is best explained by an orbiting massive perturber, most likely an intermediate-mass black hole (IMBH), that is inclined with respect to the accretion flow around the primary supermassive black hole (SMBH). In this way, the orbiting body pushes the disc gas into the outflow funnel, where it is accelerated by the ordered magnetic field (Sukov\'a et al. 2021). Quasiperiodic ultrafast outflows (QPOuts) are thus a novel phenomenon that can help reveal new extreme-/intemediate-mass ratio inspiral (EMRI/IMRI) candidates that otherwise do not exhibit significant periodic patterns in the continuum flux density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12090v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Zaja\v{c}ek, Petra Sukov\'a, Vladim\'ir Karas, Dheeraj R. Pasham, Francesco Tombesi, Petr Kurf\"urst, Henry Best, Izzy Garland, Mat\'u\v{s} Labaj, Monika Pikhartov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of a 25 parsec-long precessing jet emanating from the old nova GK Persei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12103v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical nova eruptions result from thermonuclear-powered runaways in, and ejection of, the hydrogen-rich envelopes of white dwarf stars accreted from their close binary companions. Novae brighten to up to 1,000,000 solar luminosities, and recur thousands of times over their lifetimes spanning several billion years. Between eruptions, mass transfer from the donor star to the white dwarf proceeds via an accretion disk unless the white dwarf possesses a strong magnetic field which can partially or totally disrupt the disk. In that case, accretion is focussed by the white dwarf's magnetic field towards its magnetic poles. Optical spectroscopy and interferometric radio maps demonstrate the presence of bipolar jets, typically arcsec in angular size, and orders of magnitude smaller than one parsec in linear size, during the days to months after nova eruptions. These jets expel collimated matter from the white dwarfs in nova binary stars, but well-resolved images of them are lacking. Here we report the Condor telescope's detection of a hitherto unknown, highly resolved and braided jet, three degrees (at least 25 parsecs) in length. The jet originates at the white dwarf of the old nova GK Persei (nova Per 1901 CE). It precesses on a ~ 3600 yr timescale, and must be at least 7200 years old. Detected across four decades of wavelength, the jet's ultimate energy source is likely the strong accretion shocks near the white dwarf's magnetic poles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12103v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael M. Shara, Kenneth M. Lanzetta, James T. Garland, David Valls-Gabaud, Stefan Gromoll, Mikita Misiura, Frederick M. Walter, John K. Webb, Barrett Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearby Supernova and Cloud Crossing Effects on the Orbits of Small Bodies in the Solar System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12275v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Supernova blasts envelop many surrounding stellar systems, transferring kinetic energy to small bodies in the systems. Geologic evidence from $^{60}\rm Fe$ points to recent nearby supernova activity within the past several Myr. Here, we model the transfer of energy and resulting orbital changes from these supernova blasts to the Oort Cloud, the Kuiper belt, and Saturn's Phoebe ring. For the Oort Cloud, an impulse approximation shows that a 50 pc supernova can eject approximately half of all objects less than 1 cm while altering the trajectories of larger ones, depending on their orbital parameters. For stars closest to supernovae, objects up to $\sim$100 m can be ejected. Turning to the explored solar system, we find that supernovae closer than 50 pc may affect Saturn's Phoebe ring and can sweep away Kuiper belt dust. It is also possible that the passage of the solar system through a dense interstellar cloud could have a similar effect; a numerical trajectory simulation shows that the location of the dust grains and the direction of the wind (from a supernova or interstellar cloud) has a significant impact on whether or not the grains will become unbound from their orbit in the Kuiper belt. Overall, nearby supernovae sweep micron-sized dust from the solar system, though whether the grains are ultimately cast towards the Sun or altogether ejected depends on various factors. Evidence of supernova-modified dust grain trajectories may be observed by New Horizons, though further modeling efforts are required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12275v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad7e1a</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL 974 L29 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Leeanne Smith, Jesse A. Miller, Brian D. Fields</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relation between black hole spin and molecular gas in massive galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12322v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Molecular gas is the key probe for the complex interaction between the accretion of black holes and star formation of the host galaxy of active galactic nuclei (AGN). The molecular gas discovered around the AGN indicates that this gas is providing fuel for the AGN. According to the theoretical model of the relativistic jet, the spin of a black hole enhances the relativistic jet of AGN. The spin of the black hole is used as an indicator of AGN activity. Therefore, we study the relationship between the activity of AGN and molecular gas. We find a significant strong correlation between molecular gas fraction and CO luminosity and black hole spin for the early-type galaxies. However, there is no correlation between molecular gas fraction and CO luminosity and black hole spin for the late-type galaxies. These results indicate that the spin of black holes mainly regulates the accretion of molecular gas in massive early-type galaxies. The activity of AGN depends on the amount of gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12322v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yongyun, Gu Qiusheng, Fan Junhui, Yu Xiaoling, Ding Nan, Guo Xiaotong, Xiong Dingrong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot Star Winds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The properties, impact, and fate of hot stars cannot be understood without considering their winds. Revealed to be an almost ubiquitous phenomenon in the regime of massive stars, the winds of hot stars arise from a complex physical mechanism that still provides a major challenge for our understanding of massive stars. Different flavours of hot stars vary significantly in their winds with current evolution models still having problems to connect the zoo of observed phenomena. Moreover, the driving of hot star winds is inherently connected to the opacities arising from spectral line transitions, making the properties and strength of the winds strongly dependent on metallicity and changing them over cosmic time.
  In these proceedings, the current status in our understanding of hot star winds is briefly reviewed and recent progress in our perception of hot star winds and the consequences for the evolution of massive stars are presented. A particular emphasis is given on current efforts with hydrodynamically-consistent atmosphere models towards a better description of radiatively-driven mass loss of Wolf-Rayet stars with remaining hydrogen envelopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12484v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas A. C. Sander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photometric detection of internal gravity waves in upper main-sequence stars. IV. Comparable SLF variability in SMC, LMC and Galactic massive stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive main-sequence stars have convective cores and radiative envelopes, and sub-surface convection zones. However, their properties strongly depend on a star's opacity and metallicity. Non-rotating 1D evolution models of main-sequence stars between $7 \leq M \leq 40$ M$_{\odot}$ and metallicity of the SMC suggest tenuous sub-surface convection zones when using the Rayleigh number as a criterion for convection. We test if massive stars of different metallicities inside and outside of stability windows for sub-surface convection exhibit similar properties in their observed SLF variability. We extract customised light curves from the ongoing TESS mission for a sample of massive stars using an effective point spread function (ePSF) method, and compare them using a Gaussian process (GP) regression methodology. We demonstrate that the properties of SLF variability observed in time-series photometry of massive stars are consistent across the metallicity range from the Milky Way down to the SMC galaxy, for stars both inside and outside of the sub-surface stability windows. We conclude that non-rotating 1D stellar structure models of sub-surface convection cannot alone be used to explain the mechanism giving rise to SLF variability in light curves of massive stars. Additionally, the similar properties of SLF variability across a large range in metallicity, which follow the same trends in mass and age in the Hertzsprung-Russell (HR) diagram at both high and low metallicity, support a transition in the dominant mechanism causing SLF variability from younger to more evolved stars. Specifically, core-excited internal gravity waves (IGWs) are more favourable for younger stars that lack substantial sub-surface convection zones, especially at low-metallicity, and sub-surface convection zones are more favourable for the most massive and evolved stars. (abstract abridged for arxiv submission)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12726v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic M. Bowman, Pieterjan Van Daele, Mathias Michielsen, Timothy Van Reeth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Nature of a Recently Discovered Wolf-Rayet Binary: Archetype of Stripping?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12776v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: LMCe055-1 was recently discovered in a survey for WRs in the Large Magellanic Cloud, and classified as a WN4/O4, a lower excitation version of the WN3/O3 class discovered as part of the same survey. Its absolute magnitude precluded it from being a WN4+O4 binary. OGLE photometry show shallow primary and secondary eclipses with a 2.2 day period. The spectral characteristics and short period pointed to a possible origin due to binary stripping. Such stripped WR binaries should be common but have proven elusive to identify conclusively. In order to establish its nature, we obtained HST UV and Magellan optical spectra, along with imaging. Our work shows that the WR emission and He II absorption arise in one star, and the He I absorption in another. The He I contributor is the primary of the 2.2-day system and exhibits ~300 km/sed radial velocity variations on that time scale. However, the WR star shows 30-40 km/sed radial velocity variations, with a likely 35-day period and a highly eccentric orbit. Possibly LMCe055-1 is a physical triple, but that would require the 2.2-day pair to have been captured by the WR star. A more likely explanation is that the WR star has an unseen companion in a 35-day orbit and that the 2.2-day pair is in a longer period orbit about the two. Such examples of multiple systems are well known among massive stars, such as HD 5980. Regardless, we argue that it is highly unlikely that the WR component of the LMCe055-1 system resulted from stripping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12776v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Massey, Kathryn F. Neugent, Nidia I. Morrell, Desmond John Hillier, Laura R. Penny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The conditional colour-magnitude distribution: II. A comparison of galaxy colour and luminosity distribution in galaxy groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.04966v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Conditional Colour-Magnitude Distribution (CCMD) is a comprehensive formalism of the colour-magnitude-halo mass relation of galaxies. With joint modelling of a large sample of SDSS galaxies in fine bins of galaxy colour and luminosity, Xu et al. inferred parameters of a CCMD model that well reproduces colour- and luminosity-dependent abundance and clustering of present-day galaxies. In this work, we provide a test and investigation of the CCMD model by studying the colour and luminosity distribution of galaxies in galaxy groups. An apples-to-apples comparison of group galaxies is achieved by applying the same galaxy group finder to identify groups from the CCMD galaxy mocks and from the SDSS data, avoiding any systematic effect of group finding and mass assignment on the comparison. We find an overall nice agreement in the conditional luminosity function (CLF), the conditional colour function (CCF), and the CCMD of galaxies in galaxy groups inferred from CCMD mock and SDSS data. We also discuss the subtle differences revealed by the comparison. In addition, using two external catalogues constructed to only include central galaxies with halo mass measured through weak lensing, we find that their colour-magnitude distribution shows two distinct and orthogonal components, in line with the prediction of the CCMD model. Our results suggest that the CCMD model provides a good description of halo mass dependent galaxy colour and luminosity distribution. The halo and CCMD mock catalogues are made publicly available to facilitate other investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.04966v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 533, Issue 2, pp.1485-1502, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Haojie Xu, Zheng Zheng, Xiaohu Yang, Qingyang Li, Hong Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital dynamics in galactic potentials under mass transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16367v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-dependent potentials are common in galactic systems that undergo significant evolution, interactions, or encounters with other galaxies, or when there are dynamic processes like star formation and merging events. Recent studies show that an ensemble approach along with the so-called snapshot framework in dynamical system theory provide a powerful tool to analyze time dependent dynamics.
  In this work, we aim to explore and quantify the phase space structure and dynamical complexity in time-dependent galactic potentials consisting of multiple components. We apply the classical method of Poincar\'e-surface of section to analyze the phase space structure in a chaotic Hamiltonian system subjected to parameter drift. This, however, makes sense only when the evolution of a large ensemble of initial conditions is followed. Numerical simulations explore the phase space structure of such ensembles while the system undergoes a continuous parameter change. The pair-wise average distance of ensemble members allows us to define a generalized Lyapunov-exponent, that might also be time dependent, to describe the system stability. We provide a comprehensive dynamical analysis of the system under circumstances where linear mass transfer undergoes between the disk and bulge components of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16367v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edu\'ard Ill\'es, D\'aniel J\'anosi, Tam\'as Kov\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JADES -- The Rosetta Stone of JWST-discovered AGN: deciphering the intriguing nature of early AGN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: JWST has discovered a large population of Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) at high redshift. Many of these newly discovered AGN have broad permitted lines (typically H$\alpha$), but are extremely weak in the X-rays. Here we present the NIRSpec spectrum of the most extreme of these objects, GN-28074, an AGN at $z=2.26$ with prominent Balmer, Paschen and \HeI broad lines, and with the highest limit on the bolometric to X-ray luminosity ratio among all spectroscopically confirmed AGN in GOODS. This source is also characterized by a mid-IR excess, most likely associated with the AGN torus' hot dust. The high bolometric luminosity and moderate redshift of this AGN allow us to explore its properties more in depth relative to other JWST-discovered AGN. The NIRSpec spectrum reveals prominent, slightly blueshifted absorption of H$\alpha$, H$\beta$ and \HeI$\lambda$10830. The Balmer absorption lines require gas with densities of $n_{\rm H}&gt; 10^8~{\rm cm}^{-3}$, inconsistent with an ISM origin, but fully consistent with clouds in the Broad Line Region (BLR). This finding suggests that at least part of the X-ray weakness is due to high (Compton thick) X-ray absorption by (dust-free) clouds in the BLR, or in its outer, slowly outflowing regions. GN-28074 is also extremely radio-weak. The radio weakness can also be explained in terms of absorption, as the inferred density of the clouds responsible for H$\alpha$ absorption makes them optically thick to radio emission through free-free absorption. Alternatively, in this and other JWST-discovered AGN, the nuclear magnetic field may have not developed properly yet, resulting both in intrinsically weak radio emission and also lack of hot corona, hence intrinsic X-ray weakness. Finally, we show that recently proposed scenarios, invoking hyper-dense and ultra-metal-poor outflows or Raman scattering to explain the broad H$\alpha$, are completely ruled out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08643v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2367</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ignas Juod\v{z}balis, Xihan Ji, Roberto Maiolino, Francesco D'Eugenio, Jan Scholtz, Guido Risaliti, Andrew C. Fabian, Giovanni Mazzolari, Roberto Gilli, Isabella Prandoni, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stefano Carniani, St\'ephane Charlot, Emma Curtis-Lake, Anna de Graaff, Kevin Hainline, Eleonora Parlanti, Michele Perna, Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, Brant Robertson, Sandro Tacchella, Hannah \"Ubler, Christina C. Williams, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Correlation Between Dust and Gas Contents in Molecular Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02057v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecular clouds are regions of dense gas and dust in space where new stars and planets are born. There is a strong correlation between the distribution of dust and molecular gas in molecular clouds. The present work focuses on the three-dimensional morphological comparisons between dust and gas within 567 molecular clouds identified in a previously published catalog. We confirm a sample of 112 molecular clouds, where the cloud morphology based on CO observations and dust observations displays good overall consistency. There are up to 334 molecular clouds whose dust distribution might be related to the distribution of gas. We are unable to find gas structures that correlate with the shape of the dust distribution in 24 molecular clouds. For the 112 molecular clouds where the dust distribution correlates very well with the distribution of gas, we use CO observational data to measure the physical properties of these molecular clouds and compare them with the results derived from dust, exploring the correlation between gas and dust in the molecular clouds. We found that the gas and dust in the molecular clouds have a fairly good linear relationship, with a gas-to-dust ratio of $\mathrm{GDR}=(2.80_{-0.34}^{+0.37})\times10^{21}\mathrm{\,cm^{-2}\, mag^{-1}}$. The ratio varies considerably among different molecular clouds. We measured the scale height of dust-CO clouds exhibiting strong correlations, finding $h_{Z} = 43.3_{-3.5}^{+4.0}\mathrm{\,pc}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02057v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui-Zhi Li, Bing-Qiu Chen, Guang-Xing Li, Bo-Ting Wang, Hao-Ming Ren, Qi-Ning Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST Reveals Bulge-dominated Star-forming Galaxies at Cosmic Noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08328v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hubble Space Telescope imaging shows that most star-forming galaxies at cosmic noon -- the peak of cosmic star formation history -- appear disk-dominated, leaving the origin of the dense cores in their quiescent descendants unclear. With the James Webb Space Telescope's (JWST) high-resolution imaging to 5 {\mu}m, we can now map the rest-frame near-infrared emission, a much closer proxy for stellar mass distribution, in these massive galaxies. We selected 70 star-forming galaxies with 10$&lt;$log(M)$&lt;$12 and 1.5$&lt;$z$&lt;$3 in the CEERS survey and compare their morphologies in the rest-frame optical to those in the rest-frame near-IR. While the bulk of these galaxies are disk-dominated in 1.5 {\mu}m (rest-frame optical) imaging, they appear more bulge-dominated at 4.4 {\mu}m (rest-frame near-infrared). Our analysis reveals that in massive star-forming galaxies at z$\sim$2, the radial surface brightness profiles steepen significantly, from a slope of $\sim$0.3/dex at 1.5 {\mu}m to $\sim$1.4/dex at 4.4 {\mu}m within radii $&lt;$ 1 kpc. Additionally, we find their total flux contained within the central 1 kpc is approximately 7 times higher in F444W than in F150W. In rest-optical emission, a galaxy's central surface density appears to be the strongest indicator of whether it is quenched or star-forming. Our most significant finding is that at redder wavelengths, the central surface density ratio between quiescent and star-forming galaxies dramatically decreases from $\sim$10 to $\sim$1. This suggests the high central densities associated with galaxy quenching are already in place during the star-forming phase, imposing new constraints on the transition from star formation to quiescence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08328v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad7e27</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 ApJL 974 L28</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chlo\"e E. Benton, Erica J. Nelson, Tim B. Miller, Rachel Bezanson, Justus Gibson, Abigail I Hartley, Marco Martorano, Sedona H. Price, Katherine A. Suess, Arjen van der Wel, Pieter van Dokkum, John R. Weaver, Katherine E. Whitaker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the Diffuse Interstellar Bands at 5780, 5797, and 6614 {\AA} in Low-Resolution Spectra of Cool Stars from LAMOST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19539v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We attempt to measure the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614 in over two million low-resolution spectra of cool stars from LAMOST. Based on the DIB measurements, the correlation between DIBs and extinction, the kinematics of DIBs, and the Galactic distribution of DIBs are reviewed and investigated from the perspective of statistics. A pipeline is developed to measure the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614 in the LAMOST low-resolution spectra. We obtain the DIB measurements of spectra of late-type stars from LAMOST, and screen out 176,831, 13,473 and 110,152 high-quality (HQ) measurements of the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614, respectively, corresponding to 142,074, 11,480 and 85,301 unique sources. Utilizing these HQ measurements, we present the Galactic maps of the DIBs $\lambda$5780 and $\lambda$6614 in the northern sky for the first time. The central wavelengths of the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614 in air are determined to be 5780.48 $\pm$ 0.01, 5796.94 $\pm$ 0.02 and 6613.64 $\pm$ 0.01 {\AA}, respectively, based on their kinematics. The equivalent widths of these three DIBs per unit extinction are statistically fitted to be 0.565, 0.176 and 0.256 {\AA}/mag. As a part of our work, three catalogs of the HQ measurements for the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614 are provided online. To the best of our knowledge, this is the largest number of measurements of these three DIBs to date. It is also the first time that the Galactic maps of the DIBs $\lambda$5780 and $\lambda$6614 in the northern hemisphere are presented, and the central wavelengths of the DIBs $\lambda$5780, $\lambda$5797 and $\lambda$6614 are estimated from the kinematics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19539v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Xiao Ma, Jian-Jun Chen, A-Li Luo, He Zhao, Ji-Wei Shi, Jing Chen, Jun-Chao Liang, Shu-Guo Ma, Cai-Xia Qu, Bi-Wei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comparative high-resolution spectroscopic analysis of in situ and accreted globular clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06702v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Globular clusters (GCs) are extremely intriguing systems that help in reconstructing the assembly of the Milky Way via the characterisation of their chemo-chrono-dynamical properties. In this study, we use high-resolution spectroscopic archival data from UVES and UVES-FLAMES at VLT to compare the chemistry of GCs dynamically tagged as either Galactic (NGC 6218, NGC 6522 and NGC 6626) or accreted from distinct merger events (NGC 362 and NGC 1261 from Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus, and Ruprecht 106 from the Helmi Streams) in the metallicity regime where abundance patterns of field stars with different origin effectively separate ($-1.3 \le$ [Fe/H] $\le -1.0$ dex). We find remarkable similarities in the abundances of the two Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus GCs across all chemical elements. They both display depletion in the $\alpha$-elements (Mg, Si and Ca) and statistically significant differences in Zn and Eu compared to in situ GCs. Additionally, we confirm that Ruprecht 106 exhibits a completely different chemical makeup from the other target clusters, being underabundant in all chemical elements. This demonstrates that when high precision is achieved, the abundances of certain chemical elements can not only efficiently separate in situ from accreted GCs, but can also distinguish among GCs born in different progenitor galaxies. In the end, we investigate the possible origin of the chemical peculiarity of Ruprecht 106. Given that its abundances do not match the chemical patterns of field stars associated to its most likely parent galaxy (i.e. the Helmi Streams), being depleted in the abundances of $\alpha$-elements in particular, we believe Ruprecht 106 to originate from a less massive galaxy compared to the progenitor of the Helmi Streams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06702v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Ceccarelli, A. Mucciarelli, D. Massari, M. Bellazzini, T. Matsuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy populations in protoclusters at cosmic noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08412v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the physical properties and redshift evolution of simulated galaxies residing in protoclusters at cosmic noon, to understand the influence of the environment on galaxy formation. This work is to build clear expectations for the ongoing ODIN survey, devoted to mapping large-scale structures at z=2.4, 3.1, and 4.5 using Ly$\alpha$-emitting galaxies (LAEs) as tracers. From the IllustrisTNG simulations, we define subregions centered on the most massive clusters ranked by total stellar mass at z=0 and study the properties of galaxies within, including LAEs. To model the LAE population, we take a semi-analytical approach that assigns Ly$\alpha$ luminosity and equivalent width based on the UV luminosities to galaxies in a probabilistic manner. We investigate stellar mass, star formation rate, major mergers, and specific star formation rate of the population of star-forming galaxies and LAEs in the field and protocluster environment and trace their evolution. We find that the overall shape of the UV luminosity function (LF) in simulated protocluster environments is characterized by a shallower faint-end slope and an excess on the bright end, signaling different formation histories for galaxies therein. The difference is milder for the Ly$\alpha$ LF. While protocluster galaxies follow the same SFR-$M_{\odot}$ scaling relation as average field galaxies, a larger fraction appears to have experienced major mergers in the last 200 Myr and as a result shows enhanced star formation at a ~60% level, leading to a flatter distribution in both SFR and $M_{\odot}$ relative to galaxies in the average field. We find that protocluster galaxies, including LAEs, begin to quench much earlier (z~0.8-1.6) than field galaxies (z~0.5-0.9); our result is in agreement with recent observational results and highlights the importance of large-scale environment on the overall formation history of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08412v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moira Andrews, M. Celeste Artale, Ankit Kumar, Kyoung-Soo Lee, Tess Florek, Kaustub Anand, Candela Cerdosino, Robin Ciardullo, Nicole Firestone, Eric Gawiser, Caryl Gronwall, Lucia Guaita, Sungryong Hong, Ho Seong Hwang, Jaehyun Lee, Seong-Kook Lee, Nelson Padilla, Jaehong Park, Roxana Popescu, Vandana Ramakrishnan, Hyunmi Song, F. Vivanco C\'adiz, Mark Vogelsberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Discovery of Polarized Water Vapor Megamaser Emission in a Molecular Accretion Disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10569v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For the first time in an extragalactic source, we detect linearly polarized water maser emission associated with the molecular accretion disk of NGC 1068. The position angles of the electric polarization vectors are perpendicular to the axes of filamentary structures in the molecular accretion disk. The inferred magnetic field threading the molecular disk must lie within approximately 35 degrees of the sky plane. The orientation of the magnetic fields relative to the disk plane implies that the maser region is unstable to hydromagnetically powered outflow; we speculate that the maser region may be the source of the larger scale molecular outflow found in ALMA studies. The new VLBI observations also reveal a compact radio continuum source, NGC 1068*, aligned with the near-systemic maser spots. The molecular accretion disk must be viewed nearly edge-on, and the revised central mass is (16.6 +/- 0.1) million solar masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10569v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack F. Gallimore, C. M. Violette Impellizzeri, Samaneh Aghelpasand, Feng Gao, Virginia Hostetter, Boy Lankhaar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Milky Way Insights from Cepheids I: Infrared Period-Luminosit-Metallicity Relations and the Time Evolution of Metallicity Gradient</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calibrate the period--luminosity--metallicity (PLZ) relations of classical Cepheid (DCEP) in three near-infrared bands ($J$, $H$, and $K_S$) and four mid-infrared bands ($W1$, $W2$, $[3.6]$, and $[4.5]$). The PLZ relations of $W1$ and $W2$ bands are calibrated for the first time. The distance moduli of the Large Magellanic Cloud estimated by these PLZ relations are in good agreement with the most accurate published value measured by geometric methods. These seven homogenous PLZ relations can aid in obtaining more robust distances for DCEPs. Applying our PLZ relations to trace the metallicity gradient of the Galactic disc, we find that the gradient for sources with logarithmic age less than 7.67 is almost fixed: $-0.056 \,\pm\, 0.002 \,\textrm{dex}\, \textrm{kpc}^{-1}$; the gradient for sources with logarithmic age greater than 7.67 is period--dependent (i.e., age-dependent): $(-0.074 \,\pm\, 0.003)+(-0.022 \,\pm\, 0.002)\log P)\,\textrm{dex}\, \textrm{kpc}^{-1}$. In addition, we find that DCEPs in the $R_{GC} \gtrsim 14.5\,\textrm{kpc}$ region tend to migrate toward the Galactic center, while DCEPs in the $10.5\,\textrm{kpc} \lesssim R_{GC} \lesssim 14.5\,\textrm{kpc}$ region tend to migrate toward the anti-Galactic center, which may be the reason for the obvious break of the metallicity gradient at $R_{GC} \thickapprox 14.5\,\textrm{kpc}$. We conclude that the evolution of the metallicity gradient of DCEPs may be related to their radial migration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10747v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huajian Wang, Ye Xu, Zehao Lin, Yingjie Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"SNe Ia twins for life" towards a precise determination of H$_{0}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10334v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Here we present an approach to the measurement of extragalactic distances using twin SNe Ia, taken from the early down to the nebular phase.The approach is purely empirical, although we can give a theoretical background on why the method is reliable. By studying those twins in galaxies where peculiar velocities are relatively unimportant, we can tackle the H$_{0}$ tension problem. Here we apply the method to the determination of the distances to NGC 7250 and NGC 2525, who hosted respectively SN 2013dy and SN 2018gv, twins of two different SNe Ia prototypes: SN 2013aa/SN 2017cbv and SN2011fe. From the study of the SN 2013aa and SN 2017cbv twin pair, by comparing it with SN 2011fe and applying the difference between the SN 2013aa/2017cbv and the SN 2011fe class, we find as well a good estimate of the distance to NGC 5643. We have just started to measure distances with this method for the samples in Freedman et al. and Riess et al. There are differences in measured distances to the same galaxy using Cepheids or TRGBs. In this context of discrepancy, the ''twins for life '' method is very competitive because it can provide distance estimates with a modulus error of $\sigma_{\mu}$ $=$ 0.04 mag. Our findings called for a revision of the distances measured with Cepheids in Riess et al. (2022). NGC 7250 and NGC 2525 needed better measurements with Cepheids. We have noticed that the Cepheids--based distance obtained with the {\it JWST} in Riess et al. (2024a) for NGC 5643 is in a a good agreement with what we find, unlike their previous estimate in Riess et al. (2022). We address the local SNe Ia distances as part of the Hubble tension problem. We expect to apply the 'twin' SNe Ia comparison from the local sample to galaxies with z $&gt;$0.02--0.03 well into the Hubble flow to obtain a reliable value of H$_{0.}$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10334v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pilar Ruiz-Lapuente, Jonay I. Gonz\'alez Hern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine Structure of the Age-Chromospheric Activity Relation in Solar-Type Stars: II. H$\alpha$ Line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12519v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Excess chromospheric emissions within deep photospheric lines are effective proxies of stellar magnetism for FGK stars. This emission decays with stellar age and is a potential determinant of this important stellar quantity. We report absolutely calibrated H$\alpha$ chromospheric fluxes for 511 solar-type stars in a wide interval of precisely determined masses, $[$Fe/H$]$, ages, and evolution states from high S/N, moderately high$-$resolution spectra. The comparison of H$\alpha$ and H+K chromospheric fluxes reveals a metallicity bias (absent from H$\alpha$) affecting Ca II H+K fluxes thereby metal-rich stars with deep line profiles mimic low chromospheric flux levels, and vice versa for metal-poor stars. This bias blurs the age-activity relation, precluding age determinations for old, inactive stars unless mass and $[$Fe/H$]$ are calibrated into the relation. The H+K lines being the most widely studied tool to quantify magnetic activity in FGK stars, care should be exercised in its use whenever wide ranges of mass and $[$Fe/H$]$ are involved. The H$\alpha$ age-activity-mass-metallicity calibration appears to be in line with the theoretical expectation that (other parameters being equal) more massive stars possess narrower convective zones and are less active than less massive stars, while more metal-rich stars have deeper convective zones and appear more active than metal-poorer stars. If regarded statistically in tandem with other age diagnostics, H$\alpha$ chromospheric fluxes may be suitable to constrain ages for FGK stars with acceptable precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12519v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1532</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, Volume 532, Issue 1, July 2024, Pages 563-576</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paulo V. Souza dos Santos, Gustavo F. Porto de Mello, Erica Costa-Bhering, Diego Lorenzo-Oliveira, Felipe Almeida-Fernandes, Let\'icia Dutra-Ferreira, Ignasi Ribas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Masses of Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Galaxy Clusters Detected by The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Stacked Lensing Measurements with Subaru HSC Year 3 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08201v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a stacked lensing analysis of 96 galaxy clusters selected by the thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (SZ) effect in maps of the cosmic microwave background (CMB). We select foreground galaxy clusters with a $5\sigma$-level SZ threshold in CMB observations from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope, while we define background source galaxies for the lensing analysis with secure photometric redshift cuts in Year 3 data of the Subaru Hyper Suprime Cam survey. We detect the stacked lensing signal in the range of $0.1 &lt; R\, [h^{-1}\mathrm{Mpc}] &lt; 100$ in each of three cluster redshift bins, $0.092&lt;z\le0.445$, $0.445&lt;z\le0.695$, and $0.695&lt;z\le1.180$, with 32 galaxy clusters in each bin. The cumulative signal-to-noise ratios of the lensing signal are $14.6$, $12.0$, and $6.6$, respectively. Using a halo-based forward model, we then constrain statistical relationships between the mass inferred from the SZ observation (i.e. SZ mass) and the total mass derived from our stacked lensing measurements. At the average SZ mass in the cluster sample ($2.1-2.4\times10^{14}\, h^{-1}M_\odot$), our likelihood analysis shows that the average total mass differs from the SZ counterpart by a factor of $1.3 \pm 0.2$, $1.6 \pm 0.2$, and $1.6 \pm 0.3$ ($68\%$) in the aforementioned redshift ranges, respectively. Our limits are consistent with previous lensing measurements, and we find that the cluster modeling choices can introduce a $1\sigma$-level difference in our parameter inferences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08201v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masato Shirasaki, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Hironao Miyatake, Erwin Lau, Zhuowen Zhang, Neta Bahcall, Mark Devlin, Jo Dunkley, Arya Farahi, Matt Hilton, Yen-Ting Lin, Daisuke Nagai, Suzanne T. Staggs, Tomomi Sunayama, David Spergel, Edward J. Wollack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Siril: An Advanced Tool for Astronomical Image Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03346v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Siril is a powerful open-source software package designed for the preprocessing and post-processing of astronomical images. It is particularly well-suited for astrophotography enthusiasts and professional astronomers alike. Siril provides advanced tools for tasks such as image stacking, calibration, registration, and enhancement, enabling users to produce high-quality images of celestial objects. The version discussed here is the development branch 1.4, which, while not officially released, is available for testing and includes the latest features and improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03346v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21105/joss.07242</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Open Source Software, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cyril Richard, Vincent Hourdin, C\'ecile Melis, Adrian Knagg-Baugh</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
