<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High N/O ratio at high redshift as a result of a strong burst of star formation and differential galactic winds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observations by JWST have revealed supersolar $^{14}$N abundances in galaxies at very high redshift. On the other hand, these galaxies show subsolar metallicity. The observed N/O ratios are difficult to reproduce in the framework of chemical evolution models for the Milky Way. Our aim is to reproduce these high N/O ratios with chemical evolution models assuming different histories of star formation triggering galactic winds coupled with detailed nucleosynthesis prescriptions for $^{14}$N, $^{12}$C, $^{16}$O and $^{56}$Fe. We compute several models for small galaxies ($10^{9}\text{ - }10^{10}\text{ M}_{\odot}$) with high star formation efficiency and strong galactic winds. These winds are assumed to be differential, carrying out mainly the products of the explosion of core-collapse supernovae. We find that only models with high star formation rates, normal initial mass function, and differential galactic winds can reproduce the observed chemical abundances. We also find that with the same assumptions about star formation and galactic winds, but with a very rapid formation resulting from fast gas infall, we can also reproduce the estimated ages of these objects. We find no necessity to invoke peculiar nucleosynthesis from Population III stars, very massive stars and supermassive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05363v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Rizzuti, F. Matteucci, P. Molaro, G. Cescutti, R. Maiolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Origins of Outflowing Cold Clouds in Local Star-forming Dwarf Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the physical origins of outflowing cold clouds in a sample of 14 low-redshift dwarf ($M_{\ast} \lesssim 10^{10}$ $M_{\odot}$) galaxies from the COS Legacy Archive Spectroscopic SurveY (CLASSY) using Keck/ESI data. Outflows are traced by broad (FWHM ~ 260 $\rm{km}$ $\rm{s^{-1}}$) and very-broad (VB; FWHM ~ 1200 $\rm{km}$ $\rm{s^{-1}}$) velocity components in strong emission lines like [O III] $\lambda 5007$ and $\rm{H}\alpha$. The maximum velocities ($v_{\rm{max}}$) of broad components correlate positively with SFR, unlike the anti-correlation observed for VB components, and are consistent with superbubble models. In contrast, supernova-driven galactic wind models better reproduce the $v_{\rm{max}}$ of VB components. Direct radiative cooling from a hot wind significantly underestimates the luminosities of both broad and VB components. A multi-phase wind model with turbulent radiative mixing reduces this discrepancy to at least one dex for most VB components. Stellar photoionization likely provides additional energy since broad components lie in the starburst locus of excitation diagnostic diagrams. We propose a novel interpretation of outflow origins in star-forming dwarf galaxies$-$broad components trace expanding superbubble shells, while VB components originate from galactic winds. One-zone photoionization models fail to explain the low-ionization lines ([S II] and [O I]) of broad components near the maximal starburst regime, which two-zone photoionization models with density-bounded channels instead reproduce. These two-zone models indicate anisotropic leakage of Lyman continuum photons through low-density channels formed by expanding superbubbles. Our study highlights extreme outflows ($v_{\rm{max}} \gtrsim 1000$ $\rm{km}$ $\rm{s^{-1}}$) in 9 out of 14 star-forming dwarf galaxies, comparable to AGN-driven winds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05371v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixuan Peng, Crystal L. Martin, Zirui Chen, Drummond B. Fielding, Xinfeng Xu, Timothy Heckman, Lise Ramambason, Yuan Li, Cody Carr, Weida Hu, Zuyi Chen, Claudia Scarlata, Alaina Henry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary and Grouped Open Clusters: A New Catalogue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Understanding the formation and evolution of star clusters in the Milky Way requires precise identification of clusters that form binary or multiple systems. Such systems offer valuable insight into the dynamical processes and interactions that influence cluster evolution. Aims. This study aims to identify and classify star clusters in the Milky Way as part of double or multiple systems. Specifically, we seek to detect clusters that form gravitationally bound pairs or groups of clusters and distinguish between different types of interactions based on their physical properties and spatial distributions. Methods. We used the extensive star cluster database of Hunt &amp; Reffert (2023, 2024), which includes 7167 clusters. By estimating the tidal forces acting on each cluster through the tidal factor (TF), and considering only close neighbours (within 50 pc), we identified a total of 2170 star clusters forming part of double and multiple systems. Pairs were classified as Binaries (B), Capture pairs (C), or Optical pairs (O/Oa) based on proper motion distributions, cluster ages, and color-magnitude diagrams. Results. Our analysis identified 617 paired systems, which were successfully classified using our scheme. Additionally, we found 261 groups of star clusters, each with three or more members, further supporting the presence of multiple systems within the Milky Way that exhibit significant tidal interactions. Conclusions. The method presented provides an improved approach for identifying star clusters that share the same spatial volume and experience notable tidal interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05376v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tali Palma, Valeria Coenda, Gustavo Baume, Carlos Feinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Compton-thick AGN luminosity function in the local Universe: A robust estimate combining BAT detections and NuSTAR spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Compton-thick Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) arguably constitute the most elusive class of sources as they are absorbed by large column densities above logN_H(cm^-2)=24. These extreme absorptions hamper the detection of the central source even in hard X-ray energies. In this work, we use both SWIFT and NuSTAR observations in order to derive the most accurate yet Compton-thick AGN luminosity function. We, first, compile a sample of candidate Compton-thick AGN (logN_H(cm^-2)= 24-25) detected in the Swift BAT all-sky survey in the 14-195 keV band. We confirm that they are Compton-thick sources by using the follow-up NuSTAR observations already presented in the literature. Our sample is composed of 44 sources, consistent with a column density of logN_H(cm^-2)=24-25 at the 90% confidence level. These have intrinsic luminosities higher than L(10-50 keV) ~ 3x10^41 erg/s and are found up to a redshift of z=0.05 (200 Mpc). We derive the luminosity function of Compton-thick AGN using a Bayesian methodology where both the full column density and the luminosity distributions are taken into account. The faint end of the luminosity function is flat, having a slope of 0.01(+0.51,-0.74), rather arguing against a numerous population of low luminosity Compton-thick AGN. Based on our luminosity function, we estimate that the fraction of Compton-thick AGN relative to the total number of AGN is of the order of 24 (+5,-5) % in agreement with previous estimates in the local Universe based on BAT samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05432v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Georgantopoulos, E. Pouliasis, A. Ruiz, A. Akylas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Galactic Halos: A Detailed Review of Star Formation in NGC 5128 (Cen A)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NGC 5128 (Centaurus A), the closest giant elliptical galaxy outside the Local Group to the Milky Way, is one of the brightest extragalactic radio sources. It is distinguished by a prominent dust lane and powerful jets, driven by a supermassive black hole at its core. Using previously identified long-period variable (LPV) stars from the literature, this study aims to reconstruct the star formation history (SFH) of two distinct regions in the halo of NGC 5128. These regions reveal remarkably similar SFHs, despite being located about 28 kpc apart on opposite sides of the galaxy's center. In Field 1, star formation rates (SFRs) show notable increases at approximately 800 Myr and 3.8 Gyr ago. Field 2 exhibits similar peaks at these times, along with an additional rise around 6.3 Gyr ago. The increase in SFR around 800 Myr ago is consistent with earlier research suggesting a merger event. Since no LPV catalog exists for the central region of NGC 5128, we focused our investigation on its outer regions, which has provided new insights into the complex evolutionary history of this cornerstone galaxy. The SFH traced by LPVs supports a scenario in which multiple events of nuclear activity have triggered episodic, jet-induced star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05642v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Abdollahi, Sima Taefi Aghdam, Atefeh Javadi, Seyed Azim Hashemi, Jacco Th. van Loon, Habib Khosroshahi, Roya Hamedani Golshan, Elham Saremi, Maryam Saberi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star Formation History of the Local Group Dwarf Irregular Galaxy, NGC 6822</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NGC 6822 is an isolated dwarf irregular galaxy in the local group at a distance of 490 kpc. In this paper, we present the star formation history (SFH) within a field with a radius of 3 kpc, beyond the optical body of the galaxy (1.2 kpc). We utilized a novel method based on evolved asymptotic giant branch (AGB) stars. We collected the Near infrared data of 329 variable stars, including long-period and amplitude variables and Carbon-rich AGB stars. We used stellar evolutionary track and theoretical isochrones to obtain the birth mass, age, and pulsation duration of the detected stars to calculate the star formation rate (SFR) and trace the SFH of the galaxy. We studied the star formation history of the galaxy for the mean metallicity value (Z) of 0.003. We reconstructed the SFH for two regions. The bar region, a central rectangular area, and the outer region, which covers a circular field beyond the bar region and extends to a radius of 3 kpc. Our results show a significant burst of star formation around 2.6 and 2.9 Gyr ago in the bar and outer regions, respectively. Additionally, we observed a notable enhancement in the SFR in the bar region over the past 200 Myr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05646v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Khatamsaz, Mahdi Abdollahi, Hedieh Abdollahi, Atefeh Javadi, Jacco Th. van Loon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffuse Ionized Gas in the Anti-center of the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using data from the LAMOST Medium-Resolution Spectroscopic Survey of Nebulae, we create a sample of 17,821 diffuse ionized gas (DIG) spectra in the anti-center region of the Milky Way, by excluding fibers in the directions of H II regions and supernova remnants. We then analyze the radial and vertical distributions of three line ratios ([N II]/H$\alpha$, [S II]/H$\alpha$, and [S II]/[N II]), as well as the oxygen abundance.
  [N II]/H$\alpha$ and [S II]/H$\alpha$ do not exhibit a consistent, monotonic decrease with increasing Galactocentric distance (R$_{gal}$). Instead, they show enhancement within the interarm region, positioned between the Local Arm and the Perseus Arm. [S II]/[N II] has a radial gradient of 0.1415 $\pm$ 0.0646 kpc$^{-1}$ for the inner disk (8.34 $ &lt; R_{gal} &lt; $ 9.65 kpc), and remains nearly flat for the outer disk ($R_{gal} &gt; $ 9.65 kpc). In the vertical direction, [N II]/H$\alpha$, [S II]/H$\alpha$, and [S II]/[N II] increase with increasing Galactic disk height ($|z|$) in both southern and northern disks.
  Based on the N2S2H$\alpha$ method, which combines [S II]/[N II] and [N II]/H$\alpha$, we estimate the oxygen abundance. The oxygen abundance exhibits a consistent radial gradient with R$_{gal}$, featuring a slope of -0.0559 $\pm$ 0.0209 dex kpc$^{-1}$ for the inner disk and a similar slope of -0.0429 $\pm$ 0.0599 dex kpc$^{-1}$ for the outer disk. A single linear fitting to the entire disk yields a slope of -0.0317 $\pm$ 0.0124 dex kpc$^{-1}$. In the vertical direction, the oxygen abundance decreases with increasing $|z|$ in both southern and northern disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiming Wen, Wei Zhang, Lin Ma, Yunning Zhao, Man I. Lam, Chaojian Wu, Juanjuan Ren, Jianjun Chen, Yuzhong Wu, Guozhen Hu, Yonghui Hou, Yongheng Zhao, Hong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A semi-analytical perspective on massive red galaxies: I. Assembly history, environment &amp; redshift evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Investigating the assembly history of the most massive and passive galaxies will enhance our understanding of why galaxies exhibit such a remarkable diversity in structure and morphology. In this paper, we simultaneously investigate the assembly history and redshift evolution of semi-analytically modelled galaxy properties of central galaxies between 0.56 &lt; z &lt; 4.15, alongside their connection to their halos as a function of large-scale environment. We extract sub-samples of galaxies from a mock catalogue representative for the BOSS-CMASS sample, which includes the most massive and passively evolving system known today. Utilising typical galaxy properties such as star formation rate, (g-i) colour, or cold gas-phase metallicity (Zcold), we track the redshift evolution of these properties across the main progenitor trees. We present results on galaxy and halo properties, including their growth and clustering functions. Our findings indicate that galaxies in the highest stellar and halo mass regimes are least metal-enriched (using Zcold as a proxy) and consistently exhibit significantly larger black hole masses and higher clustering amplitudes compared to sub-samples selected by e.g. colour or star formation rate. This population forms later and also retains large reservoirs of cold gas. In contrast, galaxies in the intermediate and lower stellar/halo mass regimes consume their cold gas at higher redshift and were among the earliest and quickest to assemble. We observe a clear trend where the clustering of the galaxies selected according to their Zcold-values (either low-Zcold or high-Zcold) depends on the density of their location within the large-scale environment. We assume that in particular galaxies in the low/high-Zcold sub-samples form and evolve through distinct evolutionary channels, which are predetermined by their location within the large-scale environment of the cosmic web.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05745v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Stoppacher, A. D. Montero-Dorta, M. C. Artale, A. Knebe, N. Padilla, A. J. Benson, C. Behrens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST Discovery of a Very Fast Biconical Outflow of Warm Molecular Gas in the Nearby Ultra-Luminous Infrared Galaxy F08572+3915 NW</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05859v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present new James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI) Medium-Resolution Spectrometer (MRS) observations of the nearby ultra-luminous infrared galaxy (ULIRG) F08572+3915 NW. These integral field spectroscopic (IFS) data reveal a kpc-scale warm-molecular rotating disk and biconical outflow traced by the H$_2$ $\nu$ = 0$-$0 S(1), S(2), S(3), and S(5) rotational transitions. The outflow maintains a relatively constant median (maximum) projected velocity of 1100 km s$^{-1}$ (3000 km s$^{-1}$) out to $\sim$ 1.4 kpc from the nucleus. The outflowing H$_2$ material is slightly warmer (640 $-$ 700 K) than the rotating disk material (460 $-$ 520 K), perhaps due to shock heating in the highly turbulent outflowing material. This outflow shares the same kinematics and orientation as the sub-kpc scale warm-H$_2$ outflow traced by the ro-vibrational H$_2$ lines in Keck AO near-infrared IFS data. However, this warm-H$_2$ outflow is significantly faster than the sub-kpc scale cold-molecular outflow derived from multi-transition far-infrared OH observations with Herschel and the $\gtrsim$ kpc-scale cold-molecular outflow mapped by mm-wave interferometric CO 1$-$0 observations with IRAM-PdBI and NOEMA. The new JWST data bolster the scenario where the buried quasar in this ULIRG is excavating the dust screen, accelerating perhaps as much as 60\% of the dusty warm-molecular material to velocities beyond the escape velocity, and thus influencing the evolution of the host galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05859v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad9a50</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kylie Yui Dan, Jerome Seebeck, Sylvain Veilleux, David Rupke, Eduardo Gonzalez-Alfonso, Ismael Garcia-Bernete, Weizhe Liu, Dieter Lutz, Marcio Melendez, Miguel Pereira Santaella, Eckhard Sturm, Francesco Tombesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spectral Behaviour and Variability of Narrow-line Seyfert 1 Galaxies with Australia Telescope Compact Array Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05933v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present multi-frequency radio data for a sample of narrow-line Seyfert 1 galaxies. We first focus on the sub-class of gamma-ray emitting narrow-line Seyfert 1 galaxies, studying the long-term radio variability of five sources and comparing it to their gamma-ray state. We then extend the observations of the southern narrow-line Seyfert 1 galaxy sample of Chen et al. by observing several candidate narrow-line Seyfert 1 sources for the first time, and re-observing several other gamma-ray quiet sources to obtain a first indication of their radio variability. We find that the gamma-ray emitting narrow-line Seyfert 1 galaxies are highly variable radio emitters and that there are instances of contemporaneous flaring activity between the radio and gamma-ray band (PKS 0440$-$00, PMN J0948+0022 and PKS 1244$-$255). However, there are also cases of significant radio outbursts without gamma-ray counterparts (PMN J0948+0022 and PKS 2004$-$447). The five gamma-ray NLS1s favour flat or inverted radio spectra, although the spectral indices vary significantly over time. For the gamma-ray quiet sample, the difference between the previous observations at 5.5 GHz and new ATCA observations indicates that over half of the 14 sources exhibit apparent variability. In contrast to gamma-ray loud sources, gamma-ray quiet objects tend to have steep spectra especially in the lower radio band (887.5$-$1367.5 MHz), with a number of the variable sources having flatter spectra at higher radio frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05933v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Shao, Philip G. Edwards, Jamie Stevens, Minfeng Gu, Timothy J. Galvin, Minh T. Huynh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Predictive Capacity of FLARES Simulations for High Redshift "Little Red Dots"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05946v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent discovery of little red dots - a population of extremely compact and highly dust-reddened high redshift galaxies - by the James Webb Space Telescope presents a new challenge to the fields of astrophysics and cosmology. Their remarkably high luminosities at redshifts 5 &lt; z &lt; 10, appear to challenge LambdaCDM cosmology and galaxy formation models, as they imply stellar masses and star formation rates that exceed the upper limits set by these models. LRDs are currently subjects of debate as the mechanisms behind their high luminosities are not yet fully understood. LRD energy outputs are thought to be either dominated by star formation or their energy output results from the hosting of active galactic nuclei. We investigate the starburst hypothesis by attempting to replicate the stellar properties of LRDs using output data from the FLARES simulation suite. Comparative analysis of galactic properties such as galactic number density, stellar mass and star formation rate yield significant tension between simulated and observed galaxies. The FLARES simulation overestimates the number densities of galaxies with stellar masses similar to observed LRDs by several orders of magnitude. Additionally, the simulation shows an overestimation of star formation rates. These tensions suggest a potential underestimation by the FLARES model of stellar feedback mechanisms such as active galactic nuclei feedback. These results suggest that the starburst hypothesis may be insufficient to explain the observed properties of these galaxies. Instead, the AGN scenario should be further investigated by repeating the methods in this study with a hydrodynamic galaxy simulation suite that models a higher influence of AGN feedback mechanisms on stellar activity in high redshift galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05946v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis M. T. Arts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Double-White-Dwarf Merger Rate from ZTF</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF), Burdge et al. (2020) discovered systems of eclipsing double white dwarfs (EDWDs) having orbital periods &lt;1 hr. From the properties of 3 of the discovered systems, I estimate a merger rate of DWDs, per WD in the Galaxy, of $R_{\rm merge, WD}\approx8\times 10^{-12}$yr$^{-1}$, or a rate per unit stellar mass in the Galaxy, of $R_{\rm merge, M*}\approx4.8\times 10^{-13}$yr$^{-1}$M$_\odot^{-1}$.This likely somewhat underestimates the rate, because of several known effects that work against EDWD detection in ZTF. The derived merger rate is within the uncertainty range, $R_{\rm merge, M*} =(4.6-5.8)\times 10^{-13}$yr$^{-1}$M$_\odot^{-1}$, measured independently by Maoz et al. (2018) based on two samples of DWDs discovered via radial-velocity variations. Based on the expected period distribution of DWDs and their detectability, of order 100 additional eclipsing DWDs with periods &gt;1 hr are discoverable in ZTF, with potential to significantly improve the merger-rate's measurement precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06019v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Maoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Barred Galaxies in the Young Universe at $z\sim$2 Using $\textit{JWST}$ CEERS Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06100v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studying barred galaxies at early epochs can shed light on the early evolution of stellar bars, their impact on secular evolution and the star formation activity of young galaxies, and the origins of present-day barred galaxies like the Milky Way. We analyze data from the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Cosmic Evolution Early Release Science (CEERS) Survey to explore the impact of rest-frame wavelength and spatial resolution on detecting and characterizing some of the youngest barred galaxies known to date. We apply both visual classification and ellipse-fitting to JWST F115W, F200W, and F444W images of the barred galaxy CEERS-30155 at $z\sim$2.136, an epoch when the universe was only $\sim$22$\%$ of its current age. We find that the stellar bar in CEERS-30155 is not visible in the F115W image, which traces rest-frame ultraviolet (UV) light at $z\sim$2, a rest-frame wavelength highly obscured by dust. The stellar bar is visible in the F200W image, but is most prominent in the F444W image, likely due to the F444W image tracing rest-frame near-infrared (NIR) light at $z\sim$2. Rest-frame NIR light is not obscured by dust and traces low-mass, long-lived stars that dominate the stellar mass in galaxies. However, ellipse fits of the F444W image only robustly detect stellar bars whose semimajor axis are at least one PSF ($\sim$ 0.16" or $\sim$ 1.4 kpc at $z\sim$2). At $z\sim$2, stellar bars smaller than 1.5 kpc will be more robustly detected in the sharper F200W image (PSF $\sim$ 0.08" or $\sim$0.7 kpc at $z\sim$2), provided that the rest-frame optical light it traces is not overly impacted by dust and can still unveil the bar structure. Using a combination of both JWST F200W and F444W images can improve the detection of barred galaxies at $z\sim$2 to 4. At even higher redshifts (z &gt; 4), the Giant Magellan Telescope will be a cornerstone facility to explore young barred galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06100v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keith Pritchett Jr., Shardha Jogee, Yuchen Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do some Ultra Diffuse Galaxies have Rich Globular Cluster Systems?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06155v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Some ultra diffuse galaxies (UDGs) reveal many more globular clusters (GCs) than classical dwarf galaxies of the same stellar mass. These UDGs, with a mass in their GC system (M$_{GC}$) approaching 10\% of their host galaxy stellar mass (M$_{\ast}$), are also inferred to have high halo mass to stellar mass ratios (M$_{halo}$/M$_{\ast}$). They have been dubbed Failed Galaxies. It is unknown what role high GC formation efficiencies and/or low destruction rates play in determining the high M$_{GC}$/M$_{\ast}$ ratios of some UDGs. Here we present a simple model, which is informed by recent JWST observations of lensed galaxies and by a simulation in the literature of GC mass loss and tidal disruption in dwarf galaxies. With this simple model, we aim to constrain the effects of GC efficiency/destruction on the observed GC richness of UDGs and their variation with the integrated stellar populations of UDGs. We assume no ongoing star formation (i.e. quenching at early times) and that the disrupted GCs contribute their stars to those of the host galaxy. We find that UDGs, with high M$_{GC}$/M$_{\ast}$ ratios today, are most likely the result of very high GC formation efficiencies combined with modest rates of GC destruction. The current data loosely follow the model that ranges from the mean stellar population of classical dwarfs to that of metal-poor GCs as M$_{GC}$/M$_{\ast}$ increases. As more data becomes available for UDGs, our simple model can be refined and tested further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06155v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duncan A. Forbes, Maria Luisa Buzzo, Anna Ferre-Mateu, Aaron J. Romanowsky, Jonah Gannon, Jean P. Brodie, Michelle Collins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating lower limit of metallicity for Galactic thin disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the metal-poor regime of the Galactic disk on the distribution of stars in the [$\alpha$/M]-$V_{\phi}$ plane, to identify the most metal-poor thin disk (MPTnD) stars belonging to the low-$\alpha$ sequence. Chemical abundances and velocities of sample stars are either taken or derived from APOGEE DR17 and Gaia DR3 catalogs. We find the existence of a well-separated extension of the kinematically thin disk stars in the metallicity range of -1.2 $&lt;$[M/H]$&lt;$ -0.8 dex. Based on two-by-two distributions of [Mg/Mn], [Al/Fe] and [C+N/Fe], we further confirmed 56 high-possibility metal-poor thin disk (HP-MPTnD) giant stars and suggested the lower metallicity limit of the thin disk below -0.95 dex. A comparative analysis of HP-MPTnD sample with other Galactic components revealed its chemo-dynamical similarities with canonical thin disk stars. These low-$\alpha$ metal-poor stars are predominantly located in the outer disk region and formed in the early stage of the formation of thin disk. Their existence provides compelling support for the two-infall model of the Milky way's disk formation. Moreover, these stars impose observational constraints on the timing and metallicity of the second gas infall event.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06187v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guozhen Hu, Zhengyi Shao, Erbil Gugercinoglu, Wenyuan Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Complex Organic Molecules Formation in Cold Cores: Multi-phase Models with Non-thermal Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, a significant number of oxygen-bearing complex organic molecules (COMs) have been detected in the gas phase of cold dark clouds such as TMC-1. The formation of these COMs cannot be explained by diffusive mechanisms on grains and gas phase reactions. This study investigates the formation of oxygen-bearing COMs in cold dark clouds using multiphase gas-grain models that incorporate cosmic ray-induced non-diffusive radiation chemistry and non-thermal sputtering desorption mechanisms. Additionally, we present the effects of varying elemental C/O ratio and different sputtering rates. We utilized an accelerated Gillespie algorithm, based on the regular Gillespie algorithm. The results of our models for dimethyl ether (CH3OCH3), methyl formate (HCOOCH3), acetaldehyde (CH3CHO), ethanol (C2H5OH), and methanol (CH3OH) show reasonable agreement with observations toward TMC-1, within a factor of 3. Out of the 94 species compared with observations, 63 show agreement within 1 order of magnitude, accounting for 67.02%. Overall inclusion of non-thermal mechanisms in multi-phase models shows notable improvement of modeling on oxygen-bearing COMs in the interstellar medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06397v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Lu, Donghui Quan, Qiang Chang, Long-Fei Chen, Di Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedback from Intermediate Mass Black Holes on Dwarf Galaxy Morphology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the influence of intermediate-mass black holes (IMBHs) on galactic morphology, focusing on their evolution within dwarf galaxies at high redshift (z~2). Using high-resolution zoom-in cosmological simulations, we explore how IMBH properties, including seed masses, formation times, and feedback mechanisms, shape the morphology and properties of central dwarf galaxies. The simulations analyze galaxies in both high- and low-spin dark matter halos, under varying conditions of AGN feedback and black hole seeding methods, to assess their effects on gas fractions, star formation, and structural characteristics.
  Results indicate that AGN feedback, particularly wind strength, significantly impacts galactic properties. Strong feedback results in lower stellar masses, flatter morphologies, and intermediate rotational support, along with prominent central structures and low Sersic indices (n &lt; 2). These findings challenge the applicability of low-redshift diagnostics like Gini-M20 at high redshift. Synthetic JWST observations reveal that pixelation effects may overestimate galaxy sizes, highlighting the complexity of linking IMBH evolution with dwarf galaxy formation and morphology. This study provides new insights into the typical environments of IMBHs in dwarf galaxies and their role in shaping early galactic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06495v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Da Bi, Dominik R. G. Schleicher, Andres Escala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What can we learn from the Nitrogen abundance of High-z galaxies?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present measurements of the gas-phase Oxygen and Nitrogen abundances obtained by applying the direct method to JWST NIRspec $R\sim1000$ spectroscopy for 6 galaxies at redshift greater than 3. Our measurements are based on rest-frame optical Nitrogen [N II]$_{\lambda\lambda6548,6583}$ lines and are complemented by 6 additional objects from the literature at $3\leq z \leq 6$. We find that 9 out of 12 objects have values of log(N/O) that are compatible with those found for low-redshift, metal-poor, dwarf galaxies and for HII regions of more luminous local galaxies. However, 3 out of 12 objects have log(N/O) values that are overabundant compared to what is expected on the basis of their Oxygen abundance. We explore a few standard scenarios to explain the observations and conclude that, within the limited statistics available to us, none of them can be definitely excluded even though we prefer dilution by pristine gas infall in between star formation bursts as this is predicted by simulations to take place as a natural part of bursty star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06517v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo Stiavelli, Takahiro Morishita, Marco Chiaberge, Nicha Leethochawalit, Colin Norman, Massimo Ricotti, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Tommaso Treu, Eros Vanzella, Rosemary F. G. Wyse, Yechi Zhang, Kit Boyett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shocked POststarburst Galaxy Survey. IV. Outflows in Shocked Post-Starburst Galaxies Are Not Responsible For Quenching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shocked POst-starburst Galaxies (SPOGs) exhibit both emission lines suggestive of shock-heated gas and post-starburst-like stellar absorption, resulting in a unique subset for galaxy evolution studies. We have observed 77 galaxies that fulfilled the SPOGs criteria selection using the DeVeny Spectrograph on the Lowell Discovery Telescope. Our long-slit minor axis spectra detect H$\alpha$ and [O III] in some SPOGs out to 6 kpc above the galactic plane. We find extraplanar ionized gas in 31 targets of our sample overall. Using their internal and external kinematics, we argue that 22 galaxies host outflows with ionized gas masses ranging from $10^2 M_{\odot}$ to $10^5 M_{\odot}$. The rest are likely extended diffuse ionized gas. A positive correlation exists between AGN luminosity and the extraplanar gas extent, velocity dispersion, and mass$\unicode{x2013}\unicode{x2013}$suggesting that the AGN may indeed drive the outflows detected in AGN hosts. The low masses of the extraplanar gas suggest that these outflows are not depleting each galaxy's gas reserves. The outflows, therefore, are not likely a significant quenching mechanism in these SPOGs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06621v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad900f</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Antoniu Fodor, Taylor Tomko, Mary Braun, Anne M. Medling, Thomas M. Johnson, Alexander Thompson, Victor D. Johnston, Matthew Newhouse, Yuanze Luo, K. Decker French, Justin A. Otter, Akshat Tripathi, Margaret E. Verrico, Katherine Alatalo, Kate Rowlands, Timothy Heckman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of large-scale structure on the anisotropic quenching of satellites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxies within groups exhibit characteristics different from those of galaxies that reside in regions of average density (the field). Galaxy properties also depend on their location within the host structure and orientation with respect to the central galaxy: galaxies in the inner regions that are aligned to the major axis of the central galaxy tend to be more quenched and redder than galaxies in the outskirts and with random orientation. This phenomenon, called anisotropic satellite galaxy quenching (ASGQ), can be explained in two different ways: invoking either external influences (large-scale distribution of matter) or internal factors (black hole activity of the central galaxy). In this work, we study the impact of filaments in shaping the ASGQ in the local Universe, exploiting the magneto-hydrodynamic (MHD) simulation IllustrisTNG. We separated all surviving satellites into young and old populations depending on their infall times. We show that only young satellites contribute to the observed ASGQ. These satellites preferentially infall along the major axis of the central galaxy, which tends to have the same direction of the filament feeding the groups. We demonstrate that old satellites were quenched inside their hosts and do not exhibit signatures of ASGQ. We show that the ASGQ emerges at the time of the infall of the young satellites and is also visible outside $\rm R_{200}$. In contrast, there is no sign of anisotropic distribution in the inner regions ($R&lt;0.5 R_{200}$). We argue that our results support a scenario in which a large-scale structure is imprinted on the ASGQ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06640v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Zakharova, S. McGee, B. Vulcani, G. De Lucia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inelastic H + H^+_3 Collision rates and their impact in the determination of the excitation temperature of H^+_3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. In dffuse interstellar clouds the excitation temperature derived from the lowest levels of H+3 is systematically lower than that derived from H2. The differences may be attributed to the lack of state-specific formation and destruction rates of H+ 3 needed to thermalize the two species. Aims. In this work, we want to check the role of rotational excitation collisions of H+3 with atomic hydrogen on its excitation temperature. Methods. A time independent close-coupling method is used to calculate the state-to-state rate coefficients, using a very accurate and full dimensional potential energy surface recently developed for H+4. A symmetric top approach is used to describe a frozen H+3 as equilateral triangle. Results. Rotational excitation collision rate coefficients of H+3 with atomic Hydrogen have been derived in a temperature range appropriate to diffuse interstellar conditions up to (J; K; ?) = (7; 6; +) and (J; K; ?) = (6; 4; +) for its ortho and para forms. This allows to have a consistent set of collisional excitation rate coefficients and to improve the previous study where these contributions were speculated. Conclusions. The new state-specific inelastic H+3 + H rate coeffcients yield differences up to 20% in the excitation temperature, and their impact increases with decreasing molecular fraction. We also confirm the impact of chemical state-to-state destruction reactions in the excitation balance of H+3 , and that reactive H + H+3 collisions are also needed to account for possible further ortho to para transitions</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06697v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Felix-Gonzalez, Pablo del Mazo-Sevillano, Alfredo Aguado, Octavio Roncero, Jacques Le Bourlot, Evelyne Roueff, Franck Le Petit, Emeric Bron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Ionization Models and the Shocking Nitrogen Excess at z &gt; 5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The new era of galaxy evolution studies hearkened in by JWST has led to the discovery of z &gt; 5 galaxies exhibiting excess nitrogen with log(N/O)~1 dex or more than expected from log(N/O) vs 12+log(O/H) trends in the local Universe. A variety of novel enrichment pathways have been presented to explain the apparent nitrogen excess, invoking a wide range of processes from very massive stars to stripped binaries to fine-tuned star-formation histories. However, understanding the excitation mechanism responsible for the observed nebular emission is necessary to accurately infer chemical abundances. As of yet, the ionization sources of these galaxies have not been thoroughly explored, with radiative shocks left out of the picture. We present a suite of homogeneous excitation models for star-forming galaxies, active galactic nuclei, and radiative shocks, with which we explore possible explanations for the apparent nitrogen excess. We propose new BPT-style diagnostics to classify galaxies at z &gt; 5, finding that, when combined with O iii] 1660,66 and He ii 1640, N iii] 1747-54 / C iii] 1907,09 best selects shock-dominated galaxies while N iv] 1483,86 / C iii] 1907,09 best distinguishes between active black holes and star forming galaxies. From our diagnostics, we find that slow/intermediate radiative shocks (v = 75-150 km/s) are most consistent with observed UV emission line flux ratios in nitrogen-bright galaxies. Accounting for the effects of shocks can bring nitrogen estimates into better agreement with abundance patterns observed in the local Universe and may be attributable to Wolf Rayet populations actively enriching these galaxies with nitrogen and possibly driving winds responsible for these shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06763v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophia R. Flury, Karla Z. Arellano-C\'ordova, Edward C. Moran, Alaina Einsig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mass Distribution of Stars Stripped in Binaries: The Effect of Metallicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stars stripped of their hydrogen-rich envelopes through binary interaction are thought to be responsible for both hydrogen-poor supernovae and the hard ionizing radiation observed in low-$Z$ galaxies. A population of these stars was recently observed for the first time, but their prevalence remains unknown. In preparation for such measurements, we estimate the mass distribution of hot, stripped stars using a population synthesis code that interpolates over detailed single and binary stellar evolution tracks. We predict that for a constant star-formation rate of $1 \,M_\odot$/yr and regardless of metallicity, a population contains $\sim$30,000 stripped stars with mass $M_{\rm strip}&gt;1M_\odot$ and $\sim$4,000 stripped stars that are sufficiently massive to explode ($M_{\rm strip}&gt;2.6M_\odot$). Below $M_{\rm strip}=5M_\odot$, the distribution is metallicity-independent and can be described by a power law with the exponent $\alpha \sim -2$. At higher masses and lower metallicity ($Z \lesssim 0.002$), the mass distribution exhibits a drop. This originates from the prediction, frequently seen in evolutionary models, that massive low-metallicity stars do not expand substantially until central helium burning or later and therefore cannot form long-lived stripped stars. With weaker line-driven winds at low metallicity, this suggests that neither binary interaction nor wind mass loss can efficiently strip massive stars at low metallicity. As a result, a "helium-star desert" emerges around $M_{\rm strip} =15\, M_\odot$ at $Z=0.002$, covering an increasingly large mass range with decreasing metallicity. We note that these high-mass stars are those that potentially boost a galaxy's He$^+$-ionizing radiation and that participate in the formation of merging black holes. This "helium-star desert" therefore merits further study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05356v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Hovis-Afflerbach, Y. G\"otberg, A. Schootemeijer, J. Klencki, A. L. Strom, B. A. Ludwig, M. R. Drout</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotational Velocities and Radii Estimates of Low-Mass Pre-Main Sequence Stars in NGC 2264</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Investigating the angular momentum evolution of pre-main sequence (PMS) stars provides important insight into the interactions between Sun-like stars and their protoplanetary disks, and the timescales that govern disk dissipation and planet formation. We present projected rotational velocities (v sin i values) of 254 T Tauri stars (TTSs) in the ~3 Myr-old open cluster NGC 2264, measured using high-dispersion spectra from the WIYN 3.5m telescope's Hydra instrument. We combine these with literature values of temperature, rotation period, luminosity, disk classification, and binarity. We find some evidence that Weak-lined TTSs may rotate faster than their Classical TTS counterparts and that stars in binary systems may rotate faster than single stars. We also combine our v sin i measurements with rotation period to estimate the projected stellar radii of our sample stars, and then use a maximum likelihood modeling technique to compare our radii estimates to predicted values from stellar evolution models. We find that starspot-free models tend to underestimate the radii of the PMS stars at the age of the cluster, while models that incorporate starspots are more successful. We also observe a mass dependence in the degree of radius inflation, which may be a result of differences in the birthline location on the HR diagram. Our study of NGC 2264 serves as a pilot study for analysis methods to be applied to four other clusters ranging in age from 1 to 14 Myr, which is the timescale over which protoplanetary disks dissipate and planetary systems begin to form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05401v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad924b</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Laurin M. Gray, Katherine L. Rhode, Catrina M. Hamilton-Drager, Tiffany Picard, Luisa M. Rebull</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Temperature versus Orbital Period relation of AM CVns: Insights from their Donors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We studied the spectral energy distribution (SED) of 22 known AM~CVns with orbital periods ($P_{orb}$) larger than 35~min using multiwavelength public photometric data to estimate the effective temperature of the accreting white dwarf. We find an infrared (IR) excess in all systems when compared to a single blackbody, both when the disk should be extended and when it should be truncated by the accretor's magnetic field. This suggests a dominant contribution from the donor to the IR flux. When fitting two blackbodies, the temperature of the hot component decreases with $P_{orb}$, as expected by evolutionary models. Temperatures for systems with $35&lt;P_{orb}&lt;45~\text{min}$ are consistent with models. Systems with $P_{orb}\gtrsim45~\text{min}$ have higher temperatures than expected. The second blackbody temperature does not correlate with $P_{orb}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05442v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin W. Macrie, Liliana Rivera Sandoval, Yuri Cavecchi, Tin Long Sunny Wong, Manuel Pichardo Marcano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The First JWST View of a 30-Myr-old Protoplanetary Disk Reveals a Late-stage Carbon-rich Phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05535v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a JWST MIRI/MRS spectrum of the inner disk of WISE J044634.16$-$262756.1B (hereafter J0446B), an old ($\sim$34 Myr) M4.5 star but with hints of ongoing accretion. The spectrum is molecule-rich and dominated by hydrocarbons. We detect 14 molecular species (H$_2$, CH$_3$, CH$_4$, C$_2$H$_2$, $^{13}$CCH$_2$, C$_2$H$_4$, C$_2$H$_6$, C$_3$H$_4$, C$_4$H$_2$, C$_6$H$_6$, HCN, HC$_3$N, CO$_2$ and $^{13}$CO$_2$) and 2 atomic lines ([Ne II] and [Ar II]), all observed for the first time in a disk at this age. The detection of spatially unresolved H$_2$ and Ne gas strongly supports that J0446B hosts a long-lived primordial disk, rather than a debris disk. The marginal H$_2$O detection and the high C$_2$H$_2$/CO$_2$ column density ratio indicate that the inner disk of J0446B has a very carbon-rich chemistry, with a gas-phase C/O ratio $\gtrsim$2, consistent with what have been found in most primordial disks around similarly low-mass stars. In the absence of significant outer disk dust substructures, inner disks are expected to first become water-rich due to the rapid inward drift of icy pebbles, and evolve into carbon-rich as outer disk gas flows inward on longer timescales. The faint millimeter emission in such low-mass star disks implies that they may have depleted their outer icy pebble reservoir early and already passed the water-rich phase. Models with pebble drift and volatile transport suggest that maintaining a carbon-rich chemistry for tens of Myr likely requires a slowly evolving disk with $\alpha-$viscosity $\lesssim10^{-4}$. This study represents the first detailed characterization of disk gas at $\sim$30 Myr, strongly motivating further studies into the final stages of disk evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05535v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Long, Ilaria Pascucci, Adrien Houge, Andrea Banzatti, Klaus M. Pontoppidan, Joan Najita, Sebastiaan Krijt, Chengyan Xie, Joe Williams, Gregory J. Herczeg, Sean M. Andrews, Edwin Bergin, Geoffrey A. Blake, Mar\'ia Jos\'e Colmenares, Daniel Harsono, Carlos E. Romero-Mirza, Rixin Li, Cicero X. Lu, Paola Pinilla, David J. Wilner, Miguel Vioque, Ke Zhang, the JDISCS collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Externally irradiated young stars in NGC 3603. A JWST NIRSpec catalogue of pre-main-sequence stars in a massive star formation region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05650v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: NGC 3603 is the optically brightest massive star forming region (SFR) in the Milky Way, representing a small scale starburst region. Studying young stars in regions like this allows us to assess how star and planet formation proceeds in a dense clustered environment with high levels of UV radiation. JWST provides the sensitivity, unbroken wavelength coverage, and spatial resolution required to study individual pre-main-sequence (PMS) stars in distant massive SFRs in detail for the first time. Using the Micro-Shutter Assembly (MSA) onboard the Near InfraRed Spectrograph (NIRSpec), multi-object spectroscopy was performed, yielding 100 stellar spectra. We fit the PMS spectra to derive their photospheric properties, extinction, and NIR veiling. From this, we determined the masses and ages of our sources by placing them on the Hertzsprung-Russel diagram (HRD). Their accretion rates were determined by converting the luminosity of hydrogen emission lines to an accretion luminosity. We have classified 42 as actively accreting. Our sources span a range of masses from 0.5 to 7 $M_{\odot}$. Twelve of these accreting sources have ages consistent with $\ge$ 10 Myrs, with four having ages of $\ge$ 15 Myrs. Their mass accretion rates span 5 orders of magnitude and are systematically higher for a given stellar mass than for a comparative sample taken from low-mass SFRs. We report an environmental relationship between $\dot{M}_{acc}$ and the density of ambient molecular gas as traced by nebular $H_2$ emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05650v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ciar\'an Rogers, Guido de Marchi, Bernhard Brandl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic evidence of magnetospheric accretion for Herbig Ae stars with JWST NIRSpec</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05668v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hydrogen emission lines are routinely used to estimate the mass accretion rate of pre-main-sequence stars. Despite the clear correlation between the accretion luminosity of a star and hydrogen line luminosities, the physical origin of these lines is still unclear, with magnetospheric accretion and magneto-centrifugal winds as the two most often invoked mechanisms. Using a combination of HST photometry and new JWST NIRSpec spectra, we have analysed the SED and emission line spectra of five sources in order to determine their underlying photospheric properties, and to attempt to reveal the physical origin of their hydrogen emission lines. These sources reside in NGC 3603, a Galactic massive star forming region. We have fitted the SED of the five sources employing a Markov Chain Monte Carlo exploration to estimate $T_{eff}$, $R_{*}$, $M_{*}$ and $A(V)$ for each source. We have performed a kinematic analysis across three spectral series of hydrogen lines, Paschen, Brackett, and Pfund, totalling $\ge 15$ lines. The FWHM and optical depth of the spectrally resolved lines have been studied in order to constrain the emission origin. The five sources all have SEDs consistent with young intermediate-mass stars. We have classified three of these sources as Herbig Ae type stars based on their effective temperature. Their hydrogen lines show broad profiles with FWHMs $\ge 200$ km s$^{-1}$. Hydrogen lines with high upper energy levels $n_{up}$ tend to be significantly broader than lines with lower $n_{up}$. The optical depth of the emission lines is also highest for the high velocity component of each line, becoming optically thin in the low velocity component. This is consistent with emission from a magnetospheric accretion flow, and cannot be explained as originating in a magneto-centrifugal wind, or other line emission mechanisms thought to be present in protoplanetary disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05668v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ciar\'an Rogers, Bernhard Brandl, Guido de Marchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Machine Learning Models Systematically Underestimate Extreme Values</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05806v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A persistent challenge in astronomical machine learning is a systematic bias where predictions compress the dynamic range of true values -- high values are consistently predicted too low while low values are predicted too high. Understanding this bias has important consequences for astronomical measurements and our understanding of physical processes in astronomical inference. Through analytical examination of linear regression, we show that this bias arises naturally from measurement uncertainties in input features and persists regardless of training sample size, label accuracy, or parameter distribution. In the univariate case, we demonstrate that attenuation becomes important when the ratio of intrinsic signal range to measurement uncertainty ($\sigma_{\text{range}}/\sigma_x$) is below O(10) -- a regime common in astronomy. We further extend the theoretical framework to multivariate linear regression and demonstrate its implications using stellar spectroscopy as a case study. Even under optimal conditions -- high-resolution APOGEE-like spectra (R=24,000) with high signal-to-noise ratios (SNR=100) and multiple correlated features -- we find percent-level bias. The effect becomes even more severe for modern-day low-resolution surveys like LAMOST and DESI due to the lower SNR and resolution. These findings have broad implications, providing a theoretical framework for understanding and addressing this limitation in astronomical data analysis with machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05806v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan-Sen Ting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLTE abundances of Eu for a sample of metal-poor stars in the Galactic Halo and Metal-poor Disk with 1D and &lt;3D&gt; models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate measurements of europium abundances in cool stars are essential for an enhanced understanding of the r-process mechanisms. We measure the abundance of Eu in solar spectra and a sample of metal-poor stars in the Galactic halo and metal-poor disk, with the metallicities ranging from \GG{$-2.4$} to $-0.5$ dex, using non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (NLTE) line formation. We compare these measurements with Galactic Chemical Evolution (GCE) models to \GG{explore the impact of the NLTE corrections on the contribution of r-process site in Galactic chemical evolution. In this work, we use NLTE line formation, as well as one-dimensional (1D) hydrostatic and spatial averages of 3D hydrodynamical ($&lt;$3D$&gt;$) model atmospheres to measure the abundance of Eu based on both the Eu II 4129 \AA\ and Eu II 6645 \AA\ lines for solar spectra and metal-poor stars. We find that \GG{for Eu II 4129 \AA\ line the NLTE modelling leads to higher (0.04 dex) solar Eu abundance in 1D and higher (0.07 dex) in \GG{$&lt;$3D$&gt;$} NLTE while} NLTE modelling leads to higher (0.01 dex) solar Eu abundance in 1D and lower (0.03 dex) in \GG{$&lt;$3D$&gt;$} NLTE for Eu II 6645 \AA\ line. Although the NLTE corrections for the Eu II $\lambda$ 4129 \AA\ and Eu II $\lambda$ 6645 \AA\ lines are opposite, the discrepancy between the abundances derived from these individual lines reduces after applying NLTE corrections, highlighting the critical role of NLTE abundance determinations. By comparing these measurements with Galactic chemical evolution (GCE) models, we find that the \G{amount of NLTE correction does not require significant change of the parameters for Eu production} in the GCE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06277v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanjun Guo, Nicholas Storm, Maria Bergemann, Jianhui Lian, Sofya Alexeeva, Hongliang Yan, Yangyang Li, Rana Ezzeddine, Gerber Jeffrey, XueFei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of Classical Cepheid's Physical Parameters from NIR Light Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06386v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent space-borne and ground-based observations provide photometric measurements as time series. The effect of interstellar dust extinction in the near-infrared range is only 10% of that measured in the V band. However, the sensitivity of the light curve shape to the physical parameters in the near-infrared is much lower. So, interpreting these types of data sets requires new approaches like the different large-scale surveys, which create similar problems with big data. Using a selected data set, we provide a method for applying routines implemented in R to extract most information of measurements to determine physical parameters, which can also be used in automatic classification schemes and pipeline processing. We made a multivariate classification of 131 Cepheid light curves (LC) in J, H, and K colors, where all the LCs were represented in 20D parameter space in these colors separately. Performing a Principal Component Analysis (PCA), we got an orthogonal coordinate system and squared Euclidean distances between LCs, with 6 significant eigenvalues, reducing the 20-dimension to 6. We also estimated the optimal number of partitions of similar objects and found it to be equal to 7 in each color; their dependence on the period, absolute magnitude, amplitude, and metallicity are also discussed. We computed the Spearman rank correlations, showing that periods and absolute magnitudes correlate with the first three PCs significantly. The first two PC are also found to have a relationship with the amplitude, but the metallicity effects are only marginal. The method shown can be generalized and implemented in unsupervised classification schemes and analysis of mixed and biased samples. The analysis of our Classical Cepheid near-infrared LC sample showed that the J, H, K curves are insufficient for determination of stellar metallicity, with mass being the key factor shaping them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06386v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lajos G. Bal\'azs, G\'abor B. Kov\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White Dwarf Stars in the Big Data Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06516v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: White dwarf stars are the most common endpoint of stellar evolution. Therefore, these old, numerous and compact objects provide valuable information on the late stages of stellar evolution, the physics of dense plasma and the structure and evolution of our Galaxy. The ESA Gaia space mission has revolutionized this research field, providing parallaxes and multi-band photometry for nearly 360,000 white dwarfs. Furthermore, this data, combined with spectroscopical and spectropolarimetric observations, have provided new information on their chemical abundances and magnetic fields. This large data set has raised new questions on the nature of white dwarfs, boosting our theoretical efforts for understanding the physics that governs their evolution and for improving the statistical analysis of their collective properties. In this article, I summarize the current state of our understanding of the collective properties of white dwarfs, based of detailed theoretical models and population synthesis studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06516v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/asna.20240118</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astronomische Nachrichten published by Wiley-VCH GmbH. Proceedings of the XMM-Newton 2024 Science Workshop "The X-ray mysteries of neutron stars and white dwarfs". Published on 28 November 2024 (open access)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maria Camisassa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating a stellar contact binary merger -- II. Obtaining a light curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06583v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Luminous Red Novae (LRNe) are enigmatic transient events distinguished by a rapid rise in luminosity, a plateau in luminosity, and spectra which become redder with time. The best-observed system before, during, and after the outburst is V1309 Sco. We model a candidate V1309 Sco progenitor binary configuration (1.52+0.16Msun) using the Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics (SPH) code StarSmasher with a modified energy equation that implements flux-limited emission-diffusion radiative transport in a Lagrangian case. We developed an imaging technique allowing us to capture the flux an observer would measure. In this novel method, the outgoing radiative flux of each SPH particle in the observer's direction is attenuated by other particles along the path to the observer. We investigated how the light curve is affected in various models: with and without dust formation; constant, Planck, or Rosseland mean opacities; different donor star sizes; different companion star masses and types; radiative heating included in our modified energy equation; and different SPH simulation resolutions. The resulting evolution in bolometric luminosity and spectrum peak temperature is in good agreement with V1309 Sco observations. Our simulations rule out V1309 Sco models that do not assume dust formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06583v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roger Hatfull, Natalia Ivanova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting the disk and the jet of a massive (proto)star. An ALMA view of IRAS20126+4104</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06589v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate one of the best examples of disk+jet systems around an early B-type (proto)star, IRAS20126+4104. This object is an ideal target for resolution of its disk and the determination of its physical and kinematical structure. Despite its high declination, it has been possible to perform successful observations with the Atacama Large Millimeter and submillimeter Array at 1.4 mm in the continuum emission and a number of molecular tracers. The new data allow us to improve on previous similar observations and confirm the existence of a Keplerian accretion disk around a ~12 Msun (proto)star. From methyl cyanide, we derived the rotation temperature and column density as a function of disk radius. We also obtained a map of the same quantities for the jet using the ratio between two lines of formaldehyde. We use two simple models of the jet and the disk to estimate the basic geometrical and kinematical parameters of the two. We conclude that the disk is stable at all radii. We also estimate an accretion rate of ~0.001 Msun/yr. Our analysis confirms that the jet from IRAS20126+4104 is highly collimated, lies close to the plane of the sky, and expands with velocity increasing with distance. As expected, the gas temperature and column density peak in the bow shock. The disk is undergoing Keplerian rotation but a non-negligible radial velocity component is also present that is equal to ~40% of the rotational component. The disk is slightly inclined with respect to the line of sight and has a dusty envelope that absorbs the emission from the disk surface. This causes a slight distortion of the disk structure observed in high-density tracers. We also reveal a significant deviation from axial symmetry in the SW part of the disk, which might be caused by either tidal interaction with a nearby, lower-mass companion or interaction with the outflowing gas of the jet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06589v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Cesaroni, D. Galli, M. Padovani, V. M. Rivilla, A. Sanchez-Monge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NGC 4993, the shell galaxy host of GW170817: constraints on the recent galactic merger</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1801.01493</link>
      <description>arXiv:1801.01493v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: NGC 4993 is the shell galaxy host of the GRB170817A short gamma-ray burst and the GW170817 gravitational-wave event produced during a binary-neutron-star coalescence. The galaxy shows signs, including the stellar shells, that it has recently accreted a smaller, late-type galaxy. The accreted galaxy might be the original host of the binary neutron star. We measured the positions of the stellar shells of NGC 4993 in an HST/ACS archival image and use the shell positions to constrain the time of the galactic merger. According to the analytical model of the evolution of the shell structure in the expected gravitational potential of NGC 4993, the galactic merger happened at least 200 Myr ago, with a probable time roughly around 400 Myr and the estimates higher than 600 Myr being improbable. This constitutes the lower limit on the age of the binary neutron star, because the host galaxy was probably quenched even before the galactic merger, and the merger has likely shut down the star formation in the accreted galaxy. We roughly estimate the probability that the binary neutron star originates in the accreted galaxy to be around 30%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1801.01493v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/201935219</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 634, A73 (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ivana Ebrov\'a, Michal B\'ilek, Mustafa K. Y{\i}ld{\i}z, Ji\v{r}\'i Eli\'a\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Quenching of Galaxies at Cosmic Noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.03747v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The existence of massive quiescent galaxies at high redshift seems to require rapid quenching, but it is unclear whether all quiescent galaxies have gone through this phase and what physical mechanisms are involved. To study rapid quenching, we use rest-frame colors to select 12 young quiescent galaxies at $z \sim 1.5$. From spectral energy distribution fitting, we find that they all experienced intense starbursts prior to rapid quenching. We confirm this with deep Magellan/FIRE spectroscopic observations for a subset of seven galaxies. Broad emission lines are detected for two galaxies and are most likely caused by AGN activity. The other five galaxies do not show any emission features, suggesting that gas has already been removed or depleted. Most of the rapidly quenched galaxies are more compact than normal quiescent galaxies, providing evidence for a central starburst in the recent past. We estimate an average transition time of $300\,\rm Myr$ for the rapid quenching phase. Approximately $4\%$ of quiescent galaxies at $z=1.5$ have gone through rapid quenching; this fraction increases to $23\%$ at $z=2.2$. We identify analogs in the TNG100 simulation and find that rapid quenching for these galaxies is driven by AGN, and for half of the cases, gas-rich major mergers seem to trigger the starburst. We conclude that these massive quiescent galaxies are not just rapidly quenched but also rapidly formed through a major starburst. We speculate that mergers drive gas inflow towards the central regions and grow supermassive black holes, leading to rapid quenching by AGN feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.03747v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/acd54a</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Minjung Park, Sirio Belli, Charlie Conroy, Sandro Tacchella, Joel Leja, Sam E. Cutler, Benjamin D. Johnson, Erica J. Nelson, Razieh Emami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling biases from constant stellar mass-to-light ratio assumption in galaxy dynamics and strong lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07442v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A constant stellar mass-to-light ratio $M_\star/L$ has been widely-used in studies of galaxy dynamics and strong lensing, which aim at disentangling the mass distributions of dark matter and baryons. However, systematic biases arising from constant $M_\star/L$ assumption have not been fully quantified. In this work, we take massive early-type galaxies from the TNG100 simulation to investigate possible systematic biases in the inferences due to a constant $M_\star/L$ assumption. We construct two-component matter density models, where one component describes the dark matter, the other for the stars, which is made to follow the light profile by assuming a constant $M_\star/L$. We fit the two-component model directly to the {\it total} matter density distributions of simulated galaxies to eliminate systematics coming from other model assumptions. We find that galaxies generally have more centrally-concentrated stellar mass profile than their light distribution. Given the light profiles adopted (i.e., single- and double-S{\'e}rsic profiles), the assumption of a constant $M_\star/L$ would artificially break the model degeneracy between baryons and dark matter {\it for non-constant} $M_\star/L$ systems. For such systems, without knowing the true $M_{\star}/L$ but assuming a constant ratio, the two-component modeling procedure tend to generally overestimate $M_{\star}/L$ by $30\%-50\%$, and underestimate the central dark matter fraction $f_{\rm DM}$ by $\sim 20\%$ on average.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07442v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Liang, Dandan Xu, Dominique Sluse, Alessandro Sonnenfeld, Yiping Shu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dormant, overmassive black hole in the early Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03872v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent observations have found a large number of supermassive black holes already in place in the first few hundred million years after Big Bang. The channels of formation and growth of these early, massive black holes are not clear, with scenarios ranging from heavy seeds to light seeds experiencing bursts of high accretion rate. Here we present the detection, from the JADES survey, of broad Halpha emission in a galaxy at z=6.68, which traces a black hole with mass of ~ 4 * 10^8 Msun and accreting at a rate of only 0.02 times the Eddington limit. The host galaxy has low star formation rate (~ 1 Msun/yr, a factor of 3 below the star forming main sequence). The black hole to stellar mass ratio is ~ 0.4, i.e. about 1,000 times above the local relation, while the system is closer to the local relations in terms of dynamical mass and velocity dispersion of the host galaxy. This object is most likely the tip of the iceberg of a much larger population of dormant black holes around the epoch of reionisation. Its properties are consistent with scenarios in which short bursts of super-Eddington accretion have resulted in black hole overgrowth and massive gas expulsion from the accretion disk; in between bursts, black holes spend most of their life in a dormant state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03872v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignas Juod\v{z}balis, Roberto Maiolino, William M. Baker, Sandro Tacchella, Jan Scholtz, Francesco D'Eugenio, Raffaella Schneider, Alessandro Trinca, Rosa Valiante, Christa DeCoursey, Mirko Curti, Stefano Carniani, Jacopo Chevallard, Anna de Graaff, Santiago Arribas, Jake S. Bennett, Martin A. Bourne, Andrew J. Bunker, St\'ephane Charlot, Brian Jiang, Sophie Koudmani, Michele Perna, Brant Robertson, Debora Sijacki, Hannah \"Ubler, Christina C. Williams, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the accuracy of the star formation rate measurements by direct star count in molecular clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00095v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Star formation estimates based on the counting of YSOs is commonly applied to nearby star-forming regions in the Galaxy. With this method, the SFRs are measured using the counts of YSOs in a particular protostellar Class, a typical protostellar mass, and the lifetime associated with this Class. However, the assumptions underlying the validity of the method such as that of a constant star formation history (SFH) and whether the method is valid for all protostellar Classes has never been fully tested. In this work, we use Monte Carlo models to test the validity of the method. We build synthetic clusters in which stars form at times that are randomly drawn from a specified SFH. The latter is either constant or time-dependent with a burst like behavior. The masses of the protostars are randomly drawn from an IMF which can be either similar to that of the Milky Way field or be variable . For each star in every cluster, the lifetimes associated with the different protostellar classes are also randomly drawn from Gaussian distribution functions centered around their most likely value as suggested by the observations. We find that only the SFR derived using the Class 0 population can reproduce the true SFR at all epochs, and this is true irrespective of the shape of the SFH. For a constant SFH, the SFR derived using the more evolved populations of protostars (Classes I, F, II, and III) reproduce the real SFR only at later epochs which correspond to epochs at which their numbers have reached a steady state. For a time-dependent burst-like SFH, all SFR estimates based on the number counts of the evolved populations fail to reproduce the true SFR. We also show how the offsets between Class I and Class II based SFRs and the true SFR plotted as a function of the number ratios of Class I and Class II versus Class III YSOs can be used in order to constrain the SFH of observed molecular clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00095v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sami Dib, Jian Wen Zhou, S\'ebastien Comer\'on, Luis E. Gardu\~no, Valery V. Kravtsov, Paul C. Clark, Guang-Xing Li, Maritza A. Lara-L\'opez, Tie Liu, Mohsen Shadmehri, James R. Doughty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Small Sizes and High Implied Densities of `Little Red Dots' with Balmer Breaks Could Explain Their Broad Emission Lines Without an AGN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07745v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Early JWST studies found an apparent population of massive, compact galaxies at redshifts $z\gtrsim7$. Recently three of these galaxies were shown to have prominent Balmer breaks, demonstrating that their light at $\lambda_{\rm rest} \sim 3500$ $\r{A}$ is dominated by a stellar population that is relatively old ($\sim$200 Myr). All three also have broad H$\beta$ emission with $\sigma &gt; 1000 \,\rm km s^{-1}$, a common feature of such `little red dots'. From S\'ersic profile fits to the NIRCam images in F200W we find that the stellar light of galaxies is extremely compact: the galaxies have half-light radii of $r_{\rm e}\sim$ 100 pc, in the regime of ultra compact dwarfs in the nearby Universe. Their masses are uncertain, as they depend on the contribution of possible light from an AGN to the flux at $\lambda_{\rm rest}&gt;5000$ $\r{A}$. If the AGN contribution is low beyond the Balmer break region, the masses are $M_* \sim 10^{10}-10^{11}\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$, and the central densities are higher than those of any other known galaxy population by an order of magnitude. Interestingly, the implied velocity dispersions of $\sim$1500 kms$^{-1}$ are in very good agreement with the measured H$\beta$ line widths. We suggest that some of the broad lines in `little red dots' are not due to AGNs but simply reflect the kinematics of the galaxies, and speculate that the galaxies are observed in a short-lived phase where the central densities are much higher than at later times. We stress, however, that the canonical interpretation of AGNs causing the broad H$\beta$ lines also remains viable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07745v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josephine F. W. Baggen, Pieter van Dokkum, Gabriel Brammer, Anna de Graaff, Marijn Franx, Jenny Greene, Ivo Labb\'e, Joel Leja, Michael V. Maseda, Erica J. Nelson, Hans-Walter Rix, Bingjie Wang, Andrea Weibel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrostatic mass of galaxy clusters within some theories of gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14280v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The mass of galaxy clusters (GCs) can be determined by calculating the hydrostatic equilibrium equation. In this work, we derive the hydrostatic mass of GCs within Eddington-inspired Born-Infeld (EiBI) theory, beyond Horndeski gravity (BHG), and modified emergent Newtonian gravity (MENG) with generalized uncertainty principle (GUP) correction. We apply the formulations on the masses of 10 GCs. We compare our results with the Newtonian mass of GCs. Within a regime, we get an insight that all formulations could match the Newtonian mass. Thus, the impact of the modified theories of gravity used in this work can be neglected in this regime. The noteworthy impact starts if we set $\kappa=5\times10^{40}$ m$^2$ for EiBI theory, $\Upsilon=-0.1655\times10^{69}$ for BHG, and $\beta_0=-1.656\times10^{110}$ for MENG. We also compare our results from EiBI theory and BHG with the baryonic masses $M_{bar}$ of the GCs. A better linear fit is achieved by EiBI theory with $\kappa=5.80\times10^{40}$ m$^2$, which gives the slope $\mathcal{M}$ of $0.126\pm0.086$. This value is closer to unity than the one of BHG. This leads us to the fact that EiBI theory is more effective than BHG in alleviating the mass discrepancy between hydrostatic mass and baryonic mass in GCs. Nevertheless, neither EiBI theory nor BHG completely addresses the mass discrepancy problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14280v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feri Apryandi, M. Lawrence Pattersons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Quenched, Faint Dwarf Galaxies in the Direction of NGC 300: New Probes of Reionization and Internal Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16345v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the discovery of three faint and ultra-faint dwarf galaxies -- Sculptor A, Sculptor B and Sculptor C -- in the direction of NGC 300 (D=2.0 Mpc), a Large Magellanic Cloud-mass galaxy. Deep ground-based imaging with Gemini/GMOS resolves all three dwarf galaxies into stars, each displaying a red giant branch indicative of an old, metal-poor stellar population. No young stars or HI gas are apparent, and the lack of a GALEX UV detection suggests that all three systems are quenched. Sculptor C (D=2.04$^{+0.10}_{-0.13}$ Mpc; $M_V$=$-$9.1$\pm$0.1 mag or $L_V$=(3.7$^{+0.4}_{-0.3}$)$\times$10$^5$ $L_{\odot}$) is consistent with being a satellite of NGC 300. Sculptor A (D=1.35$^{+0.22}_{-0.08}$ Mpc; $M_V$=$-$6.9$\pm$0.3 mag or $L_V$=(5$^{+1}_{-1}$)$\times$10$^4$ $L_{\odot}$) is likely in the foreground of NGC 300 and at the extreme edge of the Local Group, analogous to the recently discovered ultra-faint Tucana B in terms of its physical properties and environment. Sculptor B (D=2.48$^{+0.21}_{-0.24}$ Mpc; $M_V$=$-$8.1$\pm$0.3 mag or $L_V$=(1.5$^{+0.5}_{-0.4}$)$\times$10$^5$ $L_{\odot}$) is likely in the background, but future distance measurements are necessary to solidify this statement. It is also of interest due to its quiescent state and low stellar mass. Both Sculptor A and B are $\gtrsim$2-4 $r_{vir}$ from NGC 300 itself. The discovery of three dwarf galaxies in isolated or low-density environments offers an opportunity to study the varying effects of ram pressure stripping, reionization and internal feedback in influencing the star formation history of the faintest stellar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16345v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. J. Sand, B. Mutlu-Pakdil, M. G. Jones, A. Karunakaran, J. E. Andrews, P. Bennet, D. Crnojevic, G. Donatiello, A. Drlica-Wagner, C. Fielder, D. Martinez-Delgado, C. E. Martinez-Vazquez, K. Spekkens, A. Doliva-Dolinsky, L. C. Hunter, J. L. Carlin, W. Cerny, T. N. Hai, K. B. W McQuinn, A. B. Pace, A. Smercina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the quiescent galaxy population in the Spiderweb protocluster at z=2.16 with deep HST/WFC3 slitless spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the HST WFC3 G141 grism slitless spectroscopy observation of the core region of the Spiderweb protocluster at $z=2.16$. We analyzed the spectra of all objects in a $\sim 2 \times 2 \text{ arcmin}^2$ field of view and identified 40 protocluster members, recovering 19 previously identified H$\alpha$-emitters in addition to revealing 21 new members. The spectra allowed us to identify 11 galaxies with quiescent spectra. Three galaxies with quiescent spectra are possibly still star-forming according to SED fitting, indicating a possible left-over or dust-obscured star formation. We estimate a quiescent fraction of $\sim 50\%$ for $M_\star &gt; 10^{11} M_\odot$. About half of the quiescent galaxies possibly host AGN, hinting at AGN's key role in quenching galaxies in the protocluster environment. These quiescent galaxies have relatively more compact and concentrated light profiles than the star-forming members, but they are not yet as bulge-dominated as local ellipticals. These results are consistent with previous studies that indicate the Spiderweb protocluster is in the maturing stage, with a red sequence that has begun forming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16643v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad8dcf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 2024, Volume 977, Number 1, 58</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abdurrahman Naufal, Yusei Koyama, Chiara D'Eugenio, Helmut Dannerbauer, Rhythm Shimakawa, Jose Manuel P\'erez-Mart\'inez, Tadayuki Kodama, Yuheng Zhang, Kazuki Daikuhara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the star formation rate surface density main sequence. Insights from a semi-analytic simulation since $z = 12$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent high-redshift ($z&gt;4$) spatially resolved observations with the James Webb Space Telesescope have shown the evolution of the star formation rate (SFR) surface density ($\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$) and its main sequence in the $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$-$M_*$ diagram ($\Sigma_{\rm SFR}{\rm MS}$). The $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}{\rm MS}$\ is already observed at cosmic morning ($z\sim7.5$). The use of $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$\ is physically motivated because it is normalized by the area in which the star formation occurs, and this indirectly considers the gas density. The $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$-$M_*$ diagram has been shown to complement the widely used (specific) SFR-$M_*$, particularly when selecting passive galaxies. We establish the $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$\ evolution since $z=12$ in the framework of the L-Galaxies2020 semi-analytical model (SAM), and we interpret recent observations. We estimated $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$(-$M_*$) and the cosmic star formation rate density (CSFRD) for the simulated galaxy population and for the subsamples, which were divided into stellar mass bins in the given redshift. The simulated $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$\ decreases by $\sim3.5$ dex from $z=12$ to $z=0$. We show that galaxies with different stellar masses have different paths of $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}$\ evolution. We find that $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}{\rm MS}$\ is already observed at $z\sim11$. The simulated $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}{\rm MS}$\ agrees with the observed one at $z=0, 1, 2, 5$, and $7.5$ and with individual galaxies at $z&gt;10$. We show that the highest $\Sigma_{\rm SFR}{\rm MS}$\ slope of $0.709\pm0.005$ is at $z\sim3$ and decreases to $\sim0.085\pm0.003$ at $z=0$. This is mostly driven by a rapid decrease in SFR with an additional size increase for the most massive galaxies in this redshift range. This coincides with the dominance of the most massive galaxies in the CSFRD from the SAM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00188v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Nadolny, Micha{\l} J. Micha{\l}owski, Massimiliano Parente, Mart\'in Solar, Przemys{\l}aw Nowaczyk, Oleh Ryzhov, Aleksandra Le\'sniewska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular gas and dust properties in $z&gt;7$ quasar hosts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02688v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Observational campaigns hunting the elusive reservoirs of cold gas in the host galaxies of quasars at the Epoch of Reionization (EoR) are crucial to study the formation and evolution of the first massive systems at early epochs.
  We present new Northern Extended Millimetre Array (NOEMA) observations tracing CO(6--5), CO(7--6) emission lines, and the underlying continuum in five of the eight quasars at redshift $z&gt;7$ known to date, thus completing the survey of the cold molecular gas reservoir in the host galaxies of the first quasars.
  Combining NOEMA observations with archival Atacama Large Millimeter Array (ALMA) data available, we model the far-infrared spectral energy distribution with a modified blackbody to measure dust properties and star formation rates.
  We use CO and [CII] lines to derive molecular gas masses, which we compare with results from semi-analytical models and observations of galaxies at different epochs.
  No statistically significant detection of CO emission lines was reported for the five quasars in this sample, resulting in a relatively low amount of cold molecular gas in the host when compared with galaxies at later epochs.
  Nonetheless, gas-to-dust ratios are consistent with the local value, suggesting that the scaling relation between dust and cold gas holds up to $z&gt;7$.
  Quasars at the EoR show star formation efficiencies which are among the highest observed so far, but comparable with that observed in luminous quasar at Cosmic Noon and that predicted for the brightest ($L_{bol}&gt;3\times10^{46}$ erg s$^{-1}$) quasar objects drawn from the semi-analytical model GAEA.
  Quasar host galaxies at the EoR are undergoing an intense phase of star formation, which suggests a strong coupling between the luminous phase of the quasar and the rapid growth of the host.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02688v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Salvestrini, Chiara Feruglio, Roberta Tripodi, Fabio Fontanot, Manuela Bischetti, Gabriella De Lucia, Fabrizio Fiore, Michaela Hirschmann, Umberto Maio, Enrico Piconcelli, Ivano Saccheo, Alessia Tortosa, Rosa Valiante, Lizhi Xie, Luca Zappacosta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BEACON: JWST NIRCam Pure-parallel Imaging Survey. I. Survey Design and Initial Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04211v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the Bias-free Extragalactic Analysis for Cosmic Origins with NIRCam (BEACON) survey, a JWST Cycle2 program allocated up to 600 pure-parallel hours of observations. BEACON explores high-latitude areas of the sky with JWST/NIRCam over $\sim100$ independent sightlines, totaling $\sim0.3$deg$^2$, reaching a median F444W depth of $\approx28.2$AB mag (5$\sigma$). Based on existing JWST observations in legacy fields, we estimate that BEACON will photometrically identify 25--150 galaxies at $z&gt;10$ and 500--1000 at $z\sim7$--10 uniquely enabled by an efficient multiple filter configuration spanning $0.9$--5.0$\mu$m. The expected sample size of $z&gt;10$ galaxies will allow us to obtain robust number density estimates and to discriminate between different models of early star formation. In this paper, we present an overview of the survey design and initial results using the first 19 fields. We present 129 galaxy candidates at $z&gt;7$ identified in those fields, including 11 galaxies at $z&gt;10$ and several UV-luminous ($M_{\rm UV}&lt;-21$mag) galaxies at $z\sim8$. The number densities of $z&lt;13$ galaxies inferred from the initial fields are overall consistent with those in the literature. Despite reaching a considerably large volume ($\sim10^5$Mpc$^3$), however, we find no galaxy candidates at $z&gt;13$, providing us with a complimentary insight into early galaxy evolution with minimal cosmic variance. We publish imaging and catalog data products for these initial fields. Upon survey completion, all BEACON data will be coherently processed and distributed to the community along with catalogs for redshift and other physical quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04211v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Morishita, Charlotte A. Mason, Kimi C. Kreilgaard, Michele Trenti, Tommaso Treu, Benedetta Vulcani, Yechi Zhang,  Abdurro'uf, Anahita Alavi, Hakim Atek, Yannick Bahe, Marusa Bradac, Larry D. Bradley, Andrew J. Bunker, Dan Coe, James Colbert, Viola Gelli, Matthew J. Hayes, Tucker Jones, Tadayuki Kodama, Nicha Leethochawalit, Zhaoran Liu, Matthew A. Malkan, Vihang Mehta, Benjamin Metha, Andrew B. Newman, Marc Rafelski, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Michael J. Rutkowski, Claudia Scarlata, Massimo Stiavelli, Ryo A. Sutanto, Kosuke Takahashi, Harry I. Teplitz, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting the diversity of modeling methods to probe systematic biases in strong lensing analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08484v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Challenges inherent to high-resolution and high signal-to-noise data as well as model degeneracies can cause systematic biases in analyses of strong lens systems. In the past decade, the number of lens modeling methods has significantly increased, from purely analytical methods, to pixelated and non-parametric ones, or ones based on deep learning. We embraced this diversity by selecting different software packages and use them to blindly model independently simulated Hubble Space Telescope (HST) imaging data. To overcome the difficulties arising from using different codes and conventions, we used the COde-independent Organized LEns STandard (COOLEST) to store, compare, and release all models in a self-consistent and human-readable manner. From an ensemble of six modeling methods, we studied the recovery of the lens potential parameters and properties of the reconstructed source. We find that, overall, both lens and source properties are recovered reasonably well, but systematic biases arise in all methods. Interestingly, we do not observe that a single method is significantly more accurate than others, and the amount of bias largely depends on the specific lens or source property of interest. By combining posterior distributions from individual methods using equal weights, the maximal systematic biases on lens model parameters inferred from individual models are reduced by a factor of 5.4 on average. We investigated a selection of modeling effects that partly explain the observed biases, such as the cuspy nature of the background source and the accuracy of the point spread function. This work introduces, for the first time, a generic framework to compare and ease the combination of models obtained from different codes and methods, which will be key to retain accuracy in future strong lensing analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08484v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451095</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 692, A87 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Galan, G. Vernardos, Q. Minor, D. Sluse, L. Van de Vyvere, M. Gomer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Formation of Planets in the Milky Way's Thick Disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09319v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Exoplanet demographic surveys have revealed that close-in (${\lesssim}$1 au) small planets orbiting stars in the Milky Way's thick disk are ${\sim}50\%$ less abundant than those orbiting stars in the Galactic thin disk. One key difference between the two stellar populations is the time at which they emerged: thick disk stars are the likely product of cosmic noon (redshift $z {\sim}2$), an era characterized by high star formation rate, massive and dense molecular clouds, and strong supersonic turbulence. Solving for the background radiation field in these early star-forming regions, we demonstrate that protoplanetary disks at cosmic noon experienced radiation fields up to ${\sim}7$ orders of magnitude more intense than in solar neighborhood conditions. Coupling the radiation field to a one-dimensional protoplanetary disk evolution model, we find that external UV photoevaporation destroys protoplanetary disks in just ${\sim}$0.2--0.5 Myr, limiting the timescale over which planets can assemble. Disk temperatures exceed the sublimation temperatures of common volatile species for ${\gtrsim}$Myr timescales, predicting more spatial homogeneity in gas chemical composition. Our calculations imply that the deficit in planet occurrence around thick disk stars should be even more pronounced for giant planets, particularly those at wide orbital separations, predicting a higher rocky-to-giant planet ratio in the Galactic thick disk vs.~thin disk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09319v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Hallatt, Eve J. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blue straggler stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10314v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Blue straggler stars are unique main-sequence stars that appear more luminous, hotter, and therefore younger, than their coeval counterparts. In star clusters, these stars are located above the cluster turn-off in the Hertzsprung-Russell diagram or color-magnitude diagram. First identified in the 1950s, these stars are found across diverse environments, from sparse galactic fields to dense star clusters. They are crucial for understanding stellar and binary evolution and star cluster dynamics. Despite extensive research, many challenges concerning their properties and origin mechanisms remain unresolved. This chapter delves into the properties and origins of blue stragglers, examining how theoretical tools are employed to study them and the implications of each proposed formation mechanism. We assess how contemporary observational data either support or challenge these theoretical predictions. Continued theoretical and observational efforts are essential for advancing our understanding of these enigmatic stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10314v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Wang, Taeho Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
