<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 19:08:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of optically emitting circumgalactic nebulae around the majority of UV-luminous quasars at intermediate redshift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the discovery of large ionized, [O II] emitting circumgalactic nebulae around the majority of thirty UV luminous quasars at $z=0.4-1.4$ observed with deep, wide-field integral field spectroscopy (IFS) with the Multi-Unit Spectroscopy Explorer (MUSE) by the Cosmic Ultraviolet Baryon Survey (CUBS) and MUSE Quasar Blind Emitters Survey (MUSEQuBES). Among the 30 quasars, seven (23%) exhibit [O II] emitting nebulae with major axis sizes greater than 100 kpc, twenty greater than 50 kpc (67%), and 27 (90%) greater than 20 kpc. Such large, optically emitting nebulae indicate that cool, dense, and metal-enriched circumgalactic gas is common in the halos of luminous quasars at intermediate redshift. Several of the largest nebulae exhibit morphologies that suggest interaction-related origins. We detect no correlation between the sizes and cosmological dimming corrected surface brightnesses of the nebulae and quasar redshift, luminosity, black hole mass, or radio-loudness, but find a tentative correlation between the nebulae and rest-frame [O II] equivalent width in the quasar spectra. This potential trend suggests a relationship between ISM content and gas reservoirs on CGM scales. The [O II]-emitting nebulae around the $z\approx1$ quasars are smaller and less common than Ly$\alpha$ nebulae around $z\approx3$ quasars. These smaller sizes can be explained if the outer regions of the Ly$\alpha$ halos arise from scattering in more neutral gas, by evolution in the cool CGM content of quasar host halos, by lower-than-expected metallicities on $\gtrsim50$ kpc scales around $z\approx1$ quasars, or by changes in quasar episodic lifetimes between $z=3$ and $1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00088v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sean D. Johnson, Zhuoqi Will Liu, Jennifer I. Li, Joop Schaye, Jenny E. Greene, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Gwen C. Rudie, Zhijie Qu, Hsiao-Wen Chen, Marc Rafelski, Sowgat Muzahid, Mandy C. Chen, Wolfram Kollatschny, Nishant Mishra, Michael Rauch, Fakhri S. Zahedy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating emission line galaxies for the next generation of large-scale structure surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate emission line galaxies across cosmic time by combining the modified L-Galaxies semi-analytical galaxy formation model with the JiuTian cosmological simulation. We improve the tidal disruption model of satellite galaxies in L-Galaxies to address the time dependence problem. We utilise the public code CLOUDY to compute emission line ratios for a grid of HII region models. The emission line models assume the same initial mass function as that used to generate the spectral energy distribution of semi-analytical galaxies, ensuring a coherent treatment for modelling the full galaxy spectrum. By incorporating these emission line ratios with galaxy properties, we reproduce observed luminosity functions for H$\alpha$, H$\beta$, [OII], and [OIII] in the local Universe and at high redshifts. We also find good agreement between model predictions and observations for auto-correlation and cross-correlation functions of [OII]-selected galaxies, as well as their luminosity dependence. The bias of emission line galaxies depends on both luminosity and redshift. At lower redshifts, it remains constant with increasing luminosity up to around $\sim 10^{42.5}\rm \, erg\,s^{-1}$ and then rises steeply for higher luminosities. The transition luminosity increases with redshift and becomes insignificant above $z$=1.5. Generally, galaxy bias shows an increasing trend with redshift. However, for luminous galaxies, the bias is higher at low redshifts, as the strong luminosity dependence observed at low redshifts diminishes at higher redshifts. We provide a fitting formula for the bias of emission line galaxies as a function of luminosity and redshift, which can be utilised for large-scale structure studies with future galaxy surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00092v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxiang Pei, Qi Guo, Ming Li, Qiao Wang, Jiaxin Han, Jia Hu, Tong Su, Liang Gao, Jie Wang, Yu Luo, Chengliang Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Growth of Supermassive Black Holes as a Function of Galaxy Stellar Mass and Redshift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growth of supermassive black holes is strongly linked to their galaxies. It has been shown that the population mean black-hole accretion rate ($\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$) primarily correlates with the galaxy stellar mass ($M_\star$) and redshift for the general galaxy population. This work aims to provide the best measurements of $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$ as a function of $M_\star$ and redshift over ranges of $10^{9.5}&lt;M_\star&lt;10^{12}~M_\odot$ and $z&lt;4$. We compile an unprecedentedly large sample with eight thousand active galactic nuclei (AGNs) and 1.3 million normal galaxies from nine high-quality survey fields following a wedding-cake design. We further develop a semiparametric Bayesian method that can reasonably estimate $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$ and the corresponding uncertainties, even for sparsely populated regions in the parameter space. $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$ is constrained by X-ray surveys sampling the AGN accretion power and UV-to-infrared multi-wavelength surveys sampling the galaxy population. Our results can independently predict the X-ray luminosity function (XLF) from the galaxy stellar mass function (SMF), and the prediction is consistent with the observed XLF. We also try adding external constraints from the observed SMF and XLF. We further measure $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$ for star-forming and quiescent galaxies and show that star-forming $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$ is generally larger than or at least comparable to the quiescent $\overline{\mathrm{BHAR}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00097v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad27cc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ, 964, 183 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fan Zou, Zhibo Yu, W. N. Brandt, Hyungsuk Tak, Guang Yang, Qingling Ni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It's a Breeze: The Circumgalactic Medium of a Dwarf Galaxy is Easy to Strip</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00129v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The circumgalactic medium (CGM) of star-forming dwarf galaxies plays a key role in regulating the galactic baryonic cycle. We investigate how susceptible the CGM of dwarf satellite galaxies is to ram pressure stripping (RPS) in Milky Way-like environments. In a suite of hydrodynamical wind tunnel simulations, we model an intermediate-mass dwarf satellite galaxy ($M_{*} = 10^{7.2}~M_{\odot}$) with a multiphase interstellar medium (ISM; $M_{\rm ISM} = 10^{7.9}~M_{\odot}$) and CGM ($M_{\rm CGM,vir} = 10^{8.5}~M_{\odot}$) along two first-infall orbits to more than 500 Myr past pericenter of a Milky Way-like host. The spatial resolution is $\sim$79 pc in the star-forming ISM and $316-632$ pc in the CGM. Our simulations show that the dwarf satellite CGM removal is fast and effective: more than $95\%$ of the CGM mass is ram-pressure-stripped within a few hundred Myrs, even under a weak ram pressure orbit where the ISM stripping is negligible. The conditions for CGM survival are consistent with the analytical halo gas stripping predictions in McCarthy et al. (2008). We also find that including the satellite CGM does not effectively shield its galaxy, and therefore the ISM stripping rate is unaffected. Our results imply that a dwarf galaxy CGM is unlikely to be detected in satellite galaxies; and that the star formation of gaseous dwarf satellites is likely devoid of replenishment from a CGM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00129v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyao Zhu, Stephanie Tonnesen, Greg L. Bryan, Mary E. Putman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational lensing by an ellipsoidal Navarro--Frenk--White dark-matter halo: an analytic solution and its properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The analysis of gravitational lensing by galaxies and galaxy clusters typically relies on ellipsoidal lens models to describe the deflection of light by the involved dark-matter halos. These models are most often based on the isothermal density profile -- not an optimal description of the halo, but easy to use because it leads to an analytic deflection-angle formula. Dark-matter halos are better described by the Navarro--Frenk--White (NFW) density profile. We set out to study lensing by a general triaxial ellipsoidal NFW halo, with the aim of providing an analytic model that would be more consistent with the current understanding of dark-matter halos. We computed the conversion between the properties of a triaxial ellipsoidal lens model and its elliptical surface-density profile. In the case of the NFW lens model, its angular scale is defined by the projected scale semi-major axis of the halo, while its lensing regime depends on two parameters: the projected eccentricity $e$ and the convergence parameter $\kappa_\text{s}$. We employed the Bourassa \&amp; Kantowski formalism to compute the complex scattering function of the model, which yields the deflection-angle components when separated into its real and imaginary parts. We present the obtained closed-form expressions for the deflection-angle components, valid for an arbitrary eccentricity of the surface-density profile. We use them to compute and describe the lensing properties of the model, including: the shear, its components, and the phase; critical curves, caustics, and the parameter-space mapping of their geometries; the deformations and orientations of images. The analytically solved ellipsoidal NFW lens model is available for implementation in gravitational lensing software. The techniques introduced here such as the image-plane analysis can prove to be useful for understanding the properties of other lens models as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00169v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Heyrovsk\'y, Michal Karamazov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Velocity Dispersion and H$\alpha$ emission of Ionized Gas in Star-forming Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For understanding the nature of gaseous flows in star-forming regions of nearby galaxies it is usually utilized the relation between surface brightness in H$\alpha$ line and velocity dispersion of ionized gas known as ''surface brightness -- velocity dispersion diagram''. Using the three-dimensional gasdynamic simulations we consider the evolution of the synthetic diagrams for supershells driven by multiple supernova explosions in stellar cluster located in the galactic disk. We investigate the shape and structure of the diagrams depending on gaseous density and metallicity, disk scale height values. We show that there are several loci of values typical for young bubbles evolved in dense or rarefied gas at large heights above the disk midplane. We find that the structure of the diagram is depended on age of a supershell and physical conditions of a gas in the disk. We argue that the diagrams obtained for the nearby dwarf galaxies can be interpreted by only using the dynamics of bubbles driven by multiple supernova explosions in low-mass stellar clusters of different age.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00378v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1134/S1990341323600242</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophysical Bulletin, 2024, v.79, p.60</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Evgemii O. Vasiliev, Yuri A. Shchekinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking Dusty Cloud Crushed by a Hot Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00381v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The destruction of clouds by strong shocks and hot winds is the key process responsible for the transp orting of metals and dust from the ISM to the ICM/IGM, and establishing the multiphase structure in and around galaxies. In this work, we perform a detailed analysis of this process using two different approaches for tracking the cloud material (gas and dust): the so-called 'colored' fluid, and the Lagrangian (trace) particles. We find that for the clouds in the hot phase ($T&gt;10^5$ K), the two methods produce significantly different mass fractions and velocities of the cloud material. In contrast, the two methods produce similar results for the clouds that are in the warm/cold phases ($T &lt; 10^5$ K). We find that the Kelvin--Helmholtz instability is suppressed in the warm clouds of size $\sim$100 pc and metallicity $Z\gt 0.1 Z_\odot$ due to effective gas cooling. This causes a delay in the destruction of such clouds that are interacting with the hot ICM flow. We demonstrate that the dust particles that are evacuated from their 'parent' clouds to the hot medium show different dynamics when compared to that of the Lagrangian (trace) particles. Our results indicate that the dust grains swept out to the hot gas are destroyed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00381v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10040155</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10(4), 155</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Svyatoslav Dedikov, Evgenii Vasiliev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comparative Study of Star Forming Dwarf Galaxies using the UVIT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a Far-Ultraviolet (FUV) study of sixteen star-forming dwarf galaxies (SFDGs) using the Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (UVIT). Morphologically, SFDGs are classified as dwarf spirals, dwarf irregulars, and blue compact dwarfs (BCDs). We extracted the star-forming complexes (SFCs) from the sample galaxies, derived their sizes, and estimated the FUV+24$\mu m$ star formation rates (SFRs). We also determined the approximate stellar disk mass associated with the SFCs using IRAC 3.6-micron images. We derived the specific SFRs (sSFRs), as well as the SFR densities ($\Sigma(SFR)$) for the SFCs. We find that the lower $\Sigma(SFR)$ for each type is different, with the dwarf irregulars having the lowest $\Sigma(SFR)$ compared to others. However, the median size of the SFCs in the dwarf irregulars is the largest compared to the other two types when compared at roughly the same distance. We have derived the star-forming main sequence (SFMS) on the scale of SFCs for all three classes of SFDGs. We find that although all SFDGs approximately follow the global SFMS relation, i.e. $SFR\propto {M_{*}}^{\alpha}$ (where globally $\alpha\approx1$ for low surface brightness galaxies and $0.9$ for SFDGs), on the scale of SFCs the $\alpha$ value for each type is different. The $\alpha$ values for dwarf spirals, dwarf irregulars, and BCDs are found to be 0.74$\pm$0.13, 0.8$\pm$0.16, and 0.8$\pm$0.19, respectively. However, the age of all SFCs approximately corresponds to 1 Gyr. Finally, we find that the outer SFCs in most galaxies except BCDs have a high sSFR, supporting the inside-out model of galaxy growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00537v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae907</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S Amrutha, Mousumi Das, Jyoti Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gas-rich Ultra-diffuse Galaxies Are Originated from High Specific Angular Momentum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-diffuse galaxies, characterized by comparable effective radii to the Milky Way but possessing 100-1,000 times fewer stars, offer a unique opportunity to garner novel insights into the mechanisms governing galaxy formation. Nevertheless, the existing corpus of observational and simulation studies has not yet yielded a definitive constraint or comprehensive consensus on the formation mechanisms underlying ultra-diffuse galaxies. In this study, we delve into the properties of ultra-diffuse galaxies enriched with neutral hydrogen using a semi-analytic method, with the explicit aim of constraining existing ultra-diffuse galaxy formation models. We find that the gas-rich ultra-diffuse galaxies are statistically not failed $L^{\star}$ galaxies nor dark matter deficient galaxies. In statistical terms, these ultra-diffuse galaxies exhibit comparable halo concentration, but higher baryonic mass fraction, as well as higher stellar and gas specific angular momentum, in comparison to typical dwarf galaxy counterparts. Our analysis unveils that higher gas specific angular momentum serves as the underlying factor elucidating the observed heightened baryonic mass fractions, diminished star formation efficiency, expanded stellar disk sizes, and reduced stellar densities in ultra-diffuse galaxies. Our findings make significant contributions to advancing our knowledge of ultra-diffuse galaxy formation and shed light on the intricate interplay between gas dynamics and the evolution of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00555v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Rong, Huijie Hu, Min He, Wei Du, Qi Guo, Hui-Yuan Wang, Hong-Xin Zhang, Houjun Mo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALMA Confirmation of Millimeter Time Variability in the Gamma-Ray Detected Seyfert Galaxy GRS 1734-292</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: GRS 1734-292 is a radio-quiet galaxy, exhibiting neither intense starburst nor jet activities. However, Fermi-LAT detected this object in the GeV band. The origin of non-thermal activity in this Seyfert galaxy is an intriguing question. We report Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA) observations of GRS 1734-292 at frequencies of 97.5, 145, and 225 GHz. These observations confirmed the millimeter excess within the central &lt;100 pc region and its time variability based on two separate observations conducted four days apart. The timescale of variability aligns with the light crossing time for a compact source smaller than &lt;100 Schwarzschild radius. If we take into account the power-law synchrotron emission originating from the corona (i.e., the hot plasma located above the accretion disk), the millimeter spectrum indicates the coronal magnetic field of ~10 G and the size of ~10 Schwarzschild radius. An alternative explanation for this millimeter emission could be synchrotron and free-free emission from disk winds (i.e., fast wide-opening angle outflows from the disk) with the size of ~10 pc, although it may be difficult to explain the fast variability. Future millimeter observations with higher resolution (~0.01") will enable the differentiation between these two scenarios. Such observations will provide insights into the acceleration sites of high-energy particles at the core of active galactic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00647v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonari Michiyama, Yoshiyuki Inoue, Akihiro Doi, Tomoya Yamada, Yasushi Fukazawa, Hidetoshi Kubo, Samuel Barnie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How common can the origin of clusters Cha I, Cha II, epsilon Cha and eta Cha be?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00669v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The trajectories of the clusters $\eta$ Cha, $\epsilon$ Cha and Cha I, Cha II, constructed backward in time, have been studied. We concluded that the hypothesis about the joint formation of all four of these clusters from one molecular cloud cannot be completely excluded. However, 10-15 Myr ago, all these four clusters were located at approximately the same height above the plane of the Galaxy. Thus, the gas-dust clouds from which all these four clusters were formed were located on one broad front. It is possible that the appearance of the Cha I, Cha II, $\epsilon$ Cha and $\eta$ Cha clusters may be associated with the impact on such a front of shock waves formed after supernova explosions in the Scorpius-Centauri association. New estimates of the kinematic ages of the clusters Cha I and Cha II are obtained as $0.12\pm0.19$ and $0.05\pm0.15$, respectively. It is shown that the minimum size of the Cha I-north and Cha I-south clusters corresponded to the time of $0.55\pm0.24$ Myr and $0.04\pm0.18$ Myr ago, respectively, and approximately 1.5 Myr ago the distance between the trajectories of these two groupings was minimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00669v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-4527/ad392d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Vadim V. Bobylev, Anisa T. Bajkova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Interaction Between Stars and Past AGN Disk: Possible Explanation for the Kinematic Distributions of S-stars in the Galactic Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00937v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The presence of young stars, aged around several million years and situated within the range of $\sim 0.04-1$ parsec from our Galactic Center raises a question about their origins and dynamical evolutions. Their kinematics provide an opportunity to explore their formation or possible subsequent dynamical evolution. If Sagittarius A* was active in the past as suggested by several observations, the accretion disk may have a significant impact on the dynamics of stars in the Galactic Center. The drag force exerted on stars during star-disk interaction could lead some of them to sink into the accretion disk, and these embedded stars will rapidly migrate inward and eventually be disrupted within $\sim10^5$ years. This could roughly explain the absence of stars within $2.5 \times 10^4 R_{\rm g}$ ($\sim$ 1000 AU). Additionally, Kozai-Lidov oscillations, induced by the gravitational perturbation of the disk, could contribute to the bimodal distribution of S-star inclinations and drive a majority of stars into high eccentricity orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00937v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Fan, Qingwen Wu, Jiancheng Wu, Xiangli Lei, Mengye Wang, Fulin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spiral Galaxies' Disk Dominance and Testing MOND</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many Hubble type S galaxies have a flat rotation curve, V extending into the outer disk. The surface brightness there is too low to create V from stars of a reasonable mass-to-light ratio. To maintain a stable disk, a massive dark matter halo is usually assumed to dominate in creating V. Gravitational arm amplification is used here to estimate whether V is created by a disk mixture, or by a 100 percent halo. The disk surface density is not estimated from the disk surface brightness and an assumed mass to light ratio. The observed arm pitch angle is presumed to be long term maximally amplified. This permits calculation of the disk surface mass density with radius relative to a 100 percent disk which would fully create V. NGC 7217's tightly wound 4.8 degree arm pitch angle indicates a disk component contributing 43 percent of the observed V for the range over the spiral arms (important but not dominant). It has too low a disk density to create V with the rest presumably arising from a halo. V is proportional to the square root of surface density. By contrast a loose arm galaxy disk can dominate in creating V. For example NGC 3198's arm pitch angle of 30 degrees implies a disk surface density sufficient to account for 88 percent of V which is a dominant fraction. Little dark matter halo is needed for galaxies like this. Observationally, the dark outer disk may be molecular hydrogen. NGC 3198's dominant disk also provides a counter example to the need for any universal (MOND) force law modification over the outer disk spiral arms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00944v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gene Byrd, Sethanne Howard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of thionylimide, HNSO, in space: the first N-, S- and O-bearing interstellar molecule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first detection in space of thionylimide (HNSO) toward the Galactic Center molecular cloud G+0.693-0.027, thanks to the superb sensitivity of an ultradeep molecular line survey carried out with the Yebes 40$\,$m and IRAM 30$\,$m telescopes. This molecule is the first species detected in the interstellar medium containing, simultaneously, N, S and O. We have identified numerous $K$$_a$ = 0, 1 and 2 transitions belonging to HNSO covering from $J$$_{\rm up}$ = 2 to $J$$_{\rm up}$ = 10, including several completely unblended features. We derive a molecular column density of $N$ = (8 $\pm$ 1)$\times$10$^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$, yielding a fractional abundance relative to H$_2$ of $\sim$6$\times$10$^{-10}$, which is about $\sim$37 and $\sim$4.8 times less abundant than SO and SO2, respectively. Although there are still many unknowns in the interstellar chemistry of NSO-bearing molecules, we propose that HNSO is likely formed through the reaction of the NSO radical and atomic H on the surface of icy grains, with alternative routes also deserving exploration. Finally, HNSO appears as a promising link between N- , S- and O- interstellar chemistry and its discovery paves the route to the detection of a new family of molecules in space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01044v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Sanz-Novo, V\'ictor M. Rivilla, Holger S. P. M\"uller, Izaskun Jim\'enez-Serra, Jes\'us Mart\'in-Pintado, Laura Colzi, Shaoshan Zeng, Andr\'es Meg\'ias, \'Alvaro L\'opez-Gallifa, Antonio Mart\'inez-Henares, Bel\'en Tercero, Pablo de Vicente, David San Andr\'es, Sergio Mart\'in, Miguel A. Requena-Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comparative Study of Dust Grain Polarisation Efficiencies in the Interstellar and Intracluster Mediums towards Anti-Center Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dust polarisation observations at optical wavelengths help understand the dust grain properties and trace the plane-of-the-sky component of the magnetic field. In this study, we make use of published optical polarisation data acquired with AIMPOL along with distances ($d$) and extinction ($A_{\mathrm{V}}$) data. We study the variation of polarisation efficiency ($P/A_{\mathrm{V}}$) as a function of $A_{\mathrm{V}}$ in the diffuse interstellar medium (ISM) and intracluster mediums (ICM) using the already published polarisation data of six clusters. Among these clusters, NGC 2281, NGC 1664, and NGC 1960 are old; while Stock 8, NGC 1931, and NGC 1893 are young. We categorize stars towards each cluster into foreground, background, and cluster members by employing two clustering algorithms GMM and DBSCAN. Thus, classified field stars and cluster members are used to reveal the polarisation properties of ISM and ICM dust, respectively. We find that the dust grains located in the diffuse ISM show higher polarisation efficiencies when compared to those located in the ICM of younger clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01169v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae749</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, Volume 529, Issue 4, Pages 4234-4247 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. Bijas, Chakali Eswaraiah, Panigrahy Sandhyarani, Jessy Jose, Maheswar Gopinathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing Robust Background IFU spectra using Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In astronomy, spectroscopy consists of observing an astrophysical source and extracting its spectrum of electromagnetic radiation. Once extracted, a model is fit to the spectra to measure the observables, leading to an understanding of the underlying physics of the emission mechanism. One crucial, and often overlooked, aspect of this model is the background emission, which contains foreground and background astrophysical sources, intervening atmospheric emission, and artifacts related to the instrument such as noise. This paper proposes an algorithmic approach to constructing a background model for SITELLE observations using statistical tools and supervised machine learning algorithms. We apply a segmentation algorithm implemented in photutils to divide the data cube into background and source spaxels. After applying a principal component analysis (PCA) on the background spaxels, we train an artificial neural network to interpolate from the background to the source spaxels in the PCA coefficient space, which allows us to generate a local background model over the entire data cube. We highlight the performance of this methodology by applying it to SITELLE observations obtained of a SIGNALS galaxy, \NGC4449, and the Perseus galaxy cluster of galaxies, NGC 1275. We discuss the physical interpretation of the principal components and noise reduction in the resulting PCA-based reconstructions. Additionally, we compare the fit results using our new background modeling approach to standard methods used in the literature and find that our method better captures the emission from HII regions in NGC 4449 and the faint emission regions in NGC 1275. These methods also demonstrate that the background does change as a function of the position of the datacube.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01175v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carter Lee Rhea, Julie Hlavacek-Larrondo, Justine Giroux, Auriane Thilloy, Hyunseop Choi, Laurie Rousseau-Nepton, Marie-Lou Gendron-Marsolais, Mario Pasquato, Simon Prunet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallicity and $\alpha$-abundance for 48 million stars in low-extinction regions in the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We estimate ([M/H], [$\alpha$/M]) for 48 million giants and dwarfs in low dust extinction regions from the Gaia DR3 XP spectra by using tree-based machine-learning models trained on APOGEE DR17 and metal-poor star sample of Li et al. The root mean square error of our estimation is 0.0890 dex for [M/H] and 0.0436 dex for [$\alpha$/M], when we evaluate our models with the test data. Our estimation is most reliable for giants and metal-rich stars, because the training data are dominated by such stars. The high-[$\alpha$/M] stars and low-[$\alpha$/M] stars selected by our ([M/H], [$\alpha$/M]) show different kinematical properties for giants and low-temperature dwarfs. We further investigate how our machine-learning models extract information on ([M/H], [$\alpha$/M]). Intriguingly, our models seem to extract information on [$\alpha$/M] from Na D lines (589 nm) and Mg I line (516 nm). This result is understandable given the observed correlation between Na and Mg abundances in the literature. The catalog of ([M/H], [$\alpha$/M]) as well as their associated uncertainties will be publicly available online.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01269v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Hattori (NAOJ, The Institute of Statistical Mathematics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The galaxy cluster AC114 III. The role of galaxy clusters in the mass-metallicity relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01289v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the role of galaxy clusters in the mass-metallicity relation by using a sample of galaxies belonging to the AC114 (z=0.317) galaxy cluster. The data was taken from archival VIMOS-MOS spectroscopy to estimate gas-phase metallicities by using strong-line methods. On the other hand, the data obtained from DECaLS DR10 and VIKING DR4 ESO surveys were used to estimate photometric masses. We found that passive galaxies dominate the population of AC114 in the cluster center, whereas the star-forming members tend to be located outside this region. The constructed MZR from the latter indicates that AC114 SF galaxies have a lower metallicity content than foreground galaxies (z up to 0.28) and the same or even lower metallicities with respect to background galaxies (spanning redshifts 0.34 to 0.70), producing slightly a shallower slope compared to the field MZR at z~0.3. Additionally, it shows a higher scatter of 0.17 dex, consistent with MZRs of galaxy clusters reported in the literature. The responsible mechanisms behind the scatter are consistent with simulations and observations where dynamic and environmental effects such as galaxy-galaxy interactions and ram-pressure stripping are shaping the chemical evolution of the AC114 SF members. The former mechanism can decrease gas-phase metallicities because of pristine gas infall to the galaxy's outskirts, and the latter increases gas-phase metallicities because of the stripping of the metal-poor gas located at the outskirts of the SF members. The AC114 SF members are metal-poorer than field galaxies at the same redshift, so the cluster dominated by galaxy-galaxy interactions is the best scenario that explains the slightly shallower slope and the higher scatter of the AC114-MZR compared to the field MZR at z~0.3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01289v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Andrade, I. Saviane, L. Monaco, I. Yegorova, D. Proust</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp departure beyond post-Newtonian formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00094v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a concrete example exhibiting marked deviation from the parametrized post-Newtonian (PPN) approximation in a modified theory of gravity. Specifically, we derive the exact formula for the Robertson parameter $\gamma$ in Brans-Dicke gravity for compact mass sources, explicitly incorporating the pressure content of these sources. We achieve this by exploiting the $\textit integrability$ of the 00-component of the Brans-Dicke field equation. In place of the conventional PPN result $\gamma_{\,PPN}=\frac{\omega+1}{\omega+2}$, we obtain the analytical expression $\gamma_{\,exact}=\frac{\omega+1+(\omega+2)\varTheta}{\omega+2+(\omega+1)\varTheta}$ where $\varTheta$ is the ratio of the total pressure $P_\parallel^*+2P_\perp^*$ and total energy $E^*$ contained within the mass source. Our non-perturbative formula is valid for all field strengths and types of matter comprising the mass source. We draw four key conclusions: (1) The usual $\gamma_{\,PPN}$ formula is violated in the presence of pressure, viz. when $\varTheta\neq0$, revealing a limitation of the PPN approximation in Brans-Dicke gravity. (2) The PPN result mainly stems from the assumption of pressureless matter. Even in the weak-field star case, non-zero pressure leads to a violation of the PPN $\gamma$ formula. Conversely, the PPN result is a good approximation for low-pressure matter, i.e. when $\varTheta\approx0$, for all field strengths. (3) Observational constraints on $\gamma$ set joint bounds on $\omega$ and $\varTheta$, with the latter representing a global characteristic of a mass source. If the equation of state of matter in the mass source approaches the ultra-relativistic form, entailing $\varTheta\simeq1$, $\gamma_{\,exact}$ converges to 1 irrespective of $\omega$. (4) In a broader context, our findings indicate the latent significance of considering the interior structure of stars in observational astronomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00094v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Ky Nguyen, Bertrand Chauvineau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of the Longest-Period Classical Cepheid in the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00151v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of the classical Cepheid OGLE-GD-CEP-1884 (= GDS_J1535467-555656) with the longest pulsation period known in our Galaxy. The period of 78.14 d is nearly 10 d longer than that of the previous record-holding Cepheid, S Vulpeculae, and thus, OGLE-GD-CEP-1884 can be categorized as the first ultra long period Cepheid in the Milky Way. This star is present in the ASAS-SN and Gaia DR3 catalogs of variable stars, but it has been classified as a long-period variable in those catalogs. Based on more than 10 years of the photometric monitoring of this star carried out by the OGLE project in the I and V bands and a radial velocity curve from the Gaia Focused Product Release, we unequivocally demonstrate that this object is a fundamental-mode classical Cepheid. By employing the mid-infrared period-luminosity relation, we determine the distance to OGLE-GD-CEP-1884 (4.47 +- 0.34 kpc) and place it on the Milky Way map, along with about 2400 other classical Cepheids. We also discuss the potential of finding additional ultra long period Cepheids in our Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00151v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Soszy\'nski, D. M. Skowron, A. Udalski, P. Pietrukowicz, M. Gromadzki, M. K. Szyma\'nski, J. Skowron, P. Mr\'oz, R. Poleski, S. Koz{\l}owski, P. Iwanek, M. Wrona, K. Ulaczyk, K. Rybicki, M. Mr\'oz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic mass-richness relation of clusters from THE THREE HUNDRED hydrodynamic simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main systematics in cluster cosmology is the uncertainty in the mass-observable relation. In this paper, we focus on the most direct cluster observable in optical surveys, i.e. richness, and constrain the intrinsic mass-richness (MR) relation of clusters in THE THREE HUNDRED hydrodynamic simulations with two runs: GIZMO-SIMBA and GADGET-X. We find that modeling the richness at fixed halo mass with a skewed Gaussian distribution yields a simpler and smaller scatter compared to the commonly used log-normal distribution. Additionally, we observe that baryon models have a significant impact on the scatter, while exhibiting no influence on the mass dependence and a slight effect on the amplitude in the MR relation. We select member galaxies based on both stellar mass $M_\star$ and absolute magnitude $\mathscr{M}$. We demonstrate that the MR relation obtained from these two selections can be converted to each other by using the $M_\star-\mathscr{M}$ relation. Finally, we provide a 7-parameter fitting result comprehensively capturing the dependence of the MR relation on both stellar mass cutoff and redshift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00321v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingjing Chen, Weiguang Cui, Wenjuan Fang, Zhonglue Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proposal for enhancing technosignature search toward the Galactic center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00840v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss the possibility of enhancing intelligent life searches toward the Galactic center. From the clockwork orbital motions of stars around the Sgr A${}^*$ black hole, we can determine the distance to the Galactic center at an exceptional accuracy, despite its remoteness $\sim 8.3$kpc. In addition, we can define precise reference epochs by selecting a prominent object such as the bright B-type star S2. These properties have a particular affinity for the coordinated signaling scheme which was hypothesized by Seto (2019) for systematically connecting intentional senders to searchers without a prior communication. If S2 is actually being used as a common reference clock, we can compress the search directions around the Galactic center by more than two orders of magnitude, with the scanning interval of $\sim16$yr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00840v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Seto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clues in Bailey Diagrams Indicate that the Horizontal Branch Evolutionary Effect Is the Direct Reason for Oosterhoff Phenomenon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00911v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Noticing the potential relationship between the pulsation amplitude of fundamental mode RR Lyrae stars and their average effective temperatures, we derived the relation between them from observational data. Using these relationships, we present the zero-age horizontal branch lines and corresponding evolutionary tracks in the Bailey diagrams. We first find that the trends of zero-age horizontal branch lines are consistent with the distributions of Oosterhoff I RR Lyrae stars, and there is a period shift effect in relatively metal-rich samples ([Fe/H] &gt; -1). Main results show that evolutionary effects are the direct cause of the Oosterhoff dichotomy. The vast majority of Oosterhoff I RR Lyrae stars are in the early stage of horizontal branch evolution, while most of the Oosterhoff II stars are near the end of the horizontal branch phase. Our Bailey diagrams can intuitively explain some Oosterhoff phenomena (e.g., long-period RR Lyrae stars in the metal-rich globular clusters NGC 6388 and NGC 6441), and also have the potential to become an important tool for in-depth study of RR Lyrae stars. Further research is needed on the Oosterhoff dichotomy to explore the formations and evolutionary processes of the Milky Way and its substructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00911v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. -J. Li, S. -B. Qian, L. -Y. Zhu, X. -D. Shi, W. -P. Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic axion vortex and very light QCD axions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00997v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that a stable vortex soliton, carrying a constant magnetic flux, exists in the homogeneous medium of axions with a constant time-derivative. Axions can be bound in the vortex, having energy less than the axion mass. If the observed magnetic fields in galaxies are those of the vortex, the axion-photon coupling has to be smaller than $10^{-17}\,{\rm GeV^{-1}}$. Otherwise, axions decay too quickly to constitute dark matter in galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00997v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deog Ki Hong, Stephen J. Lonsdale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for gravitationally lensed interstellar transmissions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01201v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider interstellar light transmission aided by a gravitational lens. We find that optimal reception efficiency occurs in lensing geometries where the transmitter, lens, and receiver are nearly aligned. We explore various signal detection strategies, employing both existing and emerging technologies. With this study, our understanding of interstellar power transmission via gravitational lensing has significantly progressed. We observe that detection signals from nearby stars, may leverage established photonics and optical engineering technologies, and networks of collaborative astronomical facilities. Our findings support the feasibility of interstellar power transmission via gravitational lensing, directly contributing to the ongoing optical SETI efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01201v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Slava G. Turyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Hole Dark Matter Simulations Using PopSyCLE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.06771v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs), theorized to have originated in the early universe, are speculated to be a viable form of dark matter. If they exist, they should be detectable through photometric and astrometric signals resulting from gravitational microlensing of stars in the Milky Way. Population Synthesis for Compact-object Lensing Events, or PopSyCLE, is a simulation code that enables users to simulate microlensing surveys, and is the first of its kind to include both photometric and astrometric microlensing effects, which are important for potential PBH detection and characterization. To estimate the number of observable PBH microlensing events we modify PopSyCLE to include a dark matter halo consisting of PBHs. We detail our PBH population model, and demonstrate our PopSyCLE + PBH results through simulations of the OGLE-IV and Roman microlensing surveys. We provide a proof-of-concept analysis for adding PBHs into PopSyCLE, and thus include many simplifying assumptions, such as $f_{\text{DM}}$, the fraction of dark matter composed of PBHs, and $\bar{m}_{\text{PBH}}$, mean PBH mass. Assuming $\bar{m}_{\text{PBH}}=30$ $M_{\odot}$, we find $\sim$ 3.6$f_{\text{DM}}$ times as many PBH microlensing events than stellar evolved black hole events, a PBH average peak Einstein crossing time of $\sim$ 91.5 days, estimate on order of $10^2f_{\text{DM}}$ PBH events within the 8 year OGLE-IV results, and estimate Roman to detect $\sim$ 1,000$f_{\text{DM}}$ PBH microlensing events throughout its planned microlensing survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.06771v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Pruett, W. Dawson, M. S. Medford, C. Lam, J. R. Lu, S. Perkins, P. McGill, N. Golovich, G. Chapline</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Cluster Process Models for Detecting Ultra-Diffuse Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06567v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel set of Poisson Cluster Process (PCP) models to detect Ultra-Diffuse Galaxies (UDGs), a class of extremely faint, enigmatic galaxies of substantial interest in modern astrophysics. We model the unobserved UDG locations as parent points in a PCP, and infer their positions based on the observed spatial point patterns of their old star cluster systems. Many UDGs have somewhere from a few to hundreds of these old star clusters, which we treat as offspring points in our models. We also present a new framework to construct a marked PCP model using the marks of star clusters. The marked PCP model may enhance the detection of UDGs and offers broad applicability to problems in other disciplines. To assess the overall model performance, we design an innovative assessment tool for spatial prediction problems where only point-referenced ground truth is available, overcoming the limitation of standard ROC analyses where spatial Boolean reference maps are required. We construct a bespoke blocked Gibbs adaptive spatial birth-death-move MCMC algorithm to infer the locations of UDGs using real data from a \textit{Hubble Space Telescope} imaging survey. Based on our performance assessment tool, our novel models significantly outperform existing approaches using the Log-Gaussian Cox Process. We also obtained preliminary evidence that the marked PCP model improves UDG detection performance compared to the model without marks. Furthermore, we find evidence of a potential new ``dark galaxy'' that was not detected by previous methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06567v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dayi Li, Alex Stringer, Patrick E. Brown, Gwendolyn M. Eadie, Roberto G. Abraham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sloan Digital Sky Survey Reverberation Mapping Project: Key Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01014v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the final data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey Reverberation Mapping (SDSS-RM) project, a precursor to the SDSS-V Black Hole Mapper Reverberation Mapping program. This data set includes 11-year photometric and 7-year spectroscopic light curves for 849 broad-line quasars over a redshift range of 0.1&lt;z&lt;4.5 and a luminosity range of Lbol=1E44-47.5 erg/s, along with spectral and variability measurements. We report 23, 81, 125, and 110 reverberation mapping lags (relative to optical continuum variability) for broad Halpha, Hbeta, MgII and CIV using the SDSS-RM sample, spanning much of the luminosity and redshift ranges of the sample. Using 30 low-redshift RM AGNs with dynamical-modeling black hole masses, we derive a new estimate of the average virial factor of &lt;log f&gt;=0.62+-0.07 for the line dispersion measured from the RMS spectrum. The intrinsic scatter of individual virial factors is 0.31+-0.07 dex, indicating a factor of two systematic uncertainty in RM black hole masses. Our lag measurements reveal significant R-L relations for Hbeta and MgII at high redshift, consistent with the latest measurements based on heterogeneous samples. While we are unable to robustly constrain the slope of the R-L relation for CIV given the limited dynamical range in luminosity, we found substantially larger scatter in CIV lags at fixed L1350. Using the SDSS-RM lag sample, we derive improved single-epoch (SE) mass recipes for Hbeta, MgII and CIV, which are consistent with their respective RM masses as well as between the SE recipes from two different lines, over the luminosity range probed by our sample. The new Hbeta and MgII recipes are approximately unbiased estimators at given RM masses, but there are systematic biases in the CIV recipe. The intrinsic scatter of SE masses around RM masses is ~0.45 dex for Hbeta and MgII, increasing to ~0.58 dex for CIV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01014v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Shen, Catherine J. Grier, Keith Horne, Zachary Stone, Jennifer I. Li, Qian Yang, Yasaman Homayouni, Jonathan R. Trump, Scott F. Anderson, W. N. Brandt, Patrick B. Hall, Luis C. Ho, Linhua Jiang, Patrick Petitjean, Donald P. Schneider, Charling Tao, Fergus. R. Donnan, Yusra AlSayyad, Matthew A. Bershady, Michael R. Blanton, Dmitry Bizyaev, Kevin Bundy, Yuguang Chen, Megan C. Davis, Kyle Dawson, Xiaohui Fan, Jenny E. Greene, Hannes Groller, Yucheng Guo, Hector Ibarra-Medel, Yuanzhe Jiang, Ryan P. Keenan, Juna A. Kollmeier, Cassandra Lejoly, Zefeng Li, Axel de la Macorra, Maxwell Moe, Jundan Nie, Graziano Rossi, Paul S. Smith, Wei Leong Tee, Anne-Marie Weijmans, Jiachuan Xu, Minghao Yue, Xu Zhou, Zhimin Zhou, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning the Dark Matter Halo Mass of Milky Way-Like Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06476v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite the Milky Way's proximity to us, our knowledge of its dark matter halo is fairly limited, and there is still considerable uncertainty in its halo mass. Many past techniques have been limited by assumptions such as the Galaxy being in dynamical equilibrium as well as nearby galaxies being true satellites of the Galaxy, and/or the need to find large samples of Milky Way analogs in simulations.Here, we propose a new technique based on neural networks that obtains high precision ($&lt;0.14$ dex mass uncertainty) without assuming halo dynamical equilibrium or that neighboring galaxies are all satellites, and which can use information from a wide variety of simulated halos (even those dissimilar to the Milky Way) to improve its performance. This method uses only observable information including satellite orbits, distances to nearby larger halos, and the maximum circular velocity of the largest satellite galaxy. In this paper, we demonstrate a proof-of-concept method on simulated dark matter halos; in future papers in this series, we will apply neural networks to estimate the masses of the Milky Way's and M31's dark matter halos, and we will train variations of these networks to estimate other halo properties including concentration, assembly history, and spin axis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06476v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elaheh Hayati, Peter Behroozi, Ekta Patel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transfer learning for galaxy feature detection: Finding Giant Star-forming Clumps in low redshift galaxies using Faster R-CNN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03503v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Giant Star-forming Clumps (GSFCs) are areas of intensive star-formation that are commonly observed in high-redshift (z&gt;1) galaxies but their formation and role in galaxy evolution remain unclear. High-resolution observations of low-redshift clumpy galaxy analogues are rare and restricted to a limited set of galaxies but the increasing availability of wide-field galaxy survey data makes the detection of large clumpy galaxy samples increasingly feasible. Deep Learning, and in particular CNNs, have been successfully applied to image classification tasks in astrophysical data analysis. However, one application of DL that remains relatively unexplored is that of automatically identifying and localising specific objects or features in astrophysical imaging data. In this paper we demonstrate the feasibility of using Deep learning-based object detection models to localise GSFCs in astrophysical imaging data. We apply the Faster R-CNN object detection framework (FRCNN) to identify GSFCs in low redshift (z&lt;0.3) galaxies. Unlike other studies, we train different FRCNN models not on simulated images with known labels but on real observational data that was collected by the Sloan Digital Sky Survey Legacy Survey and labelled by volunteers from the citizen science project `Galaxy Zoo: Clump Scout'. The FRCNN model relies on a CNN component as a `backbone' feature extractor. We show that CNNs, that have been pre-trained for image classification using astrophysical images, outperform those that have been pre-trained on terrestrial images. In particular, we compare a domain-specific CNN -`Zoobot' - with a generic classification backbone and find that Zoobot achieves higher detection performance and also requires smaller training data sets to do so. Our final model is capable of producing GSFC detections with a completeness and purity of &gt;=0.8 while only being trained on ~5,000 galaxy images.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03503v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\"urgen Popp, Hugh Dickinson, Stephen Serjeant, Mike Walmsley, Dominic Adams, Lucy Fortson, Kameswara Mantha, Vihang Mehta, James M. Dawson, Sandor Kruk, Brooke Simmons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first quenched galaxies, when and how?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01314v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many quiescent galaxies discovered in the early Universe by \textit{JWST} raise fundamental questions on when and how these galaxies became and stayed quenched. Making use of the latest version of the semi-analytic model GAEA that provides good agreement with the observed quenched fractions up to $z\sim 3$, we make predictions for the expected fractions of quiescent galaxies up to $z\sim 7$ and analyze the main quenching mechanism. We find that in a simulated box of $685~{\rm Mpc}$ on a side, the first quenched massive ($M_{\star} \sim 10^{11} {\rm M}_{\odot}$), Milky Way mass, and low mass ($M_{\star} \sim 10^{9.5} {\rm M}_{\odot}$ ) galaxies appear at $z\sim 4.5$, $z\sim 6.2$, and before $z = 7$. Most quenched galaxies identified at early redshifts remain quenched for more than 1 Gyr. Independently of galaxy stellar mass, the dominant quenching mechanism at high redshift is accretion disk feedback (quasar winds) from a central massive black hole, which is triggered by mergers in massive and MW-mass galaxies, and by disk instabilities in low-mass galaxies. Environmental stripping becomes increasingly more important at lower redshift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01314v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lizhi Xie, Gabriella De Lucia, Fabio Fontanot, Michaela Hirschmann, Yannick M Bah\'e, Michael L. Balogh, Adam Muzzin, Benedetta Vulcani, Devontae C. Baxter, Ben Forrest, Gillian Wilson, Gregory H. Rudnick, M. C. Cooper, Umberto Rescigno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian characterization of the young open cluster NGC 6383 using HDBSCAN and Gaia DR3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01030v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study focuses on determining the characteristics of the young open cluster NGC 6383. To achieve this, the HDBSCAN clustering algorithm is utilized to identify potential cluster members based on proper motions and parallaxes from Gaia Data Release 3. Various parameters of NGC 6383, such as tidal radius, core radius, distance through parallax and isochrone-fitting, proper motion, age, metallicity, and relevant others, are assessed. To perform this analysis, we utilize an extension of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, the No-U-Turn Sampler. The results of this analysis point out that NGC 6383 is a very young open cluster $(\sim 1 - 4~\mathrm{Myr})$, with a distance of $\sim 1.1~\mathrm{kpc}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01030v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. Pulgar-Escobar, N. A. Henr\'iquez-Salgado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Molecular Clouds of M31</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19746v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deep interferometric observations of CO and dust continuum emission are obtained with the Sub-Millimeter Array (SMA) at 230 GHz to investigate the physical nature of the giant molecular cloud (GMC) population in the Andromeda galaxy (M31). We use J = 2-1 $^{12}$CO and $^{13}$CO emission to derive the masses, sizes and velocity dispersions of 162 spatially resolved GMCs. We perform a detailed study of a subset of 117 GMCs that exhibit simple, single component line profile shapes. Examining the Larson scaling relations for these GMCs we find: 1- a highly correlated mass-size relation in both $^{12}$CO and $^{13}$CO emission; 2- a weakly correlated $^{12}$CO linewidth-size (LWS) relation along with a weaker, almost non-existent, $^{13}$CO LWS relation, suggesting a possible dependence of the LWS relation on spatial scale; and 3-that only 43\% of these GMCs are gravitationally bound. We identify two classes of GMCs based on the strength and extent of their $^{13}$CO emission. Examination of the Larson relations finds that both classes are individually characterized by strong $^{12}$CO mass-size relations and much weaker $^{12}$CO and $^{13}$CO LWS relations. The majority (73\%) of strong $^{13}$CO emitting GMCs are found to be gravitationally bound. However, only 25\% of the weak $^{13}$CO emitting GMCs are bound. The resulting breakdown in the Larson relations in the weak $^{13}$CO emitting population decouples the mass-size and LWS relations demonstrating that independent physical causes are required to understand the origin of each. Finally, in nearly every aspect, the physical properties of the M31 GMCs are found to be very similar to those of local Milky Way clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19746v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles J. Lada, Jan Forbrich, Glen Petitpas, Sebastien Viaene</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear redshift space distortion in halo ellipticity correlations: Analytical model and N-body simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07384v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an analytic model of nonlinear correlators of galaxy/halo ellipticities in redshift space. The three-dimensional ellipticity field is not affected by the redshift-space distortion (RSD) at linear order, but by the nonlinear one, known as the Finger-of-God effect, caused by the coordinate transformation from real to redshift space. Adopting a simple Gaussian damping function to describe the nonlinear RSD effect and the nonlinear alignment model for the relation between the observed ellipticity and underlying tidal fields, we derive analytic formulas for the multipole moments of the power spectra of the ellipticity field in redshift space expanded in not only the associated Legendre basis, a natural basis for the projected galaxy shape field, but also the standard Legendre basis, conventionally used in literature. The multipoles of the corresponding correlation functions of the galaxy shape field are shown to be expressed by a simple Hankel transform, as is the case for those of the conventional galaxy density correlations. We measure these multipoles of the power spectra and correlation functions of the halo ellipticity field using large-volume N-body simulations. We then show that the measured alignment signals can be better predicted by our nonlinear model than the existing linear alignment model. The formulas derived here have already been used to place cosmological constraints using from the redshift-space correlation functions of the galaxy shape field measured from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (Okumura and Taruya, 2023).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07384v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teppei Okumura, Atsushi Taruya, Toshiki Kurita, Takahiro Nishimichi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology and Astrophysics with Standard Sirens and Galaxy Catalogs in View of Future Gravitational Wave Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05302v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the growing number of gravitational-wave detections and the advent of large galaxy redshift surveys, a new era in cosmology is unfolding. This study explores the synergies between gravitational waves and galaxy surveys to jointly constrain cosmological and gravitational-wave population parameters. We introduce CHIMERA, a novel code for gravitational-wave cosmology combining information from the population properties of compact binary mergers and galaxy catalogs. We study constraints for scenarios representative of LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA O4 and O5 observing runs, assuming to have a complete catalog of potential host galaxies with either spectroscopic or photometric redshift measurements. We find that a percent-level measurement of $H_0$ could be achieved with the best 100 binary black holes in O5 using a spectroscopic galaxy catalog. In this case, the intrinsic correlation that exists between $H_0$ and the binary black hole population mass scales is broken. Instead, by using a photometric catalog the accuracy is degraded up to a factor of $\sim\! 9$, leaving a significant correlation between $H_0$ and the mass scales that must be carefully modeled to avoid bias. Interestingly, we find that using spectroscopic redshift measurements in the O4 configuration yields a better constraint on $H_0$ compared to the O5 configuration with photometric measurements. In view of the wealth of gravitational-wave data that will be available in the future, we argue the importance of obtaining spectroscopic galaxy catalogs to maximize the scientific return of gravitational-wave cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05302v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad20eb</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 964 (2024) 191</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Borghi, Michele Mancarella, Michele Moresco, Matteo Tagliazucchi, Francesco Iacovelli, Andrea Cimatti, Michele Maggiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FORECASTOR -- I. Finding Optics Requirements and Exposure times for the Cosmological Advanced Survey Telescope for Optical and UV Research mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08137v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Cosmological Advanced Survey Telescope for Optical and ultraviolet Research (CASTOR) is a proposed Canadian-led 1m-class space telescope that will carry out ultraviolet and blue-optical wide-field imaging, spectroscopy, and photometry. CASTOR will provide an essential bridge in the post-Hubble era, preventing a protracted UV-optical gap in space astronomy and enabling an enormous range of discovery opportunities from the solar system to the nature of the Cosmos, in conjunction with the other great wide-field observatories of the next decade (e.g., Euclid, Roman, Vera Rubin). FORECASTOR (Finding Optics Requirements and Exposure times for CASTOR) will supply a coordinated suite of mission-planning tools that will serve as the one-stop shop for proposal preparation, data reduction, and analysis for the CASTOR mission. We present the first of these tools: a pixel-based, user-friendly, extensible, multi-mission exposure time calculator (ETC) built in Python, including a modern browser-based graphical user interface that updates in real time. We then provide several illustrative examples of FORECASTOR's use that advance the design of planned legacy surveys for the CASTOR mission: a search for the most massive white dwarfs in the Magellanic Clouds; a study of the frequency of flaring activity in M stars, their distribution and impacts on habitability of exoplanets; mapping the proper motions of faint stars in the Milky Way; wide and deep galaxy surveys; and time-domain studies of active galactic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08137v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ad2987</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Isaac Cheng, Tyrone E. Woods, Patrick C\^ot\'e, Jennifer Glover, Dhananjhay Bansal, Melissa Amenouche, Madeline A. Marshall, Laurie Amen, John Hutchings, Laura Ferrarese, Kim A. Venn, Michael Balogh, Simon Blouin, Ryan Cloutier, Nolan Dickson, Sarah Gallagher, Martin Hellmich, Vincent H\'enault-Brunet, Viraja Khatu, Cameron Lawlor-Forsyth, Cameron Morgan, Harvey Richer, Marcin Sawicki, Robert Sorba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New catalog of distances to planetary nebulae based on Gaia parallaxes and statistical distances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04606v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have developed a method to determine the most reliable distances for a large group of planetary nebulae. For this purpose, we analyze the distances obtained from \textit{Gaia} parallaxes and three determinations of statistical distances. The most reliable distance is derived for 2211 objects, and uncertainties for these distances are calculated in a homogeneous way. Using our most reliable distances, we compare the distributions of Galactic heights of hydrogen-poor and hydrogen-rich central stars of planetary nebulae. We find that [WR] central stars are closer to the Galactic plane than hydrogen-rich central stars and than other hydrogen-poor central stars. The latter have a similar distribution to hydrogen-rich central stars, which is significantly different from the one of [WR] central stars. This result disagrees with the proposed evolutionary sequence for hydrogen-poor central stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04606v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Hern\'andez-Ju\'arez, M\'onica Rodr\'iguez, Miriam Pe\~na</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Runaway OB Stars in the Small Magellanic Cloud III. Updated Kinematics and Insights on Dynamical vs. Supernova Ejections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17198v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use the kinematics of field OB stars to estimate the frequencies of runaway stars generated by the dynamical ejection scenario (DES), the binary supernova scenario (BSS), and the combined two-step mechanism. We update the proper motions for field OB and OBe stars in the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC) using Gaia DR3. Our sample now contains 336 stars from the Runaways and Isolated O-Type Star Spectroscopic Survey of the SMC (RIOTS4), and we update our algorithm to calculate more accurate velocities compared to those obtained previously from DR2. We find a decrease in median velocity from 39 to 29 km/s, implying that the proper motions from our previous work were systematically overestimated. We present the velocity distribution for OBe stars and quantitatively compare it to those of non-compact binaries and high-mass X-ray binaries. We confirm that OBe stars appear to be dominated by the BSS and are likely post-SN binary systems, further supporting the mass-transfer model to explain the origin of their emission-line disks. In contrast, normal OB stars may show a bimodal velocity distribution, as may be expected from different processes that occur with dynamical ejections. The kinematics of fast-rotating OB stars are similar to those of normal OB stars rather than OBe stars, suggesting that the origin of their high v_r*sin(i) is different from that of OBe stars. We update our model parameters describing the kinematic origins of the SMC field population, still confirming that for runaway stars, the DES mechanism dominates, and two-step ejections seem comparable in frequency to pure BSS ejections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17198v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grant D. Phillips, M. S. Oey, Maria Cuevas, Norberto Castro, Rishi Kothari</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
