<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ages and metallicities of quiescent galaxies: confronting broadband ($UVJ$) colours with stellar absorption lines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08858v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For decades, studying quiescent galaxies beyond $z\sim1$ has been challenging due to the reliance on photometric spectral energy distributions (SEDs), which are highly susceptible to degeneracies between age, metallicity, dust, and star-formation history (SFH). Only recently has deep, rest-frame, optical spectroscopy made robust metallicity and age measurements possible, allowing us to empirically assess their effects on continuum shapes. To this end, we measure ages and metallicities of $\sim700$ massive ($10.2\lesssim\log(M_*/M_\odot)\lesssim11.8$), quiescent galaxies at $0.6\lesssim z\lesssim1.0$ from the Large Early Galaxy Astrophysics Census (LEGA-C) via continuum-normalized, absorption-line spectra, and compare with independent rest-frame $U-V$ and $V-J$ colours. Age increases along the quiescent sequence as both colours redden, consistent with stellar population synthesis (SPS) model predictions. Metallicity increases perpendicularly to the age trend, with higher metallicities at redder $U-V$ and bluer $V-J$ colours. Thus, age and metallicity behave differently in the $UVJ$ diagram. Moreover, this trend conflicts with SPS model expectations of increasing metallicity approximately along the quiescent sequence. Independent dynamical mass-to-light ratio trends also differ dramatically from SPS model predictions. These results demonstrate that relying on model fits to continuum shapes alone may lead to systematic biases in ages, metallicities, and stellar masses. The cause of these data-model disparities may stem from non-solar abundance patterns in quiescent galaxies or the treatment of evolved stellar phases in the models. Resolving these discrepancies is crucial, as photometric data remain central even with \textit{JWST}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08858v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chloe M. Cheng, Mariska Kriek, Aliza G. Beverage, Martje Slob, Rachel Bezanson, Marijn Franx, Joel Leja, Pavel E. Mancera Pi\~na, Katherine A. Suess, Arjen van der Wel, Jesse van de Sande, Pieter G. van Dokkum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marvelous Metals: Surveying the Circumgalactic Medium of Simulated Dwarf Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08861v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dwarf galaxies are uniquely sensitive to energetic feedback processes and are known to experience substantial mass and metal loss from their disk. Here, we investigate the circumgalactic medium (CGM) of 64 isolated dwarf galaxies ($6.0&lt;$log(M$_*/M_{\odot}$)$&lt;9.5$) at $z=0$ from the Marvel-ous Dwarfs and Marvelous Massive Dwarfs hydrodynamic simulations. Our galaxies produce column densities broadly consistent with current observations. We investigate these column densities in the context of mass and metal retention rates and the physical properties of the CGM. We find $48\pm11\%$ of all baryons within $R_{200c}$ reside in the CGM, with $\sim70\%$ of CGM mass existing in a warm gas phase, $10^{4.5}&lt;T&lt;10^{5.5}$ K that dominates beyond $r/R_{200c}\sim0.5$. Further, the warm and cool ($10^{4.0}&lt;T&lt;10^{4.5}$ K) gas phases each retain $5-10\%$ of metals formed by the dwarf galaxy. The significant fraction of mass and metals residing in the warm CGM phase provides an interpretation for the lack of observed low ion detections beyond $b/R_{200c}\sim0.5$ at $z\sim0$. We find a weak correlation between galaxy mass and total CGM metal retention despite the fraction of metals lost from the halo increasing from $\sim10\%$ to $&gt;40\%$ towards lower masses. Our findings highlight the CGM (primarily its warm component) as a key reservoir of mass and metals for dwarf galaxies across stellar masses and underscore its importance in understanding the baryon cycle in the low-mass regime. Finally, we provide individual galaxy properties of our full sample and quantify the fraction of ultraviolet observable mass to support future observational programs, particularly those aimed at performing a metal budget around dwarf galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08861v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel R. Piacitelli, Alyson M. Brooks, Charlotte Christensen, N. Nicole Sanchez, Yakov Faerman, Sijing Shen, Akaxia Cruz, Ben Keller, Thomas R. Quinn, James Wadsley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GA-NIFS: Mapping $z\simeq3.5$ AGN-driven ionized outflows in the COSMOS field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) are a key ingredient in galaxy evolution, possibly shaping galaxy growth through the generation of powerful outflows. Little is known regarding AGN-driven ionized outflows in moderate-luminosity AGN (logLbol[erg/s]&lt;47) beyond cosmic noon (z&gt;3). We present the first systematic analysis of the ionized outflow properties of a sample of X-ray-selected AGN (logLx[erg/s]&gt;44) from the COSMOS-Legacy field at z~3.5 and with logLbol[erg/s]=45.2-46.7, by using JWST NIRSpec/IFU spectroscopic observations as part of the GA-NIFS program. We spectrally isolate and spatially resolve the ionized outflows, by performing a multi-component kinematic decomposition of the rest-frame optical emission lines. JWST/NIRSpec IFU data also revealed a wealth of close-by companions, of both non-AGN and AGN nature, and ionized gas streams likely tracing tidal structures and large-scale ionized gas nebulae, extending up to the circum-galactic medium. Ionized outflows are detected in all COS-AGN targets, which we compare with previous results from the literature up to z~3, opportunely (re-)computed for a coherent comparison. We normalize outflow energetics ($\dot{M}_{out}$, $\dot{E}_{out}$) to the outflow density to standardize the various assumptions that were made in the literature. Our choice is equal to assuming that each outflow has the same gas density. We find GA-NIFS AGN to show outflows consistent with literature results, within the large scatter shown by the collected measurements, suggesting no strong evolution with redshift in terms of total mass outflow rate, energy budget and outflow velocity for fixed bolometric luminosity. Moreover, we find no clear redshift evolution of the ratio of mass outflow rate and kinetic power over AGN bolometric luminosity beyond z&gt;1. In general, our results indicate no significant evolution of the physics driving outflows beyond z~3. [abridged]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08867v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Bertola, G. Cresci, G. Venturi, M. Perna, C. Circosta, G. Tozzi, I. Lamperti, C. Vignali, S. Arribas, A. J. Bunker, S. Charlot, S. Carniani, R. Maiolino, B. Rodr\'iguez Del Pino, H. \"Ubler, C. J. Willott, T. B\"oker, M. A. Marshall, E. Parlanti, J. Scholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxies in the Epoch of Reionization Are All Bark and No Bite -- Plenty of Ionizing Photons, Low Escape Fractions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Early results from JWST suggest that epoch-of-reionization (EoR) galaxies produce copious ionizing photons, which, if they escape efficiently, could cause reionization to occur too early. We study this problem using JWST imaging and prism spectroscopy for 426 galaxies at 4.5 &lt; z &lt; 9.0. We fit these data simultaneously with stellar--population and nebular--emission models that include a parameter for the fraction of ionizing photons that escape the galaxy, f_esc. We find that the ionization production efficiency, $\xi_\mathrm{ion}$ = Q(H) / L(UV), increases with redshift and decreasing UV luminosity, but shows significant scatter, $\sigma( \log \xi_\mathrm{ion})$ ~= 0.3 dex. The inferred escape fractions averaged over the population are $\langle f_\mathrm{esc} \rangle$ = 3 +\pm 1% with no indication of evolution over 4.5 &lt; z &lt; 9.0. This implies that in our models nearly all of the ionizing photons need to be absorbed to account for the nebular emission. We compute the impact of our results on reionization, including the distributions for $\xi_\mathrm{ion}$ and f_esc, and the evolution and uncertainty of the UV luminosity function. Considering galaxies brighter than M(UV) &lt; -16 mag, we would produce an IGM hydrogen-ionized fraction of x_e=0.5 at 5.5 &lt; z &lt; 7.1, possibly too late compared to constraints from from QSO sightlines. Including fainter galaxies, M(UV) &lt; -14 mag, we obtain x_e = 0.5 at 6.7 &lt; z &lt; 9.6, fully consistent with QSO and CMB data. This implies that EoR galaxies produce plenty of ionizing photons, but these do not efficiently escape. This may be a result of high gas column densities combined with burstier star-formation histories, which limit the time massive stars are able to clear channels through the gas for ionizing photons to escape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08870v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Casey Papovich (Texas A &amp; M University), Justin W. Cole (Texas A &amp; M University), Weida Hu (Texas A &amp; M University), Steven L. Finkelstein (University of Texas at Austin), Lu Shen (Texas A &amp; M University), Pablo Arrabal Haro (NASA-Goddard), Ricardo O. Amor\'in (Instituto de Astrofiscia de Andalucia), Bren Backhaus (Kansas), Micaela B. Bagley (University of Texas at Austin, Kansas), Rachana Bhatawdekar (European Space Agency), Antonello Calabr\'o (INAF Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma), Adam C. Carnall (University of Edinburgh), Nikko Cleri (Penn State University), Emanuele Daddi (Universite Paris-Saclay), Mark Dickinson (NSF's NOIRlab), Norman Grogin (STScI), Benne W. Holwerda (University of Louisville), Anne E. Jaskot (Williams College), Anton E. Koekemoer (STScI), Mario Llerena (INAF Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma), Ray A. Lucas (STScI), Sara Mascia (Institute of Science and Technology Austria), Fabio Pacucci (Harvard CfA), Laura Pentericci (INAF Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma), Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez (Centro de Astrobiologica, CAB/CSIC-INTA), Nor Pirzkal (ESA/AURA STScI), Srinivasan Raghunathan (Center for AstroPhysical Surveys, National Center for Supercomputing Applications), Lisa-Marie Seill\'e (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), Rachel Somerville (Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute), L. Y. Aaron Yung (STScI)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic Study of Molecular Gas in Cometary Globule -- LBN 437</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bright-rimmed, cometary-shaped star-forming globules, associated with HII regions, are remnants of compressed molecular shells exposed to ultraviolet radiation from central OB-type stars. The interplay between dense molecular gas and ionizing radiation, analysed through gas kinematics, provides significant insights into the nature and dynamic evolution of these globules. This study presents the results of a kinematic analysis of the cometary globule, Lynds Bright Nebula (LBN) 437, focusing on the first rotational transition of 12CO and C18O molecular lines observed using the Taeduk Radio Astronomy Observatory (TRAO). The averaged 12CO spectrum shows a slightly skewed profile, suggesting the possibility of a contracting cloud. The molecular gas kinematics reveals signatures of infalling gas in the cometary head of LBN 437, indicating the initial stages of star formation. The mean infall velocity and mass infall rate towards the cometary head of LBN 437 are 0.25 km s^-1 and 5.08 * 10^-1 Msun yr^-1 respectively, which align well with the previous studies on intermediate or high-mass star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08872v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Aardra, Namitha Issac, Archana Soam, Blesson Mathew, Chang Won Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FEAST: JWST uncovers the emerging timescales of young star clusters in M83</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present JWST NIRCam observations of the emerging young star clusters (eYSCs) detected in the nearby spiral galaxy M83. The NIRcam mosaic encompasses the nuclear starburst, the bar, and the inner spiral arms. The eYSCs, detected in Pa$\alpha$ and Br$\alpha$ maps, have been largely missed in previous optical campaigns of young star clusters (YSCs). We distinguish between eYSCI, if they also have compact 3.3~$\mu$m PAH emission associated to them, and eYSCII, if they only appear as compact Pa$\alpha$ emitters. We find that the variations in the 3.3~$\mu$m PAH feature are consistent with an evolutionary sequence where eYSCI evolve into eYSCII and then optical YSCs. This sequence is clear in the F300M-F335M (tracing the excess in the \PAHlambda\ feature) and the F115W-F187N (tracing the excess in Pa$\alpha$) colors which become increasingly bluer as clusters emerge. The central starburst stands out as the region where the most massive eYSCs are currently forming in the galaxy. We estimate that only about 20~\% of the eYSCs will remain detectable as compact YSCs. Combining eYSCs and YSCs ($\leq$10 Myr) we recover an average clearing timescale of 6~Myr in which clusters transition from embedded to fully exposed. We see evidence of shorter emergence timescales ($\sim$5~Myr) for more massive ($&gt;5\times10^3$ \msun) clusters, while star clusters of $\sim 10^3$ \msun\ about 7~Myr. We estimate that eYSCs remain associated to the \PAHlambda\ emission 3--4~Myr. Larger samples of eYSC and YSC populations will provide stronger statistics to further test environmental and cluster mass dependencies on the emergence timescale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08874v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Knutas, Angela Adamo, Alex Pedrini, Sean T. Linden, Varun Bajaj, Jenna E. Ryon, Benjamin Gregg, Ahmad A. Ali, Eric P. Andersson, Arjan Bik, Giacomo Bortolini, Anne S. M. Buckner, Daniela Calzetti, Ana Duarte-Cabral, Bruce G. Elmegreen, Helena Faustino Vieira, John S. Gallagher, Kathryn Grasha, Kelsey Johnson, Thomas S. -Y. Lai, Drew Lapeer, Matteo Messa, G\"oran \"Ostlin, Elena Sabbi, Linda J. Smith, Monica Tosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamically-Driven Evolution of Molecular Gas in M83 Traced by CO 2-1/1-0 Line Ratio Variations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show the variations of the CO J=2-1/1-0 line ratio (R21) across the barred spiral galaxy M83, using the 46 pc resolution data from ALMA. The R21 map clearly evidences the systematic large-scale variations as a function of galactic structures. Azimuthally, it starts from low R21&lt;~0.7 in the interarm regions and becomes high ~&gt;0.7 in the bar and spiral arms, suggesting that the density and/or kinetic temperature of molecular gas increase by about a factor of 2-3. This evolution is seen even in the parts of spiral arms without star formation, and R21 is often elevated even higher to ~0.8-1.0 when HII regions exist in the vicinity. Radially, R21 starts very high &gt;~1.0 at the galactic center, remains low &lt;~0.7 in the bar region, increases to &gt;~0.7 around the bar end, and again decreases to &lt;~0.7 in the rest of disk where the spiral arms dominate. The evolutionary sequence is synchronized with galactic rotation, and therefore, it is determined largely by the galactic structures and dynamics and is governed by the galactic rotation timescales. The R21 map also shows that the influence of stellar feedback is localized and limited. Massive, large, and non-star forming molecular structures have low R21, which also suggests that the bulk molecular gas in the disk is not regulated by stellar feedback, but more likely by galactic structures and dynamics. These results are consistent with suggestions by the earlier studies of the Milky Way and other barred spiral galaxies, and thus, are likely general among barred spiral galaxies in the local Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08876v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Koda, Fumi Egusa, Akihiko Hirota, Amanda M Lee, Tsuyoshi Sawada, Fumiya Maeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XMM-Newton Conclusively Identifies an Active Galactic Nucleus in a Green Pea Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Green Pea galaxies are a class of compact, low-mass, low-metallicity star-forming galaxies in the relatively local universe. They are believed to be analogues of high-redshift galaxies that re-ionised the universe and, indeed, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) is now uncovering such populations at record redshifts. Intriguingly, JWST finds evidence suggestive of active galactic nuclei (AGN) in many of these distant galaxies, including the elusive Little Red Dots, that broadly lack any detectable X-ray counterparts. Intuitively, one would expect to detect an AGN in their low-redshift analogues with X-rays, yet no study to date has conclusively identified an X-ray AGN within a Green Pea galaxy. Here we present the deepest X-ray campaign of a Green Pea galaxy performed to date, obtained with the goal of discerning the presence of a (potentially low-luminosity) AGN. The target $-$ SDSS J082247.66 +224144.0 (J0822+2241 hereafter) $-$ was previously found to display a comparable X-ray spectral shape to more local AGN ($\Gamma$ $\sim$ 2) and a high luminosity ($L_{2-10\,{\rm keV}}$ $\sim$ 10$^{42}$ erg s$^{-1}$). We show that over 6.2 years (rest-frame), the 2$-$10 keV luminosity of J0822+2241 is constant, whereas the soft 0.5$-$2 keV flux has decreased significantly by $\sim$60%. We discuss possible scenarios to explain the X-ray properties of J0822+2241, finding transient low-column density obscuration surrounding an AGN to be the only plausible scenario. J0822+2241 thus provides further evidence that low-luminosity AGN activity could have contributed to the epoch of reionisation, and that local analogues are useful to derive a complete multi-wavelength picture of black hole growth in high redshift low luminosity AGN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08885v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter G. Boorman (Caltech, Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Ji\v{r}\'i Svoboda (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Daniel Stern (Jet Propulsion Laboratory), Bret D. Lehmer (Department of Physics, University of Arkansas, Arkansas Center for Space and Planetary Sciences), Abhijeet Borkar (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Murray Brightman (Caltech), Hannah P. Earnshaw (Caltech), Fiona A. Harrison (Caltech), Konstantinos Kouroumpatzakis (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Barbora Adamcov\'a (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Roberto J. Assef (Universidad Diego Portales), Matthias Ehle (European Space Agency), Brian Grefenstette (Caltech), Romana Grossov\'a (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences, Masaryk University), Maitrayee Gupta (Astronomical Institute of the Czech Academy of Sciences), Elias Kammoun (Caltech), Taiki Kawamuro (Osaka University), Lea Marcotulli (Yale Center for Astronomy and Astrophysics, Department of Physics, Yale University, Caltech), Romana Miku\v{s}incov\'a (INAF Istituto di Astrofisica e Planetologia Spaziali), Matthew J. Middleton (University of Southampton), Edward Nathan (Caltech), Joanna M. Piotrowska (Caltech), Jean J. Somalwar (Caltech), N\'uria Torres-Alb\`a (University of Virginia), Dominic J. Walton (University of Hertfordshire), Daniel R. Weisz (University of California, Berkeley)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALMA FACTS. II. Large Scale Variations in the 12CO(J=2-1) to 12CO(J=1-0) Line Ratio in Nearby Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present 12CO(J=1-0) mapping observations over ~1/2 of the optical disk of 12 nearby galaxies from the Fundamental CO 1-0 Transition Survey of nearby galaxies (FACTS), using the ALMA Total Power array. Variations in the 12CO(J=2-1)/12CO(J=1-0) line ratio r21 are investigated. The luminosity-weighted r21 of the 11 sample galaxies ranges from 0.52 to 0.69 with an average of 0.61. We use position-velocity diagrams along the major axis and tilted ring models to separate the normal rotating galactic disk from kinematic outliers that deviate from pure circular rotation. We find that r21 is systematically higher in outliers compared to the disk. We compare r21 between SA, SAB and SB galaxies, and find no significant difference in the average r21 depending on the presence of galactic bars. We find, however, that the radial gradient in r21 is bimodal, where a group containing all SA galaxies prefer constant or very shallow r21 gradients out 40% of the optical radius, while another group containing all SB galaxies have a steep r21 gradient, decreasing by ~20% before 40% of the optical radius, which also corresponds to the radius of the stellar bar. After this radius, these galaxies become consistent with a constant or shallow trend in r21. The large scale trend in r21 can have implications for how we interpret observations made solely in the 12CO(J=2-1) line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08912v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ada6b5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, Volume 980, Issue 1, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shinya Komugi, Tsuyoshi Sawada, Jin Koda, Fumi Egusa, Fumiya Maeda, Akihiko Hirota, Amanda M. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of Giant Radio Galaxies larger than 3 Mpc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Giant radio galaxies (GRG) are radio galaxies with physical sizes of their radio emission larger than 0.7 Mpc. Recently, the sample of GRGs has become large enough to study the extreme end of the GRG size distribution. We examine the properties of GRGs with largest linear sizes larger than 3 Mpc in order to shed light on the nature and origin of GRGs. We select, corroborate, and revise if necessary, the largest GRGs from literature. We add to these the GRGs we identified in our own search, combined with optical surveys and catalogues of spectroscopic and photometric redshifts in order to find their projected linear radio size. We study their radio power--size relation, the asymmetry in the lobes, their association with clusters of galaxies, as well as their bending angles.
  We present an unprecedented sample of 143 GRGs larger than 3 Mpc, of which 69 were newly found by us. The sample includes six GRGs with projected linear sizes clearly exceeding 5 Mpc and reaching up to 6.6 Mpc. We find that GRGs larger than 3 Mpc are distributed in redshift and radio luminosity indistinguishable from those of smaller GRGs. At most a single one of the GRGs larger than 3 Mpc can be classified as a clear Fanaroff-Riley (FR) type I source, and only 6 per cent deviate from a clear FR II radio morphology. One quarter of our GRGs show very diffuse lobes typical for remnant radio galaxies, and only 59 per cent show indications of hotspots in at least one lobe, with 38 per cent featuring a hotspot in both lobes. As in the case of smaller radio galaxies, the shorter lobe is most often also the brighter one. We find tentative evidence that the bending angle decreases with size of the GRG, but no trend with redshift is detected. The bending angles of GRGs &gt; 3 Mpc in known clusters are larger than for those GRGs not associated with clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09181v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Andernach, M. Br\"uggen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST &amp; ALMA Joint Analysis with [OII]$\lambda\lambda$3726,3729, [OIII]$\lambda$4363, [OIII]88$\mu$m, and [OIII]52$\mu$m: Multi-Zone Evolution of Electron Densities at $\mathbf{z\sim0-14}$ and Its Impact on Metallicity Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a JWST and ALMA detailed study of the ISM properties of high-redshift galaxies. Our JWST/NIRSpec IFU spectroscopy targeting three galaxies at $z=6-7$ detects key rest-frame optical emission lines, allowing us to derive [OII]$\lambda\lambda$3726,3729-based electron densities of $n_\mathrm{e,optical}\sim1000$ cm$^{-3}$ on average and [OIII]$\lambda$4363-based metallicities of $\mathrm{12+log(O/H)}=8.0-8.2$ in two galaxies. New ALMA Band 9/10 observations detect the [OIII]52$\mu$m line in one galaxy but do not in the others, resulting in FIR-based densities of $n_\mathrm{e,FIR}\lesssim500$ cm$^{-3}$ from the [OIII]52$\mu$m/[OIII]88$\mu$m ratios, systematically lower than the optical [OII]-based measurements. These low FIR-based densities are comparable to those at both $z\sim0$ and $z&gt;6$ in the literature, including JADES-GS-z14-0 at $z=14.18$, suggesting little evolution up to $z\sim14$, in contrast to the increasing trend of optical-based densities with redshift. By conducting a JWST and ALMA joint analysis using emission lines detected with both telescopes, we find that the observed FIR [OIII]52,88$\mu$m luminosities are too high to be explained by the optical-based densities at which they would be significantly collisionally de-excited. Instead, a 2-zone model with distinct high- and low-density regions is required to reproduce all observed lines, indicating that FIR [OIII] emission arises predominantly from low-density gas, while optical [OIII] and [OII] lines trace both regions. We further demonstrate that the direct-$T_\mathrm{e}$ method can sometimes significantly underestimate metallicities up to 0.8 dex due to the presence of the low-density gas not fully traced by optical lines alone, highlighting the importance of combining optical and FIR lines to accurately determine gas-phase metallicities in the early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09186v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichi Harikane, Ryan L. Sanders, Richard Ellis, Tucker Jones, Masami Ouchi, Nicolas Laporte, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Harley Katz, Kimihiko Nakajima, Yoshiaki Ono, Mansi Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Self-Interacting Dark Matter via Gravitational-Wave Background from Eccentric Supermassive Black Hole Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09219v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nature of dark matter is still mysterious despite various astronomical evidence. As a possible candidate, self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) can potentially resolve some issues appearing in cold dark matter paradigm. Here we investigate how SIDM around supermassive black holes (SMBH) in galaxy centers may form a density spike and imprint in the spectrum shape of stochastic gravitational-wave background from SMBH binaries (SMBHBs). Employing a refined dynamical friction formula and consistently evolving the orbital dynamics, we demonstrate that current pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) data is sensitive to the cross section of SIDM with $\sigma(v)/m_\chi\lesssim0.66\,\mathrm{cm}^2/\mathrm{g}$, comparable to other astrophysical probes. We also highlight the importance of including the eccentricity of SMBHBs in the parameter inference, which would affect the results significantly. Our findings reveal the promising potential of PTAs observations in probing the nature of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09219v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mu-Chun Chen, Yong Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Shape and Mass of the Galactic Dark Matter Halo from the Axisymmetric Jeans Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the density profile, shape, and virial mass of the Milky Way's dark matter halo using K giants (KG) from LAMOST and SDSS/SEGUE, as well as blue horizontal branch (BHB) stars from SDSS. Incorporating Gaia DR3 proper motions, we first investigate the velocity ellipsoid distribution within the $(R, |z|)$ space. The ellipsoids projected onto the $(v_R, v_z)$ plane exhibit near-spherical alignment. We then probe the underlying dark matter distribution using the axisymmetric Jeans equations with multi-Gaussian expansion (MGE) and the spherically aligned Jeans anisotropic modelling (JAM${\rm sph}$), allowing for different flattened dark matter density models. For each model, we apply two fitting approaches: fitting the KGs and BHBs separately or fit them simultaneously as two dynamical tracers in one gravitational potential. We find consistent results on the dark matter density profiles, $r_{200}$, and $M_{200}$ within a 1-$\sigma$ confidence region for models constrained by KGs, BHBs, and both. We find the strongest consistency between KGs and BHBs in constraining dark matter profiles for models incorporating radially varying halo flattening ($q(r_{\rm gc})$), which suggests the Milky Way's dark matter halo shape evolves with Galactocentric distance ($r_{\rm gc}$). Specifically, the halo flattening parameter $q_h$ decreases within $r_{\rm gc} &lt; 20$ kpc and increases for $r_{\rm gc} &gt; 20$ kpc. In this model, $M_{\rm tot} (&lt; 60~{\rm kpc}) = 0.533^{+0.061}_{-0.054} \times 10^{12}$ $M_{\odot}$, $r_{200}$ is $188\pm15$ kpc, with $M_{200}$ estimated at $0.820^{+0.210}_{-0.186} \times 10^{12} M_{\odot}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09243v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lan Zhang, Xiang-Xiang Xue, Ling Zhu, Ruizhi Zhang, Chengqun Yang, Shi Shao, Jiang Chang, Feilu Wang, Hao Tian, Gang Zhao, Chao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Presence of Angular-Velocity Offsets in Disk Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The well-known discrepancy in galactic rotation curves refers to the mismatch between observed rotational velocities and the velocities predicted by baryonic matter. In this study we investigate a potential pattern in the discrepancy, which may point to an underlying pattern in dark-halo distributions. By looking at rotational-velocity curves from an alternate perspective, the angular-velocity curves, it appears that the observed angular velocities and their corresponding baryonic predictions differ by a constant shift. That is, the discrepancy may be reduced to a constant angular-velocity term, independent of the radius. We test the generality of the suggested property by analysing 143 high-quality rotation curves. The property appears significant as it performs equally well (or better) than well-established dark-halo models. Compared to a Burkert profile, it is preferred in 60% of the cases, while relative to a Navarro Frenk White profile (NFW), it is superior in 73% of the cases. Next, by including the new phenomenological property within the dynamical equations, we find an explicit expression for the dark-halo profile. The new single-parameter profile is characterised by a remarkable property: it is intrinsically related to the baryonic distribution. Thus, information regarding the cuspy or cored nature of a particular dark halo, according to this profile, is encoded (and explicitly determined) by the respective baryonic behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09300v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomer Zimmerman, Lev Tal-Or, Roy Gomel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A weak Ly$\alpha$ halo for an extremely bright Little Red Dot. Indications of enshrouded SMBH growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09542v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The abundant population of "Little Red Dots" (LRDs)-compact objects with red UV to optical colors and broad Balmer lines at high redshift-is unveiling new insights into the properties of early active galactic nuclei (AGN). Perhaps the most surprising features of this population are the presence of Balmer absorption and ubiquitous strong Balmer breaks. Recent models link these features to an active supermassive black hole (SMBH) cocooned in very dense gas ($N_{\rm H}\sim10^{24}\,\rm cm^{-2}$). We present a stringent test of such models using VLT/MUSE observations of A2744-45924, the most luminous LRD known to date ($L_{\rm H\alpha}\approx10^{44}~\rm erg\,s^{-1}$), located behind the Abell-2744 lensing cluster at $z=4.464$ ($\mu=1.8$). We detect a moderately extended Ly$\alpha$ nebula ($h\approx5.7$ pkpc), spatially offset from the point-like H$\alpha$ seen by JWST. The Ly$\alpha$ emission is narrow ($\rm FWHM=270\pm 15~km\,s^{-1}$), spatially offset to H$\alpha$, and faint ($\rm Ly\alpha=0.07H\alpha$) compared to Ly$\alpha$ nebulae typically observed around quasars of similar luminosity. We detect compact N$\,$IV]$\lambda$1486 emission, spatially aligned with H$\alpha$, and a spatial shift in the far-UV continuum matching the Ly$\alpha$ offset. We discuss that H$\alpha$ and Ly$\alpha$ have distinct physical origins: H$\alpha$ originates from the AGN, while Ly$\alpha$ is powered by star formation. In the environment of A2744-45924, we identify four extended Ly$\alpha$ halos ($\Delta z&lt;0.02$, $\Delta r&lt;100$ pkpc). Their Ly$\alpha$ luminosities match expectations based on H$\alpha$ emission, indicating no evidence for radiation from A2744-45924 affecting its surroundings. The lack of strong, compact, and broad Ly$\alpha$ and the absence of a luminous extended halo, suggest that the UV AGN light is obscured by dense gas cloaking the SMBH with covering factor close to unity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09542v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Torralba, Jorryt Matthee, Gabriele Pezzulli, Tanya Urrutia, Max Gronke, Sara Mascia, Francesco D'Eugenio, Claudia Di Cesare, Anna-Christina Eilers, Jenny E. Greene, Edoardo Iani, Yuzo Ishikawa, Ruari Mackenzie, Rohan P. Naidu, Benjam\'in Navarrete, Gauri Kotiwale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expanding Ejecta Method: II. Framework for Cosmological Distance Measurements via Intensity Interferometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08856v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the potential of the expanding ejecta method (EEM) as a cosmological probe, leveraging its ability to measure angular diameter distances to supernovae (SNe) with intensity interferometry. We propose three distinct applications of the EEM: (1) using Type IIP SNe as moderate-distance geometric anchors to calibrate Cepheids, replacing other local distance indicators; (2) directly calibrating Type Ia SNe, bypassing conventional calibration methods; (3) constructing a fully independent Hubble diagram with Type IIP (Type Ia) SNe, entirely decoupled from the traditional distance ladder. Incorporating realistic SN populations, we forecast a Hubble constant precision with next-generation intensity interferometers of $1.6\%$, $1.1\%$, and $9.3\% \,(3.6\%)$, respectively, for the three different proposed applications. Future intensity interferometry could yield improvements to $1.2\%$, $0.6\%$, and $1.5\%\,(0.4\%)$. The EEM thus offers a powerful geometric alternative for cosmic distance determination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08856v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Dunsky, I-Kai Chen, Junwu Huang, Ken Van Tilburg, Robert V. Wagoner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured ionized winds shooting out from a quasar at relativistic speeds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Evidence indicates that supermassive black holes exist at the centers of most galaxies. Their mass correlates with the galactic bulge mass, suggesting a co-evolution with their host galaxies, most likely through powerful winds. X-ray observations have detected highly ionized winds outflowing at sub-relativistic speeds from the accretion disks around supermassive black holes. However, the limited spectral resolution of current X-ray instruments has left the physical structure and location of the winds poorly understood, hindering accurate estimates of their kinetic power. Here, the first XRISM observation of the luminous quasar, PDS 456, is reported. The high-resolution spectrometer Resolve onboard XRISM enabled the discovery of five discrete velocity components outflowing at 20-30% of the speed of light. This demonstrates that the wind structure is highly inhomogeneous, which likely consists of up to a million clumps. The mass outflow rate is estimated to be 60-300 solar masses per year, with the wind kinetic power exceeding the Eddington luminosity limit. Compared to the galaxy-scale outflows, the kinetic power is more than 3 orders of magnitude larger, while the momentum flux is 10 times larger. These estimates disfavor both energy- and momentum-driven outflow models. It suggests that such wind activity occurs in less than 10% of the quasar phase and/or that its energy/momentum is not efficiently transferred to the galaxy-scale outflows due to the clumpiness of the wind and the interstellar medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09171v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-025-08968-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature, May 14, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> XRISM collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation and Early Evolution of Protoplanetary Disks under Nonuniform Cosmic-Ray Ionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09231v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Angular momentum transport by magnetic fields is important for formation and evolution of protoplanetary disks. The effects of magnetic fields are suppressed due to non-ideal magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) effects such as ambipolar diffusion and Ohmic dissipation, which depend on the degree of ionization. Cosmic rays (CRs) are the primary source of ionization in star-forming clouds, and their distribution is nonuniform as it is affected by gas density and magnetic fields. Therefore, CRs, magnetic fields, and gas interact with each other. In this work, we develop a new fully implicit cosmic ray transport module in Athena++ and perform three-dimensional simulations of disk formation from collapse of molecular cloud cores. Since CRs are strongly attenuated in the dense gas at the disk scale, distribution of magnetic fields is considerably altered compared to conventional models assuming a uniform ionization rate. While the total magnetic fluxes accreted onto the disks remain similar as the gas outside the disks remain sufficiently ionized and well coupled, the magnetic fields in the disks are less twisted due to the stronger non-ideal MHD effects. As a consequence, magnetic angular momentum transport is strongly suppressed at the disk scale, resulting in more gravitationally unstable disks with more prominent spiral arms. Our simulations demonstrate influence of non-uniform ionization resulting from CR transport and attenuation on the disk formation and evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09231v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erika Nishio, Kengo Tomida, Yuki Kudoh, Shigeo S. Kimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating statistical significance for massive black hole binary mergers with space-based gravitational wave detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09446v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Important scientific discoveries should be backed by high statistical significance. In the 2030s, multiple space-based gravitational wave detectors are expected to operate. While many works aim to achieve quick and reliable detection and parameter estimation of millihertz gravitational wave sources, dedicated studies are lacking to assess the significance of space-based detectors. In this work, we propose a framework to assess the statistical significance of massive black hole binaries (MBHBs) detections with space-based gravitational wave detectors. We apply this algorithm to simulated data with Gaussian stationary noise and the complex LDC-2a dataset to measure the false alarm rate and significance of MBHB signals. We also analyze factors affecting the significance of MBHBs and design a method to mitigate multi-source confusion interference. In Gaussian noise conditions, MBHBs with a signal-to-noise ratio of about 7 can achieve $3 \sigma$ significance, and those with a signal-to-noise ratio of about 8 achieve $4 \sigma$. Our analysis demonstrates that all MBHB signals in the LDC-2a dataset have a significance exceeding $4.62 \sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09446v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yu Chen, En-Kun Li, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A 70 pc-Diameter Nova Super-remnant Surrounding the Recurrent Nova RS Ophiuchi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09510v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recurrent novae undergo thermonuclear-powered eruptions separated by less than 100 years, enabled by subgiant or red giant donors transferring hydrogen-rich matter at very high rates onto their massive white dwarf companions. The most-rapidly moving parts of envelopes ejected in successive recurrent nova events are predicted to overtake and collide with the slowest ejecta of the previous eruption, leading to the buildup of vast (~ 10 - 100 parsec) super-remnants surrounding all recurrent novae; but only three examples are currently known. We report deep narrowband imaging and spectroscopy which has revealed a ~ 70-parsec-diameter shell surrounding the frequently recurring nova RS Ophiuchi. We estimate the super-remnant mass to be ~ 20 - 200 solar masses, expanding at a few tens of km/s, with an age of order 50-100 kyr. Its extremely low surface brightness and large angular size help explain the hitherto surprising absence of nova super-remnants. Our results support the prediction that ALL recurrent novae are surrounded by similar extended structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09510v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael M. Shara, Kenneth M. Lanzetta, Alexandra Masegian, James T. Garland, Stefan Gromoll, Alexei Kniazev, Lee Townsend, David Zurek, Joanna Mikolajewska, David Valls-Gabaud, Frederick M. Walter, John K. Webb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The vertical structure of debris discs and the role of disc gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Debris discs provide valuable insights into the formation and evolution of exoplanetary systems. Their structures are commonly attributed to planetary perturbations, serving as probes of as-yet-undetected planets. However, most studies of planet-debris disc interactions ignore the disc's gravity, treating it as a collection of massless planetesimals. Here, using an analytical model, we investigate how the vertical structure of a back-reacting debris disc responds to secular perturbations from an inner, inclined planet. Considering the disc's axisymmetric potential, we identify two dynamical regimes: planet-dominated and disc-dominated, which may coexist, separated by a secular-inclination resonance. In the planet-dominated regime ($M_d/m_p\ll1$), we recover the classical result: a transient warp propagates outward until the disc settles into a box-like structure centered around the planetary orbit's initial inclination $I_p(0)$, with a distance-independent aspect ratio $\mathcal{H}(R)\approx I_p(0)$. In contrast, in the disc-dominated regime ($M_d/m_p\gtrsim1$), the disc exhibits dynamical rigidity, remaining thin and misaligned, with significantly suppressed inclinations and a sharply declining aspect ratio, $\mathcal{H}(R)\propto I_p(0)R^{-7/2}$. In the intermediate regime ($M_d/m_p\lesssim1$), the system exhibits a secular-inclination resonance, leading to long-lived, warp-like structures and a bimodal inclination distribution, containing both dynamically hot and cold populations. We provide analytic formulae describing these effects as a function of system parameters. We also find that the vertical density profile is intrinsically non-Gaussian and recommend fitting observations with non-zero slopes of $\mathcal{H}(R)$. Our results may be used to infer planetary parameters and debris disc masses based on observed warps and scale heights, as demonstrated for HD110058 and $\beta$ Pic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09578v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antranik A. Sefilian, Kaitlin M. Kratter, Mark C. Wyatt, Cristobal Petrovich, Philippe Th\'ebault, Renu Malhotra, Virginie Faramaz-Gorka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broad-Line AGN at 3.5&lt;z&lt;6: The Black Hole Mass Function and a Connection with Little Red Dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06772v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a sample of 50 H-alpha detected broad-line active galactic nuclei (BLAGN) at redshifts 3.5&lt;z&lt;6.8 using data from the CEERS and RUBIES surveys. We select these sources directly from JWST/NIRSpec G395M/F290LP spectra. We use a multi-step pre-selection and a Bayesian fitting procedure to ensure a high-quality sample of sources with broad Balmer lines and narrow forbidden lines. We compute rest-frame ultraviolet and optical spectral slopes for these objects, and determine that 10 BLAGN in our sample are also little red dots (LRDs). These LRD BLAGN, when examined in aggregate, show broader H-alpha line profiles and a higher fraction of broad-to-narrow component H-alpha emission than non-LRD BLAGN. Moreover, we find that ~66% of these objects are intrinsically reddened (beta (optical)&gt;0), independent of the contributions of emission lines to the broadband photometry. We construct the black hole (BH) mass function at 3.5&lt;z&lt;6 after computing robust observational and line detection completeness corrections. This BH mass function shows broad agreement with both recent JWST/NIRSpec and JWST/NIRCam WFSS based BH mass functions, though we extend these earlier results to log(M(BH)/M(sun)) &lt; 7. The derived BH mass function is consistent with a variety of theoretical models, indicating that the observed abundance of black holes in the early universe is not discrepant with physically-motivated predictions. The BH mass function shape resembles a largely featureless power-law, suggesting that any signature from black-hole seeding has been lost by redshift z~5-6. Finally, we compute the BLAGN UV luminosity function and find good agreement with JWST-detected BLAGN samples from recent works, finding that BLAGN hosts constitute &lt;10% of the total observed UV luminosity at all but the brightest luminosities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06772v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony J. Taylor, Steven L. Finkelstein, Dale D. Kocevski, Junehyoung Jeon, Volker Bromm, Ricardo O. Amorin, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Bren E. Backhaus, Micaela B. Bagley, Eduardo Ba\~nados, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Madisyn Brooks, Antonello Calabro, Oscar A. Chavez Ortiz, Yingjie Cheng, Nikko J. Cleri, Justin W. Cole, Kelcey Davis, Mark Dickinson, Callum Donnan, James S. Dunlop, Richard S. Ellis, Vital Fernandez, Adriano Fontana, Seiji Fujimoto, Mauro Giavalisco, Andrea Grazian, Jingsong Guo, Nimish P. Hathi, Benne W. Holwerda, Michaela Hirschmann, Kohei Inayoshi, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Yana Khusanova, Anton M. Koekemoer, Vasily Kokorev, Rebecca L. Larson, Gene C. K. Leung, Ray A. Lucas, Derek J. McLeod, Lorenzo Napolitano, Masafusa Onoue, Fabio Pacucci, Casey Papovich, Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, Nor Pirzkal, Rachel S. Somerville, Jonathan R. Trump, Stephen M. Wilkins, L. Y. Aaron Yung, Haowen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star formation and stellar &amp; AGN feedback in the absence of accretion, not gas stripping, set the quenching timescale in satellite galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Observational measurements hint at a peak in the quenching timescale of satellite galaxies in groups and clusters as a function of their stellar masses at $M_{\star} \approx 10^{9.5} \mathrm{M}_{\odot}$; less and more massive satellite galaxies quench faster. We investigate the origin of these trends using the EAGLE simulation in which they are qualitatively reproduced for satellites with $10^{9}&lt;M_{\star}/\mathrm{M}_\odot&lt;10^{11}$ around hosts of $10^{13}&lt;M_\mathrm{200c}/\mathrm{M}_\odot&lt;10^{14.6}$. We select gas particles of simulated galaxies at the time that they become satellites and track their evolution. Interpreting these data yields insights into the prevailing mechanism that leads to the depletion of the interstellar medium (ISM) and the cessation of star formation. We find that for satellites across our entire range in stellar mass the quenching timescale is to leading order set by the depletion of the ISM by star formation and stellar &amp; AGN feedback in the absence of sustained accretion of fresh gas. The turnover in the quenching timescale as a function of stellar mass is a direct consequence of the maximum in the star formation efficiency (or equivalently the minimum in the total -- stellar plus AGN -- feedback efficiency) at the same stellar mass. We can discern the direct stripping of the ISM by ram pressure and/or tides in the simulations; these mechanisms modulate the quenching timescale but do not drive its overall scaling with satellite stellar mass. Our findings argue against a scenario in which the turnover in the quenching timescale is a consequence of the competing influences of gas stripping and 'starvation'.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15183v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatolii I. Visser-Zadvornyi (Kapteyn Institute), Mary E. Carstairs (Durham-ICC), Kyle A. Oman (Durham-ICC), Marc A. W. Verheijen (Kapteyn Institute)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster-lensed supernova yields from the Vera C. Rubin Observatory and Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01068v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Through gravitational lensing, galaxy clusters can magnify supernovae (SNe) and create multiple images of the same SN. This enables measurements of cosmological parameters, which will be increasingly important in light of upcoming telescopic surveys. We study the prospects of detecting strongly lensed SNe in cluster fields with the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope (Roman)'s High Latitude Time Domain Survey (HLTDS) and the Vera C. Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST). We employed two approaches: one focusing on known multiply imaged galaxies behind clusters, along with the SN rates specific to those galaxies, and another based on the expected number of lensed SNe exploding in a given volume behind a galaxy cluster. We collected all the clusters in the literature that feature a well-constrained lens model and multiply imaged galaxies behind clusters with high-quality data for the lensed galaxies. This allowed us to determine the SN rate for each galaxy. We provide predictions for 46 clusters visible to the Vera C. Rubin Observatory, as well as for 9 observable by Roman's HLTDS, depending on whether the clusters fall within the survey's observing field. We predict that the number of multiply imaged SNe discovered by LSST in its first three years is $3.95 \pm 0.89$ from the first approach or $4.94 \pm 1.02$ from the second. For the HLTDS, the expected number of multiply imaged SNe ranges from $0.38 \pm 0.15$ to $5.2 \pm 2.2$, depending on the specific cluster observed, however, the fields to be targeted remain a matter of discussion. We conclude that LSST offers great prospects for detecting multiply imaged SNe. Our predictions are effectively lower limits, as we only considered the most massive and well-studied clusters. We provide a recommendation for HLTDS observing field selection, namely: either MACS J0553.4-3342 or Abell 1758a should be observed by the survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01068v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451457</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 697, A146 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Bronikowski, T. Petrushevska, J. D. R. Pierel, A. Acebron, D. Donevski, B. Apostolova, N. Blagorodnova, T. Jankovi\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Deuterated Hydrocarbon Nanoparticles in the Whirlpool Galaxy, M51</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02538v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deuteration of hydrocarbon material, including polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs), has been proposed to account for the low gas-phase abundances of D in the interstellar medium. JWST spectra of four star-forming regions in M51 show an emission feature, with central wavelength $\sim$4.647$\mu$m and FWHM 0.0265$\mu$m, corresponding to the C-D stretching mode in aliphatic hydrocarbons. The emitting aliphatic material is estimated to have (D/H)$_{\rm aliph}\approx 0.17\pm0.02$ -- a factor $\sim$$10^4$ enrichment relative to the overall interstellar medium (ISM). On $\sim$$50\,$pc scales, deuteration levels toward four H$\,$II regions in M51 are 2-3 times higher than in the Orion Bar photodissociation region (PDR), with implications for the processes responsible for the formation and evolution of hydrocarbon nanoparticles, including PAHs. The deuteration of the aliphatic material is found to anticorrelate with helium ionization in the associated H$\,$II, suggesting that harsh FUV radiation may act to lower the deuteration of aliphatics in PDRs near massive stars. No evidence is found for deuteration of aromatic material, with (D/H)$_{\rm arom} \lesssim 0.016$: deuteration of the aliphatic material exceeds that of the aromatic material by at least a factor 10. The observed levels of deuteration may account for the depletion of D observed in the Galactic interstellar medium. If so, the $4.65\mu$m feature may be detectable in absorption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02538v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adc991</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophys. J. Letters, 948:L42 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>B. T. Draine, Karin Sandstrom, Daniel A. Dale, J. -D. T. Smith, Ryan Chown, Grant P. Donnelly, Sara E. Duval, Cory M. Whitcomb, Angela Adamo, L. Armus, Danielle A. Berg, Torsten B\"oker, Alberto D. Bolatto, Martha L. Boyer, Daniela Calzetti, B. G. Elmegreen, Brandt A. L. Gaches, Karl D. Gordon, L. K. Hunt, R. C. Kennicutt, Ralf S. Klessen, Thomas S. -Y. Lai, Adam K. Leroy, Sean T. Linden, Alex Pedrini, Noah S. J. Rogers, Julia C. Roman-Duval, Eva Schinnerer, Evan B. Skillman, Fabian Walter, Tony D. Weinbeck, Benjamin F. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spheroidal Analog Method for Modeling Irregular Porous Aggregates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02970v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is shown that the optical properties of an irregular porous grain with effective radius $a_{\rm eff}\lesssim 3\lambda$ (where $\lambda$ is the wavelength) can be well approximated by a ``spheroidal analog'': a spheroid with appropriate axial ratio and size, with a dielectric function obtained from an effective medium theory. Prescriptions for specifying the axial ratio and porosity of the spheroidal analog, based on simple geometric properties, are given. The accuracy of the spheroidal analogue method is studied for irregular grains with a range of structures and porosities. Different effective medium theories are compared; Bruggeman's theory is found to give the best results. The accuracy of the spheroidal analog method justifies the use of spheroids for modeling absorption, scattering and polarization by interstellar, circumstellar, or interplanetary dust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02970v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adc57d</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophysical Journal, 985:10 (2025 May 20)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>B. T. Draine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CEERS: Forging the First Dust Grains in the Universe? A Population of Galaxies with spectroscopically-derived Extremely Low Dust Attenuation (GELDA) at 4.0&lt;z&lt;11.4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13118v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the coevolution of metals and dust in 173 galaxies at $4.0&lt;z&lt;11.4$ using NIRSpec spectroscopy. Focusing on galaxies with extremely low dust attenuation, we explore their physical processes using a new CIGALE version that incorporates spectroscopic and photometric data. Comparing observations with models, we derive key physical parameters. We identify 49 galaxies with extremely low dust attenuation (GELDAs), characterized by $A_{FUV}=0$ within $2\sigma$ and $M_{star}&lt;10^9 M_\odot$. The stacked spectra reveal a very blue UV slope ($\beta_{FUV} =-2.451\pm-0.066$) and Balmer decrement H$\alpha$/H$\beta = 2.932\pm-0.660$, consistent with no dust attenuation. GELDAs are more common at $z&gt;8.8$ (83.3%) than at $z&lt;8.8$ (26.3%) suggesting they dominate the early Universe. Assuming a prior FIR dust spectrum (from ALPINE), we examine dust-stellar mass trends. The $M_{dust}$ vs. $M_{star}$ diagram shows upper and lower sequences linked by possible transitional galaxies. A transition at $M_{star}=10^8.5 M_\odot$ ($Z_{crit}=12+\log_{10}(O/H)=7.60$ or $Z/Z_\odot=0.1$) may mark the shift from stellar dust production to ISM grain growth, in agreement with theoretical predictions. Our full sample has a high mean gas fraction ($f_{gas}&gt;0.9$), indicating retained gas across all galaxies. Their small sizes and large gas masses imply high gas surface densities but relatively low star formation efficiency. High-redshift GELDAs may naturally explain the observed excess of bright galaxies at $z&gt;9$ compared to theoretical expectations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13118v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Burgarella, V\'eronique Buat, Patrice Theul\'e, Jorge Zavala, Mark Dickinson, Pablo Arrabal Haro, Micaela B. Bagley, M\'ed\'eric Boquien, Nikko Cleri, Tim Dewachter, Henry C. Ferguson, Vital Fern\`andez, Steven L. Finkelstein, Eric Gawiser, Andrea Grazian, Norman Grogin, Benne W. Holwerda, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Lisa Kewley, Allison Kirkpatrick, Dale Kocevski, Anton M. Koekemoer, Arianna Long, Jennifer Lotz, Ray A. Lucas, Bahram Mobasher, Casey Papovich, Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\`alez, Nor Pirzkal, Swara Ravindranath, Giulia Rodighiero, Yannick Roehlly, Caitlin Rose, Lise-Marie Seill\'e, Rachel Somerville, Steve Wilkins, Guang Yang, L. Y. Aaron Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kinematic Signature of the Warp and Waves in the Milky Way Disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18014v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using over 170,000 red clump (RC) stars selected from LAMOST and APOGEE, we conduct a detailed analysis of the stellar $V_{Z}$ as a function of $L_{Z}$ (or $R_{g}$) across different $\phi$ bins for various disk populations. The $V_{Z}$ of the whole RC sample stars exhibits a wave-like pattern superimposed on an exponentially increasing trend, indicating the contribution from disk warp, disk flare and disk waves. Our results across various populations suggest that the thin disk is similar to the whole RC sample behavior, while the thick disk displays a wave-like pattern superimposed on a linearly increasing trend, meaning that the features of disk warp and waves are present in both thin and thick disks, and the disk flare feature is only present in the thin disk. These results indicate that the disk warp is potentially driven by secular processes like disk perturbations from intergalactic magnetic fields and a misaligned dark halo. The line-of-node of the disk warp of various populations displays a slight difference, with $\phi_{0}$ = 5.68 $\pm$ 2.91 degree for the whole RC sample stars, $\phi_{0}$ = 5.78 $\pm$ 2.89 degree for the thin disk stars, and $\phi_{0}$ = 4.10 $\pm$ 3.43 degree for the thick disk stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18014v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weixiang Sun, Han Shen, Biwei Jiang, Xiaowei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PECCARY: A novel approach for characterizing orbital complexity, stochasticity, and regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11970v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Permutation Entropy and statistiCal Complexity Analysis for astRophYsics (PECCARY) is a computationally inexpensive, statistical method by which any time-series can be characterized as predominantly regular, complex, or stochastic. Elements of the PECCARY method have been used in a variety of physical, biological, economic, and mathematical scenarios, but have not yet gained traction in the astrophysical community. This study introduces the PECCARY technique with the specific aims to motivate its use in and optimize it for the analysis of astrophysical orbital systems. PECCARY works by decomposing a time-dependent measure, such as the x-coordinate or orbital angular momentum time-series, into ordinal patterns. Due to its unique approach and statistical nature, PECCARY is well-suited for detecting preferred and forbidden patterns (a signature of chaos), even when the chaotic behavior is short-lived or when working with a relatively short duration time-series or small sets of time-series data. A variety of examples are used to demonstrate the capabilities of PECCARY. These include mathematical examples (sine waves, varieties of noise, sums of sine waves, well-known chaotic functions), a double pendulum system, and astrophysical tracer particle simulations with potentials of varying intricacies. Since the adopted timescale used to diagnose a given time-series can affect the outcome, a method is presented to identify an ideal sampling scheme, constrained by the overall duration and the natural timescale of the system. The accompanying PECCARY Python package and its usage are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11970v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S\'oley \'O. Hyman, Kathryne J. Daniel, David A. Schaffner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chasing the beginning of reionization in the JWST era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02989v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent JWST observations at $z &gt; 6$ may imply galactic ionizing photon production above prior expectations. Under observationally motivated assumptions about escape fractions, these suggest a $z \sim 8-9$ end to reionization, in tension with the $z &lt; 6$ end required by the Ly$\alpha$ forest. In this work, we use radiative transfer simulations to understand what different observations tell us about when reionization ended and when it started. We consider a model that ends too early ($z_{\rm end} \approx 8$) alongside two more realistic scenarios with $z_{\rm end} \approx 5$: one starting late ($z \sim 9$) and another early ($z \sim 13$). We find that the latter requires up to an order-of-magnitude evolution in galaxy ionizing properties at $6 &lt; z &lt; 12$, perhaps in tension with measurements of $\xi_{\rm ion}$ by JWST, which indicate little evolution. We study how these models compare to recent measurements of the Ly$\alpha$ forest opacity, mean free path, IGM thermal history, visibility of $z &gt; 8$ Ly$\alpha$ emitters, and the patchy kSZ signal from the CMB. We find that neither of the late-ending scenarios is strongly disfavored by any single data set. However, a majority of observables, spanning several distinct types of observations, prefer a late start. Not all probes agree with this conclusion, hinting at a possible lack of concordance arising from deficiencies in observations and/or theoretical modeling. Observations by multiple experiments (including JWST, Roman, and CMB-S4) in the coming years will establish a concordance picture of reionization's beginning or uncover such deficiencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02989v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Cain, Garett Lopez, Anson D'Aloisio, Julian B. Munoz, Rolf A. Jansen, Rogier A. Windhorst, Nakul Gangolli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Red giant - jet collisions in galactic nuclei I: 3D hydrodynamical model of a few stellar orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17773v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Several models have been proposed to explain missing red giants (RGs) near the Galactic centre. Recently, a scenario has been suggested that predicts, among other processes, a long-term ablation of the surface layers of RGs during their repetitive passages through the Galactic jet (Zaja\v{c}ek et al., 2020). In this study, we perform detailed three-dimensional numerical modelling of this phenomenon. We calculate the ablation rate of the surface layers of a RG orbiting the supermassive black hole (SMBH) as it passes through the nuclear jet. In particular, we model the jet-star interaction for approximately 10 passages for the closer orbital distance of $10^{-3}\,\text{pc}$ and 2 passages for $10^{-2}\,\text{pc}$. We find that the mass loss due to ablation by the jet behaves with time as $\Delta M_{\star}\propto \sqrt{t}$ and the total ablated mass during a single active galactic nucleus (AGN) phase ($10^5$ years) is $\sim 10^{-4}\,M_{\odot}$. We arrive at similar rates of the stellar ablation for the relatively smaller jet luminosity $10^{42}\,\text{erg}\,\text{s}^{-1}$ as in the previous analytical calculations. For larger jet luminosities of $10^{44}$ and $10^{48}\,\text{erg}\,\text{s}^{-1}$, the ablation rates inferred from $\sim 10$ interactions as well as extrapolated power-law fits are significantly lower than analytical values. Overall, the mass ablation rate per interaction and the extrapolated cumulative mass loss during the jet activity are comparable to the stellar-wind mass loss. For the smallest orbital distance of $10^{-3}\,\text{pc}$, we also track the thermal behaviour of the stellar surface layer, whose temperature appears to grow rapidly during the first 10 passages from $\sim 3600\,{\rm K}$ (spectral type M) to $\sim 8500\,{\rm K}$ (spectral type A). RG-jet interactions can thus lead to observable changes in the nuclear stellar population during the jet existence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17773v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Kurf\"urst (MUNI, Brno), Michal Zaja\v{c}ek (MUNI, Brno), Norbert Werner (MUNI, Brno), Ji\v{r}\'i Krti\v{c}ka (MUNI, Brno)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weakness of X-rays and Variability in High-redshift AGNs with Super-Eddington Accretion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03653v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) observations enable the exploration of active galactic nuclei (AGNs) with broad-line emission in the early universe. Despite their clear radiative and morphological signatures of AGNs in rest-frame optical bands, complementary evidence of AGN activity - such as X-ray emission and UV/optical variability - remains rarely detected. The weakness of X-rays and variability in these broad-line emitters challenges the conventional AGN paradigm, indicating that the accretion processes or environments around the central black holes (BHs) differ from those of low-redshift counterparts. In this work, we study the radiation spectra of super-Eddington accretion disks enveloped by high-density coronae. Radiation-driven outflows from the disk transport mass to the poles, resulting in moderately optically-thick, warm coronae formed through effective inverse Comptonization. This mechanism leads to softer X-ray spectra and larger bolometric correction factors for X-rays compared to typical AGNs, while being consistent with those of JWST AGNs and low-redshift super-Eddington accreting AGNs. In this scenario, UV/optical variability is suppressed due to photon trapping within super-Eddington disks, while X-ray emissions remain weak yet exhibit significant relative variability. These characteristics are particularly evident in high-redshift AGNs powered by lower-mass BHs with $\lesssim 10^{7-8}~M_\odot$, which undergo rapid mass accretion following overmassive evolutionary tracks relative to the BH-to-stellar mass correlation in the local universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03653v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Inayoshi, Shigeo S. Kimura, Hirofumi Noda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectropolarimetry of A Nuclear Transient AT2023clx: Revealing The Geometrical Alignment between The Transient Outflow and The Nuclear Dusty Region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19024v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: AT2023clx, which occurred in NGC3799 with a Low-Ionization Nuclear Emission-Line Region (LINER), is one of the most nearby nuclear transients classified as a tidal disruption event (TDE). We present three-epoch spectropolarimetric follow-up observations of AT2023clx. We detected two polarization components; one is a constant polarization of $\sim 1\%$ originated from an aspherical outflow associated with the transient, while the other is a blue-excess polarization toward $\sim 2\%$ originated from a nuclear dusty environment via light echoes. The polarization angle flipped by 90 degrees between the two epochs, indicating that the outflow direction was perpendicular to the dust plane. Furthermore, the polarized flux might suggest that the nuclear dust favors relatively large grains, potentially offering constraints on its physical properties. Such polarization features -- the blue excess and the 90-degree flip -- have never been observed in previous TDE polarization samples, highlighting unique mechanisms behind AT2023clx. We propose possible scenarios: the disruption of a star formed within or captured by a nuclear dusty cloud. Given the LINER nature of NGC3799, the dusty region may possibly be linked to a torus or disk associated with a weak Active Galactic Nucleus (AGN). Furthermore, as a more speculative scenario, the event might have been triggered by AGN-like activity, potentially linked to changing-look AGNs or ambiguous nuclear transients. These findings highlight the power of time-series spectropolarimetry of TDEs, not only in probing the origins of nuclear transients, but also in investigating the physical properties of nuclear dust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19024v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohki Uno, Keiichi Maeda, Takashi Nagao, Giorgos Leloudas, Panos Charalampopoulos, Seppo Mattila, Kentaro Aoki, Kenta Taguchi, Miho Kawabata, Javier Moldon, Miguel P\'erez-Torres, Miika Pursiainen, Thomas Reynolds</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IAEmu: Learning Galaxy Intrinsic Alignment Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05235v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The intrinsic alignments (IA) of galaxies, a key contaminant in weak lensing analyses, arise from correlations in galaxy shapes driven by tidal interactions and galaxy formation processes. Accurate IA modeling is essential for robust cosmological inference, but current approaches rely on perturbative methods that break down on nonlinear scales or on expensive simulations. We introduce IAEmu, a neural network-based emulator that predicts the galaxy position-position ($\xi$), position-orientation ($\omega$), and orientation-orientation ($\eta$) correlation functions and their uncertainties using mock catalogs based on the halo occupation distribution (HOD) framework. Compared to simulations, IAEmu achieves ~3% average error for $\xi$ and ~5% for $\omega$, while capturing the stochasticity of $\eta$ without overfitting. The emulator provides both aleatoric and epistemic uncertainties, helping identify regions where predictions may be less reliable. We also demonstrate generalization to non-HOD alignment signals by fitting to IllustrisTNG hydrodynamical simulation data. As a fully differentiable neural network, IAEmu enables $\sim$10,000$\times$ speed-ups in mapping HOD parameters to correlation functions on GPUs, compared to CPU-based simulations. This acceleration facilitates inverse modeling via gradient-based sampling, making IAEmu a powerful surrogate model for galaxy bias and IA studies with direct applications to Stage IV weak lensing surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05235v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sneh Pandya, Yuanyuan Yang, Nicholas Van Alfen, Jonathan Blazek, Robin Walters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Astrophysical Anomalies in 99.6 Million Cutouts from the Hubble Legacy Archive Using AnomalyMatch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03508v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Astronomical archives contain vast quantities of unexplored data that potentially harbour rare and scientifically valuable cosmic phenomena. We leverage new semi-supervised methods to extract such objects from the Hubble Legacy Archive. We have systematically searched approximately 100 million image cutouts from the entire Hubble Legacy Archive using the recently developed AnomalyMatch method, which combines semi-supervised and active learning techniques for the efficient detection of astrophysical anomalies. This comprehensive search rapidly uncovered a multitude of astrophysical anomalies presented here that significantly expand the inventory of known rare objects. Among our discoveries are 138 new candidate gravitational lenses, 18 jellyfish galaxies, and 417 mergers or interacting galaxies. The efficiency and accuracy of our iterative detection strategy allows us to trawl the complete archive within just 2-3 days, highlighting its potential for large-scale astronomical surveys. We present a detailed overview of these newly identified objects, discuss their astrophysical significance, and demonstrate the considerable potential of AnomalyMatch to efficiently explore extensive astronomical datasets, including, e.g., upcoming Euclid data releases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03508v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David O'Ryan, Pablo G\'omez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
