<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 01:27:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>MrMARTIAN: A Multi-resolution Mass Reconstruction Algorithm Combining Free-form and Analytic Components</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present ${\tt MrMARTIAN}$ (Multi-resolution MAximum-entropy Reconstruction Technique Integrating Analytic Node), a new hybrid strong lensing (SL) modeling algorithm. By incorporating physically motivated analytic nodes into the free-form method ${\tt MARS}$, ${\tt MrMARTIAN}$ enables stable and flexible mass reconstructions while mitigating oversmoothing in the inner mass profile. Its multi-resolution framework increases the degrees of freedom in regions with denser strong lensing constraints, thereby enhancing computational efficiency for a fixed number of free parameters. We evaluate the performance of ${\tt MrMARTIAN}$ using publicly available simulated SL data and find that it consistently outperforms ${\tt MARS}$ in recovering both mass and magnification. In particular, it delivers significantly more stable reconstructions when multiple images are sparsely distributed. Finally, we apply ${\tt MrMARTIAN}$ to the galaxy cluster MACS J0416.1--2403, incorporating two analytic nodes centered on the northeastern and southwestern BCGs. Our mass model, constrained by 412 multiple images, achieves an image-plane rms scatter of ~0".11, the smallest to date for this dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13262v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangjun Cha, M. James Jee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A catalog to unite them all: REGALADE, a revised galaxy compilation for the advanced detector era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13267v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many applications in transient science, gravitational wave follow-up, and galaxy population studies require all-sky galaxy catalogs with reliable distances, extents, and stellar masses. However, existing catalogs often lack completeness beyond $\sim 100$ Mpc, suffer from stellar contamination, or do not provide homogeneous stellar mass estimates and size information. Our goal is to build a high-purity, high-completeness, all-sky galaxy catalog out to 2,000 Mpc, specifically designed to support time-domain and multi-messenger astrophysics. We combined major galaxy catalogs and deep imaging surveys -- including the Legacy Surveys, Pan-STARRS, DELVE, and SDSS -- and added spectroscopic, photometric, and redshift-independent distances. We cleaned the sample using the Gaia catalog to remove stars, and visually inspected all ambiguous cases below 100 Mpc through a classification platform that gathered 20,000 expert votes. Stellar masses were estimated using optical and mid-infrared profile-fit photometry, and we improved the accuracy of photometric distances by combining multiple independent estimates. The resulting catalog, REGALADE, includes nearly 80 million galaxies with distances under 2,000 Mpc. It provides stellar masses for 88\% of the sample and ellipse fits for 80\%. REGALADE is more than 90\% complete for massive galaxies out to 360 Mpc. In science tests, it recovers 60\% more known supernova hosts, doubles the number of low-luminosity transient hosts, and identifies more reliable hosts for ultraluminous and hyperluminous X-ray sources. REGALADE is the most complete and reliable all-sky galaxy catalog to date for the nearby Universe, built for real-world applications in transient and multi-messenger astrophysics. The full dataset, visual classifications, and code will be released to support broad community use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13267v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Tranin, Nadejda Blagorodnova, Marco A. G\'omez-Mu\~noz, Maxime Wavasseur, Paul J. Groot, Lloyd Landsberg, Fiorenzo Stoppa, Steven Bloemen, Paul M. Vreeswijk, Dani\"elle L. A. Pieterse, Jan van Roestel, Simone Scaringi, Sara Faris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPARCS -- combining radiation hydrodynamics with non-equilibrium metal chemistry in the SWIFT astrophysical code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present SPARCS, which combines the moment-based radiative transfer method SPH-M1RT with the non-equilibrium metal chemistry solver CHIMES in the modern highly-parallel astrophysical code SWIFT. SPARCS enables on-the-fly radiation hydrodynamics simulations, with multi-frequency ultraviolet radiative transfer coupled with all ionisation states of 11 major elements, in the presence of dust, cosmic ray ionization and heating, and self-gravity. Direct radiation pressure on gas and dust is also accounted for. We validate SPARCS against analytic solutions and standard photo-ionization codes such as CLOUDY in idealized tests. As an example application, we simulate an ionization front propagating through an inhomogeneous interstellar medium with solar metallicity. We produce mock optical emission line observations with the level population calculation code HyLight and the diagnostic radiative transfer code RADMC3D. We find that non-equilibrium effects and inhomogeneities can boost the low ion fractions by up to an order of magnitude. Possible applications of SPARCS include studying the dynamical impact of radiation on gas in star-forming regions, and in the interstellar and circumgalactic medium, as well as interpreting line diagnostics in such environments, and galactic or AGN outflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13277v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsang Keung Chan, Alexander J. Richings, Tom Theuns, Yuankang Liu, Matthieu Schaller, Mladen Ivkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of Turbulence in Post-shock Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersonic isothermal turbulence is ubiquitous in the interstellar medium. This work presents high-resolution AREPO hydrodynamical simulations of isolated shocks moving through supersonic turbulence to study the development and evolution of turbulence in the pre- and post-shock regions. We find that shocks can amplify turbulent energy in the post-shock region while inducing a preferential orientation for the vorticity. This results in the creation of anisotropic turbulence in the post-shock region. Turbulent energy and dissipation are also strongly enhanced near the shock front. By applying typical scalings from the cold neutral medium to simulations, we find that shocks moving into turbulence on the scale of superbubbles can generate compressive flows on the order of $10^{3} M_{\odot}$/Myr. Our results also show good agreement with related studies on turbulent fluctuations generated by shocks in pure fluid mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13291v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael M. Foley, Philip Mocz, Blakesley Burkhart, Lars Hernquist, Alyssa Goodman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact groups of galaxies in the TNG100 simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the TNG100 cosmological simulation, we study the formation and evolution of compact groups of galaxies. Over a redshift range of $0 \lesssim z \lesssim 0.2$, we identify these compact groups as FoF galaxy groups with high mean surface brightness ($\overline{\mu}_r &lt; 26.33 ~ \mathrm{mag~arcsec^{-2}}$) and a minimum of 4 galaxy members. Typically, our compact groups have a median characteristic size of $\sim$$150$ kpc, 1D velocity dispersions of $150 ~ {\rm km ~ s^{-1}}$, and stellar masses around $2\times 10^{11} ~ M_{\odot}$. Roughly 1\% of galaxies of stellar mass above $10^9 ~ M_{\odot}$ lie in physically dense compact groups. We found that these systems do not constitute a separate category within the broader population of galaxy groups; instead, they represent the lower end of the size distribution in the sequence of galaxy group sizes. We traced their evolution backward in time, revealing that they initially form as galaxies systems with a mean low surface brightness that systematically increases to a peak value before stabilizing over time, exhibiting oscillatory behaviour over the following several Gyrs during which mergers may occur. Mergers often transform compact groups with typically four members into galaxy pairs or triplets, which may eventually can increase again their number of members accreting a new galaxy. Nevertheless, the full merging of all constituent galaxies into a single massive galaxy is a rare phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13293v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno M. Celiz, Jos\'e A. Benavides, Mario G. Abadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeerKAT-derived HI kinematics and the Baryonic Tully-Fisher Relation in the X-ray luminous cluster Abell 3408</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Significant advances in observational capabilities are continuously transforming our understanding of the dense environment of galaxy clusters and its impact on individual galaxies. Discerning between intrinsic and externally-induced properties of galaxies, including their gas kinematics, is a key diagnostic in the field of galaxy evolution. In this work, we present MeerKAT HI spectral line observations of the redshift z $\sim$ 0.042 galaxy cluster Abell 3408. A total of 64 galaxies are detected in HI in this X-ray-luminous galaxy cluster (L$_{X}$ $\sim$ 3 $\times$ 10$^{43}$ ergs s$^{-1}$). We model the HI morphology and gas kinematics of the individual galaxies, using a semi-automated pipeline based on CANNUBI and pyBBarolo. The pipeline was developed and tested as part of this study. Of the 64 galaxies detected in the cluster, we successfully modelled 16, while the remaining galaxies exhibit disturbed HI morphologies, insufficient angular or velocity resolution. We combine the galaxies with converged kinematic fits with 67 field galaxies from the MeerKAT spectral line survey early science data ($\langle$z$\rangle$ = 0.0435) to produce a measurement of the Baryonic Tully-Fisher Relation (bTFr) that encompasses a broader range of environment and provides a useful comparison. We find a slope ($\alpha$ = 3.66$^{+0.32}_{-0.28}$) for this relation, which is consistent with that found from the MIGHTEE bTFr derived from the same definition. Interestingly, HI detections of the Abell 3408 galaxy cluster galaxies are seen to extend the bTFr of the MIGHTEE sample, both in mass and velocity, despite their cluster environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13312v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xola Ndaliso, Tariq Blecher, Roger Deane, Ed Elson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A $\tau-$DM relation for FRB hosts?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13317v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been proposed that measurements of scattering times ($\tau$) from fast radio bursts (FRB) may be used to infer the FRB host dispersion measure (DM) and its redshift. This approach relies on the existence of a correlation between $\tau$ and DM within FRB hosts such as that observed for Galactic pulsars. We assess the measurability of a $\tau - $DM$_{\rm host}$ relation through simulated observations of FRBs within the ASKAP/CRAFT survey, taking into account instrumental effects. We show that even when the FRB hosts intrinsically follow the $\tau - $DM relation measured for pulsars, this correlation cannot be inferred from FRB observations; this limitation arises mostly from the large variance around the average cosmic DM value given by the Macquart relation, the variance within the $\tau - $DM relation itself, and observational biases against large $\tau$ values. We argue that theoretical relations have little utility as priors on redshift, e.g., for purposes of galaxy identification, and that the recent lack of an observed correlation between scattering and DM in the ASKAP/CRAFT survey is not unexpected, even if our understanding of a $\tau - $DM$_{\rm host}$ relation is correct.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13317v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lluis Mas-Ribas, Clancy W. James</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Little Red reionization factories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note, we suggest the possibility that an elucidation of the nature of the numerous Little Red Dots (LRDs) at high redshifts, may facilitate the resolution of another concurrent cosmic puzzle, namely reionization. Specifically, it is hypothesized that intergalactic HI gas is compelled by the tidal field associated with a growing gravitational entropy, in the form of gas streams, into colliding at the LRD sites. The resulting shock heating and compression encourage starburst activities, which subsequently photo-ionize the gas into HII, that in turn shines into the rest-optical via bremsstrahlung radiation within the minimal-timescale-cutoff (i.e., red) regime, before escaping back into the intergalactic space, propelled by the newly fusion-injected energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13541v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cosmic Dance: Observational Detection of Coherent Spin in Galaxy Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin of galaxy clusters encodes key information about their formation, dynamics, and the influence of large-scale structure. However, whether clusters possess statistically significant spin and how to measure it observationally remain open questions. Here, we present the first observational statistical detection of coherent spin in galaxy clusters, by using a sample of 2,170 systems with $M &gt; 10^{14}\, M_\odot$ selected from a publicly available group catalog based on the SDSS galaxy. Cluster spin is quantified by identifying the orientation in the projected plane that maximizes the redshift difference ($\Delta Z_{\rm max}$) between member galaxies in two regions divided by a trial axis. We find strong statistical evidence for coherent rotation, with the observed $\Delta Z_{\rm max}$ distribution significantly exceeding randomized controls (nearly $\sim150\sigma$ confidence at $\sim380~\mathrm{km\,s}^{-1}$), especially in richer clusters ($N_{\mathrm{gal}} &gt; 10$, up to $\sim300\sigma$). Stacked visualizations confirm the spatial segregation of redshifted and blueshifted galaxies across the rotation axis. The radial profile of the rotational velocity indicates that it increases as a function of radius. The cluster rotation speed increases with mass, from $\sim330~\mathrm{km\,s}^{-1}$ at $10^{14} M_\odot$ to $\sim800~\mathrm{km\,s}^{-1}$ at $10^{15} M_\odot$. Additionally, cluster spin tends to align parallel with the central galaxy spin and perpendicular to the nearest cosmic filament, particularly in richer systems. These results reveal significant coherent spin in galaxy clusters, shaped by both internal dynamics and large-scale structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13597v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-xiao Tang, Peng Wang, Yu Rong, Weiguang cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gas-phase Molecules in Protoplanetary Nebulae with the 21 {\mu}m Emission Feature II. Carbon monosulfide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The carrier of the 21 ${\mu}$m emission feature discovered in a handful of protoplanetary nebulae (PPNe) is one of the most intriguing enigmas in circumstellar chemistry. Investigating the gas-phase molecules in PPNe could yield important hints for understanding the 21 ${\mu}$m feature. In this paper, we report observations of the CS $J = 5 \to 4$ line at 245 GHz and the CO $J = 1 \to 0$ line at 115 GHz toward seven PPNe exhibiting the 21 ${\mu}$m feature. We find that CS is extremely scarce in these PPNe and the CS line is only detected in one source, IRAS Z02229+6208. Based on the assumption of local thermal equilibrium and negligible optical depth, we derive that the CS column densities and fractional abundances relative to H$_{2}$ are $N$(CS) &lt; 9.1 ${\times}$ 10$^{13}$cm$^{-2}$ and $f$(CS) &lt; 8.1 ${\times}$ 10$^{-7}$. A comparison of the CS abundances across different circumstellar envelopes reveals that the variations in CS abundance are complex, depending not only on the evolutionary stages but also on the properties of individual objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13629v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian-Jie Qiu, Yong Zhang, Deng-Rong Lu, Zheng-Xue Chang, Jiang-Shui Zhang, Xiao-Hu Li, Xin-Di Tang, Yisheng Qiu, Jun-ichi Nakashima, Lan-Wei Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Milky Way is a less massive galaxy--new estimates of the Milky Way's local and global stellar masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stellar mass is the most fundamental property of a galaxy. While it has been robustly measured for millions of external galaxies, it remains poorly constrained for the Milky Way because of the strong selection effect from our inside perspective. In this work, we reconstruct the intrinsic vertical mass density profile in the solar neighborhood and the radial mass density profile across the entire Galaxy using data from the Gaia and APOGEE surveys, following careful correction for the selection function. The local density profile exhibits strong north-south asymmetry in the geometric thick disk regime and increases steeply toward the disk mid-plane, favoring an exponential model over the sech$^2$ model. Integrating the local vertical density profile yields a surface stellar mass density of 31.563$\pm$2.813(syst.)$\pm$0.024(stoch.)~${\rm M_{\odot}pc^{-2}}$, of which 25.074 and 6.489~${\rm M_{\odot}pc^{-2}}$ correspond to living stars and stellar remnants, respectively. The radial surface mass density profile {of the Milky Way} shares the same flat inner component as observed in the brightness profile. With this mass density profile {and local mass density from Gaia}, we derive a new estimate of the total stellar mass of the Milky Way of 2.607$\pm$0.353(syst.)$\pm$0.085(stoch.)${\rm \times10^{10}M_{\odot}}$, a factor of two lower than the previous results. This discrepancy arises primarily from the inner disk profile, which was previously unavailable and extrapolated from the outer disk profile. The lower stellar mass estimate of the Milky Way significantly reduces its rarity in terms of supermassive black hole mass among external galaxies and implies a larger dark matter-to-baryon mass ratio in the inner Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13665v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhui Lian (Yunnan Uni.), Tao Wang (Yunnan Uni.), Qikang Feng (Peking Uni.), Yang Huang (U of Chinese Academy of Sciences), Helong Guo (Yunnan Uni.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray selected broad absorption line quasars in SDSS-V: BALs and non-BALs span the same range of X-ray properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Broad absorption line (BAL) quasars are often considered X-ray weak relative to their optical/UV luminosity, whether intrinsically (i.e., the coronal emission is fainter) or due to large column densities of absorbing material. The SDSS-V is providing optical spectroscopy for samples of quasar candidates identified by eROSITA as well as Chandra, XMM or Swift, making the resulting datasets ideal for characterising the BAL quasar population within an X-ray selected sample. We use the Balnicity Index (BI) to identify the BAL quasars based on absorption of the CIV $\lambda\,1549$ emission line in the optical spectra, finding 143 BAL quasars in our sample of 2317 X-ray selected quasars within $1.5\le z \le3.5$. This observed BAL fraction of $\approx$ 6 per cent is comparable to that found in optically selected samples. We also identify absorption systems via the Absorption Index (AI) which includes mini-BALs and NALs, finding 954 quasars with AI $&gt;0$. We consider the CIV emission space (equivalent width vs. blueshift) to study the BAL outflows within the context of the radiatively driven accretion disc-wind model. X-ray selection excludes the highest outflow velocities in emission but includes the full range of absorption velocities which we suggest is consistent with the BAL gas being located further from the X-ray corona than the emitting gas. We observe both X-ray weak and X-ray strong BALs (via the optical-to-X-ray spectral slope, $\alpha_\text{ox}$) and detect little evidence for differing column densities between the BAL and non-BAL quasars, suggesting the BALs and non-BALs have the same shielding gas and intrinsic X-ray emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13682v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1352</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pranavi Hiremath, Amy L. Rankine, James Aird, W. N. Brandt, Paola Rodr\'iguez Hidalgo, Scott F. Anderson, Catarina Aydar, Claudio Ricci, Donald P. Schneider, M. Vivek, Zsofi Igo, Sean Morrison, Mara Salvato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of interstellar phenalene ($c$-C$_{13}$H$_{10}$): A new piece for the chemical puzzle of PAHs in space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the discovery of the unsubstituted polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) phenalene ($c$-C$_{13}$H$_{10}$) in TMC-1 as part of the QUIJOTE line survey. In spite of the low dipole moment of this three-ring PAH we have found a total of 267 rotational transitions with quantum numbers $J$ and $K_a$ up to 34 and 14, respectively, corresponding to 100 independent frequencies. The identification of this new PAH from our survey was based on the agreement between the rotational parameters derived from the analysis of the lines and those obtained by quantum chemical calculations. Subsequent chemical synthesis of this PAH and the investigation of its laboratory microwave spectrum unequivocally support our identification. The column density of phenalene in TMC-1 is (2.8$\pm$1.6)$\times$10$^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13857v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Cabezas, Marcelino Ag\'undez, Crist\'obal P\'erez, Daniel Villar-Castro, Germ\'an Molpeceres, Dolores P\'erez, Amanda L. Steber, Ra\'ul Fuentetaja, Bel\'en Tercero, Nuria Marcelino, Alberto Lesarri, Pablo de Vicente, Jos\'e Cernicharo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of methane and cyclohexane through the hydrogenation of toluene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Methylated polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) have been hypothesised to be present in the interstellar medium (ISM) through their 3.4 and 6.9 $\mu$m absorption bands. To investigate the hydrogenation of these methylated PAHs, the simplest, toluene ($\mathrm{CH_3C_6H_5}$), was exposed to H-atoms. This demonstrated how the presence of a methyl group changes the reactivity towards atomic hydrogen as compared to benzene and other PAHs and how this may alter its chemistry in the ISM. Toluene was deposited onto a graphite surface in an ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) chamber and then exposed to a H-atom beam. Temperature programmed desorption (TPD) measurements were used to investigate the reaction between H-atoms and toluene and the masses of hydrogenation products were measured with a quadrupole mass spectrometer (QMS). H-atom exposure of toluene leads to superhydrogenation of toluene and the formation of methyl-cyclohexane ($\mathrm{CH_3C_6H_{11}}$) at long exposure times. The initial cross-section of H-addition is lower than that of other PAHs. Methyl-cyclohexane can be further hydrogenated, leading to the detachment of the methyl group and production of cyclohexane ($\mathrm{C_6H_{12}}$) and methane ($\mathrm{CH_4}$). Toluene may be fully hydrogenated through its interaction with H-atoms, although it has a smaller initial cross-section for H-atom addition compared to other PAHs. This likely reflects it having a smaller geometric cross-section and the low flexibility of the benzene ring when undergoing sp$^3$ hybridization. The removal of the methyl group at high H-atom fluences provides a top down formation route to smaller molecules with the possibility of the formation of a radical cyclohexane combining with other species in an interstellar environment to form prebiotic molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13864v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. T. Hopkinson, F. G. Doktor, J. Pitfield, M. Moll, J. D. Thrower, L. Hornek{\ae}r</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary stars in the Milky Way nuclear stellar cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13893v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intermediate-mass galaxies, including the Milky Way, typically host both a supermassive black hole (SMBH) and a nuclear stellar cluster (NSC). Binaries in an NSC evolve via close encounters with surrounding stars and secular processes related to the SMBH. We study moderately soft and hard binaries ($0.03$-$2.5\,\mathrm{au}$, $M \lesssim 2\,M_\odot$) initially at galactocentric radii 0.1 and 0.3 pc using three-body simulations including von Zeipel-Lidov-Kozai oscillations and tidal dissipation over $\sim 10$ Gyr. Binaries migrate both inward and outward as a consequence of kicks received in the three-body encounters. Inward migration leads to destruction via mergers and evaporation, while outward migration is a pathway to retaining intact binaries for $\gtrsim 10$ Gyr. All surviving binaries are hard and circular, but outcomes for binaries initially at the hard-soft boundary are stochastic. We find that: (i) about $0.3$ percent of evaporated binaries fall into the SMBH's loss cone, (ii) at least $1$ percent of mergers occur late enough to appear as blue straggler stars (BSSs) on the main sequence or as recently evolved red giants, (iii) about $1$ percent of binaries initially at 0.1 pc merge within the inner arcsec of the NSC, and (iv) less than about $80$ percent of field-star collisions with a binary star lead to a subsequent merger; a three-body pile up, which are relatively common in the first 1-2 Gyr and could serve as a way to form more massive BSSs in the NSC. We predict that a small fraction of binaries originate closer to the SMBH than their present-day orbits, and vice versa for evaporated binaries and BSSs. The mergers confined to the inner arcsec occur after $\gtrsim 300$ Myr, too long to be directly related to the formation of the S-stars or G-objects, but suggest that the inner arcsec is contaminated with BSSs from earlier star formation events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13893v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arn Marklund, Ross P. Church, Alessandro A. Trani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractality of open clusters in singles, pairs, and groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the global structural properties and fractality of 1,876 open clusters (OCs) in different environments, including 1,145 singles, 392 pairs, and 339 groups. We analyze cluster mass, age, size, concentration, and fractal structure using the Q parameter and the fractal dimension fdim, and examine their correlations with key physical parameters. Our results reveal systematic environmental trends: clusters in groups are generally younger, less massive, slightly larger, and less centrally concentrated than those in pairs or singles. Fractality is more pronounced in clusters within pairs and groups, with 44% of group clusters exhibiting fractal substructure compared to 38.5% for pairs and 33.2% for singles. Similarly, median fdim values increase from singles (1.13) to pairs (1.16) to groups (1.25), reflecting greater substructure in denser environments. These findings indicate that both intrinsic cluster properties and environmental context significantly influence cluster evolution. More massive clusters tend to evolve toward centrally concentrated, radially symmetric configurations, while less massive clusters retain fractal features for longer periods. Overall, our study demonstrates that open clusters do not evolve in isolation: interactions with the environment play a critical role in shaping their structural evolution and dynamical state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13980v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Almat Akhmetali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Wide Triples to UCXBs: Multimessenger Detection of Dynamically-formed Black Hole-White Dwarf Systems with LISA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultracompact X-ray binaries (UCXBs) are a subclass of low-mass X-ray binaries characterized by tight orbits and degenerate donors, which pose significant challenges to our understanding of their formation. Recent discoveries of black hole (BH) candidates with main-sequence (MS) or red giant (RG) companions suggest that BH-white dwarf (BH-WD) binaries are common in the Galactic field. Motivated by these observations and the fact that most massive stars are born in triples, we show that wide BH-WD systems can naturally form UCXBs through the eccentric Kozai-Lidov (EKL) mechanism. Notably, EKL-driven eccentricity excitations combined with gravitational wave (GW) emission and WD dynamical tides can effectively shrink and circularize the orbit, leading to mass-transferring BH-WD binaries. These systems represent promising multimessenger sources in both X-ray and GW observations. Specifically, we predict that the wide triple channel can produce $\sim5-45$ ($\sim1-8$) detectable UCXBs in the Milky Way (Andromeda galaxy), including $\sim1$ system observable by the mHz GW detection of LISA. If the final WD mass can reach sufficiently small values, this channel could contribute up to $\sim 10^3$ UCXBs in the Galaxy. Furthermore, the identification of tertiary companions in observed UCXBs would provide direct evidence for this formation pathway and yield unique insights into their dynamical origins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13264v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyuan Xuan, Cheyanne Shariat, Smadar Naoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triples as Links between Binary Black Hole Mergers, their Electromagnetic Counterparts, and Galactic Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13270v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a formation pathway linking black holes (BHs) observed in gravitational-wave (GW) mergers, wide BH-stellar systems uncovered by Gaia, and accreting low-mass X-ray binaries (LMXBs). In this scenario, a stellar-mass BH binary undergoes isolated binary evolution and merges while hosting a distant, dynamically unimportant tertiary stellar companion. The tertiary becomes relevant only after the merger, when the remnant BH receives a GW recoil kick. Depending on the kick velocity and system configuration, the outcome can be: (i) a bright electromagnetic (EM) counterpart to the GW merger; (ii) an LMXB; (iii) a wide BH-stellar companion resembling the Gaia BH population; or (iv) an unbound, isolated BH. Modeling the three-body dynamics, we find that $\sim 0.02\%$ of LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) mergers may be followed by an EM counterpart within $\sim$10 days, produced by tidal disruption of the star by the BH. The flare is likely brightest in the optical-UV and lasts days to weeks; in some cases, partial disruption causes recurring flares with a period of $\sim$2 months. We further estimate that this channel can produce $\sim 1-10\%$ of Gaia BH systems in the Milky Way. This scenario provides the first physically motivated link between GW sources, Gaia BHs, and some X-ray binaries, and predicts a rare but robust pathway for EM counterparts to binary BH mergers, potentially detectable in LVK's O5 run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13270v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Smadar Naoz, Zoltan Haiman, Eliot Quataert, Liz Holzknecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIPCALs: A fully-automated calibration pipeline for VLBI data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13282v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Very long baseline interferometry (VLBI) is a powerful technique that can achieve sub-milliarcsecond resolution. However, it requires complex and often manual post-correlation calibration to correct for instrumental, geometric, and propagation-related errors. Unlike connected-element interferometers, VLBI arrays typically provide raw visibilities rather than science-ready data, and existing pipelines are largely semi-automated and reliant on user supervision. We present VIPCALs, a fully automated, end-to-end calibration pipeline for continuum VLBI data that operates without human intervention or prior knowledge of the dataset. Designed for scalability to thousands of sources and heterogeneous archival observations, VIPCALs addresses the needs of initiatives such as the Search for Milli-Lenses (SMILE) project. Implemented in Python using ParselTongue, VIPCALs reproduces the standard AIPS calibration workflow in a fully unsupervised mode. Besides the usual calibration tasks, the pipeline also performs automatic reference antenna selection, calibrator identification, and generates diagnostic outputs for inspection. We validated it on a representative sample of Very Long Baseline Array (VLBA) data corresponding to 1 000 sources from the SMILE project. VIPCALs successfully calibrated observations of 955 of the test sources across multiple frequency bands. Over 91% of the calibrated datasets achieved successful fringe fitting on target in at least half of the solutions attempted. The median ratio of calibrated visibilities to initial total visibilities was 0.87. The average processing time was below 10 minutes per dataset, demonstrating both efficiency and scalability. VIPCALs enables robust, reproducible, and fully automated calibration of VLBI continuum data, significantly lowering the entry barrier for VLBI science and making large-scale projects like SMILE feasible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13282v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego \'Alvarez-Ortega, Carolina Casadio, Felix M. P\"otzl, Avinash Kumar, Michael Janssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Dimensional Polarimetric Structure of Jets from Radio Galaxy MRC 0600-399 in Abell 3376</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: MRC 0600-399, in the merging galaxy cluster Abell 3376, is one of the unique Head-Tail radio galaxies having abruptly bending structures, the origin of which is still under discussion. A previous study suggested that the interaction between the jets and the magnetic fields on the cold front has produced such an outstanding feature; however, it is still not known how the jet propagates the long distance keeping the sharp shape. In this study, we performed a polarization analysis of MRC 0600-399 and a nearby radio source using MeerKAT L-band data. To interpret the Faraday structure, we constructed the Pseudo-3D visualization map of the reconstructed Faraday dispersion function 3D cube. MRC 0600-399 has a complicated Faraday depth structure, and some of the Faraday depth features are in good agreement with the 2D structure on the celestial sphere. For the northern jet of MRC 0600-399, the Faraday depth values show a clear gap at the tip region. Based on the polarization analysis and comparison with the other observation, we concluded that the synchrotron radiation from the tip region of the northern jet originates from the magnetic field on the cold front.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13454v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruka Sakemi, James O. Chibueze, William D. Cotton, Viral Parekh, Takumi Ohmura, Mami Machida, Taichi Igarashi, Takuya Akahori, Hiroki Akamatsu, Hiroyuki Nakanishi, Tsutomu T. Takeuchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Narrowing the discovery space of the cosmological 21-cm signal using multi-wavelength constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13761v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmic 21-cm signal is a promising probe of the early Universe, owing to its sensitivity to the thermal state of the neutral intergalactic medium (IGM) and properties of the first luminous sources. In this work, we constrain the 21-cm signal and infer IGM properties by leveraging multi-wavelength synergies. This builds on our earlier study, where we developed the synergy between high-redshift UV luminosity functions (UVLFs), cosmic X-ray and radio backgrounds (CXB and CRB), 21-cm global signal non-detection from SARAS~3, and 21-cm power spectrum upper limits from HERA, to constrain the astrophysical properties of Population II galaxies. Through a combination of CXB and HERA data, we find the IGM kinetic temperature to be $T_\text{K}(z=15)\lesssim 7.7~\text{K}$, $2.5~\text{K} \lesssim T_\text{K}(z=10) \lesssim 66~\text{K}$, and $20~\text{K}\lesssim T_\text{K}(z=6) \lesssim 2078~\text{K}$ at 95\% credible interval (C.I.). Similarly, CRB and HERA data place an upper limit on the radio emission efficiency of galaxies, giving $T_\text{rad}(z=15) \lesssim 47~\text{K}$, $T_\text{rad}(z=10)\lesssim 51~\text{K}$, and $T_\text{rad}(z=6)\lesssim 101~\text{K}$. These constraints, strengthened by the inclusion of UVLFs from HST and JWST, allow us to place the first \textit{lower bound} on the cosmic 21-cm signal. We infer an absorption trough of depth ${-201~\text{mK}\lesssim T_\text{21,min} \lesssim -68~\text{mK}}$ at $z_\text{min}\approx10-16$, and a power spectrum of $8.7~\text{mK}^2 &lt; \Delta_{21}^2(z=15) &lt; 197~\text{mK}^2$ at $k=0.35~h\text{Mpc}^{-1}$. Our results provide promising predictions for upcoming 21-cm experiments, and highlight the power of multi-wavelength synergies in constraining the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13761v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiten Dhandha, Anastasia Fialkov, Thomas Gessey-Jones, Harry T. J. Bevins, Sandro Tacchella, Simon Pochinda, Eloy de Lera Acedo, Saurabh Singh, Rennan Barkana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unexplored Dusty Nova LMCN 2009-05a in the Large Magellanic Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a detailed spectrophotometric study of nova LMCN 2009-05a, located in the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC). Photometric observations reveal a dust dip in the optical light curve, classifying it as a D-class nova. Light curve analysis yields t2 and t3 decline times of approximately 46 and 80 days, respectively, placing the nova in the category of moderately fast novae. Spectroscopic observations cover multiple phases, including pre-maximum, early decline, and nebular. The spectra are initially dominated by hydrogen Balmer and Fe II lines with P-Cygni profiles, which later transition into pure emission. During the optical minimum, a discrete absorption feature was observed in the H{\alpha} and [O I] line profiles. The physical and chemical properties during the early decline and nebular phases were analyzed using the photoionization code CLOUDY. Dust temperature, mass, and grain size were estimated through spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting to the WISE data. On day 395 post-outburst, we estimate the dust temperature to be approximately 700 K. Additionally, we examined the correlation between dust condensation time (tcond ) and t2 for LMC novae, finding a trend consistent with previous studies of Galactic novae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13851v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohit Singh Bisht, A. Raj, F. M. Walter, Anatoly S. Miroshnichenko, D. Bisht, K. Belwal, Shraddha Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing the core-cusp and diversity problem of dwarf and disk galaxies using cold collisionless DARKexp theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15879v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dwarf galaxies are observed to have linearly rising rotation curves, which indicate constant density cores in their centers. These do not arise naturally from dark matter only simulations, giving rise to the ``core-cusp'' problem. Hydrodynamic simulations incorporating baryonic feedback can create cored profiles, but this solution requires some fine tuning. Additionally, there is a related ``diversity'' problem in which simulations cannot reproduce the large range in rotation curve shapes for galaxies of similar mass. Here we investigate, for the first time, whether a theoretical model based on statistical mechanics (DARKexp) can produce flat density cores with its single shape parameter. We find that these theoretical profiles are able to fit the observed rotation curves of galaxies with last measured velocities in the range ~ 20-200 km/s by producing fits to 96 SPARC catalog galaxies covering this range. We additionally show that the projected stellar density distributions of ultrafaint dwarfs that show cores are also well fit, and that wave, or fuzzy dark matter is unable to fit the full range of SPARC galaxies. Thus, DARKexp appears to be able to address the core-cusp problem and the diversity of rotation curves in these dark matter dominated galaxies with cold collisionless dark matter alone, i.e., without introducing baryonic feedback, or alternative nature of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15879v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/052</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 08(2025)052</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Liliya L. R. Williams, Jens Hjorth, Evan D. Skillman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Sample of Active Galactic Nuclei with Intermediate-mass Black Holes Extended to $z \approx$ 0.6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12898v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a sample of 930 intermediate-mass black hole active galactic nuclei (AGNs) with black hole masses of $M_\mathrm{BH} \leqslant 2 \times 10^{6}$ M$_{\odot}$, uniformly selected from the Seventeenth Data Release of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey, based on the detection of broad H$\alpha$ or H$\beta$ emission lines. Taking advantage of the wide wavelength coverage of BOSS/eBOSS spectroscopy, our sample extends the redshift coverage of low-$z$ intermediate-mass black hole AGNs to $z\leqslant0.57$, significantly improving upon previous studies that where generally limited to $z\leqslant0.35$. This sample encompasses black hole masses from $10^{4.0}$ to $10^{6.3}$ M$_{\odot}$, with Eddington ratios ranging from 0.01 to 1.9. Among the $z&gt;0.3$ subset, 24 sources exhibit detectable broad Mg II $\lambda\lambda2796,2803$ emission lines, including eight confirmed by independent DESI spectra. A preliminary analysis reveals a marked decline in both the maximum accretion rate ($L/L_\mathrm{Edd}$) and broad-H$\alpha$ luminosity with decreasing redshift, possibly reflecting a cosmic evolution of accretion activity at the low-mass end, akin to the ``downsizing'' evolutionary trend seen in high-mass AGNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12898v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Juan Liu, Luis C. Ho, Xiao-Bo Dong, Su Yao, Paulina Lira, Yicheng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the first galaxies primordial black holes shine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The presence of nine candidate galaxies at $z=17$ and $z=25$ discovered by the James Webb Space Telescope in relatively small sky areas, if confirmed, is virtually impossible to reconcile with the predictions of the current galaxy formation model. We show here that the implied UV luminosity density can be produced by a population of primordial black holes (PBHs) of mass $M_{\rm PBH} = 10^{4-5} \, M_{\odot}$ residing in low-mass halos ($M_h \approx 10^{7} \, M_{\odot}$), and accreting at a moderate fraction of the Eddington luminosity, $\lambda_E \simeq 0.36$. These sources precede the first significant episodes of cosmic star formation. At later times, as star formation is ignited, PBH emission becomes comparable to, or subdominant with respect to, the galactic emission. This PBH+galaxy scenario reconciles the evolution of the UV luminosity function (LF) from $z=25$ to $z=11$. If ultra-early sources are powered purely by accretion, this strongly disfavours seed production mechanisms requiring the presence of stars (massive stars, Pop III stars, or clusters), or their UV radiation (direct collapse BHs), leaving PBHs as the only alternative solution available so far. Alternative explanations, such as isolated, large clusters ($\approx 10^7 \,M_{\odot}$) of massive ($m_\star =10^3 M_{\odot}$) Pop III stars are marginally viable, but require extreme and unlikely conditions that can be probed via UV and far-infrared (FIR) emission lines or gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18850v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Matteri, Andrea Ferrara, Andrea Pallottini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filamentary Hierarchies and Superbubbles I: Characterizing filament properties across a simulated spiral galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01099v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High resolution surveys reveal that the interstellar medium in the Milky Way and nearby galaxies consists of interlinked hierarchies of filamentary structure and superbubbles extending from galactic to subpc scales. The characterization of filament properties across this hierarchy is of fundamental importance for the origin of giant molecular clouds and their star clusters. In this paper we characterize the properties of filaments greater than 25 pc in length that are produced in the multi-scale galactic MHD simulations of Zhao et al. 2024. By adapting the FilFinder algorithm of Koch &amp; Rosolowsky, 2015, we extract over 500 filaments ranging up to 10 kpc scales, to derive the probability distribution functions for filament masses and lengths, magnetic field orientations, and the gravitational stability and fragmentation patterns of filaments. We find power-law distributions for filament masses and lengths. The former has a power law index $\alpha_m = 1.85$ that is nearly identical to that of observed GMC mass functions in extragalactic and Galactic surveys, suggesting that GMC properties are inherited from their host filaments. The fragmentation of magnetized filaments on 200 pc scales or less occurs when they exceed an average critical line mass, as predicted by theory. On larger scales however, kpc filaments form out of the cold neutral medium (CNM) and fragmentation follows local variations in the critical line mass along spiral arms or at the boundaries of superbubbles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01099v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/add68a</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Pillsworth, Erica Roscoe, Ralph E. Pudritz, Eric W. Koch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CGM cloud sizes from refractive FRB scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19562v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore constraints on the size of cool gas clouds in the circumgalactic medium (CGM) obtainable from the presence, or lack thereof, of refractive scattering in fast radio bursts (FRBs). Our refractive analysis sets the most conservative bounds on parsec-scale CGM clumpiness as it does not make assumptions about the turbulent density cascade. We find that the bulk of low-redshift cool CGM gas, constrained to have densities of $n_{\rm e} \lesssim 10^{-2}\,{\rm cm^{-3}}$, likely cannot produce two refractive images and, hence, scattering. It is only for extremely small cloud sizes $\lesssim 0.1$ pc (about a hundred times smaller than the so-called shattering scale) that such densities could result in detectable scattering. Dense $n_{\rm e} \gtrsim 0.1\,{\rm cm^{-3}}$ gas with shattering-scale cloud sizes is more likely to inhabit the inner several kiloparsecs of the low-redshift CGM: such clouds would result in multiple refractive images and large scattering times $\gtrsim 1 - 10$ ms, but a small fraction FRB sightlines are likely to be affected. We argue that such large scattering times from an intervening CGM would be a signature of sub-parsec clouds, even if diffractive scattering from turbulence contributes to the overall scattering. At redshift $z\sim 3$, we estimate $\sim 0.1\%$ of FRBs to intersect massive proto-clusters, which may be the most likely place to see scattering owing to their ubiquitous $n_{\rm e} \approx 1\,{\rm cm^{-3}}$ cold gas. While much of our discussion assumes a single cloud size, we show similar results hold for a CGM cloud-size distribution motivated by hydrodynamic simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19562v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lluis Mas-Ribas, Matthew McQuinn, J. Xavier Prochaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The eROSITA view on the halo mass-temperature relation: From low-mass groups to massive clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galaxy groups and clusters are among the best probes of structure formation and growth in a cosmological context. Most of their baryonic component is dominated by the intracluster medium (ICM), whose thermodynamical properties serve as indicators of the halo's dynamical state and can be used for the halo mass determination in the self-similar scenario. However, baryonic processes, such as AGN feedback and gas cooling, may affect the global properties of the ICM, especially in the group regime. These effects might lead to deviations from self-similar predictions in galaxy groups' scaling relations, while they remain in place for massive galaxy clusters. Additionally, the low-mass end of the scaling relations, ranging from $10^{13}$ to $10^{14} M_\odot$, remains unclear and poorly populated, as current X-ray surveys detect only the brightest groups. Here, we present the Mass-Temperature relation across the full mass range, from massive clusters to low-mass groups ($10^{13}M_\odot$), as observed by eROSITA. Using spectral stacking from eROSITA eRASS1 data for optically selected galaxy groups, we find that, in the lower mass range, galaxy groups follow the power-law relation known for galaxy clusters. We further validate these results by conducting the same stacking procedure on mock eRASS:4 data using the Magneticum hydrodynamical simulation. This indicates that AGN feedback is more likely to affect the distribution of baryons in the intragroup medium rather than the overall halo gas temperature. No significant changes in the Mass-Temperature relation slope suggest that temperature can serve as a reliable mass proxy across the entire mass range. This validates the use of temperature-derived masses, particularly in cosmological studies, significantly broadening the mass range and enabling applications such as improving the cluster mass function studies and cosmological parameter estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01502v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202554352</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 700, A167 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. Toptun, P. Popesso, I. Marini, K. Dolag, G. Lamer, X. Yang, Q. Li, B. Csizi, L. Lovisari, S. Ettori, V. Biffi, S. Vladutescu-Zopp, A. Dev, D. Mazengo, A. Merloni, J. Comparat, G. Ponti, E. Bulbul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bar properties as a function of wavelength in TNG50: analysis of mock images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent studies used TNG50 galaxies to study bar formation, evolution, and properties like length, strength, and pattern speed. In simulations, these are typically derived from particle positions and mass distribution, neglecting stellar light and extinction effects. However, observational studies indicate that bar appearance depends on wavelength. To test whether this dependence exists in TNG50 at $z \sim 0$, we analysed 50 strongly barred galaxies using mock images from SKIRT radiative transfer simulations covering infrared to ultraviolet filters (Spitzer 3.6 um, SDSS i, r, g, S-PLUS J0378, GALEX NUV, and GALEX FUV). Bar ellipticity and length were measured via ellipse fitting. Ellipticity generally increases by 6 percent from 3.6 um to g band, and by 9 percent to J0378 band. On average, TNG50 bars cannot be said to be longer in bluer filters when the entire sample is used. However, the trend is detected when only star-forming galaxies are considered. In this star-forming subsample, bar length increases by 10 percent from 3.6 um to g band, and by 17 percent to J0378 band; moreover, the bar can appear up to 20${-}$30 percent longer in bluer mocks than in the mass map. Over 90 percent of bars vanish in UV due to minimal emission by dominant stellar populations. We reproduced the bar properties morphological dependence phenomenon using age-filtered mass maps, where older stars form shorter, rounder bars, and younger stars generate longer, more elliptical ones. TNG50 bars exhibit a wavelength-dependent trend similar to observations: bars appear more elliptical and longer in bluer filters, with this effect being stronger in star-forming galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19373v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo F. Gon\c{c}alves, Rubens E. G. Machado, Kar\'in Men\'endez-Delmestre, Thiago Bueno-Dalpiaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tale of Two Sightlines: Comparison of Hydrocarbon Dust Absorption Bands toward Cygnus OB2-12 and the Galactic Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Infrared spectra of hydrocarbon dust absorption bands toward the bright hypergiant Cygnus OB2-12 are compared to published spectra of the Quintuplet Cluster, a sightline to the Galactic center. The Cyg OB2-12 data include a new ground-based 2.86-3.70 microns spectrum and a previously published, but here further analyzed, spectrum of the 5.50-7.34 microns region. Higher spectral resolution data for the Cyg OB2-12 sightline in the 3 micron region allows a detailed comparison of the 3.4 micron aliphatic bands to those observed toward the Quintuplet. Despite differences in interstellar environments along each sightline, strong similarities are observed in the central wavelengths and relative strengths for bands at 3.3, 3.4, 5.85, 6.2, and 6.85 microns. Analysis of these bands, produced by aromatic, aliphatic, olefinic, hydrogenated, and oxygenated components, shows that carbonaceous dust is a significant component of the diffuse interstellar medium, second in abundance only to silicates, and is primarily aromatic in nature. The grains producing these bands likely consist of large aromatic carbon cores with thin aliphatic mantles composed of hydrogenated amorphous carbon (HAC). Laboratory analog spectra reproduce the observed aliphatic absorption bands well, supporting the presence of such mantles. We present evidence that the carriers of both the 3.4 micron aliphatic and the 3.3 micron aromatic bands reside exclusively in the diffuse ISM, and that the 3.3 micron bands observed in the diffuse ISM differ from those seen in dense clouds, implying chemically distinct carriers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12601v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yvonne J. Pendleton, T. R. Geballe, Laurie E. U. Chu, Marjorie Decleir, Karl D. Gordon, A. G. G. M. Tielens, Louis J. Allamandola, Jeroen Bouwman, J. E. Chiar, Curtis Dewitt, Burcu Gunay, Thomas Henning, Vito Mennella, M. E. Palumbo, Alexey Potapov, Maisie Rashman, Sascha Zeegers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition metal abundance as a key parameter for the search of Life in the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03748v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The search for Life in the Universe generally assumes three basic life's needs: I) building block elements (i.e., CHNOPS), II) a solvent to life's reactions (generally, liquid water) and III) a thermodynamic disequilibrium. It is assumed that similar requirements might be universal in the Cosmos. On our planet, life is able to harvest energy from a wide array of thermodynamic disequilibria, generally in the form of redox disequilibrium. The amount of different redox couples used by living systems has been estimated to be in the range of several thousands of reactions. Each of these energy yielding reactions requires specialised proteins called oxidoreductases, that have one or more metal cofactors acting as catalytic centres to exchange electrons. These metals are de facto the key component of the engines that life uses to tap into the thermodynamic disequilibria needed to fuel metabolism. The availability of these transition metals is not uniform in the Universe, and it is a function of the distribution (in time and space) of complex dynamics. Despite this, Life's need for specific metals to access thermodynamic disequilibria has been so far completely overlooked in identifying astrobiological targets. We argue that the availability of at least some transition elements appears to be an essential feature of habitability, and should be considered a primary requisite in selecting exoplanetary targets in the search for life.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03748v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.33232/001c.143246</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Open Journal of Astrophysics, vol. 8, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Covone, Donato Giovannelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Universal Analytic Model for Gravitational Lensing by Self-Interacting Dark Matter Halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14964v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a model for analytically calculating gravitational lensing by self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) halos. Leveraging the universal behavior of SIDM halos during gravothermal evolution, we calibrate the lensing potential using a fluid simulation, normalizing the evolution time to align with established scenarios. From this potential, we derive explicit equations for the deflection angle and surface density profile, quantifying their deviations from numerical results. Our model builds on the parametric approach of arXiv:2305.16176, providing refinements in the deep core-collapse regime and enabling more comprehensive lensing studies. We explore characteristic lensing features, including critical curves and caustics, for SIDM halos in isolation and within a main halo, tracking their evolution through the gravothermal phase. We also examine signatures in the self-similar regime of core collapsed halos and highlight the role of baryonic effects in realistic halos. The application of our model extends to generic halos, whose profiles fit one or a superposition of our parametric forms. We make our implementation publicly available on https://github.com/HouSiyuan2001/SIDM_Lensing_Model to support further research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14964v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/048</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 08 (2025) 048</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Hou, Daneng Yang, Nan Li, Guoliang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial Profiles of Radio Halos in Massive Galaxy Clusters: Diffuse Giants Over 2 Mpc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05415v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present new, high frequency radio observations of the merging galaxy clusters PLCK G287.0+32.9, Abell 2744, and Bullet. These clusters are known to host $\sim$Mpc scale sources, known as radio halos, which are formed by the acceleration of cosmic rays by turbulence injected into the intracluster medium during cluster mergers. Our new images reveal previously undetected faint outermost regions of halos, extending to over 2 Mpc. This discovery highlights the presence of radio halos with large extents at high frequencies and suggests that their observable size depends on a combination of the observation sensitivity and uv-coverage, and their radio power. We additionally compare the properties of these three clusters with MACS J0717+3745 and Abell 2142, both of which are known to host prominent large radio halos. Remarkably, all five halos, despite their exceptionally large extents, exhibit properties similar to other classical halos: their radial profiles are described by a single-component exponential fit, they show radial spectral index steepening, and have an average radio emissivity of about $10^{-42}\, \mathrm{erg\,s^{-1}\,cm^{-3}\,Hz^{-1}}$. Our results demonstrate that radio halos can extend to the cluster periphery, without the transition to an observationally distinguishable different halo component in the outermost regions. Our findings highlight that careful subtraction of unrelated sources embedded in the halo is necessary to measure the radio surface brightness accurately, as incomplete subtraction can introduce an apparent secondary component in the peripheral regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05415v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Rajpurohit, A. Botteon, E. O'Sullivan, W. Forman, M. Balboni, L. Bruno, R. J. van Weeren, M. Hoeft, G. Brunetti, C. Jones, A. S. Rajpurohit, S. P. Sikhosana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kerr black hole in a uniform magnetic field: An exact solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05199v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new class of exact spacetimes in Einstein's gravity, which are Kerr black holes immersed in an external magnetic (or electric) field that is asymptotically uniform and oriented along the rotational axis, is presented. These are axisymmetric stationary solutions to the Einstein-Maxwell equations such that (unlike in the Plebanski-Demianski spacetime) the null directions of the Faraday tensor are not aligned with neither of the two principal null directions of the Weyl tensor of algebraic type D (unlike the Kerr-Melvin spacetime). Three physical parameters are the black hole mass $m$, its rotation $a$, and the external field value $B$. For vanishing $B$ the metric directly reduces to standard Boyer-Lindquist form of the Kerr black hole, while for zero $m$ we recover conformally flat Bertotti-Robinson universe with a uniform Maxwell field. For zero $a$ the spacetime is contained in the Van den Bergh-Carminati solutions which can be understood as the Schwarzschild black hole in a magnetic field. Our family of black holes with non-aligned Maxwell hair - that can be called the Kerr-Bertotti-Robinson (Kerr-BR) black holes - may find application in various studies ranging from mathematical relativity to relativistic astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05199v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiri Podolsky, Hryhorii Ovcharenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
