<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The JWST EXCELS survey: Probing strong-line diagnostics and the chemical evolution of galaxies over cosmic time using Te-metallicities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an analysis of the rest-frame optical spectra of 22 [OIII]$\lambda$4363 detected galaxies in the redshift range $1.65 &lt; z &lt; 7.92$ (with $\langle z \rangle$ = 4.05) from JWST/NIRSpec medium-resolution observations taken as part of the EXCELS survey. To supplement these high-redshift sources, we also consider a sample of 782 local [OIII]$\lambda$4363 detected galaxies from the DESI Early Data Release. Our analysis demonstrates that many strong-line calibrations are biased in the early Universe due to the systematic evolution in ionization conditions with redshift. However, the recently introduced $\widehat{R}$ calibration mostly removes the dependence on ionization state and can be considered a largely redshift-independent calibration. In a similar spirit, we introduce a new strong-line diagnostic, $\widehat{RNe}$, which can be used to robustly estimate metallicities when the [OIII]$\lambda$5007 is redshifted out of the wavelength range of JWST/NIRSpec at $z &gt; 9.5$. We also show that strong-line diagnostics using the [NII]$\lambda$6584 emission line are likely to be biased at high-redshift due to a moderate enhancement in the average N/O abundance ratios (at fixed O/H) in these sources. Finally, we discuss the location of our new [OIII]$\lambda$4363 detected galaxies at $z \simeq 4$ on the mass-metallicity plane and investigate the redshift evolution of the fundamental metallicity relation (FMR). We find tentative evidence for an increasing deviation from the FMR at $z &gt; 4$ which might indicate fundamental differences in the baryon cycle at these redshifts. However, more data are required as our high-redshift constraints are still based on a relatively small sample of galaxies and the significance of the deviation is strongly dependent on the assumed form of the fundamental metallicity relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10499v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Scholte, F. Cullen, A. C. Carnall, K. Z. Arellano-C\'ordova, T. M. Stanton, L. Barrufet, C. T. Donnan, J. S. Dunlop, H. -H. Leung, D. J. McLeod, R. J. McLure, J. M. Moustakas, C. L. Pollock, A. E. Shapley, S. Stevenson, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially resolved dust properties over 50 kpc in a hyperluminous galaxy merger at $z = 4.6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present spatially resolved dust-continuum ALMA observations from rest-frame $\sim$60 to $\sim$600 $\mu$m (bands 3-10) of the hyperluminous hot dust-obscured galaxy (hot DOG) WISE J224607.6-052634.9 (W2246-0526), at redshift $z=4.6$. W2246-0526 is interacting with at least three companion galaxies, forming a system connected by tidal streams. We model the multiwavelength ALMA observations of the dust continuum using a modified blackbody, from which we derive the dust properties (mass, emissivity index, area of the emitting region, and temperature) in the hot DOG and resolved structures across a region of nearly $\sim$50 kpc. The peak temperature at the location of the hot DOG, $\sim$110 K, is likely the consequence of heating by the central quasar. The dust temperature drops to $\sim$40 K at a radius of $\sim$8 kpc, suggesting that heating by the quasar beyond that distance is nondominant. The dust in the connecting streams between the host and companion galaxies is at temperatures between 30-40 K, typical of starburst galaxies, suggesting it is most likely heated by recent, in-situ star formation. This is the first time dust properties are spatially resolved over several tens of kpc in a galaxy system beyond Cosmic Noon --this is more than six times the scales previously probed in galaxies at those redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10503v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rom\'an Fern\'andez Aranda, Tanio D\'iaz Santos, Evanthia Hatziminaoglou, Manuel Aravena, Daniel Stern, Lee Armus, Roberto J. Assef, Andrew W. Blain, Vassilis Charmandaris, Roberto Decarli, Peter R. M. Eisenhardt, Carl Ferkinhoff, Jorge Gonz\'alez-L\'opez, Hyunsung D. Jun, Guodong Li, Mai Liao, Victoria Shevill, Devika Shobhana, Chao-Wei Tsai, Andrey Vayner, Jingwen Wu, Dejene Zewdie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Velocity Structure and Molecular Formation in Polaris Molecular Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a wide-field $(60\arcmin \times 30\arcmin)$ study of a dense region within the Polaris Flare, hereafter referred to as the `Polaris molecular cloud', using $^{12}$CO, $^{13}$CO, and C$^{18}$O ($J=1-0$) observations at $20\arcsec$ resolution, obtained with the Nobeyama 45 m Radio Telescope. The analysis reveals molecular gas formation occurring at column densities up to $\sim10^{21}$ cm$^{-2}$, evidenced by an anti-correlation between $\textsc{Hi}$ and CO distributions, indicating active atomic-to-molecular gas conversion. We found a threshold column density for molecular formation at $\sim5\times10^{20}$ cm$^{-2}$, which is common among more evolved molecular clouds. The CO-to-H$_2$ conversion factor, $X_{\rm CO}$, was found to be $0.7 \times 10^{20}$ H$_2$ cm$^{-2}$ (K km s$^{-1})^{-1}$, lower than the solar neighborhood average. Our chemical models estimate the cloud's age to be $\sim10^{5}-10^{6}$ years, suggesting an early stage of molecular cloud evolution. This interpretation is consistent with the observed low $X_{\rm CO}$ factor. While virial analysis suggests that the entire cloud is gravitationally unbound, we identified several filamentary structures extending from the main cloud body. These filaments show systematic velocity gradients of $0.5-1.5$ km s$^{-1}$ pc$^{-1}$, and analysis of the velocities shows that the molecular gas within them is falling toward the main cloud body, following a free-fall model. This suggests ongoing mass accumulation processes through the filaments, demonstrating that gravitational processes can be important even at column densities of $\sim10^{21}$ cm$^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10668v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomomi Shimoikura, Kazuhito Dobashi, Fumitaka Nakamura, Kotomi Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FEASTS Combined with Interferometry. III. The Low-column-density HI Around M51 and Possibility of Turbulent-mixing Gas Accretion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With a new joint-deconvolution pipeline, we combine the single-dish and interferometric atomic hydrogen (HI) data of M51 observed by the FAST (FEASTS program) and VLA (THINGS). The product data cube has a typical line width of $13\,\text{km}\,\text{s}^{-1}$ and a $2\sigma$ line-of-sight (LOS) sensitivity of HI column density $N_\text{HI}\sim3.2\times10^{18}\,\text{cm}^{-2}$ at a spatial resolution of ${\sim}18''$ (${\sim}0.7\,\text{kpc}$). Among the HI-detected LOSs extending to ${\sim}50\,\text{kpc}$, ${\sim}89\%$ consist of diffuse HI only, which is missed by previous VLA observations. The distribution of dense HI is reproduced by previous hydrodynamical simulations of this system, but the diffuse component is not, likely due to unresolved physics related to the interaction between the circumgalactic and interstellar media. With simple models, we find that these low-$N_\text{HI}$ structures could survive the background ultraviolet photoionization, but are susceptible to the thermal evaporation. We find a positive correlation between LOS velocity dispersion ($\sigma_v$) and $N_\text{HI}$ with a logarithmic index of ${\sim}0.5$. Based on existing turbulent mixing layer (TML) theories and simulations, we propose a scenario of hot gas cooling and accreting onto the disk through a TML, which could reproduce the observed power index of ${\sim}0.5$. We estimate the related cooling and accretion rates to be roughly $1/3$ to $2/3$ of the star-formation rate. A typical column density of diffuse HI (${\sim}10^{19}\,\text{cm}^{-2}$) can be accreted within $300\,\text{Myr}$, the interaction time scale previously estimated for the system. Such a gas accretion channel has been overlooked before, and may be important for gas-rich interacting systems and for high redshift galaxy evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10672v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuchen Lin, Jing Wang, Lister Staveley-Smith, Suoqing Ji, Dong Yang, Xinkai Chen, Fabian Walter, Hsiao-Wen Chen, Luis C. Ho, Peng Jiang, Nir Mandelker, Se-Heon Oh, Bo Peng, C\'eline P\'eroux, Zhijie Qu, Q. Daniel Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical friction by coupled dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10676v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine dynamical friction at galactic scales within the framework of coupled dark energy. This model posits dark energy as coupled quintessence, which maintains a minimal coupling to gravity but interacts non-minimally with both dark matter and baryonic matter. Since our focus is primarily on the Newtonian regime within galaxies, we begin by deriving the Newtonian limit of the model. Subsequently, we calculate the dynamical friction force using three different approaches. We demonstrate that, in the absence of interaction between dark energy and matter, standard quintessence does not generate any dynamical friction at the galactic scale. However, the presence of interaction does cause dynamical friction. By applying the resulting analytic expressions to a real self-gravitating system, namely the Fornax galaxy, and by implementing the constraints on the free parameter of the model obtained from galactic observations, we demonstrate that the coupled dark energy model leads to significant deviations from the standard cold dark matter model at galactic scales. On the other hand, if the cosmological constraints are assumed for the free parameter, the effects of the model are expected to be negligible at the galactic level, at least in dynamical friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10676v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nasrin Nari, Mahmood Roshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network of velocity-coherent filaments formed by supersonic turbulence in a very-high-velocity HI cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The warm neutral medium (WNM) was thought to be subsonically/transonically turbulent, and it lacks a network of intertwined filaments that are commonly seen in both molecular clouds and cold neutral medium (CNM). Here, we report HI~21 cm line observations of a very-high-velocity (-330 km s$^{-1}$ $&lt;V_{\rm LSR}&lt;$ -250 km s$^{-1}$) cloud (VHVC), using the Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical radio Telescope (FAST) with unprecedented resolution and sensitivity. For the first time, such a VHVC is clearly revealed to be a supersonic WNM system consisting of a network of velocity-coherent HI~filaments. The filaments are in the forms of slim curves, hubs, and webs, distributed in different layers within the position-position-velocity ({\it ppv}) data cube. The entire cloud has skewed log-normal probability distribution of column density and the filaments themselves show asymmetrical radial density profiles, indicating shock compression by supersonic magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) turbulence, as is also confirmed by our MHD simulation (sonic Mach number $M_{\rm s}=3$ and Alfv\'en Mach number $M_{\rm A}=1$). This work suggests that hierarchical filaments can be established by shocks in a low-density WNM, where gravity is negligible, offering a viable pathway to structure formation in the earliest evolutionary phases of the interstellar medium (ISM).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10897v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunchuan Liu, Tie Liu, Pak-Shing Li, Xiaofeng Mai, Christian Henkel, Paul F. Goldsmith, Sheng-Li Qin, Yan Gong, Xing Lu, Fengwei Xu, Qiuyi Luo, Hong-Li Liu, Tianwei Zhang, Yu Cheng, Yihuan Di, Yuefang Wu, Qilao Gu, Ningyu Tang, Aiyuan Yang, Zhiqiang Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Bars, Spirals and Bulge-Size on Gas-Phase Metallicity Gradients in MaNGA Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As galaxies evolve over time, the orbits of their constituent stars are expected to change in size and shape, moving stars away from their birth radius. Radial gas flows are also expected. Spiral arms and bars in galaxies are predicted to help drive this radial relocation, which may be possible to trace observationally via a flattening of metallicity gradients. We use data from the Mapping Nearby Galaxies at Apache Point Observatory (MaNGA) survey, part of the fourth phase of the Sloan Digital Sky Surveys (SDSS-IV), to look for correlations of the steepness of gas-phase metallicity gradients with various galaxy morphological features (e.g. presence and pitch angle of spiral arms, presence of a large scale bar, bulge size). We select from MaNGA a sample of star forming galaxies for which gas phase metallicity trends can be measured, and use morphologies from Galaxy Zoo. We observe that at fixed galaxy mass (1) the presence of spiral structure correlates with steeper gas phase metallicity gradients; (2) spiral galaxies with larger bulges have both higher gas-phase metallicities and shallower gradients; (3) there is no observable difference with azimuthally averaged radial gradients between barred and unbarred spirals and (4) there is no observable difference in gradient between tight and loosely wound spirals, but looser wound spirals have lower average gas-phase metallicity values at fixed mass. We discuss the possible implications of these observational results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10922v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. E. Wisz, Karen L. Masters, Kathryne J. Daniel, David V. Stark, Francesco Belfiore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Halo Occupation Distribution Modeling of the X-ray-selected AGNs at 0.6 &lt; z &lt; 2.6 in the COSMOS field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We conducted precise measurements of Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs) clustering at $z\sim1$ and $z\sim2$ by measuring the two-point cross-correlation function (CCF) between galaxies and X-ray-selected AGNs, and the two-point auto-correlation function (ACF) of galaxies in the COSMOS field to interpret the CCF results. The galaxy sample was selected from the COSMOS2015 catalog, while the AGN sample was chosen from the {\sl Chandra} COSMOS-Legacy survey catalog. For the AGN samples at $z\sim1$ and $z\sim2$, we calculated AGN bias values of $b=1.16\ (1.16;1.31)$ and $b=2.95\ (2.30;3.55)$, respectively. These values correspond to typical host dark matter halo (DMH) masses of log$(M_{\rm typ}/M_{\odot})=11.82\ (11.82;12.12)$ and log$(M_{\rm typ}/M_{\odot})=12.80\ (12.38;13.06)$, respectively. Subsequently, we performed Halo Occupation Distribution (HOD) modeling of X-ray-selected AGNs using the CCF and ACF of galaxies. We have found a significant satellite AGN population at $z\sim 1$ all over the DMH mass ($M_{\rm DMH}$) range occupied by AGNs. While $z\sim 2$ AGNs in our sample are associated with higher mass DMHs and smaller satellite fractions. The HOD analysis suggests a marginal tendency of increasing satellite slope with redshift, but larger samples are needed to confirm this with sufficient statistical significance. We find that the best-fit values of satellite slope in both redshift bins are greater than 0, suggesting tendencies of increasing satellite AGN number with $M_{\rm DMH}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10944v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyuki Ikeda, Takamitsu Miyaji, Taira Oogi, Yoshiki Toba, H\'ector Aceves, Stefano Marchesi, Viola Allevato, Akke Viitanen, Francesca Civano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the stellar streams and satellites around the giant low surface brightness galaxy Malin 1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Giant Low Surface Brightness galaxies, such as Malin 1, host extended stellar and gaseous disks exceeding 100 kpc in radius. Their formation and evolution remain debated, with interactions with satellite galaxies and accretion streams proposed as key contributors. Malin 1 has multiple satellites, including Malin 1A, Malin 1B, and the newly reported Malin 1C, along with eM1 at 350 kpc. Additionally, it exhibits two giant stellar streams, the largest extending 200 kpc, likely linked to past interactions.
  Aims. We investigate the orbital dynamics of Malin 1's satellites and their relationship with the observed stellar streams, testing their consistency with different formation scenarios.
  Methods. We constructed gravitational potentials using optical and H I rotation curve data, using stellar, gaseous, and dark matter components. We explored a wide parameter space to see if the candidate progenitors of the stellar streams could have originated from past interactions, testing both NFW and isothermal halo profiles.
  Results. Among ten explored scenarios, seven produced bound orbital solutions. The isothermal halo model, with a virial mass of 3.8 x 10^12 solar masses and a virial radius of approximately 323 kpc, favors bound satellite orbits more than the NFW model (1.7 x 10^12 solar masses). We find that eM1 probably had a pericenter passage 1.3 Gyr ago, Malin 1A around 1.4 Gyr ago, and Malin 1B's leading arm may be experiencing one now. Malin 1C displays both leading and trailing arms. Furthermore, we identify three unbound orbital solutions that could link eM1, Malin 1A, or Malin 1B to the streams.
  Conclusions. The alignment of satellites and streams supports the idea that past interactions contributed to Malin 1's morphology, enriched its gas reservoir, and influenced the development of its extended disk, providing insights into the evolution of gLSBGs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11041v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roy O. E. Bustos-Espinoza, Matias Bla\~na, Gaspar Galaz, Marcelo Mora,  Junais, Mousumi Das, Sudhanshu Barway, Ankit Kumar, Evelyn J. Johnston, Thomas Puzia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Red Supergiant Stars in the other side of our Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Red supergiant stars (RSGs) are massive stars in a late stage of evolution, crucial for understanding stellar life cycles and Galactic structure. However, RSGs on the far side of our Galaxy have been underexplored due to observational challenges. In this study, we introduce a novel method and present a new catalogue comprising 474 RSGs situated on the far side of the Milky Way, sourced from the OGLE-III catalogue of Variable Stars (OIII-CVS). The identification of these RSGs was made possible by analyzing the granulation parameters extracted from OGLE I-band time-series data and the stellar parameters from Gaia DR3. Additionally, we estimate the distances to these RSGs using an empirical relation between their characteristic amplitude, absolute magnitude, and intrinsic color, achieving a distance uncertainty of 13%. These newly identified RSGs are distributed at Galactocentric distances between 0 and 30kpc, and reside roughly 1 to 4kpc above and below the Galactic plane. This distribution provides new insights into the structure of the Milky Way, particularly at its outer boundaries. Our results reveal that the vertical distribution of these RSGs is consistent with the flare structure of the Galactic disk, confirming that the far side of the Milky Way exhibits a similar flaring pattern to the near side. This catalogue offers a valuable resource for future detailed studies of RSGs and contributes to a more comprehensive understanding of the Galactic structure and stellar evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11496v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Zhang, Bingqiu Chen, Yi Ren, Zehao Zhang, Jian Gao, Biwei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The JCMT BISTRO Survey: Magnetic Fields Align with Orbital Structure in the Galactic Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the magnetic field in the dense material of the Central Molecular Zone (CMZ) of the Milky Way, traced in 850 $\mu$m polarized dust emission as part of the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope (JCMT) B-fields In STar-forming Region Observations (BISTRO) Survey. We observe a highly ordered magnetic field across the CMZ between Sgr B2 and Sgr C, which is strongly preferentially aligned with the orbital gas flows within the clouds of the CMZ. We find that the observed relative orientations are non-random at a $&gt;$99% confidence level and are consistent with models in which the magnetic field vectors are aligned within 30$^{o}$ to the gas flows in 3D. The deviations from aligned magnetic fields are most prominent at positive Galactic longitudes, where the CMZ clouds are more massive, denser, and more actively forming stars. Our observed strongly preferentially parallel magnetic field morphology leads us to hypothesize that in the absence of star formation, the magnetic field in the CMZ is entrained in the orbital gas flows around Sgr A$^{*}$, while gravitational collapse and feedback in star-forming regions can locally reorder the field. This magnetic field behavior is similar to that observed in the CMZ of the nuclear starburst galaxy NGC 253. This suggests that despite its current low star formation rate, the CMZ of the Milky Way is analogous to those of more distant, actively star-forming, galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11552v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janik Karoly, Derek Ward-Thompson, Kate Pattle, Steven N. Longmore, James Di Francesco, Anthony Whitworth, Doug Johnstone, Sarah Sadavoy, Patrick M. Koch, Meng-Zhe Yang, Ray Furuya, Xing Lu, Motohide Tamura, Victor Debattista, David Eden, Jihye Hwang, Frederick Poidevin, Bijas Najimudeen, Szu-Ting Chen, Eun Jung Chung, Simon Coude, Sheng-Jun Lin, Yasuo Doi, Takashi Onaka, Lapo Fanciullo, Tie Liu, Guangxing Li, Pierre Bastien, Tetsuo Hasegawa, Woojin Kwon, Shih-Ping Lai, Keping Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JADES: Average Nitrogen Enhancement in High-Redshift Broad-Line Active Galactic Nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The unexpectedly high nitrogen-to-oxygen (N/O) ratios observed in high-redshift (z) galaxies have challenged our understanding of early star formation. Notably, many of these nitrogen-rich galaxies show signatures of active galactic nuclei (AGNs), suggesting a possible connection between black hole formation and nitrogen enrichment. To explore this connection, we analyse stacked spectra of z=4-7 broad-line and narrow-line AGNs using deep NIRSpec data from the JADES survey. We identify a significant Niii] quintuplet and a high electron density ($\sim10^{4}\,\mathrm{cm^{-3}}$) only in the broad-line AGN stack, indicating nitrogen-rich ($\log(\mathrm{N/C})\simeq0.5$, $\log(\mathrm{N/O})&gt;-0.6$) and dense gas similar to the high-z nitrogen-rich galaxies. Our findings suggest that dense nuclear star formation may trap nitrogen-rich gas in proto-globular clusters, in line with the high N/O observed in local globular clusters; associated runaway stellar collisions could produce intermediate-mass black hole seeds, as predicted by some models and simulations, whose accretion results into AGN signatures. These findings support scenarios connecting the early black hole seeding and growth to merging processes within and between proto-globular clusters in primeval galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12091v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Isobe, Roberto Maiolino, Francesco D'Eugenio, Mirko Curti, Xihan Ji, Ignas Juod\v{z}balis, Jan Scholtz, Anne Feltre, St\'ephane Charlot, Hannah \"Ubler, Andrew J. Bunker, Stefano Carniani, Emma Curtis-Lake, Zhiyuan Ji, Nimisha Kumari, Pierluigi Rinaldi, Brant Robertson, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar System Elemental Abundances from the Solar Photosphere and CI-Chondrites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solar photospheric abundances and CI-chondrite compositions are reviewed and updated to obtain representative solar system abundances of the elements and their isotopes. The new photospheric abundances obtained here lead to higher solar metallicity. Full 3D NLTE photospheric analyses are only available for 11 elements. A quality index for analyses is introduced. For several elements, uncertainties remain large. Protosolar mass fractions are H (X = 0.7060), He (Y = 0.2753), and for metals Li to U (Z = 0.0187). The protosolar (C+N)/H agrees within 13% with the ratio for the solar core from the Borexino experiment. Elemental abundances in CI-chondrites were screened by analytical methods, sample sizes, and evaluated using concentration frequency distributions. Aqueously mobile elements (e.g., alkalis, alkaline earths, etc.) often deviate from normal distributions indicating mobilization and/or sequestration into carbonates, phosphates, and sulfates. Revised CI-chondrite abundances of non-volatile elements are similar to earlier estimates. The moderately volatile elements F and Sb are higher than before, as are C, Br and I, whereas the CI-abundances of Hg and N are now significantly lower. The solar system nuclide distribution curves of s-process elements agree within 4% with s-process predictions of Galactic chemical evolution models. P-process nuclide distributions are assessed. No obvious correlation of CI-chondritic to solar elemental abundance ratios with condensation temperatures is observed, nor is there one for ratios of CI-chondrites/solar wind abundances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10575v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Lodders, Maria Bergemann, Herbert Palme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing an unexpectedly low electron injection threshold via reinforced shock acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10643v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Collisionless shock waves, found in supernova remnants, interstellar, stellar, and planetary environments, and laboratories, are one of nature's most powerful particle accelerators. This study combines in situ satellite measurements with recent theoretical developments to establish a reinforced shock acceleration model for relativistic electrons. Our model incorporates transient structures, wave-particle interactions, and variable stellar wind conditions, operating collectively in a multiscale set of processes. We show that the electron injection threshold is on the order of suprathermal range, obtainable through multiple different phenomena abundant in various plasma environments. Our analysis demonstrates that a typical shock can consistently accelerate electrons into very high (relativistic) energy ranges, refining our comprehension of shock acceleration while providing insight on the origin of electron cosmic rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10643v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-55641-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Raptis, S., Lalti, A., Lindberg, M., Turner, D. L., Caprioli, D., &amp; Burch, J. L. (2025). Revealing an unexpectedly low electron injection threshold via reinforced shock acceleration. Nature Communications, 16(1), 488</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Savvas Raptis, Ahmad Lalti, Martin Lindberg, Drew L. Turner, Damiano Caprioli, James L. Burch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Statistical Isotropy using 21cm Power Spectrum and Bispectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10717v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Cosmological Principle states that the universe is statistically isotropic and homogeneous on large length scales, typically $\gtrsim 70$Mpc. A detection of significant deviation would help us falsify the simplest models of inflation. In this regard, there are potential indications of departures from this principle, e.g., observations from WMAP and Planck show signs of a preferred direction in the temperature fluctuations known as hemispherical asymmetry in CMB. Phenomenologically, this has been studied using a dipole modulation model. In addition to this, a number of possible mechanisms have been proposed in the literature to explain this anomaly. Some of these scenarios generate dipolar asymmetry or predict quadrupolar asymmetry in the primordial power spectrum of curvature perturbations. In this paper, we study both these asymmetries. To fulfill the objective, we employ 21cm intensity mapping technique post during post-reionization era, i.e., $z\lesssim 7$. We apply Fisher formalism to constrain dipolar and quadrupolar anisotropy parameters using both 21cm power and bispectra and give forecasts for three intensity mapping surveys: SKA-Mid, HIRAX and PUMA. Although 21cm intensity mapping is a very promising cosmological probe, the signals are severely affected by foregrounds. To mitigate the foreground effects, we use foreground avoidance approach. For the interferometer mode of operation, we also include the wedge effect. From our analysis, we find that PUMA, on account of its high redshift range is able to constrain both dipolar and quadrupolar parameters to better than $\sim 10^{-3}$ for redshifts $z \gtrsim 1$. This is one order of magnitude better constraints as compared to those provided by the latest CMB surveys. We also find that as compared to power spectrum, the constraining power of bispectrum is more sensitive towards foregrounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10717v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhuwan Joshi (IIT Mandi), Rahul kothari (IIT Mandi)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Pre-Processing Framework for Time-Domain Astronomy in the Artificial Intelligence Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid advancement of image analysis methods in time-domain astronomy, particularly those leveraging AI algorithms, has highlighted efficient image pre-processing as a critical bottleneck affecting algorithm performance. Image pre-processing, which involves standardizing images for training or deployment of various AI algorithms, encompasses essential steps such as image quality evaluation, alignment, stacking, background extraction, gray-scale transformation, cropping, source detection, astrometry, and photometry. Historically, these algorithms were developed independently by different research groups, primarily based on CPU architecture for small-scale data processing. This paper introduces a novel framework for image pre-processing that integrates key algorithms specifically modified for GPU architecture, enabling large-scale image pre-processing for different algorithms. To prepare for the new algorithm design paradigm in the AI era, we have implemented two operational modes in the framework for different application scenarios: Eager mode and Pipeline mode. The Eager mode facilitates real-time feedback and flexible adjustments, which could be used for parameter tuning and algorithm development. The pipeline mode is primarily designed for large scale data processing, which could be used for training or deploying of artificial intelligence models. We have tested the performance of our framework using simulated and real observation images. Results demonstrate that our framework significantly enhances image pre-processing speed while maintaining accuracy levels comparable to CPU based algorithms. To promote accessibility and ease of use, a Docker version of our framework is available for download in the PaperData Repository powered by China-VO, compatible with various AI algorithms developed for time-domain astronomy research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10783v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Cao, Peng Jia, Jiaxin Li, Yu Song, Chengkun Hou, Yushan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The X-ray Integral Field Unit at the end of the Athena reformulation phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Athena mission entered a redefinition phase in July 2022, driven by the imperative to reduce the mission cost at completion for the European Space Agency below an acceptable target, while maintaining the flagship nature of its science return. This notably called for a complete redesign of the X-ray Integral Field Unit (X-IFU) cryogenic architecture towards a simpler active cooling chain. Passive cooling via successive radiative panels at spacecraft level is now used to provide a 50 K thermal environment to an X-IFU owned cryostat. 4.5 K cooling is achieved via a single remote active cryocooler unit, while a multi-stage Adiabatic Demagnetization Refrigerator ensures heat lift down to the 50 mK required by the detectors. Amidst these changes, the core concept of the readout chain remains robust, employing Transition Edge Sensor microcalorimeters and a SQUID-based Time-Division Multiplexing scheme. Noteworthy is the introduction of a slower pixel. This enables an increase in the multiplexing factor (from 34 to 48) without compromising the instrument energy resolution, hence keeping significant system margins to the new 4 eV resolution requirement. This allows reducing the number of channels by more than a factor two, and thus the resource demands on the system, while keeping a 4' field of view (compared to 5' before). In this article, we will give an overview of this new architecture, before detailing its anticipated performances. Finally, we will present the new X-IFU schedule, with its short term focus on demonstration activities towards a mission adoption in early 2027.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10866v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Peille (CNES, Toulouse), Didier Barret (IRAP, Toulouse), Edoardo Cucchetti (CNES, Toulouse), Vincent Albouys (CNES, Toulouse), Luigi Piro (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Aurora Simionescu (SRON, Leiden), Massimo Cappi (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Elise Bellouard (CNES, Toulouse), C\'eline C\'enac-Morth\'e (CNES, Toulouse), Christophe Daniel (CNES, Toulouse), Alice Pradines (CNES, Toulouse), Alexis Finoguenov (Univ. Helsinki, Helsinki), Richard Kelley (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), J. Miguel Mas-Hesse (CAB), St\'ephane Paltani (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Gregor Rauw (Univ. Li\`ege, Li\`ege), Agata Rozanska (CAMK PAN, Warsaw), Jiri Svoboda (ASU, Prague), Joern Wilms (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Marc Audard (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Enrico Bozzo (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Elisa Costantini (SRON, Leiden), Mauro Dadina (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Thomas Dauser (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Anne Decourchelle (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Jan-Willem den Herder (SRON, Leiden), Andrea Goldwurm (APC, Paris), Peter Jonker (SRON, Leiden), Alex Markowitz (CAMK PAN, Warsaw), Mariano Mendez (Univ. Groningen, Groningen), Giovanni Miniutti (CAB), Silvano Molendi (INAF-IASF Milano, Milano), Fabrizio Nicastro (INAF-OA Roma, Roma), Fran\c{c}ois Pajot (IRAP, Toulouse), Etienne Pointecouteau (IRAP, Toulouse), Gabriel W. Pratt (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Joop Schaye (Leiden Obs., Leiden), Jacco Vink (Univ. Amsterdam, Amsterdam), Natalie Webb (IRAP, Toulouse), Simon Bandler (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Marco Barbera (Unipa, Palermo), Maria Teresa Ceballos (IFCA), Ivan Charles (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Roland den Hartog (SRON, Leiden), W. Bertrand Doriese (NIST, Boulder), Jean-Marc Duval (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Flavio Gatti (Univ. Genova, Genova), Brian Jackson (SRON, Groningen), Caroline Kilbourne (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Claudio Macculi (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Sylvain Martin (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Yann Parot (IRAP, Toulouse), Frederick Porter (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Damien Pr\^ele (APC, Paris), Laurent Ravera (IRAP, Toulouse), Stephen Smith (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Jan Soucek (IAP, Prague), Tanguy Thibert (CSL, Li\`ege), Eija Tuominen (VTT, Espoo), Fabio Acero (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Stefano Ettori (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Nicolas Grosso (LAM, Marseille), Jelle Kaastra (SRON, Leiden), Pasquale Mazzotta (Univ. Tor Vergata, Roma), Jon Miller (Univ. Michigan, Ann Arbor), Salvatore Sciortino (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Sophie Beaumont (CNES, Toulouse), Matteo D'Andrea (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Jelle de Plaa (SRON, Leiden), Megan Eckart (LLNL, Livermore), Luciano Gottardi (SRON, Leiden), Maurice Leutenegger (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Simone Lotti (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Alexei Molin (IRAP, Toulouse), Lorenzo Natalucci (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Muhammad Qazi Adil (VTT, Espoo), Andrea Argan (INAF-HQ, Roma), Elisabetta Cavazzuti (ASI, Roma), Mauro Fiorini (INAF-IASF Milano, Milano), Pourya Khosropanah (SRON, Leiden), Eduardo Medinaceli Villegas (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Gabriele Minervini (INAF-HQ, Roma), James Perry (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Frederic Pinsard (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Desi Raulin (CNES, Toulouse), Manuela Rigano (Univ. Genova, Genova), Peter Roelfsema (SRON, Groningen), Denis Schwander (CNES, Toulouse), Santiago Terron (AVS, Elgoibar), Guido Torrioli (CNR-IFN, Roma), Joel Ullom (NIST, Boulder), Monika Zuchniak (CAMK PAN, Warsaw), Laurence Chaoul (CNES, Toulouse), Jose Miguel Torrejon (Univ. de Alicante, Alicante), Frank Brachet (CNES, Toulouse), Beatriz Cobo (IFCA), Malcolm Durkin (NIST, Boulder), Valentina Fioretti (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Herv\'e Geoffray (CNES, Toulouse), Lionel Jacques (CSL, Li\`ege), Christian Kirsch (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Ugo Lo Cicero (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Joseph Adams (Univ Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore), Emilie Gloaguen (CNES, Toulouse), Manuel Gonzalez (APC, Paris), Samuel Hull (Univ Maryland College Park, College Park), Erik Jellyman (VTT, Espoo), Mikko Kiviranta (VTT, Espoo), Kazuhiro Sakai (Univ Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore), Emanuele Taralli (SRON, Leiden), Davide Vaccaro (SRON, Leiden), Paul van der Hulst (SRON, Leiden), Jan van der Kuur (SRON, Groningen), Bert-Joost van Leeuwen (SRON, Leiden), Dennis van Loon (SRON, Leiden), Nicholas Wakeham (CSST-Univ Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore), Natalia Auricchio (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Daniele Brienza (ASI, Roma), Oscar Cheatom (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Philippe Franssen (CSL, Li\`ege), Sabine Julien (CNES, Toulouse), Isabelle Le Mer (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), David Moirin (HENSOLDT, Toulouse), Vitor Silva (SRON, Leiden), Michela Todaro (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Nicolas Clerc (IRAP, Toulouse), Alexis Coleiro (APC, Paris), Andy Ptak (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Simonetta Puccetti (ASI, Roma), Christian Surace (LAM, Marseille), Shariefa Abdoelkariem (SRON, Leiden), Christophe Adami (LAM, Marseille), Corinne Aicardi (CNES, Toulouse), J\'er\^ome Andr\'e (CNES, Toulouse), Matteo Angelinelli (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Shebli Anvar (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Luis Horacio Arnaldi (APC, Paris), Anthony Attard (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Damian Audley (SRON, Groningen), Florian Bancel (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Kimberly Banks (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Vivian Bernard (CNES, Toulouse), Jan Geralt Bij de Vaate (SRON, Leiden), Donata Bonino (INAF-Obs. Torino, Pino Torinese), Anthony Bonnamy (IRAP, Toulouse), Patrick Bonny (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Charles Boreux (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Ayoub Bounab (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Ma\"imouna Brigitte (ASU, Prague), Marcel Bruijn (SRON, Leiden), Cl\'ement Brysbaert (CNES, Toulouse), Andrea Bulgarelli (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Simona Calarco (CNES, Toulouse), Thierry Camus (IRAP, Toulouse), Florent Canourgues (CNES, Toulouse), Vito Capobianco (INAF-Obs. Torino, Pino Torinese), Nicolas Cardiel (UCM, Madrid), Edvige Celasco (Univ. Genova, Genova), Si Chen (APC, Paris), James Chervenak (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Fabio Chiarello (CNR-IFN, Roma), S\'ebastien Clamagirand (CNES, Toulouse), Odile Coeur-Joly (IRAP, Toulouse), Leonardo Corcione (INAF-Obs. Torino, Pino Torinese), Mickael Coriat (IRAP, Toulouse), Anais Coulet (CNES, Toulouse), Bernard Courty (APC, Paris), Alexandre Coynel (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Antonino D'Ai (INAF-IASF Palermo, Palermo), Eugenio Dambrauskas (APC, Paris), Fabio D'anca (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Lea Dauner (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Matteo De Gerone (Univ. Genova, Genova), Natalie DeNigris (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Johannes Dercksen (SRON, Leiden), Martin de Wit (SRON, Leiden), Pieter Dieleman (SRON, Groningen), Michael DiPirro (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Eric Doumayrou (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Lionel Duband (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Luc Dubbeldam (SRON, Leiden), Michel Dupieux (IRAP, Toulouse), Simon Dupourqu\'e (IRAP, Toulouse), Jean Louis Durand (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Dominique Eckert (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Philippe Ferrando (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Lorenzo Ferrari Barusso (Univ. Genova, Genova), Fred Finkbeiner (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Mariateresa Fiocchi (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Herv\'e Fossecave (CAP Gemini, Blagnac), Stefano Gabici (APC, Paris), Giovanni Gallucci (Univ. Genova, Genova), Florent Gant (CNES, Toulouse), Jian-Rong Gao (SRON, Leiden), Fabio Gastaldello (INAF-IASF Milano, Milano), Ludovic Genolet (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Simona Ghizzardi (INAF-IASF Milano, Milano), Elisa Giovannini (CNR-IFN, Roma), Margherita Giustini (CAB), Alain Givaudan (APC, Paris), Olivier Godet (IRAP, Toulouse), Alicia Gomez (CAB), Raoul Gonzalez (CNES, Toulouse), Ghassem Gozaliasl (Aalto University, Espoo), Laurent Grandsire (APC, Paris), David Granena (CNES, Toulouse), Michel Gros (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Corentin Guerin (IRAP, Toulouse), Emmanuel Guilhem (CAP Gemini, Blagnac), Gian Paolo Guizzo (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Liyi Gu (SRON, Leiden), Kent Irwin (Stanford, Stanford), Christian Jacquey (IRAP, Toulouse), Agnieszka Janiuk (CFT PAN, Warsaw), Jean Jaubert (CNES, Toulouse), Antoine Jolly (CNES, Toulouse), Thierry Jourdan (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), J\"urgen Kn\"odlseder (IRAP, Toulouse), Ole K\"onig (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Andrew Korb (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Ingo Kreykenbohm (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), David Lafforgue (IRAP, Toulouse), Radek Lan (IAP, Prague), Ma\'elyss Larrieu (IRAP, Toulouse), Philippe Laudet (CNES, Toulouse), Philippe Laurent (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Sylvain Laurent (NanoXplore, S\`evres), Monica Laurenza (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Ma\"el Le Cam (APC, Paris), Jean Lesrel (APC, Paris), Sebastiano Ligori (INAF-Obs. Torino, Pino Torinese), Maximilian Lorenz (Remeis-Observatory,ECAP, Bamberg), Alfredo Luminari (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Kristin Madsen (NASA/GSFC, Greenbelt), Oc\'eane Maisonnave (CNES, Toulouse), Lorenzo Marelli (CNES, Toulouse), Wilfried Marty (Infor'marty, Rabastens), Zo\'e Massida (IRAP, Toulouse), Didier Massonet (CNES, Toulouse), Irwin Maussang (CNES, Toulouse), Pablo Eleazar Merino Alonso (Univ. de Alicante, Alicante), Jean Mesquida (APC, Paris), Teresa Mineo (INAF-IASF Palermo, Palermo), Nicola Montinaro (Department of Engineering, Palermo), David Murat (IRAP, Toulouse), Kenichiro Nagayoshi (SRON, Leiden), Ya\"el Naz\'e (Univ. Li\`ege, Li\`ege), Lo\"ic Nogu\`es (IRAP, Toulouse), Fran\c{c}ois Nouals (CNES, Toulouse), Cristina Ortega (AVS, Elgoibar), Francesca Panessa (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Luigi Parodi (Univ. Genova, Genova), Enrico Piconcelli (INAF-OA Roma, Roma), Ciro Pinto (INAF-IASF Palermo, Palermo), Delphine Porquet (LAM, Marseille), Thomas Prouv\'e (CEA-DSBT, Grenoble), Michael Punch (APC, Paris), Guillaume Rioland (CNES, Toulouse), Marc-Olivier Riollet (CNES, Toulouse), Louis Rodriguez (DAp-AIM, Gif-sur-Yvette), Anton Roig (CNES, Toulouse), Mauro Roncarelli (INAF-OAS Bologna, Bologna), Lionel Roucayrol (CNES, Toulouse), Gilles Roudil (IRAP, Toulouse), Lander Ruiz de Ocenda (CNES, Toulouse), Luisa Sciortino (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Olivier Simonella (CNES, Toulouse), Michael Sordet (Univ. Gen\`eve, Geneva), Ulrich Taubenschuss (IAP, Prague), Guilhem Terrasa (CSL, Li\`ege), R\'egis Terrier (APC, Paris), Pietro Ubertini (INAF-IAPS, Roma), Ludek Uhlir (IAP, Prague), Michela Uslenghi (INAF-IASF Milano, Milano), Henk van Weers (SRON, Leiden), Salvatore Varisco (INAF-Obs. Palermo, Palermo), Peggy Varniere (APC, Paris), Angela Volpe (ASI, Roma), Gavin Walmsley (CNES, Toulouse), Michael Wise (SRON, Leiden), Andreas Wolnievik (IRAP, Toulouse), Grzegorz Wo\'zniak (CAMK PAN, Warsaw)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of $^{12}$C($\alpha, \gamma$)$^{16}$O Reaction on the Presupernova Evolution and Explodability of Massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11012v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Among the uncertainties of stellar evolution theory, we investigate how the $^{12}$C($\alpha, \gamma$)$^{16}$O reaction rate affects the evolution of massive stars for the initial masses of $M ({\rm ZAMS})=$ 13 - 40 M$_\odot$ and the solar metallicity. We show that the {\sl explodability} of these stars, i.e., which of a neutron star (NS) or a black hole (BH) is formed, is sensitive to the strength of convective shell burning of C and O, and thus the mass fractions of C ($X$(C)) and O in the shell. For the small $^{12}$C($\alpha, \gamma$)$^{16}$O reaction rate that yields larger $X$(C), $X$(C) is further enhanced by mixing of C from the overlying layer and then C shell burning is strengthened. The extra heating by C shell burning tends to prevent the contraction of outer layers and decrease the {\sl compactness parameter} at $M_r$ = 2.5 M$_\odot$. This effect leads to the formation of smaller mass cores of Si and Fe and steeper density and pressure gradients at the O burning shell in the presupernova models. If the pressure gradient there is steeper, the model is more likely to explode to form a NS rather than a BH. We describe the pressure gradient against $M_r$ with $V/U$ and the density drop with $1/U$, where $U$ and $V$ are non-dimensional variables to describe the stellar structure. We estimate the critical values of $V/U$ and $1/U$ at the O-burning shell above which the model is more likely to explode. We conclude that the smaller $^{12}$C($\alpha, \gamma$)$^{16}$O reaction rate makes the mass range of $M ({\rm ZAMS})$ that forms a NS larger.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11012v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenyu Xin, Ken'ichi Nomoto, Gang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Spiral Structure in the Inner Oort Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As the Galactic tide acts to decouple bodies from the scattered disk it creates a spiral structure in physical space that is roughly 15,000 au in length. The spiral is long-lived and persists in the inner Oort cloud to the present time. Here we discuss dynamics underlying the Oort spiral and (feeble) prospects for its observational detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11252v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Nesvorny, Luke Dones, David Vokrouhlicky, Hal F. Levison, Cristian Beauge, Jacqueline Faherty, Carter Emmart, Jon P. Parker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nature of gravitational wave events with host environment escape velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel method to probe the parameters and origin channels of gravitational wave events using the escape velocities of their host environments. This method could lead to more convergent posterior distributions offering additional insights into the physical properties, formation, and evolution of the sources. It also enables testing general relativity and improves source localization, which the latter is instrumental in multi-messenger astronomy. The method provides more accurate parameter estimation for events that represent previous mergers in the hierarchical triple merger scenario and is valuable for the search for such mergers with third-generation ground-based detectors. To demonstrate this approach, we take six recently identified events in LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA data, considered as potential previous mergers in hierarchical triple mergers, as examples. The use of escape velocities results in posterior spin distributions that are concentrated near zero, aligning with the expected birth spins of first-generation black holes formed from the collapse of stars. The uncertainty in the posterior primary mass distribution is significantly reduced comparing with the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA distributions, especially for events originating from globular clusters. We rule out the possibility that GW190512, GW170729, and GW190708 originates from globular clusters as previous mergers in the hierarchical triple merger scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11489v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Peng Li, Xi-Long Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSST Large Scale Structure Analysis Pipeline: III. Emission-line Redshift Measurement for Slitless Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11536v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The China Space Station Telescope (CSST) is a forthcoming space-based optical telescope designed to co-orbit with the Chinese Space Station. With a planned slitless spectroscopic survey spanning a broad wavelength range of $255-1000$nm and an average spectral resolution exceeding 200, the CSST holds significant potential for cosmic large-scale structure analysis. In this study, we focus on redshift determinations from slitless spectra through emission line analysis within the CSST framework. Our tailored redshift measurement process involves identifying emission lines in one-dimensional slitless spectra, aligning observed wavelengths with their rest-frame counterparts from prominent galaxy emissions, and calculating wavelength shifts to determine redshifts accurately. To validate our redshift measurement algorithm, we leverage simulated spectra generated by the CSST emulator for slitless spectroscopy. The outcomes demonstrate a remarkable redshift completeness exceeding 95 per cent for emission line galaxies (ELGs), alongside a purity surpassing 85 per cent. The redshift uncertainty remains impressively below than $\sim 0.001$. Notably, when concentrating on galaxies with more than three matched emission lines, the completeness of ELGs and the purity of measurable galaxies can reach 98 per cent and 97 per cent, respectively. Furthermore, we explore the influence of parameters like magnitude, spectral signal-to-noise ratio, and redshift on redshift completeness and purity. The discussion also delves into redshift degeneracies stemming from emission-line matching confusion. Our developed redshift measurement process will be applied to extensive simulated datasets and forthcoming CSST slitless spectroscopic observations for further cosmological and extragalactic analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11536v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sui Jipepng, Zou Hu, Yang Xiaohu, Zheng Xianzhong, Wen Run, Gu Yizhou, Ding Weiyu, Feng Lu, Guo Hong, Guo Wei-Jian, Han Yunkun, Jing Yipeng, Li Cheng, Li Wenxiong, Liu Shufei, Shen Zhixia, Singh Gaurav, Wang Jiali, Wei Peng, Xiao Yunao, Xue Suijian, Zhan Hu, Zhang Pengjie, Zhao Gongbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A population synthesis study of the Gaia 100 pc unresolved white dwarf-main sequence binary population</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Binary stars consisting of a white dwarf and a main sequence star (WDMS) are valuable for studying key astrophysical questions. However, observational biases strongly affect the known population, particularly unresolved systems where the main sequence star outshines the white dwarf. This work aims to comprehensively simulate the population of unresolved WDMS binaries within 100 pc of the Sun and to compare the outcome with the currently most complete volume-limited sample available from Gaia data. We employ a population synthesis code, MRBIN, extensively developed by our group and based on Monte Carlo techniques, which uses a standard binary stellar evolutionary code adapted to cover a wide range of stars across all ages, masses, and metallicities. Selection criteria matching those of Gaia observations are applied to generate synthetic populations comparable to the observed WDMS sample. The synthetic data accurately populate the expected regions in the Gaia color-magnitude diagram. However, simulations predict a lower number of extremely low-mass white dwarfs, suggesting potential issues in observed mass derivations. Additionally, our analysis constrains the common envelope efficiency to 0.1-0.4, consistent with previous findings, and estimates a total completeness of about 25% for the observed sample, confirming the strong observational limitations for unresolved WDMS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11593v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Santos-Garc\'ia, Santiago Torres, Alberto Rebassa-Mansergas, Alex J. Brown</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive Gaia view of ellipsoidal and rotational red giant binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11667v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The latest Gaia Focused Product Release (FPR) provided variability information for $\sim$1000 long-period red giant binaries, the largest sample to date of this binary type having both photometric and spectroscopic time series observations. We cross-matched the Gaia DR3 measurements with the catalogue of long-period red giant candidates from the Gaia FPR, having photometric and radial velocity variability information. Combined with the photo-geometric distances, the extinction, bolometric magnitude, luminosity, spectroscopic radius and mass were estimated. ELL variables are characterized to be low to intermediate-mass stars, with radii as large as the Roche lobe radius of the binary. Eccentricities tend to be lower for primary stars with smaller radii, as the expected result of tidal circularization. Combined with the orbital properties, estimates for the minimum mass of the companion agree with the scenario of a low-mass compact object as the secondary star. There are at least 14 ELL binaries with orbital periods and masses compatible with model predictions for Type Ia SN progenitors. For the rotational variables, their orbital periods, enhanced chromospheric activity, smaller radii and low mass point to a different type of binaries than the original ELL sample. The velocity dispersion is much higher in ELL than in rotational binaries, probably indicating older/younger dynamical ages. The enhanced [$\alpha$/Fe] abundances for some of the ELL binaries resemble the population of young $\alpha$-rich binaries in the thick disk. An episode of mass transfer in those systems may have produced the enhanced $\alpha$ abundances, and the enhanced [Ce/Fe] abundances reported in a few ELL binaries. Luminosities, radii and masses were derived for 243 ELL and 39 rotational binary candidates, the largest Galactic sample of these variables, having chemo-dynamical and physical parameterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11667v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camila Navarrete, Alejandra Recio-Blanco, Patrick de Laverny, Ana Escorza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for an accretion bridge in the DX Cha circumbinary system from VLTI/MATISSE observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: DX Cha (HD 104237) is a spectroscopic binary consisting of a Herbig A7.5Ve-A8Ve primary star and a K3-type companion. Here we report on new $3.55$ micrometer interferometric observations of this source with the Multi Aperture Mid-Infrared Spectroscopic Experiment (MATISSE) at the Very Large Telescope Interferometer (VLTI). To model the four MATISSE observations obtained between 2020 and 2023, we constructed a time-dependent interferometric model of the system, using the oimodeler software. The model consists of an asymmetric ring and two point sources on a Keplerian orbit. Our best-fit model consists of a circumbinary ring with a diameter of $0.86$ au ($8.1$ mas), featuring a strong azimuthal asymmetry. We found that the position angle of the asymmetry changes tens of degrees between the MATISSE epochs. The ring is relatively narrow, with a full width at half maximum (FWHM) of $\sim$$0.13$ au ($1.23$ mas). The presence of circumstellar dust emission so close to the binary is unexpected, as previous hydrodynamic simulations predicted an inner disk cavity with a diameter of $\sim$$4$ au ($\sim$$37.5$ mas). Thus, we argue that the narrow envelope of material we detected is probably not a gravitationally stable circumbinary ring, but may be part of tidal accretion streamers channeling material from the inner edge of the disk toward the stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11722v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T\'imea Juh\'asz, J\'ozsef Varga, P\'eter \'Abrah\'am, \'Agnes K\'osp\'al, Foteini Lykou, Lei Chen, Attila Mo\'or, Fernando Cruz-S\'aenz de Miera, Bruno Lopez, Alexis Matter, Roy van Boekel, Michiel Hogerheijde, Margaux Abello, Jean-Charles Augereau, Paul Boley, William C. Danchi, Thomas Henning, Mathis Letessier, Jie Ma, Philippe Priolet, Marten Scheuck, Gerd Weigelt, Sebastian Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Most Extreme Gamma-Ray Blazars Using Broadband Spectral Energy Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extreme high-synchrotron peaked blazars (EHSPs) are rare high-energy sources characterised by synchrotron peaks beyond 10$^{17}$ Hz in their spectral energy distributions (SEDs). Their extreme properties challenge conventional blazar emission models and provide a unique opportunity to test the limits of particle acceleration and emission mechanisms in relativistic jets. However, the number of identified EHSPs is still small, limiting comprehensive studies of their population and characteristics. This study aims to identify new EHSP candidates and characterise their emission properties. A sample of 124 $\gamma$-ray blazars is analysed, selected for their high synchrotron peak frequencies and $\gamma$-ray emission properties, with a focus on sources showing low variability and good broadband data coverage. Their SEDs are constructed using archival multi-wavelength data from the SSDC SED Builder service, supplemented with recent Swift-UVOT, Swift-XRT, and Fermi-LAT observations. The SEDs are modelled with a one-zone synchrotron/synchrotron-self-Compton framework, classifying sources by synchrotron peak frequency. We identify 66 new EHSP candidates, significantly expanding the known population. Their synchrotron peak frequencies are statistically higher than in previous studies, and they exhibit low Compton dominance, consistent with environments lacking strong external photon fields. A clear correlation between synchrotron peak frequency and the magnetic-to-kinetic energy density ratio is found, with the most extreme EHSPs nearing equipartition. Our analysis suggests that 9 high-synchrotron peaked/EHSPs could be observed by the Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) at $&gt;5\sigma$ (20 at $&gt;3\sigma$) in 20-hour exposures, highlighting their potential to improve studies of extreme jet physics and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11888v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. L\'ainez, M. Nievas-Rosillo, A. Dom\'inguez, J. L. Contreras, J. Becerra Gonz\'alez, A. Dinesh, V. S. Paliya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reionization and its sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reionization represents an important phase in the history of our Universe when ultraviolet radiation from the first luminous sources, primarily stars and accreting black holes, ionized the neutral hydrogen atoms in the intergalactic medium (IGM). This process follows the ``Dark Ages'', a period with no luminous sources, and is initiated by the formation of the first sources, marking the ``Cosmic Dawn''. Reionization proceeds through multiple stages: initially, ionized bubbles form around galaxies, then expand and overlap across the IGM, culminating in a fully ionized state, with neutral hydrogen remaining only in dense regions. Understanding reionization involves a diverse range of physical concepts, from large-scale structure formation and star formation to radiation propagation through the IGM. Observationally, reionization can be explored using the cosmic microwave background (CMB), Lyman-$\alpha$ absorption, high-redshift galaxy surveys, and emerging 21~cm experiments, which together offer invaluable insights into this transformative epoch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12004v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Chakraborty, Tirthankar Roy Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights from leptohadronic modelling of the brightest blazar flare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12111v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The blazar 3C 454.3 experienced a major flare in November 2010 making it the brightest $\gamma$-ray source in the sky of the Fermi-LAT. We obtain seven daily consecutive spectral-energy distributions (SEDs) of the flare in the infra-red, optical, ultra-violet, X-ray and $\gamma$-ray bands with publicly available data. We simulate the physical conditions in the blazar and show that the observed SEDs are well reproduced in the framework of a "standing feature" where the position of the emitting region is almost stationary, located beyond the outer radius of the broad-line region and into which fresh blobs of relativistically moving magnetized plasma are continuously injected. Meanwhile, a model with a single "moving blob" does not describe the data well. We obtain a robust upper limit to the amount of high-energy protons in the jet of 3C 454.3 from the electromagnetic SED. We construct a neutrino light curve of 3C 454.3 and estimate the expected neutrino yield at energies $\geq 100$ TeV for 3C 454.3 to be up to $6 \times 10^{-3}$ $\nu_{\mu}$ per year. Finally, we extrapolate our model findings to the light curves of all Fermi-LAT flat-spectrum radio quasars. We find that next-generation neutrino telescopes are expected to detect approximately one multimessenger ($\gamma + \nu_{\mu}$) flare per year from bright blazars with neutrino peak energy in the hundreds TeV -- hundreds PeV energy range and show that the electromagnetic flare peak can precede the neutrino arrival by months to years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12111v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Egor Podlesnyi, Foteini Oikonomou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pylevin: efficient numerical integration of integrals containing up to three Bessel functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12142v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Integrals involving highly oscillatory Bessel functions are notoriously challenging to compute using conventional integration techniques. While several methods are available, they predominantly cater to integrals with at most a single Bessel function, resulting in specialised yet highly optimised solutions. Here we present pylevin, a Python package to efficiently compute integrals containing up to three Bessel functions of arbitrary order and arguments. The implementation makes use of Levin's method and allows for accurate and fast integration of these highly oscillatory integrals. In benchmarking pylevin against existing software for single Bessel function integrals, we find its speed comparable, usually within a factor of two, to specialised packages such as FFTLog. Furthermore, when dealing with integrals containing two or three Bessel functions, pylevin delivers performance up to four orders of magnitude faster than standard adaptive quadrature methods, while also exhibiting better stability for large Bessel function arguments. pylevin is available from source via github or directly from PyPi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12142v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Reischke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematics of the Milky way from the statistical analysis of the Gaia Data Release 3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11060v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of the analysis of data from the Gaia Space Observatory is to obtain kinematic parameters of the collective motion of stars in a part of our galaxy. This research is based on a statistical analysis of the motion of {$55,038,539$} stars selected in different directions from the Sun up to a distance of 3--6 kpc. We developed statistical methods for the analysis working with input data represented by the full astrometric solution (five parameters). Using the proposed statistical methods, we obtained the local velocity of the Sun $\left( U_{\odot}% ,V_{\odot},W_{\odot}\right) =(9.58,16.25,7.33)\pm(0.05,0.04,0.02)_{stat}% \pm(0.7,0.9,0.1)_{syst}$ km/s and the rotation velocity of the galaxy at different radii. For the Sun's orbit radius, we obtained the velocity of the galaxy rotation$\ V_{c}\approx234\pm4$ km/s. Collective rotation slows down in the region under study linearly with distance from the disk plane: $\Delta V/\Delta Z\cong33.5~\mathrm{km\,s}^{-1}\mathrm{kpc}^{-1}$. We showed that the different kinematic characteristics and distributions, which depend on the position in the galaxy, can be well described in the studied 3D region by a simple Monte Carlo simulation model, representing an axisymmetric approximation of the galaxy kinematics. The optimal values of the six free parameters were tuned by comparison with the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11060v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/galaxies13010010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Galaxies 2025, 13(1), 10</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Petr Zavada, Karel P\'i\v{s}ka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Core Mass Function Across Galactic Environments. IV. The Galactic Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04032v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The origin of the stellar Initial Mass Function (IMF) and how it may vary with galactic environment is a matter of debate. Certain star formation theories involve a close connection between the IMF and the Core Mass Function (CMF) so it is important to measure this CMF in a range of Milky Way locations. Here we study the CMF of three Galactic Center clouds: G0.253+0.016 ("The Brick"), Sgr B2 (Deep South field) and Sgr C. We use ALMA 1 mm continuum images and identify cores as peaks in thermal dust emission via the dendrogram algorithm. We develop a completeness correction method via synthetic core insertion, utilizing a realistic mass-dependent size distribution. A power law $\text{d}N/\text{d}\log M \propto M^{-\alpha}$ is fit to the CMFs $&gt;2\:M_\odot$. The Brick has a Salpeter-like index $\alpha=1.28\pm0.09$, while the other regions have shallower indices: Sgr C has $\alpha=0.99\pm0.06$; Sgr B2-DS has $\alpha=0.70\pm0.03$. When smoothed to a common resolution, the differences between the Brick and the others increase as we obtain $\alpha=1.36\pm0.12$, $\alpha=0.66\pm0.06$ and $\alpha=0.62\pm0.04$, respectively, for masses $\gtrsim3\:M_\odot$. Furthermore, we analyze the spatial distribution and mass segregation of cores: Sgr C and Sgr B2-DS show signs of mass segregation, but the Brick does not. We compare our results to several other CMFs from different Galactic regions derived with the same methods. Finally, we discuss how our results may help define an evolutionary sequence of star cluster formation and be used to test star formation theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04032v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alva V. I. Kinman, Maya A. Petkova, Jonathan C. Tan, Giuliana Cosentino, Yu Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Evidence of a Major Merger in the Perseus Cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00115v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Although the Perseus cluster has often been regarded as an archetypical relaxed galaxy cluster, several lines of evidence including ancient, large-scale cold fronts, asymmetric plasma morphology, filamentary galaxy distribution, etc., provide a conflicting view of its dynamical state, suggesting that the cluster might have experienced a major merger. However, the absence of a clear merging companion identified to date hampers our understanding of the evolutionary track of the Perseus cluster consistent with these observational features. In this paper, through careful weak lensing analysis, we successfully identified the missing subcluster halo ($M_{200}=1.70^{+0.73}_{-0.59}\times10^{14}~M_{\odot}$) at the &gt;5$\sigma$ level centered on NGC1264, which is located ~430 kpc west of the Perseus main cluster core. Moreover, a significant ($&gt;3\sigma$) mass bridge, which is also traced by the cluster member galaxies, is detected between the Perseus main and sub clusters, which serves as direct evidence of gravitational interaction. With idealized numerical simulations, we demonstrate that a ~3:1 off-axis major merger can create the cold front observed ~700 kpc east of the main cluster core and also generate the observed mass bridge through multiple core crossings. This discovery resolves the long-standing puzzle of Perseus' dynamical state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00115v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim HyeongHan, M. James Jee, Wonki Lee, John ZuHone, Irina Zhuravleva, Wooseok Kang, Ho Seong Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star Proper Motions Based on Two-epoch Observations from the SDSS and DESI Imaging Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04016v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we present the construction of a new proper motion catalog utilizing the photometric data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) and Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) imaging surveys, with a median time baseline of about 13 years. To mitigate systematic errors, the DESI galaxy positions are employed to establish a reference frame and to correct the position-, magnitude-, and color-dependent discrepancies between SDSS and DESI imaging datasets. Spanning 12,589 square degrees, the catalog encompasses about 223.7 million non-Gaia objects down to $m_r \sim$ 23. Based on 734k quasars, the assessment of the global systematic errors in the DESI-SDSS proper motion catalog yields values of 0.06 mas yr$^{-1}$ for $\mu_{\alpha_{*}}$ and 0.12 mas yr$^{-1}$ for $\mu_{\delta}$. The catalog exhibits precision surpassing 3.4 mas yr$^{-1}$, albeit varying with position, color, and magnitude. An additional evaluation employing approximately 2,644 distant star samples yields an overall precision of approximately 2.5 and 2.9 mas yr$^{-1}$ for $\mu_{\alpha_{*}}$ and $\mu_{\delta}$, respectively. Further comparisons with proper motions from SDSS Stripe 82 reveal a strong consistency between the two datasets. As a practical application, we utilize fainter non-Gaia objects in our catalog to update the proper motions of 15 star clusters. The resulting proper motions for these clusters exhibit excellent consistency with those derived from Gaia data. Our proper motion measurements, characterized by a deeper limiting magnitude, stand as a valuable complement to the Gaia dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04016v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun-Ao Xiao, Hu Zou, Xin Xu, Lu Feng, Wei-Jian Guo, Wen-Xiong Li, Shu-Fei Liu, Zhi-Xia Shen, Gaurav Singh, Ji-Peng Sui, Jia-Li Wang, Sui-Jian Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GA-NIFS: Multi-phase analysis of a star-forming galaxy at $z \sim 5.5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19008v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we present a detailed multiphase analysis of HZ4, a main-sequence star-forming galaxy at z ~ 5.5, known for being a turbulent rotating disk and having a detection of a [CII] outflow in the ALMA observations. We exploit JWST/NIRSpec observations in the integral field spectroscopy mode with low- and high-spectral resolution that allow us for the first time to spatially resolve the rest-frame UV and optical emission of the galaxy to investigate the galaxy properties. In particular, the high-resolution dataset allows us to study the kinematics of the ionized gas phase, and the conditions of the interstellar medium, such as the excitation mechanism, dust attenuation, and metallicity. The lower-spectral resolution observations allow us to study the continuum emission and infer the stellar populations' ages and properties. Our findings suggest that HZ4 is a galaxy merger rather than a rotating disk as previously inferred from lower resolution [CII] data. The merger is associated with an extended broad, blueshifted emission, potentially indicative of an outflow originating from a region of intense star formation and extending up to 4 kpc. In light of these new observations we reanalyzed the ALMA data to compare the multiphase gas properties. If we interpret the broad components seen in [CII] and [OIII]$\lambda$5007\.A as outflows, the neutral and ionized components are co-spatial, the mass loading factor of the ionized phase is significantly lower than that of the neutral phase, aligning with trends observed in multi-phase systems at lower redshifts. Nonetheless, additional observations and larger statistical samples are essential to determine the role of mergers and outflows in the early Universe and to clarify the origin of the broad emission components observed in this system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19008v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleonora Parlanti, Stefano Carniani, Giacomo Venturi, Rodrigo Herrera-Camus, Santiago Arribas, Andrew J. Bunker, Stephane Charlot, Francesco D'Eugenio, Roberto Maiolino, Michele Perna, Hannah \"Ubler, Torsten B\"oker, Giovanni Cresci, Mirko Curti, Gareth C. Jones, Isabella Lamperti, Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, Bruno Rodr\'iguez Del Pino, Sandra Zamora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AGN -- host galaxy photometric decomposition using a fast, accurate and precise deep learning approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01437v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Identifying active galactic nuclei (AGN) is extremely important for understanding galaxy evolution and its connection with the assembly of supermassive black holes (SMBH). With the advent of deep and high angular resolution imaging surveys such as those conducted with the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), it is now possible to identify galaxies with a central point source out to the very early Universe. In this study, we develop a fast, accurate and precise method to identify galaxies which host AGNs and recover the intrinsic AGN contribution to the observed total light ($f_{AGN}$). We trained a deep learning (DL) based method Zoobot to estimate the fractional contribution of a central point source to the total light. Our training sample comprises realistic mock JWST images of simulated galaxies from the IllustrisTNG cosmological hydrodynamical simulations. We injected different amounts of the real JWST point spread function (PSF) models to represent galaxies with different levels of $f_{AGN}$. We analyse the performance of our method and compare it with results obtained from the traditional light profile fitting tool GALFIT. We find excellent performance of our DL method in recovering the injected AGN fraction $f_{AGN}$, both in terms of precision and accuracy. The mean difference between the predicted and true injected $f_{AGN}$ is -0.002 and the overall root mean square error (RMSE) is 0.013. The relative absolute error (RAE) is 0.076 and the outlier (defined as predictions with RAE &gt;20%) fraction is 6.5%. In comparison, using GALFIT on the same dataset, we achieve a mean difference of -0.02, RMSE of 0.12, RAE of 0.19 and outlier fraction of 19%. We applied our trained DL model to real JWST observations and found that 33% of X-ray-selected AGN and 15% of MIR-selected AGN are also identified as AGN using a cut at $f_{\rm AGN} &gt; 0.1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01437v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Berta Margalef-Bentabol, Lingyu Wang, Antonio La Marca, Vicente Rodriguez-Gomez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blowing star formation away in AGN Hosts (BAH) - II. Investigating the origin of the H2 emission excess in nearby galaxies with JWST MIRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06960v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI) medium-resolution spectrometer (MRS) observations of 3C 293 (UGC 8782), CGCG 012-070 and NGC 3884 to investigate the origin of the H$_2$ emission. These three nearby Active Galactic Nucleus (AGN) hosts are known to present H$_2$ emission excess relative to star-forming galaxies, as traced by the H$_2$ S(3)/PAH$_{\rm 11.3\mu m}$ line ratio. We define the kinematically disturbed region (KDR) by the AGN and the virially dominated region (VDR) based on the H$_2$ line widths, using the $W{\rm 80}$ parameter. From the correlations between $W{\rm 80}$ and H$_2$ S(3)/PAH${\rm 11.3\mu m}$, as well as the higher H$2$ S(5)/H$2$ S(3) and [Fe II]${\rm 5.34 \mu m}$/PAH${\rm 11.3\mu m}$ ratios and flatter power-law temperature distributions observed in the KDR, we conclude that the H$_2$ emission in the KDR is primarily driven by shock-heated gas. For 3C 293, the KDR is co-spatial with the radio core, indicating that the origin of the shocks is the interaction of the radio jet with the interstellar medium, which is also responsible for the observed molecular and ionized gas outflows in this source. The other galaxies are weak radio sources; however, due to the lack of high-resolution radio images, we cannot rule out low-power jets as the origin of the shock-heated H$_2$. Our results indicate that the excess H$_2$ emission excess is associated to shock heating of the gas, generated by outflows or by the interaction of the radio jet with the ambient gas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06960v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rogemar A. Riffel, Gabriel L. Souza-Oliveira, Jos\'e Henrique Costa-Souza, Nadia L. Zakamska, Thaisa Storchi-Bergmann, Rog\'erio Riffel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Untangling Magellanic Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Magellanic Stream (MS) has long been known to contain multiple H I strands and corresponding stellar populations are beginning to be discovered. Combining a sample of 17 stars from the H3 ("Hectochelle in the Halo at High Resolution") survey with 891 stars drawn from the Gaia DR3 catalog, we trace stars along a sub-dominant strand of the MS, as defined by gas content, across 30$^\circ$ on the sky. We find that the corresponding dominant strand at the similar position along the MS is devoid of stars with Galactocentric distance $\lesssim 55$ kpc while the subdominant strand shows a close correspondence to such stars. We conclude that (1) these two Stream strands have different origins, (2) they are likely only close in projection, (3) the subdominant strand is tidal in origin, and (4) the subdominant strand is composed of "disk" material, gas and stars, with a chemical composition that marginally favors it coming from the Small Magellanic Cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15044v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Zaritsky, Vedant Chandra, Charlie Conroy, Ana Bonaca, Phillip A. Cargile, Rohan P. Naidu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed origins: strong natal kicks for some black holes and none for others</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16847v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using stellar kinematic data from Gaia DR3, we revisit constraints on black hole (BH) natal kicks from observed accreting and detached BH binaries. We compare the space velocities and Galactic orbits of a sample of 12 BHs in the Galactic disk with well-constrained distances to their local stellar populations, for which we obtain proper motions and radial velocities from Gaia DR3. Compared to most previous studies, we infer lower minimum kick velocities, because our modeling accounts for the fact that most BH binaries are old and have likely been kinematically heated by processes other than kicks. Nevertheless, we find that half of the BHs have at least weak evidence for a kick, being kinematically hotter than at least 68% of their local stellar populations. At least 4 BHs are kinematically hotter than 90% of their local stellar populations, suggesting they were born with kicks of $\gtrsim 100$ km s$^{-1}$. On the other hand, 6 BHs have kinematics typical of their local populations, disfavoring kicks of $\gtrsim 50$ km s$^{-1}$. For two BHs, V404 Cyg and VFTS 243, there is strong independent evidence for a very weak kick $\lesssim 10$ km s$^{-1}$. Our analysis implies that while some BHs must form with very weak kicks, it would be wrong to conclude that most BHs do, particularly given that selection biases favor weak kicks. Although the uncertainties on most individual BHs' kicks are still too large to assess whether the kick distribution is bimodal, the data are consistent with a scenario where some BHs form by direct collapse and receive weak kicks, and others form in supernovae and receive strong kicks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16847v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Nagarajan, Kareem El-Badry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fading Light, Fierce Winds: JWST Snapshot of a Sub-Eddington Quasar at Cosmic Dawn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04548v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The majority of most luminous quasars during the epoch of reionization accrete near or above the Eddington limit, marking the vigorous growth of primitive supermassive black holes (SMBHs). However, their subsequent evolution and environmental impact remain poorly characterized. We present JWST/NIRSpec prism IFU observations of HSC J2239+0207, a low-luminosity quasar at $z\sim6.25$ likely in a late stage of mass assembly with an overmassive SMBH relative to its host galaxy. Using H$\beta$ and H$\alpha$ broad emission lines, we estimate an SMBH mass $M_{\rm BH}\sim3\times10^8~M_{\odot}$ and confirm its sub-Eddington accretion at $\lambda_{\rm Edd}\sim0.4$. Strong FeII emission and a proximity zone of typical size suggest a metal-rich, highly evolved system. In the far-UV, this quasar presents strong broad-absorption-line features, indicative of high-velocity winds ($\nu\sim10^4~{\rm km/s}$). Meanwhile, minimal dust reddening is inferred from the quasar continuum and broad-line Balmer decrement, suggesting little dust along the polar direction. Most interestingly, we identify a gas companion $\sim$5 kpc from the quasar with a high [OIII]/H$\beta$ ratio ($\gtrsim10$), likely representing outflowing gas blown away by AGN feedback. These results highlight HSC J2239+0207 as a likely fading quasar in transition, providing rare insights into SMBH evolution, AGN feedback, and AGN-galaxy interactions in the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04548v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianwei Lyu, George H. Rieke, Meredith Stone, Jane Morrison, Stacey Alberts, Xiangyu Jin, Yongda Zhu, Weizhe Liu, Jinyi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-raying CAMELS: Constraining Baryonic Feedback in the Circum-Galactic Medium with the CAMELS simulations and eRASS X-ray Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04559v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The circumgalactic medium (CGM) around massive galaxies plays a crucial role in regulating star formation and feedback. Using the CAMELS simulation suite, we develop emulators for the X-ray surface brightness profile and the X-ray luminosity--stellar mass scaling relation to investigate how stellar and AGN feedback shape the X-ray properties of the hot CGM. Our analysis shows that at CGM scales ($10^{12} \lesssim M_{\rm halo}/M_\odot \lesssim 10^{13}$, $10\lesssim r/{\rm kpc} \lesssim 400$), stellar feedback more significantly impacts the X-ray properties than AGN feedback within the parameters studied. Comparing the emulators to recent eROSITA All-Sky Survey observations, it was found that stronger feedback than currently implemented in the IllustrisTNG, SIMBA, and Astrid simulations is required to match observed CGM properties. However, adopting these enhanced feedback parameters causes deviations in the stellar-mass-halo-mass relations from observational constraints below the group mass scale. This tension suggests possible unaccounted systematics in X-ray CGM observations or inadequacies in the feedback models of cosmological simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04559v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erwin T. Lau, Daisuke Nagai, \'Akos Bogd\'an, Isabel Medlock, Benjamin D. Oppenheimer, Nicholas Battaglia, Daniel Angl\'es-Alc\'azar, Shy Genel, Yueying Ni, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering the properties of the interstellar medium through integrated spectroscopy: application to the z~0 ECO volume-limited star-forming galaxy sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15860v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deriving physical parameters from integrated galaxy spectra is paramount to interpret the cosmic evolution of star formation, chemical enrichment, and energetic sources. We develop modeling techniques to characterize the ionized gas properties in the subset of 2052 star-forming galaxies from the volume-limited, dwarf-dominated, z~0 ECO catalog. The MULTIGRIS statistical framework is used to evaluate the performance of various models using strong lines as constraints. The reference model involves physical parameters distributed as power-laws with free parameter boundaries. Specifically, we use combinations of 1D photoionization models (i.e., considering the propagation of radiation toward a single cloud) to match optical HII region lines, in order to provide probability density functions of the inferred parameters. The inference predicts non-uniform physical conditions within galaxies. The integrated spectra of most galaxies are dominated by relatively low-excitation gas with a metallicity around 0.3 solar. Using the average metallicity in galaxies, we provide a new fit to the mass-metallicity relationship which is in line with direct abundance method determinations from the calibrated range at low metallicity to stacks at high metallicity. The average metallicity shows a weakly bimodal distribution which may be due related to external (e.g., refueling of non-cluster early-type galaxies above ~10^9.5 solar masses) or internal processes (more efficient star-formation in metal-rich regions). The specific line set used for inference affects the results and we identify potential issues with the use of the [SII] line doublet. Complex modelling approaches are limited by the inherent 1D model database as well as caveats regarding the gas geometry. Our results highlight, however, the possibility to extract useful and significant information from integrated spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15860v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Lebouteiller, C. T. Richardson, M. S. Polimera, D. S. Carr, Z. L. Hutchens, S. J. Kannappan, L. Ramambason, A. J. Moffett, M. Varese, S. C. Madden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full disc [CII] mapping of nearby star-forming galaxies: SOFIA FIFI/LS observations of NGC 3627, NGC 4321, and NGC 6946</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17645v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As a major cooling line of interstellar gas, the far-infrared 158 {\mu}m line from singly ionised carbon [CII] is an important tracer of various components of the interstellar medium in galaxies across all spatial and morphological scales. Yet, there is still not a strong constraint on the origins of [CII] emission. In this work, we derive the resolved [CII] star formation rate relation and aim to unravel the complexity of the origin of [CII]. We used the Field-Imaging Far-Infrared Line Spectrometer on board the Stratospheric Observatory for Infrared Astronomy to map [CII] in three nearby star-forming galaxies at sub-kiloparsec scales, namely, NGC 3627, NGC 4321, and NGC 6946, and we compared these [CII] observations to the galactic properties derived from complementary data from the literature. We find that the relationship between the [CII] fine structure line and star formation rate shows variations between the galaxies as well as between different environments within each galaxy. Our results show that the use of [CII] as a tracer for star formation is much more tangled than has previously been suggested within the extragalactic literature, which typically focuses on small regions of galaxies and/or uses large-aperture sampling of many different physical environments. As found within resolved observations of the Milky Way, the picture obtained from [CII] observations is complicated by its local interstellar medium conditions. Future studies will require a larger sample and additional observational tracers, obtained on spatial scales within galaxies, in order to accurately disentangle the origin of [CII] and calibrate its use as a star formation tracer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17645v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202450062</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 694, A87 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. Kova\v{c}i\'c (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Universit\"at Bonn, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), A. T. Barnes (European Southern Observatory, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Universit\"at Bonn, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), F. Bigiel (Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Universit\"at Bonn, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), I. De Looze (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium), S. C. Madden (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), R. Herrera-Camus (Departamento de Astronom\'ia, Universidad de Concepci\'on, Barrio Universitario, Concepci\'on, Chile), A. Krabbe (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), M. Baes (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium), A. Beck (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), A. D. Bolatto (Department of Astronomy, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742, USA), A. Bryant (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), S. Colditz (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), C. Fischer (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), N. Geis (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur extraterrestrische Physik, Gie{\ss}enbachstrasse 1, D-85748 Garching, Germany), C. Iserlohe (Deutsches SOFIA Institut, Universit\"at Stuttgart, Pfaffenwaldring 29, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany), R. Klein (SOFIA-USRA, NASA Ames Research Center, MS N232-12, Moffett Field, CA 94035-1000, USA), A. Leroy (Department of Astronomy, The Ohio State University, 140 West 18th Avenue, Columbus, OH 43210, USA), L. W. Looney (Department of Astronomy, University of Illinois, 1002 W Green Street, Urbana, IL 61801, USA, National Radio Astronomy Observatory, 520 Edgemont Rd. Charlottesville, VA 22903, USA), A. Poglitsch (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur extraterrestrische Physik, Gie{\ss}enbachstrasse 1, D-85748 Garching, Germany), N. S. Sartorio (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium), W. D. Vacca (NSF's NOIRLab, 950 N. Cherry Avenue, Tucson, AZ 85719, USA), S. van der Giessen (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium, Departamento de F\'isica Te\'orica y del Cosmos, Universidad de Granada), A. Nersesian (STAR Institute, Universit\'e de Li\`ege, Quartier Agora, All\'ee du Six Ao\^ut 19c, 4000 Li\`ege, Belgium, Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 / S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An intriguing coincidence between the majority of vast polar structure dwarfs and a recent major merger at the M31 position</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00870v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A significant part of the Milky Way (MW) dwarf galaxies orbit within a Vast POlar Structure (VPOS), which is perpendicular to the Galactic disc and whose origin has not yet been identified. It includes the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) and its six dynamically associated dwarf galaxies. Andromeda Galaxy (M31) experienced a major merger two to three billion years ago, and its accurate modelling predicts that an associated tidal tail is pointing towards the Galaxy. Here, we tested a possible association between M31 tidal tail particles and MW dwarf galaxies, focusing first on the LMC and its associated dwarfs since they are less affected by ram pressure. We traced back these dwarf galaxy orbits by one billion years and calculated their association with the tidal tail particles in the 6D phase space, based on their proper motion from \textit{Gaia} DR3. We find that for low-mass MW models (total mass less than 5 $\times 10^{11} M_{\odot}$), the separation in the 6D space can be less than 1$\sigma$ for most of the M31 modelling, albeit with a significant degree of freedom due to the still unknown proper motion of M31. We further discover that many other dwarfs could also be associated with the M31 tidal tails if their motions had been radially slowed, as expected from the ram pressure exerted by the MW corona. This intriguing coincidence could explain the origin of the VPOS, which resulted from a matter exchange between M31 and MW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00870v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202452131</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 694, A66 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Istiak Akib, Fran\c{c}ois Hammer, Yanbin Yang, Marcel S. Pawlowski, Jianling Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Group-Dominant Elliptical NGC 5044 in the Radio Band: Continuum Emission and Detection of HI Absorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02076v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present new MeerKAT L-band (continuum and HI) and upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (300-850 MHz) observations of the archetypal cool-core group-dominant early-type galaxy NGC 5044. Our new continuum images reveal diffuse, steep spectrum ($\alpha_{0.99\,\rm GHz}^{1.56\,\rm GHz}=-1.53\pm0.6$) radio emission extending about 25 kpc around the unresolved radio core. The observed radio emission overlaps with the known X-ray cavities, but is not confined to them. We also find the first direct evidence of neutral atomic gas in NGC 5044, in the form of a 3.8$\sigma$ significant two-component HI absorption line seen against the emission of the active nucleus. The peak velocities are well correlated with the previously reported CO(2-1) absorption, but the HI lines are moderately broader, spanning velocities from $265\,\rm \, km\,s^{-1}$ to $305\,\rm \, km\,s^{-1}$. We do not detect HI emission, but place an upper limit of $M_{HI}&lt; 5.4 \times 10^{7} \, M_{\odot}$ in the central 15 arcsec (2.2 kpc) of the galaxy. This is significantly less than the estimated molecular gas content, and implies a molecular-to-atomic mass ratio of $\geq $1.7:1, consistent with these gas phases forming through cooling from the hot intra-group medium. We also constrain the spin temperature to $T_{\rm spin}\leq 950\,\rm K$, indicating that the detected HI is in the cold neutral phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02076v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamlesh Rajpurohit, Tirna Deb, Konstantinos Kolokythas, Kshitij Thorat, Ewan O'Sullivan, Gerrit Schellenberger, Laurence P. David, Jan M. Vrtilek, Simona Giacintucci, William Forman, Christine Jones, Mpati Ramatsoku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Filamentary Nebula of NGC 1275 with Multiwavelength SITELLE Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05406v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The filamentary nebula encompassing the central galaxy of the Perseus Cluster, NGC 1275, is a complex structure extending dozens of kiloparsecs from NGC 1275. Decades of previous works have focused on establishing the primary formation and ionization mechanisms in different filaments. These studies have pointed to a lack of star formation in the majority of the filaments, the importance of magnetic fields and turbulence in several regions, and the role of interactions between the intercluster medium (ICM) and the cool gas in the filaments, as well as the role of interaction between the central radio source, 3C84, and the filaments. In this paper, we present multi-filter observations of the entire filamentary system that cover the optical bandpass, using the SITELLE instrument at the Canada-France-Hawai'i Telescope. Here, we use the data analysis software, \href{https://crhea93.github.io/LUCI/index.html}{\texttt{LUCI}}, to produce flux maps of the prominent emission lines present in the filters: \oii{}$\lambda$3726/3729, \oiii{}$\lambda$5007, H$\beta$, \nii{}$\lambda$6548, \nii{}$\lambda$6583, and H$\alpha$. We use these maps to produce BPT and WHAN diagrams to study the ionization mechanisms at play in each distinct region of the filamentary nebula. First, we confirm the absence of \oiii{}$\lambda$5007 in the extended filaments, although we detect this line in the central core, revealing a compact region where photoionization by the AGN might affect local conditions. Our findings corroborate previous claims that the ionization in the extended filaments could be caused by the cooling ICM via collisional excitation and/or mixing. Moreover, they support the conclusion that magnetic fields play an important role in the formation and continued existence of the filaments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05406v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carter Lee Rhea, Julie Hlavacek-Larrondo, Marie-Lou Gendron-Marsolais, Benjamin Vigneron, Megan Donahue, Auriane Thilloy, Laurie Rousseau-Nepton, Mar Mezcua, Norbert Werner, Jorge Barrera-Ballesteros, Hyunseop Choi, Alastair Edge, Andrew Fabian, G. Mark Voit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black hole spectroscopy in environments: detectability prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ringdown phase following a binary black hole coalescence is a powerful tool for measuring properties of the remnant black hole. Future gravitational wave detectors will increase the precision of these measurements and may be sensitive to the environment surrounding the black hole. This work examines how environments affect the ringdown from a binary coalescence. Our analysis shows that for astrophysical parameters and sensitivity of planned detectors, the ringdown signal is indistinguishable from its vacuum counterpart, suggesting that ringdown-only analyses can reliably extract the (redshifted) mass and spin of the remnant black hole. These conclusions include models with spectral instabilities, suggesting that these are not relevant from an observational viewpoint. Deviations from inspiral-only estimates could then enhance the characterisation of environmental effects present during the coalescence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05950v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas F. M. Spieksma, Vitor Cardoso, Gregorio Carullo, Matteo Della Rocca, Francisco Duque</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the CREDIT history of supernova remnants as cosmic-ray sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11012v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Supernova remnants (SNRs) have long been suspected to be the primary sources of Galactic cosmic rays. Over the past decades, great strides have been made in the modelling of particle acceleration, magnetic field amplification, and escape from SNRs. Yet, while many SNRs have been observed in non-thermal emission in radio, X-rays, and gamma-rays, there is no evidence for any individual object contributing to the locally observed flux. Here, we propose a particular spectral signature from individual remnants that is due to the energy-dependent escape from SNRs. For young and nearby sources, we predict fluxes enhanced by tens of percent in narrow rigidity intervals; given the percent-level flux uncertainties of contemporary cosmic-ray data, such features should be readily detectable. We model the spatial and temporal distribution of sources and the resulting distribution of fluxes with a Monte Carlo approach. The decision tree that we have trained on simulated data is able to discriminate with very high significance between the null hypothesis of a smooth distribution of sources and the scenario with a stochastic distribution of individual sources. We suggest that this cosmic-ray energy-dependent injection time (CREDIT) scenario be considered in experimental searches to identify individual SNRs as cosmic-ray sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11012v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adaea8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Anton Stall et al 2025 ApJL 980 L21</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anton Stall, Chun Khai Loo, Philipp Mertsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the Mean Free Path of HI Ionizing Photons at $3.2\leq z\leq4.6$ with DESI Y1 Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15838v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The mean free path of ionizing photons ($\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}$) in the intergalactic medium (IGM) is a crucial quantity in modelling the ionization state of IGM and the extragalactic ultraviolet background (EUVB), and is widely used in hydrodynamical simulations of galaxies and reionization. We construct the largest quasar spectrum dataset to date -- 12,595 $\mathrm{S/N}&gt;3$ spectra -- using the Y1 observation of Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) to make the most precise model-independent measurement of the mean free path at $3.2\leq z\leq 4.6$. By stacking the spectra in 17 redshift bins and modelling the Lyman continuum profile, we get a redshift evolution $\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}\propto(1+z)^{-4.27}$ at $2\leq z\leq 5$, which is much shallower than previous estimate $\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}\propto(1+z)^{-5.4}$. We then explore the sources of systematic bias, including the choice of intrinsic quasar continuum, the consideration of Lyman series opacity and Lyman limit opacity evolution and the definition of $\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}$. Combining our results with estimates of $\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}$ at higher redshifts, we conclude at high confidence that the evolution in $\lambda_\mathrm{mfp}^{912}$ steepens at $z \approx 5$. We interpret this inflection as the transition from the end of HI reionization to a fully ionized plasma which characterizes the intergalactic medium of the past $\sim10$ billion years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15838v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anning Gao, Jason X. Prochaska, Zheng Cai, Siwei Zou, Cheng Zhao, Zechang Sun, S. Ahlen, D. Bianchi, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, A. de la Macorra, Arjun Dey, P. Doel, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, G. Gutierrez, K. Honscheid, S. Juneau, A. Kremin, P. Martini, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, A. Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, J. A. Newman, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, M. Schubnell, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarl\'e, B. A. Weaver, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beam Measurements of Full Stokes Parameters for the FAST L-band 19-beam Receiver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18865v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical radio Telescope (FAST) has been fully operational since 11 January 2020. We present a comprehensive analysis of the beam structure for each of the 19 feed horns on FAST's L-band receiver across the Stokes I, Q, U, and V parameters. Using an on-the-fly mapping pattern, we conducted simultaneous sky mapping using all 19 beams directed towards polarization calibrators J1407+2827 and J0854+2006 from 2020 to 2022. Electromagnetic simulations were also performed to model the telescope's beam patterns in all Stokes parameters. Our findings reveal a symmetrical Gaussian pattern in the Stokes I parameter of the central beam without strong sidelobes, while the off-center beams exhibit significant asymmetrical shapes that can be fitted using a combination of log-normal and Gaussian distributions. The inner beams have higher relative beam efficiencies and smaller beam sizes compared to those of the outer beams. The sidelobes of the inner beams contribute approximately 2% of the total flux in the main lobe, increasing to 5% for outer beams, with a peak at 6.8%. In Stokes U, a distinct four-lobed cloverleaf beam squash structure is observed, with similar intensity levels in both inner and outer beams. In Stokes V, a two-lobed beam squint structure is observed in the central beam, along with a secondary eight-lobed structure. The highest squint peak in Stokes V is about 0.3% of the Stokes I in the outer beams. These results align closely with the simulations, providing valuable insights for the design of radio multi-beam observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18865v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ada8aa</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xunzhou Chen, Tao-Chung Ching, Di Li, Carl Heiles, Timothy Robishaw, Xuan Du, Marko Krco, Peng Jiang, Qingliang Yang, Jiguang Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eclipsing Binaries via Artificial Intelligence. II. Need for Speed in PHOEBE Forward Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In modern astronomy, the quantity of data collected has vastly exceeded the capacity for manual analysis, necessitating the use of advanced artificial intelligence (AI) techniques to assist scientists with the most labor-intensive tasks. AI can optimize simulation codes where computational bottlenecks arise from the time required to generate forward models. One such example is PHOEBE, a modeling code for eclipsing binaries (EBs), where simulating individual systems is feasible, but analyzing observables for extensive parameter combinations is highly time-consuming.
  To address this, we present a fully connected feedforward artificial neural network (ANN) trained on a dataset of over one million synthetic light curves generated with PHOEBE. Optimization of the ANN architecture yielded a model with six hidden layers, each containing 512 nodes, provides an optimized balance between accuracy and computational complexity. Extensive testing enabled us to establish ANN's applicability limits and to quantify the systematic and statistical errors associated with using such networks for EB analysis. Our findings demonstrate the critical role of dilution effects in parameter estimation for EBs, and we outline methods to incorporate these effects in AI-based models.
  This proposed ANN framework enables a speedup of over four orders of magnitude compared to traditional methods, with systematic errors not exceeding 1\%, and often as low as 0.01\%, across the entire parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11837v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/ada4ae</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series 277 (2025) 1</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marcin Wrona, Andrej Pr\v{s}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A differentiable binary microlensing model using adaptive contour integration method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07268v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present microlux, which is a Jax-based code that can compute the binary microlensing light curve and its derivatives both efficiently and accurately. The key feature of microlux is the implementation of a modified version of the adaptive sampling algorithm that was originally proposed by V. Bozza to account for the finite-source effect most efficiently. The efficiency and accuracy of microlux have been verified across the relevant parameter space for binary microlensing. As a differentiable code, microlux makes it possible to apply gradient-based algorithms to the search and posterior estimation of the microlensing modeling. As an example, we use microlux to model a real microlensing event and infer the model posterior via both Fisher information matrix and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, neither of which would have been possible without the access to accurate model gradients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07268v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/adb1b2</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Haibin Ren, Wei Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
