<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 04:05:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Variations of angular momentum $L_z$ as an indicator of orbital chaos of globular clusters in the central region of the Galaxy with a bar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown how the violation of the invariance of the $Z$-component of the orbital angular momentum $L_z$ in the axially symmetric potential of the Galaxy with a bar can serve as an indicator of the degree of orbital chaos of globular clusters in the central region of the Galaxy. In this case, the higher the variations of $L_z$ of the orbit over a certain period of time, the higher the chaos of the orbit. In essence, a new method for analyzing orbital dynamics -- regular or chaotic -- is proposed. A high level of correlation between the results of orbit classification by the proposed method and the results of classification by other methods is shown. As a result, a sample of 45 globular clusters in the central region of the Galaxy with a radius of 3.5 kpc is divided into regular, chaotic, and weakly chaotic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10682v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.31725/0367-7966-2025-238-1-10</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Publications of the Pulkovo Observatory, N 238, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. T. ~Bajkova, A. A. ~Smirnov, V. V. ~Bobylev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaching for the Edge II: Stellar Halos out to Large Radii as a Tracer of Dark Matter Halo Mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The diffuse outskirts of brightest cluster galaxies (BCGs) encode valuable information about the assembly history and mass of their host dark matter halos. However, the low surface brightness of these stellar halos has historically made them difficult to observe. Recent deep imaging, particularly with Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC), has shown that the stellar mass within relatively large projected annuli, such as within $50$ and $100$ kpc, is a promising proxy for halo mass. However, the optimal radial definition of this "outskirt mass" remains uncertain. We construct an HSC-like mock observing pipeline to measure the stellar mass density profiles of BCGs in the IllustrisTNG simulations. Our mock observations closely reproduce HSC profiles across six orders of magnitude in surface density. We then systematically measure stellar masses within different annuli and how tightly they are connected to halo mass. We find that stellar masses measured within simple apertures exhibit considerably more scatter in the stellar mass-halo mass relation than those measured within projected ellipsoidal annuli. We identify an optimal range of definitions, with inner radii between $\sim 70$-$200$ kpc and outer radii between $\sim 125$-$500$ kpc. We also introduce two halo-mass-dependent S\'ersic models for the average stellar halo profiles. We present a S\'ersic-based fitting function that describes the profiles as a function of the halo mass, $M_{\rm vir}$, with a median error of $54\%$. Adding the central stellar mass of the BCG as a second parameter slightly improves the accuracy to a median error of $39\%$. Together, these results provide fitting functions for BCG stellar halos that can be applied to future wide-field surveys to infer halo masses from deep imaging data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10723v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katya Leidig, Benedikt Diemer, Song Huang, Shuo Xu, Conghao Zhou, Alexie Leauthaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back to basics: Little Red Dots as galaxies and dust-obscured AGNs in a synthetic NIRCam sky simulated with L-GalaxiesBH</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The enigmatic Little Red Dots (LRDs) discovered by the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) exhibit properties challenging their interpretation as common galaxies or Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN). Understanding their nature is key to placing them within our picture of early galaxy and massive black hole (MBH) evolution. To this aim, we build a realistic comparison between LRD observations with photometric properties of galaxies and AGN simulated by the L-GalaxiesBH model in a NIRCam mock sky. We model stellar continua and emission lines, the MBH emission from accretion disk, infrared radiation from dusty torus, and lines from narrow and broad line regions, accounting for dust attenuation and obscuration. Using realistic photometric cuts, we select a population of LRDs including both AGN and galaxies. The LRD fraction peaks at 40% ($\sim10^{-4}\rm Mpc^{-3}$) at $z\sim4$. Our LRDs are central galaxies spanning $M_*=10^8-10^{10.5}\rm M_\odot$. A population of galaxies with $M_*&lt;10^9\rm M_\odot$ appear as LRDs due to older stellar populations. At higher masses, LRDs dominate the halo and stellar mass functions ($M_{\rm vir} &gt; 10^{11.5}\rm M_\odot$, $M_* &gt; 10^{9.5}\rm M_\odot$), and the interplay between AGN and galaxy emission drives the LRD selection. AGN dominate rest-frame UV-optical emission, while dust obscuration is secondary. LRDs host lighter MBHs ($\sim 10^{6.5}\rm M_\odot$) than non-LRDs ($\sim 10^{7.5}\rm M_\odot$), with fainter emission unable to balance their hosts Balmer breaks. We find no evidence for dominant heavy-seed origin of MBHs. LRD Galaxies (97% hosting MBHs) and LRD AGNs are disk-dominated, with LRD AGNs showing larger bulges formed mainly via disk instabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10725v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Herrero-Carri\'on, Daniele Spinoso, David Izquierdo-Villalba, Tong Su, Silvia Bonoli, Pablo Renard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Structure in COSMOS-Web: Tracing Galaxy Evolution in the Cosmic Web up to $z \sim 7$ with the Largest JWST Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a reconstruction of the large-scale structure using the James Webb Space Telescope's (JWST) COSMOS-Web program to trace environmentally driven galaxy evolution up to $z\sim7$. We applied a weighted kernel density estimation method to 160,000 galaxies with robust photometric redshifts. We find that stellar mass has a positive correlation with density at all redshifts, stronger for quiescent galaxies (QGs) at $z\lesssim2.5$, while at higher redshifts ($2.5\lesssim z\lesssim5.5$) this trend is confined to extreme overdense environments, consistent with early mass assembly in proto-clusters. The star-formation rate (SFR) shows a negative trend with density for QGs at $z\lesssim1.2$, reversing at $z\gtrsim1.8$, while star-forming galaxies (SFGs) show a mild positive correlation up to $z\sim5.5$. The specific SFR remains nearly flat for SFGs and declines with density for QGs at $z\lesssim1.2$. Moreover, mass and environmental quenching efficiencies show that mass-driven processes dominate at $z\gtrsim2.5$, the two processes act with comparable strength between $0.8\lesssim z\lesssim2.5$, and environmental quenching becomes stronger for low-mass galaxies ($M_\star\lesssim10^{10} M_\odot$) at $z\lesssim0.8$. These findings reveal that large-scale structure drives galaxy evolution by enhancing early mass assembly in dense regions and increasingly suppressing star formation in low-mass systems at later times, establishing the environmental role of the cosmic web across cosmic history. COSMOS-Web, the largest JWST survey, provides accurate and deep photometric redshifts, reaching 80% mass completeness at $\log(M_\star/M_\odot)\sim8.7$ at $z\sim7$, enabling the first view of how environments shaped galaxy evolution from the epoch of reionization to the present day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10727v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Hatamnia, Bahram Mobasher, Sina Taamoli, Jeyhan S. Kartaltepe, Caitlin M. Casey, Hollis B. Akins, Malte Brinch, Nima Chartab, Nicole E. Drakos, Andreas L. Faisst, Steven L. Finkelstein, Maximilien Franco, Finn Giddings, Ghassem Gozaliasl, Ali Hadi, Aryana Haghjoo, Santosh Harish, Olivier Ilbert, Pascale L. Jablonka, Shuowen Jin, Ali Ahmad Khostovan, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ronaldo Laishram, Daizhong Liu, Matteo Maturi, Henry Joy McCracken, Crystal L. Martin, Lauro Moscardini, Diana Scognamiglio, Marko Shuntov, Greta Toni, Alexander de la Vega, John R. Weaver, Lilan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REBELS-IFU: Steeply rising star formation histories and the importance of dust obscuration in massive $z \simeq7$ galaxies revealed by multi-wavelength observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10741v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable star formation rate (SFR) measurements are essential for understanding early galaxy evolution, yet derived values rely on several assumptions. To address this problem, we investigate the SFRs of 12 massive ($9~&lt;~\log(M_{\star}/{\rm M}_{\odot})~&lt;~10$) Lyman-break galaxies at $z=6.5-7.7$, drawn from the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA) Reionization Era Bright Emission Line Survey (REBELS) program. The multi-wavelength data, including JWST NIRSpec IFU spectroscopy and ALMA observations, make this a unique sample for investigating SFR tracers at this epoch. We compare SFRs derived from the rest-UV, H$\alpha$, and far-infrared emission, and from spectral energy distribution (SED) fits. We apply robust dust attenuation corrections, which are crucial since between $50-80$ per cent of the star formation is obscured, and find a stellar-to-nebular attenuation ratio of $f=0.50\pm0.08$, consistent with local star-forming galaxies. The majority of the derived total SFRs (medians $25-120$ ${\rm M}_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$) place the REBELS galaxies systematically above $z=7$ literature star-forming main-sequence relations, and our best-fit star formation histories (SFHs) rise more steeply than lower-mass galaxies at the same redshift. We show that these rising SFHs mean commonly used luminosity-to-SFR conversion factors, derived assuming a constant SFH over given timescales, overestimate the SFRs averaged over these timescales for our galaxies. We provide updated luminosity-to-SFR calibrations for $z\simeq7$ galaxies with rising SFHs, showing that commonly assumed rest-UV conversion factors overestimate the $100$ Myr average SFR by a factor of $\simeq3$. Finally, we investigate burstiness indicators in the REBELS-IFU galaxies, finding that the rising SFHs imply that the H$\alpha$-to-UV luminosity ratio is an unreliable probe of bursty star formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10741v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Fisher, R. A. A. Bowler, R. K. Cochrane, L. E. Rowland, M. Stefanon, H. S. B. Algera, M. Aravena, R. Bouwens, E. da Cunha, P. Dayal, A. Ferrara, J. A. Hodge, H. Inami, L. Komarova, R. Smit, L. Sommovigo, D. P. Stark, P. P. van der Werf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REBELS-IFU: Spatially Resolved Ionizing Photon Production Efficiencies of 12 Bright Galaxies in the Epoch of Reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measuring the ionizing photon production efficiency $\xi_{\mathrm{ion,0}}$ -- the ratio of ionizing photon output rate $Q_{\rm H^0}$ to UV continuum luminosity $L_{\rm UV}$ -- in galaxies at $z &gt; 6$ is crucial for constraining their contribution to cosmic reionization. We present integrated and spatially resolved measurements of $\xi_{\mathrm{ion,0}}$ for 12 exceptionally bright ($M_\mathrm{UV} \sim -22$ mag) star-forming galaxies at $z \sim 7$ from the REBELS survey. These measurements are based on JWST NIRSpec/IFU PRISM spectroscopy, probing the rest-frame UV and optical regime. Notably, in 8 of the 12 galaxies, the spectral coverage includes H$\alpha$, enabling self-consistent dust attenuation estimates in both the ionized gas and stellar continuum via the Balmer decrement and rest-UV slope, respectively. We find global $\log\xi_{\mathrm{ion,0}}$ values ranging from $25.19\pm0.11$ to $25.61\pm0.11$, with a weighted mean of $25.44\pm0.15$, consistent with the canonical value of $\sim25.3$. Using a sample of 25 star-forming clumps within these galaxies, we explore local variations in LyC production efficiency, finding a broader range, from $24.52\pm0.21$ to $26.18\pm0.61$. We identify strong correlations between $\xi_{\mathrm{ion,0}}$ and specific star formation rate, star formation surface density, H$\beta$ equivalent width, and stellar mass. Clumps with the highest $\xi_{\mathrm{ion,0}}$ exhibit $\mathrm{EW}_0(\mathrm{H}\beta) \ge 150$ Angstrom, consistent with young stellar ages. From previous Ly$\alpha$ measurements in three galaxies, we estimate a typical Ly$\alpha$ escape fraction of $f_{\rm esc, Ly\alpha} \sim 2\%$, suggesting similar or lower escape fractions for LyC photons. Combining this with our H$\alpha$ measurements, we infer ionized bubble sizes $\sim 1$ pMpc, aligned with expectations from Ly$\alpha$-detected systems and reionization models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10743v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lena Komarova, Mauro Stefanon, Andres Laza-Ramos, Hiddo S. Algera, Manuel Aravena, Rychard J. Bouwens, Rebecca Bowler, Elisabete da Cunha, Pratika Dayal, Andrea Ferrara, Rebecca Fisher, Themiya Nanayakkara, Lucie E. Rowland, Sander Schouws, Renske Smit, Laura Sommovigo, Daniel P. Stark, Paul van der Verf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of supermassive black holes on exoplanet habitability: I. Spanning the natural mass range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While the influence of supermassive black hole (SMBH) activity on habitability has garnered attention, the specific effects of active galactic nuclei (AGN) winds, particularly ultrafast outflows (UFOs), on planetary atmospheres remain largely unexplored. This study aims to fill this gap by investigating the relationship between SMBH mass at the galactic center and exoplanetary habitability, given that SMBH masses are empirically confirmed to span approximately 5 orders of magnitude in galaxies. Through simplified models, we account for various results involving the relationships between the distance from the planet to the central SMBH and the mass of the SMBH. Specifically, we show that increased SMBH mass leads to higher atmospheric heating and elevated temperatures, greater molecular thermal velocities, and enhanced mass loss, all of which diminish with distance from the galactic center. Energy-driven winds consistently have a stronger impact than momentum-driven ones. Crucially, ozone depletion is shown to rise with SMBH mass and decrease with distance from the galactic center, with nearly complete ozone loss ($\sim100\%$) occurring across galactic scales for SMBHs $\geq 10^8 M_\odot$ in the energy-driven case. This study emphasizes that SMBH growth over cosmic time may have produced markedly different impacts on galactic habitability, depending on both the mass of the central black hole (BH) and the location of planetary systems within their host galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10794v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jourdan Waas, Eric S. Perlman, Manasvi Lingam, Emily Lohmann, Jackson Kernan, Francesco Tombesi, Amadeo Balbi, Alessandra Ambrifi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALMAGAL V. Relations between the core populations and the parent clump physical properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. The fragmentation of massive molecular clumps into smaller, potentially star-forming cores plays a key role in the processes of high-mass star formation. The ALMAGAL project offers high-resolution data to investigate these processes across various evolutionary stages in the Galactic plane. Aims. This study aims at correlating the fragmentation properties of massive clumps, obtained from ALMA observations, with their global physical parameters (e.g., mass, surface density, and temperature) and evolutionary indicators (such as luminosity-to-mass ratio and bolometric temperature) obtained from Herschel observations. It seeks to assess whether the cores evolve in number and mass in tandem with their host clumps, and to determine the possible factors influencing the formation of massive cores (M &gt; 24M_\odot). Methods. We analyzed the masses of 6348 fragments, estimated from 1.4 mm continuum data for 1007 ALMAGAL clumps. Leveraging this unprecedentedly large data set, we evaluated statistical relationships between clump parameters, estimated over about 0.1 pc scales, and fragment properties, corresponding to scales of a few 1000 au, while accounting for potential biases related to distance and observational resolution. Our results were further compared with predictions from numerical simulations. Results. The fragmentation level correlates preferentially with clump surface density, supporting a scenario of density-driven fragmentation, whereas it does not show any clear dependence on total clump mass. Both the mass of the most massive core and the core formation efficiency show a broad range and increase on average by an order of magnitude in the intervals spanned by evolutionary indicators such as clump dust temperature and the luminosity-to-mass ratio. This suggests that core growth continues throughout the clump evolution, favoring clump-fed over core-fed theoretical scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10825v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Elia, A. Coletta, S. Molinari, E. Schisano, M. Benedettini, \'A. S\'anchez-Monge, A. Traficante, C. Mininni, A. Nucara, S. Pezzuto, P. Schilke, J. D. Soler, A. Avison, M. T. Beltr\'an, H. Beuther, S. Clarke, G. A. Fuller, R. S. Klessen, R. Kuiper, U. Lebreuilly, D. C. Lis, T. M\"oller, L. Moscadelli, A. J. Rigby, P. Sanhueza, F. van der Tak, Q. Zhang, K. L. J. Rygl, M. Merello, C. D. Battersby, P. T. P. Ho, P. D. Klaassen, P. M. Koch, J. Allande, L. Bronfman, F. Fontani, P. Hennebelle, B. Jones, T. Liu, G. Stroud, M. R. A. Wells, A. Ahmadi, C. L. Brogan, F. De Angelis, T. R. Hunter, K. G. Johnston, C. Y. Law, S. J. Liu, S. -Y. Liu, Y. Maruccia, V. -M. Pelkonen, Y. -N. Su, Y. Tang, L. Testi, S. Walch, T. Zhang, H. Zinnecker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spatial Evolution of Star Clusters in NGC 628 with JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11115v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the spatial distribution of star clusters in NGC 628 using the statistical tool INDICATE to quantify clustering tendencies. Our sample, based on HST and JWST observations, is the most complete to date, spanning ages from 1 Myr to &gt;100 Myr. We find cluster spatial behaviour varies with galactic position, age, and mass. Most emerging young clusters are tightly spatially associated with each other, while fully emerged clusters are in \sim1.5 times looser spatial associations, irrespective of age. Young Massive Clusters (YMCs \ge 10^4 M_{\odot}) tend to associate with lower-mass clusters but not strongly with other YMCs, implying that intense star formation regions produce a few YMCs alongside many lower-mass clusters rather than multiple YMCs together. Young concentrated clusters show a wide radial distribution in the galactic disk, which narrows with age; with concentrated clusters &gt;100 Myr mostly residing between 2-6 kpc. This pattern may reflect either faster dispersal of isolated tight cluster spatial "structure" in a lower gas density outer disk or gradual inside-out growth, with the formation of this structure shifting outward over time. We also detect distinct spatial behaviours for clusters within 2 kpc, linked to the inner Lindblad resonance (\le1 kpc), nuclear ring (\sim0.5-1 kpc), and the start of spiral arms (\sim1.25-2 kpc), suggesting these regions exhibit strong radial motions that could hinder clusters from forming and remaining in tight concentrations. Our results highlight how spatially-resolved studies of clusters can reveal the influence of galactic dynamics on star formation and cluster evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11115v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne S. M. Buckner, Ana Duarte-Cabral, Angela Adamo, Sean Linden, Michele Cignoni, Varun Bajaj, Arjan Bik, Giacomo Bortolini, Daniela Calzetti, Matteo Correnti, Bruce G. Elmegreen, Debra M. Elmegreen, Helena Faustino Vieira, John S. Gallagher III, Kathryn Grasha, Benjamin Gregg, Rob A. Gutermuth, Kelsey Johnson, Mark Krumholz Drew Lapeer, Matteo M. Messa, G\"oran \"Ostlin, Alex Pedrini, Jenna E. Ryon, Linda J. Smith, Monica Tosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiation magnetohydrodynamics simulations of Population III star formation during the Epoch of Reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmological simulations find that pockets of star-forming gas could remain pristine up until the Epoch of Reionization (EoR) due to the inhomogeneous nature of metal mixing and enrichment in the early Universe. Such pristine clouds could have formed Population III stars, which could have distinct properties compared to their very high redshift ($z \geq 20$) counterparts. We investigate how Population III stars form and grow during the EoR, and whether the resulting mass distribution varies with environment or across cosmic time. We perform high-resolution ($7.5\,\rm{au}$) radiation-magnetohydrodynamics simulations of identical primordial clouds exposed to the CMB appropriate for $z=30$ and $z=6$, respectively, as part of the POPSICLE project. We also run a simulation at $z=6$ with a strong external Lyman-Werner (LW) background, to span across radiative environments which could host metal-free clumps during the EoR. In the limit of no external LW radiation, we find that while the evolution of the most massive star ($M_{\star} \approx 70\,\rm{M_{\odot}}$) is almost identical between $z=30$ and $z=6$, the latter exhibits less fragmentation, leading to a smaller cluster of stars with a higher median stellar mass. In the limit of high external LW radiation, we see vigorous accretion and high star formation efficiencies, leading to the formation of very massive ($M_{\star} &gt; 100\,\rm{M_{\odot}}$) stars. Our results suggest that Population III IMF could vary with redshift simply due to the CMB, independent of the environment. We find that less massive and more compact Pop III star clusters could form during the EoR as compared to $z \geq 20$, with the formation of very massive and supermassive stars likely in strongly irradiated environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11314v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lisanne van Veenen, Piyush Sharda, Serena Viti, Shyam H. Menon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planetary nebulae as tracers of stellar population properties: a pilot study with MUSE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Planetary nebulae (PNe) are the only single stars in galaxies outside the Local Group that can be used as kinematic tracers of the diffuse light in the extended halo. Analysing their luminosity-specific number density across galaxies of different morphologies has also shown hints that they may be used as tracers of the age and metallicity of stellar populations. A proper understanding of this relation has been hindered by the fact that simultaneously detecting PNe and accurately measuring stellar properties is extremely difficult using classical narrow-band imaging methods, which cannot detect PNe in the bright centres of galaxies. In this work, we use integral-field spectroscopy to overcome this challenge, analysing the inner regions of a sample of ten early-type galaxies from the Extended Planetary Nebulae Survey (ePN.S) for which archival MUSE data was available. With the Diffuse Emission-Line Filter (DELF) technique, we automate the detection of PNe, and perform spectral fitting on the diffuse light to infer kinematics and stellar population parameters. We compare the PN number density profile and its associated alpha-parameter with multiple properties of the host galaxies. We find that our sample follows the previously observationally constrained correlation with the metallicity of the host galaxy. We find a weak anti-correlation between the alpha-parameter and the FUV excess, highlighting the possible relation between the visibility lifetime of PNe on the spectral energy distribution of their host galaxies, with fewer PNe detected in association with stellar populations characterized by a UV excess.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11479v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana In\'es Ennis, Johanna Hartke, Fuyan Bian, Claudia Pulsoni, Chiara Spiniello, Magda Arnaboldi, Roberto de Propris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking at infrared background radiation anisotropies with Spitzer II. Small scale anisotropies and their implications for new and upcoming space surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spitzer-based cosmic infrared background (CIB) fluctuations at arcminute-to-degree scales indicate the presence of new populations, whereas sub-arcminute power arises from known $z\lesssim 6$ galaxies. We reconstruct the evolution of the near-IR CIB anisotropies on sub-arcminute scales by known galaxy populations. This method is based on, and significantly advanced over, the empirical reconstruction by \cite{Helgason2012} which is combined with the halo model connecting galaxies to their host dark matter (DM) halos. The modeled CIB fluctuations from known galaxies produce the majority of the observed small-scale signal down to statistical uncertainties of $&lt; 10\%$ and we constrain the evolution of the halo mass regime hosting such galaxies. Thus the large-scale CIB fluctuations from new populations are produced by sources with negligible small-scale power. This appears to conflict with the presented Intra-halo light (IHL) models, but is accounted for if the new sources are at high $z$. Our analysis spanning several Spitzer datasets allows us to narrow the estimated contributions of remaining known galaxies to the CIB anisotropies to be probed potentially from surveys by new and upcoming space missions such as Euclid, SPHEREx, and Roman. Of these, the Roman surveys have the best prospects for measuring the source-subtracted CIB and probing the nature of the underlying new populations at $\lambda &lt;2\ \mu$m, followed by Euclid's surveys, while for SPHEREx the source-subtracted CIB signal from them appears significantly overwhelmed by the CIB from remaining known galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11501v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan J. Kaminsky, Alexander Kashlinsky, Richard G. Arendt, Nico Cappelluti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The signature of major mergers on the hydrostatic mass bias of galaxy clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While galaxy cluster masses are fundamental cosmological observables, estimates based on intra-cluster medium observations rely on hydrostatic equilibrium, introducing a systematic bias. We investigate how mergers drive the time evolution of this hydrostatic mass bias, identifying the dominant physical mechanisms and their dependence on dynamical state and merger history. Using a high-resolution AMR Eulerian+$N$-body cosmological simulation, we analyse a sample of cluster mergers within $1.5 \leq z \leq 0$, comparing true and hydrostatic masses derived from gas density and temperature profiles, and tracing their evolution. At $z=0$, the hydrostatic mass bias shows a mild correlation with dynamical state. During major mergers, the bias follows a characteristic trend: a sharp negative dip around the merger time, a transient positive peak, and a gradual return to pre-merger levels. This behaviour is primarily driven by morphological and dynamical reconfigurations of the gas density within the ICM, while thermodynamical processes play a secondary role. The pattern shows no strong dependence on secondary parameters, such as mass ratio or impact parameter, but it can be fitted to a simple time-dependent functional form. This trend is present at radii $r\le R_{\mathrm{vir}}$, although with reduced amplitude and shorter timescales as the radius decreases. Hydrostatic mass bias is closely linked, albeit in a non-trivial way, with the merging history of galaxy clusters. We find that the bias values are weakly correlated with the dynamical state of clusters. Nevertheless, our results give a robust estimation of the hydrostatic mass bias values in the pre-merger, merging, and post-merger phases. These findings highlight the importance of delving deeper into the observational assessment of cluster assembly state in order to improve mass estimations for cosmological analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10730v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isac Barranco-Llorca, David Vall\'es-P\'erez, Susana Planelles, Vicent Quilis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quiescent Merging Nature of the Coma Cluster Revealed by ICM Velocity Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The hot gas permeating galaxy clusters-the intracluster medium (ICM)-is a key tracer of their assembly history and internal dynamics. Understanding the motion of this gas provides critical insight into processes such as mergers, turbulence, and energy dissipation in the largest gravitationally bound structures in the Universe. The Coma cluster is a nearby, massive system long suspected to be dynamically disturbed. Previous high-resolution X-ray spectroscopy with the XRISM mission revealed bulk motions in the cluster core and southern regions. Here we present new XRISM Resolve observations of a northern region in Coma, which reveal a coherent velocity gradient of nearly $530 km/s across the cluster from south to north. We find that the hot gas in this northern region exhibits modest line-of-sight motions and uniform thermodynamic properties, indicating relatively mild local disturbances. The consistent levels of turbulence throughout the cluster suggest that the energy from a past merger has been distributed on large scales. These findings provide compelling evidence for an off-axis merger event and demonstrate how high-resolution X-ray spectroscopy can uncover subtle dynamical signatures in the ICM, offering important constraints for simulations of cluster evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10740v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Gatuzz, J. Sanders, A. Liu, A. Fabian, C. Pinto, D. Eckert, S. Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dawes Review 13: A New Look at The Dynamic Radio Sky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10785v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astronomical objects that change rapidly give us insight into extreme environments, allowing us to identify new phenomena, test fundamental physics, and probe the Universe on all scales. Transient and variable radio sources range from the cosmological, such as gamma-ray bursts, to much more local events, such as massive flares from stars in our Galactic neighbourhood. The capability to observe the sky repeatedly, over many frequencies and timescales, has allowed us to explore and understand dynamic phenomena in a way that has not been previously possible. In the past decade, there have been great strides forward as we prepared for the revolution in time domain radio astronomy that is being enabled by the SKA Observatory telescopes, the SKAO pathfinders and precursors, and other `next generation' radio telescopes. Hence it is timely to review the current status of the field, and summarise the developments that have happened to get to our current point. This review focuses on image domain (or `slow') transients, on timescales of seconds to years. We discuss the physical mechanisms that cause radio variability, and the classes of radio transients that result. We then outline what an ideal image domain radio transients survey would look like, and summarise the history of the field, from targeted observations to surveys with existing radio telescopes. We discuss methods and approaches for transient discovery and classification, and identify some of the challenges in scaling up current methods for future telescopes. Finally, we present our current understanding of the dynamic radio sky, in terms of source populations and transient rates, and look at what we can expect from surveys on future radio telescopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10785v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tara Murphy, David L. Kaplan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mock Observations for the CSST Mission: Main Surveys -- the Mock Catalogue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Chinese Space Station Survey Telescope (CSST) is a flagship space mission, designed to carry out a large-area sky survey to explore the nature of dark matter and dark energy in the Universe. The onboard multi-band imaging and slitless spectroscopic modules will enable us to obtain photometric data for billions of galaxies and stars, as well as hundreds of millions of spectroscopic measurements, advancing various scientific analyses such as galaxy clustering and weak gravitational lensing. To support the image simulations for the main survey of the CSST mission, we present a mock catalogue of stars and galaxies. For stars, the mock catalogue is generated using either Galaxia or TRILEGAL, both of which provide a range of stellar properties to meet the requirements of CSST image simulations. For galaxies, we built a mock light-cone up to redshift z~3.5 from the cosmological Nbody simulation and populated the mock galaxy catalogue from the dark mater haloes using a semi-analytical galaxy formation model. We then performed a full-sky ray-tracing simulation of weak gravitational lensing to obtain lensing shear at the position of each galaxy in the light-cone. To support both multi-band imaging and slitless spectroscopic simulations, we computed the spectral energy distribution (SED) for each galaxy based on its star formation history using a supervised deep-learning model and determined the magnitudes in each band using the CSST throughputs. Finally, the properties of our mock galaxies include positions, redshifts, stellar masses, shapes, sizes, SEDs, lensing shears and magnifications. We have validated our mock catalogue against observational data and theoretical models, with results showing good overall agreement. The catalogue provides a flexible dataset for the development of CSST image processing and can support a wide range of cosmological analyses within the CSST mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10805v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Liang Wei, Yu Luo, Hao Tian, Ming Li, Yi-Sheng Qiu, Guo-Liang Li, Yue-Dong Fang, Xin Zhang, De-Zi Liu, Nan Li, Ran Li, Huan-Yuan Shan, Lin Nie, Zizhao He, Lei Wang, Xi Kang, Dongwei Fan, Yang Chen, Xiaoting Fu, Chao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the Chemical Complexity and C/O Ratio of the HD 163296 Protoplanetary Disk: Constraints from Multi-line ALMA Observations of Organics, Nitriles, Sulfur-bearing, and Deuterated Molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The physical and chemical conditions within a protoplanetary disk play a crucial role in determining its chemical composition, which is subsequently inherited by any forming planets. To probe these conditions, high-resolution molecular line observations, coupled with modelling, are essential. In this study, we investigate the chemistry of the nearby, massive, and relatively line-rich protoplanetary disk around HD 163296 using high-resolution observations from ALMA across Bands 3, 4, 6, and 7. We constrain the disk-averaged and radial distributions of column density and excitation temperature for the detected molecules using the new retrieval code DRive. The disk chemistry is modelled using the astrochemical code PEGASIS, with variations in the initial elemental C/O ratio. Our modelling, informed by molecular observations of HCO+, DCO+, HCN, DCN, CS, HC3N, H2CO, CH3OH, HNCO, and NH2CHO, allows us to place strong constraints on the C/O ratio, with a best-fit value of 1.1 that is broadly consistent with previous estimates. We present the highest-resolution DCO+ emission map of this disk to date, revealing triple-ringed chemical substructures that closely align with the dust continuum rings. Additionally, our results provide the first and most stringent upper limits on the column densities of NH2CHO and HNCO in this protoplanetary disk, measured at &lt; 7e11 cm-2 and &lt; 1e11 cm-2, respectively. Our chemical models suggest that NH2CHO and HNCO predominantly form on grain surfaces within the disk. However, physico-chemical desorption mechanisms are inefficient at releasing these species into detectable gas-phase abundances, yet they remain promising targets for future ALMA observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10882v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parashmoni Kashyap, Liton Majumdar, Edwin A. Bergin, Geoffrey A. Blake, Karen Willacy, St\'ephane Guilloteau, Anne Dutrey, Sheng-Yuan Liu, Thomas Henning, Paul F. Goldsmith, Dariusz C. Lis, S. Maitrey, Neal Turner, Raghvendra Sahai, Chin-Fei Lee, Masao Saito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRIMA General Observer Science Book Volume 2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This PRobe far-Infrared Mission for Astrophysics (PRIMA) mission concept is a proposed mission to NASA's Astrophysics Probe Explorer (APEX) call. The concept features a cryogenically cooled 1.8 m diameter telescope, and is designed to carry two science instruments covering the 24 to 264 $\mu$m wavelength range: an imaging polarimeter (PRIMAger) and a spectrometer (FIRESS). The majority of PRIMA's time (75%) will be open to observations proposed by the community (General Observer science / GO), and all of data will be publicly available for archival research (Guest Investigator science / GI). Following up on the successful community engagement created by the first volume of the GO PRIMA Science Book (arXiv:2310.20572), Volume 2 gathers 120 new and updated contributed science cases which could be performed within the context of the PRIMA GO/GI program. This volume reflects the strong development of the community interest, awareness and involvement in PRIMA, and further develops how PRIMA's unprecedented capabilities can be leveraged for an impactful and innovative GO/GI program covering most areas of astrophysics and over 90% of the scientific questions and discovery areas in the Astro2020 decadal survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10927v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Moullet (NRAO), D. Burgarella (Laboratoire d'Astrophysique de Marseille), T. Kataria (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology), H. Beuther (Max Planck Institute for Astronomy), C. Battersby (University of Connecticut), M. Cheng (UC Irvine), T. Essinger-Hileman (NASA Goddard Space Flight Center), H. Inami (Hiroshima University), E. Mills (University of Kansas), T. Nagao (Ehime University), S. Unwin (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of an X-ray bridge between the comma-shaped gas and the main cluster in MCXC J0157.4-0550</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of a faint X-ray bridge connecting between the comma-shaped gas and the main cluster in MCXC J0157.4-0550, using {\it XMM-Newton} image. The filamentary structure is found in a model-independent manner in both topological features and Gaussian Gradient Magnitude filtering. The X-ray surface brightness profile perpendicular to the filament is detected at a $5.5\sigma$ level. Weak-lensing (WL) analysis using the Subaru/HSC-SSP Survey archive data strongly supports the two mass components. Given a prior from the stellar masses, we obtain $M_{200}^{\rm main}=2.68_{-0.92}^{+1.11}\times 10^{14}\,h_{70}^{-1}M_\odot$ and $M_{200}^{\rm sub}=0.46_{-0.22}^{+0.38}\times 10^{14}\,h_{70}^{-1}M_\odot$. The main axis of the projected halo distribution is more likely to align with the direction of the main cluster than to be oriented perpendicularly. Similar X-ray distributions have been identified in the literature on numerical simulations. The filamentary structure forms in the following manner: as the gas is stripped by ram pressure near the pericenter, it gets dragged by tidal rotation. Once free from this rotation, the gas moves inertially in a direction parallel to the tangential velocity at the pericenter. The comma-shaped gas, with tails pointing in the opposite direction to the main cluster, is also formed by the current tidal rotation as it moves away from the main cluster. This warrants us that, although it is sometimes thought based on the X-ray morphology alone that the tail is pointing in the opposite direction to the merger motion, this is not necessarily the case. The information of the X-ray filamentary remnant from the cluster merger, together with the 2D WL shear data, provides constraints on the merger parameters, indicating an infalling velocity of approximately $1000\, {\rm km\, s^{-1}}$ and an impact parameter of $0.9$ Mpc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10968v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Yang, Nobuhiro Okabe, Yasushi Fukazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shadow-Induced Warps in Protoplanetary disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11358v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Shadows are commonly observed in protoplanetary disks in near-infrared and (sub)millimeter images, often cast by misaligned inner disks or other obscuring material. While recent studies show that shadows can alter disk dynamics, only the case symmetric across the midplane (e.g., from a polar-aligned inner disk) has been studied. Here we study shadows cast by an inner disk with a $30^\circ$ mutual inclination using 3D radiation-hydrodynamical simulations. Given the same shadow shape and amplitude, the $30^\circ$ inclined shadow leads to a much stronger accretion compared with the polar case, reaching $\alpha \sim$ 1, because the disk is squeezed twice in one azimuth, leading to shocks and strong radial flows near the midplane. The outer disk develops a warp: the inner disk region tilts toward alignment with the shadow, while the outer, exponentially tapered disk tilts and twists in a different direction, inclined $\sim$ 32$^\circ$ relative to the inner region. Locally isothermal simulations with a prescribed temperature structure reproduce the effect, confirming that it is thermally driven. Fourier-Hermite analysis shows that it is the m=1, n=1 temperature perturbation that drives the warp by launching bending waves, with the tilting response of the disk approximately proportional to the modal amplitude. This mode always exists unless the shadow is coplanar or polar. Given a fixed temperature contrast, the m=1,n=1 mode peaks at $\sim$15$^\circ$ mutual inclination, but still contributes substantially across 3$^\circ$ to 30$^\circ$. Shadows cause disk warps--they are not only a consequence of them. We discuss testable predictions for current and future ALMA and NIR observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11358v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shangjia Zhang, Zhaohuan Zhu, Callum W. Fairbairn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star clusters in the gamma-ray sky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive Star Clusters (SCs) have been proposed as additional contributors to Galactic Cosmic rays (CRs), to overcome the limitations of supernova remnants (SNRs) to reach the highest energy end of the CR spectrum. Thanks to fast mass losses due to the collective stellar winds, the environment around SCs is potentially suitable for particle acceleration up to PeV energies, and their energetics is enough to account for a non-negligible fraction of the Galactic CRs. Anyhow, the theoretical expectations need to be corroborated by clear observations. Despite the increasing number of detections at different energies, the contamination of other sources often makes it difficult to constrain the contribution arising from stellar winds only, unless one selects objects younger than a few million years, namely before stars start to explode inside clusters. I will review the results obtained with gamma-ray data towards a few massive young star clusters and discuss what implications these result have, especially concerning their contribution to the bulk of Galactic CRs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11432v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(ICRC2025)1390</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giada Peron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survival of higher overdensity cold gas in a turbulent, multiphase medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20962v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cold gas clouds embedded in a hot, turbulent medium are expected to be short-lived due to disruptive hydrodynamic instabilities. However, radiative cooling might allow such clouds to survive and grow. We present 3D \texttt{Athena++} simulations of clouds with a density contrast of $\chi = 1000$, exploring turbulent Mach numbers $\mathcal{M}\in (0.25, 0.75)$ and cloud radii chosen to span cooling-to-crushing ratios $\alpha \in [0.001, 10]$. We find a shift in the survival boundary, with cloud survival occurring only when the cooling-to-cloud-crushing ratio ($t_{\text{cool,mix}} / t_{\text{cc}}$) $\lesssim 0.01$, which is lower than the expected boundary of $\sim 1$. This result shows that it is more difficult for higher over-density cold clouds to survive in a turbulent, hot medium, and suggests another `survival criterion'.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20962v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin Vergis George, Hitesh Kishore Das, Max Gronke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid preparation LXXIX. Using mock low surface brightness dwarf galaxies to probe Euclid Wide Survey detection capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13163v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Local Universe dwarf galaxies can serve as both cosmological and mass assembly probes. Deep surveys have enabled the study of these objects down to the low surface brightness (LSB) regime. In this paper, we estimate Euclid's dwarf detection capabilities as well as limits of its MERge processing function (MER pipeline), which is responsible for producing the stacked mosaics and final catalogues. To do this, we injected mock dwarf galaxies in a real Euclid Wide Survey (EWS) field in the VIS band and compared the input catalogue to the final MER catalogue. The mock dwarf galaxies were generated using simple Sersic models with structural parameters (including size and surface brightness) drawn from observed dwarf galaxy catalogues. These simulations represent an idealised case in the sense they do not account for additional factors such as ellipticity, morphology, or crowding. To characterise the detected dwarfs, we used the mean surface brightness inside the effective radius SB_e (in mag arcsec^-2). The final MER catalogues achieve completenesses of 91% for SB_e in [21,24] and 54% for SB_e in [24,28]. These numbers do not take into account possible contaminants, including confusion with background galaxies at the location of the dwarfs. After taking those effects into account, they respectively became 86% and 38%. The MER pipeline performs a final local background subtraction with a small mesh size, leading to a flux loss for galaxies with R_e &gt; 10 arcsec. By using the final MER mosaics and reinjecting this local background, we obtained an image in which we recover reliable photometric properties for objects under the arcminute scale. This background-reinjected product is thus suitable for the study of Local Universe dwarf galaxies. Euclid's data reduction pipeline serves as a test bed for other deep surveys, particularly regarding background subtraction methods, a key issue in LSB science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13163v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Euclid Collaboration, M. Urbano (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), P. -A. Duc (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), M. Poulain (Space physics and astronomy research unit, University of Oulu, Pentti Kaiteran katu 1, FI-90014 Oulu, Finland), A. A. Nucita (Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, University of Salento, Via per Arnesano, CP-I93, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Lecce, Via per Arnesano, CP-193, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INAF-Sezione di Lecce, c/o Dipartimento Matematica e Fisica, Via per Arnesano, 73100, Lecce, Italy), A. Venhola (Space physics and astronomy research unit, University of Oulu, Pentti Kaiteran katu 1, FI-90014 Oulu, Finland), O. Marchal (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), M. K\"ummel (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), H. Kong (Institut de F\'isica d'Altes Energies), F. Soldano (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), E. Romelli (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), M. Walmsley (David A. Dunlap Department of Astronomy \&amp; Astrophysics, University of Toronto, 50 St George Street, Toronto, Ontario M5S 3H4, Canada, Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Oxford Road, Manchester M13 9PL, UK), T. Saifollahi (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), K. Voggel (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), A. Lan\c{c}on (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), F. R. Marleau (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), E. Sola (Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, UK), L. K. Hunt (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Arcetri, Largo E. Fermi 5, 50125, Firenze, Italy), J. Junais (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), D. Carollo (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), P. M. Sanchez-Alarcon (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), M. Baes (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Universiteit Gent, Krijgslaan 281 S9, 9000 Gent, Belgium), F. Buitrago (Departamento de F\'isica Te\'orica, At\'omica y \'Optica, Universidad de Valladolid, 47011 Valladolid, Spain, Laboratory for Disruptive Interdisciplinary Science, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Tapada da Ajuda, 1349-018 Lisboa, Portugal), Michele Cantiello (INAF - Osservatorio Astronomico d'Abruzzo, Via Maggini, 64100, Teramo, Italy), J. -C. Cuillandre (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), H. Dom\'inguez S\'anchez (Instituto de F\'isica de Cantabria, Edificio Juan Jord\'a, Avenida de los Castros, 39005 Santander, Spain), A. Ferr\'e-Mateu (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), A. Franco (INFN, Sezione di Lecce, Via per Arnesano, CP-193, 73100, Lecce, Italy, Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, University of Salento, Via per Arnesano, CP-I93, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INAF-Sezione di Lecce, c/o Dipartimento Matematica e Fisica, Via per Arnesano, 73100, Lecce, Italy), J. Gracia-Carpio (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), R. Habas (INAF - Osservatorio Astronomico d'Abruzzo, Via Maggini, 64100, Teramo, Italy), M. Hilker (European Southern Observatory, Karl-Schwarzschild-Str. 2, 85748 Garching, Germany), E. Iodice (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), J. H. Knapen (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), M. N. Le (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), D. Mart\'inez-Delgado (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Andaluc\'ia, CSIC, Glorieta de la Astronom\'i a, 18080, Granada, Spain), O. M\"uller (Institute of Physics, Laboratory of Astrophysics, Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne, Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, UK, Visiting Fellow, Clare Hall, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK), F. De Paolis (Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, University of Salento, Via per Arnesano, CP-I93, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Lecce, Via per Arnesano, CP-193, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INAF-Sezione di Lecce, c/o Dipartimento Matematica e Fisica, Via per Arnesano, 73100, Lecce, Italy), P. Papaderos (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Universidade do Porto, CAUP, Rua das Estrelas, PT4150-762 Porto, Portugal), R. Ragusa (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), J. Rom\'an (Departamento de F\'isica de la Tierra y Astrof\'isica, Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Plaza de las Ciencias 2, E-28040 Madrid, Spain), E. Saremi (School of Physics \&amp; Astronomy, University of Southampton, Highfield Campus, Southampton SO17 1BJ, UK), V. Testa (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), B. Altieri (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), L. Amendola (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik, University of Heidelberg, Philosophenweg 16, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany), S. Andreon (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), N. Auricchio (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), C. Baccigalupi (IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy), M. Baldi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Via Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), S. Bardelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), P. Battaglia (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), A. Biviano (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy), E. Branchini (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), M. Brescia (Department of Physics "E. Pancini", University Federico II, Via Cinthia 6, 80126, Napoli, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), S. Camera (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a degli Studi di Torino, Via P. Giuria 1, 10125 Torino, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Torino, Via P. Giuria 1, 10125 Torino, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), G. Ca\~nas-Herrera (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands, Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands), V. Capobianco (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), C. Carbone (INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy), J. Carretero (Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), S. Casas (Institute for Theoretical Particle Physics and Cosmology), M. Castellano (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), G. Castignani (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Cavuoti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy, INFN section of Naples, Via Cinthia 6, 80126, Napoli, Italy), A. Cimatti (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), C. Colodro-Conde (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), G. Congedo (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), C. J. Conselice (Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Oxford Road, Manchester M13 9PL, UK), L. Conversi (European Space Agency/ESRIN, Largo Galileo Galilei 1, 00044 Frascati, Roma, Italy, ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), Y. Copin (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), F. Courbin (Institut de Ci\`encies del Cosmos, Instituci\'o Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avan\c{c}ats), H. M. Courtois (UCB Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IUF, IP2I Lyon, 4 rue Enrico Fermi, 69622 Villeurbanne, France), M. Cropper (Mullard Space Science Laboratory, University College London, Holmbury St Mary, Dorking, Surrey RH5 6NT, UK), A. Da Silva (Departamento de F\'isica, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Edif\'icio C8, Campo Grande, PT1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Campo Grande, 1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal), H. Degaudenzi (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), G. De Lucia (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), H. Dole (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CNRS, Institut d'astrophysique spatiale, 91405, Orsay, France), F. Dubath (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), C. A. J. Duncan (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), X. Dupac (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), S. Dusini (INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), S. Escoffier (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), M. Farina (INAF-Istituto di Astrofisica e Planetologia Spaziali, via del Fosso del Cavaliere, 100, 00100 Roma, Italy), R. Farinelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Ferriol (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), F. Finelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), M. Frailis (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), E. Franceschi (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Fumana (INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy), S. Galeotta (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), K. George (University Observatory, LMU Faculty of Physics, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 Munich, Germany), B. Gillis (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), C. Giocoli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), A. Grazian (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy), F. Grupp (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany, Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), L. Guzzo (Dipartimento di Fisica "Aldo Pontremoli", Universit\`a degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy), S. V. H. Haugan (Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1029 Blindern, 0315 Oslo, Norway), W. Holmes (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), I. M. Hook (Department of Physics, Lancaster University, Lancaster, LA1 4YB, UK), F. Hormuth (Felix Hormuth Engineering, Goethestr. 17, 69181 Leimen, Germany), A. Hornstrup (Technical University of Denmark, Elektrovej 327, 2800 Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark, Cosmic Dawn Center), K. Jahnke (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), M. Jhabvala (NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD 20771, USA), B. Joachimi (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, UK), E. Keih\"anen (Department of Physics and Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), S. Kermiche (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), A. Kiessling (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), B. Kubik (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), M. Kunz (Universit\'e de Gen\`eve, D\'epartement de Physique Th\'eorique and Centre for Astroparticle Physics, 24 quai Ernest-Ansermet, CH-1211 Gen\`eve 4, Switzerland), H. Kurki-Suonio (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), R. Laureijs (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), A. M. C. Le Brun (Laboratoire d'etude de l'Univers et des phenomenes eXtremes, Observatoire de Paris, Universit\'e PSL, Sorbonne Universit\'e, CNRS, 92190 Meudon, France), S. Ligori (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), P. B. Lilje (Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1029 Blindern, 0315 Oslo, Norway), V. Lindholm (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), I. Lloro (SKAO, Jodrell Bank, Lower Withington, Macclesfield SK11 9FT, United Kingdom), G. Mainetti (Centre de Calcul de l'IN2P3/CNRS, 21 avenue Pierre de Coubertin 69627 Villeurbanne Cedex, France), D. Maino (Dipartimento di Fisica "Aldo Pontremoli", Universit\`a degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy, INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy), E. Maiorano (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), O. Mansutti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), O. Marggraf (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), M. Martinelli (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro, 2 - c/o Dipartimento di Fisica, Edificio G. Marconi, 00185 Roma, Italy), N. Martinet (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France), F. Marulli (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), R. J. Massey (Department of Physics, Institute for Computational Cosmology, Durham University, South Road, Durham, DH1 3LE, UK), E. Medinaceli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Mei (Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CNRS, Astroparticule et Cosmologie, 75013 Paris, France, CNRS-UCB International Research Laboratory, Centre Pierre Bin\'etruy, IRL2007, CPB-IN2P3, Berkeley, USA), Y. Mellier (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, 98bis Boulevard Arago, 75014, Paris, France, Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), M. Meneghetti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), E. Merlin (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), G. Meylan (Institute of Physics, Laboratory of Astrophysics, Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), A. Mora (Telespazio UK S.L. for European Space Agency), M. Moresco (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), L. Moscardini (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), R. Nakajima (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), C. Neissner (Institut de F\'isica d'Altes Energies, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), S. -M. Niemi (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands), C. Padilla (Institut de F\'isica d'Altes Energies), S. Paltani (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), F. Pasian (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), K. Pedersen (DARK, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 155, 2200 Copenhagen, Denmark), V. Pettorino (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands), S. Pires (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), G. Polenta (Space Science Data Center, Italian Space Agency, via del Politecnico snc, 00133 Roma, Italy), M. Poncet (Centre National d'Etudes Spatiales -- Centre spatial de Toulouse, 18 avenue Edouard Belin, 31401 Toulouse Cedex 9, France), L. A. Popa (Institute of Space Science, Str. Atomistilor, nr. 409 M\u{a}gurele, Ilfov, 077125, Romania), L. Pozzetti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), F. Raison (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), R. Rebolo (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cientificas, Calle Serrano 117, 28006 Madrid, Spain, Universidad de La Laguna, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, 38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), A. Renzi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), J. Rhodes (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), G. Riccio (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), M. Roncarelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), R. Saglia (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), Z. Sakr (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik, University of Heidelberg, Philosophenweg 16, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany, Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie, Universit\'e St Joseph, Faculty of Sciences, Beirut, Lebanon), D. Sapone (Departamento de F\'isica, FCFM, Universidad de Chile, Blanco Encalada 2008, Santiago, Chile), B. Sartoris (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), P. Schneider (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), T. Schrabback (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), A. Secroun (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), G. Seidel (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), S. Serrano (Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Satlantis, University Science Park, Sede Bld 48940, Leioa-Bilbao, Spain, Institute of Space Sciences), P. Simon (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), C. Sirignano (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), G. Sirri (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), L. Stanco (INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), J. -L. Starck (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), J. Steinwagner (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), P. Tallada-Cresp\'i (Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), A. N. Taylor (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), H. I. Teplitz (Infrared Processing and Analysis Center, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), I. Tereno (Departamento de F\'isica, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Edif\'icio C8, Campo Grande, PT1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Tapada da Ajuda, 1349-018 Lisboa, Portugal), N. Tessore (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, UK), S. Toft (Cosmic Dawn Center, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 128, 2200 Copenhagen, Denmark), R. Toledo-Moreo (Universidad Polit\'ecnica de Cartagena, Departamento de Electr\'onica y Tecnolog\'ia de Computadoras, Plaza del Hospital 1, 30202 Cartagena, Spain), F. Torradeflot (Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra, Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas), I. Tutusaus (Institute of Space Sciences, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie), L. Valenziano (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), J. Valiviita (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), T. Vassallo (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, University Observatory, LMU Faculty of Physics, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 Munich, Germany), G. Verdoes Kleijn (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), A. Veropalumbo (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), Y. Wang (Infrared Processing and Analysis Center, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), J. Weller (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), G. Zamorani (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), I. A. Zinchenko (Astronomisches Rechen-Institut, Zentrum f\"ur Astronomie der Universit\"at Heidelberg, M\"onchhofstr. 12-14, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany), E. Zucca (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Ballardini (Dipartimento di Fisica e Scienze della Terra, Universit\`a degli Studi di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy, Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, Sezione di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Bolzonella (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), E. Bozzo (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), C. Burigana (INAF, Istituto di Radioastronomia, Via Piero Gobetti 101, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), R. Cabanac (Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie), A. Cappi (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, Universit\'e C\^ote d'Azur, Observatoire de la C\^ote d'Azur, CNRS, Laboratoire Lagrange, Bd de l'Observatoire, CS 34229, 06304 Nice cedex 4, France), D. Di Ferdinando (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), J. A. Escartin Vigo (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), L. Gabarra (Department of Physics, Oxford University, Keble Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, UK), M. Huertas-Company (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, Universit\'e PSL, Observatoire de Paris, Sorbonne Universit\'e, CNRS, LERMA, 75014, Paris, France, Universit\'e Paris-Cit\'e, 5 Rue Thomas Mann, 75013, Paris, France), J. Mart\'in-Fleitas (Aurora Technology for European Space Agency), S. Matthew (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), N. Mauri (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), R. B. Metcalf (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), A. Pezzotta (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), M. P\"ontinen (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), C. Porciani (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), I. Risso (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), V. Scottez (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, 98bis Boulevard Arago, 75014, Paris, France, ICL, Junia, Universit\'e Catholique de Lille, LITL, 59000 Lille, France), M. Sereno (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), M. Tenti (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), M. Viel (IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy), M. Wiesmann (Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1029 Blindern, 0315 Oslo, Norway), Y. Akrami (Instituto de F\'isica Te\'orica UAM-CSIC, Campus de Cantoblanco, 28049 Madrid, Spain, CERCA/ISO, Department of Physics, Case Western Reserve University, 10900 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44106, USA), I. T. Andika (Technical University of Munich, TUM School of Natural Sciences, Physics Department, James-Franck-Str. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany, Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astrophysik, Karl-Schwarzschild-Str. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), S. Anselmi (INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, Laboratoire Univers et Th\'eorie, Observatoire de Paris, Universit\'e PSL, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CNRS, 92190 Meudon, France), M. Archidiacono (Dipartimento di Fisica "Aldo Pontremoli", Universit\`a degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy), F. Atrio-Barandela (Departamento de F\'isica Fundamental. Universidad de Salamanca. Plaza de la Merced s/n. 37008 Salamanca, Spain), D. Bertacca (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), M. Bethermin (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), A. Blanchard (Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie), L. Blot (Center for Data-Driven Discovery, Kavli IPMU, Laboratoire d'etude de l'Univers et des phenomenes eXtremes, Observatoire de Paris, Universit\'e PSL, Sorbonne Universit\'e, CNRS, 92190 Meudon, France), M. Bonici (Waterloo Centre for Astrophysics, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario N2L 3G1, Canada, INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy), S. Borgani (Dipartimento di Fisica - Sezione di Astronomia, Universit\`a di Trieste, Via Tiepolo 11, 34131 Trieste, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy), M. L. Brown (Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Oxford Road, Manchester M13 9PL, UK), S. Bruton (California Institute of Technology, 1200 E California Blvd, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), A. Calabro (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), B. Camacho Quevedo (IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), F. Caro (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), C. S. Carvalho (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Tapada da Ajuda, 1349-018 Lisboa, Portugal), T. Castro (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy), F. Cogato (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Conseil (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), A. R. Cooray (Department of Physics \&amp; Astronomy, University of California Irvine, Irvine CA 92697, USA), O. Cucciati (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Davini (INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), G. Desprez (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), A. D\'iaz-S\'anchez (Departamento F\'isica Aplicada, Universidad Polit\'ecnica de Cartagena, Campus Muralla del Mar, 30202 Cartagena, Murcia, Spain), J. J. Diaz (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), S. Di Domizio (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), J. M. Diego (Instituto de F\'isica de Cantabria, Edificio Juan Jord\'a, Avenida de los Castros, 39005 Santander, Spain), M. Y. Elkhashab (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, Dipartimento di Fisica - Sezione di Astronomia, Universit\`a di Trieste, Via Tiepolo 11, 34131 Trieste, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy), A. Enia (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Via Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy), Y. Fang (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), A. G. Ferrari (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), A. Finoguenov (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), K. Ganga (Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CNRS, Astroparticule et Cosmologie, 75013 Paris, France), J. Garc\'ia-Bellido (Instituto de F\'isica Te\'orica UAM-CSIC, Campus de Cantoblanco, 28049 Madrid, Spain), T. Gasparetto (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), V. Gautard (CEA Saclay, DFR/IRFU, Service d'Astrophysique, Bat. 709, 91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France), E. Gaztanaga (Institute of Space Sciences, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Institute of Cosmology and Gravitation, University of Portsmouth, Portsmouth PO1 3FX, UK), F. Giacomini (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), F. Gianotti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), G. Gozaliasl (Department of Computer Science, Aalto University, PO Box 15400, Espoo, FI-00 076, Finland, Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), M. Guidi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Via Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), C. M. Gutierrez (Instituto de Astrof\'i sica de Canarias, c/ Via Lactea s/n, La Laguna 38200, Spain. Departamento de Astrof\'i sica de la Universidad de La Laguna, Avda. Francisco Sanchez, La Laguna, 38200, Spain), A. Hall (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), H. Hildebrandt (Ruhr University Bochum, Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Astronomical Institute), J. Hjorth (DARK, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 155, 2200 Copenhagen, Denmark), J. J. E. Kajava (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Vesilinnantie 5, University of Turku, 20014 Turku, Finland, Serco for European Space Agency), Y. Kang (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), V. Kansal (ARC Centre of Excellence for Dark Matter Particle Physics, Melbourne, Australia, Centre for Astrophysics \&amp; Supercomputing, Swinburne University of Technology, Hawthorn, Victoria 3122, Australia), D. Karagiannis (Dipartimento di Fisica e Scienze della Terra, Universit\`a degli Studi di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of the Western Cape, Bellville, Cape Town, 7535, South Africa), K. Kiiveri (Department of Physics and Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), J. Kim (Department of Physics, Oxford University, Keble Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, UK), C. C. Kirkpatrick (Department of Physics and Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland), S. Kruk (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), J. Le Graet (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), L. Legrand (DAMTP, Centre for Mathematical Sciences, Wilberforce Road, Cambridge CB3 0WA, UK, Kavli Institute for Cosmology Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge, CB3 0HA, UK), M. Lembo (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France, Dipartimento di Fisica e Scienze della Terra, Universit\`a degli Studi di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy, Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare, Sezione di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy), F. Lepori (Department of Astrophysics, University of Zurich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, 8057 Zurich, Switzerland), G. Leroy (Department of Physics, Centre for Extragalactic Astronomy, Durham University, South Road, Durham, DH1 3LE, UK, Department of Physics, Institute for Computational Cosmology, Durham University, South Road, Durham, DH1 3LE, UK), G. F. Lesci (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), J. Lesgourgues (Institute for Theoretical Particle Physics and Cosmology), L. Leuzzi (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), T. I. Liaudat (IRFU, CEA, Universit\'e Paris-Saclay 91191 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France), A. Loureiro (Oskar Klein Centre for Cosmoparticle Physics, Department of Physics, Stockholm University, Stockholm, SE-106 91, Sweden, Astrophysics Group, Blackett Laboratory, Imperial College London, London SW7 2AZ, UK), J. Macias-Perez (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, Avenue des Martyrs, 38000, Grenoble, France), G. Maggio (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), M. Magliocchetti (INAF-Istituto di Astrofisica e Planetologia Spaziali, via del Fosso del Cavaliere, 100, 00100 Roma, Italy), F. Mannucci (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Arcetri, Largo E. Fermi 5, 50125, Firenze, Italy), R. Maoli (Dipartimento di Fisica, Sapienza Universit\`a di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro 2, 00185 Roma, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), C. J. A. P. Martins (Centro de Astrof\'isica da Universidade do Porto, Rua das Estrelas, 4150-762 Porto, Portugal, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Universidade do Porto, CAUP, Rua das Estrelas, PT4150-762 Porto, Portugal), L. Maurin (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CNRS, Institut d'astrophysique spatiale, 91405, Orsay, France), M. Miluzio (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain, HE Space for European Space Agency), P. Monaco (Dipartimento di Fisica - Sezione di Astronomia, Universit\`a di Trieste, Via Tiepolo 11, 34131 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy), C. Moretti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy), G. Morgante (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), K. Naidoo (Institute of Cosmology and Gravitation, University of Portsmouth, Portsmouth PO1 3FX, UK, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, UK), A. Navarro-Alsina (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), S. Nesseris (Instituto de F\'isica Te\'orica UAM-CSIC, Campus de Cantoblanco, 28049 Madrid, Spain), D. Paoletti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), F. Passalacqua (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), K. Paterson (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), L. Patrizii (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), A. Pisani (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), D. Potter (Department of Astrophysics, University of Zurich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, 8057 Zurich, Switzerland), S. Quai (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Radovich (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy), G. Rodighiero (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy), S. Sacquegna (INAF - Osservatorio Astronomico d'Abruzzo, Via Maggini, 64100, Teramo, Italy, Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, University of Salento, Via per Arnesano, CP-I93, 73100, Lecce, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Lecce, Via per Arnesano, CP-193, 73100, Lecce, Italy), M. Sahl\'en (Theoretical astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, Uppsala University, Box 516, 751 37 Uppsala, Sweden), D. B. Sanders (Institute for Astronomy, University of Hawaii, 2680 Woodlawn Drive, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA), E. Sarpa (SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy), A. Schneider (Department of Astrophysics, University of Zurich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, 8057 Zurich, Switzerland), D. Sciotti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro, 2 - c/o Dipartimento di Fisica, Edificio G. Marconi, 00185 Roma, Italy), E. Sellentin (Mathematical Institute, University of Leiden, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands, Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands), L. C. Smith (Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, UK), J. G. Sorce (Univ. Lille, CNRS, Centrale Lille, UMR 9189 CRIStAL, 59000 Lille, France, Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CNRS, Institut d'astrophysique spatiale, 91405, Orsay, France), K. Tanidis (Department of Physics, Oxford University, Keble Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, UK), C. Tao (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), G. Testera (INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), R. Teyssier (Department of Astrophysical Sciences, Peyton Hall, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ 08544, USA), S. Tosi (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), A. Troja (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), M. Tucci (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), C. Valieri (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), D. Vergani (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), G. Verza (Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute, 162 5th Avenue, 10010, New York, NY, USA), P. Vielzeuf (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), N. A. Walton (Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, UK)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interstellar Dust-Catalyzed Molecular Hydrogen Formation Enabled by Nuclear Quantum Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecular hydrogen (H$_2$) plays a critical role in astrophysical processes from galaxy evolution to the formation of planets. While the dominant formation channel in the interstellar medium is considered as dust-catalyzed H$_2$ formation, this process could become inefficient at low temperatures suppressed by the Boltzmann factor. This work demonstrates that quantum tunneling can dominate the formation of H$_2$, resolving the long-standing problem of formation efficiency. Path integral Monte Carlo simulations reveals that the quantum tunneling of hydrogen atoms maintains stable reaction rates at temperatures below 50 K on both graphitic and silicate grain surfaces. Kinetic Monte Carlo calculations further indicate that the actual H$_2$ formation efficiency is governed not by atomic diffusion, but rather by the energy barriers associated with chemisorption, desorption, and the association of two hydrogen atoms. These findings establish a robust physical basis for dust-catalyzed H$_2$ formation, offer quantitative reaction rates for refining astrophysical models, and provide a framework for interpreting observations of interstellar molecular materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25070v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaolong Yang, Lile Wang, Di Li, Shenzhen Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHEMOUT: CHEMical complexity in star-forming regions of the OUTer Galaxy. V. Chemical composition gradients as a function of the galactocentric radius</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26556v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The outer Galaxy is characterized by a lower metallicity than regions near the Sun, suggesting differences in the formation and survival of molecules in star-forming regions. To understand chemical evolution across the Milky Way, deriving molecular abundances in star-forming regions in the outer Galaxy is essential for refining models of sub-Solar metallicity environments. We analyzed IRAM 30 m observations at 3 and 2 mm toward 35 sources at Galactocentric distances of 9$-$24 kpc, within the "CHEMical complexity in star-forming regions of the outer Galaxy" (CHEMOUT) project. We focused on species with the highest detection rates (i.e., HCN, HCO$^+$, c-C$_3$H$_2$, H$^{13}$CO$^+$, HCO, SO) and searched for trends in column densities, abundances, and line widths with Galactocentric distance. Abundances for H$_2$CO and CH$_3$OH were updated using H$_2$ column densities from new NIKA2 dust maps. Fractional abundances relative to H$_2$ of most species (HCN, HCO$^+$, c-C$_3$H$_2$, HCO, H$_2$CO, CH$_3$OH) scale at most with the elemental carbon abundance ([C/H]) up to $\sim$24 kpc. SO shows a steeper gradient than sulfur abundance ([S/H]), while H$^{13}$CO$^+$ shows a shallower gradient than [$^{13}$C/H]. Gas turbulence, inferred from line widths, decreases with Galactocentric distance, suggesting a more quiescent environment in the outer Galaxy with respect to the inner Galaxy. In the outer Galaxy, the formation efficiency of most molecules, following the parent element availability, is comparable or higher (e.g., for H$^{13}$CO$^+$) than in the local Galaxy, whereas SO forms less efficiently. These results have significant implications for chemical models of the outermost star-forming regions and for understanding molecule formation under lower metallicity conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26556v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Gigli, F. Fontani, L. Colzi, G. Vermari\"en, S. Viti, V. M. Rivilla, A. S\'anchez-Monge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of the bar fraction and bar lengths in the last 12 billion years</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07407v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the evolution of the bar fraction and length using an extended JWST NIRCam imaging dataset of galaxies at $1 \leq z \leq 4$. We assess the wavelength dependence of the bar fraction and bar length evolution by selecting a nearly mass-complete CEERS disc sample and performing visual classifications on the short (F200W) and long (F356W+F444W) wavelength channels. A similar bar fraction is observed for both samples, and combined, we find a declining bar fraction from $0.16^{+0.03}_{-0.03}$ to $0.07^{+0.03}_{-0.01}$ over the redshift range. No evolution in the F356W+F444W bar length is measured, with a mean of 3.6 kpc. A slight increase of $\sim 1$ kpc towards $z = 1$ is measured in the F200W sample, with a mean of 2.9 kpc. We find that the correlation between bar length and galaxy mass, for massive galaxies at $z &lt; 1$, is unseen at $z &gt; 1$. By incorporating barred galaxies at $z&lt;1$, we show that there is a modest increase in the bar length ($\approx 2$ kpc) towards $z=0$, but bars longer than $\approx8$ kpc are only found at $z&lt;1$. We show that bars and discs grow in tandem, for the bar length normalised by disc size does not evolve. Not only is a significant population of bars forming beyond $z = 1$, but our results also show that some of these bars are as long and strong as the average bar at $z\approx0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07407v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf2010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, 2025, staf2010, 10.1093/mnras/staf2010</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zoe A. Le Conte, Dimitri A. Gadotti, Leonardo Ferreira, Christopher J. Conselice, Camila de S\'a-Freitas, Taehyun Kim, Justus Neumann, Francesca Fragkoudi, E. Athanassoula, Nathan J. Adams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting outflows with radio emission in active galactic nuclei at cosmic noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14152v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: AGN feedback is a well known mechanism in the evolution of galaxies. One open question is the driving mechanism of galaxy-scale outflows. At low redshift, radio jets often interact with the ISM, generating turbulence and driving ionized outflows. Despite this evidence at low redshift, relatively few studies have investigated the radio-ionized gas connection at cosmic noon. Thus, our main goal is to conduct a pilot study using VLA data for three quasars with moderate/high radio power, which have ionized outflows identified in observations from the SUPER survey. We used [OIII] data from SINFONI analyzed in earlier studies, along with new 6.2 GHz VLA radio observations, at comparable spatial resolution. We also incorporate radio data from the literature to explore the radio emission. We detected extended radio structure in our VLA A-array data for two quasars. The extended structure in J1333+1649 aligns with the smaller-scale emission seen in archival images, suggesting a jet propagating from nuclear to galaxy-wide scales. In all three quasars, we found that the brightest radio emission and ionized gas have comparable spatial scales. Furthermore, the position angles of the radio emission and ionized gas present small offsets for the two targets with extended structures. Given that the kinematics of the ionized gas in all three quasars is dominated by outflows, our results suggest a strong connection between radio emission and ionized outflows in typical AGN at cosmic noon. Based on energetic considerations and comparisons with archival data, radio jets could be a significant mechanism for driving outflows in AGN from cosmic noon to low redshifts. However, with the exception of one object (J1333+1649), we cannot rule out the possibility that the radio emission arises from shocks in the interstellar medium caused by disk winds or radiatively driven outflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14152v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele S. Ilha, C. M. Harrison, V. Mainieri, Ann Njeri, E. Bertola, M. Bischetti, C. Circosta, C. Cicone, G. Cresci, V. A. Fawcett, A. Georgakakis, D. Kakkad, I. Lamperti, A. Marconi, M. Perna, A. Puglisi, D. Rosario, G. Tozzi, C. Vignali, G. Zamorani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic scaling relations of disc galaxies from ionised gas at $z\sim~1$ and their connection with dark matter halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive the Tully-Fisher (TFR, $M_\ast-V_{\rm circ, f}$) and Fall (FR, $j_\ast-M_\ast$) relations at redshift $z = 0.9$ using a sample of 43 main-sequence disc galaxies with H$\alpha$ IFU data and JWST/HST imaging. The strength of our analysis lies in the use of state-of-the-art 3D kinematic models to infer galaxy rotation curves, the inclusion and morphological modelling of NIR bands, and the use of SED modelling applied to our photometry measurements to estimate stellar masses. After correcting the inferred H$\alpha$ velocities for asymmetric drift, we find a TFR of the form $\log(M_\ast / M_\odot) = a \log(V_{\rm circ,f} / 150~\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}) + b$, with $a=3.82^{+0.55}_{-0.40}$ and $b=10.27^{+0.06}_{-0.07}$, as well as a FR of the form $\log(j_\ast / \mathrm{kpc\,km\,s^{-1}}) = a \log(M_\ast / 10^{10.5} M_\odot) + b$, with $a=0.44^{+0.06}_{-0.06}$ and $b=2.86^{+0.02}_{-0.02}$.
  When compared to their $z=0$ counterparts, we find moderate evolution in the TFR and strong evolution in the FR over the past $8$ Gyr. We interpret our findings in the context of the galaxy-to-halo scaling parameters $f_{\rm M}=M_\ast/M_{\rm vir}$ and $f_{\rm j}=j_\ast/j_{\rm vir}$. We infer that at $z=0.9$ both $f_{\rm M}$ and $f_{\rm j}$ are higher and less mass-dependent than at $z=0$. We speculate that the evolution of $f_{\rm j}$ can be driven by more efficient and centrally concentrated stellar feedback at $z=0.9$, or by an appreciable dry merger history. We also show that assuming the galaxies populating our $z=0.9$ relations evolve into those populating the $z=0$ relations leads to an apparent discrepancy with the hierarchical growth of dark matter halos. To solve this issue, one needs to evoke a progenitor bias scenario, unknown systematics affecting our and previous measurements, or consider the possibility that H$\alpha$ kinematics is not a reliable dynamical tracer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08685v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel E. Mancera Pi\~na, Enrico M. Di Teodoro, S. Michael Fall, Antonino Marasco, Mariska Kriek, Marco Martorano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Simulation Based Inference for Galaxy Photometric Fitting with Synthesizer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10640v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce Synference, a new, flexible Python framework for galaxy SED fitting using simulation-based inference (SBI). Synference leverages the Synthesizer package for flexible forward-modelling of galaxy SEDs and integrates the LtU-ILI package to ensure best practices in model training and validation. In this work we demonstrate Synference by training a neural posterior estimator on $10^6$ simulated galaxies, based on a flexible 8-parameter physical model, to infer galaxy properties from 14-band HST and JWST photometry. We validate this model, demonstrating excellent parameter recovery (e.g. R$^2&gt;$0.99 for M$_\star$) and accurate posterior calibration against nested sampling results. We apply our trained model to 3,088 spectroscopically-confirmed galaxies in the JADES GOODS-South field. The amortized inference is exceptionally fast, having nearly fixed cost per posterior evaluation and processing the entire sample in $\sim$3 minutes on a single CPU (18 galaxies/CPU/sec), a $\sim$1700$\times$ speedup over traditional nested sampling or MCMC techniques. We demonstrate Synference's ability to simultaneously infer photometric redshifts and physical parameters, and highlight its utility for rapid Bayesian model comparison by demonstrating systematic stellar mass differences between two commonly used stellar population synthesis models. Synference is a powerful, scalable tool poised to maximise the scientific return of next-generation galaxy surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10640v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Harvey, Christopher C. Lovell, Sophie Newman, Christopher J. Conselice, Duncan Austin, William J. Roper, Aswin P. Vijayan, Stephen M. Wilkins, Patricia Iglesias-Navarro, Vadim Rusakov, Qiong Li, Nathan Adams, Kai Magdwick, Caio M. Goolsby, Marc Huertas-Company, Matthew Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor Matters, but Matter Flavors: Matter Effects on Flavor Composition of Astrophysical Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that high-energy astrophysical neutrinos produced in the cores of heavily obscured active galactic nuclei (AGNs) can undergo strong matter effects, thus significantly influencing their source flavor ratios. In particular, matter effects can completely modify the standard interpretation of the flavor ratio measurements in terms of the physical processes occurring in the sources (e.g., $pp$ versus $p\gamma$, full pion-decay chain versus muon-damped pion decay). We contrast our results with the existing flavor ratio measurements at IceCube, as well as with projections for next-generation neutrino telescopes like IceCube-Gen2. Signatures of these matter effects in neutrino flavor composition would not only bring more evidence for neutrino production in central AGN regions, but would also be a powerful probe of heavily Compton-thick AGNs, which escape conventional observation in $X$-rays and other electromagnetic wavelengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17315v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/mdhq-s9yp</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 093003 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Bhupal Dev, Sudip Jana, Yago Porto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
