<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 01:54:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ambipolar diffusion and the mass-to-flux ratio in a turbulent collapsing cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of stars is governed by the intricate interplay of nonideal magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) effects, gravity, and turbulence. Computational challenges have hindered a comprehensive 3D exploration of this interplay, posing a longstanding challenge in our understanding of clouds and cores. Our objective was to study the spatial features and time evolution of the neutral-ion drift velocity and the mass-to-flux ratio in a 3D nonideal MHD chemo-dynamical simulation of a supercritical turbulent collapsing molecular cloud. The resistivities of the cloud were computed self-consistently from a vast non-equilibrium chemical network containing 115 species. To compute the resistivities we used different mean collisional rates for each charged species in our network. We additionally developed a new generalized method for measuring the true mass-to-flux ratio in 3D simulations. Despite the cloud's turbulent nature, at early times, the neutral-ion drift velocity follows the expected structure from 2D axisymmetric non-ideal MHD simulations with an hourglass magnetic field. At later times, however, the neutral-ion drift velocity becomes increasingly complex, with many vectors pointing outward from the cloud's center. Specifically, we find that the drift velocity above and below the cloud's ``midplane'' is in ``antiphase''. We explain these features on the basis of magnetic helical loops and the correlation of the drift velocity with the magnetic tension force per unit volume. Despite the complex structure of the neutral-ion drift velocity, we demonstrate that, when averaged over a region, the true mass-to-flux ratio monotonically increases as a function of time and decreases as a function of the radius from the center of the cloud. In contrast, the ``observed'' mass-to-flux ratio shows poor correlation with the true mass-to-flux ratio and the density structure of the cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20391v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aris Tritsis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the interplay of dust and gas phases in DustPedia star-forming galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular gas is the key ingredient of the star formation cycle, and tracing its dependencies on other galaxy properties is essential for understanding galaxy evolution. In this work, we explore the relation between the different phases of the interstellar medium (ISM), namely molecular gas, atomic gas, and dust, and galaxy properties using a sample of nearby late-type galaxies. To this goal, we collect CO maps for 121 galaxies from the DustPedia project, ensuring an accurate determination of $M_{H2}$, the global molecular gas mass. We investigate which scaling relations provide the best description of $M_{H2}$, based on the strength of the correlation and its intrinsic dispersion. Commonly used correlations between $M_{H2}$ and star formation rate (SFR) and stellar mass ($M_{\star}$) are affected by large scatter, which accounts for galaxies that are experiencing quenching of their star formation activity. This issue can be partially mitigated by considering a "fundamental plane" of star formation, fitting together $M_{H2}$, $M_{\star}$, and SFR. We confirm previous results from the DustPedia collaboration that the total gas mass has the tightest connection with the dust mass and that the molecular component also establishes a good correlation with dust. Although dust grains are necessary for the formation of hydrogen molecules, the strength of gravitational potential driven by the stellar component plays a key role in driving density enhancements and the atomic-to-molecular phase transition. Eventually, we investigated the correlations between ISM components and monochromatic luminosities at different wavelengths: we proposed mid and far-IR luminosities as reliable proxies of $L^{\prime}_{CO}$ for sources lacking dedicated millimeter observations. Luminosities in mid-IR photometric bands collecting PAH emission can be used to trace molecular gas and dust masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20392v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Salvestrini, Simone Bianchi, Edvige Corbelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NEXUS: A Spectroscopic Census of Broad-line AGNs and Little Red Dots at $3\lesssim z\lesssim 6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a spectroscopic sample of 23 broad-line AGNs (BLAGNs) at $3\lesssim z\lesssim 6$ selected using F322W2+F444W NIRCam/WFSS grism spectroscopy of the central 100 ${\rm arcmin^2}$ area of the NEXUS survey. Among these BLAGNs, 15 are classified as Little Red Dots (LRDs) based on their rest-frame UV-optical spectral slopes and compact morphology. The number density of LRDs is $\sim 10^{-5}\,{\rm cMpc^{-3}}$, with a hint of declining towards the lower end of the probed redshift range. These BLAGNs and LRDs span broad H$\alpha$ luminosities of $\sim 10^{42.2}-10^{43.7}\,{\rm erg\,s^{-1}}$, black hole masses of $\sim 10^{6.3}-10^{8.4}\,M_\odot$, and Eddington ratios of $\sim 0.1-1$ (median value 0.4), though the black hole mass and Eddington ratio estimates carry large systematic uncertainties. Half of the LRDs show strong Balmer absorption, suggesting high-density gas surrounding the line-emitting region. We detect extended (hundreds of parsec) rest-frame UV-optical emission from the host galaxy in the majority of these LRDs, which contributes significantly or even dominantly to their total UV emission. This host emission largely accounts for the peculiar UV upturn of the LRD spectral energy distribution. We also measure the small-scale ($\lesssim 1\,{\rm cMpc}$) clustering of these BLAGNs and LRDs by cross-correlating with a photometric galaxy sample. Extrapolating the power-law two-point correlation function model to large linear scales, we infer a linear bias of $3.30_{-2.04}^{+2.88}$ and typical halo masses of a few $\times 10^{11}\,h^{-1}M_\odot$ for BLAGNs at the sample median redshift of $z\sim 4.5$. However, the inferred linear bias and halo masses of LRDs, while formally consistent with those for BLAGNs at $\sim 1.5\sigma$, appear too large to be compatible with their space density, suggesting LRDs may have strong excess clustering on small scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20393v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Yang Zhuang, Junyao Li, Yue Shen, Xiaojing Lin, Alice E. Shapley, Feige Wang, Qiaoya Wu, Qian Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutral gas phase distribution from HI morphology: phase separation with scattering spectra and variational autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unraveling the multi-phase structure of the diffuse interstellar medium (ISM) as traced by neutral hydrogen (HI) is essential to understanding the lifecycle of the Milky Way. However, HI phase separation is a challenging and under-constrained problem. The neutral gas phase distribution is often inferred from the spectral line structure of HI emission. In this work, we develop a data-driven phase separation method that extracts HI phase structure solely from the spatial morphology of HI emission intensity structures. We combine scattering spectra (SS) statistics with a Gaussian-mixture variational autoencoder (VAE) model to: 1. derive an interpretable statistical model of different HI phases from their multi-scale morphological structures; 2. use this model to decompose the 2D channel maps of GALFA-HI emission in diffuse high latitude ($|b|&gt;30$\degree) regions over narrow velocity channels ($\Delta v=3$ km/s) into cold neutral medium (CNM), warm neutral medium (WNM), and noise components. We integrate our CNM map over velocity channels to compare it to an existing map produced by a spectrum-based method, and find that the two maps are highly correlated, while ours recovers more spatially coherent structures at small scales. Our work illustrates and quantifies a clear physical connection between the HI morphology and HI phase structure, and unlocks a new avenue for improving future phase separation techniques by making use of both HI spectral and spatial information to decompose HI in 3D position-position-velocity (PPV) space. These results are consistent with a physical picture where processes that drive HI phase transitions also shape the morphology of HI gas, imprinting a sparse, filamentary CNM that forms out of a diffuse, extended WNM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20407v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minjie Lei, S. E. Clark, Rudy Morel, E. Allys, Iryna S. Butsky, Caleb Redshaw, Drummond B. Fielding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI Emission Line Galaxies: Clustering Dependence one Stellar Mass and [OII] Luminosity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We measure the projected two-point correlation functions of emission line galaxies (ELGs) from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) One-Percent Survey and model their dependence on stellar mass and [OII] luminosity. We select $\sim$180,000 ELGs with redshifts of $0.8 &lt; z &lt; 1.6$ and define 27 samples according to cuts in redshift and both galaxy properties. Following a framework that describes the conditional [OII] luminosity-stellar mass distribution as a function of halo mass, we simultaneously model the clustering measurements of all samples at fixed redshift. Based on the modeling result, most ELGs in our samples are classified as central galaxies, residing in halos of a narrow mass range with a typical median of $\sim$10$^{12.2-12.4}$ $h^{-1} M_\odot$. We observe a weak dependence of clustering amplitude on stellar mass, which is reflected in the model constraints and is likely a consequence of the 0.5-dex measurement uncertainty in the stellar mass estimates. The model shows a trend between galaxy bias and [OII] luminosity at high redshift ($1.2 &lt; z &lt; 1.6$) that is otherwise absent at lower redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20430v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Hagen, K. S. Dawson, Z. Zheng, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, S. BenZvi, D. Bianchi, D. Brooks, F. J. Castander, T. Claybaugh, A. Cuceu, A. de la Macorra, P. Doel, S. Ferraro, A. Font-Ribera, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gaztanaga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, V. Gonzalez-Perez, G. Gutierrez, C. Hahn, K. Honscheid, M. Ishak, S. Juneau, R. Kehoe, T. Kisner, A. Kremin, C. Lamman, M. Landriau, L. Le Guillou, A. Leauthaud, M. E. Levi, M. Manera, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, S. Nadathur, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, F. Prada, I. Perez-Rafols, A. J. Ross, G. Rossi, S. Saito, E. Sanchez, D. Schlegel, M. Schubnell, J. Silber, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarle, B. A. Weaver, R. Zhou, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of star clusters with initial bulk rotation via N-body simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Young star clusters can inherit bulk rotation from the molecular clouds from which they have formed. This rotation can affect the long-term evolution of a star cluster and its constituent stellar populations. In this study, we aim to characterize the effects of different degrees of initial rotation on star clusters with primordial binaries. The simulations are performed using NBODY6++GPU. We find that initial rotation strongly affects the early evolution of star clusters. Rapidly rotating clusters show angular momentum transport from the inner parts to the outskirts, resulting in a core collapse. Angular momentum transport is accompanied by a highly elongated bar-like structure morphology. The effects of bulk rotation are reduced on the timescale of two-body relaxation. Rotating and non-rotating clusters experience changes in the direction of angular momentum near the dissolution and early evolution due to the tidal field, respectively. We present synthetic observations of simulated clusters for comparison with future observations in filters of Gaia, CSST, and HST. This work shows the effects of bulk rotation on systems with primordial binaries and could be used for the identification of rotation signatures in observed open clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20432v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abylay Bissekenov, Xiaoying Pang, Albrecht Kamlah, M. B. N. Kouwenhoven, Rainer Spurzem, Bekdaulet Shukirgaliyev, Mirek Giersz, Abbas Askar, Peter Berczik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaseous Dynamical Friction on Hyperbolic Scatterings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a study of equal-mass hyperbolic encounters, embedded in a uniform gaseous medium. Using linear perturbation theory, we calculate the density wakes excited by these perturbers and compute the resulting forces exerted on them by the gas. We compute the changes to orbital energy, orbital angular momentum and apsidal precession across a wide range of eccentrities and pericenter Mach numbers. We identify six distinct classes of hyperbolic orbits, differing through their wake structure and subsequent orbital evolution. We find the gas to always dissipate orbital energy, leading to smaller semi-major axes and higher pericenter Mach numbers. The orbital angular momentum can either increase or decrease, whereas we typically find the orbital eccentricity to be damped, promoting supersonic gas-captures. Additionally, we find that the force exerted by the gas is not strictly frictional -- particularly for asymptotically subsonic trajectories. Therefore, despite the orbit-integrated changes to orbital parameters being similar to those predicted by the \cite{O99} prescription, the time evolution of the density wakes and the instantaneous forces exerted on the perturbers are significantly different.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20470v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David O'Neill, Daniel J. D'Orazio, Martin E. Pessah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Star Formation and HI Gas Properties of Galaxies Along Large-scale Structures Around the Virgo Cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20669v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the star formation and neutral atomic hydrogen (HI) gas properties of galaxies along three large-scale filaments and two galaxy groups in the wide field around the Virgo cluster. Our goal is to understand how galaxies are processed in low-density environments before falling into high-density regions. Combining the spatial distribution of galaxies with multiwavelength colors such as W3-W1, NUV-r, and g-r, we find a predominance of blue galaxies across the structures, indicating normal-to-enhanced star formation, similar to that of isolated galaxies. However, one filament and one group show a significant number of red galaxies (32% and 20%, respectively), suggesting that star formation has been suppressed in low-density environments before reaching high-density regions. Intriguingly, these red galaxies span a wide range of stellar masses, and the presence of red dwarfs support that not only mass but also environment plays an important role in the quenching of star formation in cluster outskirts. One particular filament, potentially connected to Virgo, already has a group of red populations outside Virgo's R_200, making these galaxies good candidates for being "preprocessed" before entering the Virgo cluster. In addition, several galaxies in the filaments and groups possess relatively low HI gas contents, similar to cluster galaxies. However, the overall fraction of HI-deficient galaxies is not as significantly high as the fraction of red galaxies in these structures. This suggests that HI gas properties are less influenced by the environment than star formation properties in low-density regions, possibly due to gas replenishment through accretion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20669v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyein Yoon, O. Ivy Wong, Aeree Chung, Shan Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quasar-associated 2175 \AA\ Dust Absorbers in the SDSS DR16 Quasar Catalog</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present, for the first time, a systematic study of quasar-associated 2175 \AA\ dust absorbers using spectroscopic data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) Data Release 16 (DR16). By analyzing the optical spectra and multi-band magnitudes of 557,674 quasars in the redshift range of $0.7 \le z \le 2.4$, we identify 843 absorbers that share the same redshifts as quasars and are believed to originate from dust in the quasar nuclei, the host galaxies, or their surrounding environments. These absorbers exhibit weak bump strengths ($A\rm_{bump}=0.49\pm0.15~\mu m^{-1}$) and narrow widths ($\gamma\rm=0.81\pm0.14~\mu m^{-1}$), while their peak positions span a broad range from $x_0 = 4.2$ to $4.84~ \mu m^{-1}$. Their average extinction curves resemble those of the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) but exhibit a shallower slope. In broad absorption line (BAL) quasars, the absorption bumps show systematic shifts in peak positions. Although further confirmation is needed, this may suggest environmental differences in dust grain properties. We find a statistically significant negative correlation between bump strength and redshift, suggesting possible evolution in dust properties. These findings highlight the changing composition and physical conditions of dust in quasar environments, likely influenced by factors such as metallicity, radiation fields, and dust processing mechanisms. Future studies incorporating ultraviolet and infrared data will be essential for refining the dust evolution models. Machine learning techniques and high-resolution spectroscopic follow-ups could enhance sample completeness and provide deeper insights into the chemical properties of the dust absorbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20706v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaohua Zhang, Yuchong Luo, Shangchun Xie, Chao Gao, Zhijian Luo, Chenggang Shu, Hubing Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A candidate for True Type-2 AGN without hidden central BLRs Identified by central Tidal Disruption Event</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this manuscript, through applications of TDE (tidal disruption event) expected variability properties, a potential candidate for True type-2 AGN without hidden central broad line regions (=TT2AGN) is reported in the SDSS J233454.07+145712.9 (=SDSS J2334). Through analyzing the 20-years optical light curves of SDSS J2334 from different Sky Survey projects, a TDE is preferred with a $4.7{\rm M_\odot}$ main-sequence star tidally disrupted by the central BH with mass $11.7\times 10^6{\rm M_\odot}$, indicating that central region within distance about 20 light-days to central BH in SDSS J2334 is directly in the line-of-sight. Moreover, AGN activities in SDSS J2334 can be confirmed through applications of BPT diagrams. Meanwhile, comparing virial BH mass determined through assumed broad Balmer emission components and M-sigma expected BH mass by well measured stellar velocity dispersion through stellar absorption features, optical broad emission lines in SDSS J2334 are disfavored with confidence level higher than 6$\sigma$. Therefore, combining the unique properties of the TDE and the spectroscopic results with only narrow emission lines, SDSS J2334 can be well identified as a potential candidate for a TT2AGN. The results indicate the to detect TDE expected flares in normal Type-2 AGN classified by spectroscopic results should be a new practicable method for identifying</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20821v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gu Ying, Zheng Qi, Cheng Peizheng, Li Xiao, Xing-Qian Cheng, Zhang XueGuang, Liang EnWei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Compton-thick AGNs with Machine learning algorithm in Chandra Deep Field-South</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Compton-thick active galactic nuclei (CT-AGNs), which are defined by column density $\mathrm{N_H} \geqslant 1.5 \times 10^{24} \ \mathrm{cm}^{-2}$, emit feeble X-ray radiation, even undetectable by X-ray instruments. Despite this, the X-ray emissions from CT-AGNs are believed to be a substantial contributor to the cosmic X-ray background (CXB). According to synthesis models of AGNs, CT-AGNs are expected to make up a significant fraction of the AGN population, likely around 30% or more. However, only $\sim$11% of AGNs have been identified as CT-AGNs in the Chandra Deep Field-South (CDFS). To identify hitherto unknown CT-AGNs in the field, we used a Random Forest algorithm for identifying them. First, we build a secure classified subset of 210 AGNs to train and evaluate our algorithm. Our algorithm achieved an accuracy rate of 90% on the test set after training. Then, we applied our algorithm to an additional subset of 254 AGNs, successfully identifying 67 CT-AGNs within this group. This result significantly increased the fraction of CT-AGNs in the CDFS, which is closer to the theoretical predictions of the CXB. Finally, we compared the properties of host galaxies between CT-AGNs and non-CT-AGNs and found that the host galaxies of CT-AGNs exhibit higher levels of star formation activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21105v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Zhang, Xiaotong Guo, Qiusheng Gu, Guanwen Fang, Jun Xu, Hai-Cheng Feng, Yongyun Chen, Rui Li, Nan Ding, Hongtao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The MUSE view of ram pressure stripped galaxies in clusters: the GASP sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the full sample of 76 galaxies in 39 galaxy cluster fields at z=0.04-0.07 observed with VLT/MUSE by the GASP survey. Most of them (64) were observed as possible ram pressure stripped galaxies (stripping candidates) based on optical B-band images, while the remaining 12 were a control sample of both star-forming and passive galaxies. Based on spatially resolved ionized gas and stellar kinematics, we assess the physical origin of the gas asymmetries and find that 89% of the stripping candidates are confirmed by the VLT/MUSE data. In addition, also 3 of the 4 star-forming galaxies in the control sample show signs of ram pressure. These control galaxies display a ring of unusual emission line ratios, which we see also in field galaxies, possibly originating from the interaction with a hotter surrounding medium. The stripped galaxies are classified into various classes corresponding to different degrees of stripping, from weakest stripping to strong and extreme (jellyfish galaxies) stripping, as well as truncated gas disks with gas left only in the galaxy center. Our results show that selecting cluster stripping candidates based on optical imaging yields a sample that is indeed largely dominated by galaxies affected by ram pressure at different stages and stripping strength, though some contamination is present, mostly by tidal processes. Strong ram pressure cases are found in galaxies over the whole range of stellar masses studied (10^9-10^11.5 Msun) both in low-mass and high-mass clusters (cluster velocity dispersions sigma = 500-1100 km/s). We examine the possible connection between the progressive stages of stripping, up to the phase of a truncated gas disk, and the subsequent complete stripping of gas. We discuss the incompleteness intrinsic to this and other methods of selection to obtain a complete census of ram pressure stripping in clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21107v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bianca M. Poggianti (INAF-OaPD), Benedetta Vulcani, Neven Tomicic, Alessia Moretti, Marco Gullieuszik, Cecilia Bacchini, Jacopo Fritz, Koshy George, Myriam Gitti, Alessandro Ignesti, Augusto Lassen, Antonino Marasco, Mario Radovich, Paolo Serra, Rory Smith, Stephanie Tonnesen, Anna Wolter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The TYPHOON Stellar Population Synthesis Survey. II. Pushing Full Spectral Fitting to the Limit in the Nearby Grand Design Barred Spiral M83</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply population synthesis techniques to analyze TYPHOON long slit spectra of the starburst barred spiral galaxy M83. The analysis covers a central square of 5 arcmin side length. We determine the spatial distribution of dust through the analysis of reddening and extinction, together with star formation rates, ages, and metallicities of young and old stellar populations. For the first time, a spatial one-to-one comparison of metallicities derived from full-spectral fitting techniques with those obtained from individual young stellar probes has been carried out. The comparison with blue supergiant stars, young massive star clusters, and super star clusters shows a high degree of concordance when wavelength coverage in the $B$-band is available. The metallicity of the young population is supersolar and does not show a radial metallicity gradient along the investigated part of the disk, in agreement with our chemical evolution model. However, a notable decrease in metallicity is observed in a tightly confined region at the galaxy center, coinciding with circumnuclear orbits. We attribute this to matter infall either from the circumgalactic medium or a dwarf galaxy interloper or, alternatively, to AGN-interrupted chemical evolution. We confirm the presence of a dust cavity with a diameter of 260~pc close to the galaxy center. Dust absorption and molecular CO emission are spatially well correlated. We find an anticorrelation between R$_V$, the ratio of dust attenuation to reddening, and the emission strength of molecular species present in photo-dissociation regions. We confirm our results by using alternative fitting algorithms and stellar libraries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21127v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eva Sextl, Rolf-Peter Kudritzki, Fabio Bresolin, Kathryn Grasha, Hye-Jin Park, Qian-Hui Chen, Andrew J. Battisti, Mark Seibert, Barry F. Madore, Jeffrey A. Rich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark-matter-induced transients over cosmic time: The role of star formation history profiles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dark matter (DM) conundrum is one of the most intriguing due to its resistance in direct detection experiments. In recent years, attempts to identify non-gravitational signatures as the result of DM traversing or accumulating within stars have attracted a lot of attention. These calculations are usually evaluated at the order-of-magnitude level for stellar populations where the DM density is highest, such as galactic centers. However, if the signature implies the destruction of the host star, their population could have been diminished over a Hubble time in the most DM-dense regions, unless replenished by star formation. This circumstance exemplifies the need for galactic star formation history profiles when deriving DM-induced transient rates, in particular for predicting the host-offset distribution. Here, we combine theoretical and empirical scaling relations of galaxy structure, star formation, and stellar initial mass function to construct a simple and efficient framework that permits us to estimate the target population formation rate and mass function within galactocentric radial zones across galaxy stellar masses and cosmic time. In a companion paper, we apply the framework to the hypothesis that DM in the form of primordial black holes accounts for the ignition of normal type Ia supernovae when colliding with white dwarf stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21260v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heinrich Steigerwald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotational equilibrium of C$_2$ in diffuse interstellar clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Recent spectroscopic measurements have revealed absorption from higher rotational levels in C$_2$ than previous observations. These improvements are accompanied by the availability of updated radiative and collisional data. Aims. We revisit the density and radiation field intensity diagnostics provided by the observations of many rotational levels of inter- stellar C$_2$ and extensive molecular information. Methods. We built an excitation model of C2 without spatial structure, including levels up to J= 34 where updated radiative and collisional excitation data are introduced as well as excitation by chemical formation. Results. We confirm the importance of the recent collisional excitation rate coefficients of C$_2$ by molecular H$_2$. We show that the new higher level observations cannot be explained by the standard balance between collisional excitation and radiative transitions. We propose that chemical excitation at formation provides a plausible mechanism to explain the observed high excitation of C$_2$. In addition, it allows us to lift the degeneracy of the density over radiation field strength parameter in the excitation model. Conclusions. A 0D model remains limited and it is highly desirable to use a full Photon Dominated Region (PDR) model, which includes all excitation processes introduced here and full chemical and thermal balance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21273v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Le Bourlot, E. Roueff, S. R. Federman, A. M. Ritchey, D. L. Lambert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRODIGE - envelope to disk with NOEMA: V. Low 12C/13C ratios for CH3OH and CH3CN in hot corinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 12C/13C isotope ratio has been derived towards numerous cold clouds (20-50 K) and a couple protoplanetary disks and exoplanet atmospheres. However, direct measurements of this ratio in the warm gas (&gt;100 K) around young low-mass protostars remain scarce, but are required to study its evolution during star and planet formation. We derived 12C/13C ratios from the isotopologues of the complex organic molecules (COMs) CH3OH and CH3CN in the warm gas towards seven Class 0/I protostellar systems to improve our understanding of the evolution of the 12C/13C ratios during star and planet formation. We used the data that were taken as part of the PRODIGE large program with the NOEMA at 1mm. The emission of CH3OH and CH3CN is spatially unresolved in the PRODIGE data (300au scale). Derived rotational temperatures exceed 100K, telling us that they trace the gas of the hot corino, where CH3CN probes hotter regions than CH3OH on average (290 K versus 180 K). The column density ratios between the 12C and 13C isotopologues, derived from LTE analysis, range from 4 to 30, thus, are significantly lower than the expected local ISM isotope ratio of about 68. Assuming that CH3CN and CH3OH may inherit the 12C/13C ratio from their precursor species, astrochemical models were conducted for the latter and compared with our observational results. We conclude that an enrichment in 13C in COMs at the earliest protostellar stages is likely inherited from the COMs' precursor species, whose 12C/13C ratios are set during the prestellar stage via isotopic exchange reactions. This also implies that low 12C/13C ratios observed at later evolutionary stages could at least partially be inherited. A final conclusion on 12C/13C ratios in protostellar environments requires improved observations to tackle current observational limitations and additional modelling efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21307v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. A. Busch, J. E. Pineda, O. Sipil\"a, D. M. Segura-Cox, P. Caselli, M. J. Maureira, C. Gieser, T. -H. Hsieh, M. T. Valdivia-Mena, L. Bouscasse, Th. Henning, D. Semenov, A. Fuente, M. Tafalla, J. J. Miranzo-Pastor, L. Colzi, Y. -R. Chou, S. Guilloteau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of a kinematically distinct component in the central region of the collisional ring galaxy AM0644-741</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the discovery of a peculiar central stellar structure in the collisional ring galaxy AM0644-741 using HST imaging and MUSE integral field unit (IFU) data. We identified two S\'ersic components with a S\'ersic index of 1.72 (inner part) and 1.11 (outer part) in the HST F814W band optical image using \textsc{Galfit}. We utilized the MUSE data cube to construct stellar line of sight velocity (V$_{\rm LOS}$), velocity dispersion ($\sigma_{\rm LOS}$), h$_3$ \&amp; h$_4$ velocity moments, and stellar population age maps using the \textsc{GIST} pipeline for further investigating both S\'ersic components, which have a difference of $\sim$ 60 degrees in their position angle. The inner component, with an effective radius $\sim$1 kpc, shows a strong anticorrelation between V$_{\rm LOS}$/$\sigma_{\rm LOS}$ and h$_3$, indicating the presence of a rotating stellar structure. In addition, the inner component also shows a relatively higher velocity dispersion (average values reaching up to $\sim$240 km sec$^{-1}$) along with disky isophotes and stronger Mg~$b$ line strength, which all together highlight a peculiar dynamical state of AM0644-741's central region. Our analysis suggests that the recent encounter has had a smaller impact on the stellar orbits within the inner component. In contrast, it has specifically affected the stellar orbits of the progenitor's outer disk when forming the star-forming ring. The BPT analysis of the unresolved nuclear source shows a LINER-type ionization, hinting at AGN activity in the galaxy. Our study projects the dynamical evolution of collisional systems and provides scope for simulations to explore the central region in greater detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21352v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chayan Mondal, Sudhanshu Barway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Evolution of Rotating Population III Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21463v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Population III (Pop III) stars, the first generation of stars formed from primordial gas, played a fundamental role in shaping the early universe through their influence on cosmic reionization, early chemical enrichment, and the formation of the first galaxies. However, to date they have eluded direct detection due to their short lifetimes and high redshifts. The launch of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has revolutionized observational capabilities, providing the opportunity to detect Pop~III stars via caustic lensing, where strong gravitational lensing magnifies individual stars to observable levels. This prospect makes it compelling to develop accurate models for their spectral characteristics to distinguish them from other stellar populations. Previous studies have focused on computing the spectral properties of non-rotating, zero-age main sequence (ZAMS) Pop III stars. In this work, we expand upon these efforts by incorporating the effects of stellar rotation and post-ZAMS evolution into spectral calculations. We use the JWST bands and magnitude limits to identify the optimal observing conditions, both for isolated stars, as well as for small star clusters. We find that, while rotation does not appreciably change the observability at ZAMS, the subsequent evolution can significantly brighten the stars, making the most massive ones potentially visible with only moderate lensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21463v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jake Hassan, Rosalba Perna, Matteo Cantiello, Tyler Parsotan, Davide Lazzati, Nathan Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dust removal timescale in galaxies across cosmic time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the evolution of dust in galaxies is crucial because it affects the dynamics and cooling of gas, star formation, and chemical evolution. Recent work on dust removal in galaxies indicates timescales of gigayears, with old stellar populations and AGNs as the primary drivers of this process. However, most statistically significant studies are focused on low redshifts $z &lt; 0.4$. Here, we determine the dust removal timescale in galaxies over a wide range of redshifts, up to $z \sim 5$. We use publicly available catalogue data of infrared-selected galaxies, observed by \textit{Herschel}. Using the inferred dust masses, stellar masses, and stellar ages, we calculate the dust removal timescale in a sample of more than 120,000 galaxies. We find that, with increasing redshift, the dust removal timescale decreases from 1.8 Gyr at redshift $z \sim 0.05$ to less than 500\,Myr at $z &gt; 3$. Galaxies at higher redshifts undergo more efficient dust removal than galaxies at lower redshift, likely driven by AGN activity, supernova shocks, and astration. These findings indicate that dust removal evolves over cosmic time, reflecting the changing mechanisms regulating dust content of galaxies as the Universe evolves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21492v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Le\'sniewska, Jens Hjorth, Christa Gall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling the Halo: Joint Model for Measurements of the Kinetic Sunyaev-Zeldovich Effect and Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20413v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first joint analysis of the kinetic Sunyaev-Zeldovich (kSZ) effect with galaxy-galaxy lensing (GGL) for CMASS galaxies in the Baryon Oscillation Spectroscopic Survey (BOSS). We show these complementary probes can disentangle baryons from dark matter in the outskirts of galactic halos by alleviating model degeneracies that are present when fitting to kSZ or GGL measurements alone. In our joint kSZ+GGL analysis we show that the baryon density profile is well constrained on scales from 0.3 to 50 Mpc/$h$. With our well constrained profile of the baryon density, we provide direct comparisons to simulations. For our model we find an outer slope of the baryon distribution that is shallower than predicted by some hydrodynamical simulations, consistent with enhanced baryonic feedback. We also show that not including baryons in a model for GGL can bias halo mass estimates low by $\sim 20\%$ compared to a model that includes baryons and is jointly fit to kSZ+GGL measurements. Our modelling code galaxy-galaxy lensing and kSZ (\texttt{glasz}) is publicly available at https://github.com/James11222/glasz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20413v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Sunseri, Alexandra Amon, Jo Dunkley, Nicholas Battaglia, Simone Ferraro, Boryana Hadzhiyska, Bernadita Ried Guachalla, Emmanuel Schaan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Properties of Little Red Dot Galaxies in the ASTRID Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20439v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present simulated counterparts of the ``Little Red Dot'' (LRD) galaxies observed with JWST, using the large cosmological hydrodynamic simulation, ASTRID. We create mock observations of the galaxies ($5 \leq z \leq 8$) in ASTRID, and find seventeen which fit the color and size criteria of LRDs. These LRDs are galaxies with high stellar masses ($\rm log(M_*/M_{\odot}) \geq 9.7$), and massive black holes ($\rm log(M_{BH}/M_{\odot}) \geq 6.8$). The host galaxies are dense, with stellar half mass radii ($\rm 325\,pc \leq r_{{\rm half},*} \leq 620\,pc$), and dust attenuation in the F444W band above 1.25. Their star formation has been recently quenched. They host relatively bright AGN that are dust-obscured and contribute significantly to the rest-frame optical red slope and have relatively low luminosity in the rest-frame ultraviolet, where the host galaxy's stars are more dominant. These LRDs are in an evolutionary phase of miniquenching that is the result of AGN feedback from their massive black holes. The LRDs in ASTRID are bright with F444W magnitudes of $23.5-25.5$. The less massive and fainter galaxies in ASTRID lack the dust concentration necessary to produce the red slope of an LRD, though this could be an effect of limited resolution. Most of the highest Eddington black holes are not LRDs due to their host galaxies having typical dust levels and relatively high star formation rates accompanying their highly accreting black holes, resulting in their spectra being too flat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20439v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick LaChance, Rupert A. C. Croft, Tiziana Di Matteo, Yihao Zhou, Fabio Pacucci, Yueying Ni, Nianyi Chen, Simeon Bird</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing population synthesis models of compact double white dwarfs to electromagnetic observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20953v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Context: Studies of the Galactic population of double white dwarfs (DWDs) that would be detectable in gravitational waves by LISA have found differences in the number of predicted detectable DWDs of more than an order of magnitude, depending on the binary stellar evolution model used. Particularly, the binary population synthesis code BPASS predicts 20 to 40 times fewer detectable DWDs than the codes SeBa or BSE, which relates to differing treatments of mass transfer and common-envelope events (CEEs).
  Aims: We aimed to investigate which of these models are closer to reality by comparing their predictions to the DWDs known from electromagnetic observations.
  Methods: We compared the DWDs predicted by a BPASS galaxy model and a SeBa galaxy model to a DWD catalogue and the sample of DWDs observed by the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF), taking into account the observational limits and biases of the ZTF survey.
  Results: We found that BPASS underpredicts the number of short-period DWDs by at least an order of magnitude compared to the observations, while the SeBa galaxy model is consistent with the observations for DWDs more distant than 500 pc. These results highlight how LISA's observations of DWDs will provide invaluable information on aspects of stellar evolution such as mass transfer and CEEs, which will allow theoretical models to be better constrained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20953v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wouter G. J. van Zeist, Jan van Roestel, Gijs Nelemans, Jan J. Eldridge, Valeriya Korol, Silvia Toonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimized quantum sensor networks for ultralight dark matter detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark matter (DM) remains one of the most compelling unresolved problems in fundamental physics, motivating the search for new detection approaches. We propose a network-based quantum sensor architecture to enhance sensitivity to ultralight DM fields. Each node in the network is a superconducting qubit, interconnected via controlled-Z gates in symmetric topologies such as line, ring, star, and fully connected graphs. We investigate four- and nine-qubit systems, optimizing both state preparation and measurement using a variational quantum metrology framework. This approach minimizes the quantum and classical Cramer-Rao bounds to identify optimal configurations. Bayesian inference is employed to extract the DM-induced phase shift from measurement outcomes. Our results show that optimized network configurations significantly outperform conventional GHZ-based protocols while maintaining shallow circuit depths compatible with noisy intermediate-scale quantum hardware. Sensitivity remains robust under local dephasing noise. These findings highlight the importance of network structure in quantum sensing and point toward scalable strategies for quantum-enhanced DM detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21188v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adriel I. Santoso, Le Bin Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Test for MOND: Gravitational Lensing by Disc Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17888v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Disc galaxies represent a promising laboratory for the study of gravitational physics, including alternatives to dark matter, owing to the possibility of coupling rotation curves' dynamical data with strong gravitational lensing observations. In particular, Euclid, DES and LSST are predicted to observe hundreds of thousands of gravitational lenses. Here, we investigate disc galaxy strong gravitational lensing in the MOND framework. We employ the concept of equivalent Newtonian systems within the quasi-linear MOND formulation to make use of the standard lensing formalism. We derive the phantom dark matter distribution predicted for realistic disc galaxy models and study the impact of morphological and mass parameters on the expected lensing. We find purely MONDian effects dominate the lensing and generate non-trivial correlations between the lens parameters and the lensing cross section. Moreover, we show that the standard realisation of MOND predicts a substantial increase in the number count of disc galaxy lenses compared to the dark matter-driven predictions, making it distinguishable from the latter in upcoming surveys. Finally, we argue that disc galaxy gravitational lensing, coupled to additional astronomical observations, can be used to constrain the interpolating function of MOND.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17888v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Harvey-Hawes, Marco Galoppo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BCDDM: Branch-Corrected Denoising Diffusion Model for Black Hole Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08528v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The properties of black holes and accretion flows can be inferred by fitting Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) data to simulated images generated through general relativistic ray tracing (GRRT). However, due to the computationally intensive nature of GRRT, the efficiency of generating specific radiation flux images needs to be improved. This paper introduces the Branch Correction Denoising Diffusion Model (BCDDM), a deep learning framework that synthesizes black hole images directly from physical parameters. The model incorporates a branch correction mechanism and a weighted mixed loss function to enhance accuracy and stability. We have constructed a dataset of 2,157 GRRT-simulated images for training the BCDDM, which spans seven key physical parameters of the radiatively inefficient accretion flow (RIAF) model. Our experiments show a strong correlation between the generated images and their physical parameters. By enhancing the GRRT dataset with BCDDM-generated images and using ResNet50 for parameter regression, we achieve significant improvements in parameter prediction performance. BCDDM offers a novel approach to reducing the computational costs of black hole image generation, providing a faster and more efficient pathway for dataset augmentation, parameter estimation, and model fitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08528v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ao liu, Zelin Zhang, Songbai Chen, Cuihong Wen, Jieci Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cartesian catalog of 30 million Gaia sources based on second-order and Monte Carlo error propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate measurements of stellar positions and velocities are crucial for studying galactic and stellar dynamics. We aim to create a Cartesian catalog from Gaia DR3 to serve as a high-precision database for further research using stellar coordinates and velocities. To avoid the negative parallax values, we select 31,129,169 sources in Gaia DR3 with radial velocity, where the fractional parallax error is less than 20% ($0 &lt; \sigma_\varpi/\varpi &lt; 0.2$). To select the most accurate and efficient method of propagating mean and covariance, we use the Monte Carlo results with $10^7$ samples (MC7) as the benchmark, and compare the precision of linear, second-order, and Monte Carlo error propagation methods. By assessing the accuracy of propagated mean and covariance, we observe that second-order error propagation exhibits mean deviations of at most 0.5% compared to MC7, with variance deviations of up to 10%. Overall, this outperforms linear transformation. Though Monte Carlo method with $10^4$ samples (MC4) is an order of magnitude slower than second-order error propagation, its covariances propagation accuracy reaches 1% when $\sigma_\varpi/\varpi$ is below 15%. Consequently, we employ second-order error propagation to convert the mean astrometry and radial velocity into Cartesian coordinates and velocities in both equatorial and galactic systems for 30 million Gaia sources, and apply MC4 for covariance propagation. The Cartesian catalog and source code are provided for future applications in high-precision stellar and galactic dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19997v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-4527/adc6da</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Research in Astronomy and Astrophysics, 25, 055010 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luyao Zhang, Fabo Feng, Yicheng Rui, Guang-Yao Xiao, Wenting Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XXL-HSC: Host properties of X-ray detected AGNs in XXL clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03422v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There is compelling evidence that AGNs are strongly influenced by their environment. Therefore, studying the AGN population of clusters is essential, as both large-scale structures and AGN play key roles in galaxy evolution, though the interactions between these elements are still not well understood. The primary objective of this study is to unravel the different factors that may significantly affect the triggering of AGN activity in cluster galaxies, including galaxy merging and interactions with other galaxies, and ram pressure from the hot intracluster medium. For our purposes, we used 82 X-ray detected AGN found within a $4r_{500}$ radius of 164 X-ray detected and spectroscopically confirmed galaxy clusters of the XXL survey, up to a redshift of $z\sim$1. This field is covered by deep optical observations of the Hyper Suprime-Cam, which allows for a reliable morphological classification of galaxies. Furthermore, using the X-ray hardness ratio, the optical spectra and the SEDs of the X-ray sources, we have studied the obscuration and other AGN properties and the SFR of the hosts as further indicators of interactions. We found a moderately significant higher fraction of X-ray AGN in galaxy clusters hosted by merging or disturbed galaxies, compared to non-active cluster galaxies or X-ray AGN in the field. This excess is primarily localised in the cluster outskirts. Also, we discovered a higher number of X-ray-hard AGN (hence, possibly obscured) in clusters than in the field particularly in the outskirts. These findings further support the idea that galaxy mergers and interactions may serve as mechanisms for the triggering and obscuration of AGN activity. The relatively high number of disturbed, merging, and possibly obscured AGN hosts in cluster outskirts suggests that galaxy merging and interactions are key drivers in triggering AGN activity in these outer regions of clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03422v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202452965</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 697, A234 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. Drigga, E. Koulouridis, E. Pouliasis, Y. Toba, M. Akiyama, C. Vignali, A. Ruiz, I. Georgantopoulos, T. Nagao, S. Paltani, M. Plionis, M. Pierre, B. Vijarnwannaluk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The chemical enrichment histories across the Milky Way disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20160v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The variation of metal production over time and its dilution in the interstellar medium depend on the star formation and gas accretion rates. Measuring age-chemistry relations across the Milky Way disk provides key constraints on the gas accretion and star formation histories, and offers insight into the birth locations of stars. We present a study based on a sample of nearly 30000 dwarf stars from the APOGEE DR17 survey within 2 kpc of the Sun, for which we measure accurate ages. Various parameter combinations are tested to optimize stellar age determination from isochrones. The resulting age-chemistry relations for a selected subsample of 12000 stars are interpreted with the aid of a chemical evolution model. The data reveal a well-defined, tight thick disk sequence, characterized by high [alpha/Fe], subsolar metallicities, and ages older than 8 Gyr. The thin disk, with lower [alpha/Fe] and younger ages, exhibits a wide spread in metallicity at all ages, with apparent structures. Dividing the sample by guiding radius into inner, intermediate, and outer disks shows distinct chemical evolution patterns. The inner disk displays a monotonic, homogeneous chemical evolution with little dispersion, while the outer disk shows little metallicity increase over the past 8 Gyr. The solar neighborhood appears as a mixture, not only due to stellar migration but also because the chemical evolution of the ISM in this intermediate region results from the mixing of gas from the inner and outer disks. In particular, we demonstrate that the solar vicinity experienced a decrease in the mean ISM metallicity 7-9 Gyr ago. A plausible explanation involves a radial inflow of lower-metallicity gas from the outer disk at that time, which diluted the gas leftover by the thick disk formation, contributing to the observed metallicity gradient in the intermediate region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20160v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeria Cerqui, Misha Haywood, Owain Snaith, Paola Di Matteo, Laia Casamiquela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Machine Learning to Estimate Near-ultraviolet Magnitudes and Probe Quenching Mechanisms of $z$=0 Nuggets in the RESOLVE and ECO Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10214v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a $z=0$ census of nuggets -- compact galaxies that form via gas-rich violent disk instability -- within the luminosity- and volume-limited REsolved Spectroscopy Of a Local VolumE (RESOLVE) and Environmental COntext (ECO) surveys. We use random forest (RF) models to predict near-ultraviolet (NUV) magnitudes for ECO galaxies that lack high-quality NUV magnitudes, thereby doubling the number of ECO galaxies with reliable extinction-corrected star formation rates (SFRs) and red/green/blue classifications based on specific SFRs (sSFRs). The resulting RF-enhanced RESOLVE+ECO nugget sample allows us to analyze rare subpopulations -- green nuggets and nuggets with active galactic nuclei (AGN) -- likely associated with quenching. Green nuggets are more similar to red nuggets than to blue nuggets in halo mass ($M_{\text{halo}}$) distribution, with both red and green nuggets being found mainly at $M_{\text{halo}} \ge 10^{11.4} M_\odot$, where permanent halo quenching is predicted. At these masses, the AGN frequency for green nuggets is higher ($\text{48.2\%}^{+5.3\%}_{-5.3\%}$) than for either blue ($\text{39.2\%}^{+2.9\%}_{-2.8\%}$) or red ($\text{29.3\%}^{+3.0\%}_{-2.8\%}$) nuggets. Between $M_{halo} = 10^{11.4}-10^{12} M_\odot$, at the onset of permanent quenching, the AGN frequency for green nuggets is nearly double the frequency for blue or red nuggets, implying AGN are associated with this transition. At $M_{halo} &lt; 10^{11.4} M_\odot$, where temporary cyclic quenching is expected, the AGN frequency for blue nuggets ($\text{7.5\%}^{+1.4\%}_{-1.2\%}$) is lower than for either green ($\text{31.3\%}^{+8.7\%}_{-7.5\%}$) or red ($\text{18.8\%}^{+11.5\%}_{-7.8\%}$) nuggets. At all masses, nuggets with AGN have reduced sSFRs and likely also atomic gas content compared to nuggets without AGN, but the quenching is more extreme below $M_{halo} = 10^{11.4} M_\odot$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10214v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. S. Carr, S. J. Kannappan, Z. L. Hutchens, M. S. Polimera, M. A. Norris, K. D. Eckert, A. J. Moffett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of High-mass Stellar Binaries in the Formation of High-mass Black Holes in Dense Star Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05947v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent detections of gravitational waves from mergers of binary black holes (BBHs) with pre-merger source-frame individual masses in the so-called upper mass-gap, expected due to (pulsational) pair instability supernova ((P)PISN), have created immense interest in the astrophysical production of high-mass black holes (BHs). Previous studies show that high-mass BHs may be produced via repeated BBH mergers inside dense star clusters. Alternatively, inside dense star clusters, stars with unusually low core-to-envelope mass ratios can form via mergers of high-mass stars, which then can avoid (P)PISN, but produce high-mass BHs via mass fallback. We simulate detailed star-by-star multi-physics models of dense star clusters using the Monte Carlo cluster evolution code, CMC, to investigate the role of primordial binary fraction among high-mass stars (&gt;=15 Msun) on the formation of high-mass BHs. We vary the high-mass stellar binary fraction (fb_15_prime) while keeping all other initial properties, including the population of high-mass stars, unchanged. We find that the number of high-mass BHs, as well as the mass of the most massive BH formed via stellar core-collapse are proportional to fb_15_prime. In contrast, there is no correlation between fb_15_prime and the number of high-mass BHs formed via BH-BH mergers. Since the total production of high-mass BHs is dominated by BH-BH mergers in old clusters, the overall number of high-mass BHs produced over the typical lifetime of globular clusters is insensitive to fb_15_prime. We study the differences in the demographics of BH-BH mergers and their implications for the LIGO-Virgo-Kagra detections as a function of fb_15_prime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05947v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/add337</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ambreesh Khurana, Sourav Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative-transfer models for dusty Type II supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10928v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dust is expected to form on a year timescale in core-collapse supernova (SN) ejecta. Its existence is revealed through an infrared brightening, an optical dimming, or a blue-red emission-line profile asymmetry. To investigate how the dust location and amount impact observations, we computed ultraviolet-to-optical spectra of interacting and standard, noninteracting Type II SNe using state-of-the-art models -- for simplicity we adopted 0.1micron silicate grains. These models account for the full ejecta and treat both radioactive decay and shock power that arises from interaction of the ejecta with circumstellar material. In a Type IIn SN such as 1998S at one year, approximately 3e-4Msun of dust within the dense shell reproduces the broad, asymmetric Halpha profile. It causes an optical dimming of ~2mag (which obscures any emission from the inner, metal-rich ejecta) but, paradoxically, a more modest dimming of the ultraviolet, which originates from the outer parts of the dense shell. In Type II SNe with late-time interaction, such as SN2017eaw, dust in the low-mass, fast outer ejecta dense shell tends to be optically thin, impacting little the optical spectrum for dust masses of order 1e-4Msun. In such SNe II with interaction, dust in the inner metal-rich ejecta has negligible effect on observed spectra in the ultraviolet and optical. In noninteracting SNe II, dust within the metal-rich ejecta preferentially quenches the [OI]6300,6364 and [CaII]7291,7323 metal lines, biasing the emission in favor of the H-rich material which generates the Halpha and FeII emission below 5500A. Our model with 5e-4Msun of dust below 2000km/s matches closely the optical spectrum of SN1987A at 714d. Modeling historical SNe requires treating both the ejecta material and the dust, as well as multiple power sources, although interaction power will generally dominate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10928v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Dessart, D. John Hillier, Arkaprabha Sarangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
