<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 01:48:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Shaping the Milky Way: The interplay of mergers and cosmic filaments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The large-scale morphology of Milky Way (MW)-mass dark matter (DM) halos is shaped by two key processes: filamentary accretion from the cosmic web and interactions with massive satellites. Disentangling their contributions is essential for understanding galaxy evolution and constructing accurate mass models of the MW. We analyze the time-dependent structure of MW-mass halos from zoomed cosmological-hydrodynamical simulations by decomposing their mass distribution into spherical harmonic expansions. We find that the dipole ($\ell=1$) and quadrupole ($\ell=2$) moments dominate the gravitational power spectrum, encoding key information about the halo's shape and its interaction with the cosmic environment. While the dipole reflects transient perturbations from infalling satellites and damps on dynamical timescales, the quadrupole -- linked to the halo's triaxiality -- is a persistent feature. We show that the quadrupole's orientation aligns with the largest filaments, imprinting a long-lived memory on the halo's morphology even in its inner regions ($\sim30$ kpc). At the virial radius, the quadrupole distortion can reach 1-2 times the spherical density, highlighting the importance of environment in shaping MW-mass halos. Using multivariate Singular Spectrum Analysis, we successfully disentangle the effects of satellite mergers and filamentary accretion on quadrupole. We find that the quadrupolar response induced by LMC-mass satellites has an order of magnitude larger gravitational power than in spherically symmetric MW models. This highlights the need for models that incorporate the MW's asymmetry and time-evolution, with direct consequences for observable structures such as disk warps, the LMC-induced wake, and stellar tracers -- particularly in the era of precision astrometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20133v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpit Arora, Nicol\'as Garavito-Camargo, Robyn E. Sanderson, Martin D. Weinberg, Michael S. Petersen, Silvio Varela-Lavin, Facundo A. G\'omez, Kathryn V. Johnston, Chervin F. P. Laporte, Nora Shipp, Jason A. S. Hunt, Gurtina Besla, Elise Darragh-Ford, Nondh Panithanpaisal, Kathryne J. Daniel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-phase investigation of outflows in the circumgalactic and interstellar media of luminous quasars at z~5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aims. Outflows from active galactic nuclei are invoked as the principal feedback process regulating the co-evolution of supermassive black holes and their host galaxies. Because of their multi-phase and multi-scale nature, an exhaustive description of these winds should exploit multiple tracers. However, connecting various outflow features remains a challenge. The aim of this work is to provide a complete characterisation of outflows in a sample of z$\sim$5 quasars, by exploiting the combination of different emission and absorption tracers. Methods. We analysed the UV/optical and FIR continuum, line emission, and absorption in a sample of 39 z$\sim$5 quasars observed with VLT/X-Shooter and ALMA (available for six objects). We identified broad and narrow absorption lines associated with the quasar and emission lines to determine black hole masses and bolometric luminosities. Results. Our sample encompasses massive (log($M_{\text{BH,MgII}}/M_\odot$) = 8.5-10) and luminous (log($L_{\text{bol}}$/(erg/s)) = 46.9-48) quasars at redshift 5-5.7. They display powerful ionised outflows detected in both emission and absorption, with velocities exceeding 48,000 km/s in some cases, and lie above the local black hole - host galaxy mass relation, exhibiting a behaviour similar to that of z$\gtrsim$6 quasars. These findings suggest a phase of efficient black hole feedback occurring at redshift z$\gtrsim$6 and likely persisting down to z$\sim$5, characterised by rapid black hole growth exceeding that of the host galaxy. The fraction of quasars with outflow detections in absorption is higher for larger CIV-MgII velocity shifts, suggesting that while the physical mechanisms powering the two outflow phenomena detected in emission and absorption may differ, a correlation exists between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20136v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matilde Brazzini, Valentina D'Odorico, Manuela Bischetti, Chiara Feruglio, Guido Cupani, George Becker, Roberta Tripodi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy evolution in groups: Transition galaxies in the IllustrisTNG simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The evolution of galaxies is significantly influenced by the environments they inhabit. While high-density regions, such as clusters of galaxies have been widely studied, the dynamics and quenching processes in intermediate environments remain less explored. These systems provide a valuable context for understanding the transition of galaxies from active star formation to quiescence. This study aims to characterise the astrophysical properties of galaxies in intermediate-mass galaxy groups $(13.5 \leq \log(M_{200}/M_{\odot}) \leq 13.7)$, with a focus on their evolutionary pathways and the key processes driving their transition through the green valley (GV) and green zone (GZ). Using the Illustris TNG300-1 hydrodynamical cosmological simulations, we classified galaxies based on their trajectories and environment into five categories: group galaxies (GRs), backsplash galaxies (BSs), recent infallers (RINs), infall galaxies (INs), and field galaxies (FGs). We examined their optical colours in the $(u-r)$-stellar mass diagram, specific star formation rates (sSFRs), gas fractions, and stellar mass evolution from $z=0.5$ to $z=0$. At $z=0$, FGs dominate the blue cloud, while GRs show progressive reddening. BSs exhibit the highest fraction of green galaxies, highlighting their transitional nature, whereas RINs show a rapid quenching upon entering $R_{200}$. Our results reveal that the timing of group entry and environmental effects, such as gas depletion, play a critical role in galaxy quenching. Green BS and RINs follow distinct evolutionary tracks, with the latter undergoing more rapid changes due to later infall into more massive systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20142v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Selene Levis, Valeria Coenda, Hern\'an Muriel, Mart\'in de los Rios, Cinthia Ragone-Figueroa, H\'ector J. Mart\'inez, Andr\'es N. Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The chemical enrichment histories across the Milky Way disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The variation of metal production over time and its dilution in the interstellar medium depend on the star formation and gas accretion rates. Measuring age-chemistry relations across the Milky Way disk provides key constraints on the gas accretion and star formation histories, and offers insight into the birth locations of stars. We present a study based on a sample of nearly 30000 dwarf stars from the APOGEE DR17 survey within 2 kpc of the Sun, for which we measure accurate ages. Various parameter combinations are tested to optimize stellar age determination from isochrones. The resulting age-chemistry relations for a selected subsample of 12000 stars are interpreted with the aid of a chemical evolution model. The data reveal a well-defined, tight thick disk sequence, characterized by high [alpha/Fe], subsolar metallicities, and ages older than 8 Gyr. The thin disk, with lower [alpha/Fe] and younger ages, exhibits a wide spread in metallicity at all ages, with apparent structures. Dividing the sample by guiding radius into inner, intermediate, and outer disks shows distinct chemical evolution patterns. The inner disk displays a monotonic, homogeneous chemical evolution with little dispersion, while the outer disk shows little metallicity increase over the past 8 Gyr. The solar neighborhood appears as a mixture, not only due to stellar migration but also because the chemical evolution of the ISM in this intermediate region results from the mixing of gas from the inner and outer disks. In particular, we demonstrate that the solar vicinity experienced a decrease in the mean ISM metallicity 7-9 Gyr ago. A plausible explanation involves a radial inflow of lower-metallicity gas from the outer disk at that time, which diluted the gas leftover by the thick disk formation, contributing to the observed metallicity gradient in the intermediate region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20160v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeria Cerqui, Misha Haywood, Owain Snaith, Paola Di Matteo, Laia Casamiquela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The H2 Glow of a Quiescent Molecular Cloud Observed with JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report JWST MIRI/MRS observations of the H2 S(1) 17.04 micron transition in two regions in the boundary of the Taurus Molecular Cloud. The two regions, denoted Edge (near the relatively sharp boundary of the 13CO J=1-0 emission) and Peak (the location of the strongest H2 emission observed with Spitzer), have average intensities of 14.5 MJy/sr and 32.1 MJy/sr, respectively. We find small scale structures of characteristic size 1.0 to 2.5 arcseconds, corresponding to 140 AU to 350 AU, with characteristic intensity above the extended background of 10 MJy/sr, corresponding to a J = 3 column density of 1.6x1017/cm2. The most plausible explanation for the observed intensities from level 845 K above the J = 1 ortho-H2 ground state level is excitation by collisions with H2 molecules (the hydrogen in this region being predominantly molecular). Two mechanisms, turbulent dissipation and shocks, have been proposed for heating of localized regions of the ISM to temperatures ~1000 K to explain abundances of and emission from particular molecules. While we cannot determine unique values of density and kinetic temperature, the solutions in best agreement with predictions of shock models are H2 density = 370 /cm3 and kinetic temperature = 1000 K. The total H2 column density of the small-scale structures under these conditions is ~8x1017/cm2. This first direct detection of heated tiny scale structure in the quiescent molecular interstellar medium has significant implications for the physical structure of this phase of the ISM and maintaining supersonic motions within it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20164v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul F. Goldsmith, Shengzhe Wang, Xin Wang, Raphael Skalidis, Gary A. Fuller, Di Li, Chao-Weo Tsai, Lile Wang, Donghui Quan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CHILES Continuum &amp; Polarization Survey-II: Radio Continuum Source Catalog and Radio Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The COSMOS HI Large Extragalactic Survey (CHILES) Continuum &amp; Polarization (CHILES Con Pol) survey is an ultra-deep continuum imaging study of the COSMOS field conducted using the Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array. We obtained 1000 hours of L-band ($\lambda = 20$ cm) observations across four spectral windows (1.063-1.831 GHz) on a single pointing and produced a confusion limited image with an apparent RMS noise of 1.67 $\mu$Jy beam$^{-1}$ with a synthesized beam of 5$.\!\!^{\prime\prime}$5$\times$5$.\!\!^{\prime\prime}$0. This paper reports a 1.4 GHz radio continuum source catalog containing 1678 sources detected above 7$\sigma$ (flux densities greater than 11.7 $\mu$Jy), identified using two independent source extraction programs applied to the Stokes $I$ image. Resolved sources dominate at flux density S$_{1.4GHz} \ge 42 $\mu$Jy. Radio spectral index for each source was derived using a power-law fit across the four spectral windows, and we found that a robust spectral index measurement requires a total signal-to-noise ratio of at least 20. Comparisons with previous 1.4 GHz radio continuum surveys show good overall consistency, but evidence for a high degree of catalog incompleteness and the effects of source confusion are evident for some of the earlier studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20200v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hansung B. Gim, Min S. Yun, Nicholas M. Luber, Emmanuel Momjian, D. J. Pisano, Kelley M. Hess, Julia Blue Bird, Lucas Hunt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CHILES Continuum \&amp; Polarization Survey-I: Survey Design \&amp; Noise Characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and describe the CHILES Continuum \&amp; Polarization (CHILES Con Pol) Survey, a 1000 hour 1.4 GHz wideband full polarization radio continuum deepfield with the Very Large Array (VLA), commensurate with the CHILES HI deepfield. We describe the observational configuration, outline the calibration of the data, and discuss the effect of Radio Frequency Interference on different observing epochs. In addition, we present a novel radio continuum imaging strategy, using well known baseline subtraction techniques in radio spectral data, and discuss the applications to the removal of artifacts from sources far from the field center. Additionally, we discuss the nature of a low-level image-wide offset, the so-called ``negative bowl" and simulate our observations in order that we may both properly understand and correct for this artifact. Using these techniques, we present the first total intensity image of the data which achieves an r.m.s. noise of 1.3 $\mu$Jy beam$^{-1}$ with a synthesized beam of 4.5\arcsec x 4.0\arcsec, the most sensitive L-band image ever taken at this resolution. We then place this image into the broader context of 1.4 GHz radio continuum surveys in the literature, in terms of image sensitivity and fidelity, and $\mu$Jy level source counts and P(D) analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20253v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas M. Luber, Min S. Yun, Hansung B. Gim, Daniel Krista-Kelsey, D. J. Pisano, Emmanuel Momjian, Chris Hales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearby stellar substructures in the Galactic halo from DESI Milky Way Survey Year 1 Data Release</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report five nearby ($d_{\mathrm{helio}} &lt; 5$ kpc) stellar substructures in the Galactic halo from a subset of 138,661 stars in the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) Milky Way Survey Year 1 Data Release. With an unsupervised clustering algorithm, HDBSCAN*, these substructures are independently identified in Integrals of Motion ($E_{\mathrm{tot}}$, $L_{\mathrm z}$, $\log{J_r}$, $\log{J_z}$) space and Galactocentric cylindrical velocity space ($V_{R}$, $V_{\phi}$, $V_{z}$). We associate all identified clusters with known nearby substructures (Helmi streams, M18-Cand10/MMH-1, Sequoia, Antaeus, and ED-2) previously reported in various studies. With metallicities precisely measured by DESI, we confirm that the Helmi streams, M18-Cand10, and ED-2 are chemically distinct from local halo stars. We have characterised the chemodynamic properties of each dynamic group, including their metallicity dispersions, to associate them with their progenitor types (globular cluster or dwarf galaxy). Our approach for searching substructures with HDBSCAN* reliably detects real substructures in the Galactic halo, suggesting that applying the same method can lead to the discovery of new substructures in future DESI data. With more stars from future DESI data releases and improved astrometry from the upcoming {\it Gaia} Data Release 4, we will have a more detailed blueprint of the Galactic halo, offering a significant improvement in our understanding of the formation and evolutionary history of the Milky Way Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20327v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bokyoung Kim, Sergey E. Koposov, Ting S. Li, Sophia Lilleengen, Andrew P. Cooper, Andreia Carrillo, Monica Valluri, Alexander H. Riley, Jiwon Jesse Han, Jessica Nicole Aguilar, Steven Ahlen, Leandro Beraldo e Silva, Davide Bianchi, David Brooks, Amanda Bystr\"om, Todd Claybaugh, Shaun Cole, Kyle Dawson, Axel de la Macorra, Jaime Forero-Romero, Oleg Y. Gnedin, Satya Gontcho A Gontcho, Gaston Gutierrez, Julien Guy, Klaus Honscheid, Robert Kehoe, Namitha Kizhuprakkat, Martin Landriau, Laurent Le Guillou, Michael Levi, Gustavo Medina Toledo, Aaron Meisner, Ramon Miquel, John Moustakas, Claire Poppett, Francisco Prada, Graziano Rossi, Eusebio S\'anchez, Michael Schubnell, Ray Sharples, David Sprayberry, Jos\'e Arturo Trelles Hern\'andez, Benjamin Alan Weaver, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Merger-Driven Turbulence and Coherent Transport in the Intracluster Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The distribution of metals and temperature in the intracluster medium (ICM) provides key insights into galaxy cluster evolution, revealing information about chemical enrichment and heating and cooling processes, respectively. To access this information, it is crucial to understand the transport processes in the ICM. Here, we systematically study the transport mechanisms in the ICM with tracer particle resimulations of the Omega500 cosmological hydrosimulation, using a sample of four galaxy clusters of comparable masses but different mass assembly histories. Through the analysis of particle pair dispersion statistics, we find a time-dependent scaling index linked to the cluster's dynamical state. It reaches or exceeds Richardson scaling briefly during major mergers but remains much lower in relaxed clusters. We identify a coherent transport mode during major mergers that causes directional flow in the ICM. Although coherent transport can move particles to outer regions, the particles transported to the cluster outskirts compose only a small fraction of the density there; thus the anisotropy it creates in the overall density distribution is limited. Moreover, strong turbulence generated by mergers quickly disperses these particles, further limiting this effect. We also provide useful statistics on the radial evolution of the ICM and the fraction of particles that ever reached the inner regions as a function of radius. Our results show that major mergers primarily drive particle transport, linking ICM transport to merger-driven dynamics, and highlighting the interplay between coherent and turbulent transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20483v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/add1b4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yiwei Zhang, Xun Shi, Daisuke Nagai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum, CO and Water vapour maps of the Orion Nebula. First millimetre spectral imaging with Concerto</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The millimetre spectrum of Galactic regions and galaxies is rich in continuum and molecular lines. That diversity is mostly tackled by either broad-band photometry or high resolution heterodyne spectroscopy. We aim to map the millimetre continuum emission of Galactic regions with a spectral resolution intermediate between broad-band photometry and heterodyne spectroscopy, enabling us to quickly cover large sky areas with spectroscopy. We report observations of the Orion Nebula with the CONCERTO instrument, which was installed at the APEX telescope focal plane from April 2021 to December 2023. We find that the spectrum of Orion is dominated by dust emission with an emissivity index from 1.3 to 2.0 along with the strong CO(2-1) and H$_2$O lines which are naturally separated from the continuum, thanks to CONCERTO spectral capabilities. Many regions show a strong free-free emission as well, at lower frequencies. We demonstrate the spectral capabilities of CONCERTO at intermediate spectral resolution, with a frequency coverage from 130 to 310 GHz. A sensitivity of 200 mK is achieved in one second, for one beam and a 6 GHz frequency width, over an 18 arcmin diameter field-of-view, which is within a factor 3 of the expectations. We show that we can spectrally disentangle the continuum from the CO line emission. The slope of the millimetre continuum is line-free mapped for the first time in Orion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20487v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. -X. D\'esert (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, IPAG, 38000 Grenoble, France), J. F. Mac\'ias-P\'erez (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), A. Beelen (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), A. Beno\^it (Institut N\'eel, CNRS, Universit\'e Grenoble Alpes, France), M. B\'ethermin (Universit\'e de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, 67000 Strasbourg, France), J. Bounmy (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), O. Bourrion (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), M. Calvo (Institut N\'eel, CNRS, Universit\'e Grenoble Alpes, France), A. Catalano (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), C. De Breuck (European Southern Observatory, Karl Schwarzschild Stra{\ss}e 2, 85748 Garching, Germany), C. Dubois (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), C. A Dur\'an (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), A. Fasano (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, E-38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, Universidad de La Laguna), J. Goupy (Institut N\'eel, CNRS, Universit\'e Grenoble Alpes, France), W. Hu (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of the Western Cape, Robert Sobukhwe Road, Bellville, 7535, South Africa), E. Ibar (Instituto de F\'isica y Astronom\'ia, Universidad de Valpara\'iso, Avda. Gran Breta\~na 1111, Valpara\'iso, Chile, Millennium Nucleus for Galaxies), G. Lagache (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), A. Lundgren (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), A. Monfardini (Institut N\'eel, CNRS, Universit\'e Grenoble Alpes, France), N. Ponthieu (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, IPAG, 38000 Grenoble, France), D. Quinatoa (Instituto de F\'isica y Astronom\'ia, Universidad de Valpara\'iso, Avda. Gran Breta\~na 1111, Valpara\'iso, Chile), M. Van Cuyck (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), R. Adam (Universit\'e C\^ote d'Azur, Observatoire de la C\^ote d'Azur, CNRS, Laboratoire Lagrange, France), P. Ade (School of Physics and Astronomy, Cardiff University, Queen's Buildings, The Parade, Cardiff, CF24 3AA, UK), H. Ajeddig (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), S. Amarantidis (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), P. Andr\'e (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), H. Aussel (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), S. Berta (Institut de RadioAstronomie Millim\'etrique), A. Bongiovanni (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), D. Ch\'erouvrier (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), M. De Petris (Dipartimento di Fisica, Sapienza Universit\`a di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro 5, I-00185 Roma, Italy), S. Doyle (School of Physics and Astronomy, Cardiff University, Queen's Buildings, The Parade, Cardiff, CF24 3AA, UK), E. F. C. Driessen (Institut de RadioAstronomie Millim\'etrique), G. Ejlali (Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences), A. Ferragamo (Dipartimento di Fisica, Sapienza Universit\`a di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro 5, I-00185 Roma, Italy), A. Gomez (Centro de Astrobiolog\'ia), C. Hanser (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), S. Katsioli (National Observatory of Athens, Institute for Astronomy, Astrophysics, Space Applications and Remote Sensing, Ioannou Metaxa and Vasileos Pavlou GR-15236, Athens, Greece, Department of Astrophysics, Astronomy &amp; Mechanics, Faculty of Physics, University of Athens, Panepistimiopolis, GR-15784 Zografos, Athens, Greece), F. K\'eruzor\'e (High Energy Physics Division, Argonne National Laboratory, 9700 South Cass Avenue, Lemont, IL 60439, USA), C. Kramer (Institut de RadioAstronomie Millim\'etrique), B. Ladjelate (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), S. Leclercq (Institut de RadioAstronomie Millim\'etrique), J. -F. Lestrade (LERMA, Observatoire de Paris, PSL Research University, CNRS, Sorbonne Universit\'e, UPMC, 75014 Paris, France), S. C. Madden (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), A. Maury (Institute of Space Sciences, ICREA, Pg. Llu\'is Companys 23, Barcelona, Spain), F. Mayet (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), A. Moyer-Anin (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), M. Mu\~noz-Echeverr\'ia (IRAP, CNRS, Universit\'e de Toulouse, CNES, UT3-UPS), I. Myserlis (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), A. Paliwal (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Roma 'Tor Vergata', Via dellaRicerca Scientifica 1, I-00133 Roma, Italy), L. Perotto (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), G. Pisano (Dipartimento di Fisica, Sapienza Universit\`a di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro 5, I-00185 Roma, Italy), V. Rev\'eret (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), A. J. Rigby (School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Leeds, Leeds LS29JT, UK), A. Ritacco (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), H. Roussel (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), F. Ruppin (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), M. S\'anchez-Portal (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), S. Savorgnano (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LPSC-IN2P3, 53, avenue des Martyrs, 38000 Grenoble, France), A. Sievers (Institut de Radioastronomie Millim\'etrique), C. Tucker (School of Physics and Astronomy, Cardiff University, Queen's Buildings, The Parade, Cardiff, CF24 3AA, UK), R. Zylka (Institut de RadioAstronomie Millim\'etrique)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular gas in cool-core brightest cluster galaxies at $z\simeq0.4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20538v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Brightest cluster galaxies (BCG) are today passive and very massive galaxies at the center of their clusters, still accreting mass through swallowing companions, and flows of cold gas, regulated by radio-mode active galactic nucleus (AGN) feedback. However, their formation history is still a matter of debate. We report new results based on millimeter observations performed with the Northern Extended Millimeter Array (NOEMA) interferometer, mapping the cold molecular gas (CO) that feeds the star formation of distant BCGs. We selected three among the strongest cool-core BCGs at intermediate redshifts ($z\simeq0.4$), namely RX 1532, MACS 1447, and CHIPS 1911. Previous unresolved millimeter observations and multi-wavelength analysis showed that they are among the most star forming (${\rm SFR}\simeq100~ M_\odot/{\rm yr}$) and gas rich ($M_{H_2}\simeq10^{11}~M_\odot$) BCGs at intermediate redshifts. The selected BCGs are thus caught in a phase of rapid mass assembly, which makes them ideal targets for high-resolution observations of their molecular gas. By combining NOEMA intensity and velocity maps with archival images from the Hubble Space Telescope, we detect in-situ star formation, filaments of accreting cold gas likely regulated by AGN feedback, disturbed morphology associated with tidal tails of molecular gas, as well as gas compression and tails originated from stripping of gas. While effective condensation of the intra-cluster medium is required to explain the large molecular gas reservoirs, the BCGs exhibit a broad variety of environment-driven mechanisms responsible for the processing of their cold gas: flows of cooling gas (RX 1532), ram pressure or sloshing of the intra-cluster medium (MACS 1447), and galactic tides (CHIPS 1911). This study thus sheds new insights on the physical mechanisms responsible for the mass assembly of galaxies hosting AGN at the center of clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20538v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Castignani, F. Combes, P. Salom\'e, A. Edge, P. Jablonka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From small dust to micron-sized aggregates: the influence of structure and composition on the dust optical properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Models of astrophysical dust are key to understand several physical processes, from the role of dust grains as cooling agents in the ISM to their evolution in dense circumstellar disks, explaining the occurrence of planetary systems around many stars. Currently, most models aim at providing optical properties for dust grains in the diffuse ISM, and many do not account properly for complexity in composition and structure when dust is expected to evolve in dense astrophysical environments. Our purpose is to investigate, with a pilot sample of micron-size dust grains, the influence of dust structure, porosity, and composition when computing the optical properties of grown dust grains in the infrared and millimetre domains, where observations are widely used to constrain the dust properties. Starting from the small dust grains developed in the THEMIS 2.0 model, we use the Discrete Dipole Approximation to compute the optical properties of 1 um grains, varying the hypotheses made on their composition and structure. We look at the dust scattering, emission and extinction to isolate potential simplifications and unavoidable differences between grain structures. We note that both dust structure and porosity influence the dust properties in infrared and millimetre ranges, demonstrating that dust aggregates cannot be correctly approximated by compact or porous spheres. In particular, we show that the dust emissivity index in the millimetre can vary with fixed grain size. We shed light on the importance of taking the dust structure and porosity into account when interpreting observations in environments where dust grains may have evolved significantly. Efforts in carrying out physical models of grain growth, for instance, are required to establish realistic constraints on the structure of grown dust grains, and will be used in the future to build realistic dust models for the dense ISM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20578v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. -A. Carpine, N. Ysard, A. Maury, A. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Component Ionized Gas Outflows in a Hot Dust-Obscured Galaxy W2026+0716 with Keck/OSIRIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present narrowband-filtered integral field unit (IFU) observations of the Hot Dust-Obscured Galaxy (Hot DOG) WISE J202615.27$+$071624.0 (hereafter W2026$+$0716) at redshift $z=2.570$ using Keck/OSIRIS. Our analysis reveals a multi-component ionized gas outflow structure in this heavily obscured AGN host galaxy. Multi-component Gaussian decomposition of the [O III] and H$\alpha$ emission lines uncovers extremely broad and asymmetric profiles, characteristic of AGN-driven outflows. Kinematic mapping shows spatially distinct structures: the [O III] and H$\alpha$ dominated components (with radii of $1.20 \pm 0.56$ kpc) are separated by a projected offset of $\sim 1.1$ kpc and exhibit divergent velocity regimes. The [O III] outflow reaches a velocity of 3210 $\pm$ 50 km s$^{-1}$, while the H$\alpha$ outflow component attains 2310 $\pm$ 840 km s$^{-1}$. Dynamical modeling supports a biconical outflow structure, with [O III] and H$\alpha$ emissions dominating separate cones and significant dust obscuration of the redshifted outflow. Their comparable momentum outflow rates and energy outflow rates suggest a potential physical connection in their driving mechanisms. Spectral energy distribution (SED) analysis reveals anomalous optical/UV excess, attributed to AGN photon scattering by dust or outflowing material, classifying W2026+0716 as a "Blue Hot DOG". The derived outflow timescale ($\sim10^{5}$ yr) aligns with the evolutionary phase of Blue Hot DOGs, suggesting AGN feedback operates persistently during this transitional stage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20611v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Liu, Chao-Wei Tsai, Peter R. M. Eisenhardt, Hyunsung D. Jun, Guodong Li, Jingwen Wu, Roberto J. Assef, Andrew W. Blain, Maren Cosens, Tanio D\'iaz-Santos, Rom\'an Fern\'andez Aranda, Lei Hao, Mai Liao, Shuai Liu, Daniel Stern, Andrey Vayner, Shelley Wright, Sherry Yeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The VMC survey -- LIII. Data release #7. Complete survey data and data from additional programmes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The near-infrared YJKs Visual and Infrared Survey Telescope for Astronomy (VISTA) survey of the Magellanic Clouds (VMC) is complete and there are also data from additional programmes enhancing its quality over the original footprint. This work presents the final data release of the VMC survey, which includes additional observations and provides an overview of the scientific results. The overall data quality has been revised and reprocessed standard data products, that already appeared in previous data releases, are made available together with new data products. These include individual stellar proper motions, reddening towards red clump stars and source classifications. Several data products, such as the parameters of some variable stars and of background galaxies, from the VMC publications are associated to a data release for the first time. The data are processed using the VISTA Data Flow System and additional products, e.g. catalogues with point-spread function photometry or tables with stellar proper motions, are obtained with software developed by the survey team. This release supersedes all previous data releases of the VMC survey for the combined (deepstacked) data products, whilst providing additional (complementary) images and catalogues of single observations per filter. Overall, it includes about 64 million detections, split nearly evenly between sources with stellar or galaxy profiles. The VMC survey provides a homogeneous data set resulting from deep and multi-epoch YJKs-band imaging observations of the Large and Small Clouds, the Bridge and two fields in the Stream. The VMC data represent a valuable counterpart for sources detected at other wavelengths for both stars and background galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20694v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. -R. L. Cioni, N. J. G. Cross, V. Ripepi, L. Girardi, R. de Grijs, G. Clementini, J. Th. van Loon, M. A. T. Groenewegen, V. D. Ivanov, J. M. Oliveira, M. Marconi, K. Bekki, R. P. Blake, M. J. Holliman, J. Irwin, M. J. Irwin, R. G. Mann, M. Read, E. Sutorius, J. E. M. Craig, F. Cusano, F. Dresbach, C. Maitra, R. Molinaro, F. Niederhofer, A. O. Omkumar, C. M. Pennock, T. Sicignano, S. Subramanian, B. L. Tatton, S. Vijayasree, S. Zaggia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Analysis of the Orbital Dynamics of Globular Clusters in the Central Region of the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new method for determining the nature of the orbital motion (chaotic or regular) of globular clusters in the central region of the Galaxy with a radius of 3.5 kpc, which are most affected by the bar, is proposed. The method is based on calculating the orbital power spectrum as a function of time and calculating the entropy of the power spectrum as a measure of orbital chaos. The sample includes 45 globular clusters. To form the 6D phase space required for integrating the orbits, the most accurate astrometric data to date from the Gaia satellite (Vasiliev \&amp; Baumgardt, 2021) were used, as well as new refined average distances (Baumgardt \&amp; Vasiliev, 2021). Orbits of globular clusters are obtained in a non-axisymmetric potential with a bar in the form of a triaxial ellipsoid embedded in an axisymmetric potential, traditionally used by us to construct orbits of globular clusters, described in detail in the paper by Bajkova et al. (2023a). The following, most realistic, bar parameters are adopted: mass $10^{10} M_\odot$, length of the major semi-axis 5 kpc, angle of rotation of the bar axis 25$^o$, angular velocity of rotation 40 km s$^{-1}$ kpc$^{-1}$. A list of 23 globular clusters with regular dynamics and 22 globular clusters with chaotic dynamics is determined. The correlation of the obtained classification of globular clusters with the classification obtained by us using other methods in the work of Bajkova et al. (2024a) was determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20749v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anisa Bajkova, Anton Smirnov, Vadim Bobylev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MUSE observations of dwarf galaxies and a stellar stream in the M83 group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectroscopy for faint dwarf galaxies outside of our own Local Group is challenging. Here, we present MUSE spectroscopy to study the properties of four known dwarf satellites and one stellar stream (KK208) surrounding the nearby grand spiral M83, which resides together with the lenticular galaxy Cen A in the Centaurus group. This data complete the phase-space information for all known dwarf galaxies around M83 down to a completeness of $-$10 mag in the $V$ band. All studied objects have an intermediate to old and metal-poor stellar population and follow the stellar luminosity-metallicity relation as defined by the Local Group dwarfs. For the stellar stream we serendipitously identify a previously unknown globular cluster, which is old and metal-poor. Two dwarf galaxies (NGC5264 and dw1341-29) may be a bound satellite of a satellite system due to their proximity and shared velocities. Having access to the positions and velocities of 13 dwarfs around M83, we estimate the mass of the group with different estimators. Ranging between 1.3 and $3.0 \times 10^{12}$ M$_\odot$ for the halo mass we find it to be larger than previously assumed. This may impact the previously reported tension for cold dark matter cosmology with the count of dwarf galaxies. In contrast to Cen A, we do not find a co-rotating plane-of-satellites around M83.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20765v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver M\"uller, Marina Rejkuba, Katja Fahrion, Marcel S. Pawlowski, Benoit Famaey, Noam Libeskind, Nick Heesters, Federico Lelli, Michael Hilker, Salvatore Taibi, Sarah Pearson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIGHTEE-HI: The radial acceleration relation with resolved stellar mass measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The radial acceleration relation (RAR) is a fundamental relation linking baryonic and dark matter in galaxies by relating the observed acceleration derived from dynamics to the one estimated from the baryonic mass. This relation exhibits small scatter, thus providing key constraints for models of galaxy formation and evolution -- allowing us to map the distribution of dark matter in galaxies -- as well as models of modified dynamics. However, it has only been extensively studied in the very local Universe with largely heterogeneous samples. We present a new measurement of the RAR, utilising a homogeneous, unbiased sample of H{\sc i}-selected galaxies. We introduce a novel approach of measuring resolved stellar masses using spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting across 10 photometric bands to determine the resolved mass-to-light ratio, which we show is essential for measuring the acceleration due to baryons in the low-acceleration regime. We find that the stellar mass-to-light ratio varies across galaxies and radially, favouring lower mass-to-light ratios compared to previous studies. Our results reveal a tight RAR with a low-acceleration power-law slope of $\sim 0.5$, consistent with previous studies. Adopting a spatially varying mass-to-light ratio yields the tightest RAR with an intrinsic scatter of only $0.045 \pm 0.022$ dex. We also find the first tentative evidence for redshift evolution in the acceleration scale, but more data will be required to confirm this. These results highlight the importance of resolved stellar mass measurements in accurately characterizing the gravitational contribution of the baryons in low-mass, gas-rich galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20857v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreea Varasteanu, Matt J. Jarvis, Anastasia A. Ponomareva, Harry Desmond, Ian Heywood, Tariq Yasin, Natasha Maddox, Marcin Glowacki, Michalina Maksymowicz-Maciata, Pavel E. Mancera Pi\~na, Hengxing Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian and Statistical Analysis of the Open Star Cluster NGC 6416</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our Bayesian and Statistical Analysis investigation of the open cluster NGC 6416, we utilized Gaia EDR3 astrometry data and ensemble-based unsupervised machine learning techniques to identify 406 cluster members. Using the MESA Isochrones and Stellar Tracks (MIST) with Gaia EDR3 data, we determined the following parameters for NGC 6416: a distance of approximately 1021pc, an age of about $12.58\pm 0.1$ Myr, a metallicity (z) of roughly $0.032\pm0.0015$, a binarity fraction near $0.419\pm0.021$, and an extinction ($A_V$) of approximately $0.995\pm0.058$ mag for an $R_V$ value of around $3.064\pm0.102$. We also fitted the radial surface density profile and conducted orbit analysis of the cluster using galpy. And finally found that the star formation scenarios are not observed in the open star cluster NGC 6416.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20909v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simanta Deka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How black hole mimickers and Shapiro-free lenses signal effective dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the existence of two exotic compact objects in the leading relativistic model of modified Newtonian dynamics, namely aether-scalar-tensor theory. This model is consistent with precision cosmology and gravitational wave constraints on tensor speed. Black hole mimickers could subtly change observations: gravitational waves from their mergers might show unusual echoes or altered ringdown patterns, and images of their horizon-scale shadows might be slightly different from those of a true black hole. Shapiro-free lenses are massless objects that deflect light without any gravitational time delay, producing distinctive lensing events. These predictions connect to ongoing and future gravitational-wave searches, horizon-scale imaging, and time-domain lensing surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20144v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lirui Yang, Will Barker, Tobias Mistele, Amel Durakovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Time-Dependent Solution for GSN 069 Disk Evolution: The Nature of 'Long-Lived' TDEs and Implications for QPE Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20148v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the implementation of a fully time-dependent relativistic disk model - based on the light curve fitting package FitTeD - into the X-ray spectral fitting environment, pyXspec. This implementation enables simultaneous fitting of multi-epoch and multi-wavelength spectral data, where the only free parameters are those describing the black hole and the initial conditions, while the subsequent evolution is fully governed by the dynamical equations of an evolving accretion flow. We apply the model to fit seven epochs of X-ray spectra and two epochs of UV spectra of the 'long-lived' tidal disruption event (TDE) and quasi-periodic eruption (QPE) source GSN 069, spanning from its discovery in 2010 through late-2019. Our results show that such 'long-lived', X-ray-bright TDEs - of which GSN 069 is a prime, but not unique, example-can be naturally explained within the same framework as events with shorter-lived X-ray emission, such as ASASSN-14li and AT2019dsg. Their key distinction lies in the 'viscous' timescale parameter - tied to the disk's stress and angular momentum transport efficiency - which should be treated as a free parameter when modeling the disk evolution of transient events. We examine the implications for QPE models by tracking the time evolution of disk properties such as mass surface density and accretion rate. We show that existing QPE models cannot reproduce the observed connection between the presence (e.g., 2018) or absence (e.g., 2014) of eruptions and disk properties. In the context of orbiter-disk collision models, the change in mass surface density appears insufficient to explain the needed variation in the eruption's temperature. The absence of eruptions in GSN 069 in 2014 remains a major challenge for QPE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20148v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Guolo, A. Mummery, A. Ingram, M. Nicholl, S. Gezari, E. Nathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic KMTNet Planetary Anomaly Search. XII. Complete Sample of 2017 Subprime Field Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20155v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the analysis of four unambiguous planets and one possible planet from the subprime fields ($\Gamma \leq 1~{\rm hr}^{-1}$) of the 2017 Korea Microlensing Telescope Network (KMTNet) microlensing survey, to complete the KMTNet AnomalyFinder planetary sample for the 2017 subprime fields. They are KMT-2017-BLG-0849, KMT-2017-BLG-1057, OGLE-2017-BLG-0364, and KMT-2017-BLG-2331 (unambiguous), as well as KMT-2017-BLG-0958 (possible). For the four unambiguous planets, the mean planet-host mass ratios, $q$, are $(1.0, 1.2, 4.6, 13) \times 10^{-4}$, the median planetary masses are $(6.4, 24, 76, 171)~M_{\oplus}$ and the median host masses are $(0.19, 0.57, 0.49, 0.40)~M_{\odot}$ from a Bayesian analysis. We have completed the AnomalyFinder planetary sample from the first 4-year KMTNet data (2016--2019), with 112 unambiguous planets in total, which nearly tripled the microlensing planetary sample. The ``sub-Saturn desert'' ($\log q = \left[-3.6, -3.0\right]$) found in the 2018 and 2019 KMTNet samples is confirmed by the 2016 and 2017 KMTNet samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20155v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ad4ce5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024, The Astronomical Journal, Volume 168, Issue 2, id.49, 16 pp</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuqian Gui, Weicheng Zang, Ruocheng Zhai, Yoon-Hyun Ryu, Andrzej Udalski, Hongjing Yang, Cheongho Han, Shude Mao, Michael D. Albrow, Sun-Ju Chung, Andrew Gould, Kyu-Ha Hwang, Youn Kil Jung, In-Gu Shin, Yossi Shvartzvald, Jennifer C. Yee, Sang-Mok Cha, Dong-Jin Kim, Hyoun-Woo Kim, Seung-Lee Kim, Chung-Uk Lee, Dong-Joo Lee, Yongseok Lee, Byeong-Gon Park, Richard W. Pogge, Przemek Mr\'oz, Micha{\l} K. Szyma\'nski, Jan Skowron, Rados{\l}aw Poleski, Igor Soszy\'nski, Pawe{\l} Pietrukowicz, Szymon Koz{\l}owski, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Krzysztof A. Rybicki, Patryk Iwanek, Marcin Wrona, Mariusz Gromadzki, Hanyue Wang, Jiyuan Zhang, Renkun Kuang, Qiyue Qian, Wei Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlensing events indicate that super-Earth exoplanets are common in Jupiter-like orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exoplanets classified as super-Earths are commonly observed on short period orbits, close to their host stars, but their abundance on wider orbits is poorly constrained. Gravitational microlensing is sensitive to exoplanets on wide orbits. We observed the microlensing event OGLE-2016-BLG-0007, which indicates an exoplanet with a planet-to-star mass ratio roughly double the Earth-Sun mass-ratio, on an orbit longer than Saturn's. We combine this event with a larger sample from a microlensing survey to determine the distribution of mass ratios for planets on wide orbits. We infer there are $\sim 0.35$ super-Earth planets per star on Jupiter-like orbits. The observations are most consistent with a bimodal distribution, with separate peaks for super-Earths and gas giants. We suggest that this reflects differences in their formation processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20158v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/science.adn6088</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025, Science, Vol 388, Issue 6745, pp. 400-404</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Weicheng Zang, Youn Kil Jung, Jennifer C. Yee, Kyu-Ha Hwang, Hongjing Yang, Andrzej Udalski, Takahiro Sumi, Andrew Gould, Shude Mao, Michael D. Albrow, Sun-Ju Chung, Cheongho Han, Yoon-Hyun Ryu, In-Gu Shin, Yossi Shvartzvald, Sang-Mok Cha, Dong-Jin Kim, Hyoun-Woo Kim, Seung-Lee Kim, Chung-Uk Lee, Dong-Joo Lee, Yongseok Lee, Byeong-Gon Park, Richard W. Pogge, Xiangyu Zhang, Renkun Kuang, Hanyue Wang, Jiyuan Zhang, Zhecheng Hu, Wei Zhu, Przemek Mr\'oz, Jan Skowron, Rados{\l}aw Poleski, Micha{\l} K. Szyma\'nski, Igor Soszy\'nski, Pawe{\l} Pietrukowicz, Szymon Koz{\l}owski, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Krzysztof A. Rybicki, Patryk Iwanek, Marcin Wrona, Mariusz Gromadzki, Fumio Abe, Richard Barry, David P. Bennett, Aparna Bhattacharya, Ian A. Bond, Hirosane Fujii, Akihiko Fukui, Ryusei Hamada, Yuki Hirao, Stela Ishitani Silva, Yoshitaka Itow, Rintaro Kirikawa, Naoki Koshimoto, Yutaka Matsubara, Shota Miyazaki, Yasushi Muraki, Greg Olmschenk, Cl\'ement Ranc, Nicholas J. Rattenbury, Yuki Satoh, Daisuke Suzuki, Mio Tomoyoshi, Paul J. Tristram, Aikaterini Vandorou, Hibiki Yama, Kansuke Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing X-ray Reprocessing and Mapping the Soft Excess of NGC 7469 with NICER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an X-ray/UV reverberation analysis of NGC 7469 across 210 days, using daily NICER observations with contemporaneous monitoring by Swift UVOT+XRT. We model the X-ray spectrum with a power law continuum and a soft excess during each NICER epoch. These emission sources demonstrate correlated flux variability with a lag consistent with zero days. We find that the power law emission is consistent with a compact X-ray corona, and that the soft excess can be explainedby reflected coronal emission from the inner accretion disk. We test the relationship between changes in the flux of the X-ray corona and the UVW2 continuum, finding strong correlation and a negative X-ray lag of less than one day. This is consistent with a scenario in which the X-ray corona drives the UVW2 light curve through thermal reprocessing</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20223v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan R. Partington, Edward M. Cackett, Rick Edelson, Keith Horne, Jake A. Miller, Aaron J. Barth, Jonathan Gelbord, Juan V. Hern\'andez Santisteban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abundance Measurements of the Metal-poor M subwarf LHS 174 Using High-resolution Optical Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Metal-poor M subdwarfs are among the oldest stellar populations and carry valuable information about the chemical enrichment history of the Milky Way. The measurements of chemical abundances of these stars therefore provide essential insights into the nucleosynthesis in the early stages of the Galaxy's formation. We present the detailed spectroscopic analysis of a nearby metal-poor M subdwarf, LHS 174 from its high-resolution optical spectrum, and apply our previously developed spectral fitting code, \texttt{AutoSpecFit}, to measure the abundances of five elements:[O/H]=$-$0.519$\pm$0.081, [Ca/H]=$-$0.753$\pm$0.177, [Ti/H]=$-$0.711$\pm$0.144, [V/H]=$-$1.026$\pm$0.077, and [Fe/H]=$-$1.170$\pm$0.135. We compare the abundances of O, Ti, and Fe derived from this work and those from previous studies and demonstrate the observed data is clearly better matched with the synthetic model generated based on our abundances than those from the other analyses. The accuracy of inferred stellar abundances strongly depends on the accuracy of physical parameters, which motivates us to develop a reliable technique to determine the parameters of low-mass M dwarfs more accurately ever than before and infer abundances with smaller uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20255v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neda Hejazi, Sebastien Lepine, Thomas Nordlander, Wei-Chun Jao, David R. Coria, Kathryn V. Lester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FALCO: a Foundation model of Astronomical Light Curves for time dOmain astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Time-domain surveys have advanced astronomical research by revealing diverse variable phenomena, from stellar flares to transient events. The scale and complexity of survey data, along with the demand for rapid classification, present significant challenges for analysis. While machine learning offers solutions, most existing models are tailored to single tasks, struggle to generalize, and depend heavily on large, accurately labeled datasets. We introduce FALCO, a foundation model for astronomical light curve analysis in time-domain astronomy. This work presents the initial version of FALCO trained via self-supervised learning on unlabeled Kepler light curves using a Transformer-based architecture. The model has been evaluated on three distinct tasks and demonstrates strong generalization: achieving 95 percent accuracy in stellar variability classification across eight classes, an overall RMSE of 0.1305 dex in surface gravity estimation (notably improved to below 0.08 dex when log g is less than 1, and approximately 0.02 dex near log g equals 3), and 87 percent precision in flare identification. These results highlight the model's versatility and ability to learn generalizable representations from light curves, enabling straightforward adaptation to diverse tasks. We further analyze the impact of model scaling and sequence length, finding performance improves with larger models and longer input sequences. We also apply FALCO to derive surface gravity (log g) measurements for 179,732 Kepler stars from their light curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20290v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxiong Zuo, Yihan Tao, Yang Huang, Zhixuan Kang, Huaxi Chen, Chenzhou Cui, Jiashu Pan, Xiao Kong, Xiaoyu Tang, Henggeng Han, Haiyang Mu, Yunfei Xu, Dongwei Fan, Guirong Xue, Ali Luo, Jifeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair-Instability Gap Black Holes in Population III Star Clusters: Pathways, Dynamics, and Gravitational Wave Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The detection of the gravitational wave (GW) event GW190521 raises questions about the formation of black holes within the pair-instability mass gap (PIBHs). We propose that Population III (Pop III) star clusters significantly contribute to events similar to GW190521. We perform $N$-body simulations and find that PIBHs can form from stellar collisions or binary black hole (BBH) mergers, with the latter accounting for 90\% of the contributions. Due to GW recoil during BBH mergers, approximately 10-50% of PIBHs formed via BBH mergers escape from clusters, depending on black hole spins and cluster escape velocities. The remaining PIBHs can participate in secondary and multiple BBH formation events, contributing to GW events. Assuming Pop III stars form in massive clusters (initially 100,000 $M_\odot$) with a top-heavy initial mass function, the average merger rates for GW events involving PIBHs with 0% and 100% primordial binaries are $0.005$ and $0.017$ $\text{yr}^{-1} \text{Gpc}^{-3}$, respectively, with maximum values of $0.030$ and $0.106$ $\text{yr}^{-1} \text{Gpc}^{-3}$. If Pop III stars form in low-mass clusters (initial mass of $1000M_\odot$ and $10000 M_\odot$), the merger rate is comparable with a 100% primordial binary fraction but significantly lower without primordial binaries. We also calculate the characteristic strains of the GW events in our simulations and find that about 43.4% (LISA) 97.8% (Taiji) and 66.4% (Tianqin) of these events could potentially be detected by space-borne detectors, including LISA, Taiji, and TianQin. The next-generation GW detectors such as DECIGO, ET, and CE can nearly cover all these signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20392v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiwei Wu, Long Wang, Shuai Liu, Yining Sun, Ataru Tanikawa, Michiko Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of a variable yellow supergiant progenitor for the Type IIb SN 2024abfo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of a progenitor candidate for the Type IIb SN 2024abfo using multi-epoch pre-explosion images from the Hubble Space Telescope and the Dark Energy Camera Legacy Survey. The progenitor exhibited a ~0.7 mag decline in F814W from 2001 to 2013, followed by significant brightness and color fluctuations in the g, r and z bands. This is the first time that a variable progenitor has been found for a SN IIb. We suggest that the variability is caused by intrinsic changes in the progenitor star instead of varying obscuration by circumstellar dust. Our results show that the progenitor of SN 2024abfo was likely a yellow supergiant star with an initial mass of 12--14, 14--15 and 15--18 Msun for different assumed values of circumstellar reddening of E(B-V)_CSM = 0, 0.1 and 0.2 mag. Our study underscores the critical role of multi-epoch imaging surveys in revealing the final stages of core-collapse supernovae progenitors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20407v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zexi Niu, Ning-Chen Sun, Justyn R. Maund, Zhen Guo, Wenxiong Li, Meng Sun, Jifeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gaia Catalogue of Galactic AGB Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20475v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper describes the identification of Gaia counterparts of a sample of oxygen-rich AGB stars with OH maser emission as a first step towards the compilation of a general Gaia Catalogue of Galactic AGB stars. With this catalogue, tests of evolutionary models for the AGB star population in the solar neighbourhood will become feasible. We cross-matched AGB star candidates showing OH maser emission with Gaia DR3 using a cross-match with AllWISE and 2MASS as intermediate steps to avoid ambiguities. With the help of the Virtual Observatory, we retrieved photometric data from the near-ultraviolet to the far-infrared and built spectral energy distributions (SEDs) of the sources. The SEDs were fitted with theoretical models. The fit results, together with information from the literature, allowed us to clean the sample from non-AGB stars and to obtain bolometric fluxes for the AGB stars. Distances based on Gaia parallaxes were used to derive the stellar luminosities. We identified unique Gaia counterparts for 1487 OH masers. Of these, 1172 had an unambiguous classification as AGB stars; they make up the Gaia OH/IR star sample. Parallaxes with relative errors $&lt;$20\% and astrometric excess noise $&lt;$1.5 mas were available for 222 OH/IR stars. We conclude that the study of the AGB population in the solar neighbourhood is limited by the obscuration by circumstellar dust, as \G\ DR3 only provides parallaxes for a few of our candidates. The location of the OH/IR stars matches that of LPV discovered by \G\ in the (BP$-$RP; G$_{abs}$) diagram, but the OH/IR star sample is biased towards redder colours (BP$-$RP$&gt;$4) mag and larger amplitudes ($&gt;$1 mag in the G-band), which are typical for periodic large-amplitude Mira variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20475v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bel\'en L\'opez Mart\'i (Universidad San Pablo CEU), Francisco M. Jim\'enez Esteban (Centro de Astrobiolog\'ia, INTA-CSIC), Dieter Engels (Hamburger Sternwarte), Pedro Garc\'ia Lario (European Space Agency)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two Decades of Dust Evolution in SN 2005af through JWST, Spitzer, and Chemical Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The evolution of dust in core-collapse supernovae (SNe), in general, is poorly constrained owing to a lack of infrared observations after a few years from explosion. Most theories of dust formation in SNe heavily rely only on SN 1987A. In the last two years, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has enabled us to probe the dust evolution in decades-old SNe, such as SN 2004et, SN 2005ip, and SN 1980K. In this paper, we present two decades of dust evolution in SN 2005af, combining early-time infrared observations with Spitzer Space Telescope and recent detections by JWST. We have used a chemical kinetic model of dust synthesis in SN ejecta to develop a template of dust evolution in SN 2005af. Moreover, using this approach, for the first time, we have separately quantified the dust formed in the pre-explosion wind that survived after the explosion, and the dust formed in the metal-rich SN ejecta post-explosion. We report that in SN 2005af, predominantly carbon-rich dust is formed in the ejecta, where the total mass of ejecta dust is about 0.02-0.03 Msun, while in the circumstellar medium the amount of surviving oxygen-rich dust is 0.001-0.004 Msun.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20574v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arkaprabha Sarangi, Szanna Zsiros, Tamas Szalai, Laureano Martinez, Melissa Shahbandeh, Ori D. Fox, Schuyler D. Van Dyk, Alexei V. Filippenko, Melina Cecilia Bersten, Ilse De Looze, Chris Ashall, Tea Temim, Jacob E. Jencson, Armin Rest, Dan Milisavljevic, Luc Dessart, Eli Dwek, Nathan Smith, Samaporn Tinyanont, Thomas G. Brink, WeiKang Zheng, Geoffrey C. Clayton, Jennifer Andrews</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling of the time-resolved spectral energy distribution of blazar OJ 287 from 2008 to 2023: a comprehensive multi-epoch study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20627v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive analysis of the time-resolved spectral energy distributions (SEDs) of the blazar OJ 287 over a 15-year period (2008-2023), using multi-wavelength data. In the $\gamma$-ray band, multiple flaring episodes were observed, with the strongest flare reaching a peak flux of $(5.60\pm1.11)\times10^{-7}\:{\rm photons\:cm^{-2}\:s^{-1}}$ on MJD 55869.03 (04 November 2011). In the optical/UV band, the source was in an active state between MJD 57360 (04 December 2015) and 57960 (26 July 2017), during which the highest flux of $(1.07\pm0.02)\times10^{-10}\:{\rm erg\:cm^{-2}\:s^{-1}}$ was observed on MJD 57681.23 (20 October 2016). In the X-ray band, both the flux and spectral index exhibit variability. To investigate the origin of the broadband emission from OJ 287, we systematically modeled 739 quasi-simultaneous SEDs using a leptonic model that self-consistently accounts for particle injection and cooling. This analysis is possible thanks to the recent development of a surrogate neural-network-based model, trained on kinetic simulations. This innovative, time-resolved, neural network-based approach overcomes the limitations of traditional single-epoch SED modeling, enabling to explore the temporal evolution of key model parameters, such as the magnetic field strength, Doppler factor, and electron injection distribution, across different states of the source. We identified distinct emission states characterized by unique combinations of magnetic field $ B $, electron index $ p $, and Doppler boost $ \delta $, associated to different underlying mechanisms such as varying acceleration processes (e.g., shocks, turbulence) and magnetic confinement. The analysis provides insights into the jet physics processes, including particle acceleration mechanisms and dynamic changes in the jet structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20627v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Harutyunyan, N. Sahakyan, D. B\'egu\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiwavelength correlation studies in the era of CTAO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20731v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Correlations between various multiwavelength (MWL) bands are an intermittent feature in blazar light curves; that is, they are observed in some instances but not in others. With the CTAO we will obtain detailed very-high-energy (VHE) gamma-ray light curves for many sources also during their low states, enabling detailed MWL correlation studies. For two blazars, the HBL Mrk\,421 and the FSRQ PKS\,1510-089, the long-term X-ray and optical light curves are used to induce variations in input parameters of the lepto-hadronic one-zone code OneHaLe. We show light curves in the CTA energy range for three different energy thresholds. The results are: 1) the presence of relativistic protons has a significant effect on the correlation of the light curves as the emerging pair cascade prolongs flaring states at the highest energies; and 2) comparison of the theoretical light curves with existing VHE gamma-ray data shows that both leptonic and hadronic models can only partially reproduce the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20731v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Zacharias (for the CTAO Consortium), Elina Lindfors (for the CTAO Consortium), Patrizia Romano (for the CTAO Consortium), Daniela Dorner (for the CTAO Consortium), Stefano Vercellone (for the CTAO Consortium), Matteo Cerruti (for the CTAO Consortium), Jonathan Biteau (for the CTAO Consortium)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible evidence for the 478 keV emission line from $^7$Be decay during the outburst phases of V1369 Cen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: After decades of uncertainty about the origin of lithium, recent evidence suggests Galactic novae as its main astrophysical source. In this work, we present possible evidence for the first detection of the $^7$Be line at 478 keV, observed with the INTEGRAL satellite. The emission is temporally and spatially coincident with the outburst of the bright nova V1369 Cen, and line significance ranges from 2.5$\sigma$ to $\sim$1.9$\sigma$, depending on the detection methodology. A bootstrap analysis, assuming a fixed FWHM of 8 keV, provides a flux of $(4.9 \pm 2.0) \times 10^{-4}$ ph/cm$^2$/s centered at 479.0 $\pm$ 2.5 keV, with a 2.5$\sigma$ significant excess. This flux implies a total $^7$Be mass of $M_{^7Be} = (1.2^{+2.0}_{-0.6})$ $\times 10^{-8}$ M$_{\odot}$ at the distance determined using several indicators including the {\em Gaia} satellite. For a nova ejected mass estimated from radio observations, this result implies a $^7$Be=Li yield corresponding to $A(Li) = 7.1^{+0.7}_{-0.3}$. This value is comparable to those measured in a dozen novae through optical observations. Crucially, we confirm optically derived $^7$Li yields and demonstrate the groundbreaking potential of using gamma-ray data to measure Li abundances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20866v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Izzo, T. Siegert, P. Jean, P. Molaro, P. Bonifacio, M. Della Valle, T. Parsotan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XRISM forecast for the Coma cluster: stormy, with a steep power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20928v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The XRISM Resolve microcalorimeter array measured the velocities of hot intracluster gas at two positions in the Coma galaxy cluster: 3'x3' squares at the center and at 6' (170 kpc) to the south. We find the line-of-sight velocity dispersions in those regions to be sigma_z=208+-12 km/s and 202+-24 km/s, respectively. The central value corresponds to a 3D Mach number of M=0.24+-0.015 and the ratio of the kinetic pressure of small-scale motions to thermal pressure in the intracluster plasma of only 3.1+-0.4%, at the lower end of predictions from cosmological simulations for merging clusters like Coma, and similar to that observed in the cool core of the relaxed cluster A2029. Meanwhile, the gas in both regions exhibits high line-of-sight velocity differences from the mean velocity of the cluster galaxies, Delta v_z=450+-15 km/s and 730+-30 km/s, respectively. A small contribution from an additional gas velocity component, consistent with the cluster optical mean, is detected along a sightline near the cluster center. The combination of the observed velocity dispersions and bulk velocities is not described by a Kolmogorov velocity power spectrum of steady-state turbulence; instead, the data imply a much steeper effective slope (i.e., relatively more power at larger linear scales). This may indicate either a very large dissipation scale resulting in the suppression of small-scale motions, or a transient dynamic state of the cluster, where large-scale gas flows generated by an ongoing merger have not yet cascaded down to small scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20928v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> XRISM Collaboration, Marc Audard, Hisamitsu Awaki, Ralf Ballhausen, Aya Bamba, Ehud Behar, Rozenn Boissay-Malaquin, Laura Brenneman, Gregory V. Brown, Lia Corrales, Elisa Costantini, Renata Cumbee, Maria Diaz Trigo, Chris Done, Tadayasu Dotani, Ken Ebisawa, Megan E. Eckart, Dominique Eckert, Satoshi Eguchi, Teruaki Enoto, Yuichiro Ezoe, Adam Foster, Ryuichi Fujimoto, Yutaka Fujita, Yasushi Fukazawa, Kotaro Fukushima, Akihiro Furuzawa, Luigi Gallo, Javier A. Garcia, Liyi Gu, Matteo Guainazzi, Kouichi Hagino, Kenji Hamaguchi, Isamu Hatsukade, Katsuhiro Hayashi, Takayuki Hayashi, Natalie Hell, Edmund Hodges-Kluck, Ann Hornschemeier, Yuto Ichinohe, Daiki Ishi, Manabu Ishida, Kumi Ishikawa, Yoshitaka Ishisaki, Jelle Kaastra, Timothy Kallman, Erin Kara, Satoru Katsuda, Yoshiaki Kanemaru, Richard Kelley, Caroline Kilbourne, Shunji Kitamoto, Shogo Kobayashi, Takayoshi Kohmura, Aya Kubota, Maurice Leutenegger, Michael Loewenstein, Yoshitomo Maeda, Maxim Markevitch, Hironori Matsumoto, Kyoko Matsushita, Dan McCammon, Brian McNamara, Francois Mernier, Eric D. Miller, Jon M. Miller, Ikuyuki Mitsuishi, Misaki Mizumoto, Tsunefumi Mizuno, Koji Mori, Koji Mukai, Hiroshi Murakami, Richard Mushotzky, Hiroshi Nakajima, Kazuhiro Nakazawa, Jan-Uwe Ness, Kumiko Nobukawa, Masayoshi Nobukawa, Hirofumi Noda, Hirokazu Odaka, Shoji Ogawa, Anna Ogorzalek, Takashi Okajima, Naomi Ota, Stephane Paltani, Robert Petre, Paul Plucinsky, Frederick S. Porter, Katja Pottschmidt, Kosuke Sato, Toshiki Sato, Makoto Sawada, Hiromi Seta, Megumi Shidatsu, Aurora Simionescu, Randall Smith, Hiromasa Suzuki, Andrew Szymkowiak, Hiromitsu Takahashi, Mai Takeo, Toru Tamagawa, Keisuke Tamura, Takaaki Tanaka, Atsushi Tanimoto, Makoto Tashiro, Yukikatsu Terada, Yuichi Terashima, Yohko Tsuboi, Masahiro Tsujimoto, Hiroshi Tsunemi, Takeshi Tsuru, Aysegul Tumer, Hiroyuki Uchida, Nagomi Uchida, Yuusuke Uchida, Hideki Uchiyama, Shutaro Ueda, Yoshihiro Ueda, Shinichiro Uno, Jacco Vink, Shin Watanabe, Brian J. Williams, Satoshi Yamada, Shinya Yamada, Hiroya Yamaguchi, Kazutaka Yamaoka, Noriko Yamasaki, Makoto Yamauchi, Shigeo Yamauchi, Tahir Yaqoob, Tomokage Yoneyama, Tessei Yoshida, Mihoko Yukita, Irina Zhuravleva, Andrew Fabian, Dylan Nelson, Nobuhiro Okabe, Annalisa Pillepich, Cicely Potter, Manon Regamey, Kosei Sakai, Mona Shishido, Nhut Truong, Daniel R. Wik, John ZuHone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLIMFLAM DR1: The First Constraints on the Cosmic Baryon Distribution from 8 FRB sightlines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00505v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dispersion measure of fast radio bursts (FRBs), arising from the interactions of the pulses with free electrons along the propagation path, constitutes a unique probe of the cosmic baryon distribution. Their constraining power is further enhanced in combination with observations of the foreground large-scale structure and intervening galaxies. In this work, we present the first constraints on the partition of the cosmic baryons between the intergalactic medium (IGM) and circumgalactic medium (CGM), inferred from the FLIMFLAM spectroscopic survey. In its first data release, the FLIMFLAM survey targeted galaxies in the foreground of 8 localized FRBs. Using Bayesian techniques, we reconstruct the underlying ~Mpc-scale matter density field that is traced by the IGM gas. Simultaneously, deeper spectroscopy of intervening foreground galaxies (at impact parameters $b_\perp \lesssim r_{200}$) and the FRB host galaxies constrains the contribution from the CGM. Applying Bayesian parameter inference to our data and assuming a fiducial set of priors, we infer the IGM cosmic baryon fraction to be $f_{\rm igm}=0.59^{+0.11}_{-0.10}$, and a CGM gas fraction of $f_{\rm gas} = 0.55^{+0.26}_{-0.29}$ for $10^{10}\,M_\odot \lesssim M_{\rm halo}\lesssim 10^{13}\,M_\odot$ halos. The mean FRB host dispersion measure (rest-frame) in our sample is $\langle \rm{DM_{host}}\rangle = 90^{+29}_{-19}\rm{pc~cm^{-3}}$, of which $\langle{\rm DM_{host}^{unk}}\rangle =69^{+28}_{-19}~\rm{pc~cm^{-3}}$ arises from the host galaxy ISM and/or the FRB progenitor environment. While our current $f_{\rm igm}$ and $f_{\rm gas}$ uncertainties are too broad to constrain most galactic feedback models, this result marks the first measurement of the IGM and CGM baryon fractions, as well as the first systematic separation of the FRB host dispersion measure into two components: arising from the halo and from the inner ISM/FRB engine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00505v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad6567</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 2024, Volume 973, Number 2, page 151</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ilya S. Khrykin, Metin Ata, Khee-Gan Lee, Sunil Simha, Yuxin Huang, J. Xavier Prochaska, Nicolas Tejos, Keith W. Bannister, Jeff Cooke, Cherie K. Day, Adam Deller, Marcin Glowacki, Alexa C. Gordon, Clancy W. James, Lachlan Marnoch, Ryan. M. Shannon, Jielai Zhang, Lucas Bernales-Cortes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Framework for ISM Emission Line Models: Connecting Multi-Scale Simulations Across Cosmological Volumes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The JWST and ALMA have detected emission lines from the ionized interstellar medium (ISM) in some of the first galaxies at $z \gtrsim 6$. These measurements present an opportunity to better understand galaxy assembly histories and may allow important tests of state-of-the-art galaxy formation simulations. It is challenging, however, to model these lines in their proper cosmological context. In order to meet this challenge, we introduce a novel sub-grid line emission modeling framework. The framework uses the high-$z$ zoom-in simulation suite from the Feedback in Realistic Environments (FIRE) collaboration. The line emission signals from HII regions within each simulated FIRE galaxy are modeled using the semi-analytic HIILines code. A machine learning approach is then used to determine the conditional probability distribution for the line luminosity to stellar-mass ratio from the HII regions around each simulated stellar particle. This conditional probability distribution can then be applied to predict the line luminosities around stellar particles in lower resolution, yet larger volume cosmological simulations. As an example, we apply this approach to the IllustrisTNG simulations at $z=6$. The resulting predictions for the [OII], [OIII], and Balmer line luminosities as a function of star-formation rate (SFR) agree well with current observations. Our predictions differ, however, from related work in the literature which lack detailed sub-grid ISM models. This highlights the importance of our multi-scale simulation modeling framework. Finally, we provide forecasts for future line luminosity function measurements from the JWST and quantify the cosmic variance in such surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03997v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengqi Yang, Adam Lidz, Andrew Benson, Yizhou Zhao, Hui Li, Amelia Zhao, Aaron Smith, Yucheng Zhang, Rachel Somerville, Anthony Pullen, Hui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lensed fast radio bursts as a probe of time-varying gravitational potential induced by wave dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01439v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ultralight bosonic wave dark matter (DM) is preponderantly contesting the conventional cold DM paradigm in predicting diverse and rich phenomena on small scales. For a DM halo made of ultralight bosons, the wave interference naturally induces slow de Broglie time-scale fluctuations of the gravitational potential. In this paper, we first derive an estimation for the effect of a time-varying gravitational potential on photon propagation. Our numerical simulations suggest that the time-varying potential of a $10^{11}M_{\odot}$ halo composed of $10^{-22}\,\mathrm{eV}$ bosons would stretch or compress a time series signal by a factor of $10^{-10}$. Here, we propose that, due to the precise measurements of their arrival times, lensed repeating fast radio bursts (FRBs) have the potential to effectively validate temporal variations in gravitational potential by monitoring their images over a period of approximately $\mathcal{O}(1)$ years. With rapidly growing FRB observations, this method would serve as a promising method to directly probe the wave nature of galactic DM halos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01439v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.L081302</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ran Gao, Shuxun Tian, Zhengxiang Li, He Gao, Kai Liao, Bing Zhang, Zong-Hong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A pilot survey on globular clusters with the Wide Field Survey Telescope (WFST)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05160v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We carry out an imaging survey of six globular clusters (GCs) with a limit magnitude to 22 mag at the 5 sigma level, down to the main sequence stars of the respective cluster, as one of the pilot observing program of the Wide Field Survey Telescope (WFST). This paper present the early results of this survey, where we investigate the tidal characters at the periphery of the clusters NGC 4147, NGC 5024, NGC 5053, NGC 5272, NGC 5904 and NGC 6341. We present the estimated number density of cluster candidates and their spatial distribution. We confirm the presence of tidal arms in NGC 4147 and NGC 5904 and identify several intriguing potential tidal structures in NGC 4147, NGC 5024, NGC 5272, corroborated the elliptical morphology of the periphery of NGC 6341. WFST shows its ability to detect faint main-sequence stars of clusters beyond 15 kpc in helio-centric distance. Our findings underscore the WFST's capability for probing faint structural features in GCs, paving the way for future in-depth studies, especially for the search of the large scale tidal streams associated with the clusters with the future wide field survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05160v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Wan, Lulu Fan, Xuzhi Li, Xu Kong, Tinggui Wang, Qingfeng Zhu, Ji-an Jiang, Minxuan Cai, Zelin Xu, Xianzhong Zheng, Jingquan Cheng, Feng Li, Ming Liang, Hao Liu, Wentao Luo, Jinlong Tang, Hairen Wang, Jian Wang, Yongquan Xue, Dazhi Yao, Hongfei Zhang, Wen Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MaNGA AGN dwarf galaxies (MAD) -- II. AGN outflows in dwarf galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07779v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) feedback is one of the most important mechanisms in galaxy evolution. It is usually found in massive galaxies and regulates star formation. Although dwarf galaxies are assumed to be regulated by supernova feedback, recent studies show evidence for the presence of AGN outflows and feedback in dwarf galaxies. We investigate the presence of AGN outflows in a sample of 2292 dwarf galaxies with AGN signatures drawn from the MaNGA survey. Thanks to the integral field unit data from MaNGA we are able to spatially resolve these outflows and study their kinematics and energetics. Using the GELATO Python code, we fit the AGN-stacked spectrum of each galaxy, which is the stack of all the spaxels classified as AGN by emission line diagnostic diagrams, and in particular the [OIII]$\lambda$5007\AA\ emission line. If the galaxies show a broad [OIII] emission line component in the stacked spectrum, we run GELATO through all the spaxels that are classified as AGN in the emission line diagnostic diagrams. We find 11 new dwarf galaxies that present outflow signatures based on the presence of a broad [OIII] emission line component. Their velocity W$_{80}$ (width containing 80$\%$ of the flux of the [OIII]$\lambda$5007\AA\ emission line) ranges from 205 to 566 km s$^{-1}$ and the kinetic energy rate ranges from $\sim10^{35}$ to $\sim10^{39}$ erg s$^{-1}$. Stellar processes are unlikely to explain these outflow kinetic energy rates in the case of seven dwarf galaxies. We find a correlation between the W$_{80}$ velocity and the [OIII] luminosity and between the kinetic energy rate of the outflow and the bolometric luminosity spanning from massive to dwarf galaxies. This suggests a similar behavior between the AGN outflows in the dwarf galaxy population with those in massive galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07779v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Rodr\'iguez Morales, M. Mezcua, H. Dom\'inguez S\'anchez, A. Audibert, F. M\"uller-S\'anchez, M. Siudek, A. Er\'ostegui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JADES: comprehensive census of broad-line AGN from Reionization to Cosmic Noon revealed by JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The depth and coverage of the first years of JWST observations have revealed low luminosity active galactic nuclei (AGN) across a wide redshift range, shedding light on black hole (BH) assembly and feedback. We present our spectroscopic sample of 34 Type 1 AGN obtained from JADES survey data and spanning $1.5 &lt; z &lt; 9$. Our sample of AGN probes a BH mass range of $10^{6-9}$~M$_{\odot}$ at bolometric luminosities down to $10^{43}$~erg~s$^{-1}$, implying generally sub-Eddington ratios of $&lt;0.5L_{\rm Edd}$. Most of these AGN are hosted in low mass ($M_{\star}\sim10^8$~M$_{\odot}$) galaxies and are overmassive relative to the local $M_{BH}-M_{\star}$ relation, while remaining consistent with the local $M_{BH}$-$\sigma_*$ relation. The wide redshift range provided by our sample allows us to trace the emergence of local $M_{BH}$-$M_*$ scaling relation across the cosmic epoch. Additionally, we explore the capability of narrow-line diagnostics in identifying Type 2 AGN and find that a significant fraction of our AGN would be missed by them due to low metallicity or lack of high energy ionizing photons (potentially due to dust absorption, dense gas blanketing the broad and narrow line regions, or intrinsically soft ionizing spectra). We explore the UV luminosity function of AGN and their hosts and find that it is subject to significant cosmic variance and is also dependent on the AGN bolometric luminosity. Finally, we show that the electron and Balmer scattering scenarios recently proposed to explain the broad components of the Balmer lines are untenable on multiple grounds. There is no evidence that the black hole masses have been overestimated by orders of magnitude as proposed in those scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03551v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignas Juod\v{z}balis, Roberto Maiolino, William M. Baker, Emma Curtis Lake, Jan Scholtz, Francesco D'Eugenio, Bartolomeo Trefoloni, Yuki Isobe, Sandro Tacchella, Andrew J. Bunker, Stefano Carniani, St\'ephane Charlot, Gareth C. Jones, Eleonora Parlanti, Michele Perna, Pierluigi Rinaldi, Brant Robertson, Hannah \"Ubler, Giacomo Venturi, Chris Willott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeding Supermassive Black Holes with Self-Interacting Dark Matter: A Unified Scenario with Baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.15132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.15132v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Observations show that supermassive black holes (SMBHs) with a mass of $\sim10^9 M_\odot$ exist when the Universe is just $6\%$ of its current age. We propose a scenario where a self-interacting dark matter halo experiences gravothermal instability and its central region collapses into a seed black hole. The presence of baryons in protogalaxies could significantly accelerate the gravothermal evolution of the halo and shorten collapse timescales. The central halo could dissipate its angular momentum remnant via viscosity induced by the self-interactions. The host halo must be on high tails of density fluctuations, implying that high-$z$ SMBHs are expected to be rare in this scenario. We further derive conditions for triggering general relativistic instability of the collapsed region. Our results indicate that self-interacting dark matter can provide a unified explanation for diverse dark matter distributions in galaxies today and the origin of SMBHs at redshifts $z\sim6-7$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.15132v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ac04b0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophys. J. Lett. 914 (2021) 2, L26</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Xiang Feng, Hai-Bo Yu, Yi-Ming Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the Soliton-Halo Relation in Fuzzy Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09908v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Soliton cores at the center of fuzzy dark matter (FDM) halos provide a promising way to distinguish FDM from other dark matter models. However, the relation between solitons and their host halos remains contentious. Here, we rigorously examine this soliton-halo relation (SHR) using a rich set of cosmological simulations across various FDM particle masses, halo masses, and redshifts. We explicitly demonstrate thermal equilibrium between solitons and surrounding halo granules, energy equipartition within halos, and an FDM concentration-mass-nonisothermality relation. For each FDM halo, we confirm that its density profile outside the central soliton matches a collisionless N-body simulation from the same initial condition, serving as stringent numerical convergence tests. Our refined SHR agrees well with virialized halos in simulations, with a $1\sigma$ deviation of less than $30\%$. These findings not only reaffirm the SHR proposed by Schive et al. (2014) but also offer a more comprehensive understanding that extends its applicability. The simulation code GAMER is accessible at https://github.com/gamer-project/gamer. A Python script for computing the theoretical SHR is available at https://github.com/calab-ntu/fdm-soliton-halo-relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09908v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pin-Yu Liao, Guan-Ming Su, Hsi-Yu Schive, Alexander Kunkel, Hsinhao Huang, Tzihong Chiueh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The properties of GSN 069 accretion disk from a joint X-ray and UV spectral analysis: stress-testing quasi-periodic eruption models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03333v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an analysis of Hubble Space Telescope (HST) and XMM-Newton data of the tidal disruption event (TDE) candidate and quasi-periodic eruption (QPE) source GSN 069. Using ultraviolet (UV) and optical images at HST resolution, we show that GSN 069's emission consists of a point source superimposed on a diffuse stellar component. The latter accounts for $\leq 5\%$ of the UV emission in the inner 0.5"$\times$0.5" region, while the luminosity of the former cannot be attributed to stars. Analyzing the 2014/2018 \hst UV spectra, we show that to leading order the intrinsic spectral shape is $\nu\,L_{\nu}\propto\nu^{4/3}$, with $\sim10\%$ far UV flux variability between epochs. The contemporaneous X-ray and UV spectra can be modeled self-consistently in a thin disk framework. At observed epochs, the disk had an outer radius ($R_{\rm out}$) of $\mathcal{O}(10^3R_{\rm g})$, showing both cooling and expansion over four years. Incorporating relativistic effects via numerical ray tracing, we constrain the disk inclination angle ($i$) to be $30^\circ\,\lesssim\,i\,\lesssim\,65^\circ$ and identify a narrow region of spin-inclination parameter space that describes the observations. These findings confirm that GSN 069 hosts a compact, viscously expanding accretion disk likely formed after a TDE. Implications for QPE models are: (i) No published disk instability model can explain the disk's stability in 2014 (no QPEs) and its instability in 2018 (QPEs present); (ii) While the disk size in 2018 allows for orbiter/disk interactions to produce QPEs, in 2014 the disk was already sufficiently extended, yet no QPEs were present. These findings pose challenges to existing QPE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03333v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Guolo, A. Mummery, T. Wevers, M. Nicholl, S. Gezari, A. Ingram, D. R. Pasham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-analytic modelling of Pop. III star formation and metallicity evolution -- II. Impact on 21cm power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08971v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulating Population (Pop.) III star formation in mini-halos in a large cosmological simulation is an extremely challenging task but it is crucial to estimate its impact on the 21cm power spectrum. In this work, we develop a framework within the semi-analytical code meraxes to estimate the radiative backgrounds from Pop. III stars needed for the computation of the 21cm signal. We computed the 21cm global signal and power spectrum for different Pop. III models varying star formation efficiency, initial mass function (IMF) and specific X-ray luminosity per unit of star formation (LX/SFR). In all the models considered, we find Pop. III stars have little to no impact on the reionization history but significantly affect the thermal state of the intergalactic medium (IGM) due to the strong injection of X-ray photons from their remnants that heat the neutral IGM at $z \geq$ 15. This is reflected not only on the 21cm sky-averaged global signal during the Cosmic Dawn but also on the 21cm power spectrum at $z \leq$ 10 where models with strong Pop. III X-ray emission have larger power than models with no or mild Pop. III X-ray emission. We estimate observational uncertainties on the power spectrum using 21cmsense and find that models where Pop. III stars have a stronger X-ray emission than Pop. II are distinguishable from models with no or mild Pop. III X-ray emission with 1000 hours observations of the upcoming SKA1-low.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08971v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele M. Ventura, Yuxiang Qin, Sreedhar Balu, J. Stuart B. Wyithe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ISW-Lensing Bispectrum &amp; Trispectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03826v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Due to the integrated Sachs-Wolfe (ISW) effect, cosmic microwave background (CMB) temperature and polarization fluctuations are correlated with the gravitational lensing potential. Famously, this induces a CMB three-point function, whose shape can be used to constrain dark energy and modifications to gravity. An analogous effect occurs at higher-order, producing an ISW-lensing trispectrum whose amplitude is hitherto unconstrained. We present a detailed discussion of this effect, and define minimum-variance estimators for the ISW-lensing three- and four-point functions. These are implemented within the PolySpec code, and bear strong similarities to the quadratic estimators used in lensing analyses. Applying these tools to Planck, we obtain strong detections of the bispectrum amplitude (consistent with previous works), but find only weak constraints on the trispectrum, due to a strong cancellation between the various ISW-induced contributions. We additionally forecast the constraints from future datasets, finding that (a) simple estimators for the ISW-lensing bispectrum will be severely limited by non-Gaussian modifications to the covariance, and (b) the ISW-lensing trispectrum will be very challenging to detect even with high-resolution future experiments. We finally consider the induced bias on primordial non-Gaussianity amplitudes (and lensing itself), which we show to be large for the bispectrum (as expected) but negligible for the trispectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03826v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver H. E. Philcox, J. Colin Hill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supermassive Binaries in Ultralight Dark Matter Solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16348v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultralight (or fuzzy) dark matter (ULDM) is an alternative to cold dark matter. A key feature of ULDM is the presence of solitonic cores at the centers of collapsed halos. These would potentially increase the drag experienced by supermassive black hole (SMBH) binaries, changing their merger dynamics and the resulting gravitational wave background. We perform detailed simulations of high-mass SMBH binaries in the soliton of a massive halo. We find more rapid decay than previous simulations and semi-analytic approximations. We confirm expectations that the drag depends strongly on the ULDM particle mass, finding masses greater than $10^{-21}$ eV could potentially alleviate the final parsec problem and that ULDM may even suppress gravitational wave production at lower frequencies in the pulsar timing band.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16348v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Russell Boey, Emily Kendall, Yourong Wang, Richard Easther</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latest developments in wide-field VLBI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19579v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) combines the signals of telescopes distributed across thousands of kilometres to provide some of the highest angular resolution images of astrophysical phenomena. Due to computational expense, typical VLBI observations are restricted to a single target and a small (few arcseconds) field-of-view per pointing. The technique of wide-field VLBI was born to enable the targeting of multiple sources and has been successful in providing new insights into Active Galactic Nuclei, the interstellar medium, supernovae, gravitational lenses and much more. However, this technique is still only employed in a few experiments, restricting the scientific potential of VLBI observations. In this conference proceeding, we outline new developments in wide-field VLBI, including an end-to-end correlation and calibration workflow, distributed correlation, and new calibration routines. These developments aim to enable wide-field VLBI to be a standard observing mode on all major VLBI arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19579v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack F. Radcliffe (Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, School of Physics and Astronomy, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK, Department of Physics, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa), J. P. McKean (Department of Physics, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa, South African Radio Astronomy Observatory), C. Herb\'e-George (Department of Physics, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa, Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands), L. Coetzer (Department of Physics, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa), T. Matsepane (Department of Physics, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
